ON THE GLORIFICATION OF THE TRINITY
AND THE PROCESSION OF THE HOLY SPIRIT
Book One.
By Rupert, Abbot of Deutz.
Chapter One
The Mystery of the Holy Trinity is a precious treasure, hidden in a field.
You are a cherished treasure to us, O wondrous mystery of the Trinity, indeed a hidden treasure, yet one that can be discovered by those who seek you with an attentive heart, their minds illuminated by faith.
Where is this hidden treasure?
In a field.
As the Lord says in the Gospel: The kingdom of heaven is like a treasure hidden in a field Matthew 13.
It's truly remarkable!
Not in a pouch, not in an inn, not in a secret room, where people usually hide their treasure for fear of thieves, but in a field, out in the open.
What kind of hiding is this, I wonder, that it is hidden in plain sight?
Yet so it is, and it is completely true.
We have now embarked on this journey, and the purpose of our work is to reveal how or where this treasure is concealed in the field.
So, let us say that we have found this treasure, hidden from those who are blind, and we point it out almost as if with a finger to those who have eyes but perhaps haven't seen enough and wish to see more.
Chapter Two
How the holy Scripture of the Old Testament is like a field and why it is appropriately represented by the name of a field.
The holy Scripture of the Old Testament can be thought of as a field.
It's fitting to call it a field because it is a public matter; it's out in the open, accessible to everyone, or rather, to all nations who wish to read or listen.
This is why it is rightly said in the Psalm: The Lord will recount in the writings of the peoples Psalm 87.
What does it mean by "in the writings of the peoples"? It suggests that these writings are made available to all nations and can be read by everyone.
This distinction wouldn't be necessary unless there were certain writings, like those of the Platonists or Aristotelians, that aren't meant for everyone. In contrast, sacred Scriptures are rightly called the writings of the peoples because they don't turn away the people, especially those who are simple, from reading them.
Even if they don't quickly understand the deeper meanings, they can still easily grasp the literal and moral sense. But the writings of those philosophers, with their complex ideas, often confuse the simple. For example, if you say, A man has died, they might say, A man is not dead. And in a way, they're right, because if it's a man, he's alive; if he's dead, both the man, the soul, and the animated body are no longer.
This can leave ordinary people, the simple ones, puzzled. Yet, it's still correct to say, A man has died, as we often use a part to represent the whole. We rightly call a lifeless human body a man, and such expressions are accepted both by the people and in our Scriptures, and this simplicity makes them the writings of the peoples.
In a similar way, when we talk about the treasure being hidden in a field, meaning it's out in the open, philosophers might argue the opposite, and other such things that people might not understand.
However, it is true, but not in the way that a part represents the whole, as was previously stated.
In fact, you should understand the whole from the whole, mainly because everything is open or public to those who see, and everything is hidden or closed to those who are envious.
Chapter Three
How and by whom such a treasure is hidden in such a field, and by whom it can be quickly found.
We've already mentioned where this treasure is hidden: in the glorious distinction of the persons of the Holy Trinity.
Now, let's discuss how it's hidden there.
We've talked about where in the field it's hidden, and now we'll explore how.
We don't need to look far for an example; it's right there if you consider where it's said: The Lord will tell in the writings of the people Psalm Eighty-seven.
You might say to me that this relates to what was mentioned earlier, posed as a question: Will Zion say a man, and a man was born in her, and the Most High established her?
Psalm Eighty-seven.
To what extent is this significant portion of the hidden treasure, this substantial talent, this sacrament of the Incarnation, relevant only to the person of the Son, hidden in the frequently mentioned field?
The mystery of the entire Trinity is hidden there just as much, and not more secretly.
It's hidden from the unworthy, from those who choose to envy and not see, so it can't be found when sought, and valuable pearls aren't thrown to pigs to be trampled.
Therefore, it says: O Zion, will this man say, and a man was born in her.
It's understood in his own city, as was said before: Glorious things are spoken of you, city of God Psalm Eighty-seven.
---and the Most High established her.
Will, I say, this man declare this, someone entirely earthly, like a Jew or a heretic?
It's understood not, for saying this belongs to gods and all the sons of the Most High Psalm Eighty-two, that this man who was born in holy Zion, the one city of all saints and chosen angels and humans, before he was born in her, the Most High established her.
A man will not say this, nor will anyone dedicated to earthly sense understand it.
Therefore, the treasure is hidden.
Likewise, when it comes to all sacraments and the distinction of the persons of the Holy Trinity, which is a great treasure;
it's important to note that the way it's concealed means an unfaithful person won't discover it.
However, the multitude of the faithful, or the children of the Most High, quickly grasp it.
Chapter Four
This treasure of Holy Scripture isn't just found in one part of the field; it's spread throughout the whole field, hidden from the unworthy and discovered by the worthy, sometimes quickly.
Where exactly in the field is this treasure hidden and found?
Some might think it's hidden or revealed in certain parts, rather than the entire field.
To this, I say: it's not confined to parts, but throughout the whole field, across all its boundaries, this treasure has long been found and continues to be found.
What does "the whole" mean?
It encompasses everything God has done from the beginning of creation until now.
In short, it's about exploring the field's boundaries and the distinctions of useful works, which make up all of Holy Scripture, and affirming that the cooperation of the Trinity, as indicated in the scriptures, is present everywhere.
It starts with the creation of heaven and earth, then the condition of the angelic creation, followed by the formation of man with the Creator's blessing;
after the flood, there's the blessing of humanity's restoration from a few people, then the promise made to Abraham about the blessed seed, which is Christ.
Then comes God's descent into Egypt to free his people, followed by the method of blessing, where Moses was instructed to bless the sons of Israel once the tabernacle was completed, and the word given to David about building the house of the Lord, along with the sacraments of the psalms and the proclamations of the prophets, and then the consolation or return from the Babylonian captivity.
After that, the victorious battles of the Maccabees.
This field stretches through all these boundaries, and in all of them, this treasure is hidden. To put it more clearly, from these works of God, the holy old Scripture was written, and it's certain that in each of these, the comparison of the holy Trinity is present, and this is what we'll demonstrate in this work.
Once this has been shown, the most significant acts of the Lord's Incarnation, Passion, Resurrection, and Ascension, along with the coming of the Holy Spirit, the Comforter, will unfold.
In whatever small way we can, this work will be able to resonate more freely and passionately in the glory of the Holy Trinity.
From here, it started being proclaimed publicly all over the world, strengthened by numerous testimonies from the words or deeds of past ages.
So, let us now begin the journey of the work we have committed to since the beginning of creation.
Chapter Five
Let's talk about the beginning of the book: "In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth." There's a kind of hidden treasure here. The Son is the beginning, as He Himself said: "I am the beginning, who also speaks to you." The earth was empty and void, with darkness over the deep, and the Spirit of God moved over the waters.
Consider the nature of this hidden treasure.
Let's not get tired or let the frequent mention of this treasure's names and hiddenness make anyone bored.
There's joy in discovery, and joy comes from what has been found; it makes one speak from the abundance of the heart.
Now, consider what kind of hiddenness this is.
When the spirit of the Holy Scriptures in this chapter wants us to understand the Holy Trinity, it conceals just one person with a small veil, hiding the face of the Trinity from the wise and prudent, revealing it to the little ones.
Under what veil is this person hidden? It's certainly the person of the Son, under the veil of the name "beginning."
For the wise and prudent, meaning the proud, some of whom asked the incarnate Son of God, "Who are you?"
In saying "In the beginning created," they found or wanted to find nothing more than to say He created first or primarily, in which sense even a notable pagan poet could say:
"In the beginning, the heavens, the earth, the flowing fields, and the shining globe of the moon, and the Titan stars, the Spirit nourishes within."
But He, addressing the little ones who were about to hear Him, when asked, "Who are you?" He said, "The beginning, who also speaks to you."
In saying this, He certainly referenced this place, this chapter of Holy Scripture, so you don't doubt that He wants you to recognize what He Himself says in the Psalm: "In the scroll of the book, it is written about me."
For what is the head of the book, if not this beginning of all the Scriptures of truth?
The entirety of sacred Scripture, the canonical Scripture, is essentially one book with a single purpose.
Originating from one God, it is written by the same Spirit.
In contrast, writings that don't come from the Spirit of truth are considered many books.
That's why the wise Ecclesiastes says, "Of making many books there is no end."
In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth, and the Spirit of God moved over the waters.
This magnificent start of the book proclaims the glory of the Holy Trinity.
Let those who hate Him flee from His presence, just as the people of Israel, in their fear, fled and hesitated to approach when Moses' face shone from conversing with God.
Chapter Six
Why the Son or Word of God is called the beginning.
Why is the Son, or Word of God, referred to as the beginning?
The reason is that all things were made through Him.
But, there's more to it than just that.
Not only were all things made through Him, but also for Him.
As the Apostle states: "It was fitting for Him, for whom and through whom all things exist, in bringing many sons to glory, to perfect the author of their salvation through suffering," as it says in Hebrews chapter two.
This is the true reason, a reason worthy of such a title as "beginning," because He is the one for whom and through whom all things exist:
He is indeed the principal and efficient cause of all creation.
Someone might ask, "And what about God the Father? Is He not the beginning?"
Indeed, the Father is the beginning, the Son is the beginning, and the Holy Spirit is the beginning.
Yet, there are not three beginnings, but one beginning, just as there are not three gods, but one God.
So why, in this chapter of the book, did the inspirer of Holy Scripture, the Spirit of God, choose to call only the person of the Son the beginning?
To this, I say: The entire book, the entire Holy Scripture, whose head is: "In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth," for whom or for what creature was it written?
Surely, it was for human beings, as Holy Scripture was created for their instruction.
Without a doubt, to this creature, the Son of God is the beginning in three distinct ways.
In two ways, He is the beginning for both angelic and human creatures, as mentioned earlier, because all things were made for Him and through Him;
in a third way, He is the beginning for human creatures alone, because through His suffering, He was perfected as the author of our salvation;
He is, indeed, the leader and beginning of our salvation.
This was not hidden from Moses when he began to write this Scripture, being instructed by the finger of God.
Therefore, rightly and honorably, according to the truth of the matter, he used the word "Bresith," meaning "beginning," instead of "Ben," meaning "son," thus calling the Son of God the beginning.
For whom and through whom were we created, seen, and foreseen to be saved?
Therefore, it's important to consider that, although the Father is also a beginning, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, as mentioned earlier, are one beginning from which everything comes, through whom everything is, and in whom everything exists.
As stated in the letter to the Romans chapter eleven, it's not explicitly mentioned anywhere that either the Father or the Holy Spirit clearly called themselves the beginning, as the Son did.
He told the Jews: "I am the beginning, who speaks to you," as recorded in the Gospel of John chapter eight.
Chapter Seven
Let's explore what the Father says to the Son in the Psalm: "With you is the beginning on the day of your power, in the splendor of the holy ones; from the womb before the morning star I have begotten you."
In this Psalm, the Lord speaks to the Lord; the Father addresses the Son: "With you is the beginning on the day of your power, in the splendor of the holy ones; from the womb before the morning star I have begotten you" (Psalm 109).
This is interpreted as the Father speaking to the son of David, the Lord of David: "Father God, I am the beginning with you, I work with you on the day of your power, during your victory or resurrection, when the holy ones shone as darkness was dispelled and sins were forgiven: I, the beginning, that is, the Father, who from the womb before the morning star, that is, before all creation, have begotten you.
For Lucifer, who fell because he wanted to be the beginning, may have been the start of God's ways, but he was younger than you" (Job 40).
This interpretation, where the Father is seen as the beginning in this verse, can be challenging for some, as we've seen from experience.
They might think it supports the idea that the Father is the beginning of the Son, drawing this meaning from the Apostle's words: "The head of Christ is God" (First Corinthians 11).
To clear up any doubts and ensure faith remains intact, it's important to understand that the text of this verse doesn't require us to interpret the Father as the beginning.
When it says Psalm 109: "The Lord said to my Lord," meaning the Father to the Son, God to Christ, "with you is the beginning," it can be rightly understood as saying: "Therefore sit at my right hand, therefore rule amidst your enemies, because you are God, not just man, the Word and not just flesh."
This phrase essentially means: "With you is the beginning."
In your human nature, seen as the least of men, the divine nature is united, the ancient and uncreated beginning (Isaiah 35).
What does Peter say in the Acts of the Apostles about this same Lord: "Who went about doing good and healing all who were oppressed by the devil, for God was with him?" (Acts 10).
Certainly, we can't say that the Lord was only with Moses.
As the Lord tells Joshua, "Just as I was with Moses, so I will be with you." This doesn't mean the same way God was with him, that is, with Christ; but rather, it signifies that he was not just a man, but both God and man.
Similarly, when you hear God the Father speaking to the mediator between God and humans, Jesus Christ, "With you is the beginning," don't let Arius use this to claim that the Father is calling himself the beginning. Thus, he is not the beginning of the Son. From this, the Apostle says, "The head of Christ is God." To put it simply, end the argument by understanding that the beginning, meaning God or the Word, and the assumed man are one person, Jesus Christ, whose human nature encompasses the Divinity of the Word, the beginning, the head, and God within it.
Furthermore, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, the undivided Trinity, are one beginning, one God, one head.
Chapter Eight
On the reason behind the name "beginning," and what the Apostle meant by saying: "For whom all things exist, and through whom all things exist."
Much can already be drawn from the faithful testimonies of the Scriptures.
But since our goal is to follow the order of the Scriptures, we must be concise and use another example to explain why Moses, or rather God speaking through Moses, chose to call the Son or Word of the Father the "beginning" in this chapter.
It's already been stated that because of Him and through Him all things exist, making it fitting to refer to Him by this name.
Yet, a similar example will clarify this reason further.
The Apostle says the man is the head of the woman because the man was not created for the woman, but the woman for the man.
First Corinthians 11.
As God said, "It is not good for the man to be alone; I will make a helper suitable for him."
Genesis 2.
This is similar to the example at hand.
What model did God have when He first created the man and then from the man created the woman, except His Word, His Son, for whom and through whom all things were made?
Ultimately, just as one woman was made for one man, so also the Church, composed of all holy angels and chosen humans, is for the one Son of God.
However, there is a difference in creation, just as grammatical prepositions differ, so does the truth of understanding.
For the woman was made for and from the man, but the Church is for the Son, though not from the Son; no creature, I say, was created from the divine substance itself.
Hence the Apostle rightly said: "For whom all things exist, and through whom all things exist."
Hebrews 2.
And the evangelist: "Through Him all things were made."
John 1.
This similar example helps us understand why the Son of God is rightly called the beginning at the start of creation.
If the man is rightly called the head, or the beginning of the woman, because she was made for him, then much more so is the Son of God rightly called the beginning in Scripture, because all things exist for Him and through Him.
Chapter Nine
How the use of the term "beginning" resonates more powerfully with the Jews than if he had simply said: I am the Son of God or I am the Christ.
When he declares himself as the beginning, referencing this from the start of the book and responding to the Jews by saying: I am the beginning, who also speaks to you John 8, it is profound to see how he both avoids their malicious intentions and does not conceal the truth of his nature. Instead, he reveals it even more deeply.
The term "beginning" indeed carries more weight than if he had said: I am the Son of God or I am the Christ.
To whom among angels or humans is it ever appropriate to be called the beginning?
This term is not applicable to any creature.
The one who dared to claim: I made myself Ezekiel 29 is rebuked through the prophetic Spirit in Ezekiel for this assertion, which equates to saying: I am the beginning; because of this, the angel fell and became the devil.
Furthermore, the name "Son" is shareable, and he shared it with his children, as they partook of his flesh and blood. The Holy Spirit testified long before in the Psalms: I said, You are gods, and all of you are children of the Most High Psalm 82.
This does not contradict what the Apostle states: For to which of the angels did he ever say: You are my Son Hebrews 1, as he adds: Today I have begotten you, a statement never made or to be made to anyone else.
The name "Christ" is also shareable. For example, when God speaks in the Psalm about the patriarchs Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, he says: Do not touch my anointed ones Psalm 105.
Therefore, as mentioned earlier, by declaring himself as "beginning," he unveiled the truth of his essence more profoundly, as if he were saying: I am the Son of God or the Christ, while also avoiding their malicious intentions so they couldn't accuse him before the Roman Empire of assuming a royal title.
Similarly, in another instance, when those around him said: How long will you keep us in suspense? If you are the Christ, tell us plainly John.
He didn't confront them directly by declaring, "I am Christ." Instead, he approached them indirectly, talking about himself as the Shepherd and his sheep.
This kind of statement wouldn't have greatly concerned the Romans if he were accused of it.
Eventually, he said, "I and the Father are one" (John chapter ten), which is a much deeper declaration than simply saying "I am Christ," because, as mentioned before, many have been called christ.
Even David didn't hesitate to call the rejected Saul the Lord's anointed (First Samuel chapter twenty-four).
Chapter Ten
How the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit are one principle, and why it was more necessary to understand the Son's role as the principle.
We've explored the person of the Son and why it was fitting for him to be called the principle.
Regarding the Father's role as the principle, it's not necessary to use scriptural evidence in the same way.
Heretical and Jewish disputes haven't questioned the Father as much as they have the Son.
The Arians were particularly aggressive, not only contradicting the Church's belief in the co-eternity of the Father and the Son but also attacking it violently.
They insisted the Father was uncreated, but the Son was a creature.
If anyone interprets "In the beginning was the Word" in John's Gospel to mean the Father, implying "the Word was in the Father," they distort the text.
This leaves no space for the next sentence, which adds, "and the Word was with God."
What does "and the Word was with God" mean if you interpret "In the beginning was the Word" the same way?
It's clearer to understand "In the beginning was the Word" as saying: Before time, the Word was Christ, who appeared as a man later.
The Gospel aims to affirm Christ's antiquity, the Son of God, who did not start existing from Mary, contrary to some heretical claims.
As the beloved disciple was exiled on Patmos and wrote this Gospel last, it makes sense to interpret "In the beginning was the Word" this way.
Christ's existence didn't begin with Mary; he was God before time and became man later.
I'm saying this not because the Father isn't the beginning, but as I mentioned before, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, the blessed Trinity, are one beginning.
It's important to defend the person of the Son, just as it was the role of the Father, using the testimony of the Scriptures against heretics.
Through the name which is the beginning, He was not made or created; rather, through Him and for Him, all things were made.
This was the intention of Moses, or the one through whom the finger of God wrote, when he made such a statement at the beginning of the book:
"In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth"
Genesis 1:1.
Chapter Eleven
On the Holy Spirit, or the procession of the Holy Spirit, which occurred in three ways.
First, to create everything, as it is said: And the Spirit of God hovered over the waters.
Second, to adorn the rational creature with spiritual gifts.
Third, to be given for the forgiveness of sins, which did not happen before the coming of Christ.
So, you have discovered a treasure here, oh man, and your treasure is the expressed Holy Trinity immediately following this statement: And the Spirit of God hovered over the waters.
For the God who created is the Father; and the beginning in which He created is the Son; and the Spirit of God who hovered over the waters is the Holy Spirit.
Regarding the third person of this Holy Trinity, it is not out of place to ask, indeed it is worthy of inquiry and knowledge, why both here and throughout nearly all the pages of the Old Testament, it is called the Spirit of God or the Spirit of the Lord.
While in the Gospel, and from the very beginning of the Gospel according to Luke, it is named the Holy Spirit without reference to God or the Lord.
You will notice this if you examine the Scriptures of both the Old and New Testaments with a diligent mind or intent.
If you seek this, you will quickly find a useful solution, because the procession of this same Spirit, whom the Holy Church of Christ calls proceeding, is described by the authority of Him who says: When the Comforter comes, whom I will send to you, the Spirit of truth, who proceeds from the Father John Fifteen.
I say, this procession occurred in three ways according to the Scriptures of truth.
First, as at the beginning, of which it has already been said, to create everything.
Second, that the human creature might be adorned with spiritual gifts, among which the greatest is what was spoken through the prophets.
Third, that it might be given for repentance and forgiveness of sins, which did not happen before the coming of Christ.
Having considered these things beforehand, you clearly understand that where it first proceeded to create everything, as you have here: And the Spirit of God hovered over the waters Genesis.
It's rightly called the Spirit of God, which, as Father Augustine notes, is understood as the very goodness of God.
Because God is good, he created everything.
Where he distributes his gifts, it's referred to as the Spirit of the Lord.
For example, there's the moment when the Spirit of the Lord departed from Saul and was with David, as mentioned in First Samuel 16.
When the forgiveness of sins began with the coming of Christ, the Son of God, it started to be known by the glorious name of the Holy Spirit.
Before the arrival of the Son of God, it was given for distributing graces, but not yet for the forgiveness of sins.
Hence, it's said that the Spirit had not yet been given because Jesus had not yet been glorified, as mentioned in John 7.
Since he is the forgiveness of all sins and our sanctification, he is rightly honored with the title Holy Spirit from our lips-not because he was sanctified, but because he is sanctifying, or the sanctifier, and the sanctification itself.
We'll need to discuss this more thoroughly in its proper context, but for now, let's return to the beginning to maintain the order.
Chapter Twelve
Since both the Father and the Son are Spirit, why is this essential name, Spirit, frequently assigned to this one person in the Holy Scriptures?
Even though Scripture refers to this person as Spirit, saying, "And the Spirit of God was moving over the waters," both God Himself, whose Spirit is being mentioned, and the Beginning, that is, the Son, in whom God created the heavens and the earth, are Spirit. They are not three spirits but one, just as there are not three gods but one God.
Hence, in the Gospel, when the Son of God said, "True worshipers will worship the Father in spirit and truth, for the Father seeks such people to worship him," he immediately added, "God is Spirit, and those who worship him must worship in spirit and truth" (John chapter four).
In these words, it is not intended that spirit is the subject and God the predicate, implying "The Holy Spirit is God," although this is rightly proclaimed in its own context.
Rather, the intention is that God is the subject, and Spirit is the predicate, meaning "God is Spirit."
Indeed, as the Holy Trinity is understood here, as already mentioned: "In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth, and the Spirit of God was moving over the waters," just as God is truly proclaimed and understood as one, so too is He truly proclaimed and understood as one Spirit.
So, why is this essential name, Spirit, frequently assigned to this one person in the Holy Scriptures?
Is it because its nature is more subtle, even though there is one nature or substance of the supreme Trinity?
It is not more subtle, for there is no dissimilarity in substance, but there is a unique and very subtle operation of this person.
This Spirit is understood in God as conscience or intention is understood in the soul.
Finally, the Apostle, after saying, "For who knows a person's thoughts except the spirit of that person, which is in him," immediately added, "So also no one comprehends the thoughts of God except the Spirit of God" (First Corinthians chapter two).
The power of the Most High is the Spirit of the Father and the Son.
We understand both persons here as one God, when it is mentioned as the Spirit of God, both in this chapter and throughout the entire Holy Scripture, where the Spirit of God or the Spirit of the Lord is frequently highlighted.
If you want a distinction of persons in this context, there's an example in the Gospel where the Lord says: "For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father who speaks in you" (Matthew, Chapter 10).
The Apostle to the Galatians also says: "Because you are sons of God, God has sent the Spirit of His Son into our hearts" (Galatians, Chapter 4), and elsewhere it is stated: "If anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to Him" (Romans, Chapter 8).
I say, the power of the Most High is similar to how the Son is the strength or arm of the Lord.
Through the arm of the Lord, that is, through the Son, all of nature was created, and all creation or substance was formed.
But through this Spirit, every chosen rational creature, both angelic and human, is brought to life and lives for God.
Chapter Thirteen
On the procession of the Holy Spirit, which began when it moved over the waters, and how far this Spirit of God has advanced in its work.
Earlier, it was mentioned that the Holy Church often refers to this Spirit of God as "proceeding," using the solemn term given by the Son of God Himself. He first used this word when He said:
"When the Advocate comes, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth who proceeds from the Father." (John 15).
Where do you think the authority of this word or term comes from, if not from this very chapter of the book, as it was said:
"And the Spirit of God was moving over the waters"?
What else could moving over the waters mean but already proceeding? Everything spoken by the Son of God, made man, walking among people, and teaching, surely has authority from the holy Scriptures.
He was referring to them even when He seemed to speak something new, just as the beloved in the Song of Songs said of Him long ago:
"His eyes are like doves by streams of water, washed with milk, set by a full stream." (Song of Solomon 5).
Therefore, just as we are sure that by saying:
"I am the beginning who also speaks to you," (John 8),
He was referring, as mentioned earlier, to that chapter of the book where it is said:
"In the beginning God created the heaven and the earth,"
so too, when He said the Holy Spirit proceeds, let us not doubt that He was also referring to that, because it was written:
"And the Spirit of God was moving over the waters."
The procession of the Holy Spirit is a significant matter, beginning when it moved over the waters. Let us lift our eyes, the eyes of our inner person, the eyes of a faith that is diligent and seeking understanding, and see how far in its work this Spirit of God has proceeded. Then we will be able to somewhat comprehend the dignity or weight of this saying about the Spirit of truth, who proceeds from the Father.
Surely, when it began to proceed, when it was moving over the waters, the earth made from nothing was formless and empty, and darkness was over the face of the deep. (Genesis 1).
So, what is the current state of the earth, and what has the Almighty accomplished on it?
It's not enough to simply acknowledge that, at first, intellectual light was created.
Then, the firmament was formed amidst the waters, separating them from each other.
Next, from the dry land, which He named earth, emerged every green plant and fruit-bearing tree, each with its own seed.
Following that, the sky was adorned with the sun, moon, and stars, all arranged in an amazing order.
Afterwards, every creature that swims in the waters, flies in the air above, or walks on the land-whether on four legs, two, or crawls without legs-was made by God's command.
The most remarkable and beautiful of these creations is the human being.
Of all these things, it's written that God saw everything He had made, and it was very good.
It's not enough, as I mentioned, to just consider these aspects of God's work unless you also look ahead to see how far it has progressed and will continue to progress until the Son of Man sits on His majestic throne, with the power to judge between right and wrong.
The Son of Man, I say, is both the beginning and the pinnacle of creation, as everything was made for Him and through Him.
This aligns with the apostolic testimony, which states: "For it was fitting for Him, for whom all things exist and through whom all things exist, in bringing many children to glory, to perfect the author of their salvation through suffering" (Hebrews, Chapter Two).
Chapter Fourteen
On the procession of the Holy Spirit and how it differs from the procession of the Son.
Since the Son said, "For I have proceeded and come from God," let's carefully follow, with the glorification of the Trinity, the majesty of this procession.
Let this be for us as if to form, or by priestly right, to present the showbread from the heavenly sanctuary's table, which the Lord has prepared for us, as mentioned in Psalm Twenty-Three.
By faithfully handling the Scriptures of truth, we can offer worthy sacrifices of beautiful praise to God, as much as we are able.
First, we need to discuss what the procession or proceeding itself is, and then how the procession of the Holy Spirit differs from the procession of the Son.
For he, speaking of himself, used this word, saying to the Jews, "If God were your Father, you would love both of us. For I have proceeded and come from God.
I did not come by myself, but he sent me," as noted in the Book of John, Chapter Eight.
He mentioned two words, "proceeded" and "came," and it's too limited if you interpret these two words as meaning the same thing.
It means more than just coming into this world; he who was invisible with God appeared visibly through assumed flesh.
The understanding is broader and more enlightening if you see his two births in these two words, "proceeded" and "came."
The birth of his divinity, by which he was begotten from the substance of the Father before all ages, and the birth of his humanity, by which he was born from the substance of the mother in the world.
Although what emerged from the Virgin's womb was also a proceeding, as it is written, "And he is like a bridegroom coming out of his chamber," in Psalm Nineteen.
Also, in another Psalm, it is said to him, "Advance prosperously, proceed, and reign," found in Psalm Forty-Five.
This is rightly understood concerning his present human life, according to which it was truly said, "The child Jesus grew in age and wisdom," as recorded in the Book of Luke.
The point is that it became evident through his words and actions that he was Wisdom itself.
As it was said, it was done, and he thrived for a little more than 30 years.
After such a brief period, behold, he now reigns with great power, as he declares:
"All authority in heaven and on earth has been given to me" (Matthew chapter 28).
However, here we are discussing his earlier journey, about which he spoke with great significance:
"For I came from God" (John chapter 8).
What kind of progress or procession was it, if not that marvelous and indescribable love of the one who said:
"Let there be light, let there be a firmament" (Genesis chapter 1),
along with lights and all other things, about which the Psalmist, reflecting on that word, says:
"He established them forever and ever; he gave a decree, and it shall not pass away" (Psalm 148).
Therefore, as mentioned earlier, we should first discuss the procession itself, or the act of proceeding, and then the procession of the Son who said:
"For I came from God,"
which differs from the procession of the Holy Spirit, about whom he also said:
"Whom I will send to you, the Spirit of truth, who proceeds from the Father" (John chapter 15).
Chapter Fifteen
What does it mean to proceed, and why did he use the past tense "I proceeded" when referring to himself, but the present tense "proceeds" when referring to the Holy Spirit?
A procession is a formal departure of highly esteemed individuals, marked by a certain solemnity, presenting themselves in a way that commands respect from those watching. It's often met with great joy and delight.
As beings bound to locations, our way of proceeding is moving from place to place. However, divinity isn't bound to any location, although a place is sometimes attributed to it. For example, when someone says, "Truly, the Lord is in this place, and I did not know it" (Genesis 28).
The procession of divinity is the result of a marvelous work, through which the majesty of such great dominion is perceived and understood in the mind, just like the dignity of a venerable person is recognized from their appearance when they proceed honorably from one place to another.
Therefore, if we are open, attentive, and willing to contemplate the beauty of such a procession, the result of this work can teach us to recognize the Lord of majesty: the Lord of majesty, I say, the Son who has already proceeded, and equally the Lord of majesty, the Holy Spirit who still proceeds.
This distinction in the tenses should be carefully understood, because when speaking of himself, the Son of God used the past tense: "For I proceeded from God" (John 8), but when speaking of the Holy Spirit, he used the present tense: "Who proceeds from the Father" (John 15).
Therefore, it's not quite accurate to say that both the Son and the Holy Spirit are "proceeding," since "proceeding" is a present participle and is specifically used to refer to the Holy Spirit.
However, the Son has already proceeded, as mentioned earlier, with His procession marking the completion of the work through which God, who created everything through Him, has since ceased.
As Scripture clearly states: "And God rested on the seventh day from all His work which He had done, and He blessed the seventh day, and sanctified it, because in it He ceased from all His work which God had created to make" (Genesis 2).
Indeed, no new species of creation has been made since then that He didn't create in its kind before His rest.
Chapter Sixteen
The Son did not create all things without the cooperation of the Holy Spirit, and likewise, the Holy Spirit does not sanctify without the Son's cooperation.
Do we truly separate or allow the procession of the Holy Spirit, which continues to sanctify rational creatures, to be apart from the procession of the Son, which, as mentioned, began long ago and ceased to create new species of creatures?
Do we claim or permit the notion that the Son created without the Holy Spirit's cooperation, or that the Holy Spirit sanctifies without the Son's cooperation?
Certainly not!
The operation of the Trinity, of one God, with one and inseparable command, is indivisible.
When the Son proceeded from the mouth of the Father, saying, "Let this or that be done," the Holy Spirit guided the entire work.
And now, as the Holy Spirit continues to sanctify and moves over the waters of baptism, it is the same Spirit that hovered over the waters in the beginning, as Scripture tells us.
The Son is the judge and the efficient cause of this sanctification.
In the act where God the Father, with the Holy Spirit through the Son, created all things-all things were made through Him, and without Him, nothing was made-and now, where God the Father, with the Son, sanctifies the chosen rational creatures, delights are prepared or perfected by the cooperation of the whole Trinity.
These are the delights of love, which the Wisdom of God, the Son of God, recalls in His procession:
"When He prepared the heavens, I was there, when He set the limits of the abyss by a fixed law and circle, when He established the sky above and balanced the fountains of the waters, when He circled the sea with its boundary and set a law for the waters not to pass their limits, when He laid the foundations of the earth, I was with Him arranging all things, and I delighted every day, playing before Him all the time, playing in the world, and my delights were with the children of men" (Proverbs 8).
What does it mean when God said, "Let there be light," or when He declared, "Let there be a firmament in the midst of the waters, let the waters under the sky be gathered into one place"? Each time He spoke these words and saw that it was good, Genesis Chapter One, I emerged from His mouth, for I am that expression, or His Word.
Thus, the procession of the Son is not separated by time or place from the procession of the Holy Spirit, because these events occurred when the Spirit of God was hovering over the waters. Just as the Father is, so the Son is, and so the Holy Spirit is one God, present everywhere, and confined to no place.
The only distinction to be noted in the effect of their work is between the procession of the Son and the Holy Spirit. From the creation of creatures or substances, made through the Son, for all things were made through Him, God rested on the seventh day. However, from the sanctification of rational creatures (a work accomplished by the Holy Spirit), neither the Father nor the Son has yet rested, nor have they ceased.
This is why the Son of God said to the Jews: "My Father is working until now, and I am working." John Chapter Five.
Regarding the delights of Wisdom, it is said: "And my delight was with the sons of men." Proverbs Chapter Eight. This will be more fully explained in its special place in the work of the Trinity, namely in the making or forming of man.
Chapter Seventeen
In response to those who claimed that the Holy Spirit proceeds only from the Father and not also from the Son, Wisdom declares: "Behold, I will pour out my Spirit to you, and I will make my words known to you."
This same declaration is made to the little ones: "Behold, I will pour out my Spirit to you, and I will make my words known to you" Proverbs chapter one.
Does this not mean that Wisdom foresaw its work and has already accomplished it in its incarnate form?
For when Wisdom rose from the dead, standing among its disciples, it breathed on them, saying: "Peace be with you, receive the Holy Spirit" John chapter twenty.
And as another evangelist records: "Then he opened their minds to understand the Scriptures" Luke chapter twenty-four.
Was this not the act of Wisdom, the Son of God, to bestow the Holy Spirit and reveal its words?
Also, in the same book, it is written: "Wisdom has built its house, it has hewn out its seven pillars" Proverbs chapter nine.
This suggests that the Word of God, the Son of God, took on human nature, and into that nature infused the Holy Spirit in its sevenfold form.
We mention this because there were some, particularly among the Greeks, who argued that the Holy Spirit proceeds only from the Father and not also from the Son.
However, the holy Roman Church, the pillar of the Latin Church, has long since refuted this through many councils, shining with the light of the gospel and standing firmly on the rock of faith, with Athanasius, the Catholic and orthodox, as its ally among the Greeks.
Therefore, we do not need to add anything except to voluntarily offer our support to this procession with our words, and in writing about such matters, we find a certain sweet delight in the depths of our hearts.
This delight is doubled and brings even greater joy to those observing such a procession when reason also supports it with the authority of the Scriptures.
Thus, our innermost faith does not doubt that this Spirit proceeds equally from the Son and the Father, God from God, not differing in substance, equal to both in majesty, yet not equal in glory.
To fully appreciate the procession and discuss meaningful topics in an engaging way, we first need to explore the various modes of the Holy Spirit's procession.
Chapter Eighteen
Reflecting on the same truth, it's significant what the Son said on the night He was betrayed:
"But I tell you the truth, it is to your advantage that I go away; for if I do not go away, the Helper will not come to you; but if I go, I will send Him to you."
This was mentioned earlier, but it needs to be repeated and explained more fully because the procession of the Holy Spirit is described in three ways according to the Scriptures.
First, so that in the beginning, that is, in the Son or through the Son, all things might be created, as it's said:
"And the Spirit of God was hovering over the waters,"
which describes the greatest and most beautiful creation, the intellectual light, namely the angelic beings.
Second, so that humans might be adorned with spiritual gifts, among which the greatest is what was spoken through the prophets.
Third, so that it might be given for repentance and the forgiveness of sins, which didn't happen before Christ's coming.
Regarding this effect of the procession, given for the forgiveness of sins, who would doubt to say this, because in this way the Holy Spirit also proceeds from the Son?
We'll discuss later about the gift through which the Spirit distributes various graces, as it also proceeds from the Son.
Let's focus now on what is given for the forgiveness of sins, without which no human has ever been or will ever be saved.
I hope the faithful listener will accept this gladly and effectively.
"I am going," says the Son of God Himself, "to Him who sent Me, and none of you asks Me, 'Where are you going?' But because I have spoken these things to you, sorrow has filled your heart.
But I tell you the truth: it is to your advantage that I go away. For if I do not go away, the Helper will not come to you; but if I go, I will send Him to you" (John 16).
I'm truly amazed by how some great and holy Fathers have interpreted this passage.
They suggested that the apostles of Christ couldn't experience spiritual love for the Lord unless His physical presence was withdrawn.
This is what He meant when He said:
"For if I do not go away, the Helper will not come to you; but if I go, I will send him to you."
However, this interpretation doesn't quite capture the full majesty of the sacrament being discussed in that most holy supper. I must say, given the significance of the matter, this explanation is good but feels a bit lacking.
Furthermore, it's fair to say that this didn't occur solely because of what was foretold here. Sadness filled their hearts when He took away His physical presence by ascending into heaven. Yet, as Luke describes more clearly, they were even more joyful:
"And it happened, while he blessed them, he was parted from them and carried up into heaven, and they worshiped and returned to Jerusalem with great joy" (Luke 24).
So, why were they supposed to be sad, or why did sadness fill their hearts?
It was certainly because of His death, which brought them sorrow until Mary Magdalene announced His resurrection to those who had been mourning and weeping, as Mark tells us (Mark 16).
Was this, He said, to go to the Father, namely to die?
Because He said: "And now I am going to him who sent me." Clearly, this was to go to the Father, from whom He would be crowned with glory and honor because of His suffering and death (Hebrews 2).
Doesn't this evangelist also mention at the beginning of the same discourse?
Jesus, knowing that His hour had come to depart from this world to the Father (John 13).
Likewise, He knew that the Father had given all things into His hands, and that He had come from God and was going to God.
Chapter Nineteen
Once again, on the same topic, let's consider that the Holy Spirit was first called the Paraclete, which means comforter, because He embodies the forgiveness of sins.
Notably, forgiveness wasn't given before, as Jesus had not yet been glorified.
So, to say something that matches the gravity of the Lord's words:
But I tell you the truth: it is better for you (John, Chapter 16).
It's important to note that before that sacred supper, during which He spoke these words, the Holy Spirit was not called the Paraclete.
It takes a learned mind to understand why this name, Paraclete, which translates to comforter in Latin, was used.
Understanding this helps us see why it was so significant that He called the Holy Spirit the Paraclete at that specific moment.
(Which He hadn't done before, neither by Himself nor through the prophets).
What was happening at that time?
It was a time of suffering, a time of glorification; indeed, His hour was approaching for Him to pass from this world to the Father through the suffering of death.
And this was so that we could receive the forgiveness of sins.
For otherwise, our sins wouldn't be forgiven, except through His blood.
And what, I ask, is the first or greatest consolation of all the saints, if not the forgiveness of sins?
Therefore, when He says: If I do not go away, the Paraclete will not come to you, He means:
If I do not pass from this world through the suffering of death, the Holy Spirit will not be given to you, nor to those before or after you, according to this gift, which is the forgiveness of sins.
This is why He is rightly called and truly is the comforter.
And when He adds: But if I go, I will send Him to you, He clearly indicates that this comforter comes from Him.
This Holy Spirit is the forgiver of sins and the forgiveness itself.
And who, except an unbeliever, would doubt or fail to know that the forgiveness of sins comes to us from this person, from this Son of God?
Doesn't the truth of the Gospel make this clearer than daylight for us, when He Himself said: "But if I go, I will send Him to you."
After He left, He returned and stood among His disciples, breathing on them and saying, "Receive the Holy Spirit."
Immediately, He added, "Whose sins you forgive, they are forgiven them" (John, Chapter 20).
Indeed, the Holy Spirit is not a physical breath, yet through this word, He breathed, two things are made clear to us: that this encouragement comes from Him and that through this Holy Spirit, sins are forgiven as easily as one can breathe when they wish.
Many things come to mind that support this truth with reason, so to make this lengthy discussion less tedious, it's as if we need to pause and conclude this little book.