Book One
Chapter One
It's impossible to truly aid in the salvation of souls without acknowledging the mortality of our bodies.
Those who reflect on or experience the confines of this life and the heavy burden on humanity from birth until burial lament with the Apostle, saying:
"Wretched man that I am! Who will rescue me from this body of death?"
Romans chapter seven.
Anyone who encounters tribulation and pain, with a contrite heart, echoes the Psalmist:
"By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat down and wept when we remembered Zion."
Psalm one thirty-seven.
Adam lost sight of the highest good when he wrongly desired the forbidden fruit, succumbing to the woman's persuasion.
The Apostle says:
"Adam was not deceived, but the woman was deceived and became a transgressor."
First Timothy chapter two.
Thus, Adam sinned knowingly, discontent with paradise's delights, and arrogantly sought to elevate himself by disobedience, wanting to be like God.
Not understanding his honor, he was likened to senseless beasts.
Psalm forty-nine.
Deprived of God's likeness, he was led by carnal desires and uncontrolled impulses, as the Apostle James states:
"Desire, when it has conceived, gives birth to sin; and sin, when it is full-grown, brings forth death."
James chapter one.
And alas! How bitter the sting of that sin has become for humanity!
This is most evident in those who are dying.
I admit, in my own misery, that while sitting by the beds of many, I have sorrowfully witnessed their pain and anguish, troubled as one who must also face death and fearing the same fate.
Not to mention many others, I saw one of our brothers suffer terribly for almost forty days, refusing food and only occasionally gesturing for water.
A feast was indeed prepared for us, and what bitterness Eve brought upon us as she wandered with her feet and eyes through that place of delight.
She crossed the boundaries of radiant joy with uncontrolled curiosity, eager to see what the world beyond was like.
Then, the fallen Satan seized the chance to oppose by using the serpent, the most cunning of all the creatures the Lord God had created on earth.
With his sweet, deceitful words, he drew closer and entered.
It's truly absurd to think he was in paradise speaking to the woman, especially since he was possessed by the devil, who had surely been cast out from the kingdom of God and the sacred seats due to his pride.
But if serpents were there, why not also allow lions, wolves, or other animals, like hairy-bearded goats or bucks that might harm the aromatic shrubs with their bites and leap through the flowery fields?
Could owls respond, and sirens, as if in a temple of pleasure, disrupt the angelic melody?
Let not moles dig and disturb the living land by burrowing and excavating, nor bats flutter around, while perpetual day never fades into night there.
Indeed, that pure and special abode accepts none of these things; it was uniquely granted by God's bounty to humans alone, nor could the evil beast, the treacherous Behemoth, ever pass through it.
Rather, it is the one who said: "I will ascend into heaven, I will exalt my throne above the stars of God, I will sit on the mount of the assembly, in the far north; I will ascend above the heights of the clouds; I will be like the Most High, and I am God, and I sat on the throne of God, and set his heart like the heart of God".
As its name suggests, the creature-Behemoth, meaning beast-is already sinking to the lowest depths.
It becomes an irrational reptile, taking on the heart and tongue of a wandering serpent.
Through its mouth, this completely irrational creature speaks these words to the woman as if they were words of reason, or rather, it hisses:
"Why did God command you not to eat from any tree in the garden?" Genesis 3.
How does it lie?
How does the deceiver distort and undermine the words of God? It's truly said about him that he was a murderer from the beginning and did not stand in the truth.
There is no truth in him, and when he lies, he speaks from his own nature, because he is a liar and the father of lies.
John 8.
In fact, God allowed Adam to enjoy all the trees in the garden, except one.
The woman admits: "We eat from the fruit of the trees in the garden, but about the tree in the middle of the garden, God commanded us not to eat from it and not to touch it, lest we die."
Genesis 3.
Oh, how the woman's mind is already subverted and reckless!
She dared to alter the truth of the divine decree by adding what God had not said-that we should not touch it.
What was established with the gravest warning and certainty, "for on the day you eat from it, you will surely die," she considered lightly and doubtfully, adding "lest we die."
How mournful, how sorrowful is that "perhaps," and to what extent, to what outcome it has led, is more to be reflected on with grief than spoken about with words.
Without a doubt, the one speaking through the serpent outwardly had already tested the minds of Paradise's inhabitants within, finding them ready and inclined to agree with him.
As even blessed Pope Gregory said: "Unless they had first swelled with pride within, they would not have so easily given in to temptation externally."
The wicked deceiver, aiming to be seen as truthful and benevolent while painting God as a liar and envious, said once more to the woman:
"You will not die at all; for God knows that on the day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened, and you will be like gods, knowing good and evil."
Chapter Two
Just like Leviathan, which means "their addition," the wicked serpent led those it poisoned to death, dragging them to destruction.
While promising them divinity, it added endless woes, much like Eve's name, which brings infinite sorrow.
It would be more fitting to call her the mother of all dying people rather than the mother of the living.
From her, all of Adam's descendants face miserable death unless they are brought to life by Christ.
The woman saw that the tree was good for food, pleasing to the eyes, and desirable, so she took its fruit and ate it.
She also gave some to her husband, who ate it, and their eyes were opened.
Genesis 3:6-7.
Before the serpent's conversation, the woman had indeed seen the tree but hadn't touched it.
Now, however, she is noted for having seen it and curiously examined it to experience its nature herself and judge by her own taste whether God or the serpent, who presented opposing claims, was telling the truth.
Although she knew the serpent, like other animals, was irrational, she believed it was speaking through another spirit and thought it was addressing her with divine guidance.
So she agreed, reached out, and grabbed the fruit, recklessly satisfying her deadly appetite.
She also impulsively and insistently persuaded her husband to do the same.
The wretched man obeyed her, weakening his masculine spirit out of foolish compassion, not wanting to separate from his partner.
Thus, he transgressed into his and our death.
Alas, alas, alas!
Disobedient to the true life, which is the Holy Trinity.
In the book "On Genesis to the Letter," the esteemed scholar Augustine says:
When Adam ate from the forbidden tree after the woman, he did so because he didn't want to upset her.
He thought she might wither away without his support if they were spiritually separated, and that discord would lead to her ruin.
He wasn't driven by physical desire, which he hadn't yet experienced due to the struggle between his body's law and his mind's law.
Instead, it was a kind of friendly goodwill, which often leads to offending God as one tries not to turn a friend into an enemy.
Therefore, he was deceived in another way, but I don't believe he could have been misled by the same deceit that tricked the woman.
The Apostle called this deception, meaning that false advice was believed to be true.
It was suggested that God prohibited them from touching that tree because He feared they would become like gods, as if He begrudged them divinity.
Even if curiosity led the man to feel a sense of pride, which God, who examines hearts, would have seen, I don't think that a spiritually minded person could believe the Lord forbade the tree out of envy, especially after seeing the woman hadn't died from eating the fruit.
Chapter Three
When you were in Liege, O William, we often discussed the ideas of this and other learned men.
By diligently examining and debating with each other in a friendly manner, we enriched each other with the fragrance of intellectual debates.
You, a scholar, did not disdain to learn from me, though I am unlearned, what I thought.
So much so that you even, when absent, would frequently urge me through letters.
You considered me sleepy and lazy if I did not reply immediately.
You were so accepting of my modest intellect that you did not criticize, no matter how hastily or awkwardly my writing may have been.
I devoted myself entirely to friendliness and, in return, sought knowledge from you.
You were adorned with philosophy, both divine and human, and your conversation enriched knowledge.
Though young in age, you shaped old age with wisdom.
As an old man once said, "The understanding of a person is grey hair, and an immaculate life is old age" (Wisdom of Solomon, Chapter Four).
Indeed, you called wisdom your sister and discretion your friend, since you so diligently avoided the company of women, who are certainly clever and effective at seduction.
You carefully attended to Solomon's saying: "A woman's soul captures a precious man's soul" (Proverbs, Chapter Six).
However, as it is written: "Grace upon grace is a holy and modest woman, and like the rising sun in the highest places of God, so is the beauty of a good woman as an ornament" (Sirach, Chapter Twenty-Six).
Nevertheless, like a prudent and cautious animal, you avoided the trap and reined in chastity, not despising the female sex but rather fearing sin and vice, as the Apostle said: "Do not be proud but fear" (Romans, Chapter Eleven).
Because from a woman sin began, and through her, we all die.
And we could not speak of the fate of that mutual friend of ours whom you knew without a sob and a certain groan of the heart.
While he was among us, he honored the habit of holy religion with a religious and celibate life.
However, he was assigned the provision of a cell in a certain desert, where he continued the duties of good exercise as an industrious hermit.
However, later on, trusting in his own maturity and forgetting that even the Son of God was tempted by the devil in the desert, he unwisely surrounded himself with frivolous women he had carelessly gathered.
In a place meant for penance, secular songs were performed, and the allure of music echoed so loudly that I imagine even the wild animals would flee in astonishment.
But can a man hide fire in his bosom without his clothes catching fire?
Or walk on hot coals without burning his feet?
Caution should never be absent, even in the most advanced years.
Even in limbs cold and weakened by age, reckless heat can creep in.
The careless and complacent are easily caught in snares.
Therefore, the enemy, who always imitates virtues, must be vigilantly watched.
Moreover, the more remote a place is, the more it seems to invite foolish people to sin.
This resulted in situations that arose from the church, sacred matters, and dwellings, which are more deserving of mourning than of writing about.
In a spiritual person, my brother, the spirit is indeed willing, but the flesh is weak.
If the mind is even slightly relaxed, it quickly becomes wanton and is stirred, with the chattering law of the mind, which is embedded in the members, rebuking it.
Truly, people are like grass.
How unstable and weak is man!
Even the strongest leader, Samson, an invincible hero against a thousand enemy troops, was defeated by a seductive prostitute and driven to death by a lost love.
He learned bitterly that though the lips of a prostitute are like a dripping honeycomb and her throat smoother than oil, her end is as bitter as wormwood and as sharp as a two-edged sword; her feet descend to death, and her steps lead straight to the grave: many are the wounded she has cast down, and all who were mighty have been killed by her.
Chapter Four
Indeed, who can truly explain how much women have been the cause of various troubles throughout the nations?
It's enough to mention that around the time of Samson, thirty-eight thousand two hundred people were killed over the abduction of a single infamous woman.
In the ten-year war between the Greeks and the Trojans, one million six hundred thousand people were also killed, as Dares Phrygius, who was there, wrote.
Clearly, for such a small amount of virtue and glory, and for the supposed advantage of strength, Europe and Asia were so shaken that many powerful and famous men perished from the world.
Don't you recall, you guide of the schools, that poetic line:
"Whenever kings go mad, the Greeks are punished, and within and outside the walls of Troy, there is sin through sedition, deceit, crime, lust, and anger."
(Horace, Epistle one, two, fourteen to sixteen)
But hell has enlarged its appetite and opened its mouth without limit, and its strong ones and people, its lofty and glorious ones, have descended into it.
Woe to the world for its scandals!
(Matthew eighteen)
Here, there is no harbor of perfect peace.
The little boat of human life is always tossed by the waves of temptations.
Sometimes the force of the storm moves the rock from its place, and the righteous person is driven from the state of justice by the force of temptation.
David, the most excellent Psalmist of the Holy Spirit, who was anointed with the full horn of spiritual grace, about whom God said: "I have found David, the son of Jesse, a man after my own heart, who will do all my will" (Acts thirteen), was himself driven and overthrown by the desire for Uriah's wife, but the Lord accepted him when he repented.
Solomon, about whom it is written: "The Lord loved him and sent a message through Nathan the prophet, and called his name Jedidiah, which means 'beloved of the Lord'" (Second Samuel twelve), who was wiser than all men, so much so that the breadth of his heart was compared to the sand on the seashore, to whom God said: "Behold, I have done according to your words and have given you a wise and discerning heart, so that there has been none like you before, nor shall any arise after you" (First Kings three).
He, who is said to be wiser than Ethan the Ezrahite, Heman, Calcol, and Darda, the sons of Mahol, as mentioned in First Kings Chapter Four, became so foolishly infatuated with the love of women that he unprecedentedly turned into an idolater and built shrines for the images of foreign nations.
Yet, his praise is such that he is mentioned as superior to the greatest patriarchs.
Ethan is interpreted as "very hard," Ezrahite as "eastern"; and he represents Abraham, a man with a very hard spirit due to his solid faith and constant justice. He was radiant in lineage and powerful in strength, as he defeated four kings in one military campaign, originating from the eastern region of Chaldea.
Heman is interpreted as "faithful," and he is the lawgiver Moses, about whom the Lord spoke to Aaron and Miriam: "If there is a prophet among you, I, the Lord, will appear to him in a vision, or I will speak to him in a dream. But not so with my servant Moses, who is most faithful in all my house: I speak to him face to face and openly; he sees the Lord not through riddles and figures," as stated in Numbers Chapter Twelve.
Calcol is interpreted as "governing"; and he is the increasing son of Joseph: an increasing son, who, after God turned Jacob's back from burdens, after his hands served in the basket, grew so much that he was called the Savior of the world by the Egyptians because of his supreme prudence and industry in governance-a truly wise and understanding man, who held power because of his innocence and the prerogative of chastity.
Darda is interpreted as "generation of knowledge"; Mahol, as "indulgence." And we take the generation of the patriarchs and prophets, namely the sons of Jacob, a very indulgent man: to all of whom Solomon is preferred in wisdom.
Chapter Five
William, as the Apostle Peter warns us, the devil prowls like a roaring lion looking for someone to devour, as stated in First Peter, chapter five.
It's crucial for anyone who is modest and sober to avoid the scandals of impurity and unchastity.
One should also be cautious of gatherings, whispers, and the deceptions of women.
Many have had their status shaken or overturned by these issues, including numerous monks.
Follow the example of the evangelical Publican: strike yourself with whips and beat yourself, oh tearful man.
These monks have committed to this discipline, and neither writings nor examples can persuade them to be less generous than necessary.
This ensures that brothers aren't excessively liberal with sisters, and sisters with brothers.
I remember a person who was considered splendid and great among secular people, who fell from grace in our time.
Under the guise of holiness, which he was pretending, he was often visited, and many things were given to him.
He acted like those whom the Lord warned, "Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, who devour widows' houses and for a pretense make long prayers. Therefore, you will receive greater condemnation," as noted in Matthew, chapter twenty-three.
On festive days, he would secretly leave his cell, living alone on a mountain, and hide in any dug-out place as if disturbed and hindered from contemplation or prayers.
But death entered through his windows because he became too close to a young woman serving him.
He engaged more freely with her, not restraining his mouth, ears, or eyes, nor the window of his cell from lustfulness.
Blind and foolish, even though he knew the danger to his soul, he was ensnared and tangled in the ropes of sin.
He became both a violator of chastity and a deserter of his purpose.
With that mistress of his, or rather an owl by night, he fled as if escaping the day and confinement, burdened with the money he had amassed.
You knew some very religious people, brave one, who would harshly criticize others for the smallest faults, while trying to hide their own major faults as if covered by a cloak of goat hair or sackcloth.
These were men of virtue, wielding Solomon's saying like Hercules' club against their subordinates:
Ecclesiasticus nineteen verse one, "Whoever neglects little things will gradually fall,"
as if Christ hadn't also said about such people:
"Blind guides, who strain out a gnat but swallow a camel" Matthew twenty-three verse twenty-four.
And elsewhere:
"Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, because you are like whitewashed tombs, which appear beautiful outwardly to people, but inside are full of the bones of the dead and all kinds of filth; in the same way, you appear righteous to people on the outside, but inside you are full of hypocrisy and wickedness" Matthew twenty-three verses twenty-seven through twenty-eight.
Chapter Six
The ancient enemy, who suffered a great fall with his followers, not only attacks openly like a lion but also, like the serpent that deceived Eve and the great dragon who enchants the world, secretly watches over and seeks the downfall of the good with all sorts of harmful arts, pressing on the awake and the asleep with countless illusions.
Once, as we discussed these matters with a brother and turned the pages of the deeds of the saints, we came across a passage about two brothers from the Picentine province, Victorinus and Severinus.
In their youth, after both their parents passed away, they sold all their inherited property and gave it to the poor.
Like the apostles, they forsook everything to be rewarded with apostolic grace.
They built a small cell in a remote area where they lived together.
They owned nothing individually, yet lacked nothing necessary.
They served each other and built each other up with their virtues.
They were never apart, teaching each other through mutual care, so it could rightly be said of them: "Behold, how good and pleasant it is when brothers dwell in unity" (Psalm one hundred thirty-three).
Meanwhile, Victorinus, striving for higher things and believing any step back was not a step towards perfection, thought it was more worthwhile to embrace a solitary life than to enjoy brotherly companionship and comfort, even though Ecclesiastes says: "Two are better than one; because they have a good reward for their labor. If one falls, the other will lift him up" (Ecclesiastes four).
He left his brother and retreated to the desert.
A river flowed past a steep, high cliff, surrounding a very narrow cave there.
He was glad to have, for free, the walls that nature, as an artisan, had built.
They were such that he could only rest by sitting, not lying down.
If he had welcomed a guest, the host would have to stand.
The duties of vigils, prayers, fasting, and sacred readings were frequently observed.
The one who envied Adam and Eve their paradise also envied Victorinus for his great diligence.
This wanderer of the earth schemes, setting a trap to deceive a stranger from the heavens.
The one who often disguises himself as an angel of light transforms into a girl, acting lost, knocks on the hermit's door, complaining about the dark night, raising cries, and pretending to cry.
She claims to have wandered into remote thorny paths, fears the teeth of wild animals, and asks only for one night's shelter.
The man feels pity for the miserable girl, fearing he would be guilty if he denied hospitality; he couldn't believe she was an enemy, only a guest.
So he opens the door and lets her in.
Not even an hour had passed, and the one thought to be a girl began plotting something wicked as the tempter moved about.
For demons are utterly restless, as Isaiah testifies: "There is no peace for the wicked," says the Lord.
With a deceitful sting like a scorpion, the tempter inflamed the man, already agitated by irreligious thoughts, with a sudden heat, especially as the face was blooming with a certain beauty, and the shining eyes sparkled even in the dark.
Then, seductive and soft speech leads to contamination.
Who can trust themselves?
Holy Spirit, how different is your warmth from such heat!
How can a harmful fire in anyone's body be extinguished except by your dew?
It is yours alone to grant the gift of self-control and the guardianship of purity.
But Victorinus was defeated, and before he was humbled, he sinned, because he needed to learn not to think of himself more highly than he should, but to think with sober judgment.
For at his fall, the ancient deceiver and fallen apostate mocked him with these jeers:
"What now, most praiseworthy hermit, who found even the company of a brother burdensome?
Look, you have joined another, and lost your chastity among the rocks of the forest, which you had kept amid the twists and turns of the world.
Did you think chastity was invincible even among the solitary?"
Caution is essential everywhere, whether in the world or the wilderness: holiness can be tested.
I constantly battle against this, and sometimes I manage to overcome it.
But then, like smoke, it slips away from my grasp.
Chapter Seven
The Lord, who is merciful to all and does not despise anything He has made, overlooks human sins for the sake of repentance and spares them, because He does not desire the death of a sinner, but rather that they turn back and live.
He took pity on Victorinus and turned him to repentance so that he might live.
Indeed, after facing temptation, Victorinus came to his senses, broke away from delays, and returned to his brother.
Though he held back his voice for a long time out of shame, he eventually revealed his tearful state to him.
Thinking as a Christian and hoping as a Catholic, he believed that with the Lord there is mercy and abundant redemption, as stated in Psalm one hundred and twenty-nine.
And that: If we judged ourselves, we would not be judged, as noted in First Corinthians chapter eleven.
He appointed himself as his own judge and avenger, condemning himself with a severe sentence.
He cut down a tree, inserted his hand, and wedged it so tightly in the split that he could neither withdraw nor move it at all, effectively imprisoning his whole body with the confinement of one limb.
But Severinus informed the bishop of the diocese about his brother's actions and the severity of the punishment.
The bishop, coming to release Victorinus from the predicament, wanted to guide him to a reasonable form of penance.
However, Victorinus refused, being well influenced by the apostolic oracle: We know that if the earthly tent we live in is destroyed, we have a building from God, a house not made with hands, eternal in the heavens, as noted in Second Corinthians chapter five.
On the contrary, the bishop decided not to disturb him, recognizing his episcopal life and knowledge, and blessed the good end of his endurance before departing.
Thus, Victorinus presented his body as a living sacrifice, pleasing to God, through his reasonable service by praying, keeping vigil, and fasting.
On all other days, he abstained, taking only a little bread and water on the Lord's Day, even doing so at the urging of his brother, who joined him in penance with truly commendable brotherly affection, partaking of no other food or drink than his brother.
Consider, O William, the meals of John the Baptist and these.
He was the cook of the desert, preparing locusts in the sun and savoring them with wild honey.
Do you question whether he is more refined than those who repent, who, like the Psalmist, ate ashes like bread and mixed their drinks with tears?
Just like John, they were clothed in soft garments made of camel hair and wore leather belts around their waists, alongside some of our abstinent people and legal experts.
The ten dishes of the Ten Commandments are scarcely enough, much like the ten changes of clothing, a blessing offered by Naaman the Syrian to the prophet Elisha.
Chapter Eight
My friend, it's incredible how quickly we can make a mistake that we may regret for a long time!
A wound can be inflicted in an instant, but it might take a long time to heal.
Victorinus was deeply troubled by just one instance of being deceived by the devil!
It's hard to explain such intense repentance, especially when you consider the hardships and needs faced by someone so burdened.
Those who sin in many ways, confess half-heartedly, and repent weakly often don't consider this.
They think they can quickly free themselves from any sin with just a little penitence, like Samson breaking ropes or chains, while confessors reluctantly pour oil and wine on those who don't understand.
Yet, they don't stop sinning, but keep repeating actions that need repentance, not just minor sins, but serious ones, as it's written: "Cursed is he who sins with hope."
They abuse God's patience, carelessly saying, "The Lord is compassionate and gracious, slow to anger and abounding in love" Psalm One Hundred Three, as if it isn't also said elsewhere: "I have kept silent, I have been quiet, I have been patient, but now I will cry out like a woman in labor" Isaiah Forty-Two.
You read about a priest from the region of Abricantine, who lived despicably, driven by carnal desires, like the sons of Eli, the sons of Belial.
His lack of self-control showed that he neither knew divine things nor the duty of a priest to the people.
Because of him, people spoke badly of the Lord's sacrifice, because when someone's behavior is wicked, it follows that their ministry will be disapproved of by the people.
Yet, he sometimes felt remorse.
But since he had no deep roots of sincerity, he was quickly torn away by the urge of lust, and he quickly fell away from sobriety when tempted.
Nevertheless, for his enormous sins, he traveled to Rome every year and visited the shrines of the apostles Peter and Paul.
But what good was this if he didn't amend his ways?
After returning home, like a dog returning to its vomit or a pig to wallowing in the mud, he went back to his filthy ways, not realizing in his foolishness that repentance is worthless unless the sin is corrected.
The Book of Wisdom asks, if someone is baptized by a dead person and then touches him again, what's the point of being washed?
In the same way, if someone fasts but continues in sin, what benefit do they gain from humbling themselves?
Who will listen to their prayers?
(Ecclesiasticus Chapter Thirty-Four).
In the ninth year, upon returning from Rome as a troublemaker, he met a horrific death.
It's shameful to say, but he died in the midst of sinful pleasures, his soul condemned to the depths of hell.
As you know, something similar happened here not too long ago.
A certain soldier, worldly and living in sin, while visiting a mistress at night, told his squire that he noticed a foul and unbearable stench.
Despite being warned by such signs, he ignored them, not realizing what awaited those who seek pleasure.
That same night, while with a prostitute, he was suffocated.
"How long, O sons of men, will you be heavy-hearted?" (Psalms Chapter Four).
How many are blinded by lust, and since fools are infinite in number (Ecclesiastes Chapter One), how many truly shine with chastity?
People often use their fragile nature as an excuse, as if no effort is needed to produce grain, and virtue comes as easily as free gold.
The Fathers showed that chastity is achieved through great discipline of mind and body.
In pure simplicity, they longed for heavenly peace, like a dove escaping earthly ties to find rest.
They withdrew, seeking solitude, like that remarkable hermit we sing about:
"In the desert caves during your youth, fleeing the crowds, so that your life remained unstained by gossip.
O exceedingly blessed and of high merit, your purity remained spotless!"
Seeing and hearing worldly things often bring great harm.
How can chastity be maintained amidst worldly delights and temptations?
In this context, you consistently and kindly reminded your students, while I would occasionally join in and celebrate their admirable efforts.
I might say something, like these lines from the poet:
"The trainer truly guides the horse with a gentle neck to follow the path the rider indicates. Since the hunting dog first barked at the deer skin in the hall, the young dog has served in the woods. Now, with a pure heart, take these words, young man, and offer yourself to greater things. The jar will long retain the scent of what it was once filled with."
Horace, Epistles, Book One, Chapter Two, Verses 64 to 70.
Chapter Nine
For three years, Victorinus suffered physically from his ordeal, yet his spirit remained strong, demonstrating the truth of the holy scripture:
"My flesh is clothed with worms and clods of dust; my skin is broken and has become loathsome; I am compared to dirt and have become like ashes and dust" from the Book of Job, Chapter Seven.
When the venerable bishop I mentioned earlier, along with the entire surrounding community, witnessed such great repentance and weariness, they were deeply moved and rushed to his aid.
Although Victorinus resisted, the bishop released him from the tree, making him more victorious than the one who shamefully entangled us by eating from the forbidden tree in paradise.
However, I have read elsewhere that his penance was even more severe than I described and that his release was even more miraculous.
It is said he placed both hands inside the hollow of the tree and hung there for three years without his feet touching the ground.
When the people wanted to take him down by force, he requested a three-day fast for this purpose.
Finally, he was freed by a heavenly fire that came with thunder, burning the knots that bound him, a sign of appeasement to God not less significant than when divine fire consumed the pleasing sacrifices of the Fathers.
Thus, having overcome human nature through patience, he lived a remarkably holy life, like the angels, apostolic in his works and victorious against demons, for indeed the hand of the Lord was with him.
Therefore, with the willing consent of the clergy and people, he was elevated as the bishop of the city of Amiternum, for "whoever humbles himself will be exalted," says the Lord.
He ruled over his subjects like the gentle Moses, a sanctuary of piety and forgiveness, for he had learned to forgive the sins of the fallen.
He also achieved martyrdom under the reign of Emperor Nerva, and while serving the second Adam, that is, Christ, he passed into paradise with the victorious palm.
Severinus, his brother, was equally distinguished in holiness.
He was a modest man and had great self-discipline, which led to his appointment as bishop in the city of Septipedana due to his exceptional grace.
He greatly honored the Church with both regular discipline and the splendor of sacred ornaments, surpassing those who came before him.
Although his life was short, he achieved much, as mentioned in the Book of Wisdom, Chapter Four.
He passed away like the patriarch Abraham, living a complete and mature life, reaching a good old age full of days, and was gathered to the people of the saints, as described in Genesis, Chapter Twenty-Five.
He had a tomb where he also established a monastery.
People frequently visited him there, receiving both the protection of prayers and the benefit of healings, as if he were still alive, having been written in the Book of Life in Jerusalem.
At one of his festivals, a priest named Innocent, who lived up to his name, was traveling to see him.
Innocent was a true Israelite, in whom there was no deceit, and he owned just one small sheep.
This sheep followed him to a river called Flosor, which had risen due to the rains.
The shepherds had built a small bridge across it, making it possible to cross.
Innocent managed to cross somehow; however, the little sheep, unsure of the narrow bridge, ran back and forth, expressing its distress with a trembling tail and shaking wool.
Then, amid its plaintive bleats, a clear voice sounded, exclaiming like a father: "To whom have you left me, poor little one?"
"In the name of Jesus the Lord," he said, "cross safely." You would think the little creature was supported by some kind of faith, as it crossed with steady and swift feet, without veering to either side.
Now, disciplined man, do not be amazed at the speaking donkey's tongue and eloquent throat, which echoed the unheard trumpet of rebuke at Balaam, who was harshly striking it with cruel kicks and a barbaric club. Since you have a purified and calm ear, what would you have found more pleasing to hear-Balaam arguing with his donkey, or Innocent speaking with his little sheep?
The audience on both sides was truly impressive.
However, if you tend to favor the little sheep more, you'd be seen as a discerning critic.
The little sheep, by staying obedient, didn't cause any trouble for the teacher.
Meanwhile, the little donkey, by resisting, almost ended up injuring the rider's foot.
Chapter Ten
Finally, William, as a passionate follower of evangelical perfection, you sold all your possessions and gave them to Christ through the poor.
By carrying your cross, you truly earned the right to be called a disciple of Christ, leaving behind your role as a schoolteacher.
So, what were you up to back then, with your foundations secured, when you would arrive unexpectedly and knock, only to be reluctantly let in?
I'll let you keep that secret: good for you!
Indeed, you imitated Christ like the glorious martyr Lawrence when you girded yourself with a towel, poured water into a basin, and washed the feet of the poor, wiping them with the towel and your hair as you shed tears over them.
Didn't you also perform the generous acts of Mary, as if you were anointing Jesus with perfume from an alabaster jar of charity, when you cared so generously for Jesus' least ones?
It soon became clear that you belonged to those of whom the Lord spoke through Hosea: "I will draw them with cords of Adam, with bands of love" (Hosea 11).
You sought Fusmacum and embraced monastic philosophy to take upon yourself the yoke of Christ, who said: "Learn from me, for I am gentle and humble in heart, and you will find rest for your souls. For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light" (Matthew 11).
Indeed, many years ago, inspired by the Lord, you left your land, your family, and your father's house, never to return, perhaps because it is written: "No one who puts a hand to the plow and looks back is fit for the kingdom of God" (Luke 9).
Like Lot's wife, who was forbidden by the angels to look back, you did not turn into a pillar of salt by looking back with tasteless curiosity at the sulfurous fires of the sinful region.
Not long ago, a brother of excellent reputation from the monastery of Seven Fountains came to me, since I was his relative, and asked me to accompany him to greet his parents and friends.
But as he went on his way, he suddenly became astonished and started speaking disdainfully about meeting and interacting with women.
He mentioned that the city, as he remembered from his boyhood, had changed quite a bit.
The houses were different, and the citizens seemed different as well, with hardly any relatives left.
He regretted coming back.
He thought it was safest not to leave the monastery's enclosure, believing that a wolf always sets traps for the lamb and a fish should stay in the water to avoid the net.
So, I won't say he left slowly; it was more like he was fleeing.
Our friend from Fontensis boldly declared that he would not return again.
Furthermore, even though you had decided not to impose your presence on your friends, why didn't you at least send letters sometimes to show that you remembered the old affection and literary friendship?
Unless, of course, someone might say such a letter of goodwill is unnecessary.
However, it makes sense to share spiritual writings with spiritual friends.
So, in loving and writing, I consider myself more justified, as I send books to those who send no letters.
But perhaps you'll claim the large distances, road difficulties, and lack of couriers.
A negligent person easily finds excuses.
Nevertheless, please accept this little work "On the Progress of Death," and add it to the piece I composed a few days ago, which I titled "Tears" according to its subject. Indeed, what I write may be less suitable and fruitful for anyone, but I benefit from practicing my modest talent and somewhat overcoming the troubles of idleness. As you know, someone once said:
"Control your mind, which unless it obeys, commands; curb it with reins, restrain it with chains." (Horace, Epistles I, 2, 62-63.)
And since you enjoy stories of accomplished deeds, just as one might delight in a meadow painted with flowers, I decorate this writing with deeds, as if with various colors.
What I began to write at the beginning of this book, I will continue in the following book.