Here's a historical note about John the Italian.
Oudin's Commentary on Ecclesiastical Writers, volume two, page 434, provides some insights.
John the Italian was a Cluniac monk, Roman by origin and Italian by nationality, serving professionally as a canon.
He was brought to Rome by Saint Odo, the abbot of Cluny, in 939.
From Rome, he was taken to Ticinum, where he became a monk, as John himself confirms in the first book of the Life of Saint Odo, numbers two and four.
After some time, he was appointed prior, as mentioned multiple times in the second book, numbers four, seven, and ten.
However, it's uncertain whether this occurred at Cluny, in Rome near Saint Paul, or somewhere else, as this doubt arises when comparing numbers ten and twenty-one.
John himself states he was sent to Naples due to the needs of his monastery, as noted in number twenty-one.
He records his entire period as Saint Odo's companion as two years in book three, number five.
John wrote the Life of Saint Odo, abbot of Cluny, in three books, documenting everything he witnessed or heard about Odo's actions and words during that time, or learned later from others.
After Saint Odo died on November eighteenth, 942, John began writing the Life of his abbot not long thereafter.
John the Italian dedicated his work to the Salernitan monks, his friends and close associates, and many later followed his example.
Nalgodus, a Cluniac monk, took up writing the same Life of Odo around 1120, refining and organizing John's work.
This Life of Saint Odo, written by John the Italian, is included in the Collection of Laurence Surius, volume six, on November eighteenth.
Both Lives, by John and Nalgodus, are also found in the Cluniac Library with notes by Andre Duchesne.
Finally, in the fifth century of the order of Saint Benedict, pages 124 and following, 150 and following, Gerardus Johannes Vossius discusses John the Italian, the author of the Life of Saint Odo, in the second book on Latin historians, chapter 40.
The reference I'm using is three twenty-four: John Mabillon and Andrew Duchesne, in the mentioned locations.
The life of Saint Odon, the second Abbot of Cluny.
Prologue to John the Italian's Book on Miracles
You have often encouraged me, most noble and distinguished consul, Lord Pantaleo.
I, the humblest John, the least among all monks and priests, to translate certain things found in the Greek books or histories, which are not available in Latin, into the Latin language.
But I often hesitated, considering the simplicity of my speech, thinking I couldn't navigate such a vast sea of knowledge with my limited understanding.
With so many speeches and books, I confidently say that if Ambrose, Augustine, Jerome, and Gregory, who were the most learned in both divine and human knowledge, and as eloquent as the four rivers of paradise, had risen, they would indeed have had much to work on for many years.
How much more so for me, since I am the least of all, with less learning in both sciences, and my understanding has already diminished with age, and my eyes have grown dim?
But as I pondered these things for a long time, not knowing whether to obey you or hide my ignorance in silence, sometimes persuaded by your encouragement, and trusting in the benevolence of the Fathers and brothers, in whose hands these chapters or narratives will come, who will kindly strive to correct and amend them, I will undertake this assigned work, invoking the help of the Holy Spirit, who opens the mouths of the mute and makes the tongues of infants eloquent.
Therefore, I ask all of you who read this:
Correct what needs correcting; amend what needs amending, and please grant me pardon.