On the Remission of Sins
by Fulgentius of Ruspe
To Euthymius, Two Books.
Book One
I can't express in words, dearest Euthymius, how much I rejoice in your zeal:
not only do you dedicate yourself to heavenly Scriptures at home,
but you also diligently attend the holy church with a vigilant heart.
While the outer ear hears the divine words, the inner soul is nourished.
It's recognized as a work of divine grace that in the house of God,
you spiritually enjoy the company of those who are fervent in their love for the divine law.
You do not take pleasure in engaging in useless conversations with some people
who come to the feast of the heavenly word without gaining any benefit for themselves.
According to the truthful words of the reproving Apostle Paul,
Second Timothy 4:4,
"turn away their ears from the truth and turn aside to myths."
These people are rightly compared to those whose stomachs, overcome by deadly aversion,
find more pleasure in fasting than in eating.
Thus, they see the healing riches laid out for them in vain.
Since they refuse to take them, they neither gain any strength nor health from them.
In the house of the doctor, they spurn the offered remedy for spiritual healing,
entering with their ailments only to leave more infirm.
Yet, the Lord is able to grant them delight and understanding of His word,
so they may be inspired by good examples.
Advised by these examples, they should cast off the negligence of their delay
and seek the effect of salvation in the wholesome precepts of the same doctor.
With those who, searching the testimonies of the Lord, seek Him, they too might persist in seeking
for their own salvation what can be found by those who seek.
Chapter Two
The letter you sent me, although it didn't reveal anything new from your heart, brought a great increase of joy in the Lord to our hearts.
We know that divine grace is mercifully at work in you, and that you often and deeply think about the forgiveness of sins.
However, the reason I said our joy increased is because you desire to obtain the forgiveness of sins in such a way that you frequently and diligently seek its effect.
You mention a question has come up among you.
Although you might recall it yourself, I preferred to include the exact words from your letter so that not only you may recognize them from your own dictation, but also anyone else who reads it can be more easily informed and instructed for understanding the answer.
So you ask whether the Creator Lord in this world forgives the sins of those He wills, allowing them to leave here forgiven; or whether by His omnipotence He forgives the sins of those He did not forgive in the present world, when they depart from the body before the Day of Judgment, or on that same future day.
You certainly remember these words, which, as I mentioned before, were contained in your letter.
Chapter Three
I see you're eager to hear my humble opinion on resolving this question.
I hope that in God's abundant goodness, which is always so rich, even our poverty can be enriched by it.
From this goodness, He gives as much as He wants to others while He remains fully complete in it.
He will graciously infuse our hearts with spiritual insights that will be beneficial for us to speak and for you to hear.
The words we share with you in God's grace also benefit us if we, too, listen to ourselves internally with meekness and humility.
It's not without reason that the most holy David says, "I will hear what the Lord God will speak in me" (Psalm 85:9).
This kind of hearing is specifically for the humble.
For this reason, the same prophet says elsewhere, "You will give joy and gladness to my hearing, and the humbled bones will rejoice" (Psalm 51:10).
In another place, the majesty itself speaks like this: "Upon whom will my Spirit rest, if not upon the humble and quiet, and those who tremble at my words" (Isaiah 66:2)?
The Spirit of God does not rest on the humble and quiet without making them humble and quiet, but finds them as such to rest upon.
The Spirit graciously rests on the humble and quiet because He makes them humble and quiet.
Therefore, the Holy Spirit works to expel the vice of pride and restlessness from the person on whom He rests.
Through the preceding action of the Holy Spirit, mercifully changing the person's will, the freely given remission of sins dissolves every bond of past human iniquity.
Chapter Four
So, we are discussing something significant, not trivial, when we talk about the forgiveness of sins, as much as divine generosity helps.
Through this, those whom God transfers into the kingdom of His beloved Son are rescued from the power of darkness.
Colossians 1:13.
They are freed from eternal punishment to enjoy eternal happiness.
The burden is lifted, whether it was from a flawed birth or added by the wickedness of a corrupt youth.
Through it, Christ refreshes those who labor and are burdened when they come to him.
He imposes the gentle yoke and light burden of his love.
Matthew 11:28.
Through this, the ungodly are justified freely so that their faith is counted as righteousness.
A person is freed from the bad life they were entangled in and receives a good life they were unworthy of.
One walks in a good life, illuminated by the gift of preceding mercy, and perseveres in it, led by the gift of following mercy.
Undeserved grace begins the gift of living well in a person, granted by the forgiveness of sins, and is completed by the granted virtue of perseverance.
Through the forgiveness of sins, people are freely distinguished from those who will be tormented forever with the devil and joined with those who will reign forever with Christ.
Finally, the forgiveness of sins is so significant that for it, the only begotten Son of God became man, and for it, his blood was shed.
One of these was revealed by the voice of the angelic vision; the other was indicated by the Lord himself.
For when Mary, his mother, was betrothed to Joseph, and, as the evangelist testifies, before they came together, she was found to be with child from the Holy Spirit, the cause of her conception was announced to Joseph, who did not know, by the angel with these words:
Joseph, son of David, do not be afraid to take Mary as your wife, for what is conceived in her is from the Holy Spirit.
She will bear a son, and you shall call his name Jesus, for he will save his people from their sins.
Matthew 1:18 and following.
But what else is saving from sins except forgiving sins?
Our Savior himself, who came to save what was lost
Matthew 18:11, testifies that he came for this reason: to call sinners to repentance.
Chapter Five
The main benefit of this call to repentance is the free forgiveness of sins.
For this reason, our Redeemer, after completing the Passover supper, announced that His blood would be poured out.
"Drink from it, all of you," He said.
"For this is my blood of the new covenant, which is poured out for many for the forgiveness of sins" (Matthew 26:28).
Therefore, as I believe, almost everyone who is called by the Christian name in any way desires this.
But it matters where, when, and how one seeks it.
For one cannot achieve the forgiveness of sins if one does not hold true faith, neglects the duty of good works, or scorns the divinely granted time for good works with deadly vanity.
These three things-faith, works, and time-are so necessary for people in this life that if anyone lacks one of these three in the present age, they cannot partake in eternal life.
And thus, will not obtain the forgiveness of sins, through which one reaches the reward of eternal life.
This must be demonstrated with the help of the Lord and the testimony of divine scriptures.
Chapter Six
Above all, we must firmly believe that our Lord God is both merciful and just.
From this, it is clear to those who seek to understand what types of sins God forgives, where He forgives them, and when He forgives them.
Knowing this, no one should hold the wrong opinion about God, neglect their own conversion, or leave the Catholic Church; and if anyone has left, they should quickly return.
No one should foolishly comfort themselves with the thought that if they refuse to turn to God in this life and serve wickedness until death, they will receive forgiveness of sins after this life.
When the time of divine tribulation comes, they will no longer be able to avoid sin through conversion but will be damned for eternity.
The devil tries in many ways to block and obscure the path to heaven.
His constant aim is to drag or force as many people as possible into his company of misery.
He makes some people, disregarding God's justice, think only of His mercy, so they neglect their conversion, believing that even if they live a sinful life until the end, they will still receive forgiveness.
Others he leads or entices to leave the Catholic Church and join heresies or schisms due to the blindness of their corrupted hearts.
He ensnares their minds with false promises, so they think they are following the right doctrine or hope that their mere belief will bring them forgiveness, even if they remain bound to the deadly fellowship of heretics until death for convenience or out of fear.
They fail to consider our Savior's words: "Whoever acknowledges me before men, I will also acknowledge before my Father in heaven; but whoever denies me before men, I will also deny before my Father in heaven" (Matthew 10:32).
"Whoever is ashamed of me and my words, the Son of Man will be ashamed of him when he comes in his glory, and the glory of the Father and the holy angels" (Luke 9:26).
The enemy of most of the human race strives to remind people of their sins, so he can cast despair over those with hardened hearts, excluding them from the remedy of conversion.
He acts deceitfully for no other reason than to take away the time in which forgiveness can be granted to those who have converted.
In his malice, if it were possible, no one would reach salvation.
He knows that God is merciful and just, and he understands that true conversion of the heart can elicit forgiveness from God.
He also knows that sins can only be forgiven to converts within the bosom of the Catholic Mother Church.
He is aware that in this age, remission of all sins can be granted to converts: where humanity, by divine order, is bound by physical birth through the death of those who die and the succession of those who are born, but is freely unbound by spiritual rebirth: where every guilt is either absolved by conversion or made unresolvable, nourished by neglect or strengthened by despair, and retained to the end by the wickedness of a hardened heart.
Chapter Seven
The urgency of this task compels me to thoroughly explain everything I mentioned earlier, with proper discussion and testimony from the Holy Scriptures.
The truthful account of both Testaments does not remain silent about everything related to human salvation, so that future deniers have no excuses.
Principally, all Scripture, divinely inspired, proclaims one true and only God, the Trinity: the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, as merciful as He is just.
It is said to Him on behalf of the Church: "I will sing of mercy and justice to You, Lord" (Psalm 101:1).
It is also sung of Him: "The Lord is merciful and just, and our God shows mercy" (Psalm 116:5).
In another place: "For the Lord is just and loves justice, the upright will see His face" (Psalm 11:7).
Again, it is said: "All the ways of the Lord are mercy and truth" (Psalm 25:10).
And again: "For the Lord loves mercy and truth" (Psalm 84:12).
In the first commandment of the Decalogue, the same Lord declares Himself just and merciful: "I am the Lord your God, a jealous God, who repays the sins of the fathers to the children to the third and fourth generation of those who hate me; but showing mercy to thousands of those who love me and keep my commandments" (Exodus 20:5).
Moses says: "The Lord God is forgiving and merciful, patient and of great mercy and truth, keeping justice and mercy to thousands, removing iniquities and injustices and sins. He will not clear the guilty, bringing the sins of the fathers upon the children and grandchildren to the third and fourth generation" (Exodus 34:6).
Through Isaiah, the Lord also recalls His mercy and justice, saying: "I am God, and there is no other besides me, a just God and a Savior; there is none besides me. Turn to me and be saved" (Isaiah 45:21).
Chapter Eight
With these and countless other testimonies, our merciful Lord God is praised and shown to be just.
This demonstrates how much His mercy should be loved and how much His justice should be feared.
The Lord is merciful and compassionate, patient, very merciful, and truthful.
Just as He knows how to remove punishment from those who repent, He also does not allow sin to go unpunished in those who refuse to repent.
If the kind goodness of God does not free someone from the domination of sin in this present age, His just severity will condemn them in the future.
This is why the wicked are constantly and beneficially admonished by divine words, so they do not remain in the bondage of sin but seek the mercy of the just God while they are in this life.
The good are also instructed in Psalms to serve the Lord with fear and rejoice with trembling, to grasp discipline; lest the Lord become angry and they perish from the right path.
Therefore, the God who is merciful and just instructs that He should be feared and loved by the wicked because of His justice and mercy, so those who repent may avoid the punishment that justice threatens and receive the forgiveness that mercy promises.
He also instructs that He should be loved and feared by the good because of His justice and mercy, so those who are good through His mercy may remain in good works out of love for His mercy and diligently guard themselves from sins out of fear of His justice.
And, being instructed by the consideration of their own weakness, they should never trust in their own strength but continually and humbly seek the help of divine power.
Chapter Nine
Both the good and the bad should love mercy and fear justice.
The good, loving God's mercy, must still fear His justice to avoid falling into the devil's traps.
The bad, focusing solely on justice's severity, might miss out on mercy, which they can find through conversion.
Hardened in this way, they not only deny forgiveness but also continue to multiply sins.
The devil often ensnares the unwary with a two-edged trap.
Some, lulled by the false hope of future forgiveness, refuse to convert out of fear of justice.
Others, despairing of any forgiveness, neglect conversion and indulge in iniquities.
In their despair, they plunge headlong into hell.
The cunning enemy of humanity drives some into recklessness through despair and deceives others with false hope.
For this reason, blessed Paul, in whom Christ spoke, advises those living well to maintain caution in their salutary work with fear and trembling.
He writes to the Philippians:
Therefore, my beloved, as you have always obeyed, not only in my presence but much more now in my absence, work out your salvation with fear and trembling.
For it is God who works in you, both to will and to work for His good pleasure.
(Philippians 2:12-13)
With these words, blessed Paul emphasizes a just God by commanding believers to maintain fear and trembling in their good works.
He also highlights a merciful God, who works in them to will and to accomplish His good pleasure.
For God would not be justly feared by those doing good if He were not just, nor would He inspire all good will and deeds in them if He were not merciful.
This fear of divine justice is strongly impressed upon the just by Paul the apostle with a stern warning:
Whoever thinks he stands must take care lest he fall.
(First Corinthians 10:12)
And again:
Brothers, if someone is caught in any wrongdoing, you who are spiritual should restore such a person with a gentle spirit, watching out for yourselves so that you also won't be tempted.
Galatians 6:1.
Even to the apostles, with their heavenly teaching, their own weakness is declared, with the suitable fear demonstrated in the humility of heart, keeping caution, as the Lord says:
Watch and pray, so that you do not fall into temptation.
The spirit is willing, but the flesh is weak.
Matthew 26:41.
Chapter Ten
Since everything in divine words aims to protect or restore human salvation, the divine word ensures that while the righteous are instilled with a fear of divine justice, sinners are not driven to despair but shown the hope of forgiveness.
This hope brings back those who have strayed, promising that through divine mercy, any wrongs they committed before their conversion will be forgiven.
Therefore, the apostle Paul, in his letter to the Romans, both terrifies the faithful and the good with the severity of divine justice, and invites the unfaithful and wicked to conversion with the certain hope of divine goodness.
In this way, the good learn to be humble and to fear, while the wicked can obtain the remedy for eternal salvation without any doubt.
The blessed Paul says:
"Behold therefore the goodness and severity of God: on those who fell, severity; but towards you, goodness, if you continue in goodness; otherwise, you too will be cut off. And they also, if they do not continue in unbelief, will be grafted in, for God is able to graft them in again" (Romans 11:22-23).
So, when the Apostle says that those who do not remain in goodness will be cut off, and those who do not remain in unbelief will be grafted in, what righteous person will not tremble and fear justice?
Or what wicked person will not run to God's mercy with confidence?
Who would not dare to hope for any good for the impious if they turn wholeheartedly, when heavenly medicine equally counsels both the healthy and the sick with wholesome precepts; instilling in them the fear of justice as the guardian of accepted salvation; and promising the benefit of mercy to others, so that, uplifted by the remedy of hope, they may regain the health they had lost.
The fear of justice is commanded to the healed, to whom it is said:
"See, you have been made well. Sin no more, lest a worse thing come upon you" (John 5:14).
Hope is extended to the weak when it is said:
A doctor is not needed for the healthy, but for those who are sick; I have not come to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance.
(Luke 5:32).
The prophetic word continually highlights the mercy and justice of God, as spoken through the prophet Ezekiel:
If a wicked person turns away from all the sins they have committed and keeps all my decrees, doing what is just and right, they will surely live; they will not die.
None of the offenses they have committed will be remembered against them.
Because of the righteous things they have done, they will live.
Do I take any pleasure in the death of the wicked, declares the Lord, rather than that they turn from their ways and live?
(Ezekiel 18:21).
Thus, by illustrating the benefit of divine patience and kindness in converting the wicked, the prophetic word also serves to warn the righteous:
But if a righteous person turns from their righteousness and commits sin, doing the same detestable things the wicked person does, none of the righteous things that person has done will be remembered.
Because of the unfaithfulness they are guilty of and because of the sins they have committed, they will die.
(Ezekiel 18:24).
Chapter Eleven
There are countless testimonies in the Divine Scriptures where God is proclaimed as merciful and just.
The entire text of heavenly words aims to warn the wicked with the fear of God's justice to quickly put an end to their evil deeds, and to encourage the good to remain diligently and humbly in their good deeds.
This is so that every wrongdoer, fearing God's fairness, may run to the mercy of divine goodness, and every righteous person, rejoicing in God's mercy, may not neglect the judgment of the most benevolent fairness.
Where perfect mercy and justice exist, the righteous cannot favor sins, nor can the merciful deny forgiveness to those who repent.
Therefore, the fact that He is proclaimed as just and merciful makes it clear that forgiveness of sins is granted only to those who repent, and eternal punishment is inflicted only on those who persist in sin.
For this reason, the Psalmist sings: Unless you repent, He will sharpen His sword, He has bent His bow and made it ready, and He has prepared instruments of death in it (Psalm 7:13).
Also, through Isaiah, a similar sentence against the stubborn and despisers of divine mercy is spoken by the divine mouth, in which it is understood that no one obeys divine commands in vain, nor remains in iniquity without punishment.
Thus, he says: Wash yourselves, be clean, remove your wicked deeds from my sight; cease from your evils, learn to do good, seek judgment, rescue the oppressed, judge the orphan, and defend the widow.
Come, let us reason together, says the Lord.
Though your sins are like scarlet, they shall be as white as snow; though they are red like crimson, they shall be as wool.
If you are willing and obedient, you shall eat the good of the land.
But if you refuse and rebel, the sword will devour you.
For the mouth of the Lord has spoken this (Isaiah 1:16 and following).
Who, I ask, is so hard or completely foolish that, upon hearing this divine warning, isn't at least compelled by the fear of punishment if not invited to conversion by the promise of delight?
Indeed, the one who disregards the divine message will not receive salvation but will be consumed by the sword.
It's shown elsewhere in the same prophet's writings that no one will reach salvation except through conversion.
For it is said: If you turn back and mourn, you will be saved (Isaiah 30:15, according to the Septuagint).
In this conditional testimony, God uses both a command and a promise.
By saying, If you turn back and mourn, you will be saved, He shows that the promise of salvation entirely depends on the condition of conversion.
This is, therefore, the condition between God and man, that is, between the commanding Lord and the servant asking, between the judge who grants mercy without compromising justice, and the sinner who rightfully expects the mercy of the just judge.
Thus, this Lord, merciful and just, stern and compassionate, says: If you do this, you will have this; if you keep what I say, I will give what you ask; I command you to convert, you ask me for salvation; if you obey the command, you will gain the benefit; if I see the commands carried out, I will grant the requests.
If you turn back and mourn, you will be saved.
Chapter Twelve
When it is said that a person who is sinning receives the benefit of salvation if they turn and lament, it means that even if they lament, they will not be saved unless they also turn.
Divine scripture includes both of these requirements for a reason: to show us that both conversion and lamentation are necessary for salvation.
Some people, terrified by their crimes, groan in prayer for their wrongdoings but do not stop their unjust behavior.
They admit they have done wrong but do not want to end their bad deeds.
They humbly confess their sins before God, yet with a perverse heart, they stubbornly continue committing the same sins they just confessed.
Through their wicked deeds, they negate the forgiveness they seek with tearful groans.
They ask for healing from the doctor but instead bring more disease upon themselves, leading to their own destruction.
Thus, they vainly try to appease the just judge with words, while their unjust actions provoke his fury.
Such people never wash away their sins by groaning because they do not stop sinning after their groans.
They groan for their crimes and then return to those crimes.
About such people, divine scripture in the book of Ecclesiasticus says: "He who is cleansed from a dead body and touches it again, what does his washing profit him? So, a man who fasts for his sins, and does the same things again, what does his humbling himself profit him? Who will listen to his prayer?" (Ecclesiasticus 34:30-31).
Therefore, God rightly says: If you turn and lament, you will be saved.
With God, who is both just and good, the prayer of the lamenting person is heard, the weeping of the one asking is attended to, and salvation is granted to the one who weeps if they have turned to God with a contrite heart.
It is necessary that God, having mercy, forgives the sinner if the sinner, having turned, acknowledges their wrongdoing.
Finally, David found divine mercy because he turned back with a humble and contrite heart, acknowledging and condemning his wrongdoing.
He did not delay in punishing himself through repentance for the wrongful desire that led to his fall.
For if he did not punish himself for his guilt, he would undoubtedly be punished.
Thus, he acknowledged his crime and turned to repentance, fearing the punishment that would come if he were condemned.
Through repentance, he vindicated himself by acknowledging what he wanted the Lord to forgive.
When he said, "Have mercy on me, O God, according to your great mercy, and according to the multitude of your tender mercies, blot out my iniquity; wash me more and more from my injustice, and cleanse me from my sin" (Psalm 50:1-2), he immediately added, "For I acknowledge my iniquity, and my sin is always before me" (Psalm 50:4).
He acknowledged his iniquity not to increase it by sinning more, but to wipe it away through repentance.
Thus, the dominion of sin, brought in by guilty pleasure, was removed by true conversion.
Because David groaned from his whole heart and turned back, he was immediately made safe, fulfilling the command through the prophet: "If you turn back and groan, you will be saved."
Chapter Thirteen
Moreover, conversion from both impiety and iniquity is commanded.
Both provoke God's wrath because God detests and condemns them, as Paul says:
For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men
(Romans 1:18).
And Solomon, whose words were also cited by the blessed Peter, says:
If the righteous is scarcely saved, where will the sinner and the ungodly appear?
(Proverbs 11:31, according to the Septuagint; First Peter 5:18).
Therefore, the Vessel of Election, full of divine love, was deeply sorrowful for those who sinned in faith.
He also grieved for those in the Church who lived impudently and luxuriously without repenting.
Concerning the Jews, who were possessed by an unbelieving heart, he says:
I speak the truth in Christ, I am not lying; my conscience bears me witness in the Holy Spirit, that I have great sorrow and unceasing anguish in my heart.
For I could wish that I myself were accursed and cut off from Christ for the sake of my brothers, my kinsmen according to the flesh, who are Israelites
(Romans 9:1-4).
But concerning those in the Church who persisted in evil deeds, he speaks to the Corinthians with a healing sermon:
Lest when I come again my God may humble me before you, and I may have to mourn over many of those who sinned earlier and have not repented of the impurity, sexual immorality, and sensuality that they have practiced
(Second Corinthians 12:21).
He would not mourn these people sadly, nor would the Apostle be humbled and mourn those who provoke divine justice without a change of heart and expect forgiveness of sins; since the forgiveness of sins only takes effect with a change of heart.
Only for those who, using their own free will, with the help of divine grace, change their lives for the better and do not stop running to seek the forgiveness of sins, which they committed either unknowingly due to ignorance or, worse, knowingly due to the stubbornness of their will.
For this reason, the Prophet prays to God:
"Remember not the sins of my youth and my ignorance" Psalm 25:7.
And our Savior says:
"The servant who does not know his master's will and does things worthy of punishment will receive few blows, but the servant who knows his master's will and does things worthy of punishment will receive many blows" Luke 12:47.
Hence, the Apostle confesses that he sinned in ignorance with these words:
"I give thanks to Christ Jesus our Lord, who has strengthened me, because He considered me trustworthy, appointing me to His service, even though I was once a blasphemer, a persecutor, and a violent man; but I was shown mercy because I acted in ignorance and unbelief" First Timothy 1:12-13.
Therefore, let no one flatter himself about his ignorance; we must heed the Apostle's words, who declares that he sinned in ignorance, but does not deny that he sinned. Indeed, he calls himself the foremost of sinners
First Timothy 1:15,
not in the course of time, but in the excess of iniquity. He obtained mercy so that the sins he committed in ignorance, he would recognize and immediately renounce upon being enlightened.
This happens so that, as the Apostle James teaches us, we may know that:
"Every good and perfect gift is from above, coming down from the Father of lights" James 1:17.
When God finds something in the sinner for which he justly deserves to be condemned, He graciously grants the sinner a change of heart, through which the torments of just condemnation may be removed.
Chapter Fourteen
In every sinner who is already using their free will, the benefit of divine grace begins through the conversion of the heart.
However, we know that infants are saved not by their own will, but by the righteous faith of the faithful who confess on their behalf.
It is fitting, according to the judgment of truth, that infants are absolved through the ministry of another's confession, as they are bound by the tie of another's sin.
So, through the spiritual confession of others, they receive the benefit of justification, just as they bear original sin through the carnal generation of others.
As the carnal union of parents harmed those not yet born and doing nothing, the spiritual affection of the faithful confessing on their behalf may benefit them in their second birth.
Therefore, as far as those who can already account for their own actions are concerned, no one will be made blessed unless they renounce their evil deeds and turn to God with total humility of heart.
Blessed are those whose iniquities are forgiven, and whose sins are covered.
Psalms 32:1.
Therefore, anyone who bears the iniquity of their own will and actions cannot receive any blessing unless they turn to the very giver of blessings.
Chapter Fifteen
The heart is blinded by sins but illuminated by forgiveness.
Just as being blinded means being deprived of light, an eye that is healed can perceive light, free from the defect of blindness.
However, this eye cannot see the light unless the light itself enters it.
Therefore, the eye can perceive light through the infusion of light.
Similarly, when forgiveness of sins is given, the blindness of the heart is expelled, allowing the light of justice to be seen with the inner eye.
How can the darkness of shadows be removed if the infusion of light is not granted?
God, when He forgives sins, infuses the light of true conversion.
Just as a blind person cannot see the light, an unrighteous person does not receive forgiveness unless they are graced with free justification and converted to God with their whole heart.
The effect of forgiveness is the conversion of the heart.
Moreover, without the grace of conversion, forgiveness of sins is not given.
To obtain forgiveness is to be freed from the domination of sin, for everyone who commits sin is a slave to sin.
John 8:34.
How can one be believed to possess the gift of liberation if they do not avoid the slavery of sin?
We know from the teaching of the Master of the Gentiles that the condemnation of those who say, "Let us do evil that good may come," is just.
Romans 3:8.
Similarly, we have heard him preach: "Neither the sexually immoral, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor men who have sex with men, nor thieves, nor the greedy, nor drunkards, nor slanderers, nor swindlers will inherit the kingdom of God."
First Corinthians 6:9-10.
Likewise, the same excellent teacher warns the Galatians: "The acts of the flesh are obvious."
Galatians 5:19.
Here are fornication, impurity, lust, idolatry, witchcraft, enmity, jealousy, anger, quarrels, dissensions, heresies, envy, murder, drunkenness, revelries, and things like these.
I warn you about these, as I warned you before, that those who do such things will not inherit the kingdom of God.
Galatians, chapter 5, verse 19 and following.
Therefore, since God is just, as long as people do such things, they will not inherit the kingdom of God.
But because the same God is merciful, the wicked, if they stop doing these things that stubbornly provoke God, and if they humble themselves, correct their ways, and turn to God, they will undoubtedly inherit the kingdom of God.
For just as the work of justice is not overcome, the work of mercy is not removed either.
God has ordered the possession of his kingdom in such a way that, because he is just, he does not give it to the impious and unjust.
But because he is merciful, he does not deny it to anyone who truly converts.
Chapter Sixteen
True conversion in a person is proven when impiety and iniquity are driven out of the heart.
The difference between impiety and iniquity is generally stated as follows: impiety either holds a false belief about God or none at all, while iniquity corrupts life with evil habits.
Impiety blasphemes God, while iniquity harms one's neighbor.
Impiety falsely measures the highest, striving to preach the sacrament of unconquerable piety to the dishonor of the divine nature.
It denies that God the Son was conceived and born in human flesh, and claims that God only appeared in a false vision.
It admits the flesh of Christ came from the Virgin Mary but denies it was conceived in the taking of flesh.
It speaks of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit in a confusing manner.
It introduces different natures for the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit through wicked separation.
It does not believe that the flesh of the Son of God was taken from the flesh of the Virgin Mary, but asserts that it was sent down from heaven.
It wants to diminish the human nature of Christ, even denying that the only begotten God took on a rational soul, that is, a full human soul, along with human flesh.
It is a crime of impiety to say that not all spiritual and bodily good nature was created by God, and to assign the substance of evil to an opposite source.
All evil does not arise from the origin or state of natural property, but from the deficiency of voluntary thought.
It's not because good nature receives evil nature, since there is no evil nature, but because when the order of love is abandoned, the rational creature, made for the love of the Creator, becomes worse by clinging to created things or false thoughts, preferring temporal things to eternal, low things to high, mutable things to immutable.
Similarly, those who argue that the righteous and the wicked should be judged not by their deeds but by their participation in the sacraments, offer no real benefit.
They imply that if someone lives justly among the unjust within the Catholic Church, their eternal reward or punishment is based not on the quality of their actions, but on their association with the sacraments.
These ideas, along with many others presented by heretics and schismatics against the Catholic and Apostolic faith, are considered impious.
This separation highlights their wickedness, marking them as adversaries rather than companions of the ecclesiastical body.
They would not be separated from the unity of the church's body if they hadn't first departed from the church's faith in their hearts due to a corrupted mind.
They would not be openly separated from legitimate union with the word of God unless they had conceived treacherous and perverse thoughts through the diabolical corruption.
By nurturing these thoughts with internal consent, they later express them with vile speech, destroying themselves like vipers that perish while giving birth, tearing apart the bodies that conceived them to bring forth their offspring, thus causing the death of their parents.
Therefore, any wicked depravity, whether conceived by consent or expressed openly, kills the soul with eternal death.
When the soul agrees with this corruption, it becomes internally inflated with the conception of infidelity, eventually leading to its own death as it gives birth to these corrupt thoughts.
The apostolic authority describes such people with these words: "Just as Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses, so these also oppose the truth, men of corrupt mind and counterfeit faith" (Second Epistle to Timothy 3:6).
Therefore, anyone who argues against the truth and separates themselves from goodness perverts the faith of the church and is undoubtedly called impious.
If anyone remains within the body of the Catholic unity, joined by the fellowship of the sacraments, but engages in crimes and vices, they are usually called unjust, not impious.
This is not something we need to argue about now.
However, we say this: not every unjust person is impious, although every impious person is unjust.
Chapter Seventeen
Therefore, a conversion that upholds the correctness of faith and the rule of a good life is pleasing and acceptable in the sight of God.
This means that, first and foremost, a correct understanding of God should be maintained, and then the love commanded by God should be shown to one's neighbor.
A person loves themselves correctly when they, being devout and humble, prioritize the love of God.
They also love their neighbor if they help them reach God with correct faith and good conduct, as much as they can.
The love for one's neighbor must be maintained in two ways: first, by not inflicting anything on others that one would not want inflicted on oneself; and second, by not denying help to the needy as much as one can, because one would not want to be denied help if they were similarly in need.
Hence, we recognize that our Savior informs us with the words: "Whatever you want people to do to you, do also to them. This is the law and the prophets" Matthew 7:12.
Christ did not say, "Whatever people have done to you, do also to them," so that we would not think it right to repay evil for evil to someone who has wronged us, or to withhold a benefit from someone because they have not benefited us. A Christian ought to offer or return assistance of goodwill to everyone; to return good for good, and to overcome evil with goodness.
For the Lord tells us: "Love your enemies, do good to those who hate you, and pray for those who persecute and slander you, so that you may be children of your Father in heaven, who makes his sun rise on the good and the evil, and sends rain on the just and the unjust" Matthew 5:44-45.
Good and faithful people suffer persecution not only from those outsiders who oppose the doctrines of the Catholic Church with faithless and perverse barking; but also from those who seem to be within the Church, but are found to live wickedly and oppose ecclesiastical tradition not in words, but in deeds.
When good people see them, they groan deeply.
The good heart, moved by holy affection, is tormented because it cannot avoid being aware of others' perversity, even though it cannot agree with it.
Chapter Eighteen
Indeed, within the Catholic Church today, the righteous and the wicked are mixed together.
They share in the sacraments but not in morals; they are united in faith but not in lifestyle.
So, they are united not in heart, but in body; by profession, not by deeds.
As long as, according to the teachings of the blessed Paul, in a great house there are not only gold vessels, but also wooden and clay ones, and some are for honor, while others are for dishonor.
As it is written in Second Timothy, chapter 2, verse 20:
"In a great house there are not only vessels of gold and silver, but also of wood and clay; some for honorable use, some for dishonorable."
Within the Church, there are both the wicked and the righteous, but outside the Church, no one is righteous.
And within the Lord's threshing floor, while we await the fearful coming of the winnower, and the final separation of the chaff from the wheat is deferred, the chaff is mixed with the wheat in local communion.
However, whoever is outside the Lord's threshing floor, even if they are called by the name of the farmer, only the chaff, which is blown away by the wind, can remain there.
But since the power of our omnipotent farmer is so great that no one can overcome His will, whoever in this present life turns and returns to the legitimate place of the Lord's threshing floor, if they persistently hold to the right faith and the purpose of a good life, will not be chaff but wheat, and will not be consigned to the burning fire, but will be gathered into the barn, enriched with fruits pleasing to God.
Forgiveness of sins is given and received only in the Catholic Church, which the bridegroom himself describes as his one dove, his one chosen one, founded upon the rock.
To this Church, he gave the keys of the kingdom of heaven and granted the power to bind and loose, as the Truth himself promises to blessed Peter, saying:
"You are Peter, and on this rock, I will build my Church, and the gates of hell will not prevail against it. I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven; and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven."
Matthew 16:18-19
Whoever is outside this Church, which received the keys of the kingdom of heaven, does not walk the path to heaven but to hell.
He does not aim for the house of eternal life, but rushes towards the punishment of eternal death.
This is true not only for those who remain pagans without baptism but also for those who, having been baptized in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, persist as heretics.
No one attains true life by the merit of baptism if, whether baptized inside or outside the Church in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, they do not end this life within the Catholic Church.
Nor will someone live through the sacrament of ecclesiastical baptism if they have not held onto the communion of ecclesiastical faith and charity.
For it is the unity of charity that keeps someone saved within the Catholic Church until the end of this present life.
Chapter Twenty
If anyone leaves the Church after being baptized or is baptized outside the Church in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, and they are not restored to the Catholic Church before the end of their life, they will not escape death and will find no rest.
During the time of the flood, anyone who did not enter Noah's ark, as stated in Genesis chapter seven, verse twenty-one, was not saved from the flood but perished, finding death instead of salvation in the water.
The water, which prefigured the sacrament of baptism, lifted those in the ark from the earth to the heavens;
but it killed those it found outside.
When Jericho was destroyed, Jesus ordered that everyone inside the house of Rahab the prostitute be saved unharmed, as stated in Joshua chapter six, verse twenty-five.
But all others outside that house were consumed by destruction.
The Church was prefigured in that ark and that house;
but those who perished in the flood outside the ark, and those who died by the sword outside that house, represent a dual mystery.
It seems appropriate to think that the flood signifies the baptism of Christian confession;
so we may recognize that heretics, if they remain outside the Church, deserve punishment through baptism, not life, and those who deny Christ and leave the Catholic Church will face eternal punishment.
The blessed Peter explains the sacrament of the ark with these words:
In the days when God's patience waited in the days of Noah, while the ark was being built, a few, that is, eight souls, were saved through water.
This now saves you, too, through baptism of a similar form, not the removal of dirt from the body, but an appeal to God for a good conscience, as stated in First Peter chapter three, verses twenty and twenty-one.
But where is a good conscience unless there is also unfeigned faith?
The apostle Paul teaches:
The end of the commandment is love from a pure heart, a good conscience, and unfeigned faith, as stated in First Timothy chapter one, verse five.
So why did the water of the flood not save those outside the ark, but kill them?
Without a doubt, it foreshadows that every heretic, even if they have the sacrament of baptism, will be submerged in those waters leading to hell, while the ark is lifted up to heaven.
They are destroyed by water because they are not within the ark's embrace, which is the only place where one can live and avoid perishing by the life-giving waters.
Chapter Twenty-One
The mystery of this ark is explained by the blessed martyr Cyprian in his book on the Simplicity of Prelates, or rather according to ancient manuscripts, in the Unity of the Catholic Church:
The bride of Christ cannot be adulterated; she is uncorrupted and chaste.
She knows one home and guards the sanctity of one bedchamber with pure modesty.
She keeps us for God and assigns to the kingdom the children she has borne.
Whoever is separated from the Church and joins with an adulteress is separated from the promises of the Church.
He will not reach the rewards of Christ if he leaves the Church of Christ.
He is an outsider, he is profane, he is an enemy.
He cannot have God as his father if he does not have the Church as his mother.
Just as no one could escape who was outside the ark of Noah, no one who is outside the Church will escape.
It is certain, therefore, by the preaching of the blessed apostle Peter and the explanation of the holy martyr Cyprian, that the ark of Noah was a figure of the Church, and the waters of the flood were a figure of baptism.
In the house of the prostitute Rahab, who alone was preserved unharmed with all those she had within her when Jericho perished by the command of Jesus, the Catholic Church from the Gentiles was signified in the sacrament of Christian confession, as it seems to me.
This Church, having cast off the filth of former fornication, secretly received the two spies of Jesus.
This means either the pure knowledge of both Testaments or the love of God and neighbor, for in those two Testaments, the love of God and neighbor is intimated, and on these two commandments hang all the law and the prophets.
Matthew 22:40
This prostitute, who was once impious and prostituted to idols, became faithful and chaste by receiving the spies of Jesus.
Keeping them safe from pursuing enemies, she did not hide them in the lower parts but secretly concealed them lifted up in the upper room of her house.
The upper room is so called because it is bathed in the light of the sun.
Who is the sun of the human heart, if not the one about whom it was said through the prophet:
"For those who fear my name, the sun of righteousness will rise with healing in its rays"
Malachi 4:2?
Concerning this rising sun, Zechariah prophesies in the Gospel:
"Because the rising sun will visit us from heaven, to shine on those living in darkness and in the shadow of death"
Luke 1:78-79.
The prophet Habakkuk also foretells Christ's ascension and the stability of the ecclesiastical order under the name of the sun and moon:
"The sun rose, and the moon stood in its place"
Habakkuk 3:11, according to the Septuagint.
Therefore, the heart of every faithful person is aptly called a spiritual sunroom, healthily illuminated by the rays of that heavenly sun.
Thus, Rahab the prostitute, who hid Joshua's spies on the roof of her house, surely kept them in the higher parts, meaning with the enlightened love of a heart illuminated by spiritual knowledge, so that she could sing the prophetic words with the truth of her actions:
"I have hidden your word in my heart that I might not sin against you"
Psalm 119:11.
True faith, conveyed by divine words, is not betrayed to persecutors but is kept inviolable and safe in the hearts of the faithful if the soul clings to heavenly and spiritual promises, not to earthly, perishable, and carnal things, and looks not at what is seen, but at what is unseen:
"For what is seen is temporary, but what is unseen is eternal," as the Apostle says
Second Corinthians 4:18.
However, whoever holds the Christian faith to acquire earthly and transitory things places Joshua's spies not in the higher parts of his house, but in the lower parts; where, once they are placed, they can be more easily found and destroyed by enemies.
For every persecutor and enemy of the Church spiritually kills those whose hearts he finds attached to earthly and perishable things, bringing upon them the destruction of eternal death.
While they fear losing or desire acquiring earthly riches, they do not hide the commandments of Christ-the scouts of Jesus-in the attic of their hearts.
Instead, they hand them over to persecuting enemies, either terrified by fear or inflamed by corrupt desire.
They lack the scarlet cord, the sign that saved that house, hanging from their window.
This signifies that they do not profess their faith but deny the sacraments.
The scarlet cord symbolizes the mystery of the blood of Christ.
Those who have it hanging from their window, firmly established in faith against pagans or any heretics by God's protection, and carefully guarding their faith, confess that they are redeemed by the blood of Christ.
For this reason, the Savior himself said: "Whoever acknowledges me before others, I will also acknowledge before my Father in heaven; but whoever disowns me before others, I will disown before my Father in heaven" (Matthew 10:32).
So, although the enemy persecutor tries to kill the scouts of Jesus in the lower parts-that is, attempts to weaken the strength of the Christian faith with earthly promises or terrors-if someone has faith in the Trinity, believing the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit to be one God, they will not fear all the dark errors, terrors, and traps of the deceiver.
Chapter Twenty-Two
Therefore, those guilty of repeated baptism should quickly return to the Church and seek God's forgiveness with tears and alms for such a great sin.
Additionally, if anyone has denied the sacrament of the Catholic faith for rewards or out of fear of punishments and has joined heretics, they should reclaim the faith they denied and return to the Church swiftly, so that when Jesus comes, they can be found within the house outside of which no one can be saved.
Just as in Jericho, anyone outside that house could not receive any means of life, so outside the Catholic Church, no one will receive forgiveness of sins.
Within the Catholic Church, one believes with the heart leading to righteousness and confesses with the mouth leading to salvation.
Romans 10:10
Outside that same Church, wrong belief is counted for punishment, and wrong confession does not grant salvation but brings death.
Outside this Church, the name Christian does not help anyone, baptism does not save, a pure sacrifice is not offered to God, forgiveness of sins is not received, and the happiness of eternal life is not found.
There is one Church of Christ, one dove, one beloved, one bride, in which the Trinity is believed to be one God of one nature and substance.
In this Church, neither the Son nor the Holy Spirit is subjected to diminishment.
The same worship and honor are given to the one Trinity, which is the true God.
This is the one true Church, which believes and proclaims the one essence of the Trinity, not preferring any one person over the others.
Thus, it worships nothing different in the substance of divinity, confessing the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, that is, the Trinity itself, as one true and only God.
It avoids the error of Sabellian confusion in the name of unity and the deadly danger of Arian diversity in the term Trinity.
Just as apostolic preaching acknowledges the Trinity in the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, it also upholds the true faith in one God.
This is because it emphasizes the natural unity within the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
Chapter Twenty-Three
Those who are outside this Church and involved in different errors will receive forgiveness for their sins if, while still in this world, they convert to the Church with true faith and a humble, contrite heart.
Therefore, let them hurry, while there is time, to their legitimate mother, who, just as she diligently cares for and nurtures her children born from her womb, does not reject those born from a servant when they return.
Instead, she searches for those who are lost with compassion and constantly invites them with affection to bring them into the fellowship of the paternal inheritance.
For she does not consider the condition of the servant's womb in them, but recognizes the truth of the paternal seed.
And what is the truth of the paternal seed, if not the baptism received in the name of the Trinity?
Wherever she finds this, she acknowledges it as her rightful jurisdiction as a legitimate mother.
For she knows, like Rachel from the Book of Genesis chapter thirty, how to bear children not only from her own womb but also to claim those born from a servant as her legitimate offspring.
This is why they should not neglect to rejoin the brotherly fellowship if they wish to share in the gift of the paternal inheritance.
Therefore, leaving heresy behind, they should quickly return to the Catholic Church.
They should neither doubt the possession of the inheritance nor despair of the forgiveness of their sins.
For anyone who does not believe that all sins can be forgiven within the Catholic Church denies themselves forgiveness if they leave this world in the same hardness of an unrepentant heart, alienated from the fellowship of the Church.
Chapter Twenty-Four
Therefore, anyone who speaks against the Holy Spirit will not be forgiven, neither in this age nor in the age to come.
Matthew 12:32.
For the love of God, which covers a multitude of sins, has been poured into our hearts through the Holy Spirit, who has been given to us.
Romans 5:5.
This love, because it holds the unbroken bond of brotherly unity, covers a multitude of sins and does not let those who persevere in unity with the most certain hope perish.
If anyone, therefore, holding the faith which works through love, repents of any former error in such a way that neither the association of error holds him any longer, nor the chain of deadly despair binds him, he will be free from that word spoken against the Holy Spirit, which is not forgiven, neither in this age nor in the age to come.
Galatians 5:6.
For by this word, our Lord and Savior did not imply that some sins would be forgiven in the age to come which had not been forgiven in this age; but to those who understand well, He showed that only those sins will be forgiven in the age to come that have been forgiven each one in this age in the one true Catholic Church.
For the Lord granted the power of binding and loosing only to her, saying:
"I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven; and whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven."
Matthew 16:19.
Therefore, what the holy Church does not loose in this age remains so unloosed that it cannot be loosed in the age to come.
Every person whom the Church has not loosed is bound, and he will not obtain any benefit of loosing who does not turn to repentance in the Church, hoping for the forgiveness of sins to be granted to him.
He speaks an unforgivable word against the Holy Spirit.
By despising the riches of God's goodness, patience, and long-suffering, and according to his own hardness and unrepentant heart, he stores up wrath for himself on the day of wrath and revelation of the righteous judgment of God, who will repay each person according to their deeds.
As stated in Romans, Chapter Two, Verse Four.
Chapter Twenty-Five
Whether it's love from a pure heart, the communion of brotherly unity, or the paternal possession of the heavenly inheritance, they all come from the gift of the Holy Spirit.
As the Doctor of the Gentiles says about love: "The love of God has been poured into our hearts through the Holy Spirit, who has been given to us" Romans 5:5.
He also praises the unity of the Spirit with the same love, saying: "I, a prisoner in the Lord, urge you to walk in a manner worthy of the calling to which you have been called, with all humility and gentleness, with patience, bearing with one another in love, eager to maintain the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace" Ephesians 4:1-3.
He confirms it as the communion of the Holy Spirit, saying: "The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God, and the fellowship of the Holy Spirit be with you all" Second Corinthians 13:13.
He also speaks about our inheritance like this: "You were sealed with the promised Holy Spirit, who is the guarantee of our inheritance" Ephesians 1:13-14.
The blessed Apostle also attributes hope, which drives out despair, to the Holy Spirit, saying: "May the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, so that by the power of the Holy Spirit you may abound in hope" Romans 15:13.
Therefore, anyone who attains the eternal fellowship of the heavenly inheritance within the Catholic Church, maintaining the unity of brotherly love, and before ending this life, lays down the deadly hardness of an impenitent heart, does not despair of receiving forgiveness of all sins through the Holy Spirit in the one and truly Catholic Church.
This is also shown by our Savior himself.
After he rose, breathing on the disciples and giving them the gift of the Holy Spirit, he granted them the power to forgive sins, saying: "Receive the Holy Spirit. If you forgive anyone's sins, they are forgiven; if you retain anyone's sins, they are retained" John 20:22-23.
Chapter Twenty-Six
Therefore, let those who are separated from the Catholic Church by any heresy or schism not close the door of mercy on themselves with deadly despair.
Let them soften their hearts if they do not want to suffer endless punishments.
For it is written, "A hard heart will fare badly at the end, and whoever loves danger will perish in it" (Sirach 3:27).
What is more dangerous than not showing obedience to divine words and disregarding the will of the calling God?
Thus, in the book of Job, just as eternal glory is promised to those who repent, the gifts of salvation are denied to the wicked because they do not obey.
For it is written: "If they listen and serve, they will complete their days in prosperity and their years in pleasantness.
But the godless do not receive salvation because they did not want to know God, and when they were warned, they were disobedient" (Job 36:11 and following).
Therefore, let them not despise the time granted for obedience, but return to the Catholic Church; in which alone, through the gift of the Holy Spirit, love covers a multitude of sins (First Peter 4:8).
If there are also those in the Catholic Church who live wrongly, let them hasten to turn away from their evil lives before they end this life; nor should they think that the name "Catholic" alone is enough for salvation if they do not do God's will.
For our Savior says: "Not everyone who says to me, 'Lord, Lord,' will enter the kingdom of heaven, but only those who do the will of my Father who is in heaven" (Matthew 7:19).
For it is also written in the book of Psalms: "The Lord is near to all who call on him in truth; he will fulfill the desire of those who fear him, he also will hear their cry and save them" (Psalm 145:18-19).
Therefore, in Proverbs, each of us is commanded to both fear the Lord and turn away from evil.
For it says there: "Fear the Lord, and turn away from all evil, and it will be health to your flesh and strength to your bones" (Proverbs 3:7-8).
In the book of Ecclesiasticus, the faithful are warned not to do evil: "Do not do wrong, and wrong will not come to you. Stay away from wickedness, and evil will stay away from you. Do not plant evil in the fields of wrongdoing, and you will not harvest it many times over" (Eccl. 7:1-3).
The same book warns against adding sin upon sin and thinking God's mercy will cover it with these words: "Do not add sin to sin and say, 'God's mercy is great,' for mercy and wrath come from Him, and His wrath will fall on sinners" (Eccl. 5:5-7).
Also, holy Job said: "Won't there be destruction for the wicked, and alienation for those who do evil?" (Job 31:3).
In Proverbs, it is written: "The wicked are trapped by their own sins; each person is bound by the cords of their own wrongdoing. They die for lack of discipline and are ruined because of their foolishness" (Prov. 5:22-23).
Chapter Twenty-Seven
So that no one thinks any human sins can be hidden from God, let's learn from the words of Saint Job, who says:
"You have counted my thoughts, and none of my sins have been hidden from you. You have sealed my iniquities in a bag and noted if I have erred unwillingly." (Job 14:16-17, according to the Septuagint).
And let no one think they will escape punishment if they refuse to repent.
Listen carefully to the words of this same holy man, who says:
"Indeed, let no one who is wicked believe they will go unpunished, no matter how much they provoke God in their anger, as if there will be no investigation into it."
Therefore, in Ecclesiasticus, a helpful warning is given, so that we lack neither the conversion to avoid sins nor the prayer to forgive past ones.
For it is said:
"My son, have you sinned? Do not do it again; but also pray for your past sins so that they may be forgiven."
"Flee from sins as you would from the face of a serpent. If you approach them, they will take hold of you, and like a lion's teeth, they will kill you by devouring you." (Ecclesiasticus 21:1-2).
It is also made clear that the impious and sinners who refuse to repent of their wickedness or iniquity will face eternal punishments in the end, but our Lord will grant mercy to those who have repented.
For in the book of Ecclesiasticus, it is written:
"For the Most High is merciful to those who repent, and will deliver vengeance upon the impious and sinners." (Ecclesiasticus 12:7).
Again, in the same book, it is said:
"Remember that wrath will not delay. Humble your spirit greatly, for the vengeance on the flesh of the impious is fire and worms." (Ecclesiasticus 7:18-19).
Isaiah also says:
"Their fire shall not be quenched, and their worm shall not die." (Isaiah 66:24).
Again in Ecclesiasticus, it is written:
"The gathered flax of the congregation of sinners, and their end is a flame of fire. The way of sinners is full of offenses, and their end is hell, darkness, and punishments." (Ecclesiasticus 21:10-11).
Chapter Twenty-Eight
This is the death that awaits those who live according to the flesh, as the holy preaching of the blessed Paul testifies, saying:
Therefore, brothers, we are debtors not to the flesh, to live according to the flesh.
For if you live according to the flesh, you will die; but if by the Spirit you put to death the deeds of the body, you will live.
Romans 8:12-13.
The deeds of the flesh follow when anyone either pursues worldly desires or remains captive to impiety.
The spiritual teaching instructs us to renounce impiety and reject worldly desires.
The Doctor of the Gentiles hints at this with these words:
For the grace of God has appeared to all men, teaching us that, denying ungodliness and worldly desires, we should live soberly, righteously, and godly in this present world, looking for the blessed hope and the glorious appearing of our great God and Savior Jesus Christ.
Titus 2:14 and following.
Therefore, their hope is blessed, their expectation is certain, their future happiness is assured, for those who, denying ungodliness and worldly desires, have lived soberly, righteously, and godly in this world.
Sobriety, justice, and piety must be diligently kept by Christians.
Sobriety is maintained by anyone who arranges their behavior and life properly.
One lives justly by neither harming their neighbor nor, as far as they can, providing assistance in good deeds.
One also lives piously by neither believing nor saying anything perverse about God.
Therefore, whoever wishes to reach the kingdom of heaven must live soberly within themselves, maintain justice with their neighbor, and persevere piously in God.
Chapter Twenty-Nine
These things will be beneficial in the future if they are possessed in the present life.
The blessed Apostle knew and taught this, instructing us to live soberly, justly, and devoutly in this world.
He emphasized that those who will receive mercy in the judgment are those who have led a just life before the judgment.
This is why divine Scripture advises us in the book of Ecclesiasticus:
"Prepare justice for yourself before the judgment, and you will find mercy in the sight of God" (Ecclesiasticus 18:19).
Therefore, anyone who desires to find mercy in the sight of God should prepare justice for themselves now.
What a person does not store up in this present world, they will not have at the time of future retribution.
To demonstrate this sufficiently with testimonies from divine Scriptures, let us first conclude this book so we can then appropriately begin the remaining part of the question.