Sermon Fragments
by Theodulf, Bishop of Orleans
It is hard for us to rise to virtues, but we fall into vices without effort.
Virtues are difficult to achieve, while vices come easily.
We endure great struggles to ascend to heaven.
Just as those striving for the peak of virtues do not start from the top, but from modest beginnings, gradually reaching higher levels; likewise, those who fall into vices do not start with great crimes, but become accustomed to small ones, eventually rushing into greater ones.
It is useless to do good mixed with evil; one must first refrain from evil, then practice good.
This is indicated by the prophet when he says: səˈs to do evil, learn to do good" (Isaiah 1:16).
Vices must first be uprooted in a person, then virtues implanted.
Truth cannot coexist with lies, modesty with boldness, faith with treachery, or chastity with lust.
The lust of the flesh is noticeable to everyone because it is immediately shameful on its own: and yet, in God's judgment, pride is lesser.
However, one who is held by pride and does not feel it may fall into the lust of the flesh, so that through this he may be humbled, rising from shame and pride.
Every sinner is proud because by doing forbidden things, he holds God's commands in contempt.
Therefore, the beginning of every sin is rightly pride, because unless disobedience to God's commands comes first, the guilt of transgression does not follow.
Pride is the origin of all crimes and the ruin of all virtues.
It is the first in sin and the last in conflict.
It either overthrows the mind through sin at the start or finally casts it down from virtues.
It is the greatest of all sins, because it destroys the human mind through both virtues and vices; from the fault of pride, one often goes into the abominable impurity of the flesh, as one depends on the other.
Just as through the pride of the mind one goes into the prostitution of lust, so through the humility of the mind, the chastity of the flesh is preserved.
Yet God sometimes casts down the hidden pride of the mind through the manifest ruin of the flesh.
The impurity of lust stems from hidden pride in the spirit, as we see with the first man.
When he became prideful against God, he immediately felt the shame of lust and covered himself.
Sometimes, a Christian faces a dual attack from the devil: secretly through pride and openly through lust.
But a servant of God, wisely aware of both, avoids lust to prevent falling into pride and fears pride to avoid succumbing to lust.
Demons are more supportive of those who are lustful and proud.
Although they promote other vices, they form a closer bond with these two, serving them more according to their desires.
The devil primarily rules over humanity through these two vices: pride of the mind and lust of the flesh.
Hence, the Lord speaks to Job about the devil, saying: "He lies under the lotus plants, in the covert of the reeds and marsh" (Job 40:21).
The reeds signify empty pride, and the marshy places represent the lust of the flesh.
Through these two vices, the devil takes hold of humans, either by elevating the mind in pride or corrupting the flesh through lust.
Therefore, lust must first be removed from the heart to prevent it from manifesting in actions.
It is said through the prophet: "Gird your loins with sackcloth" (Isaiah 32:11)>, meaning to cut off lusts in the heart.
When the mind is driven towards fornication by demonic impulses, divine judgment and the eternal torment of fire should be considered.
Every temptation is restrained by the fear of greater punishment.
The remembrance of the fire of hell extinguishes the fire of lust.
Continence is granted by God, but ask and you shall receive.
It is given when God is earnestly petitioned with internal groaning.
The beauty of chastity must be cherished, for its delight is found sweeter than that of the flesh.
For chastity is the fruit of sweetness, the untainted beauty of the saints, the health of the body, and the security of the mind.
For anyone who believes they have self-control but doesn't avoid other earthly desires, even if they aren't tainted by carnal indulgence, they are still stained by different worldly activities.
However, every sin can be healed through repentance.
No one can engage in spiritual battles unless they first conquer the flames of greed.
The mind cannot be free to contemplate God if it is burdened by worldly desires.
Greed and the love of money are the worst of all sins.
As Solomon says: "There is nothing more wicked than loving money" (Ecclesiasticus 10:10); greed is the root of all crimes.
As the Apostle Paul also says: "The love of money is the root of all evil" (First Timothy 6:10).
So if the root of crimes is cut, other branches of sin will not sprout.
Greed sold Christ, sold life, and bought death.
It is no wonder that those who have not extinguished the flame of their greed in life are consigned to the fires of hell in death.
It is useful to avoid gluttony and the desire for food.
What is more harmful than for the soul to serve the belly and food, which are destined for destruction, as the Apostle testifies: "God will destroy both them and it" (First Corinthians 6:13).
Food should be used not for indulgence or satisfaction, but solely to sustain the body for the work of God.
Just as all carnal desires are cut away by abstinence, so all the virtues of the soul are destroyed by the vice of gluttony.
No one can achieve the perfection of virtues unless they first conquer the greed of the belly.
No one can master other vices unless they first restrain the vice of gluttony.
One cannot easily expel unclean spirits from themselves without abstinence from gluttony.
Our external enemies are more strongly defeated when the internal vices are first extinguished.
For it is pointless to wage war outside when there is danger within.
Food generates gluttony, and drink produces drunkenness.
Drunkenness, in turn, creates mental disturbance, heart rage, and the flame of lust.
Drunkenness so alienates the mind that it becomes unaware of its whereabouts.
Hence, in Proverbs, "The mighty," he says, "are prone to anger: they should not drink wine, lest when they drink, they forget wisdom" Proverbs 31:5.
Many people boast about drinking a lot and not getting drunk. Let them hear the prophet speaking against them: "Woe to those who are mighty at drinking wine, and valiant men in mixing strong drink" Isaiah 5:22.
Isaiah reproves those who are given to excessive drinking and living recklessly, saying: "Woe to those who rise early in the morning to pursue drunkenness and drink until evening, so that they become inflamed with wine" Isaiah 5:11.
About such people, it is said elsewhere: "Woe to you, city, whose king is a youth and whose princes eat in the morning" Ecclesiastes 10:16.
Many serve the pleasures of drunkenness and gluttony from morning until sunset, not understanding why they were born, but held captive by bestial habits. They serve luxury and feasts all day long. The prophet Joel cries out to those who serve drunkenness, saying: "Wake up, you drunkards, and weep; wail, all you who drink wine in sweetness" Joel 1:5.
Therefore, the care of the flesh must be attentively moderated with discretion, so nothing is done excessively: for whatever is excessive and beyond measure is harmful; but whatever is done with moderation and temperance is beneficial. In every work, therefore, one must have moderation and temperance.
Hence, there are different precepts given to the faithful who live common life in the world, and others to those who renounce this world. To the former, it is said they should manage all their affairs well; to the latter, that they should forsake all their possessions: for it is not enough for those who seek perfection to renounce all their possessions unless they also renounce themselves according to the Gospel. That is, unless they abandon their own wills and renounce evil habits: so that he who was proud may become humble; he who was adulterous, may become chaste; he who was irritable, may strive to be gentle; he who was bold, may strive to be patient; he who was greedy, may become generous; he who withers in hatred or envy against his neighbor, may retain pure love of God and neighbor in his heart.
So, for each vice, let him adopt an opposing virtue and strive to embody good morals, so that he may earn forgiveness for his faults and a reward for his good deeds.
For the Lord says: ɛniˌwʌn wants to come after me, let him deny himself" (Matthew 16:24).
Therefore, those who follow the monastic life without strict commitment, the more loosely they pursue divine love, the more easily they are led back to worldly desires.
For an imperfect commitment seeks the desires of this life, and even if it has not acted on these desires, it is still tied to them through thought.
Thus, it is important to strongly resist bad thoughts.
For he who takes on the profession of holiness with the intention of eventually leading others is not a disciple of Christ but a follower of wickedness, because he strives to bear the burden of Christ's cross not for God, but for worldly love.
Those who leave the world but follow the virtues of the commandments without humility of heart fall grievously from a height, because they are cast down more severely by the pride in their virtues than they could have slipped through vices.
Every servant of God should not exalt himself because of his merits, seeing that others from a lower state can become superior to him.
The conscience of a servant of God should always be humble and sorrowful, so that he does not become proud through humility and does not let his heart dissolve into lust through beneficial sorrow.
A servant of God should read and work without ceasing, lest the spirit of fornication stealthily take possession of an idle mind.
For pleasure yields to labor but quickly seizes upon an idle mind.
Look at Solomon, who, through idleness, became involved in many fornications and, through the vice of fornication, fell into idolatry.
Those who renounce the world out of fear of God but are still entangled in worldly matters, the more they involve themselves in worldly pursuits, the more they withdraw from divine love.
Those who try to serve both earthly concerns and divine exercises at the same time cannot embrace both, as Christ says: noʊˌwʌn can serve two masters" (Matthew 6:24).
Because unless the overwhelming concerns of the world are first expelled from the secret of the heart, the soul within will never rise.
Those who wish to dedicate themselves to God and renounce the world are criticized for neglecting their own cares while attending to the needs of their relatives, separating themselves from the love of God.
A spiritual person should benefit their relatives but must be careful not to deviate from their spiritual purpose while striving to provide physical grace.
Many monks, out of love for their parents, have become entangled not only in worldly concerns but even in legal disputes, and in seeking the temporal welfare of their relatives, have lost their own souls.
Just as we should not hate our own souls, but rather their fleshly desires, we should not hate our parents, but rather the obstacles they present that hinder us from the right path.
Nonetheless, the Lord has commanded us to hate our parents as we do our own souls.
No one can understand the weight of turning from good to evil unless they first turn their whole mind to God.
The progress of each converted person is described as threefold: first, correcting from evil; second, doing good; third, receiving the reward of good works.
Therefore, each person should hasten to God in repentance while they can, for if they are unwilling when they can, when they are willing later, they may not be able at all.
Hence the prophet says: Seek the Lord while he may be found, call upon him while he is near.
Isaiah chapter fifty-five verse six.
And where can he be found, if not in this life, in which he is also near to all who call upon him in truth, Jesus Christ our Lord, who will prepare eternal life and glory for all who truly and faithfully believe in him?
Concerning All Orders of This Age
Since any sin that pleases or entices us should remain in our memory because our sins are already erased, let us not lose the reward of Christ's blood, nor stain the robe of the soul through iniquity, robbery, or lust.
We were down, now we are raised; we were wounded, now we are healed: there will be no excuse.
Whatever wrong the devil can entice us to do, he cannot drag us into it; he brings delight, not power; he suggests advice, not conflict.
Now, therefore, because of the birth of blessed Mary, let me speak to virgins, whether men or women, widows, the powerful, the poor, or servants.
There is no distinction by God except for merits.
So listen to me, all of you who are virgins in body by Christ's gift, I speak generally to everyone.
So listen to me, anyone who recognizes themselves in what I say: strive to be a virgin in heart as well.
Rejoice in the purity of the body so as not to lose the soul's grace; still rejoice in such a precious gift from Christ, rejoice with humility, weep with piety, give thanks for carrying such happiness in purity.
Be glad because you will follow the Lamb wherever he goes:
If, however, as we read in Revelation, no lie is found in your mouth, pray for perseverance, so that no worldly pleasure or the devil's envy takes away such a gift, clouds such brightness, or tarnishes such splendor.
Hold on firmly, do not lose the irreplaceable thing, do not lose the grace of the body for a moment of pleasure: do not contract the ugliness of the soul through the beauty of the corrupted form; do not let lust defeat you.
If you listen to me, you will remain; if not, you will lose what can never be restored.
Again, my message is to you.
Those who have spouses, I advise you to have them chastely.
For Elizabeth, who lived chastely with her husband for many years, and both were faithful before God, deserved to have a son from a dead seed, who would honor the holiness of his parents and convert many unbelievers through his preaching.
Once again, I speak to you, widows.
Maintain your widowhood, do not be talkative, but wait in silence for the Lord, who will take care of the orphan and the widow.
A good widow is one who is in prayer and humility, ready with alms.
If she truly lacks the means, she should have a good will and sincere thought.
Women, do not curse, do not swear, do not be quick to speak.
You might think it's inconvenient for me to say these things: it is not my choice; I fear more the one who commands than the one who criticizes.
I say, let those who recognize this correct themselves; those who do not see it in themselves, rejoice, and hold firm, so they can speak to others for their salvation.
Now I speak to you, penitents, who have received and are performing penance in the church.
Persevere in weeping, mourn wisely in your remorse.
What does it mean to mourn wisely?
Do not seek temporal things in prayer, but eternal happiness and the forgiveness of sins.
Whoever prays in this way mourns wisely.
Your tears should not fall to the ground in vain, because He is truthful when He says through the Prophet: "I have put my tears before you" Psalm fifty-six, verse eight.
You now ought to love God sufficiently and move from fear to love. Because we read in the Gospel about that sinful woman, who was forgiven much, loved much, and therefore you ought to love God greatly, who, by waiting and not punishing, has deemed you worthy to be led to repentance.
Now, a word to you, the poor. I speak to you who beg, who live from the alms of Christians, take comfort; your tribulation will turn into joy and your sorrow into happiness.
Do not be ungrateful that you beg, nor say anything against the Lord in your heart because of it.
Because He is just and merciful in all His works, and He made you poor so that by enduring hardship, you may acquire eternal life, and He made the rich so that by giving you their excess, they may find remedy for their sins: and therefore, be patient, wait for the Lord.
I am speaking to you, servants, those with earthly masters and those in servitude.
Obey your masters and love them from the heart, not just when being watched, but doing your work out of love.
For God has appointed them to rule over you, and you to serve them.
Serve well, because you will be rewarded for good service.
If you are good, you will be better than bad masters.
With the Lord, a person's soul is judged not by nobility, but by deeds; not by birth, but by actions.
Therefore, my message is for everyone, because Christ died for us.
Keep what I have said so that I may have fruit from you, and may the merciful Lord, who lives and reigns forever and ever, admit you all into the heavens where the grain is gathered.
Amen.
Now, dear brother Desiderius, do you wish for me to tell you a little about the writers, who, like lights of the firmament, shine throughout the world, and who were able to clearly bring out many things from the obscurities that hinder spiritual illumination due to carnal understanding?
I will speak, lest I fear the judgment of Susanna, the daughter of Hilkiah, upon me, saying that an unjust judgment of the elders may not be fulfilled: I am in distress on all sides, and likewise, I am in distress.
For if I wish to criticize these things, I will arouse adversaries and enmities everywhere.
But if I wish to fulfill your request, you will never find it, but whose will seems to be condemned rather than to pass over the advice of many or to despise it.
Each of them has deserved to be diligently praised in the Holy Scriptures.
But gently and lightly, with all love, I try to fulfill everything peacefully, like a most exalted bishop flying over the mountain peaks, like an eagle, not considering the many spaces of the heavens, the locations of the earth, and the circle of waters.
He proclaims in clear speech.
For whoever wants to climb a fruitful tree hastens gradually to the higher and greater branches, but leaves the nearby branches to the little ones.
We, however, are the little ones.
I urge you, dear brothers, to work diligently for the progress and betterment of the people in your care.