Prologue
It's easy to discuss obscure topics without much pushback because no one dares to challenge the speaker.
However, when someone tries to shed light on a controversial issue and people openly oppose their efforts, it creates even more doubt among the listeners since they don't know whom to believe.
Unless, perhaps, one of them is proven right by stronger and more convincing evidence.
Therefore, in this second response, we must pray to God to guide my steps on the path of truth and to strengthen the truth of what I say with unwavering support.
A Response Concerning the Damnation of Solomon
You ask, brothers, whether Solomon, the king of Israel, should be considered saved, or as some claim, judged as lost.
So many good and bad things are mentioned about him in the canonical Scriptures that many, when they read or hear them, are left uncertain about which should prevail.
Some, dismissing doubt, say he ended the good he began with a lost end, while others believe he improved by repenting of the wrongs he committed.
I have decided to respond to you, brothers, who seek an answer to this diverse and opposing opinion, and to encourage agreement as much as I can.
Let all your love first understand, therefore, that the things read about Solomon in the canonical Scriptures are distinguished in three ways, so a wise person might carefully consider, as he reads or hears them, how they ought to be understood.
That Solomon in many of his actions prefigured Christ, I think no one doubts; that he prefigured him in all things, let no one dare to affirm.
Among those things said about Solomon, some are fitting to Solomon literally and also mystically fitting to Christ; some are fitting to him but neither can nor should be applied to Christ; some are said, or seem to be said, about him that in no way fit him.
However, they fit Christ according to spiritual understanding.
I believe it is appropriate to discuss some things in which what I have said can be more surely recognized as true.
Scripture indeed says that Solomon built a temple for the Lord in Jerusalem, in which work he prefigured our Lord Jesus Christ more clearly than light.
Who indeed builds a temple for God the Father, that is, the holy Church, while he shapes and squares living stones, that is, holy men, and binds them together with the cement of love, so that being made into one soul and one heart, they may rise into a spiritual building and ascend to see the face of the Creator.
The Scripture tells us that when Solomon was old, his heart was led astray, and he loved foreign women, about whom God had warned: "You shall not associate with them." He turned away from the living and true God, the God of his ancestors, and worshipped Ashtoreth, the goddess of the Sidonians, and Chemosh, the god of the Moabites. This action isn't praised or excused by any allegory but is considered pure history. It's believed that he did this in reality, and it's known that it greatly displeased God.
We also read that the prophet Hosea took a wife of prostitution. Whether this happened literally, or as some think should be understood spiritually, doesn't matter much, as long as we understand that he did it not out of a weakness for lust, but because he was bound by the duty of obedience. In this marriage, he followed the divine command and undoubtedly symbolized Christ. However, the actions of Solomon, who was recorded as having been unfaithful to God, and who, after receiving so many gifts from God, turned to foreign women and worshipped their gods, can't be compared to this.
It's also mentioned to David as if referring to Solomon, which clearly doesn't fit Solomon: "When your days are complete and you rest with your ancestors, I will raise up your offspring after you, who will come from your body, and I will establish his kingdom. He will build a house for my name, and I will establish the throne of his kingdom forever" Second Samuel 7. If anyone carefully considers this promise to David, where his offspring is promised to be raised up-not before his death but after-they will see Solomon isn't referred to here, as he was undoubtedly raised up before David's death. Indeed, Divine Wisdom wisely arranged that Solomon was both born and reigned before his father's death, unlike any other king, so that this prophecy wouldn't be fulfilled in him, as it states: "When you rest with your ancestors, I will raise up your offspring."
It's not specifically mentioned that any of these kings were appointed before their father's death or named king by anyone.
Although King Uzziah was still alive, he was afflicted with leprosy and lived separately because of it.
His son Jotham, as it's written, managed the palace and judged the people of the land.
Jotham isn't called king, nor does the divine Scripture say he reigned until it's declared that his father Uzziah passed away.
Indeed, Jotham could lead by managing the palace and judging the people without being king, because not everyone tasked with judging is immediately given the royal anointing and title.
Solomon, however, was anointed king in Gihon while David was still alive, with the people shouting, "Long live King Solomon" (First Kings 1).
From then on, he is consistently called king, freely taking the throne of the kingdom.
This fulfilled the divine promise that his seed would be raised after David's death, which is understood in Christ.
Therefore, beyond the literal sense, this is fulfilled in Christ in a spiritual understanding, who was to be born from David's lineage long after David and reign eternally with his saints.
"I will establish his kingdom," he says; "He shall build a house for my name." To clarify it doesn't refer to Solomon, who built a material house for God, it adds, "And I will establish the throne of his kingdom forever." Since it's well-known that Solomon's kingdom wasn't everlasting, it's certain that Christ reigns eternally, so it's clear this prophecy foretold him, even though it seems to allude to Solomon.
Furthermore, the addition of: "If he commits iniquity, I will chasten him with the rod of men, but I will not take my mercy away from him, as I took it from Saul, whom I removed from before me," also truthfully refers to Christ, according to the distinctive nature of his members, from whose voice it is said in the Psalm: "Far from my salvation are the words of my transgressions" (Psalm 22).
There's a threefold way of understanding the books of the prophets and all of Scripture, which we call the Old Testament.
Some things can be understood literally, some spiritually, and some in both ways.
It's important not to interpret everything in just one way based on personal preference.
This is, in my view, why people often stumble when reading the divine Scriptures.
They insist on understanding them through their own perspective, and without careful consideration of their words, they defend their errors with bold verbosity instead of truth.
Believing themselves clever and quick to speak, they refuse to learn from their elders.
Impatient to leave the nest, they attempt to discuss before they are ready.
As a result, different people have varied opinions about Solomon, and many disagree with the canonical Scripture, whose authority is established, because they don't fully align with those who have understood and explained it.
Therefore, I thought it fitting, in this response I plan to give to my brothers about Solomon, to compile the thoughts and words of the elders and support my statements with their testimony.
Additionally, I wish to first recount what the canonical Scripture says about him, focusing only on what pertains to the current response.
After the death of the young son Bathsheba bore to King David from adultery, it's said that David comforted Bathsheba, his wife.
He went to her, and she gave birth to a son named Solomon, whom the Lord loved.
The Lord sent a message through Nathan the prophet and named him "Beloved of the Lord" because the Lord loved him. In Hebrew, as they say, it's written: He called his name Jedidiah, which means "beloved for the sake of the Lord."
According to Hebrew tradition, God loved him out of His mercy, even though he wasn't deserving of divine love, as he was born from the woman whom David had taken as his wife against the Lord's wishes.
However, being called beloved because of God, in my opinion, represents him; about whom it is said in the Gospel: "This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased" (Matthew twelve).
The man whom the Word of God assumed in unity of person also did not deserve to be chosen or loved, since whatever was given to the one assumed was credited to grace, not to merit.
The prophet foretold this, saying: "Blessed is the one you choose and bring near" (Psalm sixty-four).
Indeed, blessed was he who was chosen without choosing, so it could also be said to him what was said to us: "You did not choose me, but I chose you" (John fifteen).
As time went on and David grew old, by his command, Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet anointed Solomon as king over Israel, leading him to Gihon.
While David was still alive in Jerusalem, Solomon reigned.
When the king's servants came to him, saying: "May God make Solomon's name greater than your name," the king, they say, worshipped in his bed and spoke these words: "Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, who has provided one to sit on my throne today, with my own eyes seeing it" (First Kings one).
After David passed away, "The kingdom was established in Solomon's hand," it says, and he became related by marriage to Pharaoh, king of Egypt. He took Pharaoh's daughter and brought her to the City of David until he finished building his own house, the house of the Lord, and the wall of Jerusalem all around. However, the people were still sacrificing on the high places because the temple for the name of the Lord had not been built up to that day. So Solomon loved the Lord, walking in the commands of David his father, except that he sacrificed on the high places (First Kings three).
It seems to me that both Solomon's good and bad deeds are highlighted together in these words.
Once his kingdom was firmly established, he made a family connection with Pharaoh by marrying his daughter and bringing her to the city of David.
This was a significant wrongdoing, as he was aware that the Lord had forbidden the sons of Israel from marrying foreign women, to prevent them from being led astray by their charms into idolatry.
If anyone argues that Moses is said to have married Zipporah, the daughter of Reuel, as well as an Ethiopian woman named Tharbis, the daughter of the king of the Ethiopians, for which Miriam and Aaron later criticized him, or that Joseph took a wife in Egypt, the daughter of Potiphera, a priest, the explanation is that such a law had not yet been given by the Lord; and where there is no law, there is no transgression.
Indeed, once the law was given, Samson was reproached by his parents for loving a woman he saw in Timnah, who was one of the Philistine women, and asking for her as his wife.
They questioned, "Is there no woman among the daughters of your brothers, or among all your people, that you must take a wife from the uncircumcised Philistines?"
He could not justify this, providing only the reason that is almost always flawed, his own will.
He told his father, "Get her for me, for she pleases my eyes."
He suggested that the law and reason should be ignored; his desire should replace reason.
Regarding what is mentioned about Solomon: Until he finished building his own house, the house of the Lord, and the wall around Jerusalem, he acted righteously, as he was commanded to build the mystical temple for the Lord and to encircle the city of Jerusalem with a wall.
Yet, it was noted that the people sacrificed on high places.
The fault lay not only with the people who sacrificed on high places but also with Solomon, who did not correct their wayward actions.
For, leaving the city of Jerusalem, where the ark of the Lord was placed in the middle of the tabernacle that David had set up for it, the people sought high places to sacrifice, not because of the sanctity of the places, but because they were pleased by their pleasantness.
The action is somewhat justified by the reasoning presented, making it appear as if it were not a sin, or only a minor one.
It mentions that the temple of the Lord's name hadn't been built until then.
This wasn't to imply that it was commendable before the temple was built, but rather that after its construction, it became a greater sin and entirely inexcusable.
This magnificent temple was commanded to be built with diverse craftsmanship, adorned with golden plates, and dedicated with festive celebrations so that people would gather there to worship and sacrifice.
The temple's holiness would invite them, and its splendid structure would captivate them.
Thus, anyone who later sought other places to sacrifice had no excuse and deserved greater condemnation.
It continues: Solomon loved the Lord, following the commandments of David, his father.
Here, Solomon's righteousness is highlighted, as it's noted that he loved the Lord and followed David's commandments.
However, the text suggests Solomon didn't perfectly love the Lord or fully follow David's commandments when it adds: Except that he sacrificed on the high places.
This was not pleasing to the Lord, nor was it known to be commanded by David.
It's clear that this type of sacrifice is criticized, as it's seen as being outside the love of God and the commandments of David.
Moreover, Solomon accomplished many other things that are believed to have pleased God and were commanded by David before he died.
Then it is said that the Lord appeared to Solomon at night in a dream, saying: Ask what you wish for me to give you.
And Solomon said: Give your servant a discerning heart to judge your people and to distinguish between good and evil.
This request pleased the Lord, as Solomon had asked for such a thing.
And God said to Solomon:
"Because you have asked for this, and you did not ask for long life, nor riches, nor the lives of your enemies, but instead asked for wisdom to discern judgment: Behold, I have done according to your words. I have given you a wise and understanding heart, so that there has been no one like you before, nor shall anyone arise like you after. Moreover, I have also granted you what you did not ask for: riches and glory, so that there will be no king like you in all the days to come. However, if you walk in my ways, as your father David did, I will make your days long."
So Solomon woke up and realized it was a dream.
(First Kings, Chapter 3)
Behold the justice of Solomon again, and his honorable desire; namely, he asked for wisdom to discern judgment.
To whom God, in His goodness, granted not only what was asked but also added riches and glory, which were not requested, with generous largeness.
But it moves me, I confess to your affection; it moves me, I say, what is added: So Solomon woke up and realized it was a dream.
After this, the great and remarkable works of Solomon followed.
He excelled in judging, writing, building the temple of the Lord and its furnishings, among many other achievements that are recorded in the third book of Kings, and are greatly praised by the Scripture as a testament.
Wisdom indeed was received through a dream, which showed how perceptive he was in making judgments, as illustrated by the dispute of the prostitutes, where one said: "Your son is dead, but mine is alive," while the other replied: "You are lying, for my son is alive, and your son is dead" (First Kings, Chapter 3).
To resolve this contention, the king ordered a sword to be brought to him and instructed that the living child be divided into two parts; so that one half would be given to one, and the other half to the other.
Upon hearing this, the mother's heart was deeply moved.
Being truly the mother, she preferred that the entire child remain alive with her rival rather than possess half of him herself.
So she said, "Please, my lord, give her the living child, and do not kill him."
First Kings three twenty-six.
In contrast, the woman whose heart lacked maternal compassion said, "He shall be neither mine nor yours; divide him."
At this, the king, having dispelled the cloud of doubt and recognizing the truth through this test, declared, "Give the living child to her, and do not kill him, for she is his mother."
First Kings three twenty-seven.
The subtlety of his writing is revealed in his three volumes, which are recognized with canonical authority in the catalog of divine Scriptures: Proverbs, Ecclesiastes, and Song of Songs.
In the first, he teaches ethics, informing us of good morals; in the second, he is a natural philosopher, explaining that earthly things are naturally fleeting; in the third, he is a theologian, uniting us in an unbreakable embrace with God and our Lord Jesus Christ.
The first teaches us to love our neighbor; the second, to scorn temporary things; the third, to cling to heavenly matters.
In the first, he instructs the simple and young; in the second, he advances the more mature; in the third, he elevates those already advanced to heavenly matters.
The first teaches us to behave well among people; the second, to disdain things below humans; the third, to embrace things above humans.
Furthermore, he is known by three names, seeming to correspond to these three volumes.
He was called Jedidiah, meaning beloved by people; Ecclesiastes, meaning preacher; Solomon, meaning peaceful.
In the first volume, he teaches how one should conduct themselves blamelessly among others, showing compassion to those lesser, humility to equals, reverence to superiors, and love to all. This is indeed very useful and quite easy for people, and he was called by the name that he achieved through his writing.
In the second volume, he urged everyone to let go of worldly things, emphasizing that they are temporary and fleeting.
He suggested that everything born under the sun is moving towards destruction.
Since he preached openly to everyone, rather than in private, he was fittingly called Ecclesiastes, which means preacher.
In the third volume, titled Song of Songs, it stands out above others, guiding us, once cleansed from vices and strengthened in our disdain for worldly things, into the wedding chamber.
There, with Christ's left hand under our head and his right hand embracing us, we are delightfully nestled in his embrace.
Thus, justice that endures suffering and hardship swiftly advances, and triumphant peace meets them.
To prevent weariness from a lack of reward, it joyfully assists by counting.
These two virtues, justice and peace, celebrate equally when they meet, rushing into kisses and fulfilling the words: "Justice and peace have kissed" as found in the Book of Psalms, Chapter Eighty-Five.
When Solomon wrote about this peace, seen as justice rejoicing in the divine vision when entering the wedding chamber, he was aptly named Solomon, meaning peaceful. This foreshadows the one who became our peace, uniting us and reconciling us to God through his death, so that we, once children of wrath, might through grace become children of mercy.
Moreover, as it is written, he spoke about the trees, from the cedar in Lebanon to the hyssop growing from the wall, and discussed the animals, reptiles, and fish. However, this Scripture is found neither among us nor among the Hebrews, nor anywhere else, though sometimes it is doubted that there were three hundred sixty-five.
However, there are two volumes often read in our Church, one called the Wisdom of Solomon and the other Ecclesiasticus. Due to some similarity in style, some believe Solomon wrote them, but those who are older and wiser consider this assumption to be false.
To begin with, the Wisdom of Solomon, as Jerome notes, is renowned for its Greek eloquence.
Since it's not found among the Hebrew texts, it's believed to be the work of a certain Philo, not Solomon himself.
Ecclesiasticus, on the other hand, is said to have been written by Jesus, the son of Sirach, who lived during the era of the high priest Simon.
This Simon succeeded the priest Onias and came before another Onias, who, as the Second Book of the Maccabees tells us, was unjustly killed by Andronicus on the advice of Menelaus.
The wisdom of Solomon is apparent in the construction of the Lord's Temple and its furnishings.
If you examine it closely, you'll find not only great beauty in its literal form but also a remarkable depth of spiritual insight.
It's recorded that Solomon gained this wisdom through God's internal guidance and the external teachings of his father, David.
He completed the work with the assistance of many, both locals and newcomers.
The fact that God taught him is evident from the Third Book of Kings, which states: God gave Solomon wisdom and understanding, and a heart as expansive as the sand on the seashore.
And soon after: God gave wisdom to Solomon, as He had promised.
David's diligent instruction for this work is clearly shown in the First Book of Chronicles:
David provided Solomon with the plans for the porch, the temple, the storerooms, the upper rooms, the inner chambers, the house of atonement, all the courts, and surrounding chambers for the treasures of the house of the Lord, and for the treasures of the holy things, as well as the divisions of the priests and Levites for all the work of the house of the Lord, and for all the service vessels in the temple of the Lord.
David also supplied Solomon with pure gold and silver, by weight, to make the utensils for the house of the Lord, as detailed there.
To make sure this description is commendable and seems to come not from himself but from God, David adds:
"All these things came to me written by the hand of the Lord, so that I might understand all the works of the pattern."
Lastly, the Scripture says:
"King Solomon loved many foreign women, including the daughter of Pharaoh, as well as Moabite, Ammonite, Edomite, Sidonian, and Hittite women, from nations about which the Lord had warned the children of Israel:
'You shall not enter into marriage with them; neither shall they marry you, for they will surely turn your hearts to follow their gods.'
Despite this, Solomon was deeply attached to them in love, and the women turned his heart away.
As he grew older, the women led his heart astray to follow other gods.
His heart was not fully devoted to the Lord his God, unlike his father David's heart.
Solomon worshipped Ashtoreth, the goddess of the Sidonians, Chemosh, the god of the Moabites, and Moloch, the idol of the Ammonites.
Solomon did what was not pleasing to the Lord and did not fully follow the Lord as his father David had done.
He even built a shrine for Chemosh, the idol of Moab, on the mountain east of Jerusalem, and for Moloch, the idol of the children of Ammon.
The Lord was angry with Solomon because his heart had turned away from the Lord, the God of Israel, who had appeared to him and commanded him not to follow other gods.
But Solomon did not observe what the Lord had commanded.
As a result, the Lord raised an adversary against Solomon, Hadad the Edomite, from the royal line.
Jeroboam, son of Nebat, an official of Solomon, also rebelled against the king.
Solomon tried to kill Jeroboam, but he fled to Egypt and stayed there until Solomon's death.
The rest of Solomon's acts, everything he did, and his wisdom, are recorded in the Book of the Acts of Solomon.
Solomon rested with his ancestors and was buried in the city of David, his father.
First Kings eleven.
These are the concluding details found in the canonical Scripture about Solomon.
While they appear straightforward, they are definitely worthy of serious reflection.
Through these passages, we are reminded of the need to lament human suffering and to remember and fear only God's justice.
Our own sense of justice is either insignificant or nearly so, as it cannot initiate or complete itself.
This is why the prophet, as if lacking or disregarding justice, said, "Lord, I will remember only Your righteousness" Psalm 70.
Who wouldn't praise Solomon, supported by such incredible blessings-wisdom, power, wealth, and glory, all generously given by the divine? We would consider him happy, provided his happiness was flawless.
However, when we read that he, despite his wisdom and advanced age, succumbed to luxury and idolatry, who wouldn't mourn the transient nature of human life? Who wouldn't fear the stringent test of divine justice?
It's important to understand that anyone who boasts should do so not in themselves, but in the Lord. Remember what's written: no one can be self-disciplined unless God grants it. Hence, "I went and sought the Lord" Wisdom 8.
Even a diamond's strength doesn't persist unless God shields it with His mercy. That's why, according to the seventy interpreters, the prophet Amos saw the Lord standing over a diamond wall, holding a diamond in His hand. A diamond is a precious stone, known for its resilience against hammers, anvils, files, fire, and the passage of time. Yet, despite all this, it cannot withstand the warmth of goat's blood; if touched by it, all its strength dissolves.
The Lord fittingly appears to hold a diamond in His hand and seems to lean on a diamond wall because without His strength to protect it, no stone would remain intact.
For those who did not fear the sound of enemy trumpets, who mocked the attacks of warriors, and who did not yield to the charges of crossbows, if touched in any way by goat's blood, would tremble, collapse, and be completely shattered.
The diamond stone symbolizes any saint of remarkable strength, while goat's blood signifies the impurity of lust.
Therefore, no matter how strong someone may be due to their virtues, if they are stained by the blemish of lust, they collapse, perish, and become utterly weakened.
It's not surprising, then, that Solomon, who was once supported by such great divine power, later fell grievously due to unchecked lust, as he didn't take care to gird his loins with the belt of strength, nor did he fear departing from divine worship.
But perhaps we wonder why God allowed him to sin so grievously, when He had wished to adorn him with such virtues.
Let's recall the Angel who, due to his holiness, was called Lucifer and was permitted by God to fall from heaven.
We should not blame the divine balance of fairness for this, but rather the unchanging malice of the one who fell.
Therefore, it is not to be questioned why God allowed it to happen, but it should be understood with fear that God allowed it.
He permits, with hidden but just judgment, not for the diamond to be snatched from His hand, but to slip; and while His hand is strong enough to keep it safe, the will of the one slipping is enough for the fall.
Once slipped, even if one thinks they can resist other attacks, they cannot remain unscathed against goat's blood.
This is aptly applied to Solomon, who for a long time seemed to be held by the divine hand, but eventually slipped and fell into such great wickedness that he neither remembered having been there nor feared being far from it.
So, what I said about Scripture bringing up the issue in the end deserves closer attention, so that with the Lord's help, it can be understood correctly.
However distinguished the path may have been, it's ultimately judged by its end: it's not those who lived well at some point, but those who persevered, that are praised.
It is said that King Solomon loved many women, including the Pharaoh's daughter, as well as Moabite, Ammonite, Hittite, Edomite, and Sidonian women, about whom the Lord had said: You shall not go to them.
I'm curious when divine Scripture specifically mentions foreign women like Moabites and Ammonites and others whom Solomon is said to have loved, but it singles out the Pharaoh's daughter.
This seems to me either because Solomon is recorded to have taken no other Egyptian woman except her, because he is believed to have loved her more than the others, or because he is found to have had her before and much longer than the others.
It was mentioned earlier that when his kingdom was established in his hand, before he dreamed of being wise, he was allied with Pharaoh by marrying his daughter and bringing her to the city of the Lord.
Even though Scripture does not openly criticize him for this alliance, nor is it recorded that he forsook his God at that time or worshipped foreign gods, in the end, it is clearly shown that he is judged worthy of blame both for her and for the others.
For the Pharaoh's daughter would not have been included among those he is accused of loving unless he was proven to have sinned by loving her too.
When Scripture states that Solomon loved foreign women, including the Pharaoh's daughter and the others it lists, it clearly indicates how and to what end he loved both her and the others when it adds: So, Solomon was joined to them with an intense passion, and the women turned his heart.
It continues: And when he was already old, his heart was led astray by the women.
An intriguing contradiction has become clear through experience: while the passion of desire is intense during adolescence or youth, it cools down in old age.
The one who is restless in the vigor of youth is compelled by a natural law to become quieter as they age.
So, when a son was promised to an elderly Abraham, he responded,
Do you think a son will be born to a man who is 100 years old, and will Sarah, who is 90 years old, give birth?
(Genesis chapter 17).
Soon after, Sarah herself said, After I have grown old and my lord is old, shall I have pleasure?
(Genesis chapter 18).
This suggests that when the sparks of the flesh have cooled over time, how could they engage in acts of pleasure again?
It's clear that Abraham and Sarah came together not so much out of desire, but with the hope and intent of having children.
Furthermore, when David had grown old, as it is written, a young virgin was sought to keep him warm.
Abishag the Shunammite, a beautiful young girl, was found.
She cared for the king and lay beside him, but the king, it is said, did not know her intimately.
Here, you see a virgin at the start of puberty sleeping beside the king without losing her virginity because the king, far removed from youth's desires, was protected from lust by his old age.
However, Solomon, when he was old, instead of cooling down naturally, perversely burned with lust.
He was so led astray by his love for women that he even followed their gods.
His heart was not fully devoted to the Lord his God, unlike his father David.
This perfection, which the divine Scripture notes Solomon lacked, is also said to have been missing in some other kings.
Even though they accomplished great deeds, they did not remain steadfast in their purpose.
It is said of Abijah, the son of Rehoboam, that his heart was not fully devoted to the Lord his God.
However, the story clearly shows that Abijah, whose heart was not perfect, was rejected because it says: "He walked in all the sins of his father before him."
His father was Rehoboam, about whom it is said in the Chronicles that when Rehoboam's kingdom was established and strong, he abandoned the law of the Lord, and all Israel followed him.
It concludes that he did evil and did not prepare his heart to seek the Lord.
So, if Abijah followed all the sins of his father, it's clear he didn't end his life well, just like his father.
It's also written about Amaziah that he did what was right in the sight of the Lord, but not with a perfect heart.
The fact that he didn't act with a perfect heart is evident when it's added: "Amaziah, after defeating the Edomites, brought back the gods of the children of Seir, set them up as his gods, worshiped them, and burned incense to them" (Second Chronicles 25).
You see, according to Scripture, these two kings led reprobate lives, and it's recorded that their hearts were not perfect with God.
Finally, when Scripture wanted to commend King Asa, the son of the same Abijah I just mentioned, it said: "Nevertheless, Asa's heart was perfect with God all his days" (Second Chronicles 15).
In this perfection, I see nothing else but perseverance, about which the Lord says in the Gospel: > "He who perseveres to the end will be saved" (Matthew 10).
Even if Asa sinned at times, he is believed to have ended his life well; otherwise, it wouldn't say: "His heart was perfect with God all his days," but perhaps, "perfect for some days."
That Asa was perfect, meaning he persevered with God all his days, is hinted at earlier when it says of him: "Asa did what was right in the sight of the Lord, as David his father had done" (Second Chronicles 14).
David, indeed, even though he sinned, never completely departed from the path of righteousness, but was guided back to it by divine guidance and was found to be complete in it.
David is often praised in the books of Kings, either to commend good rulers or to criticize bad ones, emphasizing his perfection.
Regarding Jehoshaphat, a righteous man and son of Asa, Chronicles states:
"The Lord was with Jehoshaphat because he walked in the ways of his ancestor David."
Second Chronicles Chapter 17.
About Hezekiah, both Kings and Chronicles say:
"He did what was pleasing before the Lord, just as all that his father David had done."
Second Kings Chapter 20.
About Josiah in the book of Kings:
"He did what was pleasing before the Lord and walked in all the ways of his ancestor David."
Second Kings Chapter 22; and in Chronicles: "He did what was right in the sight of the Lord and walked in the ways of his ancestor David."
Second Chronicles Chapter 34.
However, about Abijah, whom we mentioned earlier as being rejected, the book of Kings says:
"His heart was not perfect with the Lord his God, like the heart of his ancestor David."
First Kings Chapter 15.
Regarding Amaziah:
"He did what was right, but not like his ancestor David."
Second Kings Chapter 14.
About Ahaz:
"He did not do what was pleasing in the sight of the Lord his God, like his ancestor David."
Second Kings Chapter 16.
You can see that none of these kings is described as having a perfect heart like David, except those considered just according to Scripture. This is not denied to anyone except those whose lives are judged as rejected. Perfection, or likeness to David, is attributed to Asa, Jehoshaphat, Hezekiah, and Josiah, who are testified by the divine word to have remained just. However, this perfection is denied to Abijah, Amaziah, and Ahaz, who are declared rejected in Scripture. This perfection frequently appears in the books of Kings and Chronicles, representing enduring righteousness.
About this, Jehoshaphat speaks in Chronicles:
"When Jehoshaphat established in Jerusalem the Levites, priests, and leaders of families, to judge the cause of the Lord and justice for its inhabitants, he commanded them, saying: 'So you shall act in the fear of the Lord faithfully and with a perfect heart.'"
Second Chronicles Chapter 19.
What does it mean to act faithfully and with a perfect heart?
It means doing well and seeing it through to the end.
When it says "faithfully," it refers to faith that works through love, and "with a perfect heart" signifies perseverance.
When the prophet Isaiah told Hezekiah, "Set your house in order, for you shall die and not live," Hezekiah turned his face to the wall and prayed to the Lord, saying, "I beseech you, Lord, remember how I have walked before you in truth and with a perfect heart." Second Kings chapter 20.
Reflecting on his past life and considering his present conscience, he saw that he had persevered in the Lord's commands up to that time; and so, even though he wept, he found joy in such perfection.
It seems to me that David also calls Solomon to this same perfection. "You, Solomon, my son," he says, "know the God of your father, and serve him with a perfect heart." First Chronicles chapter 28.
Because this cannot be achieved by human effort alone without divine grace, David himself prays to God, saying, "Lord God of Abraham, give my son Solomon a perfect heart." First Chronicles chapter 29. He also prays for himself in the Psalms: "Make my steps perfect in your paths." Psalm 17.
If this perfection is perseverance, as it seems to be, then it appears that Solomon lacked perseverance, unless perhaps he alone is exempt from what is attributed only to the reprobate kings. In reviewing the kings of Judah from David to Zedekiah, the last king, none, as far as I have considered, is denied a perfect heart with God like David, except those whose lives are judged as reprobate.
None is noted to have had a perfect heart with God like David, or to have walked in the ways of David, except those known to have completed a good life excellently. I wonder, therefore, if it is in vain that only about Solomon, it is said what is ascribed to other kings as a testimony of condemnation, that in him alone it does not have the effect that he did not have a perfect heart with God like David.
If so, I am prompted by what is still added.
When Scripture spoke about Solomon, it said, "His heart was not fully devoted to the Lord his God, as the heart of David had been." It then added, "And he did not fulfill the task of following the Lord, as David his father had."
Notice, it didn't say, "He did not begin to follow the Lord," but rather, "He did not fulfill the task of following the Lord."
So, what does it mean to fulfill?
It seems to mean simply that he did not complete, finish, or carry through to the end.
If it were true that he had repented, then indeed, he fulfilled the task of following the Lord.
For who fulfills the task of following the Lord except the one who finds a good end? And who, except the one who fulfills this task, finds a good end?
Yet, if it's said that Solomon didn't fulfill the task because he sinned while following, it could also be said that David fulfilled it, even though he sinned too.
However, it seems incorrect to say this about David since Scripture greatly praises his fulfillment.
In the very area where Solomon is criticized for not fulfilling the task, it shows that David did fulfill it.
Otherwise, it wouldn't be said, "He did not fulfill the task of following the Lord, like David," but instead, "He did not fulfill the task of following the Lord, just as neither did David."
Clearly, David fulfilled the task of following the Lord, but Solomon, as written, did not.
If another meaning exists in these words that aligns with truth and does not oppose Solomon's salvation, I am open to a better understanding, especially if it's supported by divine Scripture or the testimony of the elders.
It goes on to say that Solomon built a shrine for Chemosh, the idol of Moab, on the hill facing Jerusalem, and one for Molek, the idol of the Ammonites.
Since Scripture mentioned that his heart was led astray by women to follow foreign gods, it now explains how he followed them, showing clearly that he not only was led astray but also led others astray.
It's said that he built a shrine to Chemosh on the hill opposite Jerusalem.
It wasn't enough for him to turn his heart towards foreign women; he also worshipped their gods and encouraged others to do the same.
This shrine to Chemosh was created so people would gather there, and following the king's example, openly engage in the worship of demons.
For who among the people, seeing the wisest king building a shrine and bowing down to demons, wouldn't be inspired to commit the same sacrilege?
Especially since it's recorded that these people were always inclined towards it.
If you look into the old Scriptures, you'll find that they were quite stubborn, often forgetting to worship God and repeatedly falling into idolatry.
Even when they were called back by divine punishments, they frequently relapsed.
So, taking the cue from the king, God's people became idolatrous.
Having abandoned the temple established on Mount Moriah by God's command, the same people worshipped at the shrine to the idol Chemosh that the king built on the hill across from Jerusalem.
It's fitting that the shrine is described as being set on the hill opposite Jerusalem, symbolizing how one form of worship opposes another, with one hill said to oppose the other.
For on Mount Moriah, the temple of the Lord was situated.
It's the strange envy of the ancient enemy who, since he cannot have what God has, at least wants a counterpart.
Seeing divine worship celebrated on the mountain, he wanted a shrine dedicated to himself on a hill to overshadow the temple of the Lord to some extent and to counter Mount Moriah with an opposing hill.
This is indeed what he boasts about in his heart:
"I will sit on the mount of the covenant, and I will be like the Most High"
(Isaiah 14).
And note that where the temple of the Lord was built is called Mount Moriah, meaning the mountain of vision, while the hill where the shrine to Chemosh was built is called the mountain of offense.
Since God finds it worthy to observe those offering gifts in His temple, the place is fittingly adorned with such a name.
This reflects the truth in the name itself, and the devotion of the offerers is strengthened by the hope of being seen by God.
It is indeed the mountain where God witnessed Abraham offering his son Isaac out of obedience, as it is written in Genesis chapter twenty-two: "On the mountain, the Lord will see."
The mountain where Solomon built a shrine for Chemosh was rightly called the mountain of offense, because God was offended there, as were the worshippers of divine religion. These high places were left by Solomon as a testament to his mistake, which, much later, the just King Josiah is recorded to have destroyed. It is said that he did this for all his foreign wives, who burned incense and made sacrifices to their gods.
This indicates that he constructed shrines or idols not only for the God of the nations but for many, and worshipped not one, but many. When it is said that he did this for all his foreign wives, it is clear he worshipped their gods to satisfy the desires of all those he loved, led by voluntary error.
From this, it can also be inferred that he did not love the daughter of Pharaoh without fault, and for her sake, worshipped the Egyptian gods, just as he did for the others. Therefore, the Lord was angry with Solomon, because his heart had turned away from the Lord God of Israel, and he did not keep what the Lord had commanded him.
After these words, nothing in the canonical Scripture clearly approves or even somewhat considers Solomon's repentance. Having spoken on this chapter as I deemed appropriate, I now believe it should be shown with what testimonies my statements are supported, lest I appear to begrudge Solomon's salvation, and twist the Scriptures presumptuously rather than truthfully to my own ends.
Some people find it very troubling when it's suggested that Solomon didn't repent.
They're more inclined to believe rumors from talkative Jews than to trust what Church scholars have written.
Isidore, the bishop of Seville, when interpreting the events related to Solomon-like the building of the temple, his wisdom in writing, the judgment involving the prostitutes, and the visit from the Queen of Sheba-concluded his thoughts on the matter.
So, what can be said about his other actions, when Holy Scripture strongly criticizes and condemns him, and says nothing about his repentance or receiving forgiveness from God?
There's also no indication of anything positive in his unfortunate downfall, unless perhaps one might claim that the foreign women he loved so passionately represent the churches chosen from different nations.
This might not be entirely unreasonable if those women had turned away from their gods to worship Solomon's God.
But since he offended his God because of them and worshiped their gods, there's no good that can be inferred from this.
Yet, I don't think it's meaningless; rather, it signifies something negative, much like we discussed about Lot's wife and daughters.
In Solomon, we see both remarkable excellence and a significant downfall.
Therefore, what was good and later evil in him at different times is reflected in the Church today simultaneously.
I believe that Solomon's goodness represents the good people of the Church, while his evil represents the bad ones, as if in one ark, like one person, the good are like grains and the bad like chaff, or in one harvest, the good are the wheat and the bad are the weeds.
When Isidore mentions that Holy Scripture records nothing about Solomon's repentance or God's forgiveness, he clearly indicates that within the Scripture itself, there's no clear or hidden suggestion of his repentance.
When it says below that this person was first good and then later evil at different times, it clearly means he started well and ended badly.
It doesn't say he was good, then evil, and then good again, which it certainly would have said if it intended to prove his repentance.
Instead, it mentions that he was first good and later evil, and nothing more is mentioned about his goodness.
Furthermore, Isidore wanted to support these and other points scattered throughout his book with the testimony of the ancients.
In the preface, he states: These things are taken from authors like Origen, Victorinus, Ambrose, Jerome, Augustine, Cassian, Fulgentius, and Gregory, who speaks eloquently in our times.
However, whether all three hundred seventy of them spoke about Solomon, or what they said about him, I haven't fully discovered since I haven't read all their books.
I don't recall reading any book by Victorinus yet; as for the others, I've read some but not all.
Therefore, what I've found in their books, or in the books of others about Solomon, I will present, provided that persistent forgetfulness hasn't erased what reading has once taught me.
Origen, in the twentieth homily on the Book of Numbers, while speaking of Solomon, said: If you reread what is written about Solomon, you will find that although he was very wise, he inclined himself to many women.
So, even though he was very wise and had great merits before God, he was deceived because he gave himself to many women.
I believe that many women represent different teachings and diverse philosophies of various nations.
Wanting to explore and investigate each one, as a knowledgeable and wise man, he couldn't keep himself within the rule of divine law; Moabite philosophy deceived him and persuaded him to make offerings to the Moabite idol.
Similarly, with the Ammonites and other nations.
It's truly remarkable to be surrounded by so many doctrines, almost like being among numerous women, and still not stray from the truth.
As the scripture says:
"There are 60 queens and 80 concubines, and young women without number; yet there is one, my dove."
(Song of Solomon, Chapter 6).
In Origen's words, there's no hint of Solomon's repentance.
Instead, it's noted that he was led astray by his involvement with many women, failing to adhere to divine law.
Thus, Origen emphasizes the greatness of being immersed in numerous doctrines, like being among women, and yet remaining true to the essence of truth, consistently stating:
"There are 60 queens and 80 concubines; yet there is one, my dove."
This suggests that Solomon might have said this, but he didn't maintain consistency. To be consistent means to persevere until the end. Bede comments on the Gospel of Luke, saying:
"It is not the beginning of patience, but perseverance that grants the glory of the heavenly kingdom, because perseverance, which is also called constancy, is a certain strength and fortitude of the mind and the pillar of all virtues."
In his twenty-seventh homily on Luke, Origen explains how Matthew and Luke might have different genealogies for Christ. He states:
"In Matthew, the wife of Uriah is named, who violated her husband's bed. Because our Lord and Savior came to take upon himself the sins of men, therefore, descending into the world, he assumes the roles of sinful and flawed men and wished to be born from the lineage of Solomon, whose sins are recorded, and Rehoboam, whose transgressions are referred to. But when he rises from baptism and is described as being born for the second time, he is not born through Solomon, but through Nathan, who reproached his father over the death of Uriah and the birth of Solomon."
In these words, Origen clearly criticizes Solomon and Rehoboam, without offering any claim of their repentance.
Matthew aimed to trace Christ's lineage by moving from the higher to the lower, including the names of flawed individuals in this genealogy to show that He was born from sinners, as He came in the flesh to condemn sin.
Therefore, he mentioned Solomon and Rehoboam, whose sins, as Origen noted, were recorded.
Luke, on the other hand, ascends from the lower to the higher, describing Christ not as descending into the world but as ascending from the baptismal water.
He starts the genealogy from Joseph and leads up to God Himself.
After discussing Christ's baptism, he wrote: "And Jesus Himself was about thirty years old, as was supposed, the son of Joseph, who was the son of Heli, who was the son of Matthat, who was the son of Levi," and continues upward, ending the list with, "who was the son of Shem, who was the son of Adam, who was the son of God."
In this catalog, where he intended to place God as the ultimate end, Luke chose not to include Solomon and Rehoboam, so the lineage, which finishes with such a holy end, wouldn't be tainted by Solomon, whose sins are recorded.
Instead, he inserted Nathan the prophet, who not only isn't accused but also reproved King David, Solomon's father, with humble presumption.
Some say Nathan the prophet, who reproved David over Uriah's death, wasn't David's son but the son of Shammah, David's brother.
He is also said to be called Jonathan by another name, but when referred to as a prophet, he is only called Nathan.
Nevertheless, David had a son named Nathan, whom Luke included in his catalog instead of Solomon, whether as a prophet or not.
Augustine, in the second Tractate on Psalm eighty-nine, says: "He promised something from his seed forever, and Solomon was born.
Solomon was endowed with such great wisdom and prudence that God's promise concerning David's seed seemed fulfilled.
But Solomon fell, leaving room for hope in Christ.
Here, God would say to you: I indeed swore and promised, but he did not want to persevere."
What then? Lord God, did you not know that this one would not persevere?
Of course, you knew.
So why did you promise me something eternal in someone who would not persevere?
Augustine says in his treatise on Psalm one hundred twenty-six: Solomon was a lover of women and was rejected by God.
But if, when he fell, the things said through him were erased, it would be judged that he said them, not that they were said through him.
You see that Augustine states in the previously mentioned Psalm that Solomon did not persevere, but even so, while he was rejected by God, the things he wrote were not rejected.
Augustine speaks in the seventeenth book of "The City of God" about David and Solomon:
David reigned in earthly Jerusalem, a son of the heavenly Jerusalem, highly praised by divine testimony, because even his faults were overcome with such great humility in penance that he is among those of whom it is said:
Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiven, and whose sins are covered.
(Psalm thirty-two).
After him, his son Solomon reigned over the same whole people, who began to reign while his father was still alive.
He had a good beginning but a bad end, as the prosperity that wears out wise minds harmed him more than his wisdom, which is still memorable now and was then widely praised.
Augustine could not have given a clearer judgment about Solomon than by saying: He had a good beginning but a bad end.
He would not have said this if he had known that Solomon had repented.
For if he truly repented in the end, he had a good, not a bad end.
Finally, before his death, Augustine, having been engaged with the divine Scriptures for forty years, carefully reviewed the books he had written from the beginning of his conversion up to that time;
finding two hundred thirty-two, aside from letters and popular treatises, he compiled in one volume whatever seemed worthy of criticism, either by criticizing or by defending and explaining how it should be understood.
So, he reviewed the book "The City of God" among others, but he didn't find it necessary to correct his statements about Solomon. If he had learned over such a long period from either the canonical Scripture or the writings of previous Fathers about Solomon's repentance, he would not have said Solomon ended badly, or he would have refuted such claims if they were made.
Pope Gregory, who lived far from Augustine in both place and time, agreed with this conclusion. He states in the second book of "Morals": The quality of the end time is expressed by the action, just as Judas is said to have gone out into the night to the betrayal's treachery, never to return to grace, when the evangelist says: "It was night" (John 13).
Similarly, it is said to the wicked rich man: "This night your soul will be demanded from you" (Luke 12).
A soul that is led to darkness is remembered not during the day but at night.
Thus, Solomon, who received wisdom not to persevere, is described as having received it in a dream and at night.
These are Gregory's words.
Consider what he said: Solomon received wisdom but did not persevere, and so he received it in a dream and at night.
However, he clearly wants perseverance to be understood as the end when he says: The quality of the end time is expressed by the action.
There is no doubt that both Judas and the wicked rich man ended badly, indicated, as Gregory says, by the quality of the time.
But if Solomon, whom he associates with them, returned to the light of true wisdom through repentance, to which anyone who truly repents undoubtedly returns, then for him the quality of time expresses not the end but the middle of the action.
Therefore, when Gregory said: The quality of the end time is expressed by the action, he should not have used Solomon as an example if Solomon's actions indeed had a bright end, assuming he repented.
This is why it troubles me, as I mentioned earlier, what exactly the sacred Scripture means when it says: "Solomon awoke and realized it was a dream" (First Kings 3).
While he was in a blissful sleep, he thought that what he saw was permanent and real.
But when he awoke, he realized that what he saw was fleeting and insubstantial.
What does this mean?
What, I ask, except that he wouldn't maintain the wisdom he gained in his dream, just as he didn't stay within the dream where he became wise?
For in dreams, we don't remain, and it's only upon waking that we realize we were asleep.
Therefore, Solomon would have been fortunate if he had never awoken, obtaining in his dreams what he couldn't, or didn't want to, keep while awake.
The end of dreaming hints at the end of understanding: the darkness he found upon waking signifies the sins he fell into when he became foolish.
Indeed, you will rarely find saints who became wise through dreaming.
Rather, those who are found to possess wisdom gained it by being awake.
Even though God spoke to some ancient fathers through visions or dreams, as He tells Aaron and Miriam:
"If there is a prophet among you, I will appear to him in a vision and speak to him in a dream" (Numbers 12), it is not recorded, if I am not mistaken, that He granted the gift of wisdom to anyone through dreaming.
This was to ensure those seeking wisdom would be motivated not by laziness and idleness, but by study and diligence.
Regarding the apostles, Luke says that while they were awake: "Then he opened their minds to understand the Scriptures" (Luke 24).
The evangelist John, who drew the streams of God's word from the Lord's heart, drank from that fountain with great delight, is not recorded as having slept on Christ's chest at the supper, but as having reclined (John 21).
In secular writings, I recall reading, as if in a dream, that Ennius dreamed on Mount Parnassus and suddenly became a poet.
Hence, this poet is not highly praised by later generations.
In his writings and actions, he's judged not only to have dozed, like even the great Homer sometimes did, but to have slept deeply and snored ineffectively.
Although Solomon's wisdom is commendable because it was given by divine means, it ultimately didn't serve him well because he didn't remain faithful to it.
As Augustine said, "The troubles of this world, which tire the minds of the wise, harmed him more than his wisdom benefited him.
It is remembered now and will be in the future, and it was widely praised at that time."
Pope Gregory also supports this by using Solomon's example to say that the quality of the time reflects the end of action.
Fulgentius, without writings, in the eighth book, without hesitation, says, "My God, what does such a secret dispensing of Your judgment mean?
Why does the offspring of a stained crime enjoy the success of his father's kingdom?
Was it right that Solomon, tainted by the contamination of an adulterous womb, should receive the merit of building the temple, search the treasures of wisdom, or become the successor and more powerful ruler of his father's kingdom?
But see, the son of a crime fell into crime, and the illegitimate offspring did not meet a good end."
Though he may discuss everything from the hyssop to the cedars of Lebanon, wait for the Queen of the South to admire his wisdom, build an amazing temple, command spirits, abound in prudence, be skilled in judgment, shine with wealth, glitter with gold, and blaze with gems, in his life, he tarnished whatever he had drawn from nature.
And what is worse than anything else, in his old age, he was no longer the most prudent but an impudent worshiper of pagan gods.
When Fulgentius says that Solomon, the son of crime and an illegitimate offspring, did not meet a good end, he clearly denies his repentance, adding how much his old age was hostile to religion, as he did not preserve it with prudence but, as he says, "Polluted it with impudent worship."
Paschasius, a deacon of the Roman Church, was a man highly educated in divine writings.
Gregory speaks of his holiness and knowledge in the fourth book of Dialogues with these comments about Solomon:
"His offspring will remain forever, and his throne will be like the sun in my sight, and like the perfect moon forever and a faithful witness in heaven."
Therefore, those who want to accept this statement about Solomon should consider how his throne could be like the sun in the sight of God the Father, when Holy Scripture says that his heart was turned away due to his desire for women, and he worshiped Astaroth and Chamos, the god of the Sidonians, and other monstrous deities of the nations.
Hence, Scripture concludes that God was not with Solomon; if God was not with him, how could his throne shine like the sun in the sight of God the Father, especially when he was defiled with all the impurity of lust and condemned for idolatry?
Or how could he be a faithful witness in heaven, when he was found to be a false witness on earth by venerating idols?
But since this cannot be understood about him, it is necessary that it be interpreted, whether the enemy likes it or not, as relating to Christ.
These are Paschasius's words about Solomon, in which he says that on earth he was found to be a false witness by venerating idols and was condemned for idolatry.
Bede, a priest known for his diligent study of the works of previous Fathers, incorporated many of their insights into his own writings. In a small book he wrote to Nothelmus about certain questions in the book of Kings, he commended Josiah:
"There were high places in Jerusalem on the right side of the Mount of Offense, which Solomon, king of Israel, had built for Astaroth, the idol of the Sidonians, and Chamos, an offense to Moab. King Josiah defiled and crushed the statues."
And he added about Solomon: "Where, unless I am mistaken, it is shown, what I wish was not shown, that Solomon never perfectly repented of the crime of idolatry he committed."
If he were truly producing fruits worthy of repentance, he would be eager to remove the idols he had built from the holy city.
He wouldn't leave actions that he did mistakenly, as if they were wisely and rightly done, to become a scandal to fools.
The same words, as they appear in Bede's little book, were also included in the works of Anglosmus and Rabanus, who came after Bede.
Since I mentioned some things that are as clear as daylight regarding Solomon's repentance, I will address those claims that seem to be confirmed, so I do not appear to deliberately ignore what others choose not to remain silent about.
I found some small leaves where certain things were written as evidence of his repentance, taken from the works of the holy Fathers.
Therefore, I will share what I found collected there, so by not being silent, I do not offend those who are more sympathetic towards Solomon than is justified.
Regarding King Solomon's transgression, I will briefly mention what the holy Augustine, an excellent teacher, thought, and what the interpreter and expositor of divine law, Jerome, wrote about his repentance, or where the defender of the Catholic faith, Ambrose, called him holy.
Augustine adds: In the exposition of the book of Genesis, in the eleventh book, he says about Solomon: Is it to be believed that a man of such wisdom thought there was some deity in the worship of idols?
No, but he could not resist the allure of women leading him to this evil, doing what he knew should not be done, so as not to upset his deadly delights, in which he was perishing and declining.
Augustine says these things in the eleventh book concerning Genesis; but if anyone looks more closely at the context, they will find not an excuse, but an accusation of Solomon.
Augustine does not say this to confirm that Solomon repented, but to show that he sinned knowingly, understanding it should not be done, yet, despite God, he obeyed the will of the women.
Just like the first Adam, he sinned knowingly.
Even though he was aware he shouldn't follow the woman's urging, he did so because he feared upsetting his companion, thinking she would be devastated if he didn't join her in wrongdoing.
As the Apostle states:
"Adam was not deceived, but the woman was deceived and became a transgressor" (First Timothy 2),
indicating that she believed the serpent's lie, while he knew it was false yet still complied.
Augustine discusses this Adam, whom the Apostle mentions was not deceived, in the book we referenced earlier, asserting that Adam sinned knowingly, not out of ignorance.
Augustine clearly explained this in the fourteenth book of "The City of God," drawing a parallel:
"Just as Aaron did not agree with the misguided people's request to make an idol but yielded under pressure, and it is not believable that Solomon mistakenly thought idols should be worshipped but was compelled by the allure of women to commit such sacrilege, so too it should be believed that Adam was not deceived by mere words into breaking God's law, but obeyed out of social obligation."
Augustine adds about Adam to ensure he doesn't seem to excuse him or others:
"Nor is he any less guilty for being knowledgeable and wise."
Thus, in these words, no repentance is praised, but harmful knowledge is condemned, as per James the Apostle:
"If anyone, then, knows the good they ought to do and doesn't do it, it is sin for them" (James 4).
Also, in the small notes: Ambrose, in the book "Hexameron," mentions Solomon, saying:
"Know yourself, oh man,"
not as the Pythian Apollo would say but as the holy Solomon did, who said:
"Unless you know you are beautiful among women."
Also, Ambrose in "Apology of David":
"What shall I say about David, what about holy Solomon? Who, because the Jewish people thought he had come for Christ, lest he seem to be above man, fell by divine will."
This is Ambrose.
To clarify why Ambrose referred to Solomon as sacred, he wrote in his notes, as if agreeing with them himself:
"David," he says, "is not called holy, even though everyone knows he is holy. But Solomon is named holy to remove any doubt about his repentance."
Gregory the Pope, in his seventh homily on the final part of the prophet Ezekiel, shares a similar thought about Aaron, whom David calls holy. He references the verse from the Psalm:
"They angered Moses in the camp; Aaron, the holy one of the Lord" (Psalm 106).
He explains that Moses is not called holy, because everyone already knows he is holy; and Aaron is named holy to remove any doubt about his life.
Therefore, what Gregory says about Aaron, this person mistakenly applies to Solomon, even though the same Gregory, who confirms Aaron's holiness, denies Solomon's repentance, as previously mentioned.
Furthermore, in the same apology for David where Ambrose names Solomon as holy, he does not confirm his repentance; in fact, if examined closely, Ambrose denies Solomon's repentance.
For he states:
"Why should I speak of holy Solomon, whose later actions are not free from grave error, yet the Jewish people believe he came for Christ? And how many did the offense of grave error bring back? Was it not more beneficial that his greater fault prevented him from being considered above mere humans, who are not free from human flaws?"
When Ambrose mentions that Solomon's later actions were not free from grave error, he clearly indicates that they rejected repentance, which, if they had embraced it as some claim, would undoubtedly have freed them from grave error.
Ambrose himself seems to suggest why God allowed Solomon to sin so severely in the end: so that people would not mistake him for Christ if he had completed his initial holiness with the intended conclusion.
Many people, as he says, were turned away from the serious error of this offense because he clarified that this man was just human and should not be mistaken for Christ.
This benefited the salvation of the chosen more than persistent justice would have, which could have led to the downfall of many.
So don't be surprised if Ambrose refers to Solomon as holy in the places we mentioned earlier, as well as in other instances that aren't necessary to examine right now.
Finding it once or twice is enough.
Philip, too, in his first book on Job, calls him holy: "As the holy Solomon says, the fruits of the wicked are sins." And elsewhere, similar references can be found in the works of other Fathers, if one wishes to explore further.
However, in my view, this doesn't prove that Solomon repented, nor does calling him holy mean he returned to a life of holiness in his final days. It simply means he was holy at one point. Just like Peter was called Satan when he wasn't thinking of God's ways but human ways, even though he didn't remain in that state, Solomon can rightly be called holy, even if he didn't stay in the holiness he once had.
For those who say Peter is only called Satan when he opposed Christ, and after he abandoned that fault, he's never called Satan again, they should remember the Scriptures. The Apostle advises reading carefully, and they'll find that many are still referred to by what they once were, even if they no longer are that.
In Matthew, when Judas Iscariot approached Jesus and kissed him, Jesus said, "Friend, why have you come?" Matthew chapter 26, verse 50. It's clear he calls him friend, even though Judas was no longer a friend, but once was. It's not believable that Judas never loved Christ, even though he didn't continue in that love.
Just as the unjust often, through God's mercy, turn and become just, in the same way, the just sometimes, when God abandons them, become perverse and unjust. As it is in Ezekiel...
It's explained when it's said, "If a wicked person repents and does what is just and right, they will live and not die. But if a righteous person turns away from their righteousness and does wrong, committing the sins they have committed, they will die in them. Yet it should not be said, as is added there, 'The way of the Lord is not fair'." Indeed, it's not necessary to provide many scriptural testimonies to prove this-since in the unpredictable course of life, we see it happen more often than we read about it-saying one thing is enough, and let's return to the topic.
When Matthew was listing the apostles, he referred to himself among others as a tax collector: "Philip and Bartholomew; Thomas and Matthew the tax collector." At that time, tax collectors were involved in public business, which could hardly be conducted without sin, or they didn't hesitate to involve themselves in crimes and scandals, disregarding the standard of living well. They were allowed to do whatever they desired, not by the decree of law but by the decree of a corrupt will.
Certainly, Matthew wasn't like that when he wrote the Gospel and called himself a tax collector, but without a doubt, he had been one when he sat at the tax booth. Nevertheless, warned by Christ's call and inspiration, he gave up the tax booth along with other things he was doing or possessing wrongly, leaving behind the reality but not the name.
In that same Matthew, the Lord says, "Pharisees, tax collectors, and sinners are going ahead of you into the kingdom of God" (Gospel of Matthew 21).
How, I ask, do tax collectors go ahead of Pharisees into the kingdom of God, unless they have ceased to be tax collectors?
He refers to those who were once tax collectors, and when they enter the kingdom of God or approach later than others, they have undoubtedly stopped being tax collectors.
The Evangelist Mark speaks of this same Matthew's calling: "He saw Levi sitting at the tax booth and said to him, 'Follow me.' And he got up and followed him."
As he was reclining at the table in that house, many tax collectors and sinners were also sitting with Jesus and his disciples.
It's unlikely that these tax collectors and sinners with Jesus in Matthew's house were the same as they used to be.
I believe they received significant grace, as Christ deemed them worthy of his company and called them to repentance.
So, when the scribes and Pharisees murmured about this, he responded, "I have not come to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance."
This means: I haven't come to call those of you who think you are righteous, which you are not, but those who, by recognizing their past, have earned the right to change.
The Evangelist Luke states: One of the criminals hanging there mocked him, saying, "If you are the Christ, save yourself and us."
But the other criminal rebuked him, saying, "Do you not fear God, since you are under the same sentence?"
And he said to Jesus, "Remember me, Lord, when you come into your kingdom."
When Luke mentions one criminal mocking and the other rebuking him, he refers to both as robbers, although clearly, the blasphemer was guilty of robbery, while the other had changed, becoming a devoted confessor.
These words were spoken because Ambrose calls Solomon a saint, which, as it seems, doesn't contradict other teachers, among whom Augustine says, "He had a good beginning but a bad end."
By saying this, Augustine indicates that Solomon started well but ended poorly, which is why Ambrose attributes sainthood to him.
Similarly, the divine sermon mentions that some other kings of Judah and Israel had holy beginnings to their reigns, yet their endings were indeed evil.
While the early actions of Joash, Amaziah, and Uzziah, kings of Judah, are praised, their final acts are condemned.
The kings of Israel, whose kingdom was divided, started with Jeroboam son of Nebat and ended with Hoshea son of Elah.
All of them were disapproved, even though some of their deeds were praised.
Skipping over others, Jehu son of Jehoshaphat son of Nimshi received divine praise but was later criticized:
If you listen closely, you'll hear the Lord speaking to Jehu,
"Because you have diligently done what was right and pleasing in my eyes, and have accomplished all that was in my heart against the house of Ahab, your sons will sit on the throne of Israel to the fourth generation."
The Scripture then adds: "After this, Jehu did not take care to walk in the law of the Lord God of Israel with all his heart; for he did not turn away from the sins of Jeroboam, who made Israel sin" (Second Kings 10).
Just like King Jehu, whose works were initially pleasing to God but later tainted, the same Scripture tells us Solomon was at first pleasing to God.
However, in his old age, he incurred divine wrath because of women.
This is followed by the Little Leaves: A Testimony of Solomon's Repentance.
This was taken from a booklet by Bacharius; however, his name is not mentioned there.
In the booklet written to Januarius, Bacharius suggests that one should not despair over a brother who has fallen into fornication and highlights Solomon's fall and repentance.
Solomon, he says, was once so wonderful that he deserved to be joined to the helper of God, that is wisdom.
Yet, he fell into the arms of foreign women and, caught in the chains of lust, defiled himself with sacrilege by making an idol of Chamos, the Moabite god.
But because he acknowledged his error through a prophet, is he truly beyond heavenly healing?
Perhaps you'll say: I never read in the canon that he repented or obtained pardon.
Listen then, brother:
Some say his repentance, which is not written in the laws, might be acceptable because it wasn't done publicly but privately within his conscience, with God as his witness.
We understand he received pardon for this, as Scripture notes that when he passed, he was buried among the kings of Israel.
This honor was denied to other sinful kings who remained wicked until their deaths.
Therefore, because he was worthy of being buried among the righteous kings, he wasn't excluded from forgiveness, but he couldn't have received this forgiveness without repentance.
These are the words of Bacharius.
He asks, "Since he acknowledged his error through the prophet, is he then excluded from heavenly healing?"
I wonder which book Bacharius read to conclude that Solomon acknowledged his sin through the prophet and repented, as this isn't found in the canonical Scripture.
If he examines the books of Kings, Chronicles, or other books the Catholic Church holds as authoritative, he won't find, if I'm not mistaken, any prophet rebuking Solomon for sinning or urging him to repent, although this is recorded for David, Asa, and other kings, both just and unjust.
It is noted that God spoke to Solomon four times, without a prophet acting as an intermediary.
When his kingdom was secure in his hand, while he was in Gibeon, "The Lord appeared to Solomon in a dream at night, saying: Ask what you wish me to give you" (First Kings chapter 3); and further: "When he had completed the house he was building, with cedar ceilings, and had constructed a floor over the whole house, the word of the Lord came to Solomon, saying: This house you are building, if you walk in my commandments, I will establish my word to you that I spoke to David your father" (First Kings chapter 6), etc.
Much later: "When Solomon had finished the construction of the house of the Lord, the Lord appeared to him a second time, as he had appeared in Gibeon."
The Lord said to him, "I have heard your prayer" First Kings 9.
In the end, when he had provoked divine anger through both lust and idolatry: "The Lord was angry with Solomon," He said, "because his heart had turned away from the Lord his God, and he did not keep what the Lord had commanded him."
Therefore, the Lord said to Solomon, "Since this has happened to you, and you have not kept my covenant and my commandments that I have commanded you" First Kings 11.
Neither here nor elsewhere afterward in the canonical Scripture is Solomon read to have acknowledged his sin through a prophet, to be believed to have found heavenly healing through this.
Finally, when Ahijah the Shilonite prophet foretold to Jeroboam, son of Nebat, that he would rule over ten tribes of Israel: "Ahijah took his new cloak," he said, "tore it into twelve pieces, and said to Jeroboam, 'Take ten pieces for yourself.
For this is what the Lord says: See, I am going to tear the kingdom out of Solomon's hand and give you ten tribes, because he has forsaken me and has not walked in my ways as David his father did.
But I will take you and you will reign'" First Kings 11.
And after the speech of Ahijah the Shilonite, Scripture adds: "Therefore, Solomon wanted to kill Jeroboam" First Kings 11.
From this, it can be gathered that what the prophet had spoken, that Jeroboam would indeed rule, Solomon recognized.
But with this knowledge, he did not apply heavenly healing to his wound, as he wanted to kill out of envy and murder the one whom the divine will had decided should reign.
But he rose, it says, and fled to Egypt and stayed in Egypt until Solomon's death First Kings 11.
If Bacharius wants to refer to Josephus, the Jewish historian of antiquity, to defend what he asserts about Solomon under his patronage, he will not find that he claims Solomon repented.
Although he says a prophet came to him.
Not to seem unfairly to withhold from Bacharius, I will bring Josephus's words to the forefront.
Solomon, driven by an irrational love, married seventy wives and had three hundred concubines, including the daughter of the king of Egypt.
He was so captivated by them that he even followed their religious practices.
As he grew older, his reasoning weakened, and he could no longer maintain his father's ways.
He constantly honored the gods of two of his wives.
Then, a prophet was sent by God, saying that Solomon's wrongdoing was not hidden from Him and that he wouldn't find happiness in these things for long.
Hearing this, Solomon trembled and was greatly troubled, and he suddenly turned away from almost all the good things he had.
This is what Josephus says about Solomon.
However, how he suddenly changed is explained further: not long after the prophet foretold these events, God immediately raised an enemy against him named Hadad.
A little while later, as Solomon was already troubled by his previous transgressions and was abandoned by God, Hadad came from Pharaoh to Edom.
Since Solomon couldn't confront him, as Hadad was protected by many defenses, his presence was unwelcome, and he moved on to Syria.
There, he joined a man named Rezon, formed a close friendship, and gathered a great band of robbers around him.
He eventually took control of Syria, becoming its king.
Then he roamed around, afflicting the province of the Israelites, and continued to trouble Solomon.
Meanwhile, Jeroboam, son of Nebat, rose against Solomon.
Knowing Jeroboam's intentions and deceit, Solomon sought to capture and kill him.
In Josephus's account, there is no mention of Solomon's repentance, only his sin, and due to this sin, both he and the entire region suffered.
And it concludes: Solomon died at a very old age and was buried in Jerusalem, surpassing all kings in happiness, wisdom, and wealth-except in those areas where, in his later years, he was swayed by his passion for women and broke the law.
However, Josephus clearly points out much earlier that Solomon did not repent for his wrongdoings.
He states: "While Solomon was the most glorious and religious of all kings, surpassing all previous rulers of the Hebrews in wisdom and wealth, he did not maintain this path until the end of his life. Abandoning the observance of his father's traditions, he disgracefully succumbed to his passion for women and excess, not ending his life in the same way David did."
As you can see, Josephus also mentions that Solomon did not end his life as David did, just as the canonical Scripture notes, which we discussed earlier: "For his heart was not with the Lord like David's; and he did not fulfill his duty to follow the Lord like David."
If he had truly repented, as David undoubtedly did, it could be genuinely said that he ended his life in the same manner as David. Therefore, Josephus's words simply underscore Solomon's sin and his lack of repentance afterward.
Let's return to the canonical Scripture and Bacharius. Scripture states, "Solomon slept with his fathers and was buried in the city of David" (First Kings 2).
From this, Bacharius tries to argue that Solomon should be considered saved because he is not recorded as being excluded from the royal tombs, from which some kings were excluded.
It states he was buried in the city of David: the city of David is called Zion, which is also Jerusalem.
David was anointed king over Israel and went to Jerusalem, known as Jebus; he began at the stronghold of Zion, which is the city of David.
David lived in the stronghold, and so it was called the city of David.
David was buried there, as it is written: "David slept with his fathers and was buried in the city of David."
All the kings of Judah after David, totaling twelve, both just and unjust, were recorded as being buried up to Hezekiah.
However, as the Scripture notes, some were not included in the tombs of the kings.
For instance, in the Book of Chronicles, it's written about Joram: They buried him in the City of David, but not in the tombs of the kings.
Regarding Uzziah, also known as Azariah, the Book of Kings states: They buried him with his ancestors in the City of David.
In the Second Book of Chronicles, about the same person: They buried him in the field of the royal tombs because he was a leper.
It's worth questioning whether being buried in the field of the royal tombs differs from being in the tombs of the kings.
It might not seem different, but the additional explanation clarifies it somewhat.
Scripture, aiming to explain why he was buried in the field of the royal tombs, added that it was because he was a leper.
This doesn't appear to have been added to honor him, but rather to highlight his disgrace.
Therefore, it's understood that the field of the royal tombs was larger than the specific area of the tombs, and Uzziah is believed to have been buried in a section somewhat removed from the others, as he remained a leper until his death.
Just as when he was alive, being expelled from the temple, he lived in a separate house due to his leprosy, perhaps after death, he was buried in a separate tomb for the same reason.
Therefore, what is said in the Book of Kings, that they buried him with his ancestors in the City of David, shouldn't be interpreted as him being buried with his ancestors within their tombs, but simply in the same city with them.
For it's also written about Joram in the Book of Kings: And Joram slept with his ancestors and was buried with them in the City of David.
Similarly, in the same book, about Joash: And they buried him with his ancestors in the City of David.
However, the Chronicles mention that they were excluded from the tombs of the kings, as noted earlier.
Similarly, regarding Ahaz, the Chronicles state: They buried him in the city of Jerusalem, but he was not received into the tombs of the kings, as mentioned in Second Chronicles, chapter twenty-eight.
Only these four kings, from David to Hezekiah, are noted to have been excluded from the tombs of the kings, if Uzziah is included among them.
Scripture does not indicate that any others were excluded.
Among those others are Rehoboam, Abijah, Ahaziah, and Amaziah, who are certainly considered wicked.
Bacharius's argument isn't very suitable or convincing, specifically that Solomon should be considered saved just because he wasn't excluded from the tombs of the kings.
Being buried among kings doesn't prove eternal holiness, but rather indicates some temporary honor.
Being excluded from them isn't a judgment of eternal damnation, but reflects the people's enduring hatred towards the king.
Lastly, divine Scripture neither explicitly states nor subtly implies that being buried with righteous people makes one righteous.
Saul and Jonathan were buried under an oak in Jabesh-Gilead, where Saul is seen as unjust, yet Jonathan is declared just.
Similarly, King Manasseh of Judah and his son Amon were buried in the garden of his house, in the garden of Asa.
Scripture notes that Manasseh, after many crimes, sincerely repented before God, while Amon stubbornly continued in his wickedness.
There is another account of Solomon's repentance in the Book of Leaves.
Jerome mentions in the thirteenth book on the prophet Ezekiel: Solomon sinned and offended God, though he later repented, writing Proverbs where he says: In the end, I repented, and I looked back to choose discipline.
This verse, which Solomon is said to have stated in Proverbs, cannot be found in Proverbs, even if you read it from start to finish a thousand times.
Jerome himself translated the Proverbs of Solomon from Hebrew into Latin.
In his translation, he didn't include the same verse that, if he had found it in the Hebrew texts, he would have undoubtedly included.
Jerome was such a faithful translator that, as he often admitted, he neither added, removed, nor changed anything in the Holy Scriptures.
He carefully conveyed the Hebrew truth into Latin, either word for word or sense for sense.
However, before he translated the Holy Scriptures, other translations were already read in the Churches, namely those by the Seventy translators, Aquila, Symmachus, Theodotion, and the fifth edition.
Someone might suggest that he perhaps took the foretold verse from one of these.
In his works, he referenced many testimonies from the Scriptures, not only according to the Hebrew truth but also according to the editions of various translators.
Even if he seemed to introduce new ideas, as he said, he shouldn't be accused of destroying the old.
To address this, it's important to note that Origen, who lived long before Jerome, doesn't seem to mention this, even though he was very familiar with all those editions.
Origen had compiled a library from all of them, except that of the Seventy translators, arranging them in six rows on a single page.
This allowed a diligent reader to easily see how one edition differed from another or matched with it.
Jerome stated that the Greek read the interpreters of the old law-Aquila, Symmachus, and Theodotion-carefully, and through Origen's effort, these were dedicated to the Churches in the Hexapla.
Elsewhere, Jerome remarked that Aquila, Symmachus, and Theodotion were Judaizing heretics who obscured many of the Savior's mysteries with deceitful interpretations.
Yet, they are included in the Hexapla in the Churches, which are exemplars or libraries having six rows.
Origen, in his second homily on Leviticus, notes: Some might think there's an error in translation, but I've found through careful research that all translators have rendered it in the same way.
This shows that Origen had access to all the translations by the interpreters.
Since Origen, as mentioned, arranged six editions in a library with six columns, we can ask who the individual interpreter for each was.
We know the interpreters for four of them: the Septuagint, Aquila, Symmachus, and Theodotion.
Regarding the fifth, sixth, and seventh editions, Jerome says Origen discovered them with great effort.
Apart from the version translated by the seventy wise men, which was more commonly used in churches at that time, Origen combined the other three-Aquila, Symmachus, and Theodotion-with the fifth, sixth, and seventh editions, arranging them in one library as already mentioned.
We do not know the interpreters of these last three editions well, unless we suppose Aquila was the author of one, making him responsible for two translations, even if we don't know why he translated a second time.
Jerome clearly shows in his Commentary on Ezekiel that Aquila produced two translations, mentioning the first edition at times and the second at others.
However, since neither Jerome nor other scholars frequently specify which edition they refer to, whether the first or the second, some believe he had only one edition, and the distinction has either not been discovered or remembered.
This distinction is more clearly noted in the verse on Ezekiel, where Jerome equally mentions both the first and second editions.
The first edition, he notes, was seen as the staff of Aquila, the second as Symmachus, and the foundation by Theodotion.
Here, both the first and second are named more clearly, and it's shown that Aquila expressed different ideas in different contexts.
I believe Origen included both in his library, as previously mentioned, having collected all the interpreters' translations.
Origen himself doesn't easily claim Solomon's repentance; instead, in the places we mentioned earlier, he states that Solomon was also misled by women.
And concerning the Songs, he consistently didn't make such claims.
He also mentions that both Solomon and his son Rehoboam were excluded from the genealogy of Christ, which Luke composed.
Starting from the lowest, he led up to God, ensuring that the sins of those recorded wouldn't be mentioned in the lineage culminating in God.
Although others are omitted, David is explicitly named there, despite his adultery and murder being documented in the sacred writings.
However, as the prophet Nathan testifies, David's sins are removed, yet the sins of Solomon and Rehoboam aren't noted to have been erased through repentance.
If the canonical Scripture asserts that their sins were erased, there's no reason why Solomon, a man of such great wisdom, merit, and fame, should be left out of the catalog of the righteous, while his father David is included due to his repentance.
The other ecclesiastical teachers, who were around before Jerome or during his time and had some fame, hadn't seen Jerome's edition or accessed it through other translations of the divine Scriptures.
They didn't report finding the aforementioned verse in Proverbs.
This isn't because I've read all their writings, but because I don't believe it could have escaped Augustine, Gregory, Paschasius, Bede, Fulgentius, Isidore, who flourished in various places and times in the Church and read the writings of preceding Fathers with great zeal; yet concerning Solomon, they all shared the same opinion.
I believe, however, that Jerome's Commentary on Ezekiel was not unknown to them.
But when they read it, they either didn't approve of the testimony about Solomon's repentance found there, or perhaps they didn't find it at all.
It's possible that Jerome didn't mention it in his Commentary, or at least not in a definitive way.
But due to either a reader's diligence or a scribe's carelessness, the text was corrupted, changing its meaning.
This is exactly what Jerome frequently complains about: the manuscripts of Scripture, both Greek and Latin, being corrupted by scribes' errors.
Therefore, his friends often urged him to either correct the old ones or create new ones.
I don't dare to assert, or even consider, that Jerome, a man of such great knowledge and authority in the canon of Scripture, would hold an opinion contrary to everyone, or have everyone opposed to him.
It's one thing to interpret something in the Scriptures with consistent truth, and another to be adversarial with the same resistance.
Therefore, just as when Jerome explained another work of Solomon, namely Ecclesiastes, he didn't affirm it but attributed its affirmation to the Hebrews, he might have done the same regarding Ezekiel.
When speaking about the same Solomon, he is likely to have expressed a tentative rather than a fixed opinion, even if the texts now present it differently.
He indeed says about Ecclesiastes: The Hebrews say this book is of Solomon repenting; Jerome didn't say: This book is of Solomon repenting, which he could have confidently and truthfully stated if he had found him repenting in Proverbs.
Who would doubt that Ecclesiastes is a book of Solomon repenting if Proverbs testify that he repented, when the universal Church holds that Solomon himself wrote Proverbs first, and then Ecclesiastes?
If, however, he wrote Proverbs after repenting, then even more so Ecclesiastes, which he wrote after Proverbs.
Therefore, he could confidently say: This book belongs to Solomon, who is repenting; it should not be attributed to the Jews.
Not only here, but many times elsewhere, he tends to assign to them what he recognizes as false or, if he's unsure of its truth, does not presume to affirm.
They often make statements contrary to the truth, and Jerome himself, in many instances, and notably in the Revelation of John, highlights this, identifying them not as Jews, as they falsely claim to be, but as the synagogue of Satan.
The books that the Catholic Church reads, written by him, were believed by the Church's teachers to have been composed before his regrettable sin, not after his repentance.
They documented this in their works to ensure we remain informed.
Thus, Augustine, on the eighth step of the Gradual Psalms, previously stated: Solomon, he says, was a lover of women and was rejected by God.
However, if what was spoken through him had been erased due to his fall, it would be judged that he spoke it, not that it was said through him.
These words show that Solomon wrote first and fell later, but by God's providence for us, rather than for him, what he wrote did not fall with him.
Moreover, the sacred history first tells us that he received wisdom in a dream, then later engaged in writing, and finally, when he was an old man, he turned away from God by clinging to foreign women.
That's enough about this; let's return to Jerome.
Therefore, when discussing Ecclesiastes and asserting Solomon's repentance, he did not presume to make a rash judgment but cautiously attributed it to the Jews.
Regarding Ezekiel, he is believed to have maintained a similar manner of speaking; thus, he is rightly thought not to have accused the other learned holy men of foolishness and ignorance, nor should he himself be accused of error.
We can easily sidestep these issues by attributing any displeasure we find to the errors of the scribes.
As they transcribed Jerome's Commentary, which was carefully dictated and perhaps even more carefully revised, they might have been doing so under orders or for payment.
Speaking one thing aloud while thinking something else, or perhaps even nodding off, they either carelessly omitted what was originally there or added what shouldn't have been.
Jerome himself addresses this negligence, saying: "Correcting the book serves no purpose unless the scribes diligently preserve the correction." In his commentary on Hosea, when discussing the righteous kings, Jerome mentions: "When we have read that David, Asa, Jehoshaphat, Hezekiah, and Josiah were righteous kings."
Here, I'm quite confused as to why he overlooked Solomon, who was famous for his wisdom, power, wealth, and glory, and should have been included among the righteous kings if he returned to justice through repentance from his past sins. It's not particularly surprising that Jerome didn't include Manasseh, whom Scripture notes repented, among the righteous, as his life showed no truly righteous acts until he repented at the end.
However, Solomon, who before his serious sins of indulgence and idolatry was renowned for his wisdom, power, impressive works, wealth, and glory, even if he strayed from the path of justice for a time, should not have been excluded from the list of righteous kings. We've read that David and Asa, who also committed serious sins, were called righteous not only by Jerome but also by canonical Scripture.
Elsewhere, Jerome harshly criticizes Solomon; and after doing so, he doesn't offer any evidence of repentance, but instead claims that he and King Ahaz were involved in wicked deeds without mentioning their absolution through repentance.
When talking to the priest Vitalis about Solomon and Ahaz, King of Judah, Jonathan's son and Hezekiah's father, he mentions that both were tainted by the impurity of idolatry.
However, he doesn't mention them being cleansed over time.
Vitalis says, "Consider that Scripture accuses Solomon and Ahaz of indulgence and impiety.
Although both came from the lineage of David, they turned away from the Lord.
Solomon indulged in lust to the extent that he had seventy wives, three hundred concubines, and countless young maidens and prostitutes.
Neglecting the God of his fathers, he built idols of many nations and was no longer beloved by the Lord, but a lover of women."
Jerome doesn't mention Solomon's repentance here but rather connects him with the impious King Ahaz.
This implies that, just as they are clearly shown to agree in idolatry, neither seems to differ from the other through repentance.
If you want to hear Jerome's clearer testimony, which shows significant disagreement with Solomon's repentance, listen to what he says elsewhere to the monk Rusticus, where he clearly contradicts Solomon's repentance.
"What is wiser than Solomon?" he asks.
"Yet he becomes foolish because of women's love."
To prevent any misunderstanding of what it means to become foolish, Jerome explains by recalling this passage from the Gospel: "Salt is good, but if it loses its flavor, it is thrown out and loses its dignity to the point of not even being useful in a manure pile."
Therefore, when Jerome says Solomon became foolish and adds that salt that has lost its flavor is thrown out and is no longer useful, he clearly asserts that Solomon was rejected, meaning he was never brought back to the taste of repentance.
For it's known that salt that has lost its flavor is irreparably depleted, and having lost its true taste, it is never salted again, but is found completely useless everywhere and always, as it neither seasons itself nor anything else.
So, when the Gospels talk about salt losing its flavor, it represents a wicked person who, having lost the taste for righteousness, becomes corrupted by foolish and tasteless perversion and cannot be restored to their original state through any repentance.
David noticed this when he spoke about a certain wicked person.
Knowing that this person's counsel would not be pleasing to God, he humbly asked for that counsel to become foolish, meaning to be rejected by God's will.
"Please, Lord," he said, "make Achitophel's advice foolish."
This request was not foolish, but rather it condemned Achitophel's wickedness, as he offended the Creator's justice with his perverse and unjust advice. When his plan failed, he went home and hanged himself.
Therefore, the salt that has lost its flavor is rightly thrown out. This rejection symbolizes the same condemnation where any perverse individual is irreparably condemned. The throwing out is indeed a symbol of eternal condemnation, where the miserable are bound hand and foot and cast outside, not allowed to enter the joy of the Lord.
David seemed to dread this rejection when he considered the multitude of his sins, as if he saw it looming over him. What he had said in trembling at that time, he later sang joyfully when his fear had somewhat subsided.
He said, "I said in my alarm, 'I am cut off from your sight'" (Psalm Thirty).
When I feared, he says, the burden of my sins, I said, "I am cut off from your sight," considering myself unworthy of your grace, as if my many sins hindered your great mercy. But because I was afraid, I was humbled by my fear, and humbled, I called upon you; therefore, you heard the voice of my prayer when I cried out to you.
He says in another psalm what he cried out: "Do not cast me away from your presence."
"Do not cast me away from your presence," he says, "but hide me in the secret place of your presence."
Because once you're cast out from your presence, you are compelled to be thrown into outer darkness, but hidden in the secret place of your presence, you rejoice, free from all human disturbance.
Let us also say: "Good Jesus, do not let us lose our way, do not cast us away from your presence, lest we perish with Ahithophel or the wicked servant who was cast out, but let us rejoice in the eternal safety of your hidden face."
Therefore, since Jerome asserts that Solomon was led astray and cast out, it's clear he does not confirm his repentance.
He appears inconsistent, not only with other teachers but also with himself, if he states one thing about Solomon regarding Ezekiel and another to Rusticus.
John Chrysostom, in his treatise "On the Recovery of the Fallen," praised David's repentance magnificently and brought Solomon into the discussion, yet made no mention of Solomon's repentance.
It seemed quite appropriate for him to present Solomon as an example of repentance, just as he presented David as an example to the fallen one he was trying to bring back to repentance.
Especially since, as I mentioned before, he recalled Solomon's memory there.
For he says: "Blessed David fell in the same way as you now, and not only that, but he added something even more serious."
"For he combined murder with adultery."
"And indeed, after these things, did he remain fallen?"
"Did he not rise, and again stood against the enemy, and he overcame him so that even after his death, his merits benefited his descendants?"
For when Solomon committed that enormous crime and deserved a thousand deaths, the Lord said he would grant him the whole kingdom because of David.
For he says: "I will surely tear the kingdom away from you and give it to your servant."
"However, I will not do it in your days, for the sake of David your father, but I will take it out of the hand of your son."
First Kings eleven.
But even Hezekiah, when he came into extreme dangers, although he was just himself, the Lord said he would bring him help for David's sake.
Here, John and David are praised for their repentance, and Hezekiah is recognized as just.
Among them is Solomon, yet he is neither described as repentant nor just.
It's said that only David's merits helped Solomon so that his kingdom wouldn't be divided during his lifetime, even though he was considered deserving of a thousand deaths.
In the homily on the fiftieth psalm, the same John highly praises David's repentance and highlights many repentant figures: namely, Peter, Paul, Matthew the tax collector, Mary the sinner, and the Thief.
Among these, Solomon is not praised for repentance.
Although, no repentance would have been more noteworthy than that of such a rich, powerful, and wise king, if it had been mentioned in Proverbs or any canonical Scriptures that he had repented, or at least in the writings of the Fathers deemed credible and authoritative.
Moreover, the venerable Bede, when interpreting the Proverbs of Solomon based on Jerome's translation and revealing what was in the ancient translation, did not mention finding anything about Solomon's repentance.
Nor did he know of any discoveries by others, but in the small book he wrote to Nothelm, he stated that Solomon never repented perfectly.
It continues in the notes: The Hebrew books claim that Solomon was dragged through the city's streets five times for the sake of repentance.
They also say he went to the temple he had built with five rods and offered them to the legal experts to be beaten by them.
However, they, after consulting together, decided not to lay hands on the Lord's anointed.
Therefore, frustrated by them, he deposed himself from the kingdom.
This is noted in the records.
Jerome translated all the Scriptures in the Hebrew canon into Latin, in which there's no mention of Solomon being dragged through the city's streets for repentance or offering rods to the legal experts for punishment.
The other Scriptures they have are considered apocryphal, and their authority isn't suitable for settling disputes.
So, books like the one of Jesus, the son of Sirach, Judith, Tobit, and the First Book of Maccabees are seen as apocryphal by them because they aren't included in their canon.
If they claim to have other books, such as those including the Repentance of Solomon, these books shouldn't be trusted.
Jewish testimony suggests that anything not in the canon isn't considered credible.
In fact, Josephus, the Jewish historian, states he hasn't read anything in either the canonical or apocryphal Scriptures that indicates Solomon repented.
It's clear that it's not uncommon for Jews to lie; they often deny the truth or assert falsehoods.
This is why Jerome, urged by Sophronius, translated the Psalms of David according to the Hebrew truth.
When Sophronius debated with a Hebrew individual and presented some testimonies from the Psalms according to the Septuagint translators, the Hebrew mocked him for not knowing Hebrew letters, claiming that either the words didn't exist in Hebrew where they were found or were found where they weren't.
In the following pages, it is mentioned: The words of Solomon after he voluntarily lost the kingdom, writing Ecclesiasticus: Solomon ruled during peaceful times, and God subdued all his enemies so he could build a house in His name, and the rest follows in the same chapter.
Solomon didn't write Ecclesiasticus, as Augustine stated in the seventeenth book of The City of God, and before Augustine, Jerome mentioned in many places.
Jerome noted he found this book in Hebrew, not called Ecclesiasticus as among the Latins, but titled Proverbs.
As he mentioned, two others were added alongside him-Ecclesiastes and Song of Songs-so that his works might match Solomon's not only in the number of books but also in the types of subjects covered.
Due to this similarity in expression, it became common for the unlearned to refer to it as the Wisdom of Solomon.
However, the more ancient and wiser scholars claim it belongs to Jesus, the son of Sirach, who, as noted much earlier, lived during the time of Simon the high priest.
When he praised the mighty deeds of the earlier fathers at the end of the same volume, he honored Simon quite significantly, praising him more abundantly and loftily as he knew him more closely and perfectly.
This same Jesus is believed to have written Ecclesiasticus, as he appears to demonstrate in the same place with full praise of Simon.
He said, "The teaching of wisdom and discipline was written in this book by Jesus, son of Sirach of Jerusalem, who renewed wisdom from his heart."
Therefore, when he came to recount Solomon's deeds after listing David's praises, he first extolled Solomon's wisdom, fame, and wealth with great admiration, then highlighted his grave sin and disgrace, maintaining the same order in describing his life as he had in living it:
"He was educated in his youth," he said, "and filled with wisdom like a river." And in an address to him, he added: "Your name spread to distant islands; and you were loved in your peace. Nations marveled at your Songs and Proverbs. You gathered gold like brass and filled silver like lead."
So far, the praises. And he further remarked: "You inclined your thighs to women; you had power over your body."
One might wonder what he meant by saying, "You had power over your body," when the Apostle states: "You are not your own, for you were bought at a great price; therefore, glorify and bear God in your body" (First Corinthians, Chapter Six).
Those who see themselves as belonging to God don't use their bodies freely for personal pleasure.
Instead, they discipline and submit themselves to serve God's will.
Just like a well-trained horse follows its rider's commands rather than its own desires, a righteous person, guided by God, doesn't control their own body; it's God who holds that power.
For those who choose to live by their own will instead of their Lord's, a wise person once said: "The powerful will suffer mightily" (Wisdom of Solomon, Chapter 6).
This was the case with Solomon.
When he no longer feared God and broke away from the constraints of holiness, he became proud of his royal power.
With the freedom to indulge his desires, God patiently endured him, and no one dared to stop the king.
As a result, he faced the consequences:
"You have put a stain on your glory," he said, "and have desecrated your seed, bringing wrath upon your children, and inciting foolishness, causing the kingdom to be divided and Ephraim to rule harshly" (Ecclesiasticus, Chapter 47).
This clearly shows that just as David's righteousness greatly benefited his descendants, Solomon's wickedness severely harmed his lineage.
His children faced divine wrath and, due to their father's foolishness, didn't deserve to inherit the entire kingdom.
However, it's also mentioned: "God will not abandon His mercy nor destroy the descendants of His chosen one, and He will not corrupt the seed of those who love the Lord."
David is called His chosen one and the one who loves the Lord, whose lineage was not completely destroyed, ensuring the promise made to David was fulfilled: "I will set the fruit of your body upon your throne" (Psalm 132).
Therefore, a remnant was given to Jacob; and David came from that lineage.
To put it simply, because of David, God preserved a remnant from his lineage, Rehoboam.
This was so that David's great merit would overshadow Solomon's wickedness, ensuring his lineage continued for future generations rather than being wiped out entirely.
So, it's said that Rehoboam remained because of David's merit, but his own wayward behavior is linked to Solomon's sinfulness.
This might be what was earlier said to Solomon: "You have profaned your seed, bringing wrath upon your children" (Ecclesiasticus 47).
The rebellion of Rehoboam is documented in Ecclesiasticus, and more extensively in the books of Kings and Chronicles.
Even his son Abijah was just as malicious, fulfilling the dire warning: "I am a jealous God, punishing the iniquity of the fathers upon the children to the third generation of those who hate me" (Exodus 20).
It's noted that Solomon left foolishness in his lineage, and a lack of wisdom in Rehoboam, who led the nation astray with his advice.
During his reign, the kingdom was divided, and a harsh rule emerged from Ephraim.
While Rehoboam ruled only over Judah and Benjamin, collectively called Judah, Jeroboam son of Nebat harshly oppressed the other ten tribes, called Israel.
This is what was foretold to Solomon, that he would cause the kingdom to be divided, and a harsh rule would arise from Ephraim.
Jeroboam was from the tribe of Ephraim, and he ruled harshly over the ten tribes.
With Israel separate from Judah, Jeroboam made two golden calves, placing one in Bethel and the other in Dan, commanding the people to gather there to worship.
He feared that if they went to Jerusalem as usual, they might return to Rehoboam, king of Judah, and reunite the divided kingdom.
Because of this, it is written about him that he caused Israel to sin (First Kings 16).
Later, when the corrupt lives of his successors, particularly the rejected kings, are described, it's almost always noted that each of them followed the ways of Jeroboam, son of Nebat, who led Israel into sin.
Rehoboam himself ruled Judah with a heavy hand, and when the people asked for relief, he arrogantly replied, "My father made your yoke heavy; I will add to your yoke. My father disciplined you with whips, but I will discipline you with scorpions" First Kings Twelve.
Indeed, Solomon left them as heirs to both his kingdom and his impiety, of whom, as Jesus said, Rehoboam oppressed the people with his counsel.
Jeroboam, on the other hand, led Israel to sin and gave Ephraim a path to wrongdoing.
This clearly shows that in his narrative, Jesus includes not only the righteous but also some who are unjust: perhaps to make the holiness of the righteous stand out more sharply against the darkness of the rejected.
No one, not even Solomon, is unaware that Rehoboam and Jeroboam were rejected, except those with little or no knowledge of the Holy Scriptures.
Therefore, it's not surprising that when Jesus describes the succession of kings, Solomon is named after David, just as Rehoboam and Jeroboam are included, who are undoubtedly known to be rejected.
What puzzles me is if Jesus, by praising Solomon, intended to prove him just, why did he highlight Solomon's sin after praising him, when he didn't do this with any of the just, whom he listed many before and after Solomon?
If you examine the catalog he compiled, from Enoch, where he began his praise, to Simon, the son of Onias, whom he praised at the end, you'll find that he highlights no one's sin except Solomon's, even though some of them are found to have sinned gravely, if you look at other Scriptures more closely.
In the entire catalog, where he lists many ancient leaders who followed each other among the people of God in either holiness or rank, he only accuses Solomon, Rehoboam, and Jeroboam of injustice.
It's clear that Rehoboam and Jeroboam were considered reprobates; however, Solomon's repentance or righteousness after his sin isn't mentioned at all.
If he believed Solomon shouldn't share the same fate as Rehoboam and Jeroboam, it's puzzling why he mentioned Solomon's sin in the first place, especially since he didn't tarnish the reputation of any other righteous person by bringing up their sins.
It also raises the question of why he didn't mention Solomon's repentance after his sin, which would have enhanced his praise and ensured he was counted among the righteous without hesitation.
When the same figure praised Josiah among other righteous people, he added: "Except for David, Hezekiah, and Josiah, all have committed sin." This prompts us to question who exactly he refers to or what sin he means. If we consider all those he named earlier, we risk accusing them of more sin than is warranted, as some of them are not recorded to have sinned in the sacred texts; and some are noted to have sinned less than David. So, how can we say all except David sinned when David himself sinned more than some of them?
Let's examine the next verse to see if it can clarify who he means has committed sin. After stating, "all have committed sin," he adds: "For the kings of Judah have abandoned the powerful law." This suggests that when he said "all," he was referring to the kings, asserting that all the kings of Judah, that is, the people of Israel, sinned, except David, Hezekiah, and Josiah, who are known to have been kings. While it seems all kings are meant, we still need to ask if this includes everyone named in the books of Kings and Chronicles or if some are excluded from this generalization.
When we mention them all, Asa and Jehoshaphat come to mind, whom the canonical Scripture recognizes as righteous.
It says of Asa that he did what was right in the sight of the Lord, like David his father.
Regarding Jehoshaphat, it notes he walked in the ways of David his father.
Therefore, those who followed in the footsteps of David should not be accused of injustice.
Nor should we think that Jesus would suggest they be accused of dissimilarity, when the canonical Scripture aligns them so closely with such a great similarity of holiness.
We should focus, then, only on the kings Jesus mentioned in his book.
When listing patriarchs, prophets, judges, and priests, who, as I mentioned earlier, were among the people of God, he included not all, but specific kings of the same people: namely David, Solomon, Rehoboam, Jeroboam, Hezekiah, and Josiah.
After Josiah, when Jesus chose not to name any further kings, he reiterated what has often been said: Except for David, Hezekiah, and Josiah, all have sinned.
Specifically, all the kings he named, including Solomon, Rehoboam, and Jeroboam.
Now, we must consider what specific sin these kings committed, from which David, Hezekiah, and Josiah were exempt.
It is not every sin, but a particular sin that's referred to, as when the Lord, speaking about the Jews in the Gospel, said: If I had not come, they would not have sin (John fifteen); not every sin, but a certain sin is meant, which they did not have before his coming, but had when he was present.
The sin of Solomon, Rehoboam, and Jeroboam, as I understand it, is idolatry.
They abandoned their ancestral laws, turned to the customs of other nations, built high places, made idols, and worshipped demons.
This seems to be implied when it is stated: For they abandoned the powerful law of the kings of Judah.
The powerful law is to worship God, to adore God, according to the commandment: You shall worship the Lord your God.
If someone fully commits to this law, even if they stray from the path, they can easily return to the one they worship, as long as they remain connected by the bonds of faith.
It is no small gift of divine grace, nor a minor feat of human effort, for each person to maintain the seal of faith.
Even if they sin-for everyone does-they can still turn their hearts back to God in worship, bowing and submitting to Him alone, offering the service due to God, and not worshipping any other god alongside or in place of Him.
Thus, when the souls of the faithful are entrusted to God, this merit is beautifully presented to Him.
Although they have sinned, they have not denied You; marked with the sign of faith, they have faithfully worshipped You, the Creator of all things and them among all.
However, if someone breaks these bonds, attributing the worship due to the Creator God shamelessly to creatures, they prove to have completely abandoned the powerful law, moving far from forgiveness, since they do not even outwardly honor the giver of forgiveness.
Therefore, in the Second Book of Maccabees, when, through the wicked and unheard-of crime of the impious priest Jason, the priests and other countrymen adopted the customs of the nations, and, as it is written, rushed to become like the nations in every way by despising the temple and neglecting sacrifices, the divine word added: "Acting impiously against divine laws does not go unpunished" (Second Maccabees 4).
How it did not go unpunished is shown a little further down when it says that King Antiochus, after leaving Egypt, took the city by force of arms with fierce spirits (Second Maccabees 5).
In total, 80,000 were killed over three days, and 40,000 were taken captive.
The aforementioned kings, both in heart and in action, turned away from this law and all holiness, led by no fear, worshipped demons instead of God.
Therefore, it is added there: "They failed and despised the fear of God. For they gave their kingdom to others and their glory to a foreign nation" (Ecclesiasticus 49).
Those who could have truly ruled if they had humbly remained subject to divine authority, as it is written, "By me kings reign" (Proverbs 8:15); they handed over their kingdom and glory to others, that is, to demons, as they weakly submitted to them ruling and boasting.
After these words, nothing is found in Ecclesiasticus to testify to the repentance of these kings in any way.
Nor should it concern us that in the Book of Kings it is said about Solomon, "The rest of the acts of Solomon, and all that he did, and his wisdom, are they not written in the book of the acts of Solomon?"
And in Chronicles it says, "The rest of the acts of Solomon, first and last, are they not written in the words of Nathan the prophet, and in the prophecy of Ahijah the Shilonite, and in the visions of Iddo the seer concerning Jeroboam the son of Nebat?"
These books are found neither with us nor with the Hebrews, and therefore neither we nor they can at all know what are these remaining things contained therein.
However, our Scripture does not say that Solomon's repentance is found in those, so I do not see how it can be asserted or even guessed what is entirely unknown.
Therefore, let it suffice for us to know from canonical Scripture that these books once existed, even if they do not now,
but to claim that something is written in them which we cannot demonstrate with any evidence, is just empty words.
Just as it is said about Solomon in Chronicles, "The rest of the acts of Solomon are written in the words of Nathan the prophet, and in the prophecy of Ahijah the Shilonite, and in the visions of Iddo the seer,"
likewise shortly after it is said about his son Rehoboam: "The acts of Rehoboam, first and last, are they not written in the books of Shemaiah the prophet, and of Iddo the seer?"
If then, someone were to contentiously claim that Solomon's repentance was perhaps written in those books, which we do not have, it could similarly be contentiously said of Rehoboam, that his repentance was perhaps written in those books, which we do not have.
No one knowledgeable in the divine Scriptures doubts that Rehoboam was rejected by God.
Regarding Solomon, in connection to the eighth Gradual Psalm, Augustine states, as I mentioned earlier, that he was also rejected by God.
Therefore, the Scriptures that we cannot access, either because we do not possess them or because we do not understand them, should be entrusted to the divine fire, as commanded in the law concerning the flesh of the lamb.
Indeed, those Scriptures, which we have noted are unavailable to us or to the Hebrews, were irreparably burned by fire long ago.
During the time of Zedekiah, the last king of Judah, in the eleventh year of his reign, the hostile Chaldean army invaded Judea, besieged Jerusalem, and captured it, destroying the city.
Among other things, they completely burned the library, which had been painstakingly assembled.
Later, with the permission of King Artaxerxes of Persia, the scribe Ezra returned from Babylonian captivity.
Upon his return to Jerusalem, he restored the few books that the fire had not completely consumed, aided by miraculous knowledge and filled with ineffable grace.
If it seems unbelievable how this man, though brilliant and educated in divine letters from a young age, could encompass such a vast array of Scriptures in his memory and bring back to human knowledge the books consumed by fire, let us remember that nothing is impossible for God.
He initially wanted them written and then rewritten by Ezra.
Indeed, it is true that what is written about Him is that He can do whatever He wills and has accomplished all that He wished.
Therefore, it is not incredible that He alone can do marvelous things, whose name alone is wondrous, as was said to Manoah.
Hence, Ezra is recognized as being a swift scribe in the law of Moses, and King Artaxerxes, writing to him, says: "To Ezra, the most learned priest and scribe of the law of God, greetings."
(First Esdras Chapter Four).
And shortly after: "You have been sent," he says, "to visit Judea and Jerusalem according to the law of your God, which is in your hand."
(First Esdras Chapter Seven).
Furthermore, during that time, Ezra introduced new characters for the letters, though the sounds and number of the original letters stayed the same.
The Hebrews were quick to adopt these new characters because they were easier to read and clearer than the old ones, and they've continued to use them to this day.
Before this, they shared the same sounds and characters as the Samaritans.
So, even now, the Jews and Samaritans have identical sounds for their letters, but there's a significant difference in their characters.
Since I've uncovered writings about Solomon and shared them, it's fitting for me to conclude this response, leaving it to the wise reader to evaluate what's been said and to prioritize the truth with sound judgment.
I believe a wise reader wouldn't disagree with those who align with Augustine, Paschasius, Gregory, Bede, Fulgentius, Isidore, Anglosinus, and Rabanus, as they are found to be in harmony with the divine Scriptures, not opposing them.
Who could be so narrow-minded or rather wrong-hearted to claim that these figures envied Solomon's salvation and therefore denied his repentance, or misunderstood the divine Scriptures, causing them all to err in denying his repentance?
It's wise, therefore, to follow and respect such teachers and guides, as knowing the truth in the Scriptures through them is commendable, and perhaps being ignorant with them is forgivable.
If I had the choice, I would prefer to know what they knew in the Scriptures and remain unaware of what they did not know, rather than being ignorant of their knowledge and pretending to know the unknown, either denying what they affirmed or affirming what they denied.
Therefore, my brothers, when something is uncertain, the writings of venerable Fathers should be carefully examined over the trivialities of the unskilled, so that our ignorance may be cleansed by their assertions, and the Church may shine with their teachings like the sun and moon.
May your love embrace what I have come to understand and gather about Solomon, for the response that follows requires us to conclude here.