Dubious Works of Saint Hilary, Bishop of Arles
Sermon on the Miracle of Saint Genesius, Martyr of Arles
Sharing the stories of God's works is honorable; therefore, it's worthwhile to recount the miracles associated with Saint Genesius the martyr.
On his birthday, a frequent event in the city of Arles, the danger of a broken bridge shook the entire city with great fear.
Hearts struck by sudden fear, the joy of the celebration was made even greater by the grace of received safety, bringing doubled happiness.
When the people of Arles gathered for this celebration, the city itself became too small to contain their joy.
The paths and open fields, filled with the rising procession and everyone struggling with the crowd, moved to the far bank of the river in honor of the martyr.
A devoted army to Christ, with dear spouses and sweet children, rushed to receive many blessings at once.
Not content with offering prayers in one place, they kept vigil in the church, hurrying before dawn to the place of martyrdom.
They offered sacrifices at the tomb, as if to capture the attention of the martyr.
Neither the solemn duties of the clergy nor the time of day deterred them.
The splendor of the festival, with the whole city shining, had driven away all the horrors of the night.
Meanwhile, the naval route, by which the terrifying waters of the Rhone are crossed between allied cities, suddenly collapsed, either under an unjust load, excessive weight, or the slanting flow of the river.
It is uncertain by what accident; however, it is certain that the precious load, the crowd of faithful, was precariously deposited in the middle of the waves.
I was standing by, and barely took a step back from the very bridge, so to speak.
Immediately, a great noise erupted from the crowd, both from those rushing and those standing around.
Fear spread throughout the entire city.
Some ran to their spouses, others to their children, relatives, or friends.
Everyone was simultaneously afraid in different ways, some for their fellow citizens.
Amidst all this, the weight of the disaster fell entirely on Honoratus, the bishop of holy memory, who was then the beloved shepherd, as he alone feared for everyone.
What emotions of piety he felt at that time!
How quickly he, distressed in his soul, was present for the distressed!
Raising his eyes to heaven, with the intensity of his heart matched by the light in his eyes, he departed from us standing around him in a complete trance of the mind, so that no one doubted he stood before the tribunals of Christ with Saint Genesius to seek help for the present evil.
Meanwhile, amidst great turmoil, pitiable shipwrecks occurred.
Horses adorned with finery were mixed with people, struggling to swim, their legs surfacing with high chests.
They trampled over anything in their way, either warned by danger or driven by panicked instinct, with a fearful courage.
Clinging to their beloved burdens, the arms of mothers, and servants pressed by the burdens of their mistresses, the entire solemn procession became mixed with the debris of their journey.
Let no bad interpreter arise here.
Let no one obscure the great glory of the martyr with malicious slander, and let no one claim the crowd near the riverbank.
Let no one assert those caught in the shallows, whom the divine right hand clearly saved.
Laden with the goods of travelers, ships of inestimable burdens are daily joined to these same banks.
An ancient ordinance established a ship there for bearing bridges, as if to give up on laying the foundation with embankments.
The weight of the crowded people exposed to this vast whirlpool was as much as the beams, long and strong, could bear, even though they were broken.
Let those recalling these events bring them to their minds and eyes now: the entire Rhone, the ruin, the shipwreck, the diverse crowd of the miserable, entangled together, all conglomerated into one disaster by the devil’s snares.
Nothing was lacking in the danger so that nothing was lacking in the glory of the martyr.
For when would the river have drowned his disciples, whom he had consecrated the same day with devout birthdays?
O great glory of God!
A glorious army emerged from the vast whirlpool.
You might have thought the Jordan River had once again, by divine intervention, opened up; or that the seas had once more provided a solid path for the people of God, as they had in the past under Moses' leadership, by the command of his rod.
No one was shaken by the collapse, no one was soaked by the river, and no one was swept away by its flow.
Everyone was safely welcomed by the familiar and homely shore.
The entire procession exited just as it had entered.
The matron's secrets were revealed by the necks of their mobile servants from the depths.
The virgins, adorned in honor of God, did not lose any of their floating jewelry; even the pins remained as securely attached to their maternal hands as they had been before.
No one suffered any loss of property, and no one faced any danger.
Beloved children rushed to meet their loved ones: each person joyfully embraced the one they had feared for the most.
Whose power but Christ's, through the intercession of His martyr, accomplished this miracle?
Surely, the bishop met the martyr, and the lord met the martyr.
The faithful people's service was shown to be worthy of salvation.
And indeed, many immediately, so that the holy devotion might not be easily disturbed by the enemy, boarded boats with their clothes still wet and disregarded the morning chill of the river with fervent hope.
They hurried to the place they aimed for, the site of the martyrdom, with a victorious spirit, ready to offer their vows with even greater enthusiasm after the recent danger.
Oh, such prayers are worthy of being heard!
They, unbroken by injuries, do not blame the peril they faced: they know how to give thanks for their escape.
Everyone dances with joy, happily participating in the solemn rites.
It is a joy to have been in danger because it was a wonder to have witnessed the miracles.
It was so significant for each to have doubted their safety so that they could miraculously gain it.
With all his flock present, the honored pastor rejoices.
He could have entrusted these writings, which will endure through the ages, to a more skillful hand with greater grace, if he had not been aware of the divine gift and designated as a participant in the mission of the holy martyr.
Because the Lord had granted him this as a bishop, he feared to rejoice too arrogantly.
Indeed, many blessings reach us through various means.
But how many recognize them in their own lives?
We attribute this solely to God, who is worshipped as the creator and knower of all, and lives with the Son and the Holy Spirit for endless ages of ages.
Amen.