Four Books Against the Objections of the Greeks
by Ratramnus, a Monk of Corbie
Book Three
Chapter One
On the procession of the Holy Spirit.
The universal Church encompasses the entire world.
Scripture says: "Do not move the ancient boundary stones set up by your ancestors," Proverbs 22:28.
If the leaders of the Greeks had followed this commandment, the Roman Church would not have faced criticism regarding the Holy Spirit, nor would they have tried to create new doctrines.
Instead, they should be content with the boundaries of faith established by the Catholic Fathers and set forth by the Scriptures written through the Holy Spirit.
However, suffering from vanity or envy, they are not satisfied with the boundaries of their ancestors and seek their own glory, crossing the lines set by their predecessors.
But while they attempt to undermine the glory of their ancestors, they fall into the pit they have dug, as the Psalmist says Psalm 7:16.
They should not have raised any questions about the procession of the Holy Spirit in our times if they had either paid attention to the teachings of their ancestors or diligently studied the holy scriptures.
What we should believe about the Holy Spirit is clearly demonstrated by the Catholic teachers, who, through frequent discussions and numerous writings, have not only understood but also refuted the erroneous comments of heretics about the Holy Trinity, including the procession of the Holy Spirit.
We have already presented a considerable part of their authority above, which we believe clearly shows what we should believe about the procession of the Holy Spirit.
Anyone who tries to contradict or refuses to accept this is clearly shown to be an opponent of the Catholic faith and a blasphemer of the Holy Spirit.
We have learned from the mouth of Truth Himself what punishment such a person will suffer:
"Blasphemy against the Holy Spirit will not be forgiven, either in this age or in the age to come," Matthew 12:32.
It was also decided to include the writings of Father Augustine, an outstanding teacher and one of the most eloquent among ecclesiastical scholars.
He constantly engaged in battles against heretics.
His teachings and eloquence subdued not only the impiety of the Arians but also quelled the ferocity of other remaining heretics, such as the Macedonians, Manichaeans, and Pelagians.
Perhaps the pride of the Greeks will refuse to accept the authority of the Latins.
But what will they say about their own authors that we mentioned earlier?
What about the authors of the Holy Scriptures?
Will they refuse to accept them too, just because they see them as severe enemies of their errors and fierce opponents of their impiety?
It would be foolish to say that they do not wish to accept the authority of the Latins and, by not agreeing with them, create a schism, making themselves alien to the Catholic Church.
But may it never be that they say or believe such things, or wish to prefer their own opinion or custom over the universality of the entire Church.
For it is such wicked arrogance to even think or decide such a thing.
It cannot be tolerated and must be struck down by the authority of the universal Catholic Church.
As the Savior said to his Apostles: "Go into all the world and preach the Gospel to every creature" (Mark 16:15).
He did not commend only the Greeks but mentioned the fullness of the entire world to whom the Gospel must be preached.
It is extremely arrogant to claim as a special privilege for oneself what is clearly granted to all nations, peoples, and languages universally.
For the Holy Spirit, speaking through the prophet to Jerusalem, says: "I will bring your offspring from the east, and from the west I will gather you. I will say to the north, 'Give them up,' and to the south, 'Do not hold them back'" (Isaiah 43:5).
Are these things said about the Greeks alone?
Or is the people of Jerusalem prophesied to be gathered only from Constantinople?
The universality of the nations spread throughout the whole world is proclaimed, from which the heavenly Jerusalem is taught to be gathered.
Therefore, let them not claim for themselves what has been granted to all nations, nor should they take pride in a special privilege that is meant for all.
They should look at the Catholic Church of Christ, spread across the entire world, expanding from the East to the West, from the North to the South.
They should rejoice that Christ rules over the whole world, as foretold by David, where he portrays the Father speaking to the Son:
Ask of me, and I will make the nations your inheritance, and the ends of the earth your possession
Psalms 2:8.
And as another psalm speaks in the person of Christ:
He will rule from sea to sea, and from the river to the ends of the earth
Psalms 72:8.
Nowhere does it mention either the Greeks or Constantinople; yet it does not completely exclude them, because it includes them in universality.
It removes any special privilege to prevent arrogance and places them in generality to encourage humility, so that they may understand that they are not the entirety of the Church's body, but a part of it.
They should honor the mother Church, exalted in royal magnificence from the rising to the setting of the sun, and rejoice in being her children, not boast in being her fathers.
For the Savior says:
And do not call anyone on earth 'father,' for you have one Father, and he is in heaven
Matthew 23:9.
The Savior also, ascending to the heavens, promises his disciples:
And surely I am with you always, to the very end of the age
Matthew 28:20.
We hear Christ's promise to all believers, that is, to the entire Church, not specifically to the Greeks or the people of Constantinople.
Whatever language or nation Christ speaks in, let the emperors of the Greeks receive it with reverence.
If they despise it, they will be judged as despising the truth and thus become deprived of salvation, since they would have rejected Christ speaking the truth.
When the Holy Spirit descended upon the apostles in tongues of fire, He did not teach them only the Greek language but granted them the knowledge of all languages of all nations.
This was to show that the Church would speak to all peoples in all their languages and that the distribution of the Holy Spirit would be divinely given to all nations.
Therefore, let the glorious princes receive the Holy Spirit through the Teachers of the Church, speaking in the Latin language, so that they may learn with humility where they can make progress.
Otherwise, by looking down on the light of truth with pride, they will fall into the darkness of error.
Chapter Two
Heretics are refuted by the authority of Augustine.
Augustine, Bishop of Hippo, an outstanding teacher and defender of the Catholic faith, in his book of Questions, written to the priest Orosius, says the following about the Holy Spirit (question 2):
"Faith clearly declares that the Holy Spirit is neither unbegotten nor begotten.
If we say unbegotten, we might seem to affirm two Fathers; but if we say begotten, we might be accused of believing in two Sons.
However, faith clearly holds that the Holy Spirit is neither unbegotten nor begotten, but proceeds from both the Father and the Son."
To support this with testimony, we hear our Lord Jesus Christ teaching His disciples:
"But when the Advocate comes, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth who proceeds from the Father, he will testify about me" John 15:26.
And again, after His resurrection, to show that the Holy Spirit proceeds from Himself just as from the Father, Jesus breathed on His disciples and said:
"Receive the Holy Spirit" John 20:22.
Therefore, there is one Spirit of the Father and the Son, one Spirit of both.
Our Lord and Savior Himself says to His disciples:
"For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father speaking through you" Matthew 10:20.
And that it is also the Spirit of the Son, the Apostle Paul testifies:
"But if anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to Him" Romans 8:9.
What here, O leaders of the Greeks, do you judge worthy of reproach?
He says the Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son.
He proves this with testimony from the Gospel.
He says the Spirit belongs to both the Father and the Son; he affirms this from both the Gospel and the Apostle.
If you do not want to believe the Latins, believe the Gospel.
If you do not want to listen to Augustine, listen to Christ and the Apostle.
But if you disregard Christ and the Apostle, beware that you are not disregarded yourselves.
Because anyone who does not follow their teaching is indeed rejected by the society of Christ's disciples and will not be a part of the Church if they reject ecclesiastical teaching.
Nor will they share in Christ if they do not embrace Christ's teaching.
Gregory, bishop of the Roman see during the times of Tiberius Constantine, was an apocrisiary, then a deacon, and later an outstanding prelate, most beloved and intimate with the emperors Tiberius, Maurice, and Phocas.
While he was a deacon and envoy of the Roman see residing in Constantinople, he defeated and refuted Eutyches, the bishop of Constantinople, who was teaching falsely about the resurrection of the flesh.
This was done in the presence of the emperor, by the authority of the divine books and the catholic truth of the matter itself.
Concerning the procession of the Holy Spirit, he speaks in a homily given to the people on the eighth day of Easter (Homily 26 on the Gospel).
"For the Holy Spirit, who is equal to the Father and the Son, was not incarnate, but the Son declares that He will send Him from the Father, saying: 'When the Advocate comes, whom I will send to you from the Father' (John 15:26).
For if being sent should only be understood as being incarnate, then the Holy Spirit would by no means be said to be sent, since He was not incarnate; but His sending is His procession, by which He proceeds from the Father and the Son.
Just as the Spirit is said to be sent because He proceeds, so also the Son is not inappropriately said to be sent because He is begotten.
"
If you endeavor to scorn the authority of this prelate, see to what heights of pride you are being raised. Your predecessors were most reverent in both holiness and wisdom. When he was the envoy of the see and serving in the office of deacon, Gregory crushed with great authority the erroneous doctrines of the bishop of your Constantinople. He not only defeated him but also so thoroughly overthrew the strength of that doctrine that it never regained its power.
What he says about the procession of the Holy Spirit is supported by reason, stating that the sending of the Comforter by the Son is the same as proceeding, just as the Son, when He is said to be sent by the Father, implies His birth.
Augustine, the bishop, in his Treatise on the Gospel according to John (Treatise 99), says:
Someone might ask whether the Holy Spirit also proceeds from the Son.
The Son is the Son of the Father alone, and the Father is the Father of the Son alone; however, the Holy Spirit is not the Spirit of just one of them, but of both.
You have Him saying: For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father who speaks in you (Matthew 10:20).
You also have the Apostle: God has sent the Spirit of His Son into our hearts (Galatians 4:6).
Are there two Spirits, one of the Father and another of the Son?
No way.
For we are one body, he says, referring to the Church, and immediately adds: And one Spirit (Ephesians 4:4).
He then provides several testimonies to prove that the Holy Spirit is the Spirit of both the Father and the Son; not two separate Spirits, but the same Spirit who is of the Son and also of the Father.
Here, with clear testimonies, anyone who tries to oppose will be shown to contradict the Holy Scripture.
And below: If the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son, why did the Son say, He proceeds from the Father?
(John 15:26).
Why do you think, except in the same way that He usually attributes to the Father even what is His own, from whom He Himself is.
Hence, He says: My teaching is not mine, but His who sent me (John 7:16).
If His teaching is understood here, which He nonetheless said was not His, but the Father’s, how much more should it be understood that the Holy Spirit proceeds from Him, when He says, He proceeds from the Father, so as not to say, He does not proceed from me.
With the clearest reasoning, Doctor Augustine shows that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son, affirming His view with that testimony from the Gospel where the Son says about the Spirit that He proceeds from the Father.
For he says this should be understood in the way he said: "It proceeds from the Father," meaning it also proceeds from the Son. He did not want to deny that it proceeds from himself, but by presenting the person of the Father, he also wanted his own involvement to be understood, just as when he said, "My teaching is not mine, but his who sent me."
By saying this, he showed that it is also his own, but he says it is the Father's because, just as it is from him, his teaching is also said to be the Father's. Whatever the Son has, he received by being born from the Father.
Similarly, when he says the Spirit proceeds from the Father, he does not deny that it also proceeds from himself. He shows from where the Son has what the Spirit proceeds from him, namely from the Father, from whom he was begotten and received so that the Spirit proceeds from him.
Consequently, Saint Augustine says: But from whom does the Son have that he is God (for he is God from God)?
Surely, he has it from him, so that the Holy Spirit also proceeds from him.
Through this, the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son as he proceeds from the Father, which he has from the Father himself.
With remarkable subtlety, the excellent teacher suggests both the birth of the Son and the procession of the Holy Spirit.
He says that the Son received from the Father, as God from God, and that the Spirit proceeds from him.
Nevertheless, he also received the Holy Spirit from the same Father to proceed from the Son, as he proceeds from the Father.
By saying this, he confesses both the Son and the Holy Spirit from the Father, who is the source of divinity.
The Son received generation from the Father, and the Holy Spirit's procession from both the Father and the Son.
However, the Holy Spirit only received procession, not generation, which is only of the Son from the Father alone.
Here, he adds that question, which usually stirs some who read: if the Holy Spirit is said to be born?
He says: Here, however, it is understood, as much as it can be understood by those like us, why it is not said to be born, but rather to proceed as the Holy Spirit.
If the Son were also called the Son of both the Father and the Son, it would be absurd because no one is the son of two parents, except a father and a mother.
But let's be clear, we should not suspect anything like this between God the Father and God the Son.
A human son does not proceed simultaneously from both the father and the mother.
When he proceeds from the father into the mother, he does not proceed from the mother at that time.
And when he is born into this world, he does not proceed from the father at that time.
However, the Holy Spirit does not proceed from the Father into the Son and then from the Son to sanctify the creature.
Instead, the Holy Spirit proceeds simultaneously from both.
The Father has given this to the Son so that, just as He proceeds from Himself, He also proceeds from the Son.
We cannot say that the Holy Spirit is not life, since the Father is life and the Son is life.
Just as the Father, having life in Himself, has given the Son to have life in Himself, He also gave Him life to proceed from Him, just as it proceeds from Himself.
It is proven by the most true reason that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son, yet is not the Son of both, since He is the Spirit of both.
The Son is of two— the mother and the father— but spiritual procession knows nothing of this kind.
There is no distinction of sex here because it is not a physical propagation made of flesh or bones.
This procession does not occur through intervals of time, so it does not proceed from the Father at one time and from the Son at another time, but simultaneously from both.
Nor does it happen in the way carnal generation usually does.
There is no outflow, such as the seed from the man into the woman, and no propagation from the mother into the generation of the son.
All these involve a movement of change, which is far removed from the spiritual procession.
The Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son without any movement, change, or flow.
This procession happens through the power of the will, not through any temporal change, extension, or creation from a father or mother, but rather like one light from two sources.
The Father and the Son are not inferior to the Spirit.
They are two persons of one essence, from whom the Holy Spirit proceeds—not as a quality of the two, but as the consubstantiality of both.
As the blessed Augustine says, the Father is life, the Son is life, and the Holy Spirit is life.
However, the Father is life not by taking life from any other; the Son is life by taking life from the Father; and the Holy Spirit is life by proceeding from the Father and the Son.
The Trinity, in its perfect consubstantiality, could not exist if the Holy Spirit were not what the Father and the Son are.
Indeed, there is no question now that the Spirit proceeds from the Father.
But that it proceeds from the Son, the Son himself bears witness, saying: "He will take from what is mine and declare it to you" (John 16:14).
However, heretics wanted to construct degrees in divinity, saying: If the Son receives from the Father, and the Holy Spirit receives from the Son, then the Holy Spirit is lesser than the Son.
Blessed Augustine counters this perverse proposition in Tractate 100, near the end, saying: "But what he says: 'He will take from what is mine and declare it to you,' listen with Catholic ears, perceive with Catholic minds. For the Holy Spirit is not lesser than the Son because the Son receives from the Father, and the Holy Spirit from the Son, by certain degrees of natures. God forbid to believe this, God forbid to say this, God forbid to think this in Christian hearts."
Finally, he immediately resolves the question and explains why he said this: "All things that the Father has are mine; therefore I said that he will take from what is mine and declare it to you" (John 16:15).
What more do you want?
Therefore, the Holy Spirit receives from the Father, from whom the Son also receives: because in this Trinity, the Son is born of the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father.
However, the one who is neither born from anyone nor proceeds from anyone is the Father alone.
It is not contradictory to say now that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father, as stated earlier, where it was said that the same Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son.
This removes the diminishment that the heretics babbled about and emphasizes the equality that the Catholics believe.
For if the Holy Spirit were said to receive only from the Son and not also from the Father, it would provide a basis for the Arians to imagine degrees in divinity.
But now, by saying that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father, there is no basis for them to imagine a diminishment.
The Holy Spirit also receives from the Father in order to proceed, just as the Son receives from the Father in order to be born.
Since both receive from the Father—the Son his birth, and the Holy Spirit his procession—there is no reason for one to be preferred over the other.
However, this does not mean that it should be denied that the Holy Spirit also proceeds from the Son.
For the Son says: "All that the Father has is mine. Therefore I said that he will take from what is mine and declare it to you" (John 16:15).
The Father has it that the Holy Spirit proceeds from him, and consequently, the Son also has it that the Holy Spirit proceeds from him as well.
Therefore, the Holy Spirit proceeds from both.
Chapter Three
Also, testimonies from Augustine.
In the first book on the Holy Trinity, chapter 4, he says:
"Although the Father begot the Son, and therefore the Son is not the Father;
and the Son is begotten by the Father, and therefore the Father is not the Son:
the Holy Spirit is neither the Father nor the Son, but only the Spirit of the Father and the Son, coequal with the Father and the Son, and belonging to the unity of the Trinity."
However, the same Trinity was not born of the Virgin Mary, crucified under Pontius Pilate, buried, risen on the third day, and ascended into heaven, but only the Son.
This clearly indicates the distinct properties of each person in the Holy Trinity, and that the Incarnation pertains only to the Son.
The Father is not the same as the Son, because He begot the Son;
and the Son is not the same as the Father, but only the Son who is begotten by the Father;
and the Holy Spirit is neither the Father nor the Son, but only the Spirit of the Father and the Son.
Since He is called the Spirit of both, He must be confessed to proceed from both.
Just as He is said to be of the Father, because He proceeds from the Father, so He is also professed to be of the Son, because He proceeds from the Son.
Since the reason for being of both is similar, it is similarly confessed that He proceeds from both;
and since He is coequal with the Father and the Son and belongs to the unity of the Trinity, the Incarnation of the Son does not pertain to the Father or the Holy Spirit.
It pertains to the Father alone to have begotten the Son;
to the Son to have assumed perfect humanity;
and to the Holy Spirit to have proceeded from the Father and the Son.
Also, in the following, chapter 5:
It raises the question of how the Holy Spirit is in the Trinity, whom neither the Father nor the Son nor both together have begotten, since He is the Spirit of both the Father and the Son.
With these words, he clarifies that the Holy Spirit is not begotten by the Father alone, nor by the Son alone, nor by both together.
Yet, the Holy Spirit is of both the Father and the Son.
This indicates that the one who is not the Son by birth is the Spirit of both by proceeding.
Where birth is ruled out, and it belongs to both, it signifies procession, not from one alone, but from both, as it is the Spirit of both, not just one.
Further below in chapter twelve:
We have shown through many divine speeches that in this Trinity, what belongs to all is said of each individual, due to the inseparable operation of the one and the same substance.
As it is also said of the Holy Spirit: "When I go, I will send him to you" (John 16:7).
He did not say "we will send," but as though only the Son were to send him, and not the Father.
While in another place, he says: "I have spoken these things to you while I remain with you; but the Advocate, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, he will teach you all things" (John 14:25).
Here again, it is said as though only the Father would send him, and not the Son.
It is frequently said that the sending of the Spirit is his procession; therefore, when it is testified that the Son will send him, it signifies his procession from the Son.
Likewise, when it is said that the Father will send the Holy Spirit in the name of the Son, it signifies his procession from the Father.
And when it is said that he is sent by both, it proves that he proceeds from both.
He gives a general rule of the Holy Trinity, saying that what belongs to all is said of each individual, due to the inseparable operation of the one and the same substance.
With this statement, we are taught that when it is said that the Spirit proceeds from the Father, it should be understood that he proceeds equally from the Son.
Likewise, when it is said that he is sent by the Son, it should be understood that he is sent by the Father, because the Father and the Son, just as they are of one and the same substance, so they are of one and the same operation.
Because of this, anyone who denies that the Spirit is sent by the Son, while admitting that He is sent by the Father, undoubtedly denies that the Son works together with the Father.
By doing so, they claim that the Father and the Son do not share the same operation.
Consequently, they deny that the Father and the Son are of the same substance.
The same goes for the Son's testimony that the Spirit proceeds from the Father.
Whoever denies that the Spirit also proceeds from the Son equally denies that the Son shares the same operation with the Father.
By this, they claim that the Father and the Son are not of the same substance, but of different substances.
Seeing this as stemming from Arian impiety, let us profess with the Catholics that the whole Trinity works together.
Understand that what is said about each should be understood about all: since the whole Trinity is of the same substance, it cannot be separated in operation.
Because of this, when it is said that the Spirit proceeds from the Father, it should equally be understood that He proceeds from the Son.
Also, in book fifteen, chapter six, of De Trinitate:
It is said in the Holy Scriptures that Christ is the power of God and the wisdom of God.
How this should be understood, so that the Son does not appear to make the Father wise, is discussed in book seven.
Reason has concluded that the Son is wisdom from wisdom, just as light from light, God from God.
We could not find anything else about the Holy Spirit except that He is also wisdom, and together they are all one wisdom; just as one God, one essence.
What are we taught from this, except that the Spirit's procession is from both the Father and the Son; and that this Trinity is of one substance?
It says that the Father is wisdom, the Son is wisdom, and the Holy Spirit is wisdom as well.
But the Father is wisdom from no wisdom.
For He did not receive it from the Son to be wise; since He is the source and beginning of all things, He is wise from Himself, not by participation from anyone.
Just as God is light from Himself and not from anyone else—since He has nothing above or before Him, otherwise, He would not be the source of the universe; neither is God imperfect or in need of anything, but He is full, true, and perfect—therefore, He is wise from Himself.
The Son, however, is wisdom, but wisdom from the Father; for the Father begot what He is.
The Spirit is also wisdom, but not from no wisdom: for only the Father is from no one.
So then, from where if not from wisdom?
The Father is wisdom, the Son also is wisdom, therefore the Spirit is wisdom from the Father and the Son.
For the Father and the Son are not separated by diversity but united by unity.
Thus, both send the Spirit, wisdom proceeding from both.
Furthermore, behold then those three, that is, memory, understanding, love or will, in that supreme and unchangeable essence that is God, not the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, but the Father alone.
And because the Son is also wisdom begotten from wisdom, just as neither the Father nor the Holy Spirit understands for Him, but He understands for Himself, so neither does the Father remember for Him, nor does the Holy Spirit love for Him, but He remembers, understands, and loves for Himself: for He is His own memory, His own understanding, His own love; but He has this from the Father, from whom He was born.
The Holy Spirit, also because He is wisdom proceeding from wisdom, does not have the Father as memory, the Son as understanding, and Himself as love: for He would not be wisdom if another remembered for Him, and another understood for Him, and He only loved for Himself; but He has these three; and He has them in such a way that He Himself is these things: nonetheless, to be this way, He has it from where He proceeds.
Subtly and divinely indicating the distinctions of the persons of the Trinity, he says that the Father is wisdom, the Son is wisdom, and the Holy Spirit is wisdom; but the Son is begotten, who is wisdom from the Father who is likewise wisdom; and the Spirit proceeds, who is also wisdom, but from the Father who is wisdom, and the Son who is likewise wisdom.
And to make it more clear, let's use the previously mentioned analogy.
He defines three things: memory, understanding, and love, as a likeness of the Trinity within the inner man.
He discusses this extensively, both in the fifteenth book and in other books of the same work, affirming that in memory are contained both understanding and love.
From memory arises understanding, and from both memory and understanding proceeds love.
These three are together and of one substance.
We remember what we understand, and when we want to look at our understanding, we cannot do so unless it comes from a certain secret of memory, as if it were generated.
When we affirm that our understanding is born from memory, a certain love is created, embracing both understanding and memory.
For both the understanding, which it approves, and the memory from which it knows the understanding is born, delight.
Hence, it comes about that this love is born both from memory and from understanding.
If there were no understanding, there could be no love for it.
If there were no memory, there would be nothing from which understanding could exist.
For we understand nothing of which we have no memory.
Yet these are distinguished by their own intellectual boundaries.
Memory does not understand by itself but through understanding.
Nor does understanding remember by itself but through memory.
Thus, love does not love without memory or understanding.
If understanding is removed, there is nothing for memory to retain.
If memory is removed, love remembers nothing.
For this reason, love will no longer exist since there is nothing to love or remember to spread itself upon.
Thus, these three are together, are born from one another, and are distinguished by their own boundaries, and mutually require each other.
But the Holy Trinity is not considered in the same way, as this venerable doctor suggests.
For the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are the whole Trinity, like memory, understanding, and love.
And the Father, like a source from which the Son is born, exists as a kind of principle from which understanding is formed, just as memory exists.
The Son, being wisdom, is born from the Father, like understanding is generated from memory.
The Holy Spirit, who is also wisdom and love, proceeds from the Son and the Father, just as love proceeds from understanding and memory.
However, even though it is like this, the distinction of persons is not such that the Father is wise only through the Son, and the Son loves only through the Holy Spirit.
Just as in the trinity of a human being’s inner self, memory does not understand by itself but through understanding, and understanding does not remember by itself but through memory.
Similarly, understanding does not love by itself but through love, and love does not understand or remember by itself, but remembers through memory and understands through understanding.
For the Trinity, which is the supreme and unchanging essence, that is, God, is not memory, understanding, and love in such a way that these three are the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, as if the Father is memory, the Son is understanding, and the Holy Spirit is love.
Instead, the Father alone is all three, the Son is similarly all three, and the Holy Spirit is also all three equally.
For the Father remembers, understands, and loves from Himself; He did not receive understanding from the Son, otherwise, He would be said to be born from the Son, which is not orthodox; nor did He receive love from the Holy Spirit, otherwise, He would seem to proceed from Him, which is incorrect.
Rather, He remembers, is wise, and loves from Himself.
The Son, being wisdom born of wisdom, does not have the Father remember for Him, but He remembers for Himself.
Just as the Father does not understand for Him, but He understands for Himself, nor does the Holy Spirit love for Him, but He loves for Himself.
For He remembers, understands, and loves from Himself.
The Holy Spirit, who is wisdom proceeding from wisdom, does not have the Father as memory, the Son as understanding, and only love for Himself.
Instead, He possesses all three: memory, understanding, and love.
He remembers by Himself, understands by Himself, and loves by Himself.
However, the fact that He has these three qualities comes from where He proceeds, that is, from both the Father and the Son.
For He proceeds from both.
It has been shown with very subtle and true reasoning, which no prudent person can contradict, that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
Since He is the Spirit of both, He is not, however, the Son of either, because the love that we say is born from memory and understanding is not called the daughter of either.
Now concerning the Holy Spirit, as much as God allows us to see, we must differ.
According to the Holy Scriptures, the Holy Spirit is neither of the Father alone, nor of the Son alone, but of both.
Therefore, He signifies the mutual love between the Father and the Son, indicating the Trinity.
The Holy Spirit is not of the Father alone, nor of the Son alone, but of both, because He proceeds from both.
Therefore, He signifies the mutual love of the Trinity, binding together the Father and the Son, as proceeding from both—not as a quality of both, but existing in the Trinity as the third person, consubstantial and coequal.
For the Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Spirit is God, and all together are one God.
Yet it is not for nothing that in this Trinity it is said that only the Son is the Word of God, only the Holy Spirit is the gift of God, and the one from whom the Word is begotten, and from whom the Holy Spirit principally proceeds, is God the Father.
However, I added "principally," because it is also found that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son. But this too the Father gave to Him, not when He already existed and did not yet have it, but whatever He gave to the only-begotten Word, He gave by begetting.
Thus, He begot Him in such a way that a shared gift also proceeded from Him, and the Holy Spirit is the Spirit of both.
This testimony proves that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son.
He assigns something unique to each person of the Holy Trinity: the Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Spirit is God, and all together, they are one God.
It is unique to the Word of God to be called the only Son, and unique to the gift of God to be called the Holy Spirit.
The one from whom the Word is begotten and from whom the Spirit primarily proceeds is only called God the Father.
These are the unique properties of each person in the Holy Trinity.
He primarily said that the Spirit proceeds from the Father, but it is also found that the Spirit proceeds from the Son.
The Father gave this to the Son not as to one existing before and not having this, but gave it by begetting.
Whatever the Son has, He received from the Father by being begotten.
The Father did not first beget Him and then give that the Spirit proceeds from the Son, but conferred it upon Him by begetting, so that a shared gift also proceeded from Him.
The Holy Spirit, whom He says is the gift of both the Father and the Son, is the Spirit of both.
Also below (chapter 19):
If there is nothing greater among the gifts of God than love, and no gift of God is greater than the Holy Spirit, what follows more logically than that He Himself is love, who is called God from God?
And if the love by which the Father loves the Son, and the Son loves the Father, ineffably demonstrates the communion of both, what is more fitting than that He is properly called love, who is the common Spirit of both?
Earlier, He called the Holy Spirit the gift of God, and by this property, distinguished the person of the Holy Spirit from the persons of the Father and the Son.
Now, He calls this gift of God love, which is the chief gift among the gifts of divinity.
Because according to the Apostle, First Corinthians chapter thirteen verse three, other gifts are nothing without love.
He calls this love God from God, signifying the Holy Spirit proceeding from God.
Since the term "God" refers to both the Father and the Son, and it is unclear from whom He proceeds, he clarifies by saying:
If the love with which the Father loves the Son, and the Son loves the Father, shows their ineffable communion, what could be more fitting than to call the Spirit of both, love itself?
By saying this, he calls the Holy Spirit love and confirms that He proceeds from both the Father and the Son, for He could not be common to both unless He proceeded from both.
Later, in chapter 23, he explains:
In that supreme Trinity, which surpasses all things, there is such unity that, unlike the trinity of men which cannot be called one man, in that Trinity, He is called and is one God. In one God, there is that Trinity, but it is still one God.
Unlike the image of a man having three parts and still being one person, that Trinity is three persons: the Father of the Son, the Son of the Father, and the Spirit of the Father and the Son.
When he says the Father of the Son is only the Father, and the Son of the Father is only the Son, but the Spirit is the Spirit of both the Father and the Son, he indeed affirms that He proceeds from both.
For the Father is the Father of the Son because He begot Him, and the Son is the Son of the Father because He was begotten by Him. Consequently, the Spirit of the Father and the Son is called the Spirit because He proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
In this Trinity, he teaches such unity that, while the trinity of men cannot be called one man (as it consists of three men, just as the trinity of bodies consists of three bodies), one man cannot be called a trinity, for it is an indivisible singularity of one number.
In the supreme Trinity, both the Trinity and the one God are referred to as God.
However, this doesn't mean that each person individually is the Trinity.
In other words, neither the Father alone, the Son alone, nor the Holy Spirit alone is the Trinity.
Since the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are one God, the Trinity is one God.
Just as the image of this Trinity has three elements—memory, understanding, and love—and thus exists in one person, it's not because one man is the Trinity, but because these three elements are in one man.
Similarly, in the supreme Trinity, the three persons are the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, and these three are one God.
Therefore, the Trinity is one God.
There is such unity among the three persons and such consubstantiality that the three are one, and one God is proclaimed from the three.
They are separated only by relation but united in substance.
The Father is relative to the Son, the Son is relative to the Father, and the Holy Spirit has a relation to both the Father and the Son.
Hence, it is proven that He proceeds from both.
In chapter twenty-six, it states that in the supreme Trinity, which is God, there are no intervals of time to question whether the Son was born of the Father first and later the Holy Spirit proceeded from both.
Holy Scripture calls the Spirit of both.
The Apostle says, "And because you are sons, God has sent the Spirit of His Son into our hearts" (Galatians 4:6).
The Son Himself says, "For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father who speaks in you" (Matthew 10:20).
Many other testimonies of divine words confirm that the Spirit belongs to both the Father and the Son and is properly called the Holy Spirit in the Trinity.
The Son says, "Whom I will send to you from the Father" (John 15:26), and in another place, "Whom the Father will send in My name" (John 14:26).
This teaches that He proceeds from both because the Son says, "He proceeds from the Father."
And when He had risen from the dead and appeared to the disciples, He breathed on them and said, "Receive the Holy Spirit" (John 20:22), to show that the Spirit also proceeds from Him.
It is the power that came from Him, as written in the Gospel, which healed all (Luke 6:19).
What room is there for contradiction here?
The authority of the divine Scriptures shows that the Holy Spirit is from both the Father and the Son and proceeds from both.
If this is disputed, then let the Apostle be disputed, and let it be disputed that the Son said this.
We believe the Son who says that the Spirit proceeds from the Father; let us also believe that He sent the Spirit from Himself when He breathed on them and said to the disciples, "Receive the Holy Spirit."
Likewise, the power that healed all, coming out of Jesus, testifies that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son. Therefore, it is clearly shown that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
The most evident testimony of this procession from both is that He is said to be the Spirit of both the Father and the Son. He is the Spirit of both: not because He was created by the Son from the Father, which is impious, but because He proceeds substantially from both.
Nor can any intervals of time be shown when He proceeded either from the Father or from the Son, or if the Holy Spirit proceeded from both after the Son was begotten; for what precedes all time is contained by no measure of time.
Therefore, the order of procession is not to be sought in time, which encompasses all time. The Father was never without the Son, the Son was never without the Father, the Holy Spirit was never without the Father and the Son, and the Father and the Son were never without the Holy Spirit.
Similarly below: Can we then ask whether the Holy Spirit had already proceeded from the Father when the Son was born, or had He not yet proceeded?
And after the Son was born, He proceeded from both, where there are no times.
Just as we might ask where we find times, whether the will proceeds first from the human mind, so that what is found may be called offspring.
By which the will is perfected once it is already produced or born, resting in that end.
So that the desire of seeking becomes the love of enjoying, which now proceeds from both, that is, from the generating mind and the generated notion as from parent and offspring.
These things cannot be asked there at all, where nothing is started in time to be perfected in time.
Therefore, whoever can understand the generation of the Son from the Father without time, let him understand the procession of the Holy Spirit from both without time.
Blessed Augustine testifies that the procession of the Holy Spirit is from both the Father and the Son.
But he raises the question discussed earlier, whether the Holy Spirit proceeded from the Father before the birth of the Son, and after the Son was born, He also proceeded from Him.
This question is compelled by the analogy, which says that the will proceeds from the human mind before the word is formed from the mind.
So that a certain desire of the will arises to seek, which when found, is called the offspring of the mind, by which the will is perfected from which the desire to seek proceeded.
But this will was also first born from the mind before what was desired to be found was sought, and when found, it is fully perfected, while it multiplies from what is found; for it rejoices to have found what it sought.
Hence the will, born from both, namely from the mind and from what was found, proceeds from both; but first from the mind, and then from what was found; from there, namely to seek; but from here, to delight in what was found.
However, this will is not twofold, as if there is an earlier will of the mind and a later one of the discovered thing.
Instead, it is a singular will focused on one thing: the discovery.
It starts with the mind's intention to seek and concludes with the perfection of what was sought.
First, there is a desire to seek, and later it becomes a love of enjoying what was found.
But these things happen in created beings that are bound by time; in divinity, where no time exists, such things cannot be found.
It is not said that the Father existed before, nor that the Son was born afterward, but that the Father has always remained in the Son, and the Son in the Father; nor could the Holy Spirit, by proceeding, precede the birth of the Son: for where no time exists, neither before nor after can be found.
It cannot be perfected in subsequent time, that which has no beginning in time.
Therefore, whoever can conceive of the generation of the Son from the Father without time, should also conceive of the procession of the Holy Spirit from both the Father and the Son without time.
Just as we should not ask when the Son was born from the Father, in the same way, we should not ask when the Holy Spirit proceeded from both; nor if the Holy Spirit preceded the Son's birth from the Father by proceeding.
Where eternity exists, the order of time does not.
No law of divinity should be judged by the condition of human creation; for created things made under time follow the order of time: but the creator of time is not governed by any law of time.
It precedes all things that are contained by time.
He adds another point to prove that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son without time, just as it is established that the Son is begotten from the Father without time.
He says: And who can understand what the Son says: Just as the Father has life in himself, so he has granted the Son to have life in himself.
John 5:26
.
It's not that the Father gave life to the Son, who already existed without life, but that He begot Him timelessly.
So, the life the Father gave to the Son by begetting Him is co-eternal with the life of the Father who gave it.
Understand it as the Father having life in Himself, and the Holy Spirit proceeding from Him.
He gave this to the Son, so the same Holy Spirit proceeds from Him as well, both without time.
Thus, it is said that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father, and it is understood that He also proceeds from the Son, being from both the Father and the Son.
For whatever the Son has from the Father, He has it from the Father, including that the Holy Spirit also proceeds from Him.
But let no time be considered here, for there is no before and after, absolutely none.
The Holy Spirit proceeding from the Son, as He proceeds from the Father, is testified.
He proceeds from the Son because the Father gave to the Son, not to one who existed previously, but by begetting.
Whatever the Father gave to the Son, He did not give to a lesser being or one who existed previously but gave by begetting.
And He provides a comparison to clarify: Whoever can understand what the Son says: As the Father has life in Himself, so He gave to the Son to have life in Himself.
It's not that the Father gave life to the Son, who already existed without life.
The Son would exist without life if He had somehow existed before He lived, so that life would later be granted to Him already existing.
As Genesis speaks of the first Adam, saying: Therefore God formed man from the dust of the earth Genesis 2:7.
And then it is added: And He breathed into his face the breath of life.
First, it says that he was formed, and then, already formed and evidently existing through the quality of his formation, the breath of life was granted.
But the Father did not give life to the Son in such a way as to beget first, to whom He would later give life after being begotten.
By begetting, He gave life, because the Son is substantially life, to whom He gave life by begetting.
Finally, man existed first formed, and later received life because he received life by participation, not by birth.
For he was not substantially life but lived by participation in life.
But the only begotten Son of the Father did not receive life by participation, but was substantially begotten of the Father as life.
For life was not given to one who existed as if remaining without life, but he was begotten entirely coequal and consubstantial with the life of the Father, who gave him life by begetting.
It follows that the Father begot him without time, so that the life which the Father gave to the Son by begetting is co-eternal with the life of the Father who gave it.
By saying this, it shows that the Father is life, and the Son is life; but the Son received life from the Father, so that he might be life; not existing previously without life, but begotten as life, which is co-eternal and consubstantial with the life of the Father, who gave life to the Son by generating.
Whoever is able to understand how this is, should also understand that just as the Father has in himself the Holy Spirit proceeding from him, so he gave to the Son that the same Holy Spirit proceeds from him.
For he wants to affirm that the Son received from the Father, just as by begetting life, so also by begetting the Holy Spirit proceeds from him, not another, but the same who proceeds from the Father.
And since no one of sound mind can deny that the Son received life from the Father to be life just as the Father is, thus from the Father he could receive the Holy Spirit to proceed from him; and this both without time; because just as he proceeds from the Father without time, so also he proceeds from the Son without time; because this procession is not temporal, but eternal.
For just as the birth of the Son from the Father excludes all time, so the procession of the Holy Spirit, which is from both, acknowledges no time.
He adds: And thus it is said that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father, so that it is understood that he also proceeds from the Son, from the Father and the Son.
He wants it to be understood that when it is read or said that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father, it is equally meant that he proceeds from the Son; and therefore in the mention of the Father, the Son must be understood; because it is from the Father to the Son that the Holy Spirit proceeds from him.
Because it is attributed to the Father, the source from whom the Son received the Holy Spirit, it follows that when it is said the Spirit proceeds from the Father, it should also be understood to proceed from the Son.
It adds, if whatever the Son has, He has from the Father, then He certainly has from the Father that the Holy Spirit proceeds from Him as well.
We know from what the Son says that all things belonging to the Father also belong to the Son.
These things are rightly attributed to Him from whom they were given.
Therefore, when it is said that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, it is attributed to the Father, from whom it was given to Him to proceed.
Hence, when the Son says in the Gospel: The Spirit who proceeds from the Father (John 15:26), He intends to be understood that He also means it proceeds from Himself, but without any notion of time.
It should not be questioned whether the Holy Spirit first proceeded, and then the Son was born, or after the Son was born, the Holy Spirit then proceeded from both.
It should not be considered here first or later, because time is not to be estimated here.
Consequently, how then would it not be most absurd to say that the Son is of both?
Just as the generation gives the Son essence without beginning of time and without any change in nature, so too the Holy Spirit is given essence without any beginning of time and without any change in nature from both.
It shows that the procession of the Holy Spirit is from both the Father and the Son, but it should not be asked if first from the Father or later from the Son.
Rather, it should be considered that just as generation gives the Son substance without intervening time or any intervening change, so the procession gives the Holy Spirit substance without any time and without any change.
Nor should it be debated what is before or after.
The birth of the Son from the Father should be understood, and the procession of the Holy Spirit from both.
Since we do not say that the Holy Spirit is begotten, we also do not call him unbegotten.
This avoids suggesting that there are two Fathers in the Trinity, or two who do not originate from another.
The Father alone is not from another, which is why he is called unbegotten—though not explicitly in the Scriptures, but by those discussing this profound topic to the best of their ability.
The Son is born of the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds primarily from the Father and also from both the Father and the Son, without any interval of time.
If both the Father and the Son had begotten the Son, which is an idea rejected by all rational minds, the Son would be called the Son of both.
Therefore, he is not begotten by both but proceeds from both as the Spirit of both.
This supports the idea that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
Yet, he opposes the argument that if the Holy Spirit proceeds from both, he would be the Son of both.
First, he addresses whether the Holy Spirit should be called begotten or unbegotten and concludes that he should not be called either.
He explains that if the Holy Spirit were called begotten, he would be the Son of both the Father and the Son, which is contrary to Christian belief.
He also cannot be called unbegotten, as this term is specifically attributed to the Father, who is from no other and is the beginning of everything, the source and origin.
Therefore, since the Holy Spirit cannot be accurately called either begotten or unbegotten, he is properly described as proceeding.
He does not proceed from the Father alone, as the Son is born alone from the Father alone.
Instead, he proceeds from both the Father and the Son timelessly, or eternally.
This is why he is not said to be begotten by them; he is neither the Son of the Father nor the Son of the Son, but the Spirit of both.
Thus, it is clearly shown that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both.
It is plainly taught that He does not proceed from the Father alone,
meaning the Son is not solely from the Father; nor from the Son alone,
so the Son is not mistakenly said to be the Father.
But the Holy Spirit is said to proceed, and to proceed from both.
Chapter Four
From the same source.
Many people wonder about the difference between generation and procession.
Since this question seems to be inexplicable in the context of the incorporeal and invisible Trinity, we must explain what the distinguished author Augustine thought.
He adds in his book "On the Trinity," Book 15, Chapter 27, saying:
"However, because in that co-eternal, co-equal, incorporeal, ineffably immutable, and inseparable Trinity, it is very difficult to distinguish generation from procession, it is enough for now for those who cannot grasp more, what we said on this matter in a certain sermon addressed to the ears of the Christian people, and what we wrote down.
Among other things, since I taught through the testimonies of the Holy Scriptures, that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both.
If, therefore, I say, the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son, why did the Son say: 'He proceeds from the Father'? Why do you think, except that He often refers to Him, and what is His, from whom He Himself is?
Hence that statement: 'My teaching is not mine, but His who sent me' John 7:16.
If, therefore, His teaching is understood here, which He still said is not His but the Father's, how much more should it be understood there that the Holy Spirit proceeds from Him too, where He said: 'He proceeds from the Father': so that He did not say, 'He does not proceed from me'?
From whom does the Son have it to be God (for He is God from God), He certainly has it from Him that the Holy Spirit also proceeds from Him: and through this, the Holy Spirit also proceeds from the Son, as He proceeds from the Father, He has it from the Father Himself.
Here, as much as we, such as we are, can understand such matters, why it is not said that the Holy Spirit is born, but rather proceeds; because if He were also called the Son, He would certainly be called the Son of both; which is most absurd.
For no son is from two, except from a father and a mother.
But let it not be suspected that such a relationship exists between God the Father and God the Son.
The Son of Man does not proceed from both the Father and the mother simultaneously.
When He proceeds to the mother from the Father, He does not proceed from the mother.
And when He enters this light from the mother, He does not proceed from the Father.
However, the Holy Spirit does not proceed from the Father into the Son, and then from the Son to sanctify the creature.
Instead, the Holy Spirit proceeds from both at the same time.
The Father has given this to the Son, so just as the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father, He also proceeds from the Son.
We cannot say that the Holy Spirit is not life, since the Father is life and the Son is life.
Just as the Father has life in Himself, He has also given the Son to have life in Himself.
He also gave the Holy Spirit to proceed from Him, just as He proceeds from Himself.
Blessed Augustine transferred this from a sermon he delivered before the people into the fifteenth book on the Holy Trinity.
We have already provided evidence and briefly stated our thoughts on this sermon, which we believe is not necessary to repeat now.
It should be noted: he states there is a difference between generation and procession.
Generation pertains to the Son because He is said to be born of the Father, while procession pertains to the Holy Spirit.
The Holy Spirit cannot be said to be generated, for if He were said to be born, He would be from both the Father and the Son, which he argues is utmost foolishness and does not align with divine generation.
For when has anyone ever been born of both the Father and the Son?
Therefore, since these ideas are most absurd, let it be said that the Son is born of the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from both.
This is not inconvenient, for it has been said: the Father alone is from no one, but the Son and the Holy Spirit are from the Father.
The Father is life, the Son is also life, and the Holy Spirit is life too.
But life comes from no one but the Father.
The Son, however, has life from the Father alone, as He is begotten.
The Holy Spirit also has life, not from the Father alone, nor from the Son alone, but from both.
It's not that the Spirit proceeds from the Father to the Son and then from the Son to sanctify the creature.
There are no moments of time or order to consider here.
Finally, the Spirit proceeds from both at the same time.
When He proceeds from the Father, He also proceeds from the Son, and when He proceeds from the Son, He also proceeds from the Father, with no time or order intervening.
However, this difference remains: the Father received from no one, so the Holy Spirit proceeds from Him.
But the Son received from the Father, so the Holy Spirit also proceeds from Him.
Likewise, in the book of disputation against five heresies, ending his speech about the Holy Spirit, he says:
What else shall I say, to the weary?
Whoever separates the Holy Spirit from the Father and the Son, in eternity, substance, or communion, and denies that He is the Spirit of the Father and the Son, is filled with an unclean spirit and empty of the Holy Spirit.
Let the attackers of truth hear this: those who deny that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son.
For when they deny this, they deny that He is the Spirit of the Father and the Son.
They should fear that they are full of an unclean spirit and empty of the Holy Spirit.
Nor can they obtain forgiveness if they do not renounce such great blasphemy.
But if the wicked do not want to listen, let the friends of piety hear and shudder at the blasphemy of impiety, so that they may be filled with the Holy Spirit.
Also, in the book against Maximinus the Arian (book 3, chapter 5):
You say that you honor the Holy Spirit as a teacher, a guide, an illuminator, a sanctifier.
You worship Christ as the creator.
You adore the Father with sincere devotion as the author.
If you call the Father the author because the Son is from Him, but He is not from the Son; and because the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son in such a way that He gave this to the Son by begetting Him, so that the Holy Spirit also proceeds from Him.
If you call the Son the creator in this way, do not deny the Father or the Holy Spirit as creator.
If you call the Holy Spirit the teacher, guide, enlightener, and sanctifier in such a way that you do not dare to take these roles from the Father or the Son, these words are ours as well as yours.
These are the words of Saint Augustine against the Arians.
Let those decide for themselves whether they want to be of the faith of the emperors or the Arians.
If they deny that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son, they oppose the Catholic faith and become proponents of Arian doctrine.
But if they are Catholics and hate the falsehood of the wrong doctrine, they do not accuse the Latins but rather confess the Catholic belief that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son; denying this is clearly agreeing with Arian disbelief.
Again, in the same book, chapter 14: You ask me, addressing Maximinus the Arian, to whom he was speaking, if the Son is from the substance of the Father, and the Holy Spirit is from the substance of the Father, why is one the Son and the other not the Son?
Here is my answer, whether you understand it or not: The Son is from the Father, the Holy Spirit is from the Father; but the Son is begotten, the Spirit proceeds.
Therefore, the Son is the Son of the Father because He is begotten; the Spirit, however, is the Spirit of both because He proceeds from both.
Maximinus the Arian, against whom blessed Augustine argues, denied that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father.
He claimed that the Spirit was lesser than the Son and not consubstantial with the Father, attempting to nullify the Catholic faith which holds that the Holy Spirit is consubstantial with the Father and the Son.
And so he said: If the Holy Spirit were from the substance of the Father, just as the Son is from the substance of the Father, there would consequently be two sons.
To this, blessed Augustine responded, saying that the Spirit proceeds from the Father because He is of the same substance as the Father; however, He is not the Son because He is not begotten but proceeds.
The Son, who is begotten, is from the substance of the Father and is therefore the Son because He is begotten.
But the Holy Spirit, although from the substance of the Father, is not the Son because He is not begotten.
However, He proceeds from the substance of the Son because He is the Spirit of both and consubstantial with both.
Whoever denies this agrees with the Arians and contradicts the Catholic faith.
It follows: When the Son spoke about Him, He said, "He proceeds from the Father" (John 15:26) because the Father is the author of His procession.
The Father begot such a Son, and by begetting, gave Him so that the Holy Spirit also proceeds from Him.
For if He did not proceed from Him as well, He would not have said to the disciples, "Receive the Holy Spirit" (John 20:22) and by breathing on them, He gave it, signifying that the Spirit also proceeds from Himself, clearly showing by breathing what He was giving secretly by inspiring.
If He were born, He would be born not only from the Father but also from the Son, and undoubtedly, the Son would be called the Son of both.
Since the Son is in no way the Son of both, He did not need to be born from both.
Therefore, the Spirit is of both, proceeding from both.
This confirms that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, and that the Son wanted to signify this when He said, "He proceeds from the Father." He did not deny that the Spirit proceeds from Himself but referred the authority of the procession to the Father, who begot such a Son. By begetting, He conferred upon Him that the Holy Spirit proceeds not only from the Father but also from the Son.
He affirms this with another testimony, where after the resurrection, appearing to the disciples, the Savior said, "Receive the Holy Spirit." Not only by words but also by breathing, He gave what He commanded them to receive. He spoke to the disciples by breathing on them to receive the Holy Spirit, signifying clearly by breathing that it proceeds from Himself, which He was giving secretly by inspiring.
Likewise, resolving the question, lest the Son be of both since He proceeds from both, as the Arian impiety slandered, saying, "If the Holy Spirit were born, He would not be born only from the Father, nor only from the Son; because He proceeds from both." He proceeds, not born: but undoubtedly, He would be born from both since He proceeds from both; and without a doubt, He would be called the Son of both.
Now, however, the generation of the Spirit is removed, because He is neither the Son nor of the Father, nor of both; and therefore, it was not fitting for Him to be born of both.
Because he who does not have a birth rejects sonship, and he who is not a son should in no way be born.
However, the Spirit proceeds from both.
Therefore, it overturns the Arian slander, which is concocted out of the envy of falsehood and born of the wickedness of impiety, desiring to assert that the Spirit is not from the substance of the Father.
Because if He were, He would be the Son.
But this Catholic man, with a Catholic argument, demonstrates indeed that the Spirit is from the substance of the Father, yet is not the Son; because proceeding is not the same as being born.
Consequently, he inferred: Who can explain what the difference is between being born and proceeding, speaking of that most excellent nature?
Not everything that proceeds is born, although everything that is born proceeds; just as not everything that has two legs is a human, although every human has two legs.
This I know: but to distinguish between that generation and this procession, I do not know, I am not able, I am not sufficient.
The eminent doctor, and the most vehement conqueror of heretics, testifies that the Holy Spirit is not the Son, who is not born but proceeds, not only from the substance of the Father but also from the Son.
Since He shares in the substance of both, as being consubstantial, and is said to proceed from the Father from whom the Son is also born, a significant question arises: what is the difference between birth and procession?
And he confesses that distinguishing between being born and proceeding in that most excellent nature is not only impossible for him but for any mortal; although it is understood that not everything that proceeds is born; nonetheless, everything that is born proceeds.
For nothing can be born unless it proceeds from that of which it is born, like a son from a parent.
For when he proceeds from the secret of the mother's womb into the light, he is said to be born, but not so when he proceeds from the secret of the father into the mother.
We can't deny the procession, as it involves the flow of seed into the mother's womb, from which the son is later said to be born.
We're not saying that the Spirit proceeded from the Father at one time and from the Son at another; rather, we want to show that not every procession is a generation, but every generation is a procession.
For example, not everything that has two feet is a human, although every human has two feet.
This example distinguishes between birth and procession, but it doesn't specifically explain what it means to be born or to proceed, much like when we discuss what a species or a genus is.
Having two feet is the genus for the species that is a human, and a human is the species of the genus that has two feet.
If you consider the genus, both humans and birds with two feet fall under it; if you consider the species, a human has two feet.
Hence the saying: not everything with two feet is human, because this general term also includes birds.
But when you say human, you include every human, but not everything with two feet: the term means more than just human; and so this definition doesn't specifically mean human, nor specifically two feet, just like with procession and birth.
In procession, birth is shown, but not always, like when it is said: Honey comes from the mouth of the wise.
And the Psalmist about the sun: And he is like a groom coming out of his chamber.
The sun's chamber signifies a certain secret place, hidden from human sight, from where it comes out each day to give light to mortals.
However, birth always shows procession because it can never happen without procession: whatever is born also proceeds.
Therefore, Blessed Augustine indeed describes what generation and procession are, but in terms of genus or species, not in their own proper sense; he admits he does not know these things properly, nor can he distinguish them by their proper boundaries.
And why is this?
He gives the reason, saying: Because both of these are ineffable, that is, the generation of the Son and the procession of the Holy Spirit.
As the prophet speaks about the Son, he says:
"Who can describe His generation?"
Isaiah 53:8.
In the same way, it can very truly be said about the Holy Spirit:
"Who can describe His procession?"
These words show that the birth of the Son and the procession of the Holy Spirit cannot be explained, because they are ineffable.
Therefore, we should not investigate what cannot be explained, because it cannot be comprehended in any way.
It should be enough for us that the Holy Scripture testifies about these things:
the Son was born from the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds, not only from the Father, but also from the Son.
This is indicated when it says:
"It is enough for us, because the Son is not from Himself, but from Him from whom He was born. The Holy Spirit is not from Himself, but from Him from whom He proceeds."
And because He proceeds from both, as we have already shown, He is called the Spirit of the Father, as it is read:
"But if the Spirit of Him who raised Jesus from the dead dwells in you"
Romans 8:11.
And He is called the Spirit of the Son, as it is read:
"But if anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to Him"
Romans 8:9.
Here, against Maximinus the Arian, Doctor Augustine shows that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
Those who deny this reveal themselves to be Arians and do not acknowledge that the Holy Spirit is consubstantial with the Son.
For if He does not proceed from Him, He is not of the same substance as the Son.
Thus, they either blaspheme the Holy Spirit as a creature or deny that the Son has all that the Father has.
They cannot deny that the Holy Spirit is the Spirit of the Son, for the Apostle says:
"Because you are sons, God has sent the Spirit of His Son into our hearts, crying, 'Abba, Father'"
Galatians 4:6.
If He is the Spirit of the Son, as the Apostle confesses, He is either subject, as the Arian wants, who counts Him among creatures, or He proceeds from the Son, as Catholics confess.
Let the emperors of the Greeks choose what they will: they cannot deny that the Holy Spirit is the Spirit of the Son.
Therefore, let them explain how He is the Spirit of the Son if He does not proceed from Him.
If they deny the procession, they are essentially proclaiming creation, which is clearly the heresy of Arius.
The Spirit cannot belong to the Son unless it is either created or proceeds from Him.
In the following chapter:
What does "In the beginning was the Word" mean except that the Son was in the Father?
When the Jews asked the Son who He was, He answered: "The beginning, who also speaks to you."
The Father is the beginning, not from a beginning; the Son is the beginning from a beginning. But together, they are not two, but one beginning. Just as the Father is God and the Son is God, together they are not two Gods, but one God.
I will not deny that the Holy Spirit, proceeding from both, is the beginning. These three together, just as one God, are one beginning. He denies that the Holy Spirit is a creature, saying it is the beginning just as the Father is the beginning, and the Son is the beginning. The Father is the beginning from no beginning, the Son is the beginning from the Father as the beginning. The Holy Spirit is the beginning, not from no beginning, nor from the Father alone, but from both the Father and the Son. Yet, not three beginnings, but one beginning; just as the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are not three Gods, but one God.
In later chapters: Light from light, the Son from the Father, both together are one light. Just as God from God, both together are indeed one God, and all this not without the Spirit of both. By saying this, he testifies that it proceeds from both. If the Spirit is of the Father because it proceeds from the Father, then the Spirit is also of the Son because it proceeds from Him. There is not a different reason the Spirit is called the Spirit of the Father and the Spirit of the Son, but one and the same; because it proceeds from both, just as it is the Spirit of both.
For if you say it is the Spirit of the Father because it proceeds from the Father, what reason remains for it to be called the Spirit of the Son, unless it also proceeds from Him?
Here, the blessed Augustine, opposing Maximinus the Arian, spoke and wrote about the procession of the Holy Spirit from the Son.
He condemned Arian deceit and affirmed the piety of the Catholic faith.
Anyone who tries to contradict this is found to be an enemy of the Catholic faith.
In his dialogue disputing with Pascentius the Arian Pascentius (Pascentius' Argument with Augustine, Letter 178, middle), he also said:
For if we believe that the whole of God dwells in a believer, how can we not believe that the Father fully encompasses the Son, or the Son fully encompasses the Father?
Therefore, the Father remains in Him, and He in the Father.
We must believe that the Holy Spirit proceeds not only from the Father but also from the Son, and always proceeds to carry out the works of the Trinity.
He says that the Holy Spirit is one with the Holy Trinity as a cooperator, united not only in substance but also in operation with the Father and the Son, as proceeding from both and cooperating with both.
This He could not do if He did not, by proceeding from both, receive and continue to receive substance.
Chapter Five
From Gennadius and Fulgentius.
Gennadius, the bishop of Constantinople, a scholar well-versed in ancient texts, discusses the procession of the Holy Spirit in his book "Ecclesiastical Dogmas":
We believe in one God: the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit. The Father, because He has the Son; the Son, because He has the Father; the Holy Spirit, because He proceeds from the Father and the Son.
Therefore, the Father is the source of divinity, the principal name. Just as He has always been God, He has always been the Father, from whom the Son was born, and from whom the Holy Spirit proceeds; because He is neither the Son nor unbegotten, as He is not the Father; nor is He the created Holy Spirit, for He comes from God the Father and God the Son, proceeding as God.
Gennadius clearly states that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son, meaning He comes from their substance. He could not proceed from both in any other way if He did not substantially come from both. Hence, he says that the Holy Spirit proceeds as God from God the Father and God the Son.
Though he says the Holy Spirit proceeds, he denies that He should be called either born, because He is not the Son, or unbegotten, because He is not the Father.
Fulgentius, another bishop, known for his literary scholarship and sanctity, who endured much from the Arians for the Catholic faith, writes in his book "Questions on the Procession of the Holy Spirit":
Thus, everything that is of the very nature is common to the three persons, yet each person is uniquely identified by something that is neither separable nor common.
We say it is proper to the Father that He begot; it is proper to the Son that He alone was born of the Father alone; and it is proper to the Holy Spirit that He proceeds from the Father and the Son.
In these properties, however, there is no separation of nature, but a distinct personal recognition.
The author explains what is common and what is unique to each person of the Holy Trinity.
Common to all three persons is the consubstantiality of one nature.
Unique to each is that the Father alone begets, the Son alone is begotten from the Father alone, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
Therefore, those who accept that it is unique to the Father to be the begetter and unique to the Son to be the begotten must also accept that it is unique to the Holy Spirit to proceed from both the Father and the Son.
If they deny this, they must explain what is unique to the Holy Spirit.
For the procession from the Father is also common to the Son, because everything that is born also proceeds.
Thus, according to this teacher's view, it is unique to the Holy Spirit to proceed from both the Father and the Son, which is not common to either the Father or the Son.
The Father proceeds from no one, the Son from the Father alone, and the Holy Spirit from both.
Also consider the following:
The divinity of the Son could not receive the Holy Spirit, since the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son just as He proceeds from the Father and is given by the Son just as He is given by the Father.
Nor could that nature, from which the Holy Spirit originates, either await or receive generosity.
The Holy Spirit is entirely of the Father, entirely of the Son; because He is naturally the Spirit of both the Father and the Son.
Hence, He proceeds entirely from the Father and the Son and remains entirely in the Father and the Son; because He remains as He proceeds and proceeds as He remains.
Thus, He naturally has with the Father and the Son the fullness of unity, and the unity of fullness, so that He is entirely from the Father and entirely from the Son.
Therefore, the divinity of the Son did not receive the Holy Spirit, with whom the Holy Spirit shares one nature, and from whom He has whatever He has, indeed from whom He is what He is; because what He naturally has is what He is.
This passage discusses the fullness of Christ's divinity and His humanity.
It explains that His humanity received the Holy Spirit, not in a limited way, because the fullness of divinity resides in Him.
As the Gospel testifies about Christ: "And we saw His glory, the glory as of the only begotten from the Father, full of grace and truth" (John 1:14).
"Truth" refers to divinity, and "grace" refers to the gift. For the man born of the Virgin to be perfect God, as He is perfect man, He received this not by merit but by the gift of divine grace. However, divinity naturally possesses fullness and perfection, lacking nothing, incapable of diminution, and not subject to increase.
According to this fullness of divinity, the Son of God, Christ, could not receive the Holy Spirit since the Holy Spirit proceeds from Him just as from the Father and is given by Him just as by the Father. Therefore, the divinity of the Son, from which the Holy Spirit originates, cannot receive the largesse of the Holy Spirit, who is the cause of its existence. For the Holy Spirit is entirely of the Father and entirely of the Son; and being entirely of both or entirely of either, it does not follow that the Father and the Son are to be called the Holy Spirit as if receiving the cause of existence from Him.
Nor is the Son alone the Son of the Holy Spirit as if receiving existence from Him, because naturally, the Spirit is one of both the Father and the Son, receiving essence from them. Consequently, as the blessed Fulgentius testifies, He proceeds entirely from the Father and entirely from the Son. For no part of Him proceeds from the Father and another part from the Son; nor does part of Him remain in the Father and part again in the Son. He is indivisible and inseparable, not composed of different parts. Thus, He remains as He proceeds and proceeds as He remains.
For He naturally has with the Father and the Son the fullness of unity and the unity of fullness, and He is entirely from the Father and entirely from the Son.
Therefore, the Son's divinity did not receive the Holy Spirit as something it did not already possess, since the Holy Spirit shares the same nature as the Son, from whom He received everything He has, and indeed, from whom He is what He is.
Because He substantially comes from the divinity of the Son, this clearly shows that the procession of the Holy Spirit is no less from the Son than from the Father.
Anyone who tries to deny this will also deny the subsistence of the Holy Spirit, because He cannot subsist unless He receives His essence from the one from whom He subsists by proceeding.
Saint Fulgentius spoke about the procession of the Holy Spirit against the Arian heresy, affirming the true statement that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son, because He is the Spirit of both, receiving His essence from both.
Anyone who denies this is shown to be subject to Arian heresy.
Chapter Six
From Athanasius.
Let's return to Athanasius, the Bishop of Alexandria, whom we mentioned first among the witnesses of the Catholics at the beginning, so that he can conclude the testimony about the procession of the Holy Spirit from the Son, who was there from the start.
In the second book on the distinct Persons and the united name of divinity against the Arians, he states:
The Father is different in person because He truly begot; and the Son is different from the Father because He was truly begotten by Him.
The Holy Spirit, the main comforter, is different in person from the Father and the Son, as He was poured out on the apostles at Pentecost, truly proceeding from the united divinity of the Father and the Son.
This author distinguishes the unique properties of each person and unites them in divinity, showing what is unique to each and what is shared.
It is proper to the Father that He begot; neither the Son nor the Holy Spirit share this, otherwise, it wouldn't be unique to the Father.
The Son is distinguished from the Father because He was begotten, and the Father begot; but the Holy Spirit doesn't share in the property of generation at all, since He is begotten, proving He is not begotten.
The Holy Spirit has this unique property: He neither begot nor was begotten, but proceeds from the united divinity of the Father and the Son; in which He doesn't share with the Father or the Son.
For the Father is from no one, the Son is from the Father alone, but the Holy Spirit is from both the Father and the Son.
Whoever denies this must show from where the person of the Holy Spirit is distinguished from the properties of the Father and the Son.
These three persons of the Holy Trinity are distinguished by their own properties, yet united by the unity of divinity.
They have no difference in the communion of divinity, but there is property in the persons and undifferentiated unity in divinity.
Again, in the seventh book: Why, if you see me, do you also see my Father (John 14:9)?
Does it indicate that there is one invisible image of the nature of truth in these?
Why do you read, keeping the truth of the Spirit in the bond of peace (Ephesians)?
Section 4, 3): If you do not accept that he is from the united divinity of the Father and the Son, why do you read that the chosen vessel said, "We have all drunk of one Spirit," First Corinthians 12:13, if you separate him from the united true nature of the deity?
It testifies that the Son is of the same nature as the Father, which the Arians denied, because there is one invisible image of the nature of truth in the Father and the Son. It also testifies that the Holy Spirit is of the same substance as the Son because he exists from the united divinity of the Father and the Son. This clearly shows that he proceeds from both. Since the divinity of the Father and the Son is so united that it cannot receive any difference, the Spirit cannot proceed from the divinity of the Father unless he also proceeds from the Son.
Likewise, he cannot proceed from the divinity of the Son unless he also proceeds from the Father. Otherwise, the united divinity of the Father and the Son will no longer be indifferent if the Spirit proceeds from the divinity of the Father and does not equally proceed from the divinity of the Son. Thus, it will no longer be united, which is impious and Arian. Therefore, according to the Catholic faith, let it be said, as blessed Athanasius confesses, that the Holy Spirit is from the united divinity of the Father and the Son.
He also testifies that we have drunk of one Spirit. In saying this, he approves that the Spirit of the Father is not different from the Spirit of the Son. The one who is of the Son is also of the Father, and he is from the united true nature of the deity, that is, the substance of the Father and the Son, which consists in such unity that it is divided by no separation. Since the Holy Spirit is also one of this substance, it is evidently approved that he proceeds from the Father and the Son, to whom he is joined in the united nature of the deity.
Also, below: Hypocrites, how do you accept, "All these things are worked by one and the same Spirit, dividing to each one as he wills," First Corinthians 12:11, if you separate him from the united operation of the deity? The united deity is of the whole Holy Trinity, in which equally consists the person of the Holy Spirit, without whom there would not be a Trinity.
Therefore, by stating that divinity is united through a single operation, it confirms that the Holy Spirit, the Father, and the Son work together; and that those united by the same operation cannot be separated by nature.
Consequently, it is clear that the nature of the Father, the Son, and the Spirit is united, both in substance and in operation.
Again: Hypocrites, how do you understand the statement: The same Spirit, the same Lord, the same God, if you do not accept Him as the true God from true nature, performing wonders in all things?
He calls the Spirit Lord and God: and truly God from true nature.
By saying 'from true nature,' he acknowledges that the Holy Spirit is not from Himself, but from the true nature of the Father and the Son.
Just as the Father and the Son are not separated by the truth of nature, so too the Holy Spirit subsists from the true nature of both: because it cannot proceed from the nature of the Father if it does not also proceed from the nature of the Son: because what is the nature of the Father is also the nature of the Son.
And by saying that blessed Athanasius called the Holy Spirit true God from true nature, without adding 'of the Father' or 'of the Son,' it certainly implies that the Holy Spirit is true God from the true nature of both, performing wonders in all things.
Again: Hypocrites, through whom is the word of wisdom given, or the word of knowledge, or faith, or the gift of healing, or the working of miracles, or prophecy, or the discernment of spirits, if not from the united fullness?
No faithful person doubts that all these mentioned are gifts of the Holy Spirit.
Furthermore, by concluding that the Holy Spirit is capable of these things because He is from the united fullness, it indeed acknowledges that He proceeds from the Father and the Son.
For the united fullness of the divinity of the Father and the Son is such that it is neither increased nor divided; and this united fullness of the Father and the Son proceeds, complete and full God Himself, because He cannot receive an increase in quantity.
If, according to the new heresy, the Spirit proceeds only from the Father and not from the united fullness, then the community of the Son is not present, and singularity lies with the Father.
This is false and full of heretical depravity.
Therefore, according to the blessed Athanasius, it should be said that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the united fullness, since He consists of the true deity of both the Father and the Son, true God.
Again, below: Therefore, because it says, "By the word of the Lord the heavens were established, and all their power by the breath of His mouth" (Psalm 33:6), recognize that this substantive Word was truly born from the Father; and the breath of His mouth means the Spirit, who proceeds from the same united substance.
The Arians denied that both the Son and the Holy Spirit were consubstantial with the Father.
Thus, throughout the present text of this argument, it is contended to prove that both the Son and the Holy Spirit are consubstantial with the Father.
As in the present passage, saying "By the word of the Lord the heavens were established," signifies the divinity of the Son; and "by the breath of His mouth all their power," signifies the consubstantiality of the Holy Spirit. To this, it is also added that He proceeds from the same united substance, indicating indeed that He proceeds from both the Father and the Son, whose substance is united.
Hence it is consequently said: "Thus we find not from another nature but from the same." It is understood to refer to the Holy Spirit.
The Arians blasphemed, saying that the Holy Spirit was of a different nature than the Father, for they contended that He was a creature. Blessed Athanasius refutes them, saying that He is not of a different nature than the Father, and that He proceeds from the united substance of the Father and the Son. Thus, he testifies that the substance of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit is united, which the Greeks call οὐσίαν (ousia), and that the operation of the Trinity is united and the same.
In the eighth book: Just as two pieces of wood joined together and thrown into a fire produce an inseparable flame from the two pieces of wood, so the Holy Spirit proceeds from the power of the Father and the Son, having the same power of divinity.
No one should think that God the Father and God the Son are like two pieces of wood with one flame, suggesting that blessed Athanasius was subject to the Holy Spirit.
Instead, they used this analogy from material things to explain something that is not material or divisible by place.
They did this partially because a creature cannot be entirely similar to the Creator, and we must understand the meaning more deeply.
It is not said that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son like one fire from two pieces of wood, making the Holy Spirit seem separable.
Nor is it like two spirits, one from the Father and one from the Son.
Rather, it is one and the same Holy Spirit, sharing the same divine power as the Father and the Son, from whom He proceeds.
This should not seem impossible or unbelievable, since even in material things, something can come from two sources and still remain singular without becoming dual.
Also, in the same book: The Father is in the Son, and the Son is in the Father; and the Holy Spirit is the union of divine power and the unity of the Trinity.
This shows that the Holy Spirit is the love of the Father and the Son.
Nothing else more powerfully and fittingly perfects the unity of the Holy Trinity.
However, we must not understand this love, which is the Holy Spirit, as a quality and not a substance, since He is one person of the Holy Trinity.
The Holy Spirit is called the union or unity of the Father and the Son because He proceeds from both and unites both, remaining undivided, inseparable, and consubstantial, as one of the Holy Trinity.
Also in the booklet of Faith.
In his second letter about the unity of faith to Theophilus, he says:
The true Father begot the true Son, God from God, light from light, life from life, perfect from perfect, whole from whole, full from full; not created, but begotten, not from nothing, but from the Father, of one substance with the Father.
And the Holy Spirit, the true God, neither unbegotten nor begotten, not created, nor made, but of the Father and the Son, always in the Father and the Son.
He explains that the Holy Spirit is neither begotten nor unbegotten because the Son is begotten, as mentioned before, and the Father is unbegotten.
However, the Spirit is not created or made, since He is the Spirit of the Father and the Son, always present in both.
By saying that the Spirit is from the Father and the Son, yet not created or made, he shows that the Spirit proceeds from both, being consubstantial and co-eternal with the Father and always with the Son.
This indicates that the unity of the Holy Trinity cannot be separated by place or time.
Likewise, in the tenth book, he cites the testimony of the Apostle saying:
For who has known the mind of the Lord, that he may instruct Him?
But we have the mind of Christ.
First Corinthians 2:16.
Upon this he adds:
The Apostle has declared that the mind of Jesus Christ, in its own substance, is the Holy Spirit.
Blessed Athanasius refers to the proper substance of Christ as His divinity and asserts that the mind of this substance is the Holy Spirit.
This is not to be understood in terms of human bodily senses like hearing or sight, but in terms of what we call the sense of the mind, meaning His intellect.
He says the intellect of Jesus Christ is the Holy Spirit, not implying that Jesus does not understand by Himself, but that His intellect is the Holy Spirit; for He is the wisdom of the Father: Reaching from one end to another mightily, and sweetly ordering all things.
Wisdom of Solomon 8:1.
He wants us to understand the Holy Spirit as the essence of Christ, so that we may know the Holy Spirit is of the same substance as Christ.
Just as the sense of the mind cannot be separated from the mind, nor does it originate from anywhere else but the mind, the Holy Spirit, when described by the Apostle as the sense of Jesus Christ, is not separate from the substance of Christ's divinity, nor does it proceed from anywhere else but from it.
The Holy Spirit is consubstantial with the Son, having his procession from the divine substance.
Therefore, hearing the Savior say: "I am the life" (John 14:6);
and Paul writing: "For the law of the Spirit of life" (Romans 8:2);
and again: "God sent the Spirit of his Son into our hearts" (Galatians 4:6);
also seeing the Only Begotten breathing on the apostles and saying: "Receive the Holy Spirit" (John 20:22); we are taught that the Spirit, remaining in his own life and substance, is the Spirit.
We understand that he is neither begotten nor created by the Son.
From all these things, we are instructed that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son and remains in his own life and substance.
And although he is inspired by the Son, meaning he proceeds from the Son, he is neither created nor begotten by him.
The Holy Spirit is neither the Son nor a creature.
By these teachings, it is clearly shown that the Holy Spirit is of the same substance as the Son, as he proceeds from him; and he is not one of the creatures, but the sanctifier of the creatures.
When he is called the Spirit of the Son according to the Apostle, it does not mean he is subordinate, because he is not created; but it means he is proceeding, yet not begotten, because he is not the Son.
However, he has received his own existence from the substance of the Son, as he is one person of the Holy Trinity.
Also in the book Disputation Against Arius, it appears that the Holy Spirit is not different in substance from the Father and the Son.
Since He does not act or speak on His own as if He were a stranger and foreign, but as a partner of one and the same nature, He speaks and acts on what is common to the Father and the Son.
For if He spoke of His own things, He would undoubtedly be considered not only alien to the Father but also deceitful and a deceiver.
Because, as the Son says:
"Everyone who speaks a lie, speaks from his own things"
(John 8:44).
Therefore, He speaks the truth because He does not speak from His own, that is, not on His own, but speaks what needs to be spoken from the Father and the Son:
"He will take from what is mine and declare it to you"
(John 16:14).
And to show that this taking from Him is also taking from the Father, He said:
"That is why I said, 'He will take from what is mine,' because all that the Father has is mine"
(John 16:15).
Therefore, you see that the Holy Spirit is not separate from the Father and the Son, as He speaks what is known to be the property of the Father and the Son.
It shows more clearly that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son and is consubstantial with both.
For He says that He is not different in substance from the Father and the Son, since He does not act on His own, but from those from whom He proceeds.
Since He is of the same nature and substance as the Father and the Son, He does not speak of His own things, but what is common to the Father and the Son.
For He is not from Himself, and therefore what He speaks is certainly from those from whom He received it, so that He may be, act, and speak.
Just as He does not speak of His own things, but received from the Father what He speaks.
"Everyone who speaks a lie, speaks from his own things"
(John 8:44).
Therefore, blessed Athanasius says the Holy Spirit speaks the truth because He does not speak from His own, for He is not from Himself, but speaks what is of the Father and the Son.
For just as He is consubstantial with them, so He received from them what He speaks, not existing first and then receiving, but receiving as He proceeds.
And He brings in the Son saying:
"He will take from what is mine and declare it to you"
(John 16:14).
And why he said this, he explains when he adds:
This means, he says, that receiving from the Son is the same as receiving from the Father because the Father and the Son, just as they are not separated in substance, are also in no way divided in the procession of the Holy Spirit.
Therefore, he adds that the Son said: For this reason, He said, He will take from what is mine, because everything the Father has is mine John 16:15.
Showing that the Holy Spirit, when proceeding from the Father, also proceeds from the Son; and when proceeding from the Son, also proceeds from the Father.
Hence, concluding at the end, he says that the Holy Spirit is not separated from the Father and the Son, to whom he is united both by nature and by action.
For he speaks and says things that are known to belong to both the Father and the Son, proceeding from both, receiving from both as essence, so also operation, undivided from them in both will and power, as being one of the same Holy Trinity.
Blessed Athanasius, teaching about the procession of the Holy Spirit, approves that he proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
If the emperors of the Greeks want to contradict this, let them see which authors they follow in the profession of the Holy Trinity.
For the authority of this most blessed and most catholic man is embraced, venerated, and defended by the whole catholic Church of Christ.
Let these things we have said about the Holy Spirit be sufficient, following the authority of the elders and imitating the teaching of the holy Scriptures, we indeed wish to approve that he is God and consubstantial with the Father and the Son, co-eternal, and in all things similar in power, similar in virtue, of one and the same majesty.
For this question has been discussed and determined by the holy disputation of the Fathers, refuting the perfidy of heretics, who, thinking badly about the Holy Spirit, denied that he was true God:
however, we did not have much necessity to dispute this, although many things have been said by us on this matter, when the opportunity arose.
Regarding the procession itself, much has been discussed, raising a question; we believe it is sufficient for those who cherish devotion and truth, and who follow the light of wisdom rather than the darkness of error.
The Holy Spirit speaks of both in Solomon's words: Do not argue with a mocker, or they will hate you.
Rebuke the wise, and they will love you.
Proverbs 9:8.
And again: Do not speak to fools, for they will scorn your prudent words.
Proverbs 23:9.
Therefore, let the detractors of the Holy Spirit see that by refusing to accept the discipline of wisdom, they are like those who prefer their own folly to the teachings of the Holy Scriptures.
These modern individuals, however, are not true debaters; they neither refute nor prove anything with reason, but simply assert novelty.
Who can we say they resemble?
When they deny that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, they present neither reasoning nor authority to support their claims: it seems more like the swelling of frivolity than the weight of prudence.
They are so arrogant that whatever they assert seems authoritative: they are like those who, being blind and not seeing the light, swear that the sun is not present on the earth, even when the day shines brightly.
But let us say to them what the Savior says to the Jews: Search the Scriptures, for they are the ones that testify about me.
John 5:39.
So too, let them search the sacred volumes of the Scriptures.
For these are the ones that testify to the Holy Spirit, that He proceeds from the Father and the Son.
Let them examine the doctrines of the Catholic Fathers; they will find where to correct their error and lay down the swelling of foolishness, by which they believe in themselves rather than the truth, and replace the authority of the elders with their own madness: let them first learn what they seek to teach, lest, while boasting of their ignorance as the highest expertise, they become like the one who, after being exalted to a high place, as Solomon says, appeared foolish.
But now, it's time to move on to the rest of their accusations.
While they eagerly criticize the Latins, they clearly reveal their own reprehensible behavior.