Historical Notice on Odalric. (From Gallia Christiana Volume Nine Page Fifty-Six)
Odalric, also known as Udelric or Ulric, was the son of Count Hugh and Eva from Lorraine.
His parents were descendants of the holy Arnulf of Metz, known for their noble lineage, character, and piety.
After overseeing the provostship of the Church of Reims, according to Colvenerius, he was elected with the support of King Lothair in 962 and was consecrated the same year by bishops Guy of Soissons, Roricon of Laon, Gibuin of Chalons, Hadulf of Noyon, and Wigfrid of Verdun.
He received the pallium, as was the tradition of his predecessors, from Pope John the Twelfth.
Not long after, due to his noble heritage and the privilege of his rank, he became the chief chancellor of the realm under King Lothair, serving in this role in 963 and 968.
Flodoard noted in his Chronicle in 965 how diligent and wise Odalric was in defending the properties of his Church.
When a dispute arose over the episcopal see of Reims, severe conflicts erupted between the King of France and Herbert's family, leading to widespread devastation across the province from plundering, fires, and looting.
Some nobles, who appeared to protect the church-owned villages in the king's name, gradually claimed them as if they were hereditary.
Among them was Count Theobald, whom Odalric summoned.
When Theobald refused, he was excommunicated in 964 for wrongfully taking and stubbornly holding Codiciac Castle and other estates of Saint Remigius.
Coming to a better state of mind, Theobald returned what he had wrongfully acquired.
As a result, the bishop not only absolved him but also granted the mentioned castle to his son Odo, who had placed his trust in the bishop.
Inspired by this example, Count Herbert willingly returned the village of Sparnacum.
However, Ragenold was obstinate and was excommunicated for unjustly holding villages.
He even aggressively invaded certain places of the same episcopal see, plundering and setting them on fire.
In the year 965, Odalric attended a council of bishops held in Cologne.
At this council, the foundation of the church of Saint Martin in Liege was confirmed.
The generous bishop is praised for donating the village of Vindenissa, located in the county of Rethel, to his church in Reims.
Additionally, he reclaimed the valley of Rodigionis for his church.
This valley had been previously gifted by Hugh, the son of Count Roger, but was later seized by his descendants in the year 967.
However, it should be mentioned that, due to the murder of a relative of his, disgracefully killed in the borough of Saint Remigius, he burned down the entire borough and everything near the castle of Saint Remigius.
He devastated it and afterward allowed no one to live there.
According to an addendum to Flodoard, he died after seven years of governance, in the year 969, and was the first archbishop of Reims to be buried in the metropolitan church.
The Reims Necrology briefly mentions him with these words: "Odalric or Odalric, archbishop, died on November 6, who gave us Vindemissa; for whose soul, 24 coins with as many loaves of bread and wine are given to the poor; six poor clerics are fed in the refectory."
Under his leadership, on March 28, 966, the renowned Flodoard, born in Epernay on the Marne, first a priest and canon of Reims, then a parish priest of Cormicy, and, as some say, a monk and abbot of an uncertain monastery in the diocese of Reims, died in his seventy-third year.
For more about him, consult the abbots of Saint Basolus, the bishops of Noyon in Fulcherius, the Acts of the Saints of the Order of Saint Benedict, volume 7, page 325 and following, the Annals of the same order, volume 3, pages 397, 511, and 512, and the Literary History of France, volume 6, page 313; to which nothing new needs to be added.
Sentence Against Sacrilegious Thieves by Odalric, Archbishop of Reims (Acts of the Province of Reims, Volume One, Page Six Hundred Twenty-One)
Odalric, the Archbishop of Reims, along with Rodulf, the archdeacon, and all the clergy of the Church of Reims, address all the children of the Church.
Some wicked and vile people have entered the temple of God with criminal intent, where they should be praying and seeking God's mercy.
Instead, driven by a diabolical impulse, they fearlessly pursue theft and sacrilege.
Among them, some individuals, whose identities remain unknown, entered the basilica of the blessed Mother of God, Mary, and did not hesitate to steal the cloth from the altar of the holy cross.
Additionally, other items were recently taken, like the linens from the bed of Frederick, the church custodian.
From the chapel of Saint Peter within the cloister, a priestly garment was stolen this year, and a missal book was taken last year.
We excommunicate and anathematize the perpetrators and sacrilegious thieves of all these things by the power and authority of Almighty God the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
By the power of the holy cross, the virginity of the blessed Mother of God, Mary, and the authority of Saint Peter, the prince of the apostles, and all the saints, they are excommunicated and separated from participation in the body and blood of Christ.
They are barred from entering the church and any fellowship with Christians until they come to repentance and make amends, or return what they have stolen from this church.