Critique of Another Hymn Wrongly Attributed to Hilary
In the manuscript of Cardinal Sirleto, which was once in the library of Altemps and now belongs to Cardinal Ottoboni, this hymn is followed by another, longer one.
This could be considered late, as mentioned in the previous letter to Abraham.
It definitely suits the evening time.
It begins with the stars and serves as a kind of general confession of a soul, groaning under the attack of vices like lust, pride, envy, discord, vanity, gluttony, and unchecked joy, relying solely on God's mercy and the merits of Christ to seek forgiveness.
Moreover, it reflects the time of the Arian heresy, as it expresses a faithful spirit.
It explicitly condemns Arius and Sabellius by name, and adds no other heretics except, perhaps to complete the verses, Simon Magus.
However, the wording does not seem worthy of Hilary.
The verses are structured by the number of syllables rather than the rhythm.
And although the speech should be in the feminine gender if this hymn were meant to be sung by a daughter, it is consistently masculine.
From the beginning to the end, let the reader decide what to think of the rest of the hymn.
The Beginning
I feel unworthy to lift my sorrowful eyes to the bright stars of heaven, burdened by the weight of my sins:
Please spare those you have redeemed.
I failed to do the good I should have done and committed countless shameful acts; my offenses know no bounds:
Help me, Christ.
THE END.
Singing a hymn with a faithful voice, I reject Arius and the barking of Sabellius.
I never agree with Simon's grunting whispers.
With zeal for Christ, I am fervent in his name.
For the Holy Mother Church has nourished me with Catholic teachings through all time from her sacred breast.