Book of Synods, or On the Faith of the Easterners
by Hilary of Poitiers in the year 358
To the most beloved and blessed brothers and fellow bishops,
of the provinces of First Germany, Second Germany, First Belgium, Second Belgium,
First Lugdunensis, Second Lugdunensis,
the province of Aquitaine, the province of Novempopulana,
and to the people and clergy from Narbonensis
of Toulouse, and to the bishops of the provinces of Britain,
Hilary, servant of Christ, in God and our Lord, eternal salvation.
Dearest brothers,
during your long period of silence, I had decided not to send you any letters of ecclesiastical discourse.
Although I had frequently informed you from many cities of the Roman provinces
about what was happening with our religious brothers,
the bishops of the East, concerning faith and diligence,
and how much, under the guise of temporary disturbances,
the devil had uttered hisses of deadly doctrine with his venomous mouth and tongue; fearing that in such a grave danger of impiety or error of so many bishops,
your silence might be taken as despair of a polluted and impious conscience
(for it was not lawful for you to be ignorant when frequently warned),
I also thought it right to remain silent among you,
very mindful of the Lord's command, which, after the first
and second admonition, ordered that those who remained disobedient even under the testimony of the Church should be regarded like pagans and tax collectors
(Matthew 18:15 and following).
Upon receiving the letters of your blessed faith, which were delayed and infrequent due to the length and secrecy of my exile, I rejoiced in the Lord that you have remained uncontaminated and uninjured by any infection of the detestable heresy, and that you have shared in my exile.
Saturninus, fearing his own conscience, thrust me into exile by deceiving the emperor.
You have denied communion to him for a full three years now, staying connected with me in faith and spirit.
The faithlessness from the town of Sirmium was not only rejected by you but also condemned and announced as such.
I found it necessary and appropriate, as a bishop communicating with other bishops in Christ, to send the conversations of a saving and faithful discourse.
Those who, through fear of uncertainties, previously only congratulated me for being free from all these, now rejoice in the integrity of our common faith.
O glorious unshaken stability of your conscience!
O firm house on the foundation of the faithful rock!
O unblemished and untroubled constancy of an undefiled will!
For it has remained, and even now remains, after the profession of the Council of Béziers, in which I had announced, with some of you as witnesses, the patrons of this heresy to be introduced, innocent, inviolate, and religious.
For you have awaited the glorious triumph of holy and unchangeable perseverance, not yielding to the threats, powers, and wars of Saturninus.
When all battles of blasphemy against God were being initiated, you remained faithful with me in Christ until now.
Neither did you yield to the opportunity of the erupting heresy before, and now you have broken all its insolence in the confrontation of its eruption.
You have triumphed, Brothers, with great shared faith and joy.
Your steadfastness has brought you double honor and glory, both from the integrity of your conscience and the authority of your example.
The unwavering reputation of your faith has even moved some Eastern bishops, though late, to feel shame for the heresy they had nurtured.
Upon hearing the impious writings from Sirmium, they opposed the boldness of the irreligious with their own decrees.
Although their resistance caused some scandal and offense to their pious concerns, it was enough to compel those who had agreed with Potamius and Hosius at Sirmium to admit their ignorance and error, and to condemn what they had previously done by subscribing again.
They condemned one error to condemn another.
Your invincible faith still upholds the admirable glory of your conscience.
Acting without deceit, ambiguity, or fear, it remains secure in professing its liberty in Christ.
You abstain from the communion of those who exile bishops for opposing blasphemies, and you do not join in the guilt of unjust judgment by assenting to deceitful dissimulation.
After much grief over the irreligious actions of the impious, the communion of the Lord is now confined within us.
Since the Church began to be troubled by these disturbances—bishops exiled, priests removed, congregations frightened, faith endangered, and the Lord's doctrine established by human will and power—your unblemished faith neither pretends to be ignorant of this nor professes to endure it, understanding that even the assent of dissimulation would be guilty.
Although you have shown unwavering freedom and security in your faith through everything you do, you also display the fervor of your passionate spirit.
Some of you have sent me writings, asking that my humble letters inform you of what the Easterners have done and are doing in their professions of faith.
You have added this burden to me, the most inexperienced and unlearned of all, out of your affection and charity, asking me to share my thoughts on all their statements.
It is very difficult to express my own faith according to my inner understanding, let alone explain the understanding of what others say.
I implore you by the mercy of the Lord, since you wished for me to write to you about divine matters and the pure conscience of our faith, as you have desired through these letters, that no one judges me before the completion of the discourse based on the beginnings of the letters.
It is unfair to bring a prejudiced judgment based on the beginnings of what is said without understanding the complete reasoning until the end.
Judgment should be made not on what is started but on what is completed.
I do not fear for you, as the Lord knows my feelings, but for some who are overly cautious and prudent, not understanding the commandment given to them through the blessed Apostle Paul, Romans twelve verse three, "not to think of himself more highly than he ought to think."
I fear that they do not wish to understand all those things whose completion I will provide, avoiding understanding the truth from what will be completed.
But whoever undertakes to read and understand these things should grant both themselves and me the faithful patience to review everything until the completion.
Perhaps this entire discourse of my faith will ensure that neither the stealthy heretics deceive with what they want, nor the perfect Catholics fail to achieve what they desire.
Therefore, I comply with your most impatient will, Charity.
I have sent all the creeds issued at various times and places after the holy council of Nicaea, with explanations of all the sentences and even the words added by me.
If any faults are found, no one can blame me for the statements, for I am just the messenger, as you wished, not the creator.
However, if anything is correct and aligns with apostolic teachings, the glory belongs to the author, not the interpreter.
Nevertheless, I have faithfully transmitted what has been done.
You judge whether they are Catholic or heretical by your faith.
Although it was necessary to respond to your letters, in which you sent me the Lord's communion in your faithful writings, some of you, also called to the council which seemed to be in Bithynia in 463, maintained the firmest constancy of faith within my communion, abstaining from others outside Gaul.
It was indeed fitting for the episcopal ministry and voice, amidst such heretical rage, to share with you some pious counsels of faith through letters.
For although our bodies are in exile, the word of God could not be bound or detained, so it could still be communicated with you wherever you are.
(See Book Ten on the Trinity, number Four).
When I learned that synods were going to be held in Ancyra and Ariminum, and that two or even one representative from each of the Gallican provinces would be attending, I felt it was important to explain to you—though you may already know—about the issues that have arisen between us and the Eastern bishops due to mutual suspicions.
Since I was stationed in the Eastern regions, I thought it necessary to share this with you, so that after you had condemned the heresy emerging from Sirmium, and they had also judged it with an anathema, you would know that the very same stance you took was also affirmed by the Eastern bishops.
I didn’t want you, whom I hope will be highly regarded at future synods, to be seen as differing in any way from the purity of the Catholic faith, even unknowingly, due to misunderstandings about the language used.
I believe it is right and proper to first discuss the suspicions and disagreements over words.
I’ll clearly explain what the Eastern bishops have said and established against the heresy written at Sirmium, using the clearest language possible.
Although others have already published this in a very clear way, translating from Greek to Latin often introduces confusion, as the direct translation of words can obscure the simplicity of understanding.
You remember that in those very writings recently produced at Sirmium, it was attempted and labored to establish that while the Father was proclaimed as the one and only God of all, it was denied that the Son is also God.
Furthermore, by deciding to remain silent on the terms homoousios (of the same substance) and homoiousios (of similar substance), they effectively decreed that the Son of God was either created from nothing like a creature, or from some other essence, rather than being born from God the Father.
Additionally, by saying that the Father is greater in honor, dignity, glory, and majesty, they sought to suggest that the Son lacked all these qualities in which the Father is greater.
Finally, while his unknown birth is being asserted, through this decree of ignorance, we are commanded not to know that he is from God.
It's as though it could be commanded that someone should know what they are to be ignorant of or be ignorant of what they have known.
Although unwillingly, I have included this very plague of the most impious blasphemy, so that the strength and reasoning of the responses made by the Easterners might be more fully understood.
Their effort was to counter all the heretical arts according to the understanding of their wisdom.
Blasphemy at Sirmium by Hosius and Potamius in the year 357.
When it was thought there might be a discussion about faith, everything was carefully considered and discussed at Sirmium, with our most holy brothers and fellow bishops, Valens, Ursacius, and Germinius, present.
It was agreed that there is one omnipotent God and Father, as is believed throughout the whole world, and His only Son, Jesus Christ our Lord and Savior, begotten from Him before the ages.
But two gods neither can nor should be proclaimed, because the Lord Himself said, "I am going to my Father and your Father, to my God and your God" (John 20:17).
Therefore, there is one God for all, as the Apostle taught.
Is He the God of the Jews only?
Is He not also of the Gentiles?
Yes, of the Gentiles also.
Since there is one God who justifies the circumcised by faith and the uncircumcised through faith (Romans 3:29-30).
Other things were agreed upon, and no disagreement was found.
As for what was troubling some about the substance, which in Greek is called "ousia," that is (to be understood more clearly), "homoousion," or what is called "homoiousion," no mention should be made at all.
Nor should anyone proclaim it because it is neither contained in the divine Scriptures, nor can anyone explain the nativity of the Son, about whom it is written, "Who will declare His generation?" (Isaiah 53:8).
It is clear that only the Father knows how He begot His Son, and only the Son knows how He was begotten by the Father.
There is no ambiguity that the Father is greater.
No one can doubt that the Father, in honor, dignity, glory, majesty, and by the very name of Father, is greater than the Son, as He Himself testified, "The one who sent me is greater than I" (John 14:28).
And this is catholic, no one is ignorant of it: there are two persons, the Father and the Son; the Father is greater, and the Son is subject with all those things that the Father has subjected to Him.
The Father has no beginning, is invisible, is immortal, and is impassible.
The Son, however, is born from the Father, God from God, light from light.
As was said before, no one knows the generation of this Son except His Father.
This Son of God, our Lord and God, as it is written, took on flesh or a body, that is, became a man, from the womb of the Virgin Mary, as the Angel proclaimed in Luke chapter one, verse thirty-one.
As all the Scriptures teach, especially the Apostle, the teacher of the nations, He took on human nature from the Virgin Mary, through whom He showed compassion.
The closing statement of the entire faith and its confirmation is that the Trinity must always be preserved, as we read in the Gospel: Go and baptize all nations in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit in Matthew chapter twenty-eight, verse nineteen.
The Trinity is a complete and perfect number.
The Paraclete, the Spirit, comes through the Son; He was sent according to the promise to instruct, teach, and sanctify the Apostles and all believers.
The Son, as an image, is not just in name different from the Father.
With these numerous and significant professions of impiety published, the Eastern bishops gathered together and made contrary definitions of their beliefs.
But because we frequently use the terms "essence" and "substance," it is necessary to understand what essence means, so that when we speak of things, we do not misunderstand the terms.
Essence is what something is, or what it is made of, and what remains as it is.
Essence, nature, genus, and substance can all describe the same thing.
Properly, essence is called such because it always is.
It is also called substance because it is a thing that must subsist in itself; whatever subsists undoubtedly remains in its genus, nature, or substance.
When we say essence signifies nature, genus, or substance, we mean the thing that always exists in all these.
Now let us review the faith definitions prescribed by the Eastern bishops.
If anyone, upon hearing that the Son of God is the image of the invisible Father, claims that the image of God is the same as the invisible God, as if not truly acknowledging the Son, let them be cursed.
The assertion of those who wish to preach only the names Father and Son is excluded; since every image mirrors the one it represents, the form is indistinguishable.
No one is an image of themselves; the image must reflect the one whose image it is.
Therefore, the image is a likeness of the original and indistinguishable from it.
Thus, there is the Father, and there is the Son: because the Son is the image of the Father.
For the image to be an image of something, the nature and essence, according to which it is the image, must come from the creator.
If anyone, upon hearing the Son say, "For as the Father has life in Himself, so He has granted the Son to have life in Himself" (John 5:26), claims that the one who received life from the Father is the same as the one who gave it: let them be cursed.
The person receiving and the one giving are distinguished; so they are not the same single entity.
It is a curse on those who believe in the profession of a solitary and unique one in the receiver and giver; it cannot be understood that the same one received from himself, who gave.
Nor is He alone who lives, and through whom life exists; because one is living by themselves, and another professes to live by the creator: no one will profess the same one, who uses life, and through whom life is caused.
If anyone, upon hearing that the only begotten Son of the invisible God is similar, does not say that the Son, who is the image of the invisible God, is of the same essence as the one whose image He is: as if not truly acknowledging the Son, let them be cursed.
Since the only begotten Son of God is the image of the invisible God, it is essential that He shares the same essence in form and nature.
How can there be a distinction in nature between the Son and the Father when the Son, existing in what is proper to the Father, shares His own nature, including glory, power, authority, invisibility, and essence?
Thus, it is understood that in these equal divine attributes, the Son is not lesser because He is the Son, nor is the Father greater because He is the Father.
The Son mirrors the Father in form and is not different in nature, because the substance of the generated Son from the Father's substance does not allow for diversity.
The Son, being the image of the invisible God, encompasses all the characteristics and magnitude of the Father's divinity within Himself.
This truly defines being the Son: He perfectly reflects the truth of the Father's form in Himself with complete similarity in nature.
And if anyone, upon hearing this, says, "Just as the Father has life in Himself, so He has granted the Son to have life in Himself" and denies that the Son is also similar to the Father in essence, let him be anathema. It is clear that the life understood in the Father signifies substance. The life of the Only Begotten, which is generated from the Father, is understood as essence, thus indicating the similarity of essence to essence.
It follows that the perfect nativity of His origin is of an undifferentiated nature. For what is life in both signifies essence in both. And in the life that is generated from life, that is, the essence that is born from essence, it holds within itself the undissimilar nature of its origin, since life comes from life. The essence of the begotten and the begetter, that is, the life that is held and given (indeed given by the Father to the Son), does not differ in similarity.
For God, from Himself, generated from the similarity of His own nature; He did not abandon in whom the ungenerated similarity, the property of natural substance, resides.
He gives only what he has: just as he has life, he gives life to others.
Thus, what is essential, like life from life, similar in essence, is born.
The essence of the one being born and the one begetting remains the same, with no diversity or dissimilarity.
If anyone says, “He created or made me” Proverbs 8:22, and “He begot me” Proverbs 8:25, and hears this from the same source, they should understand “he begot me” not so much from a similarity of essence, but rather say “he begot me” and “he created me”: as if not saying the Son of God is perfect from two names signifying the son (but through two names, that is, he created me, and he begot, only describing the condition, and not at all the son); just as Wisdom conveyed a pious understanding from two things: let them be accursed.
The distinction between birth and creation.
To those saying the Son of God is a creature or a condition, reason contradicts this.
For it is the profane presumption of the impiety of heretics, claiming to have read, “The Lord created or made me”; for this condition or creation seems to be understood: but removing the subsequent sentence, from which the prior takes its understanding, they seize their authority for impiety from the first, to say it is a creature, because Wisdom said it was created.
If it was created, how could it also be born?
For every birth, whatever it may be, consists in its nature from the begetting nature: but creation takes its beginning from the power of the creator, namely the powerful Creator, to create a creature from nothing.
Therefore Wisdom, which said it was created, likewise in the subsequent Proverbs 8:25, Wisdom explains why it said it was created) said it was begotten: referring creation to the unchangeable nature of the parent, which, outside the manner and custom of human birth, without any diminishment or change of itself, created from itself what it begot.
For the work of the creator does not involve passion, or mixture, or birth.
For what is created from nothing begins to exist at some point.
The one who creates brings into being through their power: creation is the work of power, not the result of nature from nature.
Birth, however, is the perfect product of legitimate origin and genuine nature: for what is born takes its nature from what generates it.
The Son of God is not born through physical division, but a perfect God is born from a perfect God.
Therefore, Wisdom says He was created, excluding any physical passion in His generation.
Saying He was created and born at the same time aptly explains the nature of His origin.
Those who attribute only the likeness of power to the Son are condemned.
To show that His nature is of birth, not creation, He added that He was born.
By confessing that He was created and born, He provided a complete understanding of His birth: signifying the unchangeable nature of the Father in creation and showing that His birth from God the Father is of legitimate and proper substance.
The understanding of perfect birth brings forth the concepts of creation and generation: one being without change, and the other pertaining to nature.
Both become one, and one becomes both perfect: the Son, born from God without change, is created from the Father in such a way that He is born; and the unchangeable and natural Father creates the Son in such a way that He generates Him.
Therefore, the heresy that professes the Son of God as a creature is condemned: the impious opinion of creation from nothing is extinguished by the natural generation shown through the perfection of impassible divinity.
If anyone reveals the likeness of the Father in the Son according to essence, it is by the Son Himself saying: For as the Father has life in Himself, so He has granted the Son also to have life in Himself (John 5:26).
According to the efficacy of what he teaches: For what the Father does, the Son does likewise (John 5:19), granting only a similarity in efficacy.
But according to essence, which is most important to our faith, he deprives the Son: as if depriving himself of the knowledge of eternal life, which is in the Father and the Son—let him be accursed.
The similarity of power comes from the similarity of nature.
Life signifies essence.
The heretics, concluded by the authorities of the Scriptures, usually attribute this only to the Son, saying he is similar to the Father only in power, but they take away from him the similarity of nature.
Foolish and impious, not understanding that the similarity of power arises only from the similarity of nature.
A lower nature never attains the power of a higher and superior nature.
Or what will those who assert this profess about the almighty God the Father, if his power is equaled by the power of an inferior nature?
It cannot be denied that the Son can do the same things; for he said: Whatever the Father does, the Son does likewise (John 5:19).
But the similarity of power is succeeded by the similarity of nature, when he says: Just as the Father has life in himself, so he has granted the Son to have life in himself (John 5:26).
In life, there is the significance of nature and essence: which is taught to be given to be had just as it is had.
Therefore, the similarity of life holds the similarity of power: for the similarity of power cannot be different from the similarity of nature.
And so it is necessary that the similarity of essence follows the similarity of power: because just as the Father does the same things, so the Son does the same things: just as the Father has life, so he has granted the Son to have life.
Therefore, the recklessness of the impious profession is condemned, which, confessing the similarity of power, dared to proclaim the dissimilarity of nature: since the faith of our principal hope is to confess the undifferentiated substance of divinity in the Father and the Son.
7.
If anyone, while claiming to believe in the Father and the Son, says that the Father is of a different essence from the Son but has similar power, and speaks profane and novel words against the essence of the Son, denying that He is truly the Son of God, let them be accursed.
They are refuted for denying that the Son is of the same nature as the Father.
By confusing and mixing words, heretics frequently evade the truth and capture the ears of the unwary with the sound of common terms, proclaiming the Father and the Son by name only, not by the truth of natural and genuine essence.
They know that all creations are called children of God, and they remember that all saints are called sons of God.
By this example, they confess the Father and the Son according to the common names of the universe, so that the Father and the Son are named rather than truly are.
For they are named, but they are not, if in them there is a distinct nature of different essence: since the truth of the paternal name can only be acquired from the offspring of its own nature.
Therefore, the Father cannot be called the father of a substance alien and different from Himself, because a perfect birth does not have a diversity of original substance.
Therefore, all this impiety is rejected, which speaks of the Father not according to the nature of the Son begotten from Himself.
For God will not be called Father by this, if He has a creation similar to His power and efficacy, but if He has begotten a nature not different and alien from His essence: because natural birth does not receive the diversity of paternal nature.
And for this reason, those who assert that the Father is the father of a nature different from Himself are accursed: so that something other than God is born from God, and they think that the essence of the Father degenerated in begetting the Son.
For they destroy, as much as they can, the very unbegotten and immutable essence of the Father, who have dared to attribute to Him in the birth of His Only Begotten Son a dissimilarity of degenerate natural essence.
If anyone, understanding the Son to be like the Father in essence, says that the Son is the same as the Father, or a part of the Father, or came from the Father by emanation or some passion, let him be accursed.
The Son is not like physical sons who come from a physical father; rather, an incorporeal Son comes from an incorporeal Father.
This understanding protects against personal distortions and fraud.
Many heretics claim that the Son is similar to the Father in divinity, suggesting that this similarity means the Father and the Son are the same.
They argue that an indistinct similarity implies a singular entity, as things that do not differ in kind seem to remain united in nature.
However, birth does not support this idea, since union does not involve birth.
What is born has its origin in the father.
Even though the divinity of the one being born is indistinguishable from that of the begetter, the begetter and the begotten cannot be anything other than different, nor can the begotten be dissimilar to the begetter.
Therefore, he is accursed who preaches the similarity of nature between the Father and the Son in order to abolish the personal significance of the Son.
When two things do not differ due to mutual similarity, the similarity itself, without union, confirms that the Father and the Son are distinct, as the Son is the immutable similarity of the Father.
The Son is not a part of the Father, so one cannot say both are the begotten and the begetter.
Nor is the Son an emanation, as if a continuous flow through a physical and individual progression.
Rather, it is a perfect birth, with the similarity of nature, not from physical conception and birth, but as an incorporeal Son subsisting from an incorporeal Father.
The Father is never understood to be the Son, and the Son is never understood to be the Father.
If anyone says that the Son is different from the Father because the Father is one and the Son is another, as it is said, "Another is the one who testifies about me, and the one who sent me is the Father" (John 5:32), and does not say that the Son is also similar to the Father according to essence, let them be cursed.
This is due to the pious property of the persons of the Father and the Son that is understood in the Church, fearing that the Son and the Father might sometimes be understood as the same.
It was said to the apostles of the Lord: "Be as shrewd as snakes and as innocent as doves" (Matthew 10:16).
By this, He wanted us to embody the nature of beings that are different from each other: shrewdness tempered by innocence, and innocence instructed by shrewdness.
In this way, there would be both simple wisdom and wise simplicity, which has been observed in the exposition of this faith.
The previous sentence guarded against proclaiming a personal union through the similarity of essence and ensured that the birth of the Son was not destroyed through the indifference of nature.
This meant that one would not differ from the other in kind.
The following sentence met the shrewdness of the snake, with the innocence of the dove, through simple and apostolic prudence.
This was to prevent the preaching of dissimilar nature from creeping in again, since a personal union is not received, because the Father is one and the Son is another.
Since one is the sender and another is the sent (because the one who sends and the one who is sent are not the same), it should not be thought that the sent and the sender are of different and dissimilar nature, as the born and the begetter cannot be of different essence.
Therefore, the similarity of the indifferent nature is retained in the Father and the Son through the birth of essence, ensuring that the one who is sent and the one who sends are not one in the similarity of nature.
Nor, in the property of the person, since he cannot be called both Son and Father, is the likeness of nature taken away.
Thus, the truth of birth advances to the likeness of essence, and the likeness of essence does not lose the personal truth of birth.
The profession of the begetter and the begotten does not exclude the likeness of essence; for while the begetter and the begotten cannot be one, the begotten and the begetter are not of different natures.
10.
If anyone understands God the Father of the only-begotten Son, but does not understand that the only-begotten Son existed beyond time and human estimation without suffering: it is as if they bypass the evangelical proclamation, which disregards the interval of time between the Father and the Son, but faithfully teaches us what was in the beginning—the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God John 1:1:
let him be anathema.
It is a pious belief that the Father is not contained within time, for the truth of the timeless paternal name exceeds all understanding.
The religious confession of the paternal name, which acknowledges the impassible origin of the one being born, is not held within time; because the eternal and infinite God the Father cannot be understood as temporal.
According to the evangelical proclamation, the only-begotten God the Word is known to be with God from the beginning, rather than being born within time.
If anyone says that the Father is older in time than his only-begotten Son, and the Son is younger than the Father: let him be anathema.
The likeness of essence configured in kind is also taught to be indifferent to time: lest the one who is the image of God, the Word, who is God with God from the beginning, and similar to the Father, with time intervening between himself and the Father, does not have perfect in himself what is both image, and Word, and God.
If a younger person is preached about in time, he has lost both the truth of the image and the likeness: because it is no longer a likeness if it is found to be unlike in time.
Because what God the Father is, cannot have any time lest He ceases to be the Father: therefore, time cannot be in the Son lest He ceases to be the Son.
And for this reason, neither is the Father said to be older than the Son, nor the Son younger than the Father: because the truth of each name cannot exist without the other.
And if anyone refers the timeless substance of the only-begotten Son from the Father to the unbegotten essence of God, as if saying the Son is the Father: let him be accursed.
The previous definition seemed to give an opportunity to heretics, since the time of the Son's birth was denied (because it would be blasphemy if the Father were in time: but He would be in time if the Son were subjected to time): so that through this opportunity of the denial of time, under the name of the Son, the Father, who is unbegotten, would be proclaimed unique and singular as both Father and Son to Himself: because where the time of birth is excluded, the opinion of unbegottenness seems to be admitted; so that He is not thought to be born, whose birth is not in time.
Therefore, lest through this opportunity of the denial of time, the heresy (Sabellian) of union should creep in; this impiety is condemned, which dares to refer the timeless birth to the unique and singular substance of the unbegotten essence: since to be timeless is one thing, and to be unborn is another; of which one has birth (though outside of time), the other is solely the same eternal author to itself for what it is.
Beloved Brothers, we have reviewed all the definitions of faith issued by the Eastern bishops, which they established in a synod gathered among themselves against the emerging heresy.
We have done our best to adjust our explanations to fit their understanding, aligning with their statements rather than presenting foreign ideas.
For those who, against new and profane impiety, decide these matters according to their conscience and longstanding doctrine, and compel those who wrote or accepted the heresy at Sirmium to acknowledge their ignorance and agree to these decrees:
Where the Son is the perfect image of the Father:
Where, under the property of the indistinguishable image, the Son is not diminished by profane deceit, so the Father remains:
Where the 477th image of the Father is the Son, declared through the truth of likeness, differing in no way from the substance of the Father, whose image He is, despite the diversity of substance:
Where, through the life that the Father possesses and the life received by the Son, there is no difference in substance, signifying that in life, the Father has what the Son received to have:
Where the Son is not a created being but is of one substance with the nature of the Father:
Where, just as there is indistinguishable power between the Father and the Son, so their essence suffers no diversity:
Where the Father, by generating the Son, does not degenerate in Him by any diversity of nature:
Where, because the likeness of nature in both is not different, yet the property of the likeness of personal names rejects the union, so the one who subsists is not called both Father and Son:
Where it is rightly said that the Father sends and the Son is sent; yet in no way is the essence between the Father and the Son, that is, between the sent and the sender, distinguished:
Where the truth of the paternal name is not contained within time:
Where the Son is not later in time than the Father:
Where beyond all time, the perfect birth does not admit any error in the inborn nature.
And this, dear brothers, is the doctrine of faith that has been published by a few people from the East around the same time you rejected the introduced heresy.
The reason for explaining this was because silence on the single substance was being decreed.
But now, at various times, many causes have required other statements of faith to be written, and their nature will be understood from the statements themselves.
Once all their actions are known, we will bring a more complete and easier religious resolution to the matters in dispute among us, appropriate to unity.
This explanation of the ecclesiastical faith was published in the year three forty-one and presented at the synod held during the dedication of the completed Church of Antioch.
Ninety-seven bishops who were present made this explanation when one of the bishops had come under suspicion of holding incorrect beliefs.
In accordance with the evangelical and apostolic tradition, we believe in one God, the Father Almighty, the creator, maker, and provider of all things, from whom all things come; and in one Lord Jesus Christ, His only begotten Son, through whom all things were made.
He was begotten from the Father, God from God, complete from the complete, one from one, perfect from perfect, king from king, Lord from Lord, the Word, wisdom, life, true light, true path, resurrection, shepherd, gate, unchangeable and immutable, the unchangeable image of divinity, essence, power, and glory, the firstborn of all creation, who was always with God in the beginning as the Word and God, as it is said in the Gospel,
"And the Word was God"
John chapter one, verse one, through whom all things were made, and in whom all things hold together: who in the last days descended from above, and was born of a virgin according to the Scriptures, and became a lamb, mediator between God and men, predestined for our faith, and leader of life. For He said:
"For I have come down from heaven, not to do my own will, but the will of Him who sent me"
John chapter six, verse thirty-eight.
He suffered, rose again for us on the third day, ascended into heaven, and now sits at the right hand of the Father.
He will come again in glory to judge the living and the dead.
And in the Holy Spirit, given for comfort, sanctification, and completion to believers, as the Lord Jesus Christ ordained disciples, saying:
Go, and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit Matthew 28:19:
Clearly, the Father truly as Father, the Son truly as Son, and the Holy Spirit truly as Holy Spirit.
These names are not simply or idly proposed but carefully signify the proper substance, order, and glory of each one named, so that they are indeed three in substance but one in harmony.
Therefore, having this faith, from the beginning until the end in the sight of God and Christ, we anathematize every heretical and perverse sect.
If anyone teaches anything other than the wholesome Scriptures and correct faith, saying either time, or space, or age, or being or having been before the Son was begotten, let them be anathema.
If anyone says the Son is a creation, just like one of the creatures; or a birth, like other births; or a making, like other makings, and not as the holy Scriptures have handed down each one of these things mentioned above; and if anyone teaches or preaches anything other than what we have received: let them be anathema.
For we truly and with fear believe and follow all that has been handed down by the divine Scriptures from the prophets and the apostles.
This faith thus far is suspect.
It seems to have spoken less clearly about the indistinguishable similarity of the Father and the Son, especially since it felt that the proper substance, order, and glory of each one named were signified in the names, so that they are indeed three in substance but one in harmony.
Excused by the council's intent.
New heresy after the Nicene council.
The three substances of the Trinity, as rightly described by the Easterners.
First, it's important to know that the council in Antioch wasn't against the heresy that proclaimed the Father and the Son as having different substances.
Instead, it was against the one that, after the holy synod of Nicaea, went so far as to attribute three names to the Father, which we'll discuss in due course.
At the beginning of my speech, I asked for the patience and fairness of those reading and listening until all my words were completed, so no one would judge me prematurely without understanding the full speech.
Therefore, the holy synod aimed to eliminate the impiety that tried to mislead the truth of the names of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
They wanted to prevent a triple naming from falsely claiming unity of names, where the Father alone would bear the names of both the Holy Spirit and the Son.
For this reason, they said there are three substances, explaining the persons through the substances, without separating the substance of the Father and the Son by different essence.
When it's said that they are indeed three by substance but one by harmony, it's not a criticism.
With the Spirit being named, that is the Paraclete, it's fitting to proclaim unity by the similarity of substance rather than by essence.
This formula proclaims the same essence of the Father and the Son, acknowledging the distinction of nativity and innascibility.
The Son is unchanging.
The previous speech did not distinguish the Father and the Son by diversity of essence and nature.
When it is said, "God from God, the whole from the whole," there is no doubt that the whole God was born from the whole God.
The nature of God from God does not differ, and "the whole from the whole" applies to those whom He is the Father. "One from one" excludes the passions of human birth and conception, so while one is from one, it is not from elsewhere, nor different, nor another. It is one from one, perfect from perfect.
Birth does not differ from unbegotten origin except in cause, as the perfection of both is the same.
King from King.
The power called by one and the same name does not admit dissimilarity of power.
Lord from Lord.
Dominance is equal in the Lord.
The acknowledged dominion in both, without diversity, does not accept a difference.
That which, after many other things, is subjected, is the immutable and unchangeable image of divinity, essence, power, and glory.
For God from God, whole from whole, one from one, and perfect from perfect; and King from King, and Lord from Lord, since the Son, born, also subsists in all the glory and nature of divinity in which the Father remains.
He also has this from the paternal substance, so that he may not become mutable.
For in his birth, the nature from which he was born was not changed; but the born one obtained an immutable essence from the immutable authority of nature.
Although he is an image, he is an immutable image (not changed in him by dissimilarity of the paternal essence from which he is begotten), because the image of the paternal essence would be born in him.
And now, since he is taught to be the firstborn of all creation, and that same Word of God, always having been with God in the beginning, is called God; while he is firstborn, he is shown to have been born; while he always was, he is not separated from the Father by time.
Therefore, a division of substances cannot be seen, as this synod aimed at nothing else than to exclude the union by the name of three substances, of a triple term introduced to the separation of different substances in the Son and in the Father.
The whole explanation of faith does not distinguish the Father and the Son, the unbegotten and the only-begotten, by time, name, essence, dignity, or dominion.
It is also worthy of common conscience to know the other faiths written by those same Eastern bishops in different places and times, so that the sincerity of conscience may be understood through multiple confessions.
Faith According to the Synod of the East year 347
The holy synod gathered in Sardica from various provinces of the Eastern regions:
Thebaid, Egypt, Palestine, Arabia, Phoenicia, Syria Coele, Mesopotamia, Cilicia, Cappadocia, Pontus, Paphlagonia, Galatia, Bithynia, Hellespont, Asia, the two Phrygias, Pisidia, the Cyclades islands, Pamphylia, Caria, Lydia, Europe, Thrace, Emimontus, Mysia, and the two Pannonias, presented this faith.
We believe in one God, the Father Almighty, creator and maker of all things, from whom every fatherhood in heaven and on earth is named.
We also believe in His only-begotten Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, who was begotten from the Father before all ages, God from God, light from light, through whom all things were made, both in heaven and on earth, visible and invisible:
who is the word, and wisdom, and power, and life, and true light:
and who, for us, was incarnate in the last days, and born of the holy Virgin, who was crucified, died, was buried, rose from the dead on the third day, was taken up into heaven, and sits at the right hand of the Father, and is to come to judge the living and the dead, and to render to each according to their works;
whose kingdom remains without end in the endless ages.
For He sits at the right hand of the Father not only in this age but also in the age to come.
We also believe in the Holy Spirit, that is, the Paraclete, whom He promised to the Apostles after His return to heaven, to teach them and remind them of all things, through whom the souls of those who sincerely believe in Him are sanctified.
However, those who say that the Son of God is from non-existence, or from another substance, and not from God, and that there was a time or age when He was not, the holy and catholic Church knows as strangers.
Similarly, those who claim there are three gods, or that Christ is not God and was not before all ages, or that Christ, the Son, is not the Son of God; or that He is the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, or that the Son is unbegotten; or that the Father begot the Son neither by counsel nor by will: the holy and catholic Church condemns them.
This faith affirms the eternal origin of the Son, and it is from the substance of God.
It provides a concise yet comprehensive explanation of this faith.
To condemn those who said the Son came from nothing, it establishes that His origin was timeless and eternal.
It also declares as blasphemous those who claim the Son was born from some other substance and not from God.
Since He did not come from nothing, nor from anywhere other than God, it is clear that He was born from the essence of God.
The essence of the only-begotten Son is generated from the eternal substance of the Father, not from nonexistence or any other source.
It also rejects any notion of time and ages separating the Son from the Father, emphasizing that He who is the same in nature cannot be separated by time.
God is only one; in what sense are many said?
The previous faith proclaims the one substance of the Father and the Son.
It blocks all heretical approaches to ensure no diversity is proclaimed in the Son.
It condemns those who say there are three gods, because the true nature of this substance does not accept multiple names, unlike among men and Angels, where a name is given out of honor of merits, although their substances differ from God.
Therefore, there are many gods.
However, in the nature of God, there is only one God; yet the Son is also God, because His nature is not different.
Since God is from God, both must be God, as their essence is not distinguished by any difference in kind.
The name is rejected in nomination because there is no diversity in the quality of nature.
Since it is unacceptable to say there are multiple gods, and it is unacceptable to deny that the Son is God, it is clear that the unity of the name for both comes from the same substance.
In affirming the unbegotten God the Father and the only-begotten God the Son, since neither differs in essence, and since both are God, it must be believed and proclaimed that there is one God.
Thus, the faith of the bishops is strengthened with careful and diligent caution, confirming the sameness of nature between the begotten and the begetter through the unity of the name.
The faith does not teach that the Son is an unbegotten solitary God.
He is born from will.
To prevent the idea of one God from implying a solitary God without progeny, this notion is immediately condemned.
Since there is one God, it acknowledges one solitary God the Father, who embodies both the name of Father and Son.
In the begetting Father and the begotten Son, one God is proclaimed due to their shared substance.
The faith of the saints does not recognize an unbegotten Son because the Son's nature exists only through birth.
His birth is so perfect that He, born from the substance of God, is also born from His counsel and will.
From will and counsel, not from physical passion, the absolute perfection of God's essence is begotten from God's essence.
Therefore, we must revisit the faith that was established long ago, when Photinus was deposed from the bishopric.
Example of faith at Sirmium by the Easterners against Photinus, year 351.
We believe in one God, the Father almighty, creator and founder, from whom all fatherhood in heaven and on earth is named.
And in His only Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, who was born of the Father before all ages, God from God, light from light, through whom all things were made in heaven and on earth, visible and invisible.
He is the Word, Wisdom, Power, Life, and True Light:
who in the last days became incarnate for us, was born of the holy Virgin, was crucified, died, and was buried:
who also rose from the dead on the third day, ascended into heaven, sits at the right hand of the Father, and will come at the end of the age to judge the living and the dead, and to reward each according to their works:
whose kingdom, persevering without end, remains forever.
For He will be seated at the right hand of the Father, not only in this age but also in the future.
And in the Holy Spirit, the Comforter, whom He promised to the Apostles after He ascended to heaven, to send to teach them and to remind them of everything, through whom also the souls of believers in Him are sincerely sanctified.
However, those who say: The Son is from nothing, or from another substance, and not from God; and that there was a time or age when He was not: the holy and catholic Church knows them as strangers.
Moreover, if anyone says that the Father and the Son are two gods: let them be cursed.
And if anyone, while saying there is one God, does not confess that Christ, the God and Son of God before the ages, obeyed the Father in the creation of all things: let them be cursed.
And if anyone dares to say that the unbegotten God, or a part of Him, was born of Mary: let them be cursed.
And if anyone says that the Son was born of Mary according to foreknowledge or predestination, and not born of the Father before the ages, and that all things were made through Him: let them be cursed.
If anyone says that the substance of God expands and contracts: let them be cursed.
If anyone says that the extended substance of God makes the Son, or refers to the breadth of His substance as the Son, let them be cursed.
If anyone says the Word of God is the implanted or pronounced Son, let them be cursed.
If anyone says that God and man born of Mary means the unbegotten God, let them be cursed.
If anyone, hearing "The Word became flesh" John 1:14, thinks that the Word was changed into flesh or says that it took on flesh through transformation, let them be cursed.
If anyone, hearing that the only Son of God was crucified, says that His divinity suffered corruption, passibility, transformation, diminution, or death, let them be cursed.
If anyone, when hearing "Let us make man" Genesis 1:26, says that it was not the Father speaking to the Son, but God speaking to Himself, let them be cursed.
If anyone says that it was not the Son seen by Abraham in Genesis 18, but the unbegotten God or a part of Him, let them be cursed.
If anyone says that it was not the Son who wrestled with Jacob as a man in Genesis 32:24, but the unbegotten God or a part of Him, let them be cursed.
If anyone, hearing "The Lord rained from the Lord" in Genesis 19:24, does not understand it as referring to the Son and the Father, but says that He rained from Himself, let them be cursed. For the Lord the Son rained from the Lord the Father.
If anyone says that the Lord and the Lord, the Father and the Son, are two gods, let them be cursed. For we do not equalize or compare the Son to the Father, but understand Him as subject. For He did not descend into Sodom without the Father's will; nor did He rain from Himself, but from the Lord, that is, by the authority of the Father; nor does He sit at the right hand by Himself, but hears the Father saying, "Sit at my right hand" (Psalm 109:1).
If anyone says that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are one person, let them be cursed.
If anyone says that the Holy Spirit, the Paraclete, is the unbegotten God, let them be cursed.
If anyone, as the Lord taught us, does not call the Paraclete distinct from the Son, for He said, "And the Father will send you another Paraclete, whom I will ask" (John 14:16), let him be accursed.
If anyone says that the Holy Spirit is a part of the Father or the Son, let him be accursed.
If anyone says that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are three gods, let him be accursed.
If anyone interprets the words, "I am the first God, and I am the last God, and besides me there is no God" (Isaiah 44:6), as referring to the destruction of idols and those who are not gods, but also to the destruction of the only-begotten God before the ages in a Jewish manner, let him be accursed.
If anyone says that the Son was made by the will of God, like any other creature, let him be accursed.
If anyone says that the Son was born against the will of the Father, let him be accursed.
For the Father was not forced or driven by natural necessity to give birth to the Son against His will.
Instead, He willed, timelessly and without suffering, to show that the Son was begotten from Himself.
If anyone says that the Son is unbegotten and without beginning, as if speaking of two without beginning, two unbegotten, and two uncreated, making two gods, let him be accursed.
For the head, which is the beginning of all things, is the Son; but the head, which is the beginning of Christ, is God.
Thus, through the Son, we refer all things to the one who is the beginning of all things without beginning.
And again, confirming the understanding of Christianity, we say that if anyone does not call Christ God, the Son of God existing before the ages and ministering to the Father for the perfection of all things, but says that from the time He was born of Mary, He was named Christ and Son, and began to be God, let him be accursed.
The many deceits of Photinus are refuted.
The Son is neither different from the Father in substance nor in time.
The urgency and the occasion required those gathered to provide a more detailed and extensive explanation of the faith through various questions.
This necessity arose because many hidden traps were attempting to infiltrate the Catholic faith through the heresy revived by Photinus.
Thus, each aspect of the pure and untainted faith could counter each form of heretical and deceptive questioning, ensuring there would be as many affirmations of faith as there were instances of deceitful questioning.
Following that comprehensive and unequivocal explanation of the sacraments, the effort to explain the faith against heretics began here.
However, those who say: The Son is from nothing existing, or from another substance and not from God, and that there was a time or age when he was not: the holy and Catholic Church considers them to be outsiders.
What room is there for ambiguity here?
Or what is left from the conscience of sincere faith?
He is not from nothing existing, which means he has an existing origin.
He does not originate from any other substance except that which is of God, ensuring that nothing else can be born in him except all that is of God.
Since he exists from nothing, he does not derive his being from elsewhere.
He does not differ in time, making the Son timeless with the Father.
Therefore, all things between the unbegotten Father and the only begotten Son are inseparable.
Time does not distinguish them in any essence, because of the very same indifference of the one existing Father, from whom the birth is taken.
If anyone says that the Father and the Son are two gods: let him be anathema.
And if anyone, while saying there is one God, does not confess that Christ, the Son of God, existed before the ages and was obedient to the Father in the creation of all things: let him be anathema.
Just as they are one in name of essence, so they are one in kind of essence.
The religious profession of this very name provides us with complete understanding of these matters.
Since it is condemned to call the Father and the Son two gods, and it is also anathema to deny that the Son is God: the belief in different substances between the two is excluded when proclaiming two gods.
For there is no other essence besides that of God the Father, from which the Son of God, an eternal God, is born.
Since we must necessarily confess God the Father, and proclaim absolutely that Christ is the Son of God and God, and since the confession of two gods is irreligious: they cannot, according to the indifference of nature and the indistinguishable name, be anything but one in essence, whose name of essence cannot be anything but one.
If anyone dares to say that the unbegotten God, or a part of Him, was born of Mary: let him be anathema.
The Son and the Father are not one person.
Against those who assert that the Son did not exist before Mary except through predestination.
So that the name of the supposed essence in the Father and the Son, due to their dissimilar nature, would not provide an occasion for heretics to preach that the unbegotten God, or a part of Him, was born of Mary; a salvific definition of this pronouncement was made, so that whoever confesses this would be anathema.
For the religious unity of the name, constituted from the essence of an indifferent nature, does not take away the person of the begotten essence, so that the substance of the one and only God is understood through the union of the name: since the name of the essence of both, that is, one God, is proclaimed due to the indistinguishable substance of their undivided nature.
If anyone says that the Son exists according to foreknowledge and predestination before Mary, and not that He was born of the Father before all ages and that all things were made through Him: let him be anathema.
God, the Son of God for all of us, they claim, existed before being born in the body, but not by the essence of a subsisting nature; rather, according to foreknowledge and predestination.
Through the foreknowledge of the Father, who predestined Him to be born of a virgin, He was announced to us, rather than having existed before the ages in the substance of divine nature.
Everything He spoke through the prophets about the mysteries of His incarnation and passion was said by the Father about Him according to foreknowledge.
Therefore, this doctrine is condemned: that the only begotten Son of God, known to us, was born of the Father before the ages and created the ages along with all creatures, rather than being predestined to be born.
If anyone says that the substance of God can expand and contract, let them be cursed.
Expansion and contraction do not apply to God, nor is the Son an expansion of the divine substance.
Expansion and contraction are physical processes, but God, who is spirit and breathes where He wills, does not expand or contract through a change of substance.
Remaining free from the necessity of physical nature, He accomplishes what He wills, when He wills, and where He wills.
Therefore, it is blasphemous to attribute a change of substance to the freedom of such great power.
If anyone says that the Son makes the substance of God expand or calls the Son an expansion of His substance, let them be cursed.
The previous statement, even though it aimed to teach the immutability of God, prepared itself for the following heresy.
Some have dared to extend the innascible God through the expansion of substance to the holy Virgin, so that the extension of breadth, taking on a human nature, would be called the Son; and that the Son, born before the ages as perfect God, would later be born as man.
Therefore, the whole of this is condemned by the Catholic faith, in which the Father is said to be changeable, and the Son is denied to have been born.
If anyone says that the Son of God is merely a spoken or written word, let them be cursed.
Heretics proclaim the Son of God as just a word.
The Son from Mary is both God and man.
Heretics, as much as they can, diminish the Son of God, acknowledging Him merely as a spoken word from the mouth of the speaker, and as an immaterial sound of an unsubstantial voice.
As if the Son is to God the Father, as a word is to us through our natural ability to speak, which produces every word as a voice.
Therefore, all this deceit is condemned, which claims that the Word of God, which was in the beginning with God, is merely a spoken or written word.
If anyone says that the Son from Mary is only a man, let them be cursed.
We do not proclaim the Son of God from Mary unless we proclaim Him as both man and God.
But to prevent this proclamation of both God and man from becoming an occasion for deceit, it is immediately stated.
If anyone says that God and man born from Mary understands God as unbegotten, let them be cursed.
The Son is distinguished from the Father only by birth.
Taking on flesh, He was not changed.
The substance, name, and power are preserved.
For if anyone says that the Son of God from Mary is merely a man without God, they are condemned.
And the same judgment applies to anyone who says that God, who is in man, is unbegotten.
Not that the God who is in man is not God, but that the unbegotten God is denied, distinguishing the Father from the Son not by the name of nature, because there is no difference in substance, but by the authority of being unbegotten alone.
If anyone hears that the Word became flesh and thinks that the Word was transformed into flesh or says that the Word took on flesh by undergoing change, let them be cursed.
The deity did not suffer corruption when the Son of God was crucified.
The dignity of divinity is preserved, so that in the fact that the Word became flesh, while the Word became flesh, it did not lose what it was as the Word through the flesh, nor was it transformed into flesh to cease being the Word.
But the Word became flesh so that the flesh rather began to be what the Word was.
Otherwise, how does the flesh possess virtues in deeds, glory on the mountain, knowledge of human hearts, security in suffering, and life in death?
But God, who does not change, lost none of His good qualities when He became flesh.
If anyone, upon hearing that the only Son of God was crucified, says that His divinity underwent corruption, suffering, change, diminution, or destruction: let him be cursed.
What suffering and passion are.
That the Son was seen by the fathers.
It is absolutely clear why the Word, although it became flesh, was not turned into flesh.
While these kinds of sufferings affect the weakness of the flesh, God the Word made flesh could not be changed by suffering.
Suffering and changing are not the same: because suffering of any kind changes all flesh in perception, pain, and endurance.
However, the Word, which became flesh, although it submitted to suffering, was not changed by it.
For it could suffer, but it could not be susceptible to suffering: because susceptibility indicates a weak nature, while suffering is the endurance of things inflicted.
Since God is unchangeable, even though the Word became flesh, it had the capacity for suffering without the weakness of susceptibility.
Therefore, the nature remains unchangeable even in suffering, because it is born from the substance of an impassible essence indifferent to its author.
If anyone says, "Let us make man" Genesis 1:26, was not said by the Father to the Son, but by God to Himself: let him be cursed.
If anyone says that the Son was not seen by Abraham Genesis 17:1, but by the unbegotten God or part of Him: let him be cursed.
If anyone says that it was not the Son who wrestled with Jacob as a man Genesis 32:26, but the unbegotten God or part of Him: let him be cursed.
If anyone does not understand "The Lord rained down fire from the Lord" Genesis 19:24 as referring to the Son and the Father, but says that He rained down from Himself: let him be cursed.
For the Son, the Lord, rained down from the Father, the Lord.
Photini's Opinion.
Since Photinus, against whom the assembly had gathered, denied this, it had to be included in the faith: so that no one would dare to proclaim the Son of God only after being the son of the Virgin, and to attribute all the previous things, which belong to the Son of God, to the Fatherless God with the utmost heretical insanity; and while referring these things to the Father, deny the substance to the Son.
Since these have been resolved, they left us no need for interpretation.
If anyone calls the Lord and the Lord, Father and Son (because the Lord is from the Lord), two gods: let them be accursed.
For we do not equate or compare the Son to the Father, but understand Him as subordinate.
For He did not descend to Sodom without the Father's will; nor did He rain from Himself, but from the Lord, by the authority of the Father; nor does He sit at the right hand by Himself, but hears the Father saying, "Sit at my right hand" (Psalm 110:1).
This definition is freed from suspicion.
The Son, inasmuch as He cannot be equated with the Father, maintains the equality of nature.
Both the previous and subsequent points exclude any suspicion that might appear in these statements, so that the diversity of dissimilar deities is not preached in the Lord and the Lord.
And in that, He is not compared, because it is impious to call them two gods: but this does not mean that the Son is not compared or equated to the Father, so that He is not believed to be God Himself.
For since it is anathema to deny Christ as God, it cannot be considered profane to name two gods, lest Christ be preached as God; since by the property of natural essence, He is one God, because from the Fatherless God the Father, who is one God, the only begotten Son, God, is born, having His being as God from no other than from God: and by the indistinguishable essence of Him who is begotten from Him who begot, the one name of nature cannot be otherwise.
And indeed, in this context, the Son is not compared or equated with the Father, as He is subject through the obedience of submission.
While the Lord reigns from the Lord, it is so that He does not reign from Himself according to Photinus or Sabellius, but as the Lord from the Lord.
He sits at the right hand of God when it is said to Him to sit; He is sent, He receives, He obeys in all things the will of the One who sent Him.
But the submission of piety is not a diminution of essence, nor does the duty of religion make the nature degenerate: because through this, both the Father God is unbegotten, and the only-begotten Son of God is God, yet God is one.
The submission of the Son is taught alongside His dignity, as He is called by the very name "Son," which, although it belongs to the Father, is also naturally His own name. Having the name of the one whose Son He is, He is subject to the Father in both obedience and name; yet, the submission testifies to the property of a natural and undivided essence.
If anyone says that the Father and the Son are one person: let him be accursed. Fifty-two. The Father and the Son are not one person.
Absolute perversity has no need of contradicting itself: yet the foolish fury of some has burst forth to proclaim one person under two names.
If anyone calls the Holy Spirit the Paraclete and says that He is an unbegotten God: let him be accursed. Fifty-three. The Holy Spirit is not an unbegotten God. He is distinct from the Son.
The addition of the Paraclete makes the proclamation of the unbegotten God in Him subject to anathema. For it is most impious to call Him an unbegotten God who was sent for our consolation by the Son.
If anyone, as the Lord taught us, does not say that the Paraclete is different from the Son; for He said: And the Father will send you another Paraclete, whom I will ask: let him be accursed. Why He is said to be sent by the Father.
We remember that the Paraclete was sent by the Son, and this was explained at the beginning by faith itself. But because the Son frequently said that His works are the works of the Father through the power of an undivided nature, saying: I do the works of my Father.
John fourteen ten.
He will also send the Comforter, as He has frequently promised.
Sometimes, He mentioned He would send Him from the Father.
He often referred everything He did to the Father.
From this, heretics often claim that the Son is the Comforter.
However, by praying for another Comforter to be sent from the Father, He indicates a distinction between the one sent and the one who asks.
If anyone says that the Holy Spirit is a part of the Father or the Son, let them be cursed.
The Holy Spirit is not part of the Father or the Son.
The foolishness of heretical madness compelled this to be written, not out of question.
While the name of the Holy Spirit has its own significance, and the Holy Spirit, the Comforter, has His own substance, role, and order, the Father and the Son are preached as unchangeable everywhere.
How can it be asserted that the Holy Spirit is part of either the Father or the Son?
Because this kind of madness is often uttered by the impious, it had to be condemned by the saints.
If anyone says that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are three gods, let them be cursed.
The profession of two gods is irreligious, as we remember and preach that only one God is proclaimed everywhere.
How much more condemnable is the naming of three gods in the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit?
Because heretics say this, Catholics rightly condemn it.
If anyone interprets the statement, "I am the first God, and I am the last God, and besides me, there is no God" (Isaiah 44:6), as a denial of the only-begotten God before the ages, let them be cursed.
That statement, "there is no God besides me," does not deny that the Son is God.
With the multitude of gods condemned, and only one God proclaimed, the Son of God cannot be denied as God.
The genuine property of nature ensures that the name, which is denied in number, is due to the essence; and the statement, "there is no God besides me," cannot take away from the Son what He is, because there is no other God except the one who is from God.
Through the voice of God the Father, it is clear that He who is born from Himself, with an essence identical to His nature, is indeed God.
This is why the Jews refer to their union with God, as they do not recognize the only-begotten God.
However, we, while denying the existence of two gods, reject any difference in the natural essence of the Father and the Son.
What is not God beside me dispels the false belief in other gods.
While confessing one God, we also declare the Son to be God, affirming that there is no difference in substance between them under one name.
If anyone says that the Son was made as one from creation by the will of God, let him be accursed.
The Son originates from the substance of God, not like creatures that are made by His will.
God's will brought substance to all creatures, but to the Son, He gave nature from His impassible and unbegotten substance through perfect nativity.
All things were created according to God's will: but the Son, born from God, retained the same nature as God.
His nature did not produce a dissimilar nature; born from the substance of God, He inherited the nature of His origin, not merely the essence of will like creatures.
If anyone says that the Son was born against the will of the Father, let him be accursed.
The Father was not forced by unwillingness or driven by natural necessity to beget the Son when He did not want to; rather, He desired, without hesitation and impassibly, to reveal Him as His only-begotten.
However, the Son is not from an unwilling Father.
Since it was taught that the Son's existence was not a result of mere will, like everything else, to avoid the notion that His essence depended solely on will and not also on nature, heretics might claim that God the Father was compelled by a natural law to beget the Son unwillingly.
But this is not the case with God the Father: in the indescribable and perfect nativity of the Son, neither will alone begot the Son, nor was the essence of natural law altered or compelled by command.
No material was sought for creation, nor is the begetter's nature different in the begotten, nor is the father's name isolated in time.
Before all times, the Father, from His own essence, willingly and without suffering, gave natural birth to the Son.
If anyone says the Son is unbegotten and without beginning, implying there are two without beginning, two unbegotten, and two gods, let them be anathema.
The head, which is the beginning of all, is the Son, and the head of Christ is God; thus, we refer everything to one unbegotten, the beginning of all, through the Son.
The unity of God does not allow for an unbegotten Son.
To confess an unbegotten Son is impious.
There cannot be one God if there are two unbegotten beings, as the nature of one unbegotten God demands the proclamation of one God.
Since there is one God, two unbegotten beings cannot exist.
The Father is God, and the Son of God is also God because unbegottenness belongs to one alone.
The Son is God because He is born from the unbegotten essence.
Therefore, holy faith rejects the notion of an unbegotten Son, proclaiming one God through one unbegotten nature.
The head of all is the Son, but the head of the Son is God.
Everything is referred to one God, as all things take their beginning from Him, who is the beginning, namely, God the Father.
Confirming the misunderstanding of Christianity, we say: If anyone does not affirm that Christ God, the Son of God, existed before ages and ministered to the Father for the perfection of all things, but instead claims that He was named Christ and Son only after being born of Mary, let them be anathema.
The heresy of Photinus and the main point of our faith.
The condemnation of his heresy, which led to the assembly, had to conclude with the exposition of the entire faith it opposed, which falsely claimed that the beginning of the Son of God was from the birth of the Virgin.
The principal tenet of our faith, according to the teachings of the Gospels and the Apostles, is that our Lord Jesus Christ, God and the Son of God, is not separated from the Father by any distinction of honor, power, virtue, substance, or time.
The truth has been sought through the counsel and judgments of the bishops, and understanding has been explained through various professions of written faith, extinguishing impious preaching.
The infinite and immense God cannot be fully understood or conveyed by brief human expressions.
Brief words often deceive both listeners and teachers; summaries can lead to misunderstandings or distortions, lacking complete reasoning.
Therefore, the bishops, with their understanding, used many definitions and more abundant words to teach, due to the complexity of natural understanding.
They did this to enrich the listeners' understanding with the distinctions of many truths, ensuring nothing dangerous or obscure was spoken about divine matters in this multifaceted resolution of opinions.
Beloved Brothers, do not be surprised that faith has begun to be explained so frequently: this necessity is due to the fury of heresy.
The danger to the Eastern Churches is so great that it is rare to find priests or people of this faith.
Some have given authority to impiety, and the exile of bishops has strengthened the profane.
I am not speaking of foreign matters, nor am I writing about unknown things: I have heard and seen the faults of those present, not of laymen, but of bishops.
Without Bishop Eleusius and a few others like him, the majority of the ten provinces of Asia, where I live, truly do not know God.
I almost wish they were entirely ignorant, because it would be easier to forgive them for their ignorance than for their slander.
The grief of these bishops, unable to remain silent, seeks the unity of a faith that was lost long ago through the actions of others.
The faith given in the first exposition was necessary because at Sirmium, through Hosius, who had forgotten his deeds and words, a new and long-festering doctrine of impiety had emerged.
However, I say nothing about him, as it was left to human judgment to remember how he had lived before.
Everywhere there are scandals, schisms, and betrayals.
As a result, some who had previously written otherwise were compelled to subscribe to a new profession of faith.
I do not criticize the most patient men, the Eastern bishops, who were at least satisfied with the profession of faith after the will of blasphemy.
It seems a cause for rejoicing that, amid the heretical obstinacy of so many blaspheming bishops, someone among them is received as repentant.
But amidst all this, oh blessed and glorious are you in the Lord.
By the profession of conscience, you retain the perfect and apostolic faith, not knowing the written creeds until now!
You did not need the letter, as you abounded in the spirit.
You did not desire the office of writing, since what you believed in your heart, you professed with your mouth for salvation.
You did not need to read what the bishop wrote, as you held it as newly baptized initiates.
Necessity has brought about the custom for faith to be expounded and for expositions to be subscribed to.
Where the sense of conscience is endangered, the letter is required.
It is not prevented to write what is beneficial to confess.
Hilary's faith concerning the Father and the Son.
We indeed confess in the gift of the Holy Spirit always innocently, and we willingly write, not two gods, but one God: nor thereby excluding the Son of God; for He is God from God.
There are not two unbegotten beings, because by the authority of being unbegotten, God is one.
This does not mean that the Only Begotten is not God; for His origin is from the unbegotten substance.
They are not separate beings, but one substance that is not different.
There is not one name of God in different natures, but the undissimilar essence of one name and nature.
It's not about someone being superior in substance, but about one being born from the other.
The Father is greater because He is the Father; the Son is not lesser because He is the Son.
The meaning is different, but the nature is the same.
The Father is eternal, and the Son is not denied to be co-eternal with the Father.
The Father is revealed in the Son, because the Son has nothing different from the Father.
The Son is revealed in the Father, because what the Son is, comes from the Father.
They acknowledge their mutual and similar nature because they are equal.
They do not think one is alone, because they are one.
They proclaim their unity through their undissimilar nature, so that one is not alone.
I have explained, dear friends, as much as human language allows, and the Lord, as He knows, has always granted me understanding of the common faith when I prayed to Him.
And if anything is lacking, remember that it is not my understanding that falls short, but the words.
Perhaps I may find fault with my nature in this, but not with my will.
I forgive my nature if it cannot speak about God as it wishes, because belief in what pertains to God is sufficient for salvation.
Now, since our faith, as far as I know, has not been in danger with God for 500 years, and I have shown you, as you requested, the faith expressed by the Eastern bishops, I will summarize briefly.
According to the number of Eastern Churches, this reflects the faith of a few bishops.
I also shared my thoughts on divine matters based on apostolic teaching.
It is now up to you to understand, without suspicion, the errors that arise from the simplicity of security, as there is no longer any reason to listen.
Although I no longer fear judgment based on the exposition of the entire faith, still, allow me to desire to be judged about myself until everything is resolved.
When 'homoousion' is rightly preached, many of us, dear brothers, proclaim the one substance of the Father and the Son in such a way that it might seem they are doing so impiously rather than piously.
This term encompasses both the conscience of faith and hidden deceit.
For if, according to the property and likeness of nature, likeness does not bring only the form but also holds the kind, we piously preach the one substance as long as we understand it to mean the likeness of property, so that what is one does not signify singularity but equality.
By equality, I mean the indifference of likeness, so that likeness is regarded as equality, and equality is called one because it is equal.
One, where equality is signified, is not claimed as unique.
Therefore, one substance, if it does not destroy the subsisting person nor divide the one substance into two, will be piously preached.
From the property of birth and the likeness of nature, it is so indifferent that it is called one.
But truly, if the Father and the Son are said to be of one substance, meaning they are one and the same under different names, then we do not truly acknowledge the Son by name.
If we confess one substance but say that the same unique being is both the Father and the Son, we miss the point.
Moreover, this confusion arises because it might seem that the Father is divided from himself, creating a part that becomes the Son.
Heretics, proclaiming one substance, assert this idea, and our pious language can unintentionally support their error.
Because this term is vague, it can lead to misunderstanding.
There is a third error: when we say the Father and the Son are of one substance, it can be misunderstood to mean a prior substance that both share equally.
This interpretation implies three entities: one substance and two co-heirs of that substance.
Just as two heirs share an inheritance, the two could seem like partners of a prior single substance.
So, when we proclaim the one substance of the Father and the Son, it could either mean one being with two names, or a divided substance creating two incomplete beings, or a third prior substance that the two have taken on, splitting one into two.
But where, then, is the concept of birth?
How do we understand the Father and the Son if they are seen more as a division or sharing of a prior substance rather than a natural birth?
In these many and serious dangers to faith, we must use precise language.
Otherwise, what is meant piously might be interpreted impiously, and a well-meaning statement could become heretical.
A Catholic should not start by saying the one substance of the Father and the Son, nor should they consider this the most important point, as if true faith depends solely on it.
He confidently asserts one substance, even though he previously said, "The Father is unbegotten; the Son is born, existing from the Father, similar to the Father in power, honor, and nature."
He is subject to the Father as his author: he did not consider equality with God something to be grasped, but remained in God's form and was obedient unto death.
He is not from nothing, but is born. He is not unbegotten, but coeternal. He is not the Father, but the Son from Him.
He is not a part, but whole. He is not the author himself, but the image: the image of God born from God into God.
He is not a creature, but is God. Not another God in type of substance, but one God through the essence of identical substance.
God is not one person, but one nature: because the born and the begetter have nothing diverse or unlike in them.
And after this, by saying the one substance of the Father and the Son, he does not err: but by denying one substance, he sins.
Therefore, let no one think that the one substance is denied by us: whose reason is therefore shown, lest it be denied.
Let no one think the one substance should be preached in a short and bare manner: so it may be religiously said to be one substance.
For I do not hear, Christ was born of Mary 502 years ago; unless I also hear, "In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God" (John 1:1).
I do not hear, Christ was hungry; unless after forty days of fasting I hear, "Man does not live by bread alone" (Matthew 4:4).
I do not hear, Christ was thirsty; unless I hear, "Whoever drinks of the water that I shall give him will never thirst" (John 4:13).
I do not hear, Christ suffered; unless I hear, "The hour has come for the Son of Man to be glorified" (John 12:23).
I do not hear, he died; unless I hear, he rose again.
Let us not bring forth anything isolated from the divine sacraments to the suspicion of listeners and to the occasion of blasphemers.
Before the birth of the Son, before subjection, before the similarity of nature is to be preached: so it is not impiously preached that the Father and the Son are of one substance.
I do not understand why it should be preached above all else as the greatest and most important thing, which cannot be preached piously above all else, and must necessarily be denied impiously afterwards.
It can be said piously, and it can be kept silent piously.
It is not, Dearest Brothers, to be denied that the Father and the Son are of one substance, but neither should it be preached irrationally.
Let there be one substance from the property of the begotten nature; let it not be from a portion, or from a union, or from a sharing.
One substance can be said piously, and kept silent piously.
You have the birth, you have the likeness.
Why do we hold the word's meaning suspiciously, without differing in the understanding of the matter?
Let us believe, and say that there is one substance; but by the property's nature, not to signify an impious union.
Let it be one from likeness, not from solitude.
Perhaps likeness seems to have little propriety in itself.
If this is the case, I ask how can I equate one to another except through likeness?
Or is it not the same to be similar as to be equal?
If I say one, it also has the suspicion of uniqueness: if I say similar, it has the comparison of indistinguishability.
Between similar and one, I seek what place equal has: and I ask whether it is rather a matter of likeness or solitude.
There is no equality in dissimilar things, nor is there likeness within one.
Or how do similar and equal differ, so that equal is again distinguished from one?
Therefore, equals are not dissimilar: and what else can be similar except equal, since there is no equality in dissimilar things?
Likeness of nature signifies perfect equality.
What likeness is to Moses, equality is to John.
Therefore, Dearest Brothers, preaching that the Son is similar in all things to the Father, we preach nothing else but equal.
Likeness signifies perfect equality: and this must be understood from the holy Scriptures.
We read that Adam lived for 230 years and fathered a son in his own likeness, after his image, and named him Seth Genesis 5:3.
I ask, what kind of likeness and image did Adam produce in Seth?
Remove the weaknesses of bodies, the beginning of conception, the pains of childbirth, and all human necessities.
I ask whether this likeness in Seth differs by nature from the creator or if it was the essence of another kind, making Seth's essence different from Adam's.
But it is Adam's likeness, even if we deny it, because it is not a dissimilar nature.
The likeness of nature in Seth was not of another kind, because Seth was born from Adam.
Thus, likeness equates the actual things naturally, through the likeness of an indistinguishable essence.
Therefore, every son, according to natural birth, is the equality of the father because he is also the likeness of nature.
Blessed John teaches about the nature of the Father and the Son, as Moses speaks of the likeness of Seth and Adam.
This same equality of nature is stated when he says: For this reason, the Jews sought all the more to kill him, because he not only broke the Sabbath but also said that God was his Father, making himself equal to God John 5:18.
Why do we insert sluggish minds, burdened with serious sins, and dull and rash senses against indissoluble teachings, into the doctrines and sayings of such great men, and tire the impious?
Through Moses, Seth is the likeness of Adam.
Through John, the Son is equal to the Father.
We seek a third entity, I don't know what, between the Father and the Son, which nature does not accept.
He is like the Father; he is the son of the Father; he was born from him.
Only by this can it be piously proclaimed that they are one.
Confessing likeness without equality is refuted.
Nor does it escape me, dearest brothers, that some, while confessing likeness, deny equality.
But let them speak as they wish and inject the poison of their blasphemy into the ignorant.
If they say there is a difference between similarity and equality, I ask from where equality is compared.
If the Son is similar to the Father in essence, power, glory, and time, how does he not appear equal?
This is also established in the previous faith as a condemnation: that it would be anathema to say the Father is of a different essence from himself.
Therefore, if he did not give a nature different or dissimilar to the one he begot impassibly, he could only have given his own.
Thus, similarity is a property; property is equality, and equality does not differ.
And things that do not differ are one; not by union of person, but by equality of nature.
The same power of the Son and the Father.
Although it is understood by common sense and divine authorities that there is no difference between similarity and equality, since according to Moses and John, the Son is both similar to and equal to the Father, let us see whether the Lord taught that he is equal to God when the Jews were angry that he equated himself with God by calling God his Father.
For he says, "The Son can do nothing by himself, but only what he sees the Father doing" John 5:19.
He distinguished the author when he said, "The Son can do nothing by himself," indicating obedience when he adds, "but only what he sees the Father doing."
It is not a difference in power to say he cannot do it unless he sees it; because power comes more from nature than from sight.
But it is obedience to be able when he sees.
Therefore, by saying he can do it when he sees, he implies that he does not derive power from sight but presumes authority from the vision.
Thus, the power of nature does not differ in the Father and the Son: for the ability to do what the Father can do does not come from any increase in nature, but from the example of the author.
Finally, the honor preserved by subjection is equated by the power of nature.
For he subjected himself: "For whatever he does, the Son does likewise"
Is similarity not equal?
It is clearly equal even if we deny it: for he does the same things similarly.
Are things done similarly not the same?
Do they not receive equality in the same way?
Or is there some other difference between similar and equal things, when those that are made similarly are understood to be made the same?
Unless perhaps someone will deny that equal things are the same, so that similar things are not said to be equal.
When things that are made similarly are not only said to be equal but also to be the same.
It can rightly be said to be Homoeusion.
Therefore, brothers, the similarity of nature is free from any suspicion of insult, nor can the Son be seen as not being part of the Father's nature because He is similar.
Since similarity can only exist from the equality of nature, and the equality of nature cannot exist unless it is one; one not by unity of person, but by unity of kind.
This is pious faith, this is a religious conscience, this is a saving word, not to deny the one substance of the Father and the Son because it is similar, but to proclaim it similar because they are one.
Dearest ones, having explained with faithful and pious understanding the one substance, which in Greek is called "homoousion", and the similar substance, which is called "homoeusion", and having demonstrated in the most complete manner the vices that may arise from the brevity of words or dangerous nudity, my remaining speech must be directed to the holy men, the Eastern bishops. Since there is now no suspicion left among us about our faith, those things which still come into suspicion from words may be cleared up. They will forgive me for speaking more freely with them from the faith of our common conscience.
O men studious of apostolic and evangelical doctrine, whom the fervor of faith has ignited in the great darkness of heretical night! How much hope you have brought for the restoration of true faith by steadfastly repelling the bold attack of perfidy! For previously, in obscurity and in corners, the Lord Christ was denied to be the Son of God according to nature. It was preached that, lacking the essence of the Father, He had originated with creatures from non-existence.
But now, with the public endorsement of authority, heresy boldly emerges, proclaiming openly what it once whispered in secret.
In the year five hundred and six, by what hidden means had it not tried to infiltrate the Catholic Church?
What powers of the world had it not flaunted with the allure of a false religion?
Wicked people had gone so far that, while they did not dare to preach this openly themselves, they deceived the Emperor into listening.
They misled the ignorant king, so that, preoccupied with wars, he would endorse such treachery and impose a form of belief on the Churches without being regenerated.
They forced opposing bishops into exile.
Indeed, they compelled us to choose exile while imposing the necessity of impiety.
But let us always be exiled, as long as the truth begins to be preached.
Thanks be to the Lord, for the Emperor, having been warned through you, recognized his ignorance, and acknowledged the error not as his own, but as that of his advisors.
Through the declarations of your faith, he realized the falsehood and freed himself from the disgrace of impious intent before God and men.
He honored your delegation and, through their forced admission of his ignorance, recognized the deceit of those whose authority had led him into disgrace.
Christ is one, not two.
The subscription of Valens and Ursacius is suspect.
Indeed, they deceive, as I fear and it seems to me, beloved brothers, they deceive; because they have always deceived: and even this present subscription is not free from falsehood.
They excuse themselves, claiming they wanted to keep silent about "homoousion" and "homoiousion" because they believed both terms signified the same thing.
I believe they were naive bishops, ignorant of the meaning of "homoousion," as if there had never been a synod or disputes about this.
But let it be that they were ignorant of "homoousion," or did not know that "homoiousion" signified the same essence. If they did not know this, why did they want the generation of the Son to be unknown? Is it not the case that if something is indescribable, it must also be unknowable?
But if it is unknown how he was born, can it be unknown that the Son of God, born not from another substance, but from God, does not have a different essence?
Have they not read, "As the Father, so must the Son be honored" (John 5:25), so that they would honor the Father more?
Did they not know that the Father is seen in the Son (John 14:9), so that the Son differs from them in dignity, brightness, and majesty?
Or does this come from ignorance, that the Son is subject to the Father along with others, so that he is not distinguished from others?
The submission of the Son is due to his nature and devotion, but the submission of others is due to the weakness of creation.
They knew he suffered, but I ask when they knew he suffered together with someone else.
They avoid the terms "homoousion" and "homoiousion" because they are written nowhere.
I ask, where did they presume he suffered together with someone else?
Or do they want there to be two who suffered?
For that is what suffering together implies.
Where is that Jesus Christ the Son of God?
Or is Jesus Christ one, and the Son of God another?
If he is not the same and one both inside and outside as the Son of God, believe in the ignorance of "homoousion", if these things can be ignored.
But if in these very matters that ignorance itself is impious, which cannot be excused even falsely, I fear that the profession of "homoiousion" might lie about ignorance.
I do not complain much about the pardon you granted; it is religious to reserve to God what is his, and human error is ignorance.
But let Valens and Ursacius, the two bishops, forgive me, as I do not believe that they were ignorant due to their age and experience.
And it is very difficult not to think them liars, who cannot be excused in another matter except by lying.
But may the Lord grant this more, that we are mistaken, rather than that they were not ignorant.
For I prefer to be judged as thinking wrongly, than to have your faith violated by the communion of heretical conscience.
But I pray you, most holy men, to consider my concerns with good will.
For the Lord is a witness to my conscience, that in no way do I wish to overturn these explanations of faith which you brought from Sirmium.
But please forgive me if I don't understand some things, and I will console myself because I read: "The spirits of prophets are subject to prophets" (First Corinthians 14:32).
From this, perhaps it is not impertinent for me to presume that I too can understand something that another may not.
Not that I would dare to say you are ignorant of anything according to the measure of knowledge, but on the unity of the Catholic faith, allow that we are no less concerned than you are.
The letter brought to Sirmium regarding the explanation of homoousios and homoiousios.
Homoousios is wrongly rejected due to birth.
I understand the letter that Valens, Ursacius, and Germinius requested from you regarding the explanation of homoousios and homoiousios at Sirmium to be cautious in some respects and free in others in no less than 509 places.
The explanation itself of homoousios and homoiousios left no difficulty.
And indeed, the common judgment is that homoiousios, which means similar essence, is acceptable.
But regarding homoousios, which means of one essence, you first declared it should be rejected because the substance of the word would first be understood as prior to the two being distinguished from each other.
I understand the flaw in this reasoning.
This is a profane interpretation and should be rejected by the Church according to common judgment.
Secondly, you also added that our fathers, when Paul of Samosata was declared a heretic, also rejected homoousios because by this term of one essence, he preached that the Father and the Son were solitary and unique to himself.
And indeed, the Church now also rightly recognizes this as extremely profane, to refer to the Father and the Son in these terms of union and unique solitude, denying the distinct properties of persons.
Thirdly, you also mentioned this reason for rejecting homoousios: that at the council held at Nicaea, our fathers were compelled because of those who said the Son was a creature to introduce the term homoousios, which should not be accepted because it is not found anywhere in Scripture.
I am quite surprised by what you said.
If the term "homoousion" should be rejected because it is new, I fear that "homoiousion" might also be at risk, since it is not found in the scriptures.
In what sense it may be condemned by common judgment, I do not argue. I prefer to mention something new rather than reject it impiously.
Therefore, setting aside the question of novelty, the issue does not lie in those things which are condemned by the common judgment of all of us. For who in their right mind would proclaim a third substance common to both the Father and the Son? Or who, according to the Samosatian, being reborn in Christ and confessing the Son and the Father, would claim that Christ is both Father and Son?
So, our opinion is the same in condemning the heretics' impieties: it not only rejects but also hates this understanding of "homoousion." Thus, there is no issue of misunderstanding where there is a common agreement in condemning the error.
What was piously accepted by the Nicene Synod should not be disapproved. When I finally speak about the third question, I ask that where there is peace of conscience, let there be no battle of suspicions. Do not think that I bring up anything except for the advancement of unity.
It is pointless to fear the reproach of a word where the matter itself, which the word signifies, has no difficulty. Does anyone dislike that "homoousion" was accepted in the Nicene Synod? If anyone dislikes this, then it must please them that it was denied by the Arians. "Homoousion" was denied to prevent the proclamation that God the Son was born from the substance of God the Father, rather than created out of nothing like the creatures.
We speak nothing new; the very deceit of the Arians, documented in many writings, bears witness to itself. If the pious understanding of the confessors was justified by the impiety of the deniers, I ask why today it is being overturned, what was then piously accepted because it was impiously denied? If it was piously accepted, why is the establishment of piety brought into disrepute, which piously extinguished impiety through the very things by which it was impiously denied?
So, let's understand what the Council of Nicaea aimed for by confessing "homoousion," meaning "of one substance": certainly not to create a heresy from a mistaken understanding of "homoousion."
They did not mean that the Father and the Son divided one prior substance into their own substances. The faith that was written down religiously at that time is what we now also include in our discussion without irreverence.
We believe in one God, the Father Almighty, maker of all things visible and invisible.
And in one Lord Jesus Christ, the Son of God, born from the Father, the only begotten, that is, from the substance of the Father, God from God, light from light, true God from true God, born not made, of one substance with the Father, which in Greek they call "homoousion," through whom all things were made, both in heaven and on earth, who for our salvation came down, was incarnate, became man, suffered, rose again on the third day, ascended into heaven, and is coming to judge the living and the dead.
And in the Holy Spirit.
Those who say, "There was a time when he was not," and "Before he was born, he was not," and "He was made out of nothing," or "He is from another substance or essence," and believe that God is changeable and alterable: the Catholic Church condemns them.
This most holy synod of religious men does not introduce some prior substance divided into two but asserts the Son is born from the substance of the Father.
Do we deny this? Or do we confess something else?
And after explaining the other points of common faith, it says, "Born not made, of one substance with the Father," which in Greek they call "homoousion."
What is the reason for misunderstanding here? It is proclaimed that the Son is born from the substance of the Father, not made, to avoid interpreting the birth of divinity as an act of creation.
Therefore, "of one substance," not to imply that only one exists or subsists, but to show that he, born from the substance of God, does not subsist from elsewhere, nor does he subsist in any diversity of dissident substance.
Isn’t this our faith, that it stands on its own and not from somewhere else, and that it stands undivided?
Doesn't the term homousion testify to the fact that the essence of the Father and the Son is one and the same, because the essence of the Son is not from somewhere else?
Since it is not from somewhere else, both are rightly believed to be of one essence, because the Son has no substance of origin except from the authority of the Father's nature.
Should we reject homousion because it is often misunderstood?
But perhaps it will be argued conversely that we should reject it because it is often misunderstood.
If we fear this, then let us erase what is said in the Apostle:
"The mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus."
Because Photinus uses this to support his heresy: and let us not read it because he misunderstands it.
Let the letter to the Philippians also perish, either by fire or sponge, lest Marcion interpret it:
"And being found in appearance as a man,"
Confessing a phantom body, not a real body.
Let the Gospel of John not exist, lest Sabellius learn:
"I and the Father are one."
Nor should those who now preach about creation have written:
"The Father is greater than I."
Nor should those who wish to affirm that the Son is unlike the Father read:
"But of that day and hour no one knows, not even the angels in heaven, nor the Son, but only the Father."
There should also be no books of Moses, lest the darkness be coequal to God, who dwells in unapproachable light, because in Genesis
Day began after night, lest the years of Methuselah exceed the age of the flood
And not only eight souls be saved
Lest God, hearing the outcry of the Sodomites, already filled with sin, descend as if not knowing the outcry, to see if the sins are as great as the outcry, and it be found that God does not know what He knew
Lest anyone also knows the grave of Moses who buried him
Lest by these things, as heretics think, the law itself be at odds with itself. And because these things are not understood by them, let them not be read by us.
Let them perish also, if it seems so (though I am not saying this, but it is a necessity of the response), all those divine and holy Gospels of human salvation:
Lest they contradict each other in the opinion of the statements:
Lest the Lord, who is to send the Holy Spirit, be read as born of the Holy Spirit himself:
Lest he who is to announce death by the sword indicates that a sword should be bought Matthew 26:52:
Lest he who is to descend to the underworld be in paradise with the thief Luke 23:43:
Lest finally the apostles be found guilty, who were commanded to baptize in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit Matthew 28:19, but baptized only in the name of Jesus Acts 10:48.
For you, Brothers, I say this aloud, who are no longer nourished with milk, but are strong with solid food Hebrews 5:12:
Shall we become wise with the world because the wise do not understand these things and consider them foolish, so that we believe these foolish things?
And because these things are blind to the impious, shall we not shine with the understood truth of doctrine?
Holy things are judged wrongly if, because they are not held holy by some, they should not exist.
Therefore, let us not boast in the cross of Christ, because it is a scandal to the world: nor preach death in the living God, lest God be deemed dead by the impious.
Because it was rejected by 80 bishops.
The term "homoousion" is misunderstood: what does that matter to me who understands it well?
The term "homoousion" was confessed poorly by Samosatenus: but did Arius deny it better?
Eighty bishops once rejected it; but three hundred and eighteen recently accepted it.
To me, indeed, that number is sacred, in which Abraham, the victor over the impious kings Genesis 14:14, is blessed by him who is the model of eternal priesthood.
Those bishops condemned the heretic: but did not these also approve against the heretic?
The authority of the ancients is weighty: but is the sanctity of these light?
If they perceived contrary things, we ought, as judges, to approve the better: but if by approving and disapproving they established the same thing, why do we overturn what was well established?
Did Hosius, who was present at Nicaea, decide that this should be kept silent?
But perhaps someone will say to me,
"Some of those who were present at the synod back then decided that the term homoousion should be kept silent."
And I, though unwilling, will respond to the one saying this:
"Didn't they also decide that the term homoiousion should be kept silent?"
I beg you, let no one besides the old man Hosius, who is overly fond of his own grave, think that both terms should be kept silent.
And where will we end up in such a frenzy of heretics if, while we do not accept either term, we retain neither?
For it cannot be seen as blasphemous to say that if neither term is found written, then neither should be confessed, or both should be.
What Hilary understands by homoousion. Concerns about homoousion are raised.
Homoousion, most holy men, I understand as God from God, not of dissimilar essence, not divided, but born, and a natural generation from the substance of the unbegotten God in the Son, according to the likeness, the only-begotten generation.
This understanding of homoousion has greatly confirmed me.
Why do you condemn my faith in homoousion, which you cannot but approve through the profession of homoiousion?
For you condemn my faith, or rather yours, when you condemn the understanding of it in the name.
But does someone else understand it wrongly? Let us jointly condemn the faulty understanding, not remove the security of faith.
Do you think we should subscribe to the Synod of Samosata, so that no one may usurp the term homoousion according to the understanding of Samosata?
Let us also subscribe to the Synod of Nicaea, so that the Arians do not reject homoousion.
But should we fear that homoousion may not signify homoiousion according to faith?
Let it be decreed that there is no difference, that they are of one and the same substance.
But can homoousion be understood wrongly? Let it be established how it can be understood correctly.
We piously think the same; I ask that we wish that what we piously think be among us.
Forgive me, Brothers, as I frequently ask: you are not Arians; why are you considered Arians by denying homoiousion?
But you say: The ambiguity of homoousios disturbs me with scandal.
Again, listen, I beg, without scandal: and the nakedness of homoousios disturbs me.
Many things often deceive that are similar.
I fear gold leaf because it might deceive me: and yet what appears is similar to gold.
I fear the similarity of milk, lest the milk offered to me is not sheep’s milk: because it might appear similar to cow’s milk.
For sheep’s milk to be truly similar to sheep’s milk, it cannot be similar unless it is from a sheep.
True similarity is in the truth of nature.
However, truth in both natures does not deny homoousion.
For this is according to the essence of similarity: if a mass similar to a mass does not deceive in the leaf, if milk that is of the same color is not different in taste.
Nothing can be similar to gold, unless it is gold: nothing can be similar to milk, unless it is of its own kind.
The color of wine has often deceived me: and yet, by taste, I recognized a liquid of another kind.
I have seen meats similar to meats: but later taste revealed the dissimilarity of nature to me.
For I fear these similarities that are not from the unity of nature.
For I fear, Brothers, the heresies of the East sprouting up at each moment: and what I say I fear now, I have also read.
Indeed, nothing in those things which you, ministers of the assumed delegation, brought to be subscribed at Sirmium by the assent of some Easterners, nothing of suspicion was left: but they had from the beginning not a small amount of offense, which I believe you, most holy men Basil, Eustathius, and Eleusius, have silently abolished so as not to bring any scandal.
If what was written was correct, it should not have been silenced.
But if it is now being silenced because it was not written correctly, care must be taken that it is not spoken of at some point.
Sparing these matters, I say nothing further: yet you and I recognize that all the faith written at Ancyra was not like this.
I do not speak of a tale of rumor: I hold the faith of letters, not taken from laypeople, but given by bishops.
I beg you, Brothers, remove suspicion and eliminate the opportunity.
To prove the homoousion, let us not disapprove of the homoousion.
Let's remember all the holy and resting priests.
What will the Lord think of us if we anathematize them now?
What will become of us if we bring the matter to the point where, because they were not bishops, we too have not even begun?
We were ordained by them, and we are their successors.
Let us renounce the episcopacy if we have taken its office from anathema.
Forgive me, Brothers, for my sorrow: what you dare to do is impious.
I cannot bear the statement that the homoousion is within anathema according to religious understanding.
The name itself has no crime and does not disturb the sense of religion.
I do not know the homoiousion, nor do I understand it, except from the confession of similar essence.
I call God of heaven and earth to witness that even when I had heard neither, I always felt that both should be understood through the homoousion and homoiousion.
That is, nothing could be similar to itself according to nature, except what was of the same nature.
Having been regenerated long ago and staying in the episcopacy for a while, I only heard the Nicene faith when I was about to be exiled.
But the Gospels and the Apostles have informed me of the understanding of homoousion and homoiousion.
What we desire is pious.
Let us not condemn the fathers nor encourage heretics.
Lest while we call it heresy, we nourish heresy.
Our fathers have interpreted the property of homoousion religiously after the Nicene synod.
Books exist, conscience remains.
If anything needs to be added to the interpretation, let us consult together.
The best state of faith can be established among us, so that neither well-established things are disturbed, nor poorly understood things are cut off.
I have, dear brothers, disregarded the shame of human conscience.
Forgetting my humility, I have written about these profound and hidden matters.
Compelled by my love for you, I felt it necessary to share them.
I have spoken what I believe, knowing that I owe this service to the Church's mission.
Through these letters, I aim to convey the voice of my episcopate in Christ, following the teachings of the Gospels.
It is your duty to discuss, provide for, and act together, so that you may preserve with a religious conscience the faith you have held inviolably until now, and continue to hold on to it.
Remember my exile in your holy prayers.
After sharing this faith, I do not know if it is more joyful to return to you in the Lord Jesus Christ, or safer to die.
May God and our Lord keep you untouched and unharmed until the day of revelation, dear brothers.
Defense to the Critics
Response to the Books About Synods
Section 1
In this section, although it caused some scandal, the Easterners resisted the Anomoeans.
If this statement had been carefully considered, perhaps my entire argument would not have seemed suspicious.
For I did not remain silent about what would be heard as scandalous.
Section 2
At the beginning of section thirteen, after the reading of the first decree of the Council of Ancyra, all the explanations given by the Council of Ancyra, described in this book, if they have any faults, those faults belong to them; otherwise, they are not considered to have faults in public opinion.
However, I knew they had only been reported to Sirmium.
Section 3
Section seventy-seven refers to the explanation of the term homoousion, meaning "of the same substance," with a faithful and pious understanding.
I don't think anyone needs reminding why I emphasized "piety" in relation to "similar substance." It’s because I understood both the impiety and the importance of saying not only "equal" but also "the same," so that the similarity you, Brother Lucifer, wanted to be preached would not be disapproved.
Nonetheless, I remind you that only the pious understanding of similarity, which proclaims the unity of substance, should be preached.
Section 4
In manuscripts, this section continues seamlessly from the previous one and pertains to section seventy-eight: Oh zealous men of apostolic and evangelical doctrine, how much hope have you brought for the revival of true faith?
But while praising them, I was misunderstood and criticized by some.
I did not say they brought the true faith, but the hope of reviving it, so that just as they were heard, we too might be heard against Valens and Ursacius, and our respectful address would avoid any insolent abuse.
As I continue, especially in section ninety-one, I reveal the hidden scandals of their expositions even more bitterly and reproachfully.
Section 5
But I pray, most holy men, that you consider my concerns with good grace.
Consider wisely what it means to ask the holiest of men to listen kindly to the speaker, and whether flattering and rebuking are the same.
This is mentioned because the envoys sent to Sirmium left some things unspoken, which I will reveal in sections ninety and ninety-one.
However, I did not want to seem like I was making false accusations in matters that could be defended as excusable.
Section six.
Regarding these matters in section eighty-seven:
And although unwilling, I will respond, etc.
It should be clear enough, Lord brother Lucifer, that I was reluctant to mention homoiousios.
But since you were proclaiming the likeness of the Son to the Father, I had to explain it without fault.
Section Seven.
This is followed by section eighty-eight:
You think we should subscribe to the Synod of Samosata.
Let us also subscribe to the Synod of Nicaea.
Didn't I, when discussing homoiousios, show that it should only be received by referring to the unity of substance?
Section Eight.
In the eyes of the critics, this is explained in section eighty-nine:
It troubles me (with scandal) the bareness of homoiousios, etc.
Could anyone think that I wanted to accept homoousion, about which I discussed these matters?
Section Nine.
Similar to this, after bringing examples of things that deceive with external similarity, did I neglect the similarity?
Section Ten.
This corresponds to section ninety:
For sparing them, I still say nothing about the decrees made at Ancyra with scandal.
Am I thought to remove suspicion from these matters or to praise those I spare?
To spare and to spare with delay is neither improper nor lenient.
Section Eleven.
In the manuscripts, the tenth continues into section ninety-one:
To prove that homoousion is not to be condemned; likewise in this same section:
It is impious what you dare, etc.
Do I here allow a similar substance to be anything but one?
If it is not to be confessed as one before, then later it will be impiously preached as similar.
Section Twelve.
After this is section ninety-one:
I do not know nor understand homoiousios, except only from the confession of similar essence, etc.
Do I seem to have been able to prove what I did not know (by accepting homoiousios for non-substantial similarity)?
Certainly not.
The Catholic faith emphasizes unity and similarity.
It mentions similarity to exclude division, not to break unity.
So, even though I wasn't familiar with the terms homoousios and homoiousios, I still accepted similarity through unity.
The next sentence immediately clarifies this.