Letter Nine, traditionally attributed to Jerome.
To Paula and Eustochium on the Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary.
You urge me, Paula and Eustochium, and indeed, the love of Christ compels me. I have long been accustomed to speaking to you through my writings, and now you ask me to address the holy virgins who live with you, using the Latin language, for their encouragement.
I shall speak about the Assumption of the blessed and glorious ever-Virgin Mary, in the style of those who traditionally give declamations in churches. This is a form of teaching I have not yet attempted.
But because I cannot refuse anything you request, and overcome by your immense affection, I will try to comply with your wishes, much like children eager to speak whatever they hear, even if they cannot fully form the words yet.
Especially since you compel me to do this for the sake of the simpler ones, so that your holy community may have a Latin sermon to occupy themselves with praises on that day, or to engage in divine readings.
This is particularly important since various holy fathers have written eloquently about many feasts, and their works on this subject are abundantly found in the divine scriptures.
For what else do the Gospels proclaim but the Lord being born of the Virgin Mary?
All his growth, until he was in the world, is celebrated with divine praises.
Moreover, from the beginning of the holy Gospel, you have learned of the Archangel Gabriel speaking to Mary, and you have read all the other events more fully.
At the manger, Paula, as you witnessed, when the child was born amid the cries of a new birth and the innocent wailing, instead of festive jesting, you heard "Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace to people of good will" (Luke 2:14).
You heard the multitude of angels singing and saw the shining star.
You believed in the shepherds' proclamation.
Furthermore, you saw in a vision the Magi bringing three gifts with your blessed eyes; you offered those same gifts to God with all your heart.
For you worshipped the God-child in the manger with the Magi.
But perhaps you will complain that I have revealed your secrets and cry out against me.
To which I respond: If you wanted this to remain hidden with only your conscience as the witness, you shouldn't have told me in front of the manger where you cried the most.
To be honest, I can't stay completely silent about the praises of Christ or your virtues, even if I wanted to.
Therefore, let your daughters, whom you nourish with milk, ask you; you will reveal it better than I can, whether you saw it through some vision or certainly in spirit.
So, daughters, beseech your mother with prayers, knock at the door of the inviting friend, so that perhaps what has been revealed to the mother may finally be opened to you.
But what more can I say about these things?
You have learned all the deeds of the Savior, the duties of the blessed Mary, and the acts of life from the Gospel.
And now, what remains for you to ask from any of the teachers?
About the Assumption of the Blessed Mother of God and ever-virgin Mary, how she was assumed, because you requested it in your prayer, I made sure to write to you. Although absent, I offered this devotion as if I were present, so that your holy College might have a gift of Latin speech on such a solemn day.
In this tender infancy, may you learn to experience the sweetness of milk and reflect on great things from small beginnings. With God's favor, may this whole day be spent in praise every year and celebrated with joy.
If the apocryphal book, "On the Passing of the Same Virgin," comes into your hands, be cautious. Many Latins, out of love for piety and eagerness for reading, embrace its doubtful contents as certain. Remember, the only thing we know for sure from these writings is that on this glorious day, she departed from her body.
Her tomb is still shown to us in the middle of the Valley of Josaphat, located between Mount Zion and the Mount of Olives. Paula, you have seen with your own eyes the church built in her honor with marvelous stonework. It is preached by all there that she was buried, but now the mausoleum appears empty to those who see it.
I mention this because many among us doubt whether she was assumed with her body or if she departed leaving her body behind. How, at what time, or by whom her most holy body was taken, or where it was moved, whether she was resurrected, remains unknown.
Some assert that she has already been resurrected and is clothed with blessed immortality with Christ in heaven. Many also claim this about the blessed John the Evangelist, her servant, to whom Christ entrusted the Virgin. In his tomb, it is said, nothing but manna is found, which appears to flow.
Nevertheless, we remain uncertain about what is truly believed in these matters.
However, it is better to entrust everything to God, for whom nothing is impossible, than to rashly define something on our own authority that we cannot prove: just as with those whom we believe to have risen with the Lord, as the Gospel testifies.
But whether they returned to the dust of the earth, we do not know for sure, except what we read:
Many bodies of the saints who had fallen asleep were raised and came out of the tombs after Jesus' resurrection, and went into the holy city, Jerusalem, and appeared to many.
As it is written in the Book of Matthew, chapter 27, verses 52 to 53.
Some learned scholars have indeed thought, and also left it written in their works, that the eternal resurrection was already completed in them.
For they confess that they would not be true witnesses unless their resurrection was also true.
Hence, it is recorded that Blessed Peter said, when speaking about David as a testimony: "His tomb is with us to this day" (Acts 2:29),
as if he did not dare to say that David himself or his body was with us, but only the tomb where he was buried.
Therefore, they say that he rose with the other saints, and thus his tomb remained empty, just as is seen with Blessed Mary's tomb.
They attempt to assert this fact from other places in Scripture as well: that these individuals, now resurrected, reign with Christ in eternal companionship.
Because nothing is impossible for God, we do not deny that this happened with Blessed Virgin Mary, although, out of caution (with faith intact),
it is better to hold this devout desire as an opinion rather than rashly define something that is not known without risk.
Let's briefly discuss what we're certain of, to encourage you in any way we can, for the building up and praise of God's name.
This is so that religion can be preserved through service, and devotion can grow through love.
This is the Virgin who alone destroyed all heretical wickedness.
After God, she alone strengthens us in all truth, commending us by her merits and helping us with her prayers, so we too may be found worthy of her praises.
After the Lord's ascension, one thing is certain: she remained a holy Virgin in both body and mind.
The angel Gabriel, like a heavenly guardian, faithfully protected her.
And John the apostle and evangelist, to whom Christ entrusted her from the cross, kept her as a virgin, serving her with his care.
This doesn't mean that the distinguished choir of saints and apostles abandoned her; she moved freely among them after the resurrection, sharing intimately about the Incarnation of Christ.
She learned everything more fully and clearly from the beginning through the Holy Spirit, and perceived everything with her own eyes.
Although the apostles also knew everything through the same Holy Spirit and were taught all truth, they all revered the blessed Virgin and served her with loving devotion.
However, John did so more fully and specifically until the end of his life, accepting her into his own home as a son would a mother.
The kind teacher from the cross said to her, "Woman, behold your son," and to the disciple, "Behold your mother" (John 19:26-27); so that the virgin would be closely united to the virgin and serve her most diligently through the care of adoption.
It's most appropriate for the most chaste virginity to be entrusted to a disciple who is also a virgin, ensuring a mutually pleasing companionship and a flourishing appearance, as well as a beautiful manner of living together, adorned alternately by the splendor of chastity.
Indeed, the virtue of virginity was in both, but in Mary, it was of a different proportion: different indeed, because it was more fruitful, but it was still the same.
She herself, but another: because although she herself is the same incorruption, the fruitfulness of integrity is far more glorious than virginity. Therefore, the fruitfulness in her is entirely divine and virginity. Otherwise, nowhere according to the nature of birth is there virginity, where fruitfulness is proclaimed, nor fruitfulness where virginity is kept intact.
And so everything surpasses what is said about her: because they are divine and ineffable. Hence, the virginity and the fruitfulness of offspring is a surpassing novelty, although it is seen that what is born is human from the flesh. Nevertheless, although virginity in Mary is much more magnificent because of the excellence of grace: there is one integrity of the flesh, and one virtue, which are joined together as if related.
From this, John also, whatever it is that Mary gave birth to; in his gospel, he commends it with his eloquence.
"In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God" (John 1:1).
Indeed, this Word which was in the beginning, and was with God, and was God, the blessed and glorious Virgin Mary gave birth to, having been made flesh from herself. Therefore, virginity is far more sacred, and the fruitfulness (so to speak) much more ineffable, than he could explain with his eloquence.
However, as much as virginity is more akin to virginity, so much is the blessed evangelist more excellent and closer to the Word than the others. Therefore, whatever it is that the Virgin gave birth to, he preserved for us as clearly as he could through the Holy Spirit and taught us.
As an example for human life, his interaction with the apostles after the ascension of Christ continued until they were dispersed. Luke mentions, "When they returned from the Mount of Olives, they came to Jerusalem and went up to the upper room where Peter, John, James, Andrew, Philip, Thomas, Bartholomew, Matthew, James the son of Alphaeus, Simon the Zealot, and Judas the son of James were staying. These all continued with one accord in prayer with the women and Mary, the mother of Jesus, and with His brothers" (Acts 1:12, 14). Behold, as Jesus ascended, the Virgin dedicated herself to the school of virtues and meditated on the law of God's commandments to be a model of Christ's discipline and an example of perfection for virgins. She interacted with the witnesses of the holy resurrection, being a witness herself. She conversed with the senators of heaven within the court of paradise under the discipline of the Holy Spirit and the guidance of divine majesty. Blessed Mary is found among the foremost ranks of the supreme king's cohorts, whose life was no longer of the earth but of heaven. They ascended to the upper room, where the Passover was most worthily celebrated. There, they stayed with Mary, the mother of Jesus, united in love, persevering in prayer until they were endowed with power from on high. They had already begun to pray, having lived with the Lord, nourished by virtues and miracles. They persevered in prayer, doubting nothing until they received the gifts of the Holy Spirit that they sought. And you, daughters, should imitate them. You who have vowed to remain in the school of Christ, persevere in prayers, living in harmony, until you can enter the joys of eternal life, where the blessed Virgin happily entered today, accompanied by the hymns of angelic choirs within the pastures of eternal greenness: where there is one society of heavenly citizens, where there is the sweet solemnity of angels, and where after labors and hardships, there is the happy and gentle refreshment of souls.
Today, the glorious and ever-Virgin Mary ascends to the heavens. Rejoice, for she is exalted beyond words and reigns with Christ forever.
The Queen of the world has been taken from the earth and this wicked age. Rejoice once again, for she has securely reached the heavenly palace in her unfading glory. Be glad, and let the whole world be joyful. For today, through her merits, salvation has increased for all of us.
To those who love her, honor and virtue, along with the other holy virgins, are granted more abundantly and with grace. Therefore, dearest ones, be joyful and praise. If we are commanded to praise God with prophetic voice in His saints, how much more should we extol Him in this celebration of the blessed Virgin Mary, His mother, with hymns and songs. Praise Him with worthy acclamations to God and honor her with mystical gifts.
There is no doubt that whatever is worthily offered and solemnly attributed to His mother pertains entirely to her glory. As a result, I am greatly anxious and fearful, while desiring to follow your advancements, lest I be found an unworthy and improper praiser.
Indeed, neither my holiness nor eloquence is enough to praise the blessed and glorious Virgin Mary worthily. To be honest, whatever can be said in human words falls short of the praise she deserves in heaven.
For she is proclaimed and praised more excellently by divine and angelic heralds.
She was foretold by the prophets, prefigured by the patriarchs in images and enigmas, shown and demonstrated by the evangelists, and greeted most respectfully and dutifully by the angel.
Furthermore, her greatness and worth were divinely declared by the same angel when he said:
"Hail, full of grace, the Lord is with you; blessed are you among women."
Such gifts were fittingly pledged to the Virgin, so that she would be full of grace. She gave glory to the heavens, the Lord to the earth, peace to the world, faith to the nations, an end to vices, order to life, and discipline to morals.
And rightly, the angel was sent to the Virgin Mary, for virginity is always akin to angels.
Truly, to live in the flesh but beyond the flesh is not an earthly life, but a heavenly one.
Hence, acquiring an angelic life in the flesh is a greater merit than having it.
For to be an angel is a matter of happiness; to be a virgin is a matter of virtue, as the virgin strives with grace to attain by strength what the angel has by nature.
However, both being a virgin and an angel are offices of divine gift, not human.
"Hail," he said, "full of grace" (Luke 1:28); and well full, because grace is given to others in parts, but to Mary, the fullness of grace was poured out all at once.
This is what David sings: "It will descend like rain upon the fleece" (Psalm 72:6).
Thus, although the fleece is of the body, it does not know bodily passion.
Similarly, virginity, though in the flesh, does not know the vices of the flesh.
Clearly, the heavenly rain poured itself gently into the virgin fleece: the entire wave of divinity flowed into the flesh when the Word became flesh; and then, expressed through the cross's beam, it poured out the rain of salvation upon all lands and granted the drippings of grace to human minds.
The Lord, he said, is with you.
A remarkable event occurred with the Virgin, to whom God sent an Angel. God sent His messenger ahead, but He never left God's presence. He who is present everywhere cannot be confined to one place; He is everywhere entirely, without whom nothing is whole.
Therefore, the Word of the Father, never departing from the Father, became man for us through His secret mystery, which only He knows. Since He assumed everything that is human, He is fully human, and retaining everything that is divine, He could not be anything other than God, born of Mary. For God knows and can do everything.
Because of this, He knew and was able to unite with the Virgin's womb without corrupting Himself, so that Christ was one person, both God and man, one substance. Because of this, the Mother of God was chosen and preselected by the Angel's greeting, and proclaimed full of grace. Truly full, through whom all creation was abundantly blessed by the Holy Spirit. And so, the Angel devoutly venerates and greets her first. He marvels at her greatness, for it was not a simple, ordinary greeting, but one worthy of all admiration. Indeed, it was a gesture of reverence, an offering of a gift, and an act of service.
For although grace was believed to be present in the holy fathers and prophets, it was not as full as it was in Mary. In Mary, the fullness of all grace, which is in Christ, came, although in a different way. And so, he said, "Blessed are you among women," meaning more blessed than all women. Thus, whatever curse was brought through Eve was entirely removed by Mary's blessing. Moreover, the birth of Christ poured out grace that the whole world did not have before.
Therefore, what nature did not possess, what experience did not know, what reason did not understand, what the human mind cannot grasp, what heaven fears, what earth is astonished by, and what all creation, even the celestial, marvels at: this is the entire message that was divinely announced to Mary by Gabriel and fulfilled by Christ.
For this reason, I confess myself unworthy to speak of such a great and profound matter. But I also believe that no one would dare presume to speak of it unless they were completely ignorant of its magnitude.
Six. However, even if no one feels adequate, no sinner should stop praising, even if they can't fully express their feelings.
That's why the divine word, when talking about the sinner in the Psalms, says: "The sacrifice of praise will honor me," and then immediately adds, "and there is the way by which I will show him the salvation of God" Psalm 50:23. It's as if it clearly says, "There is the path of praise leading to eternal praise, but no one will grasp it unless I show them the way."
So, dearest ones, because the path of our salvation is in the praises of the Savior, I urge and remind you on this holy feast of the Mother of God, Mary, not to stop praising.
If you are a virgin, rejoice because you have deserved to be what you praise: just strive to be worthy of giving praise. If you are chaste and pure, honor and praise, for it is by the grace of Christ, which was fully in Mary whom you praise, that you can be chaste.
If you are married or a sinner, still confess and praise, because mercy and grace have flowed to all from there so that they may praise. And although praise from the mouth of a sinner is not beautiful, don't stop praising, for forgiveness is promised to you from there, just as it is to all, so that you may praise.
Otherwise, unless we strive to praise God in His saints according to the measure of our ability, how will we be able to praise Him according to the multitude of His greatness, as we sing?
We must not neglect what we will someday fulfill, as it is said: "Blessed are those who dwell in your house, Lord; they will praise you forever and ever" Psalm 84:4.
Sometimes, because He is immense, what we cannot express with words or eloquence, we should carry out with the desires and innermost thoughts of the heart: because He is great and good and immense, as great and as such as He knows Himself to be, let us confess with mouth and spirit for righteousness and salvation.
Therefore, I ask that we all devoutly celebrate the feast of the glorious ever-virgin Mary together. This is a notable day, on which she was exalted above the choirs of angels and reached beyond the nature of our humanity.
Here, substance is not taken away; rather, the greatness of glory is shown as she is elevated to the right hand of the Father, where Christ entered for us as an eternal high priest in the palace of heaven.
This, I say, is the day on which the undefiled mother and virgin ascended to the height of the throne and was exalted to the royal seat, where she gloriously sits after Christ.
Thus, the holy Church of God confidently sings everywhere that no other saint has deservedly transcended the dignity of angels and archangels. Because even if likeness is promised to the saints, the reality is denied.
This privilege is not of nature, but of the grace of the blessed virgin Mary, from whom God Himself was born as a man. Therefore, she is greater in merits, not by nature, than a virgin and a man.
Hence, even if other virgins imitate her up to the disdain of childbirth, and Gabriel's new salutation service, from then on, everything divine was accomplished in her, as testified by the angel: "Because the Holy Spirit and the power of the Most High will overshadow you."
Before this, indeed, the womb of the Virgin, although pure, spotless, and free from the contagion of sin, although holy, was still clothed in the humility of humanity.
To put it this way, as if the whitest wool, bleached by its own color, to which indeed, when the Holy Spirit approached, as if the same wool dyed with the blood of a shellfish or murex, it turned into purple.
She was transformed without intercourse into a mother, so that she is no longer what she was, but the truest purple dedicated most fittingly by divine appointment to the clothing and glory of the highest king, that no one thereafter could use her in a feminine way except God.
Indeed, the blessed and glorious Virgin Mary, although already incomparable to all virgins under the sky, was able to unite with divinity within herself, preserving both natures. She is filled with grace, suffused with the Holy Spirit, overshadowed by the power of the Most High, becoming more precious in merits, higher in sublime heights, more beautiful in sanctity, and more glorious in the prerogatives of her merits. So, she is now reserved only for divine purposes.
Therefore, O most holy virgins, while it is fitting to imitate such a great and splendid virgin and to venerate her highly, it is also very appropriate to praise her with the most worthy praises and joy, as far as is lawful. As we have said, she is exalted above the choirs of angels by the grace of Christ and is devoutly proclaimed today because our Lord and Savior, born of her in true faith, preceded her to heaven to prepare for her a place in the heavenly mansions, as He promised His disciples.
Hence, the prophet David joyfully sings to Christ: from the highest heaven is His coming forth: and His return is to its highest (Psalm 18:7). He ascended to resume the same glory, although He had not lost it, which He had before the world was made. He ascended and prepared a place of immortality for this most holy and glorious Virgin, so that she might reign with Him forever.
Today, we celebrate the festivity marking the glorious and blessed day when she reached the heavenly bridal chamber. Just as the blessed Mary is unparalleled among other virgins, this celebration is equally unparalleled among all the saints' festivities. It is also wondrous to the angelic powers.
Because of this, the Holy Spirit, marveling on behalf of the heavenly citizens at her ascension, says in the Song of Songs:
Song of Songs 3:6: "Who is this that comes up from the wilderness, like a column of smoke, perfumed with myrrh and frankincense?"
And rightly as a column of smoke, because slender and delicate, refined by divine disciplines, and internally consumed in the holocaust of loving fire and the desire of charity. As a column of smoke, perfumed with myrrh and frankincense, she is certainly filled with the fragrances of many virtues. The sweetest scent emanated from her even to the angelic spirits.
The Mother of God was ascending from the wilderness of this present age, a rod from the root of Jesse that sprouted long ago. The souls of the elect were marveling with joy, wondering who she was, surpassing even the dignity of the angels in the virtues of her merits.
About her again, the same Holy Spirit says in the same Song of Songs:
Song of Songs 6:10: "Who is this that appears like the dawn, fair as the moon, bright as the sun, majestic as the stars in procession?"
The Holy Spirit marvels, making everyone marvel at the ascension of this Virgin, who shines like the dawn of a new day, resplendent in her ascent, surrounded and supported by the hosts of saints. Hence, she is said to be majestic as the stars in procession. Indeed, she is made majestic by her virtues, like a well-ordered army, supported on all sides by the protection of angels and saints, fair as the moon, or rather, fairer than the moon, because she now shines without any defect, illuminated by heavenly splendors.
Chosen like the sun, with the radiance of virtues, because the Sun of Justice Himself chose to be born from her. At her funeral rites (as far as it is permitted to believe), angels served, and all the courts of heaven rejoiced.
No surprise, as it is the honor of his mother, born from her. The entire order of the heavens venerates and adores her, raised above with the Father in the seat of the Lord's majesty.
We read how often angels have attended the funerals and burials of saints, providing services for their obsequies. They have also carried the souls of the chosen up to the heavens, with hymns and praises. Choirs of both sexes are often mentioned as singing praises. Remarkably, they sometimes shone with much light. Moreover, those still living sensed the fragrance of a wonderful odor there for a long time.
To revive hope, dearest daughter, and to strengthen the faith of those present, our Savior Jesus Christ, to further prove the merits of his own, deigned to exhibit such great things through his heavenly ministers around the deceased. How much more should we believe that on this day the army of the heavens came festively to meet the mother of God, surrounded her with immense light, and led her to the throne prepared for her even before the foundation of the world, with praises and spiritual songs!
No doubt, all of heavenly Jerusalem then exulted with ineffable joy, rejoiced with inestimable love, and celebrated with all gratitude. This festivity, annually renewed for us today, has been made perpetual for all of them.
Nine. And not without reason: it is believed that the Savior himself joyfully meets her and seats her with him on the throne. Otherwise, how is it believed that he fulfilled what he commanded in the law: Honor your father and your mother (Matthew 15:4)?
Moreover, he himself is the witness that he honored his father when he said to the Jews: I do not seek my own glory; there is one who seeks and judges: but I honor my Father, and you dishonor me (John 8:49, 50). Regarding his mother, the Evangelist says: When he returned to Nazareth, he was obedient to them (Luke 2:51).
But there is a different nature by which God the Father is honored according to himself, and another by which he is subject to parents. Yet in both cases, it is rightly believed that Christ is one and the same: because the Word became flesh and dwelt among us, one Emmanuel, which means God with us.
The Catholic faith preserves this union of divinity and humanity as unconfused and indivisible: it understands and recognizes the natural and substantial unity, so that neither conversion into one part of the two substances is accepted, nor division. To believe this way is to honor the mother of the Lord who bore both God and man for us: not man without God, nor God without man, but one and true Jesus Christ as both God and man.
Otherwise, she could not be called the Mother of God, which many heretics have tried to deny, unless she had truly borne God incarnate: and for this reason, we rightly confess two births in Christ. One, from the Father, without beginning and without time, eternal and co-eternal with God the Father. The other, from the mother in time, when, out of compassion and mercy, he descended to us by his own free will, God born as man: and thus, according to the truth, he is carried in the womb of the mother, who is always recognized as God.
Hence, we truly confess her to be the Mother of God, specifically the bearer of God and Christ. This is not because the Word carried flesh with Him or was once united with the aforementioned flesh, but because at the time when the Word became flesh from the flesh of the Virgin, the substance of divinity and humanity was united in the womb without confusion, making one person who is both God and man, Christ.
Indeed, from two natures without confusion, only one Jesus is found. The Lord remained God in the form of God, who emptied Himself, taking the form of a servant (Philippians 2:7). He remained the same in the form of a servant which He assumed: entirely God in the flesh of the Virgin from whom He was born, and entirely man.
Hence also the Apostle says: "In Him dwells all the fullness of the Deity in bodily form" (Colossians 2:9).
Therefore, daughters, be wise as serpents and innocent as doves (Matthew 10:16), so that from the prudence of perfect understanding, you keep the ring of your faith and the pearl, for which you have left everything, whole and inviolate. Do this lest you lose the dowry and pledge of the Holy Spirit (God forbid).
Therefore, take care to diligently maintain the simplicity of the dove, which was in Mary, unharmed and inviolate in you. About her, Solomon in the Song of Songs praises her, saying: "Come, my dove, my undefiled one: For now the winter is past, the rain is over and gone" (Song of Solomon 2:11).
And then he says: "Come from Lebanon, come, you will be crowned" (Song of Solomon 4:6, 8).
It is not without reason that she is ordered to come from Lebanon, because Lebanon means 'whiteness.' She was adorned with many virtues of merit and made whiter than snow by the gifts of the Holy Spirit, representing the simplicity of the dove in all things. Because whatever was done in her, all was purity and simplicity, all was truth and grace, all was mercy and justice, which looked down from heaven. Therefore, she was immaculate, because she was corrupted in nothing.
She encompassed the man in her womb, as the holy Jeremiah testifies, and did not receive him from elsewhere.
The Lord says He will do a new thing on the earth, and a woman will surround a man. Jeremiah 31:22 This is truly a new and remarkable virtue. When God, whom the world cannot bear, nor can anyone see and live entered the womb in such a way that it did not experience the confinement of the body. Carried within, all of God was in Him, and He emerged from there, as Ezekiel describes, a completely closed gate.
Hence, it is sung in the Songs about her: A garden enclosed, a fountain sealed, your shoots are an orchard. Song of Solomon 4:12 Truly a garden of delights, where all kinds of flowers and the fragrances of virtues are planted. It is enclosed in such a way that it cannot be violated or corrupted by deceitful plots. A fountain indeed sealed with the seal of the entire Trinity, from which the fountain of life flows, and in whose light we shall all see the light.
According to John, He is the one who enlightens every person coming into this world. John 1:9 The issuing of the womb is the paradise of all the citizens of heaven. From this field of the womb, the patriarch Isaac, smelling from afar, said: Behold, the smell of my son is like the smell of a field which the Lord has blessed. Genesis 27:27 Although some may think that the early saints understood little about the mystery of the Incarnation of Christ, they too were saved by the same grace.
From this, it's clear that time did not affect the sacrament of the union between man and God. He was already present from the beginning of the world, even though He had not yet been born of the Virgin Mary. This is shown by many indications in the Scriptures. Hence, the Lord said to the Jews: Before Abraham was, I am. By these words, He showed that He who was speaking had always been part of that mystery of unity. To emphasize this, He said, Before Abraham was, I am (John 8:58).
For Abraham, before he came into being, represents the brevity of humanity. But I am declares the eternity of nature, in which He who was speaking was already present through the sacrament of His incarnation. The apostle Jude wanted to make this clearer: Jesus, he said, who saved the people out of Egypt, later destroyed those who did not believe (Jude 1:5).
And elsewhere Paul says: Let us not test Christ, as some of them did (First Corinthians 10:9). Not that Jesus or Christ had already been born of Mary, but because the unity of the person was already commended in that unique Son of God, which was hidden in the mystery. Paul also clearly states elsewhere: He chose us, he said, before the foundation of the world in Him (Ephesians 1:4). Because indeed whatever God did from the beginning, Christ did everything through the unity of the sacrament.
Therefore, Jesus was already in the Son, who led the people out, and Christ was in Him who was tested. For it is not doubted that He was always in God through the unity of the sacrament. Otherwise, unless you believe this, either Christ will not be God at all, or contrary to the prophet, God will appear to be new. But to avoid being shaken by such slanders, we must search the Scriptures, in which the unity of the person in Christ is commended, because time does not affect it, so that He may always be called one.
Hence also, blessed Peter, speaking of the fathers, said: We believe that through the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ we will be saved, just as they will (Acts 15:11).
For the Lord alone led them, and no foreign god was with them.
Thus, God is not new to us because He is the same who was their leader and is our Redeemer through the suffering of His flesh. He is one in His flesh, one in the sacrament, and one in spirit. It makes no sense to think that the Son of Man and the Son of God are different. He is neither limited by time nor separated by suffering.
Instead, all of God passes into Christ, and Christ into God, so that whatever is the Son of God is called Christ, and everything Christ suffered in the flesh is rightly believed to have been suffered by God. Otherwise, if you consider reason and human senses, divinity and human nature could not have come together as they did in Christ, where He is Emmanuel, one from both.
Therefore, it seems to me that those who thought of two sons or considered Christ to be anything other than the Son of God could not understand or see the depth of such a great mystery. Consequently, we do not worship or adore a man separately, which is blasphemous. Instead, we worship God incarnate, who united His own animated body with Himself, so that the Word of God became flesh, not in any other, but in Himself, who was always the one true Son of God.
Therefore, we worship and adore no other than the same Son of God. He was not increased by assuming humanity, nor diminished or changed by becoming flesh. Thus, the same Son is always worshipped with God the Father, not new, not recent from time, not alien to nature or kind.
If it seems new to you that He took on human form for you, know that this was always part of His plan and His counsel to do so.
And now, when the fullness of time has come, what was always in Christ has been accomplished. Indeed, the earlier saints were divinely influenced by such fragrances and inspired by such prophecies about Christ, that He would be born into the world, in whom would be the salvation and blessing of the eternal inheritance for everyone.
These are the garments of faith. These are what the earlier saints wore. These are what Rebecca, or rather the Holy Spirit, had with her at home, with which she dressed her son Jacob. But unless these garments had been kept and brought out by the Holy Spirit at home, how could their wonderful fragrance have reached Father Isaac, so that he would say, when he sensed the fragrance of the garments:
"See, the smell of my son is like the smell of a field which the Lord has blessed" (Genesis 27:27)?
But perhaps someone will ask: What does the Holy Spirit have to do with Rebecca, since in many places persons are allegorically taken for God? Nonetheless, the word for spirit in Hebrew, "RUA", is of the feminine gender. Not that gender is shown in God. Rather, lest anyone suspect otherwise, under the rule of three languages, the Holy Spirit is understood differently: in Hebrew, as I said, it is read in the feminine gender; in Greek, however, so that no gender is believed in it, it is found in the neuter form; and in Latin, it is determined to be masculine.
Indeed, the Holy Spirit is rightly understood through Rebecca. And therefore, everything that happens is in the mystery, so that through the fragrance of the garments, Christ is announced. Whom we all, whoever we are baptized, wear, in whom He blessed us not with any blessing, but with every (as the Apostle says) spiritual blessing in the heavenly places (Ephesians 1:3).
Hence, the angel speaking to Mary, starting from the blessing, said: "Blessed are you among women, and blessed is the fruit of your womb" (Luke 1:28).
Indeed, Isaac, sensing the fragrance in spirit, blessed his son, in whom all heavenly blessing blossomed for the world.
He rightly calls her full, because the Virgin Mary is proclaimed full of the grace of virtues. From her womb, the fruit of life has shone forth for believers.
And we, says the evangelist, have all received from her fullness John 1:16, grace upon grace.
Therefore, I beg you, daughters, not to receive such great grace in vain, which is in Christ Jesus, in whom God and man are united in one person.
It is often read in the divine Scriptures that man is coeternal with God due to the union of substance. And then God seems to have compassion for man, although man is not eternal, nor is God capable of suffering. Yet, God is so united with his body that no distance can be imagined between God and man by human opinion.
Let us hope that no one believes there is a different son of God and a different son of man. Especially since the divine Scripture connects and incorporates God and man so closely that man cannot be wholly separated from God in time, nor can God be discerned from man in passion.
If you look at time, you will certainly find the son of man always with the son of God. If you look at passion, you will always find the same son of God so united and indivisible with the son of man, according to the voice of Scripture, that man cannot be separated from God in time, nor can God be separated from man in passion.
To understand this more clearly, consider the words of Christ: "No one has ascended into heaven except the one who descended from heaven, the Son of Man who is in heaven" (John 3:13).
Who is speaking?
Certainly Christ.
Where was he when he said this?
Clearly on earth.
How does he claim to have descended from heaven before he was born?
Even while speaking, he confesses to be in heaven and calls himself the Son of Man; clearly, no one but God could have descended from heaven.
And while speaking on earth, he was none other than Christ.
This is a marvelous and admirable newness, indeed the most surpassing newness of all.
Unless you, prudent virgin, note this from the beginning of the holy Gospel, you will seem to err more in all divine Scripture than understand the truth.
It is evident that the one and the same Christ operated according to both forms, humanity and divinity, and thus performed two operations.
Each form or nature did what was proper to it in communion with the other: the Word performing what is of the Word, and the flesh executing what is of the flesh.
The Word shared in the same operation, while the same one is believed to be both God and man in one substance or person, without division or mixture, and the same identity is proclaimed.
Nevertheless, God is the Word, and not the flesh, although he assumed flesh rationally animated and united it to himself by natural and substantial union.
Similarly, the flesh is animated and not the Word, although it is seen and regarded as the flesh of the Word of God.
Hence John says: "That which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes, which we have looked at and our hands have touched-this we proclaim concerning the Word of life" (First John 1:1).
No one can see or touch the true God with hands, except through the sacrament of the united man.
Indeed, this union is so marvelous that it cannot be fully discerned.
Otherwise, from the beginning-the Word-how can it be rightly said that this encompasses all that the apostles heard, saw, and touched, if not because Christ was always the same?
Thus, what they heard, saw, and touched was the Word of life, not something from two separate natures, but one being according to subsistence or person. Therefore, the only begotten Son, remaining the same, is seen inseparably in both natures and naturally performed actions belonging to each substance, according to its inherent quality or natural property.
Now, while Emmanuel is one, and in Him both God and man, He truly carried out actions pertaining to both natures, working according to each nature. As God, He did divine things; as man, He did human things, showing that He is both God and man.
The same Christ performed both divine and human acts: it was not one who performed miracles and another who carried out human acts and endured suffering, but the same Christ, the Son of God and the Son of Man, did both. For Christ inseparably and indivisibly had common actions.
However, we must understand the qualities of these works: always consider the humility of the flesh and the height of divinity. Throughout the entire holy Gospel, it is seen that the flesh does nothing without the Word, nor does the Word accomplish anything without the flesh. Hence, as the Virgin conceives and gives birth, it is not without the power of the Word, nor without the truth of the flesh that what is born is wrapped in swaddling clothes and laid in a manger.
Moreover, as what is worshipped by the Magi under the guidance of a star-Matthew chapter 2, verse 11-is of the deity; so too is it of the humanity when He was brought to Egypt to avoid capture.
So, in this way, all virtuous actions must be considered. We give to God what is God's and to man what is man's.
Just as there is one who calls Lazarus with the word of his power to come out from the tomb, that same one wept with human emotion.
Thus, everything must be considered in such a way that the full divinity in Christ is understood as united with man, and full humanity as assumed into God.
I've shared these thoughts on the Incarnation of Christ, dear friends, because many in the East, caught up in their own confusion, try to cloud your understanding with complicated language or disrupt the clarity of Latin with Greek confusion. There are wise virgins and foolish ones. So, my beloved, imitate the blessed and glorious Virgin you adore and whose feast you celebrate today. It's said of her: "But Mary kept all these things (which were said about Christ) and pondered them in her heart" (Luke 2:51). Therefore, dear ones, also ponder in your hearts what is said about our Lord in a Catholic manner, to keep your faith intact and properly honor His mother. The greatest honor for her is when He is rightfully honored, as He chose to be born from her. Furthermore, I ask you, daughters and mothers, to think deeply and consider the sorrows the blessed and pure Virgin Mary endured after Christ ascended to heaven. This was when everything foretold by angels and prophesied by prophets was fulfilled, declared by divine oracles, demonstrated by virtues, and revealed through signs of humanity. If you have any compassion, reflect on the love that tormented her, the longing that burned within this virgin, as she remembered all she had heard, seen, and known.
I believe that no matter what is in the heart, mind, or human strength, it is not enough to fully grasp the unending, burning passion of pious love.
She was deeply moved by the inspirations of heavenly secrets filled with the Holy Spirit.
Even though she loved Christ with all her heart, soul, and strength, she was daily inflamed by new desires in His absence.
As divine visitations illuminated her more, the grace of the Holy Spirit filled her entirely, and divine love set her ablaze.
Worldly affections could not touch her; she was consumed by continuous ardor and an intoxication of infused love.
Christ must be loved with all one's heart, soul, and strength, and sought after, especially by her, who was both His Lord and His mother.
We believe that out of immense love, she sometimes stayed where He is said to be buried, so her inner pious love could be nourished by her eyes.
The place is so central that she could visit the traces of His ascension, His burial and resurrection, and all the places where He suffered.
She didn't seek the living among the dead but was consoled by seeing these places.
Impatient love always believes it will find what it desires.
It does not know judgment, often lacks reason, knows no limits, and cannot think of anything else but what it loves.
Love does not find comfort in impossibility or remedy in difficulty.
Although the blessed Virgin Mary was already in spirit, as long as she lived in the flesh, she was moved by bodily senses and often found joy in visiting these places.
She embraced in her mind Him whom she had given birth to.
Finally, the love of Christ gave birth to desire!
The growing desire felt renewed with new flames, so much so that I sometimes believe it surpassed everything, even itself. Because love, being entirely impatient, cannot avoid seeing what it loves. This is why, dearest ones, all the saints thought everything they had achieved was insignificant if they could not see the Lord whom they loved. Just like the venerable Blessed Virgin Mary, who sometimes felt her holy service was unworthy of countless and immense benefits, because while on earth, she could not see the giver of those benefits. And so today, beloved ones, she is lifted above the choirs of angels so she can see the face and appearance of the Savior, whom she loved and desired with all her heart.
If there's joy in heaven over any sinner who repents, imagine the celebration and glory for such a great Virgin, causing exultation in the heavens.
Her festival brings joy to all the heavenly citizens, especially because her celebration is a praise and favor to the Savior.
We believe, as mentioned earlier, that they don't just observe this solemn day annually in her honor, but continuously and eternally celebrate her with joy, happiness, and veneration, filled with love and jubilation.
Rightfully so, the entire heavenly city rejoices and venerates the mother, whose son, the King, they adore above themselves; before whom powers tremble and every knee bends.
Concerning her ascension to heaven, the contemplator of heavenly secrets in the Song of Songs says with much admiration: "I saw her, beautiful as she ascended, like a dove above the streams of water."
And truly beautiful as a dove, because she showed the appearance and simplicity of a dove, which came upon the Lord and taught John that this is He who baptizes.
Rightly, she is above the streams of water, because the Lord led her beside waters of refreshment and nourished her, as mentioned in Psalm twenty-three verse two. From these waters, many streams flow, watering the whole land of delight and infusing the garden of pleasure.
From this, daily, the blessed Mother of God ascends so beautifully and admirably on this day, her fragrance exceedingly inestimable and therefore ineffable.
Indeed, to the fragrance of her scent, the whole heavenly Jerusalem runs joyfully, surrounded by roses and lilies of the valleys, because all souls marked by martyrdom embrace her with everlasting arms of love.
Adorned with the splendor of virginity, as if lilies nurtured in the valley of humility, they surround her, serving with the grace of veneration.
Rightly so, because the blessed Mother of God was both a martyr and a virgin, even though she ended her life in peace.
From this, it is evident that she truly suffered, as the prophet Simeon testifies, speaking to her: "And a sword will pierce your own soul" (Luke 2:35). This shows she was more than a martyr.
Other saints, even if they suffered for Christ in the flesh, could not suffer in the soul because it is immortal. But the blessed mother of God, because she suffered in the part considered impassible, I must say, spiritually, her flesh also endured the sword of Christ's passion, more than a martyr.
Hence, it is clear that she loved more than all, and therefore she grieved more, to the extent that her grief completely consumed her soul, as a testament to her extraordinary love. Because she suffered in her mind, she was more than a martyr. Indeed, her love was stronger than death, as she made Christ's death her own.
Now she is surrounded by flowers of roses, continuously admired for her beauty among the daughters of Jerusalem (Song of Solomon 5:7). The king has set his throne in her because he desired her beauty and grace. She was full of love and affection; therefore, a host of those robed in purple and a flock of the pure follow her.
If you look closely, there is nothing of virtue, beauty, or glory that does not shine from her. Therefore, she is well surrounded by roses and lilies of the valley, so that virtues are supported by virtues, and the beauty of chastity is enhanced by grace.
For all splendor and glory, the more it is illuminated by its own brilliance, the more it appears superior in clarity among any subjects, and is proclaimed exceptional. Thus, the blessed Mother of God, whose planting is like the roses in Jericho, shone even more brightly, and the purity of virginity gleamed more brilliantly when surrounded by the duty of charity.
The brightness and glory of the saints are submitted to her, so that her splendor and glory may be more commended: she who is elevated above the choirs of angels is now proclaimed blessed, and now most blessed. Though the nature of angels is higher, their grace is not greater, because they too were saved by free grace, so they would not fall. Hence David says, by the Word of the Lord, the heavens were made firm, and by the breath of His mouth all their host Psalm 33:6.
If all their virtue subsists by the breath of His mouth, it is clear that the blessed and glorious Virgin Mary, upon whom the Holy Spirit came, and who carried God in her womb for nine months, as is to be believed, has deserved greater privileges of virtues, and received a grace praised even by the angels.
Therefore, if their virtue and firmness of perpetuity is wonderful, it is even more wonderful in Mary, whom the power of the Most High overshadowed, so that what was done in her surpasses all angelic virtue, and is an admirable mystery for all ages. Thus, even the angels are granted greater grace from this, as everything is restored by her, those who adore and worship Christ the King, the Lord born from the same Virgin.
Hence, Mary is all the more venerable to everyone, the more graceful she is, and the more she is exalted to the heights by the power of the Most High, the more she shines clearly in glory.
Indeed, full of grace, full of God, and full of virtues, she cannot help but fully possess the glory of eternal brightness, which she most fully received to become the mother of the Savior. All the daughters of Zion saw her and called her most blessed, and queens praised her, for they saw her in such a way that no mortal could fully describe; how much more God, who made her so great, so that He might be born through her! Hence David says: "And a man is born in her, and the Most High himself has established her" (Psalm 87:5). Therefore, blessed is such a great birth, blessed is the fellowship of the heavenly citizens, and admirable is their unity of love: where none of the angels, none of the archangels, I do not say the blessed virgin Mary, but neither does any of the saints envy her glory: but each one possesses in another what is freely given to all: so that God may be glorified in all and by all, honored and worshiped by all: where neither sex, nor age, nor dignity of birth is discerned, but only the quality of merits: where one star differs from another star in brightness, although all will be raised in their own order. For if there is one glory of the sun, and another glory of the moon, and another glory of the stars (First Corinthians 15:41): yet there is one glory that illuminates all. Therefore, the blessed mother of God, who is still praised with such great praises on earth, is rightly believed to have been exalted and glorified, and indeed made radiant today, as much as He who chose her in His wisdom knows, by which He arranged all things. For if there are many mansions in the Father's house, we believe that today the Son has provided a more splendid one for His mother than the house He once built for Himself, supported by seven pillars: in which house, indeed, the marriages of the Churches of God are prepared, and the earthly are united with the heavenly. In that womb of the Virgin, immortality is consecrated to the bridegroom, so that the entire exchange may be heavenly.
And so, dearest ones, celebrate solemnly the feast of the Virgin, who has shown you heavenly life on earth. For those who neither marry nor are given in marriage will be like angels in heaven. It's no surprise that virginity is compared to the angels, as it is united with the Lord of the angels in the bond of marriage.
If any virginity is so exalted as to be compared to the angels, much more so is the blessed and glorious Virgin Mary, who is commended with a unique privilege and declared with immense worth. Therefore, dearest ones, love whom you worship, and worship whom you love. You truly worship and love her if you wish to imitate wholeheartedly the one you praise.
This life has flowed to you from heaven, which you have professed. This life is above the natural order, which you hold. The bridegroom has come from heaven, whom you should follow with the mother. It's not unreasonable that you sought the way of life from heaven when you asked for a bridegroom from heaven.
Therefore, let your way of life always be in heaven. Because the Word of God, which you love, is found only in the bosom of the Father. Although He is everywhere and not far from each of us, He is drawn only by a pure heart. For He is near, says Moses, in your heart and in your mouth, if you seek Him with a righteous heart. His name is poured out like perfume. Therefore, young women, love with your soul what has been poured out for you.
For you, holy virgins, have a virgin bridegroom, a lover of virginity and chastity, who chose a virgin mother so that she might be an example of chastity to all, in which the form of virtue shines like a mirror. Therefore, you have in her the teachings of integrity clearly expressed, what to choose first, what to reject, and what to follow.
Her first virtue is the foundation and guardian of all virtues, humility itself, of which she boasts: Because, she says, He has regarded the humility of His handmaid. For behold, from now on all generations will call me blessed.
Therefore, the first incentive to learning is the nobility of the teacher. Then the reward for excellent work is the fruit of blessedness.
What, then, is nobler than the mother of the Lord? What is more splendid than she whom the splendor of paternal glory chose? What is purer than she who gave birth to the body of Christ without the stain of the body?
And yet, she acknowledges that the Lord looked only at her humility, which is the guardian of other virtues. She placed her lofty merits in the safe harbor of her station, and therefore she is divinely illuminated. Hence the Lord says: "To whom shall I look, but to the humble and quiet, and to the one who trembles at my words" (Isaiah 66:2)?
For He did what He had promised, and He regarded the humility of His servant: hence she is proclaimed blessed from all ages. Therefore, you too, daughters, if you truly wish to be virgins, follow humility: and seek to imitate with the love of your heart the mother of the Lord, who called herself a servant, and who learned humility from the very bridegroom to whom you have devoted yourselves, and who taught you this from Himself.
Hence He also said: "Learn from me, for I am gentle and humble in heart" Matthew 11:29. Therefore, the blessed Mother of God did not learn from her Son, our Lord, how to create the heavens, nor how to create angels, nor how to perform the great miracles of divinity: but only how to be humble, and to gather other lessons of virtue within the safeguard of humility.
Hence with her always remained the unmovable companion of modesty in every virtue: for modesty must be inseparable from virginity, without which true chastity cannot be rightly preserved. Therefore, the blessed Virgin Mary never proceeded without the guardian of her modesty, and so if such a great and noble virgin pleases you, dearest ones, let her work of virtue also please you, whose life is a discipline for all, whose habits are the principles of the Churches, who surpassed all and excels above all.
Therefore, any virgin who wishes for a reward from her and implores her help should imitate her example. I ask you, virgins, and I also ask you, widows, to imitate the widow Paula, a model of continence and chastity. Imitate Eustochium, who is with you as a virgin, and a beautiful example of perfect integrity.
There is less in them compared to the mother of the Lord; you have a fruitful offspring and a perpetual virgin. Just as no one is good in comparison to God, no one is perfect compared to the mother of the Lord, even though they are recognized for their extraordinary virtues.
We have one Father, who is in heaven. One teacher. Mary is the model of virginity, and you should all strive to match her integrity. You must imprint her image through the Holy Spirit.
She is the enclosed garden, the sealed fountain, the well of living waters, as stated in Song of Solomon, Chapter 4, Verse 15. No deceit could reach her, nor did the enemy's fraud prevail; she remained holy in mind and body, elevated by many privileges of gifts.
Therefore, imitate her in your conduct, follow her in chastity, and seek her help.
If anyone among those who are envious wants to accuse me of presumption for speaking this way, let them accuse love and affection.
I judged that this should not be denied to you who asked for it.
I preferred to endure the blush of shame rather than not follow your command, whose prayers even our God seems to obey.
Especially since you have among you those whom it is virtuous to imitate and from whom you can learn.
You asked for affection rather than teaching in praise of this day.
Therefore, I should not excuse myself out of respect for seriousness, so as not to share in your devotion, which you commanded.
If I could not teach, I at least made every effort to encourage praise for such a great virgin.
I did this so that I might not be absent from you, whom you love on this great day of festivity.
Instead, I might be joined in prayers and vows, hoping to be elevated in mind with you by your supporting merits to the things the blessed and undefiled Virgin Mary has attained.
Behold, on this day she ascends to the splendid and glorious throne of the angels through humility and purity of flesh.
From there, intemperance once cast down the distinguished archangels and pride.
Therefore, rejoice because the way to heaven has been opened to you.
Although the same promises are made to us, to you, they are now already at hand, who with the angels keep incorruption.
Even though you are in this world, with God's favor, you are not of this world.
Because even if the world deserved to have you, it could not completely hold you.
Therefore, the blessed Mary is today proclaimed far and wide by all nations.
To you who have followed the example of such a great virgin, heavenly blessedness is granted.
Those whom the allurements of the body do not disturb, the corruption of pleasure does not precipitate, nor the heat of carnal excitement inflames, but rather angelic imitation delights on earth.
Equality in the future is promised in heaven.
You are therefore blessed, daughters, and also blessed are the widows who live a celibate life in Christ with you. According to the Apostle, freed from the law of the husband, they have remained so. He said, she will be happier if she remains so, according to my advice. For I think, he said, that I also have the Spirit of God; clearly wanting to express the difference between her who is still joined by the law to a husband, and her who, already freed from the bond, is proclaimed happier.
If both are blessed because they are in Christ, yet happier is she who is already freed from the bond and follows heavenly things. Therefore, widows are always well joined with virgins, as the Apostle says: An unmarried woman or virgin is concerned about the Lord's affairs, that she may be holy in body and spirit.
First Corinthians 7:34. In a way, the example of widows, who have kept chaste marriage with husbands, instructs and strengthens the teaching of virginity, showing that integrity should be kept more by virgins for God: and that it is no less virtuous to abstain from marriage, which once pleased, than to be ignorant of the pleasures of marriage.
In both conditions, indeed, strength is praised, and the virtue of the heavenly life is proclaimed. Therefore, both orders share kinship with Christ. Hence the Lord: Whoever does the will of my Father in heaven is my brother, sister, and mother.
Matthew 12:50. Where neither sex, nor age, nor condition is distinguished, but whoever does, he said, the will of my Father in heaven.
Therefore, since freedom is granted to all, be, dearest ones, what Christ's grace has called you to be. Be mothers of Christ and brides, be sisters and relatives because what you could not achieve by the flesh, grace has granted you entirely.
And thus, love the mother of the Lord, who bore for you an immortal spouse. She is herself your sister because she did the will of the Father to be a mother. She is indeed related to you not by flesh, but by spirit, so that the unity of the Church is commended, and the fellowship of the body of Christ is understood.
For the Lord said, I desire, Father, that since you and I are one, they also may be one in us. (John 17:21)
This unity is indeed made possible through the one mediator between God and humans. Therefore, do the will of the Father, so that you can be one. Adorn your lamps, meet the bridegroom, for he is already knocking at the door, and follow the mother if you love her.
But inwardly prepare and adorn your lamps because you are daughters of the king. For all your glory should be within, and have within you what shines outside, lest perhaps among these celebrations, before the bridegroom comes, your lamps are extinguished.
For the celebration of this day is rightly conducted only with lamps lit inside and outside. Therefore, buy oil while there is time, lest when the bridegroom comes, God forbid, you are found empty.
Therefore, seek the things above, where the blessed Virgin has arrived, and not the things on earth, because your conversation, if you are now what you vowed to be, should be in the heavens. Direct your mind there, hide your life there, until the Lord's wrath passes, to where the blessed Mother of God has arrived today. There you have your spouse, there you have your high priest, there you have all that you seek.
Direct your mind there, so that when Christ, the Virgin's son, appears at the end of the age, you may also appear with him in glory. Amen.