Sermon One: On the Dedication of the Church
John the Apostle and Evangelist, chosen and beloved by Christ, was so favored in love that he reclined on His chest at the Last Supper.
It was to him alone, standing by the cross, that Jesus entrusted His own Mother.
In a wise plan, He gave John the responsibility of caring for the glorious Virgin, whom He had called to embrace virginity and chosen as pure in mind and body.
When John was sent into exile on the island of Patmos for the word of God and the testimony of Jesus Christ, the Revelation was shown to him there.
In it, for our instruction among other things, he says:
The angel said to me, "Come, I will show you the bride of the Lamb." And he took me in the spirit to a great and high mountain, and showed me the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, prepared like a bride adorned for her husband.
The great and high mountain he refers to is Christ, of whom the prophet says: "On that day, the mountain of the house of the Lord will be established on the top of the mountains, and it will be exalted above the hills," meaning above prophets and apostles; because they are called mountains and hills due to the greatness of their virtues and the excellence of their merits.
As for "on that day," it indicates that the time from Christ's passion to the end of the world is considered as one day. It continues: The heavenly Jerusalem is the multitude of saints, who are said to come with the Lord, as the prophet Zechariah says: "Behold, our Lord will come, and all His saints with Him." They are prepared by God with a pure dwelling so they may live with Him, like a bride adorned for her husband. Christ is the head and husband of the whole Church.
Thus Solomon says, when speaking of the same Church under the persona of a strong woman: "Her husband is respected at the city gate, when he sits among the elders of the land."
The holy Church's husband is Christ, who will sit with the leaders of the earth-patriarchs, prophets, and apostles-to judge the living and the dead on judgment day.
He is rightly called noble because, among all the children of men, no one is like him.
Therefore, the whole Church, meaning all the holy ones, will come adorned to be united with Jesus Christ, their groom, in holiness and righteousness, and they will remain with him forever.
This city of Jerusalem, or the holy Church, is appropriately called new because it is renewed daily through the sacrament of baptism in Christ, who is the new man.
This Church descends daily in penitence from heaven, imitating the humility of the Son of God.
Just as the Son of God, though in the form of God, took the form of a servant and descended from heaven, humbling himself even to death.
Philippians chapter two.
The descent of the Son of God from heaven is his incarnation.
Therefore, this city of Jerusalem daily imitates God and descends from heaven, following the footsteps of Jesus Christ, its groom, and keeps itself in humility.
In a wondrous way, the holy Church, or any holy soul, the more it descends in humility for the sake of God, the more it ascends by God's grace.
Hence, the Lord says in the Gospel:
Whoever exalts himself will be humbled, and whoever humbles himself will be exalted.
Matthew chapter twenty-three.
Likewise, our eloquent Isidore says:
Descend to ascend, humble yourself to be exalted, lest you be humbled when exalted.
Therefore, each person will be more precious and higher in the eyes of God to the extent that they are more despised and lowly in their own eyes for the love of God.
Why?
Because God looks upon the humble and knows the high from afar.
Psalm one hundred thirty-eight.
Hence, elsewhere in Scripture, it says:
God gives grace to the humble but resists the proud.
Proverbs chapter three.
Thus, the Lord speaks to Saul, saying:
Were you not small in your own eyes, yet I made you the head of the tribes of Israel?
First Samuel chapter fifteen.
As if he were saying:
You were great to me when you were despised by yourself.
Now, however, because you are great in your own eyes, you are despised by me.
He said this city had 12 gates, and above the gates were 12 angels, with the names of the 12 tribes of Israel written on them.
Its light was like a most precious stone, like crystal.
The prophet speaks to this city, saying: You will no longer have the sun to shine by day, nor will the brightness of the moon illuminate you; but the Lord will be your everlasting light, and your God will be your great glory.
Isaiah Chapter 60.
Just as a crystal stone is naturally clear and transparent, this city is illuminated not by the light of the stars, but by the light of God alone.
It had a great and high wall.
Hence, the prophet Zechariah says: I will be a wall around it, says the Lord.
Zechariah Chapter 2.
The Lord, therefore, is the light and protector of that most glorious city.
It says it has 12 gates, each made of a single pearl, and on the gates are angels with the names of the 12 tribes of the sons of Israel.
In the Gospel, we read the Lord said of himself: I am the door.
If anyone enters by me, they will be saved.
John Chapter 10.
Therefore, Christ is the gate of this city.
The 12 gates and the 12 tribes of Israel are the 12 apostles and the 12 prophets, representing the whole Church established in the number 12.
Yet these 12 gates lead to one gate, which is Christ.
The gates are made of single pearls because the holy apostles, who are the Church's gates, show the light of truth to those entering.
It says the city is square, showing the gathered crowd of saints, in whom the Catholic faith could not waver.
Revelation Chapter 21.
This city is set in a square because the holy Church is firmly built on the order of the four evangelists upon the Lord's incarnation and established in the four parts of the world.
He adds again, saying: And the one who talked with me had a measuring rod of gold.
In the golden reed, he reveals faith in the incarnation of our Lord Jesus Christ, who took on human frailty to give us a perfect example and show us the path to salvation.
He is the one through whom faith is measured and distributed to each person, and through whom the integrity of the Holy Trinity is known.
He measured the city with 12 stadia.
Its length, width, and height are equal.
Through these 12 stadia, the faith of Christ and the integrity of the Holy Church are recognized, reflecting the teachings of the apostles and the faith of the prophets; for nothing excessive, nothing foreign, and nothing lacking is found in them.
It also says: The structure of its wall was of jasper stone, and the city itself was pure gold, like clear glass.
In other metals, what's inside is hidden; but in glass, any liquid shows the same outwardly as it is inwardly.
What else can we understand from gold or glass but that heavenly homeland and the society of blessed citizens, whose hearts shine with love for one another and are clear with purity?
Their brightness is revealed to each other in their mutual hearts, because when each face is observed, their conscience is also unveiled.
The precious stones from which the city is built symbolize the holy and strong men in persecution, who cannot be shaken from true faith by the storm of persecutors or tribulations.
The street, said to be of the purest gold, suggests the hearts of the saints, clean from all sins, where the Lord walks.
The river of life, flowing from the throne of God and the Lamb as mentioned in Revelation Chapter 22, signifies the grace of baptism.
The tree of life on either bank signifies the coming of Christ in the flesh, foretold by the old law to come and suffer, and revealed by the Gospel as having already come.
The fruit, twelve in number for each month, represents the abundant grace given to the twelve apostles, which they received from the one wood of the cross, nourishing those who are spiritually hungry with the word of God.
The leaves of the tree are for the healing of the nations.
These leaves, which contribute to the health of the nations, symbolize the power of the holy cross.
There will be no more illness, because God will wipe away every tear from their eyes.
The throne of God and of the Lamb is there, as mentioned in Revelation chapter twenty-two.
"Thronus" in Greek is "sedes" in Latin.
Therefore, the seat of God is in that city, which is the holy Church, as the Psalmist testifies: "Your throne, O God, is forever and ever," as found in Psalm forty-five.
And His servants will serve Him, and they will see His face, as mentioned in Revelation chapter twenty-two.
Meanwhile, you should know, dearest brothers, that all the saints enter this noble city through three gates.
The holy Church has only three gates through which it joyfully enters the heavenly Jerusalem, a city being built daily with living stones in its members.
The first gate is to the east, the second to the north, and the third to the south.
The gate in the east is faith, as it brings true light into a person's mind.
The gate in the north is hope, because anyone trapped in sins will perish if they despair of God's mercy.
Therefore, it's essential that someone who was spiritually dead because of their iniquity is revived through the hope of mercy.
Indeed, the gate in the south is charity, because whoever loves God perfectly is ignited with the fire of divine love.
At the southern gate, the sun rises high, because through charity, the light of faith is elevated in the love of God and neighbor.
Through these three gates-faith, hope, and charity-every faithful person is strengthened in the love of God and neighbor and becomes a citizen of the heavenly Jerusalem we speak of.
Now, therefore, dearest brothers, strive to enter through these three gates, and work diligently so that you may be worthy to be citizens in that heavenly city.
If any of you have embraced faith and received baptism without falling into deep sin, be thankful to God and enter the kingdom of heaven through the eastern gate.
For those who have slipped into the cold and darkness of sin after starting their journey of faith, warmth, and light, seek God's forgiveness through heartfelt repentance, and find eternal joy through the northern gate.
Meanwhile, those who are filled with the Holy Spirit, burning with holy desires and virtues, and who delve into the mysteries of inner joy with spiritual insight every day, strive hard to enter the heavenly Jerusalem through the southern gate.
So, brothers and leaders, act accordingly.
Reflect on these matters with thoughtful meditation, and if you find joy in the thought of living in that city, regard all things under heaven as insignificant and quickly move toward it with acts of kindness.
Do not let an abundance of words slow your journey, nor let the sweetness of food hold you back, nor let the comfort of clothing turn you away, nor let physical beauty stop you, nor let human appearances deter you, nor let the love of temporary pleasures delay you, nor let concern for parents divert you from the right path.
Therefore, pursue it with desire and longing; sigh for it from the depths of your heart; willingly shed tears in remembrance of it, and pray to God with all your prayers that you may one day reach it.
Jesus Christ, the Son of God, who is the splendor and power of the Father and who lights up that city with the brightness of His face, may He grant us the grace to reach it through Him, alongside all the saints, and to live there eternally, praising Him with His most sacred praises: who lives and reigns with the Father and the Holy Spirit, God forever and ever.
Amen.
Sermon Two: On the Dedication of the Church Two
Dear brothers, I ask that you listen carefully to what the venerable priest Bede shares for your learning and for the Church.
He says: The house built by Solomon was a symbol of the Church, which, from the first chosen one to the last, is built every day through the grace of the peaceful king, Christ.
Part of this Church is on a journey with Him on earth, while part of it, after the journey, already reigns with Him in heaven, where, after the final judgment, it will reign fully.
Angels are part of this holy Church, and we are promised that we will be like them in the future.
As it is said: They will be equal to the angels and are the children of God, since they are children of the resurrection.
This is from the Gospel of Luke, Chapter 20.
Christ belongs to this Church, as He Himself said: Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up.
He was speaking about the temple of His body, as noted in the Gospel of John, Chapter 2.
The Apostle tells us: Do you not know that you are God's temple?
This is found in First Corinthians, Chapter 3.
He became a temple according to the flesh, and we are made so by the indwelling spirit.
It is clear that the temple symbolized all of us and the Lord Himself, that is, both the members and the head.
He is like the cornerstone, chosen, precious, and laid in the foundation, as mentioned in Isaiah 28.
We, however, are like living stones built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, which is Christ.
This is supported by First Peter, Chapter 2, and Ephesians, Chapter 2, Verse 20.
Considering this order, the construction of the temple itself becomes clearer, showing that some parts relate to Him, some to all the chosen ones, some to the joy of angels in heaven, some to the help given to humans, and some to the rewards for humans' struggles with angels.
Thus, King Solomon chose workers from all of Israel, as described in First Kings, Chapter 5.
He did not choose these workers from all of Israel in vain; it is not just from the lineage of Aaron the priest that they are to be chosen, but from the whole Church.
Those who build the house of God by example and word should be sought and promoted without partiality.
When those chosen to educate non-believers and join the fellowship of the Church are sent, it's like skilled and selected men being sent to Lebanon to cut down cedar trees for temple materials.
A decree was made for 30,000 men to be sent to Lebanon: 10,000 men each month in rotation, allowing them to return home for two months.
These 30,000 symbolize those who are perfect in the faith of the Holy Trinity, making them ideal teachers.
Since 30,000 were appointed to work in groups of ten each month, the significance of the number ten needs explanation.
Ten thousand are sent to cut timber from Israel for the work of the Lord's house.
Those tasked with educating the unwise must uphold all ten commandments and demonstrate to their listeners how to follow them, also showing the heavenly rewards represented by the number ten, which they hope for and communicate to their listeners.
The three-month intervals for each woodcutter symbolize the perfection of the three evangelical virtues: almsgiving, prayer, and fasting.
Through almsgiving, we embrace everything done to express love for our neighbor kindly towards our brothers.
Through prayer, we include everything that unites us with our Creator through internal repentance.
Through fasting, we encompass everything that protects us from vice and worldly temptations, so that with a free mind and pure body, we may always adhere to the love of God and neighbor.
Hiram, the king of Tyre, whose name means "living on high," was in charge of such a decree. "Living on high" refers to Christ, who oversees the temple workers, arranging which months each group should work and when they should return to manage their homes. He intimately instructs the minds of preachers to know when to return and examine their own conscience, as if inspecting their own home, ensuring it is worthy through prayers, fasting, and visitation.
The overseers in charge of the works numbered 3,300, reflecting the faith in the Holy Trinity as proclaimed by Holy Scripture.
However, in Chronicles, 3,600 overseers are mentioned, which refers to their completion.
(Second Chronicles, Chapter 2)
The number six, representing the completion of the world's adornment, symbolizes the perfection of good works.
And since Holy Scripture, with its commitment to truth, instructs us to pursue works of justice, it was fitting that there were 3,600 overseers of the works.
The overseers are the authors of sacred Scripture, whose teachings guide us to educate the ignorant, correct the disrespectful, and support one another.
As such, Solomon had 70,000 burden-bearers and 80,000 stonecutters in the mountains, not including the 3,300 overseers who directed the people and the work.
The 70,000 burden-bearers and 80,000 stonecutters, along with their overseers, were not Israelites but proselytes, meaning foreigners living among them.
In Greek, proselytes referred to those from other nations who joined God's people by accepting circumcision.
Thus, the workers of the house of the Lord were from Israel, proselytes, and other nations.
Scripture also says that the king commanded the use of large, precious stones, carved by Solomon's masons and Hiram's masons-men distinguished in action and holiness, who adhered closely to Christ.
The stronger their hope in Him, the more they loved the lives of others and supported the foundation's breadth.
These are the prophets and apostles who, visibly or invisibly, received the word and sacraments of truth from the wisdom of God Himself.
The foundation of the temple, or the holy Church, is Christ.
As it is said: No one can lay any foundation other than the one already laid, which is Jesus Christ.
(First Corinthians, Chapter 3)
He is rightly called the foundation of the house of God, because, as Peter says, "There is no other name under heaven given to men by which we must be saved" (Acts chapter four).
Hence, it is said, "Built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets, with Christ Jesus himself as the chief cornerstone" (Ephesians chapter two).
Therefore, the saints shaped these stones, referring to the faithful people, so they might leave behind all harmful and empty things, presenting to God only the rule of righteousness in a stable, square form.
For the building of the house of the Lord, first, wood and stones are cut from the mountain; because those we seek to instruct in faith must first be taught to renounce the devil and the transgressions in which they were born.
Then, precious and large stones must be sought and placed in the foundation; so that, having abandoned their previous way of life, we may examine all aspects of their life and conduct, proposing them as examples to be imitated by listeners, whom we know adhere especially to the Lord through the virtue of humility; and we observe that they endure steadfastly, squared against all assaults of temptation.
Great and precious in reputation and worth.
The people of Byblos prepared wood and stones for building the house.
Byblos is a city in Phoenicia and is interpreted as defining or determining.
For those who prepare the hearts of men for the spiritual building, constructed from the virtues of the soul, it is enough to teach their listeners faith and works of righteousness, if they have first been instructed by the sacred writings to learn what faith should be held and which path of virtues should be followed with the certain definition of truth.
In vain does one usurp the office of teacher who is ignorant of the discernment of faith and good works.
Nor does he build a sanctuary for the Lord, but rather ruins for himself, who presumes to teach what he has not learned.
It came to pass in the four hundred eightieth year after the children of Israel came out of the land of Egypt, in the month of Ziv, which is May, the second month of the fourth year of King Solomon's reign over Israel (First Kings chapter six).
For March, in which Passover is celebrated, is the first month of the year for the Hebrews.
After Passover, the construction of the Lord's house commenced.
The people, consecrated by the mystical celebration, embarked on this sacred task.
For 480 years, the worship and religious practices of the tabernacle continued, until the temple began to be built.
The Old Testament Scripture is so perfectly crafted that anyone who understands it well discovers it contains all the mysteries of the New Testament.
Many of the Fathers of the Old Testament lived so perfectly that they are considered on par with the apostles and apostolic men.
With such individuals laying the foundation, the house was built using prepared wood and stones, meticulously arranged after being removed from their original place.
After taking the first steps of faith, a wall of good deeds must be gradually built up, with layers of stones placed higher and higher, progressing from strength to strength.
The house that King Solomon built measured sixty cubits long, twenty cubits wide, and thirty cubits high.
The porch in front of the temple was twenty cubits long.
The length of the house symbolizes the patience of the Church, enduring trials until it reaches the heavenly homeland.
This is represented by sixty cubits, as the number six signifies the perfection of good works.
The width of the house symbolizes charity, which, with an open heart, loves friends in God and enemies for God's sake, until, whether they are converted to peace or completely eliminated, it rejoices with friends alone in God.
It was twenty cubits high, representing the twofold extent of charity, by which we love God and our neighbor.
It was also thirty cubits wide, symbolizing faith in the Trinity, in whose vision all our hopeful desires are suspended.
Each number is multiplied by ten, because through faith and observance of the law, patience is beneficially exercised, charity burns brightly, and hope is elevated to eternal joys.
The height symbolizes the hope of eternal or future reward.
It's about ignoring prosperity or adversity until one can witness the goodness of the Lord in the land of the living.
Psalm twenty-seven, verse thirteen.
The temple represents the Church; and the porch, which received sunlight before the temple, symbolizes that part of the Church that existed before the Lord's incarnation.
This is where the patriarchs and prophets were-those who first received the rising Sun of justice and testified to the Lord born in the flesh through their lives, preaching, being born, and dying.
The righteous of old waited patiently and with endurance for the Lord incarnate to bring the grace of the gospel, seeing and welcoming his promises from afar.
Hebrews eleven.
Therefore, the porch matched the length and width of the temple; because with perseverance in their hearts, they longed to reach the love of the Church, which is in Christ Jesus.
But where did Solomon start building the temple?
On Mount Moriah, which had been shown to David, his father, at the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite.
The house of the Lord is built on the mountain, that is, in Christ.
It is said: And on that day, the mountain of the house of the Lord will be prepared on the top.
Isaiah two.
He is indeed the mountain of mountains, who arose from the earth according to the flesh and surpassed all earthly power and holiness with the height of dignity.
Rightly, he is called the mountain of Moriah, meaning vision; because he finds it worthy to see and help those who labor in this life, preserving them for the eternal vision of glory.
The threshing floor symbolizes the Church.
Hence the gospel says: The Son of God will cleanse his threshing floor, that is, his Church: he will gather the wheat into his barn, but the chaff he will burn with fire.
Matthew three.
Ornan, who is called enlightened, a Jebusite by nation, signifies the Gentiles being enlightened by the Lord and becoming children of the Church.
Hence it is said: You were once darkness, but now you are light in the Lord.
Ephesians five.
Jebus is interpreted as trampled; Jerusalem is called the vision of peace.
While Ornan the Gentile reigned, it was called Jebus; when David bought the place for the burnt offering there.
First Chronicles twenty-one, verses eighteen to twenty-five.
Solomon built the temple of the Lord, which is in Jerusalem.
The people, unaware of divine worship, were often oppressed and mocked by demons.
However, when the grace of the Savior looked upon it, it became a place and name of peace.
That's why it's said:
"Blessed are the peacemakers, for they shall be called sons of God" (Matthew 5).
Solomon also made windows in the temple that were slanted.
These slanted windows had a narrow outer part and a wide inner part.
They're called windows because they let in light.
In Greek, light is called
phos.
Some believe a window is named this way because it provides light to a house, combining Greek and Latin words.
In slanted windows, the section through which light enters is narrow, but the inner section that receives the light is wide.
This symbolizes that while those contemplating may perceive the true light faintly, their minds expand greatly, though they can barely grasp the things they see.
The Lord is the door of the temple, for no one comes to the Father except through Him.
As He Himself says:
"I am the door. If anyone enters by me, he will be saved" (John 10).
The temple faced east, and its porch had a door to the east, opposite the temple door.
This arrangement allowed the rising equinox sun, with its direct rays through the three doors-of the porch, the temple, and the oracle-to illuminate the ark of the covenant.
In the first part of the porch were the first righteous ones, including Abel, Seth, Enoch, Noah, Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, and other Fathers of the Old Testament.
In its innermost part, near the temple wall, were the forerunners of the Lord, like Simeon and Anna, who, although they were worthy to see His birth, could not hear His teachings or receive His sacraments.
The temple did not have a peak on top, similar to the tabernacle, but was flat, as houses are typically built in Palestine and Egypt.
The flooring of the house symbolizes those who excel in the resurrection and have achieved the pinnacle of virtue with remarkable holiness.
To one of these, it is said, "Among those born of women there has not risen anyone greater than John" Matthew 11.
It's important to note that the height of 30 cubits, mentioned earlier, reached up to the middle floor. Then, an additional 30 cubits were added to reach the third floor, extending to the portico around the temple from the south, north, and west, as described by Josephus.
From there, up to the temple's top roof, there were 60 cubits, making the total height of the temple 120 cubits, according to Chronicles.
The complete height of the temple being 120 cubits represents the early Church, which received the gift of the Holy Spirit with this number of people Acts 1.
Fittingly, the completion of the Lord's house occurs on this third floor because, after the current labors of the faithful and after receiving future rest for their souls, the full happiness of the entire Church will be realized in the resurrection.
Therefore, Solomon built the house and finished it: and he built the walls of the house inside with cedar boards.
The walls inside are covered with cedar boards when the hearts of the faithful overflow with the love of virtues. Just as cedar represents perfect individuals, it also signifies, in appropriate contexts, the height of virtues through which one achieves that perfection.
From the floor of the house to the top, and to the ceiling, he covered it inside with wood.
Everything is covered with wood from the floor of the house to the top and to the ceilings, much like the chosen ones from the beginnings of faith to the culmination of good deeds, and to the complete entrance into the heavenly homeland, strive with good works.
When the righteous, from the first to the last in the end of the age, all pursue virtues, by whose merit they may boldly declare: "We are to God the pleasing aroma of Christ" Second Corinthians 2.
And he covered the floor of the house with planks of fir.
This is explained more fully in the book of Chronicles, where it says: "He covered the floor of the temple with the finest marble, in all its beauty" (2 Chronicles 3).
From this, we understand that the wooden boards of fir used for the floor were not laid directly on the ground.
First, it was covered with marble, then the wooden boards were placed on top, and finally, both were overlaid with gold.
The evenness of the temple floor represents the harmony and humility of the saints.
The stones of the wall or floor, the wooden boards, and the gold all represent different aspects of the saints' lives.
The "living stones" are the saints, joined together in one rule of life by the strength of their faith. The cedar or fir boards represent the variety of virtues, joined together by one faith through the gifts of the Holy Spirit.
The white marble that the temple was built from symbolizes the pure actions of the elect and a conscience purified from all stain of corruption. As Scripture says: "Let us cleanse ourselves from all defilement of body and spirit, perfecting holiness in the fear of God" (2 Corinthians 7).
The sheets of gold represent the love that surpasses all knowledge.
It also says: "He built a structure of twenty cubits at the back of the temple, lined with cedar from the floor to the top, and made the inner sanctuary; the Holy of Holies."
The front room, where the priests regularly entered to perform sacrifices, represents the present Church. In this Church, we constantly carry out good works and offer sacrifices of praise to the Lord.
The inner room, located at the back of the temple, represents eternal life in heaven. It is "interior" because it is hidden from our earthly life of exile; it is where the unending celebration of the blessed takes place in the presence of the King. This is why it is written: "Enter into the joy of your Lord" (Matthew 25).
Yet it is called "the back" or "posterior" because it comes after the labors of this world.
Furthermore, the main part of the temple, in front of the inner sanctuary, was forty cubits long. The entire house was covered in cedar, beautifully crafted with carvings and joints.
The number forty symbolizes the work and struggle of this present life, just as the number fifty symbolizes future rest and peace.
There are ten commandments that lead to life; the number ten symbolizes the life we desire and strive for.
The square represents the world where we work to achieve this, as it is written: He gathered them from the lands, from the east, north, and sea.
Psalms One hundred and seven.
The house, with its cedar panels, features carvings and crafted joints.
The chosen are linked with a beautiful bond of love, having one heart and one soul.
The carvings added to the joints of the panels form a complete panel, representing the duties of love that unite the holy brotherhood into one house of Christ throughout the world.
The oracle where the ark was located had dimensions of twenty cubits in length, width, and height, making it square.
In the heavenly homeland, where the saints see Christ the King, only the grace of divine love shines through everything.
It follows: And it covered and clothed it with purest gold, because the grace of love fills the walls of the heavenly city.
The altar of incense, which was before the oracle, is described: And covered the whole altar of the oracle with gold.
From this, we understand that the altar, made of stone, was covered with cedar and then overlaid with gold.
The cedar wall of the inner house had an opening at the top through which the smoke of incense would enter; because the eyes of the Lord are open upon His house day and night, and His ears are attentive to the prayers of His servants, extending throughout the Church across the world.
The inner house, the secret of heaven, represents the ark of the covenant, the Savior, in whom we have the covenant of peace with the Father.
After the resurrection, He ascended into heaven and placed the flesh taken from the Virgin at the right hand of the Father.
It is called an oracle when divine or angelic speech is granted to humans with the revelation of secrets.
Thus, fittingly, the oracle was made in hidden places, that is, in the inner house; because in the heavenly homeland, the vision and conversation of angels and the presence of God Himself will be revealed.
So, it's said: The time will come when I won't speak to you in parables anymore, but will tell you directly about the Father.
John Chapter Sixteen.
And again: I will love him and reveal myself to him.
John Chapter Fourteen.
The area in front of the oracle was covered with pure gold; because those who are perfect in this life can't yet fully understand a parable about the Father, nor see clearly.
But they still enhance the work of justice with divine love, so it doesn't seem lifeless or idle, allowing them to earn the full knowledge of God.
The golden nails fastening the golden plates represent the commandments of love and promises of eternal glory.
Through these, as we practice virtues, we are held together by Christ's grace, so we don't falter.
And he covered the entire altar of the oracle with gold.
This altar symbolizes the life of those who are perfect, who, being near the oracle, have moved away from trivial pleasures to focus solely on entering the kingdom.
Thus, on this altar, they didn't burn the flesh of sacrifices, only incense.
Because such individuals don't need to battle the sins of the flesh and the allurements of thoughts within themselves, but instead offer the fragrances of prayers and spiritual desires through the fire of eternal love in the presence of the Creator.
However, when the house was being built, it was constructed with hewn and perfect stones; no hammer, axe, or iron tool was heard in the house during its construction.
Because the faithful, who are part of the heavenly building, should not quarrel, murmur, slander, or engage in unnecessary matters, but live in peace and harmony.
In silence, the house of God thrives and is constructed.
For the congregation of the elect, which is the dwelling of the eternal King, it's fitting to refrain from all worldly noise.
And he made two cherubim in the oracle out of olive wood, each ten cubits high.
Cherubim is the term for angelic dignity: singularly cherub, but plural as cherubim.
Through cherubim, we can understand the angelic ministries that always attend the Creator in heaven.
The olive wood is said to be ten cubits high.
Since the angels are anointed with spiritual grace, they never lose their devotion to God, who filled them with heavenly wisdom from the moment He created them.
The two cherubim can symbolize the two testaments.
These cherubim were placed in the oracle because it was determined in the divine providence, inaccessible and incomprehensible to us, long before time, when and how, and by which authors, the Scripture would be established.
Two cherubim were crafted to signify the fellowship of love, because love cannot exist with fewer than two.
This is why the disciples were sent to preach in pairs, as mentioned in the Gospel of Luke, chapter ten.
When the wings are fixed in the minds of holy people, they signify virtues, through which they ascend to and engage with heavenly matters.
When they symbolize angels, they represent the grace of their perpetual and unfailing happiness, as they always remain in the heavenly service of their Creator.
Or, because they possess the lightness of spiritual nature, they can reach anywhere they wish, as if flying.
Each cherub has a wing five cubits long, because in the ever-changing world, holy people extend their physical senses in service to the Creator, always looking to the Lord, to listen for and desire His praise, and to recount all His wonders.
They are ten cubits high because they enjoy the reward of eternal life, maintaining the inviolate image of the Creator, and preserving the sanctity, justice, and truth in which they were created.
A denarius consists of ten obols and typically bears the name and image of the king.
The two cherubim are of one work and measure because there is no discord in will in the heavenly homeland, where all are enlightened by the same vision and glory of the present God.
Therefore, the inner wings of the cherubim touched each other over the ark because they agreed in equal testimony about the Lord.
The outer wings touch one wall, while the others touch another wall.
This signifies that the Old Testament was specifically written for the ancient people of God, and the New Testament for us who have come to faith after the incarnation of the Lord.
These are compared to the northern wall because they have been given the chance to know the light of truth after the cold and darkness of idolatry.
They extend their wings to each other over the ark, attributing the good they have received to the praise of the Creator.
They also extend their wings to both walls of the oracle, joyfully encouraging the righteous of both peoples in the heavenly homeland with the vision of their own glory to praise the Creator.
They do not only rejoice in the happiness of the righteous who are with them inside, but they also care for us, who, still outside, cry out to the Lord from the depths.
Hence, it is written about them in Chronicles: They stood with their feet upright, and their faces were turned toward the outer house, as stated in Second Chronicles chapter three; because they never strayed from the path of truth on which they were placed when created, and they desire us, rescued from the hardships of this pilgrimage, to reach their fellowship.
They stand with their feet upright, extending their wings, covered with gold, to the walls of the oracle, with their faces turned toward the outer house.
Angels continuously maintain their innocence and rejoice in the blessedness of holy souls in heaven, while also bringing help to those still wandering on earth, until they lead them to the heavenly homeland.
For they are all ministering spirits, sent in service for those who will inherit salvation, as mentioned in Hebrews chapter one.
And he carved all the walls of the temple around with various carvings and a lathe.
The walls are carved with a lathe when the faithful are strong of heart to do what the Lord commands, saying each time: I will bless the Lord at all times; His praise shall continually be in my mouth, as found in Psalm thirty-four.
And again: My heart is ready, O God, from Psalm fifty-seven.
Because turning excels other crafts in speed and adheres to its own rules to work without error, it beautifully represents the virtuous life of the saints.
They are always ready to serve the Lord and carry out His will without straying, having learned through long practice of virtues.
It creates various images, as if emerging from the wall, much like how God grants countless virtues to the faithful, such as compassion, kindness, humility, patience, modesty, and above all, love, which is the bond of perfection.
Colossians chapter three, verse fourteen.
The evenness of the pavement symbolizes the humble harmony of brotherhood, where Jews and Gentiles, barbarians and Scythians, free individuals and slaves, nobles and commoners, all take pride in being brothers in Christ and having the same Father in heaven.
Thus, Solomon covered the floor of the house with gold on the inside, because Christ filled angels and the souls of the righteous in heaven with the full gift of perfection.
He marked those traveling in the world as citizens of the heavenly homeland with the seal of eternal love, setting them apart from the baseness of mortals.
At the entrance to the oracle, he made two doors of olive wood with five-sided posts.
There was one entrance, but it was closed by two doors and opened by the same, just as the temple and the porch in front of the temple had only one entrance, because there is one Lord, one faith, one baptism, one God and Father of all.
Ephesians chapter four, verses five to six.
There are two doors because the holy angels and humans love God and their neighbor; they cannot enter the gate of life except through this double love.
The posts have five sides because not only do the souls of the chosen enter the heavenly hall, but also, at judgment, the gates open to bodies endowed with immortal glory.
For there are five senses of the body.
Therefore, each post of the oracle is five cubits high, because the entrance to the heavenly homeland is opened only to those who serve the Lord with all the senses of the heart and body.
And he carved images of cherubim, palm trees, and prominent engravings on the doors.
He covered them with gold, overlaying the cherubim, the palm trees, and the other parts with gold.
The term "anaglypha" in Greek is referred to as "engraving" in Latin.
The Church, through holy and perfect individuals entrusted with the care of the faithful and the keys to the kingdom of heaven, should diligently focus on works of virtue.
They should stand out in good deeds as much as they do in rank.
They have the carved image of cherubim when they strive to live a heavenly life on earth, both in mind and action.
They embody the images of palm trees when they focus steadfastly on the heavenly reward.
For the palm is the ornament of the victor's hand.
They have prominent engravings when they present undeniable evidence of good works, which cannot be misinterpreted.
He made square posts of olive wood at the temple's entrance, and two doors of fir wood on either side.
Each door was double and opened together.
Just as the entrance to the oracle, where one reaches the Ark of the Lord and the cherubim, symbolizes the entrance to heaven, where we long to see God and the heavenly citizens, so too, the entrance into the temple signifies the beginnings of our conversion to God as we enter the Church.
This represents our entrance to faith, and the other to the vision.
The posts of this entrance are square because of the four books of the Gospel, whose teachings guide us in the faith of truth.
Alternatively, they are considered square due to the four principal virtues: prudence, fortitude, justice, and temperance, which form the solid foundation of all good deeds.
Prudence teaches us what we ought to do and how to live.
Fortitude empowers us to do what we have learned should be done.
The Prophet aptly encapsulates this, saying: "The Lord is my light and my salvation" (Psalm twenty-seven).
Light, meaning to teach what we ought to do.
Indeed, salvation confirms that these actions are necessary.
Temperance helps us discern not to seek more or less than what is fair in terms of wisdom or courage.
Since anyone who uses wisdom, courage, and temperance is truly just, justice naturally follows as the fourth virtue after wisdom, courage, and temperance.
The entrance to the inner house had two doors, not double but single; because in eternal happiness, faith and hope are not needed, where what we believe and hope for now, we will see clearly.
A veil was added to these doors, as it is written in Chronicles: "He made a veil of blue, purple, crimson, and fine linen, and embroidered cherubim on it" (Second Chronicles 3), for beauty, so the silk would shine amidst the gilded walls.
Therefore, the careful opening of this veil, which is the revelation to those entering, signifies the opening of the law and the heavenly kingdom, granted to us through the incarnation of Christ.
Hence, when the Lord was baptized, the heavens opened (Matthew 3), showing that through the baptism He consecrated for us, we should enter the gateway to heaven.
And when He died, the same veil was torn in two from top to bottom (Matthew 27), indicating that the symbols of the law were now complete, and the truth of the Gospel and the secrets of heaven, along with the entrance to heaven itself, were no longer symbolically represented, but openly accessible to everyone who transitioned from the world in faith in the truth from the beginning of the world.
Thus, the same veil under which one entered the oracle was made of blue, purple, crimson, and fine linen, with cherubim embroidered on it.
Blue, which mimics the color of the sky, is compared to the desires for heavenly things.
Purple, created from the blood of shellfish and showing a blood-red appearance, signifies the sacrament of the Lord's passion, which we must imitate by carrying our own cross.
In crimson, the red color represents the power of God's love.
As it is said: "Was not our heart burning within us?" (Luke 24).
Fine linen, made from flax, starts as green in the earth.
Through the skilled hands of craftsmen, it loses its green color and becomes white, symbolizing the discipline of the body.
This is why the Apostle says, "Put to death your earthly members, such as sexual immorality, impurity, lust, etc." (Colossians 3).
He also encourages us to aim for purity when he says, "I urge you to present your bodies as a living sacrifice, holy and pleasing to God, etc." (Romans 12).
Cherubim are woven with the same colors.
In all our pious actions, we are shielded from the harmful arrows of demons by the protection of angels, with the Lord's help.
Next, he built the inner courtyard with three rows of polished stones and one row of cedar wood.
This construction of the temple within the courtyard represents the life of perfect priests in the Church, who, through their virtues, draw closer to the Lord and guide others towards salvation through their words and actions.
Priests are commanded to provide leadership in sacred matters to those of lower rank.
This includes not only the ministers of the altar, like bishops and priests, but also those who excel in doctrine and conduct, benefiting both themselves and others.
As they present their bodies as a living, holy, and pleasing sacrifice to God (Romans 12), they spiritually fulfill their priestly duties.
Thus, Peter addresses the whole Church: "But you are a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for God's own possession" (First Peter 2).
It is written that there were three courtyards around the temple.
When the high priest entered the Holy of Holies, purified priests stood in the temple itself.
Those who were not purified, along with the Levites, singers, and praying Jewish men, stood in the inner courtyard under the open sky, weather permitting.
If there was a storm, they would move to nearby porticoes.
In the outer courtyard were purified Jewish women, and in the furthest courtyard were Gentiles and Jews who had recently come from the Gentiles, up to the sixth day of purification.
Regarding these courtyards, the Psalmist sang:
"Look, now bless the Lord, all you servants of the Lord, who stand in the house of the Lord, in the courtyards of the house of our God" (Psalm One Hundred Thirty-Three).
In these courtyards and porticos, Jeremiah, other prophets, the Lord, and the apostles preached.
In one of these, the Lord sat and taught when the Pharisees, trying to test him, brought him a woman caught in adultery to judge (John Eight).
In these places stood those selling sheep, oxen, and doves, whom he drove out of the temple (John Two).
In these, Peter and John healed a lame man they found (Acts Three).
In these, the whole crowd of people was praying when an angel appeared to Zechariah, who was offering incense at the altar, and taught him about the birth of the Lord's forerunner (Luke One).
The crowd would approach the priest's courtyard and bring sacrifices to the gate, which the priests received, watching as they were placed on the altar.
Even when the temple itself was opened, they would gaze at it from afar, yet they could not even enter the priest's courtyard but would call out to the Lord from the lower parts.
For the simplicity of the faithful in the Church is not despised by the Lord when they faithfully offer what acts of piety they can.
They look into the temple from afar when they rejoice in learning and admiring the lives of the exalted; and those they cannot follow in the imitation of virtue, they embrace with affectionate veneration.
A single order of cedar wood represents good deeds performed without the corruption of pretense, without which faith, hope, and love cannot truly exist.
For cedar wood, because of its pleasant fragrance and incorruptible natural strength, signifies perseverance and the reputation of pious actions.
In the fourth year of King Solomon's reign, the house of the Lord was founded in the month of Ziv, which is May;
and in the eleventh year of his reign, in the month of Bul, which is October, the house was completed in all its works and furnishings.
That the house was completed in the eighth year and eighth month in all its works pertains to the future age and day of judgment, so that nothing more can be added to it.
Then Christ will reveal the Father to us, and that will be all we need.
John fourteen.
The Day of Judgment is symbolically represented by the number eight because it comes after this era, which unfolds over seven days.
He built it in seven years and completed it in the eighth, as the Church is constructed throughout this entire age, spanning a seven-day cycle from selected souls, and reaches its perfect state at the end of the age.
It also signifies spiritual grace, which allows the Church to truly be the Church: because without the gifts of the Holy Spirit, no one can become faithful, maintain their faith, or achieve the crown of righteousness through the merit of faith.
Hiram, the craftsman from Tyre, whom Solomon chose as his assistant, symbolizes preachers selected from the nations.
His widowed mother represents the current Church, for whom Christ, after experiencing death, rose again and ascended into heaven, leaving her to wander on earth.
Her children are the preachers and the faithful.
Thus, it is said: "Instead of your fathers, sons have been born to you," etc.
Psalm forty-five.
He crafted two bronze columns, each eighteen cubits high, with a circumference of twelve cubits.
Three times six makes eighteen; three relates to faith because of the Trinity, and six to action because the world was created in six days.
Three is multiplied by six when the righteous live by faith, gathering the knowledge of devout faith through the assurance of good deeds.
Habakkuk two.
The twelve-cubit circumference of each column represents the doctrine of the apostles.
Therefore, the standard of apostolic teaching surrounds each column when a teacher, sent to preach to Jews or Gentiles, ensures to do and teach only what they have received from the apostles and learned from the Church.
If someone wants to live or preach differently and ignore the apostolic decrees, they are not considered a pillar in the temple of God.
When they dismiss following the apostolic statutes, whether out of laziness or arrogance, they do not meet the twelve-cubit standard.
The two pillars symbolize the apostles and all teachers who are strong in faith and deeds, and elevated in contemplation.
There are two pillars so that through preaching, they may bring both the uncircumcised and the circumcised into the Church.
The pillars at the temple's entrance represent the ministers of the word guiding both peoples to the path of heaven.
The two capitals placed on top of the pillars represent the two testaments, to which the teachers dedicate both their minds and bodies in meditation and observance.
Each capital is five cubits high because the Mosaic Law is contained in five books.
The entire Old Testament also spans five ages of the world.
The New Testament, however, preaches only what Moses and the prophets foretold should be preached.
This is why it is said: If you believed Moses, you might believe me too, as mentioned in the Book of John, Chapter 5.
And he crafted designs of a network and chains, skillfully intertwined.
The designs of chains and the network pattern in the capitals symbolize the variety of spiritual virtues in the saints.
Hence, it is said: The queen stood at your right hand, from Psalm 45, meaning adorned in radiant love, encircled by a variety of different gifts.
The intricate interweaving of chains and the spreading net suggests the diverse roles of the teachers.
By faithfully adhering to the words of the preachers, they are like those placed on top of the column capitals, showcasing the wonder of their interconnectedness to all.
These chains are marvelously intertwined because it is through the wondrous grace of the Holy Spirit that the lives of the faithful, despite differing in place, time, rank, condition, sex, and age, are united by one faith and love.
There were seven networks of verses on each capital.
The number seven symbolizes spiritual grace.
This is why it's said: Seven spirits of God are sent into all the earth.
Revelation Five.
Thus, each capital had seven networks of verses because the Fathers of both Testaments were granted the grace of the one sevenfold Spirit to be chosen.
He completed the columns, adding two rows around each network to cover the capitals on top of the pomegranates.
These networks were designed to cover the capitals, encircling them completely.
When Holy Scripture is fully understood, it speaks of the grace of love and peace.
The capitals represent the divine volumes.
The networks symbolize the bonds of mutual love.
The capitals are adorned with networks when sacred words are enhanced with the gift of love.
Even in parts of Scripture we don't understand, love is hidden, and in those we do, it is clearly revealed.
The capitals on top of the columns were crafted to resemble lilies in a porch of four cubits.
The lilies signify the brightness of the heavenly homeland and the pleasantness of paradise, fragrant with the flowers of immortality.
The four cubits represent the evangelical message that promises eternal happiness and shows the path to reach it.
When holy teachers reveal the promised lights of the heavenly kingdom through the four books of the Gospel, they present, in essence, the heads of the columns as the work of lilies of four cubits.
Additionally, other capitals were placed on top of the columns, matching the column's measure against the networks.
The craftsmanship of these capitals symbolizes the exalted nature of the everlasting kingdom, which no eye has seen, no ear has heard, nor has it entered into the heart of man, what God has prepared for those who love Him.
First Corinthians Two.
After the four-cubit lilies, other capitals were placed, whose height is unspecified.
We read much about heavenly happiness in the Gospel, noting that the pure in heart will see God there.
Matthew.
They will be equal to the angels of God.
They will neither marry nor be given in marriage (Matthew 22).
They will no longer be able to die (Luke 20).
And where Christ is, there also His servants will be (John 12), along with many other things that are fully revealed only to the citizens of His heavenly city.
Just as many seeds are enclosed within a single outer shell of a pomegranate, so the holy Church, under one shield of faith, contains countless groups of the elect.
It is fitting that the tops of the temple's columns were decorated all around with pomegranates.
This is because the holy teachers recall to mind the lives of the faithful who came before them, and they surround their own words and actions with the examples of those saints.
If they lived differently, they would go astray.
Therefore, the pomegranates represent the whole Church.
It is said that there were two hundred rows of pomegranates surrounding the tops of both columns.
The number one hundred; which is the first to be placed on the right-hand side; represents eternal happiness.
The doubling of the number on the second column signifies that the people of both the Old and New Testaments are to be united in Christ and brought into the eternal crown of life.
It says: "He set up two columns at the entrance to the temple. When he had set up the right-hand column, he called it Jachin, which means 'firmness.' Then he set up the second column and called it Boaz, which means 'in strength.'"
The right-hand column represents those who, through prophecy, foretold that the Lord would come in the flesh. The left-hand column represents those who now testify that He has already come and redeemed the world.
Both columns have similar names: one is called firmness, the other strength; showing that all teachers should have the strength of both faith and good works. This also subtly criticizes the weakness of our times, where some who want to be seen as teachers, priests, and pillars of God's house actually lack firm faith; the kind that despises worldly vanities and longs for unseen, eternal things.
They also lack strength to correct others, and not even the effort to understand the errors of those placed under their care.
It also says: "He made a large, cast metal sea, ten cubits from rim to rim, perfectly round all around."
The sea represents baptism because from the first person baptized in the way of Jesus Christ to the last believer to be baptized at the end of time, all believers must journey along the same path of truth and hope, aiming for the common crown of righteousness from the Lord.
Its height was five cubits, symbolizing that whatever sins we've committed through sight, hearing, taste, smell, and touch, God's grace forgives us through the cleansing of the life-giving fountain.
However, forgiveness of past sins isn't enough unless one strives for good deeds afterward.
Otherwise, the devil, having left the person, may return more powerfully if he finds them idle in good works, making their last state worse than the first.
Matthew twelve.
Through the priests who were washed in this sea, all the chosen ones are represented, as members of the high priest, Jesus Christ.
Thus, it is said: You are a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people of his own.
First Peter two.
This vessel is rightly called the sea, in remembrance of the Red Sea, where the form of baptism was prefigured through the destruction of the Egyptians.
This is why it is said: Our ancestors were all under the cloud, and all passed through the sea.
First Corinthians ten.
A rope of thirty cubits encircled it.
The rope signifies the discipline of heavenly precepts that keep us away from worldly pleasures.
Thus, it is said: A threefold cord is not easily broken.
Ecclesiastes four.
Because the observance of the commandments, strengthened in the hearts of the chosen by faith, hope, and love for the heavenly reward, cannot be broken by any obstacle.
The rope encircles the sea when we strive to uphold the sacrament of baptism we've received with devout works.
The rope of thirty cubits encircled it because when our Lord Jesus Christ was thirty years old, he came to baptism.
Luke three.
Since he consecrated our baptism by his baptism at thirty years, it is fitting that the sea, symbolizing our baptism, was encircled by a rope of thirty cubits.
There were also two rows of cast sculptured oxen.
Sculpture is crafted to tell stories, often depicting various historical events.
Through sculptures surrounding the sea, we see examples from the past that illustrate how holy people have pleased God from the beginning.
Scripture says: "And they stood below twelve oxen, three facing north, three facing east, three facing west, and three facing south, with the sea above them: and their backs were hidden within."
These oxen symbolize the apostles, evangelists, and all ministers of the Word.
This is why it is written: "You shall not muzzle an ox while it is treading out the grain," from Deuteronomy chapter twenty-five.
These oxen support the sea above them, just as the apostles and their successors carry out the Gospel's mission with eager devotion.
Three face north, and so on, because they preach the faith of the Trinity to all corners of the world.
Thus, the twelve apostles are chosen in groups of three to spread the faith and confession of the Trinity to the four corners of the world, baptizing all nations in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
Today, we can easily read and understand their words, actions, and sufferings, as well as those of their successors.
However, we cannot yet see the glory of their future reward.
The laver's thickness was three inches, symbolizing how the reception of baptism is strengthened by faith, hope, and charity.
It benefits recipients only when the firm certainty of these three virtues confirms their minds and actions.
The rim of the sea was like the rim of a cup and the leaf of a spreading lily.
A lily, with its graceful fragrance, presents a white scent outwardly and a golden hue within.
This suggests the glory of His resurrection, as He showed His disciples the immortality of the body and taught that a soul shining with divine light was also within.
Before His passion, Christ was like a lily still closed, shining brightly in His miracles.
After the resurrection and ascension, he presented himself as the lily of heaven to the birds, meaning the angels and all the saints.
In the humanity he had taken on, he revealed the power of divine glory that he had before the world existed.
Hence it is said: "I am the flower of the field and the lily of the valleys" (Song of Solomon 2).
The edge of the sea, where the priests walked, resembled the rim of a chalice and the petal of an open lily.
This symbolizes the baptism that cleanses the members of the high priest from sins through faith in his passion.
Once purified, it leads us to the vision of his glory.
It was foretold that a cord of 30 cubits would encircle the sea, and a carving under the edge would measure 10 cubits around.
It's clear that the vessel was shaped like a wide-mouthed bowl, narrowing from the 30 cubits around the edge down to 10.
The sea held 2,000 baths or 3,000 measures.
A bath contained one and a half measures.
A bath is a Hebrew measure, called 'bath' by them, holding three bushels.
It's the same as the ephah, which they call 'epha'; however, the ephah pertains to the measure of grains, while the bath is for liquids like wine, water, and oil.
Therefore, the bath, as a standard measure, signifies works of fairness and justice by which those baptized for the forgiveness of sins must be established.
The sea holds 1,000 baths when, washing the Jewish people with baptismal water, it transmits them to the heavenly kingdom.
It also receives another 1,000 when it makes the Gentiles, reborn from the same source and confirmed by works of justice, participants in the same kingdom.
He also made ten bronze bases, each four cubits long, four cubits wide, and four cubits high.
The work of the bases was hollow, meaning it was carved on the inside.
In many ways and by many means, the same sacraments of our salvation are represented.
The apostles and apostolic men are depicted as carrying the sea like oxen, symbolized by the bases designed to carry the basins.
These basins also represented spiritual cleansing, much like the sea.
As noted in the Chronicles, these basins were used to wash everything offered as a burnt offering.
Second Chronicles Chapter Four.
The burnt offering of the Lord generally signifies the entire multitude of the elect, who are baptized in the Holy Spirit and fire.
Just as the priests who washed in the sea represent those who, through baptism, become companions of the high priest, Christ, so the burnt offerings symbolize these same people.
They are filled with the grace of the Holy Spirit through baptism.
The sacrifice is washed in the basin when the faithful are baptized.
It is offered as a burnt offering when they receive the gift of the Holy Spirit through the laying on of the bishop's hands.
The bases were four cubits long and wide.
Preachers endure the adversities of the world, the length of exile, and current struggles, expanding their hearts with internal joy in the love of God and neighbor.
They strive for virtues, wisely discerning internal good and evil, enduring adversities with courage, tempering their hearts against the desire for pleasures, and maintaining justice in their actions.
There were carvings among the joints, binding the boards of the basins together, forming one base from four or five boards.
The carvings on these bases, located on their sides, front and back, right and left, and above the circles, are described as:
Among the garlands and twisted chains, lions, oxen, and cherubim, as well as above the joints.
The boards from which the bases were made were square, featuring round designs called garlands or twisted chains, with carvings in between.
No part of the base's surface was flat; it was carved everywhere with mystical figures.
The minds of the saints, and indeed their entire conduct, display the grace of virtues.
No time goes by without them being engaged in pious works, conversations, or thoughts.
They have crowns engraved, symbolizing their tireless yearning for entry into eternal life.
They have braids, representing the unbroken bond between their desire for heavenly life above and their love for their brothers beside them.
Among the crowns and braids, there are lions, as they elevate their minds with hope for heavenly things and expand their love for neighbors, sometimes appearing stern and correcting those who have strayed and are entrusted to them.
Together with lions, they also have oxen, reflecting the blend of gentleness and sternness in correction.
They continually maintain split hooves, symbolizing their careful discretion in action and speech.
They always chew the cud, as they consistently ponder the words of divine reading.
After the crowns and braids, after the lions and oxen, cherubim are said to be sculpted, representing the vast knowledge of the Scriptures.
For the teachers of the faithful, the more diligently they devote themselves to the divine Scriptures, the more they fear God's judgment in the severity of discretion with which they judge sinners and in the gentleness of mercy with which they forgive penitents, lest by unjustly binding or loosing, they themselves be justly bound by Him whose judgment cannot err.
And above the lions and oxen, there are straps hanging as if made of bronze.
These straps signify the power to bind and loose, which is granted by the Lord Jesus Christ to church leaders in Peter and his successors.
It further states: And four wheels for each base, and bronze axles, on which the bases were; and on the four sides, there were cast supports under the basin, facing each other, to carry it.
The four wheels represent the four books of the Gospels; just as a rolling wheel quickly goes wherever it's led, by the Lord's command, the apostles filled the whole world in a short time.
Just as a chariot raised by a wheel lifts off the ground, going wherever the driver directs it, the books of the Gospels elevate the minds of the chosen from earthly things to heavenly realms.
They guide them towards action or the mystery of preaching, wherever the grace of the Spirit wishes to assist.
As it is added: Such were the wheels, typically made for a chariot.
We also read about the saints: The chariots of God are tens of thousands, thousands of rejoicing ones; the Lord is among them.
Psalm 68.
The small supports placed in front of the wheels, preventing them from slipping from the axles, symbolize the proclamations of the prophets, which confirm the evangelical and apostolic Scripture, leaving no doubt for the readers.
Thus it is said: We have a more certain prophetic word, to which you do well to pay attention, as to a lamp shining in a dark place.
Second Peter 1.
The axles of the wheels that support the foundations represent the hearts of the teachers, lifting them through constant evangelical teachings.
Just as the wheels raise the axles from the ground, the bases are elevated higher.
Conversely, the mouth of the basin turned inward; the opening was one cubit, the bottom one and a half cubits, while the belly was believed to be four cubits, illustrating that the path to heavenly things is opened through baptism.
What appeared externally was entirely round at one cubit, symbolizing the unity of confession and faith, in which everyone is baptized in the confession of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
Hence it is said: One Lord, one faith, one baptism, One God and Father of all, who is above all.
Ephesians 4.
It also had one and a half cubits, representing the perfection of work and the merit of contemplation.
A whole cubit in the basin indicates the perfection of good action, which holy people achieve with the help of divine grace.
In the corners of the columns, or on the sides of the bases, there were various carvings, and in the middle between the columns, it was square, not round.
The middle between the columns refers to the upper board, which, like the others, was square and similarly carved, and at its top, it had a roundness of one and a half cubits, where the basin was placed.
The wheels measure one and a half cubits, symbolizing how the Gospel Scripture guides those striving for perfection and promises the gift of eternal reward.
The bases, one cubit and a half wide at the top, were designed to hold basins.
This signifies how teachers and ministers, perfected in their work, shone in life but only partially received the light of contemplation.
Hence, it is said:
"For we know in part, and we prophesy in part" (First Corinthians 13).
Each basin held 40 baths.
The number 40 represents great perfection because it is the product of four times ten.
The ten commandments serve as the foundation for all actions under God's law, and the four books of the Gospels reveal the path to the heavenly homeland through the Lord's incarnation.
Since all who partake in baptism should demonstrate right actions through faith and the Gospel's sacraments, each basin, used for washing burnt offerings, held 40 baths.
Ten bases were set up, five on each side of the temple.
These sides are outside the temple, facing east in the inner court, known as the priests' court.
Five bases were placed on the right side for the Jews, who followed the sun of righteousness through the law's teachings.
Five were on the left for us, who, with blind hearts for longer, followed the one who said,
"I will ascend to the north and be like the Most High" (Isaiah 14).
As if to say: I wish to rest in hearts that I desire to be distant from the light of truth and the flame of divine charity.
The sea was placed on the right side of the temple in the same court.
As you enter the courtyard from the east, you first turn south, where the sea is located in the very corner, ready for the priests to wash.
As you move further inside, you'll find basins on either side for washing the sacrifices.
Additionally, there's a bronze base measuring five cubits long, five cubits wide, and three cubits high, where Solomon stood to dedicate the temple.
Hiram also crafted bronze cauldrons to collect the ashes from the altar.
He made pans, which are bronze vessels with equal width at the base and top for heating.
He also created hooks, vessels specifically for offering wine.
The clay soil used for making the molds of the vessels represents Scripture, from which we derive the principles for living well.
Just as clay hardened by fire forms vessels, Scripture provides us with the rule of justice we should follow.
The golden table where the bread is placed symbolizes Scripture, clear in spiritual understanding, as it is written:
"You prepared a table before me" (Psalm 23).
The bread of the proposition represents the holy teachers, whose works or words serve as examples in the divine pages, and those who seek well, find.
Therefore, twelve loaves were commanded to be made in Exodus, representing the twelve apostles, through whom the New Testament Scripture was established and the mysteries of the Old revealed.
In the chronicles, we read that Solomon made tables in the temple, five on the right and five on the left, where they placed the vessels of the Lord, including cups, bowls, incense burners, and mortars (Second Chronicles 4).
Just as one table with twelve loaves signifies the harmonious unity of Scripture, which nourishes us and is strengthened by apostolic authority, the ten tables proclaim the words of the law and the prophets, presenting us with examples of the faithful, much like the proposed vessels of the Lord's clarity and miracles.
The tables are fivefold because the law encompasses both the five books of Moses and the five ages of the world.
Twice; because after the incarnation of the Lord, it is entrusted to both peoples: the Jewish and the Gentile.
He established ten golden lampstands, five on the right and five on the left, opposite the oracle, all made of pure gold.
These lampstands had flowers shaped like lilies and golden lamps on top.
The flowers resemble lilies because the top part of the lampstands was designed to look like spreading lilies.
The golden lamps represent the vessels where the oil shines.
Just as tables appear in Scripture to serve the bread of the word and carry the vessels of ministry-demonstrating the actions of the just as examples for us-the lampstands symbolize bringing the light of wisdom to those who wander.
As Solomon said, "The commandment is a lamp, and the law is light" (Proverbs chapter six).
David also says, "Your word is a lamp to my feet and a light to my path" (Psalm one hundred nineteen).
The five lampstands on the right and five on the left complement what was mentioned earlier about the tables.
The oracle, where the ark resided, represents the entrance to the heavenly homeland where Christ sits at the right hand of the Father, knowing the secrets of the fathers.
The lampstands opposite the oracle signify that the words of God direct us toward the heavenly city, encouraging us to earn it.
He also made golden tongs, which are the snuffers used to trim the lamps, allowing them to shine brighter when maintained.
The snuffers represent the two testaments that purge sins, united by the Holy Spirit.
The jars symbolize the hearts of the saints, filled with the water of wisdom and the wine of contrition.
The forks, used for preparing meats, represent preachers who provide the food of understanding to their listeners, distributing the body and blood to the faithful and withholding it from unbelievers.
The bowls symbolize teachers filled with useful teachings.
Mortars represent the labor and suffering of penitent endurance, through which their earthly desires are subdued.
The pure gold incense burners represent the virtues of good works and the prayers of the saints, which rise to the Lord as a sweet fragrance from a good conscience and sincere faith.
As mentioned in First Timothy, Chapter 1.
The hinges of both doors symbolize the minds and hearts of angels and saints.
They steadfastly focus on the contemplation and love of the Creator, fulfilling their ministry correctly, never turning away from the will of the Lord.
Solomon brought in the items his father, David, had dedicated, including the gold, silver, and vessels, and stored them in the treasuries of the house of the Lord.
David, Solomon's father, sanctified the silver when God the Father empowered those speaking His word with the grace of His Spirit.
He sanctified the gold when He enlightened those with natural talent to understand the law, and He sanctified the vessels by granting the grace of the Holy Spirit to all the children of the Church.
Solomon offers these sanctified items in the temple when the Lord, after judgment, brings the assembly of learned and faithful people into the joy of the heavenly kingdom.
Solomon made all the vessels in the house of the Lord.
Previously, it was said that Hiram made all the vessels for Solomon, but now the Scripture adds that Solomon made them as well, because Solomon directed the process by dictating and Hiram executed it.
In the open region of the Jordan, the king cast the vessels of the temple of the Lord in the clay soil.
We become vessels of election and mercy only when, looking to His baptism, we strive to be cleansed in such a river.
It's important to note that the same vessels were made not only in the region of the Jordan but also in the open region of that area, indicating the multiplication of the faithful.
This growth was to occur not only in Judea but throughout all regions, according to the saying:
"The fields will rejoice, and all that is in them" from Psalm Ninety-Five.
Therefore, the king cast the vessels of the house of the Lord in the open region of the Jordan, because Christ fulfilled the baptism of salvation. Through this, He would make vessels of mercy throughout the entire world.
The celebration that Solomon and all of Israel held represents the eternal joy that the saints have with Christ, the true and peaceful king.
Emath is understood as the truth of the Lord.
The river or stream of Egypt symbolizes temporal death, which no one can escape while remaining in Egypt, or in the darkness of this world.
Thus, all of Israel celebrates the festival from the river of Egypt to Emath with Solomon, as the saints, after this life ends, truly enjoy eternal joy with the Lord Jesus Christ.
The Temple of the Lord is the holy Church, as noted in First Corinthians chapter three: "The Temple of the Lord is holy, which is you."
King Christ dedicated it when he cleansed it with his blood from the filth of sins.
The sons of Israel also dedicate it when the faithful, using the gift given to them, help their neighbors through preaching and virtuous deeds.
What does it mean that Solomon sanctified the middle of the courtyard by offering burnt offerings because the bronze altar before the temple doors couldn't hold everything? It means that Christ now fully accomplishes in the Church what couldn't be perfected in the law due to the people's weakness.
He himself is the courtyard of the house of the Lord because, through him, the entrance to the heavenly Jerusalem is open.
Since burnt offerings and sacrifices couldn't be offered on the typical altar, as everything there was done figuratively, our king established the altar of faith in the Church, where offerings and sacrifices are made daily in a spiritual way.
This is why the Lord says through Isaiah: "I did not desire burnt offerings and the blood of sacrifices, goats, and bulls," as found in Isaiah chapter one.
The priests carried the Ark of the Lord, the tabernacle of the covenant, and all the holy vessels that were in the tabernacle, and they brought the Ark into the oracle of the temple in the Holy of Holies under the wings of the cherubim.
Moses made two golden cherubim, which he placed on the mercy seat above the Ark, as described in Exodus chapter twenty-five.
However, Solomon added two larger ones, under whose wings he placed the Ark with the mercy seat and the two earlier cherubim.
The exterior of the temple symbolizes the journeying Church, while the Holy of Holies represents the joy of the heavenly homeland.
The ark, brought into the Holy of Holies, symbolizes the assumed humanity of Christ entering the heavenly kingdom beyond the veil.
The poles used to carry the ark represent the preachers through whom Christ became known to the world.
The ends of the poles were visible in front of the oracle, not always, but only when the doors of the oracle were opened; and not to everyone, but only to those who came closer and paid more attention to see the inner parts.
The poles are stored in the oracle because the chosen ones who have passed on are now hidden in the presence of God.
However, the ends of the poles are visible to those who approach when the oracle is open, as God's grace grants a glimpse of the joy above to those who purify the oracle of their hearts with greater perfection.
Contemplation is not granted to those who let their minds wander too far away.
In the ark was a golden jar containing manna, because in Christ dwells all the fullness of the deity bodily.
There was also Aaron's rod that budded again, because the power of judging belongs to Him, whose judgment seemed to be removed in humility.
And there were the tablets of the covenant, because in Him are hidden all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge of God.
The poles used to carry it were attached to it, because the teachers who labor in the word now rejoice in the present vision of the glory of Christ.
Hence, Paul says: I desire to depart and be with Christ.
Only those who entered the oracle were allowed to see what the ark was like and how it was placed, because only the citizens of the heavenly homeland fully behold the glory of the Redeemer there.
The cloud filled the house of the Lord, meaning the Synagogue, because their minds were filled with the darkness of unbelief.
Because of the cloud, the priests couldn't minister.
While they refuse to delve into the mystical meanings hidden by the veil of scripture and the mysteries of Christ's birth, they lost the true ministry of faith due to the cloud of their error.
Their own merits prevent them from truly recognizing the practice of belief.
Solomon's fleet represents the Church of Christ, placed in the world's sea, dedicated to acquiring the treasures of knowledge, wisdom, and virtues.
There are Hiram's servants, sailors, and sea experts alongside Solomon's servants, while the Gentiles, educated in secular knowledge and wisdom, join in faith with those skilled in the law of Moses.
Our Solomon, that is, Christ, sends them to Ophir, symbolizing humility, so they may return with gold, or precious understanding, to him.
How much?
Specifically, seventy talents, representing history, allegory, moral instruction, and anagogy in both Testaments.
Ophir is a region in India, named after Ophir, a descendant of Heber, also called the "land of gold," due to its golden mountains inhabited by lions and fierce beasts.
No one dares to approach except by standing near the shore, taking the earth dug up by the lions' claws into their ship, so if the beasts sense them, they can quickly retreat to the sea.
I want you, dearly beloved brothers, to know that the tabernacle built by the Hebrew people in the desert symbolizes this spiritual house.
While the tabernacle was on the journey to the promised land, this one was built in the city of Jerusalem itself.
The tabernacle was carried from place to place by the Levites until it reached the promised land, while this house was constructed immediately in its homeland, and in the royal city, to always stand on an unshakable foundation, fulfilling the heavenly gifts assigned to it.
In that tabernacle, the labor and exile of the present Church can be symbolized, and in this house, future rest and happiness.
The creation of the tabernacle wasn't exclusive to the children of Israel; converts and other nations also participated in this act.
The fathers of the Old Testament and the ancient people of God are primarily represented in the tabernacle.
However, it is in this context that the Church, gathered from all nations, is expressed.
A detailed discussion of both buildings reveals the daily efforts of the present Church and the eternal rewards awaiting in the heavenly kingdom, the selection of the early Church, and the salvation found in Christ for all nations.
Therefore, dear brothers, the physical temple was constructed as a symbol of Jesus Christ and all of us-both the head and members-by Solomon.
You are part of the building of this spiritual temple as you are members of Christ, through true belief and good deeds.
When I say you belong to the temple, I don't refer to the one that Nebuzaradan, the servant of the king of Babylon, burned and plundered.
Second Kings 25,
but rather to the one God the Father intended to create in His beloved and eternal Son, Jesus Christ, in the heavenly Jerusalem, from before all ages.
Hence, the saying: "Jerusalem is built as a city, etc." Psalm 122.
And again: "Jerusalem, the city of the great King" Psalm 48.
Therefore, my beloved, I hope and desire for you to belong to that inner sanctuary, the Holy of Holies, where the ark is placed, representing the Son of God, through whom we have a covenant of peace with the Father.
The manna is also preserved in the ark because in Christ lie all the treasures of God's wisdom and knowledge.
Colossians 2.
Aaron's rod, which budded, is also kept there, signifying the God-given authority to lead the people of Israel and the whole Church throughout the ages.
The same Son of God, after His resurrection, ascended into heaven and entered the spiritual temple, not made by hands, appointed by God as the judge of the living and the dead.
We also recognize that angels are part of this temple.
Inside the temple, before the high priest, Jesus Christ, they are always ready for his service.
They stand tall, eyes fixed on the atonement cover, which symbolizes him.
Through this, they maintain their innocence and rejoice in the happiness of the holy souls in heaven.
They continually assist us as we journey on earth, guiding us to the heavenly homeland, as God commands.
Therefore, I encourage you, beloved, to dedicate yourselves to studying the Holy Scriptures, so you can emulate these Cherubim, interpreted as a multitude of knowledge.
In the divine Scriptures, you'll discover a wealth of knowledge if you search diligently.
By being spiritually fulfilled, you'll learn to dismiss earthly things, cherish heavenly things, disregard the temporary, and long for the eternal.
Ultimately, you'll be able to keep your mind's eye focused on the atonement cover, which is Christ, without interruption.
About this atonement cover, John says: "We have an advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous; and he is the atonement for our sins" First John, chapter two.
And the Apostle Paul says: "For Jesus did not enter into holy places made by hands, which are copies of the true ones; but into heaven itself, to appear now in the presence of God for us" Hebrews, chapter nine.
The Cherubim of God, through confirming grace, perpetually preserve their innocence.
So, beloved, faithfully and diligently uphold the covenant you made with God, whether on the day of baptism or through holy orders, through good works.
Also, maintain purity of mind and body, which pleases God and imitates angelic life, because living in the flesh beyond the flesh is not earthly life, but heavenly.
Chastity, if it endures in purpose until death, will receive the reward of eternal happiness as mentioned in the Gospel of Matthew, chapter ten.
Even where the flesh can no longer be whole from intercourse, let it remain a virgin in faith and conscience.
Therefore, my dearest friends, let no improper thought lead you to anything unlawful.
Keep yourselves free from impurity. Let no lust make you guilty.
Let no greed ignite a love for worldly things in your heart.
Let no anger harm your neighbors.
Let no arrogance lift your mind into pride.
Let no injury from your neighbors disturb you.
Let no deceit pretend to show holiness before others.
Let no hypocrisy make you guilty before God.
Let no malice take away your place in the heavenly court.
Let no perversity drive you away from the company of the heavenly citizens as if you were unworthy.
Thus, even the Cherubim rejoice in the blessedness of holy souls in heaven, and they never cease to help us as they see us still journeying on earth.
Therefore, beloved, often bring to mind the examples of these blessed spirits, especially the Cherubim.
What they perfectly do in heaven without interruption, you should strive to do on earth, guided by love.
Therefore, with God's help, keep yourselves from the contagion of sin, and diligently offer prayers to the Lord for the salvation of the whole world and your neighbors.
I advise you to also offer prayers, sacrifices, sighs, and tears to God for all the faithful departed who are still in places of punishment.
Through your compassionate intercession, they may be delivered from their most bitter pains and come to places of refreshment, light, and peace.
And I do not want you to be content with just this, but also to give thanks to the Lord for those who are already in the palace of heaven by His grace.
Therefore, focus on your own progress, but do not neglect the salvation of your neighbors.
Do not do to anyone what you would not want to suffer yourself.
Do not refuse to do for others the good that you wish to be done for you.
Love God above all else, love your neighbors as yourself for God's sake, and patiently tolerate your enemies for Him.
Lift your mind's eye to our heavenly homeland with complete devotion.
Pray with all your strength and tears so that you may eventually reach it.
May He, who has chosen to guide you there through His beloved Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, prepare to build an eternal temple for His majesty from living and chosen stones.
Amen.
Sermon Three: To the Brothers, That They May Not Have Property
Dear brothers, as you've come together by God's grace to refine and enhance the conduct of your order, it's important to remember the promises you made to God and your abbot when you first joined.
When you stood before the abbot, you pledged to uphold three commitments to God: obedience, chastity, and not owning property.
It's truly appropriate, dear ones, that you promised God obedience and chastity, because without these, you cannot please God at all.
If it pleases you, let's discuss each of these, starting with obedience.
Obedience is a virtue that plants other virtues in the mind and preserves them once they take root.
Paul speaks of this when he says: Brothers, obey your leaders and submit to them, for they keep watch over your souls as those who must give an account.
This is from the book of Hebrews, chapter 13.
Solomon also says: An obedient man speaks of victories, as recorded in Proverbs, chapter 21.
Indeed, an obedient man speaks of victories because he conquers himself when he chooses another's will over his own.
Thus, when we humbly obey our abbot, we overcome ourselves in our hearts.
Hence, the prophet Samuel says: Obedience is better than sacrifice, and listening is better than the fat of rams.
For rebellion is like the sin of divination, and stubbornness is like the evil of idolatry, found in First Samuel, chapter 15.
Truly, obedience is better than sacrifice because sacrifices kill the flesh of another, but obedience restrains one's own will.
Diviners are those who make impious prayers at the altars of idols and offer wicked sacrifices to demons.
Idolatry is the worship of idols.
Latria in Greek means service in Latin.
Therefore, the greatest evil is when God's servants in a monastery fall into the sin of divination through disobedience.
I see a significant issue in the monastery: the servants of God, under the guise of religion, fall into disobedience and stubbornness, committing the sin of idolatry.
It's a deep tragedy when religious men, supposedly on the path of virtue, end up in hell.
The greatest misfortune is when men of the Church, through disobedience under the guise of religion, risk eternal damnation.
Let's listen to the Apostle Paul, who says: Just as through the disobedience of one man, Adam, many became sinners; so through the obedience of one man, Christ, many are made righteous.
And just as through the disobedience of one man many descended into hell, so through the obedience of one man many have ascended, and will ascend, into heaven.
It's also written about our Lord Jesus Christ: Christ became obedient for us to the Father unto death.
If Jesus Christ, the King of heaven and earth, chose to obey God the Father unto death, why would a man in the monastery refuse to obey his abbot?
And if our Lord Jesus Christ, the true King of glory, obeyed God the Father unto death, why would a mortal man, just food for worms, disregard the commands of his abbot?
Isn't it because he chooses not to follow Christ into heaven, but follows Adam into hell through disobedience?
Why does he refuse to obey his abbot, if not because he despises Christ and follows the devil?
Thus, the Lord says in the Gospel to his servants, to whom he entrusted the governance of his Church: Whoever hears you, hears me; and whoever rejects you, rejects me.
As if saying: Whoever obeys you, also obeys me, and whoever despises you, despises me.
Therefore, dear brothers, keep our Lord Jesus Christ's words in mind and think about them carefully, because anyone in the monastery who disobeys his abbot is not only disobedient to the abbot but also to Christ.
When someone disrespects their superior, they're not just disrespecting that person, but also Christ.
My brothers, you pledged chastity to God and your abbot when you first joined the monastery.
If you haven't kept that promise, all your efforts have been in vain.
Failing to maintain chastity from the day you pledged it to God and your abbot means you've wasted all this time.
Anyone who promised chastity to God and their abbot cannot be truly religious unless they correct this through very harsh penance.
Why is that?
Because one evil act can undo many good deeds.
One fault can destroy many just actions.
One wrongdoing can overturn many good things.
Mixing evil with good corrupts much.
A bit of bitterness can turn the sweetness of honey bitter.
A small fire can set a large forest ablaze, as noted in the book of James, chapter three.
A little yeast corrupts the whole batch, as mentioned in First Corinthians, chapter five.
Therefore, Scripture says: Whoever fails in one thing is guilty of all, as noted in James, chapter two, specifically concerning eternal life.
It's as if being entangled in all sins; if he remains in just one, he will not enter the gate of eternal life.
Thus, a person can be condemned for one sin unless they amend it through very harsh penance, especially fornication, because without chastity, no work is perfect.
Without chastity, no work is great.
Therefore, as blessed Gregory says: Neither is chastity great without good works, nor is any good work significant without chastity.
The beauty of chastity should be cherished.
Chastity is the fruit of sweetness.
Chastity is the inviolable virtue of the saints.
Chastity is the security of the mind and the health of the body.
Chastity is beloved by God and all the saints.
It's written that without chastity, no one will see God, as noted in Hebrews, chapter twelve.
Thus, the venerable Bede says in a certain homily: On the day of resurrection, only those who are chaste in body will be able to ascend to the heavens.
After the resurrection, only those pure in heart will be able to behold the essence of divine majesty.
In third place, you promised God not to own anything personally.
The devil often tempts those who've vowed to be content with little, urging them to acquire more.
Many people turn to God from secular life, enter a monastery, and willingly give all their wealth to the poor and to the monastery, choosing poverty over riches for the rest of their lives, just like the holy apostles did.
Some secular individuals also turn to God in a monastery but presume to commit fraud or theft from the monastery's resources, like Judas the betrayer, who kept the money bag and used to steal from it.
Some come from the secular world to the monastery and secretly hold onto part of their worldly wealth, fearing temporary poverty, while giving the rest to the monastery, just as Ananias and Sapphira did.
It's written that they sold a field and laid part of the proceeds at the apostles' feet, but hid another part.
(Acts 5)
Some poor individuals come from secular life to the monastery, and although they were poor in the world, they desire to become rich in the monastery, like Gehazi, the disciple of Elisha.
To whom Elisha said: "Because you pursued Naaman and received riches from him, Naaman's leprosy will cling to you forever."
(2 Kings 5)
Therefore, whoever despises all worldly possessions for God's sake, as the holy apostles did, will rejoice with those apostles and be eternally rewarded.
About them, the Lord says in the Gospel: "Blessed are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven."
(Matthew 5)
But whoever moves from the world to the monastery and commits fraud or theft from the monastery's resources is like Judas and will suffer punishment in hell with him.
However, those who turn from worldly life to serve the Lord but keep some of what they had for themselves and distribute some will share the curse of Ananias and Sapphira.
But those who come from the world to a monastery and wish to have the riches they couldn't possess outside while in the monastery will, without a doubt, suffer the leprosy of Gehazi.
What Gehazi suffered in the body, they will suffer in the soul.
Therefore, for those who truly, like the apostles, despise everything in this world for God's sake, the words of the Psalmist are fitting: "But for me, it is good to cling to God; I have put my hope in the Lord God" Psalm seventy-three.
And also: "Cast your burden on the Lord, and He will sustain you" Psalm fifty-five.
But to Judas and his followers, it is said: "They rise up to the heavens and go down to the depths; their soul melted away in evil" Psalm one hundred and seven.
To Ananias and those like him pertains: "Those who trust in their own strength and boast of the abundance of their riches" Psalm forty-nine.
To Gehazi and his companions fits: "Behold the man who did not make God his helper but trusted in the abundance of his riches and prevailed in his vanity" Psalm fifty-two.
But behold, dearest brothers, as we scrutinize the sins of others with such diligence, let us fear lest we offend the eyes of divine majesty.
Therefore, it is fitting that we, who see the specks in others' eyes with such care, hurry to remove the beams from our own eyes Matthew seven.
What then should we do in these situations? Namely, what the Psalmist says: "Make vows to the Lord your God, and fulfill them" Psalm sixty-six.
Otherwise, it would be much better not to vow than to make a vow and not fulfill the promises Sirach five.
Why? Because, as blessed Isidore says, among the unfaithful are found those who did not fulfill the good they vowed to God.
Therefore, dearest brothers, turn inward to yourselves, and if you find that you have fulfilled what you promised to God, give thanks to God.
If you realize that you've been transgressors and negligent in the vows you've made to God, seek forgiveness from Almighty Jesus Christ through sincere prayers and daily tears.
This way, on the day of His final judgment, He may not allow you to perish with the unbelievers, but instead, deem you worthy to be led with His chosen ones to the kingdom of heaven.
He lives and reigns as God with the same Father and Holy Spirit in perfect Trinity for all ages.
Amen.
Sermon Four: On the Prelates of the Church
Isidore of Spain, a man skilled in every form of speech, capable of reaching both the unlearned and the learned, spoke about the education of priests among other topics as follows:
Just as sinners and the wicked are forbidden from taking up the priestly ministry, so too are the unlearned and unskilled kept from this duty.
The former corrupt the lives of good people through bad living and setting poor examples, while the latter cannot correct the wicked due to ignorance.
How can they teach what they have not learned themselves?
Therefore, those who do not know how to teach should refrain from taking on the role of a teacher.
Every teacher should strive to have both good actions and good preaching because one without the other renders them useless and incomplete.
It is necessary for a prelate to proclaim the sweetness and kindness of God to their subordinates with diligence, encouraging them to do good works by their own example, and frequently reminding them with kind words.
Thus, they may rightly be counted among the members of the holy Church, just as the bridegroom, that is, Christ, speaks to the Church in the persona of the bride in the Song of Songs, "Your lips, my bride, drip honey; honey and milk are under your tongue" (Song of Solomon 4:11).
The preachers of the Church are rightly called the lips of the bride because through them, the Church speaks to the people, and through them, the little ones are taught faith, while the hidden things of Scripture are revealed, as if manifesting the secrets of the heart.
In a honeycomb, honey is hidden while the wax is visible.
Therefore, the lips of the bride, that is, the holy Church, are rightly called a honeycomb because, just as great wisdom is found in the frailty of the flesh, it is like honey hidden in wax.
When someone chosen preaches and reveals heavenly joys to the ignorant, the honeycomb drips because the sweetness of wisdom hidden in the heart is revealed to the listeners through the frailty of speech.
Thus, it is written: "We have this treasure in earthen vessels" (Second Corinthians 4:7).
Therefore, it is added: "Honey and milk are under your tongue."
Indeed, false preachers carry honey on their tongues.
They don't hold it under their tongue, because sometimes they preach heavenly joys as if they were true, while in reality, they desire earthly goods with all their hearts.
However, a holy mind offers honey on the tongue, showing others the sweetness of wisdom through their words, and by truthfully preaching, it refreshes listeners as if with the sweetness of honey.
A good shepherd carries milk under the tongue, nourishing the little ones in the Church with suitable teaching.
Yet, he keeps all this under the tongue for himself because he continuously carries the inner sweetness with him.
While rejecting worldly things and spurning the bitterness of vices, he feeds on the inner sweetness of wisdom, which gives him strength so that, as he walks toward eternal things, he won't falter on the challenging path.
By preaching in this way, the wise shepherd instills the sweetness and gentleness of God into the hearts of his followers, lifting them up with examples of good deeds to desire heavenly things.
Indeed, he is a wise shepherd who diligently watches over the flock entrusted to him; for while he carefully observes both himself and the sheep from every angle, he avoids hostile traps.
Therefore, let the negligent shepherd hear what the Lord says to him and to the prudent shepherd:
The good shepherd, he says, lays down his life for the sheep; but the hired hand runs away.
He lays down his life for the sheep, who, ascending the perilous place of leadership, keeps the flock of cloistered brothers in peace by closing the door of silence.
He lays down his life for the sheep, who alone, amidst worldly dangers, manages external affairs, seeking what is necessary and beneficial for the brothers.
He lays down his life, who alone goes out to endure disputes over family matters and walks in the midst of flattering and slandering tongues, works for the weak, feeds the laborers, comforts the faint-hearted, and argues by reproving the proud.
Such a shepherd, with Christ and through Christ, can say:
I know my own, and my own know me.
The sheep know the shepherd whom they often see present, whom familiarity with the subject brothers makes known, and whom benefits make a friend.
The brothers recognize the leader because he shows his usefulness and kindness in everything he does, whether through patience and love, a passion for justice, or by providing necessary support.
The followers see their leader as someone who, like a father, prepares for their needs in this life and, like a teacher, shares spiritual wisdom.
The shepherd truly knows his sheep when he carefully observes their habits and actions.
As it is written: "Pay careful attention to the condition of your flocks" (Proverbs chapter twenty-seven).
He understands the state of his flock because he isn't unaware of each follower's abilities.
He diligently examines the conditions, qualities, actions, and capabilities of the brothers he oversees.
Through confession, the followers reveal their hearts to him; through observation, he learns their actions; through experience, he understands their abilities; and through results, he sees their intentions: "And they will hear my voice," it says (John chapter ten).
The shepherd has three voices: gentle, sweet, and loud.
The gentle voice is for the weak, the sweet for those losing hope, and the loud for the deaf, meaning the disobedient.
The weak are those tempted.
Those who despair of God's mercy are losing hope.
The deaf are those who refuse to listen, meaning those who disdain obedience.
At times, the weak, who are in temptation, hear the gentle voice of comfort from the master; those who despair of God's mercy due to their sins hear the voice of pleading; the deaf, meaning the disobedient, hear the loud, harsh voice of rebuke.
Again it is said: "And they follow me: My sheep follow the shepherd." Which shepherd do the sheep follow? The good or the bad. Where do they follow him? Wherever he leads.
If he is a good shepherd, the sheep follow him to life; if he is a bad one, they follow him to death. But if a blind man leads a blind man, both will fall into a pit (Matthew chapter fifteen).
How does the good shepherd lead the sheep?
Through his life and teachings.
When the church leader lives well and teaches rightly, there is one flock and one shepherd.
A pastor should be consistent within himself and united with his flock.
What he teaches with words, he should fulfill with good deeds.
He must remain steadfast, not letting anger change his gentleness, not becoming proud in prosperity, nor broken in adversity; but staying the same with enduring patience.
Truly, he holds and loves the unity of brotherhood, finding joy in the service of love, following the example of the true shepherd, who came not to be served but to serve, and to give his life as a ransom for many.
As it says in the Book of Matthew, Chapter 20.
Indeed, he is the capable pastor, leading the flock according to God's will, working solely to bring more people to God through word and example.
He does not find delight in the honor of leadership, but in its burden; in love, not power; in service offered to others, not received from others.
As Paul says in First Corinthians, Chapter 9:
"Though I am free and belong to no one, I have made myself a servant to everyone."
A pastor also maintains unity with the flock when he is not separated from them by wearing finer clothes or eating more luxurious food; but becomes one with the weak through compassion, and with those who are delicate through understanding. Thus, a leader should live in such a way that he can rightly say with the Apostle:
"I have become all things to all people so that by all possible means I might save some."
A negligent pastor flees and withdraws from the flock. There are certain leaders who disdain to do the good things they command others to do. When they place heavy and unbearable burdens on their subjects and refuse to lift them with a finger, they scorn carrying what they command others to bear. They flee when they remove themselves from divine duties and refuse to bear the weight of the order with their brothers.
They flee, wandering through others' homes, thinking themselves happier the later they return to their cloisters. They flee, staying away from the cloister to indulge more freely in idle talk, fill their stomachs more abundantly with food, and sleep more securely than they did in the cloister. They flee, seeking not what is common to the brothers, but what is for themselves. They flee, who, although present, hide in silence when they see negligence.
They avoid those who live in leisure, separate from the community, and those who withdraw from the shared guidance of their peers, living poorly and resisting correction.
As the blessed Gregory notes: They take pleasure in doing even unlawful things without any opposition from their subordinates.
In the same text, it is noted that they consider themselves wiser than everyone else, especially those over whom they hold more power.
They enjoy appearing wise and powerful.
This attitude led to the downfall of both angels and humans.
"I will set my throne in the north, and I will be like the Most High," says the angel in Isaiah 14. And to the man, the serpent said: "You will be like gods," as stated in Genesis 3.
Therefore, leaders should fear the downfall that befell both man and angel. The angel fell for seeking more power, and man, in his quest for wisdom, became foolish.
Additionally, some leaders live well but allow their subjects to live poorly. Others live poorly yet force their subjects to live well. And there are those who live poorly and want their subjects to do the same.
Leaders who live well but let their subjects live poorly set a good example through their actions. However, when they fail to correct through rebuke, their silence becomes a sin. Even if they live well, they must account to the Lord for the flock entrusted to them.
Why do such individuals take on the care of the flock if they are unwilling to bear the burden of labor? If they do not know how to lead, why assume the responsibility of leadership? And if they know but negligently allow their subjects to sin, while they themselves could live well, why risk eternal death by endangering others' souls?
These leaders raise the sons of Eli the priest, who sleep with the women serving at the entrance of the tent of meeting, and who prevent those coming to sacrifice at Shiloh, seizing the raw meat before the fat is burned, as mentioned in First Samuel 2.
They resemble the sons of Eli, who, under well-living leaders, live recklessly and negligently, engaging with women, whether in reality or through fleshly desires.
They even prevent those coming to Shiloh from making sacrifices, turning new converts away from good deeds through their words and actions.
They don't let the fat be burned because, with the fire of love extinguished, they fail to bring sweetness to the heart's good actions.
They seek raw meat instead of cooked, avoiding the fire of tribulation, poverty, and labor, not wishing to suffer adversity for the Lord.
In the furnace of tribulation and poverty, the vices of the flesh are usually burned away.
They want raw meat so they can cook it whenever and however they please.
Some people in the cloister, like those in Shiloh, do nothing but what they desire, when and how they want.
They live as subjects in Shiloh, more eager to fulfill their own wills than to obey the commands of good superiors.
These individuals do not imitate Samuel, who anointed kings in the kingdom of the Jews, as mentioned in First Samuel, chapter ten.
Instead, they imitate Hophni and Phinehas, whose sin led to the Ark of the Lord being taken by the Philistines, as noted in First Samuel, chapter four.
Those who live poorly but force their subjects to live well may indeed turn the erring from evil, but they undermine the strong, those zealous in serving God.
They rebuke the wicked with words but undermine the pious with bad examples.
They aim to appear religious because they have religious people under them, yet they despise living religiously themselves.
They boast of their subjects' good works, not their own deeds.
They instruct others to do what they themselves refuse to do; they engage in actions they believe should not be permitted for others.
They compel their subjects to do good works but resist being compelled by anyone.
Therefore, let the shepherd maintain unity with the flock so that he can reach the heavenly kingdom's inheritance with them.
Let him not be separated from them by more luxurious clothing, finer food, or a desire for empty glory.
Be attentive to the flock entrusted to you.
Encourage the good to improve gently, and correct the bad carefully so they do not worsen.
Make an effort to visit the weak often, and don't hesitate to gently and kindly comfort the sad.
Moreover, enter the cloister regularly.
Motivate the lazy to work well, reprimand the negligent, and constantly remind everyone of the joys of paradise and the punishments of hell.
Above all, ensure you practice the good things you preach to others.
Willingly share the responsibilities of the order with the other brothers, and provide for them both spiritually and materially as a father would for his children, knowing with care that you will give an account to God for them.
But above all these things, always offer prayers to the Lord for them, so that no one from the flock entrusted to you may perish.
Make sure no ravenous wolf finds anyone wandering from the path of truth to carry away.
Strive to reach the evergreen pastures with these same sheep, with Christ leading, made possible by our Lord Jesus Christ, who with the Father and the Holy Spirit lives and reigns as God in perfect Trinity forever and ever.
Amen.
Sermon Five: On Obedience
Obey your superior as you would a father, and even more so a priest, who cares for all of you.
We should fear our superior as we fear the Lord, love him as we love a father, and trust that whatever good he commands is for the benefit of our soul.
Here, "superior" refers to the head of the cloister or the manager of the monastery.
In a community where the canonical order is maintained without a bishop or abbot, a prior is called a priest.
However, if there is a bishop or abbot present, the one with the greatest authority is considered the priest.
We are urged to maintain obedience even unto death, because without it, all regular conduct is deemed worthless.
It is also crucial to understand that through obedience, nothing evil should be commanded by the superior, nor executed by the subordinates.
As the distinguished teacher Isidore said: Do not obey any authority in wrongdoing, even if threatened with punishment or torture.
Why?
Because it is better to die than to carry out unlawful orders.
Therefore, whoever obeys a superior in wrongdoing is disobedient to Christ, who said in the Gospel: Everyone who sins is a slave to sin.
John Chapter 8.
And whoever refuses to obey his superior in wrongdoing is obedient to Christ, the Lord of all, who commanded through the Prophet to turn away from evil and do good.
Psalm 37.
If, therefore, anyone who sins is a slave to sin, we must not obey any authority in wrongdoing.
It's also vital to understand that obedience can be ineffective if it involves self-interest; sometimes, if it doesn't involve self-interest, it is minimal.
When the successes of this world are commanded, or a higher position is offered, the person accepting these things nullifies the virtue of obedience if he desires them out of personal ambition.
When a leader instructs their follower to reject worldly things and embrace insults and shame, if the follower doesn't genuinely want this from within, their obedience loses value because they're reluctantly accepting what is despised in this life.
Thus, obedience in challenging and humble matters should be personally meaningful.
In contrast, in favorable situations, they shouldn't have any personal stake at all.
This way, they will be more honorable in tough and humiliating circumstances as they willingly submit to divine will.
They will be less esteemed in prosperity as they become consumed by the current glory, mistaking it for divine.
Just like pus flows from a wound, the disease of disobedience arises from the swelling of pride and the sore of contempt.
The disease of disobedience is a weakness of the soul.
A person who doesn't want to do good works but can, lives; yet they are weak, living through power but struggling with a corrupt will.
The first human suffered from this ailment, who, while having power and a healthy will, was placed over the animals of the earth, the birds of the air, and the fish of the sea, as described in Genesis, Chapter One.
But after falling due to disobedience, was cast out from paradise's joys and now even serves flies and mosquitoes.
When the weakness of the flesh combines with swelling, it can lead to languor.
The carnal mind often falls into the languor of disobedience through pride's swelling.
There are two types of swelling: hard and soft.
The hard type of swelling is the stubbornness in carnal behavior.
This is usually treated in three ways: with a plaster, ointment, and iron, meaning by example of good deeds, words of admonition, and the discipline of correction.
When the mind doesn't release the pus of bad intention through confession or promises of improvement from admonition, it needs the iron incision, which is the harsh discipline of correction.
Thus, the blessed Isidore, a renowned teacher, says: "Whoever is not corrected by gentle words must be reproved more harshly."
Pain must be removed when it can't be gently healed.
If someone doesn't correct themselves after a private warning, they should be publicly rebuked, so that the issue, which can't be resolved in secret, is addressed openly.
The mind can become inflated when it indulges in rich foods, seeks laziness, becomes sluggish with sleep, and enjoys idle tales.
This leads to a weakness of the soul, as the proud mind, either hardened by stubbornness or softened by pleasure, fails to do anything good.
Sometimes disobedience masquerades as obedience, boasting in name only without the deed.
Since obedience can be understood in different ways, it's useful to explore it more deeply.
Obedience involves command, action, and place, indicating what is ordered, what is done, and where one resides.
Regarding command: "obedience was enjoined upon him"; action: "he completed obedience"; place: "he resides with obedience," when he keeps a house far away.
The first is easy, the second is challenging, and the third involves both. Commanding is easy, fulfilling is hard, and the place can be pleasing or displeasing.
Some enjoy obedience not for good works or enriching others, but for feasts and various pleasures.
Some prefer obedience, not to serve God more diligently than in the cloister, but to have more servants and indulge in idle tales and pleasures.
Thus, obedience appeals because they have control over everything, give what they wish to others, and keep what they want, often prioritizing their own desires over reason.
This leads to a situation where obedience is claimed but doesn't truly exist for those with a perverse will.
Many seek this form of obedience, not to fully obey God and their superior, but to find a way to be outside of true obedience.
There are many ways people claim to be in obedience.
However, obedience is often pursued in various ways.
Some seek it through parental guidance, advice from siblings, or clever deception.
When parental threats or brotherly advice fail, sometimes pretense can achieve the desired obedience.
This type of obedience, whether gained through parental demands, deceptive encouragement from siblings, or false displays of good deeds, is merely obedience in name, lacking true substance.
It's outwardly called obedience, but it doesn't bring the reward of true inner fulfillment.
This form of obedience isn't aimed at tiring the body with labor for God but indulging in the pleasures of the present life.
There are other ways to achieve this kind of obedience, where what can't be obtained by the previously mentioned methods might be secured by the promise of a reward.
This is why Simon the magician lingers in the Church with Peter, and Ananias and Sapphira are still remembered as noted in the Acts of the Apostles, Chapter 5.
Through Peter, good leaders are understood, while Simon, Ananias, and Sapphira represent poor followers.
Simon wanted to buy the grace of the Holy Spirit, as described in Acts of the Apostles, Chapter 8.
These individuals attempt to buy obedience.
Simon sought to purchase the gift of the Holy Spirit with money, and similarly, some strive to acquire Church revenues at a cost.
Therefore, they are not the children of the apostle Peter through teaching, but of Simon the magician through greed.
Each person is considered a child of the one whose teachings they adhere to.
From the founder's error, some derive both name and fault, being identified by the name of the one whose error they follow.
Thus, the Lord speaks through the prophet to Israel: Your father was an Amorite, and your mother a Hittite as mentioned in the Book of Ezekiel, Chapter 16; not by birth, but by imitation.
In a better sense, those who wholeheartedly follow God's commandments are called children of God.
Hence, we also call out to God in prayer, not by nature but by adoption, saying: Our Father, who art in heaven as found in the Gospel of Matthew, Chapter 6.
Therefore, those who buy obedience or ecclesiastical dignities at a price are rightly called children of Simon the magician, not by nature but by imitation.
Ananias and Sapphira concealed part of their property as recorded in the Acts of the Apostles, Chapter 5.
These people are focused on making money.
But as it is written: "No one serving God entangles themselves in earthly affairs,"
Second Timothy 2.
Therefore, it's clear they're not serving Christ but wealth, because they pursue not spiritual riches but the profits of this temporary life.
They aim not to please Jesus Christ, the heavenly king, but to gain temporary riches.
Furthermore, greed, which is idol worship, rules their hearts more than voluntary poverty, which leads one into the kingdom of heaven.
These individuals prefer riding through city streets over quietly reciting psalms in a cloister.
This is obedience filled with greed and empty glory, which does not raise its lover to eternal joy but plunges them into hell.
There is another form of obedience, merely labeled as such, about which it is said: "Because you listened to your wife and ate from the tree, the ground is cursed because of you,"
Genesis 3.
There are four voices: the wife, the world, the devil, and God.
So I will listen to what the Lord God will speak within me,
Psalm 85.
Will the devil speak? Will the flesh? Will the world?
The voice of the wife is the voice of the flesh; the voice of the flesh is pleasure; the voice of the world is vanity; the voice of God is goodness.
We receive the devil's suggestion through the serpent.
The woman represents the animal senses of the body, that is, the flesh, which we share with beasts, and it is called the lower part of reason.
Thus, when the suggestion of sin arises, it is as if the serpent speaks.
If the flesh delights in the wicked suggestion and consents, it is as if the woman agrees.
But if the suggestion is restrained and expelled from wrong thoughts, it is as if the woman alone ate the forbidden fruit.
However, if the sin that the serpent, meaning the devil, suggests, and the flesh delights in it, that is, the lower part of reason, namely, the woman eats, and if the person's mind, that is, the higher part of reason, consents to commit the sin, then it is as if the man has been deceived.
The woman gave the man food, much like how the rational mind succumbs to sin through the pleasures of the flesh.
So, when someone listens to the serpent's voice - that is, the devil's suggestion - and follows the voice of temptation from their own desires, they become disobedient to the Creator's voice.
Those who don't resist the pleasures of the flesh and prioritize their own desires over God's voice are following the path of temptation.
However, the Creator's voice advises leaders to tell their followers: "Do what they say, but not what they do" (from the Gospel of Matthew chapter twenty-three).
This implies obedience to corrupt leaders, as also instructed in the First Book of Peter chapter two.
So, like David with Saul, honor them as Samuel did, even if they are rejected.
Therefore, we must obey leaders if they command rightly, even if they live poorly.
Those who do not obey and respect their leaders, even if they are corrupt, show themselves to be disobedient and proud.
Listen briefly to what you should do and how to obey leaders, whether they are good or bad.
Do not follow good leaders in bad commands, nor oppose bad leaders in good ones.
Be obedient to bad leaders in good commands, and avoid obeying good ones in evil orders.
Meanwhile, dear brothers, remember the words of the Apostle Paul to better understand the power of obedience.
He said: "Whatever is ordained is ordained by God." Therefore, whoever resists authority resists God's ordinance (from the Book of Romans chapter thirteen).
So, whoever resists God's ordinance is defying their leader's commands.
Anyone who contradicts a church leader giving worthy commands is not only rebellious to man but also to God.
Dathan and Abiram perished because they were disobedient to their leaders, Moses and Aaron, when they arrogantly claimed the right to sacrifice for themselves (from the Book of Numbers chapter sixteen).
Thus, it is written in the Book of Psalms: "The earth opened up and swallowed Dathan; it covered the assembly of Abiram" (from Psalm one hundred and five).
These people, due to their reckless audacity, are swallowed alive by the earth's breaking apart and delivered to the torments of hell.
Didn't King Saul, because of his disobedience, get rejected by the Lord, expelled from his throne, handed over to Satan, and ultimately killed by the Philistines?
Consider, my beloved, how serious the sin of disobedience is, for which not only souls are tortured in hell, but bodies are also punished in this world.
Reflect on how grave it is to resist God's command, as punishment affects both soul and body.
Let the rebellious hear and let the disobedient fear the commands of their elders, lest they be handed over to the torments of hell with Dathan and Abiram.
Beware of following in the footsteps of the rebellious Korah, lest you be swallowed into the depths of hell with him.
Do not wish to imitate the rebellious Korah, who through defiance dragged many with him into hell; instead, follow Christ, who through humility obeyed God the Father even unto death.
As it is written in Philippians Chapter Two, He draws many to the kingdom daily, as mentioned in John Chapter Twelve.
Therefore, my brothers and masters, fear Christ, love Him above all, and show reverence to His commands.
For He Himself said: If anyone loves me, they will keep my word, as noted in John Chapter Fourteen.
Let His love appear in your works.
Follow His example by maintaining humility in your conduct, and for His love, be obedient to your superiors.
Willingly obey your superiors in this life so that you may reach eternal freedom.
Devotedly submit to the divine dispensation, renounce your own desires, place the will of your superior above your own wishes, and strive to fulfill their commands without complaint.
So that after this life, you may reach the heavenly homeland and rejoice eternally in the vision of God the Father; with His help, who lives and reigns with the Father and the Holy Spirit in perfect Trinity, God for all ages of ages.
Amen.
Sermon Six: On Discipline
Listen, dearest brothers, to what our Lord Jesus Christ says for the teaching and comfort of His entire Church in the Book of Revelation.
He says, "I rebuke and discipline those I love" (Revelation, Chapter 3).
With these words, He encourages us to endure and embrace discipline, like the most loving Father, so that we patiently and with all gentleness accept everything commanded to us by Him or our leaders.
Therefore, for our sins and negligence, the Lord rebukes and disciplines us through Himself and the ministers of the holy Church in this present age, so that we are not condemned in the future with this world, that is, with the lovers of the world.
Whoever does not serve God through the exercises of discipline cannot escape God without the rigor of discipline.
Hence, the Psalmist advises those living without discipline: "Embrace discipline lest the Lord become angry, and you perish from the right path" (Psalm, Chapter 2).
But what is discipline?
Discipline is the orderly correction of morals and the observance of the rules of our predecessors.
About this discipline, the Apostle Paul speaks, saying: "Persevere in discipline. God offers Himself to you as sons" (Hebrews, Chapter 12).
If you are without discipline, which all have shared in, then you are illegitimate children and not sons.
Those, therefore, who are without discipline are illegitimate and do not receive the inheritance of the heavenly kingdom.
However, the sons willingly bear the correction of paternal discipline and do not despair of receiving the inheritance of the heavenly homeland.
About this discipline, Isaiah also preaches to the undisciplined people, saying: "Cease to do evil, learn to do good" (Isaiah, Chapter 1).
And the same is continued by the Psalmist, saying: "Turn away from evil and do good" (Psalm, Chapter 36).
From this, Solomon also says: "He who rejects discipline goes astray greatly" (Wisdom, Chapter 3).
Therefore, he is unfortunate who rejects the discipline of the father, that is, of ecclesiastical governance.
Just as the soldiers who crucified Christ did not divide His tunic (John, Chapter 19), we should not tear apart or divide the discipline of the Church of Christ.
Just like a robe covers the whole body except the head, discipline adorns and covers the entire Church, except for Christ, who established that discipline.
The robe is described as woven from the top throughout because the discipline of the Church is given and completed by the Lord from heaven.
The Lord spoke about this to His disciples after He rose from the dead and before He ascended to the Father:
"But you, stay here in the city until you are clothed with power from above" Luke twenty-four.
Therefore, the robe of Christ's body is the discipline of the Church. Anyone who is outside of discipline is alienated from the body of Christ. So, let us not tear Christ's robe, but rather cast lots for it, meaning we should strive to keep it whole, lest we find ourselves without a share in its wholeness.
Let no one break any of Christ's commandments, but let each person remain in the calling in which they were called, before God. Whoever despises the discipline of Christ and the Catholic priests, whom He appointed over His Church, falls into the trap of destruction by wandering through various paths of error.
This is why the prophet, lamenting over humanity through the person of a rebellious people, says:
"We have all strayed like sheep, each one has turned to their own way" Isaiah fifty-three.
About those who reject the Lord's discipline and follow their own will, wisdom speaks through Solomon:
"There are many ways that seem right to people, but in the end, they lead to death" Proverbs fourteen.
These many paths of destruction are followed when the one royal path, namely the law of God, which does not turn to the right or to the left, is neglected. About this path, the Lord Jesus Christ, who is the end of the law for righteousness to everyone who believes Romans ten, declares saying:
"I am the way, the truth, and the life; no one comes to the Father except through me" John fourteen.
He invites all people to this path, saying:
"Come to me, all you who labor and are burdened, and I will refresh you" Matthew eleven, because God shows no favoritism Deuteronomy ten.
In Galatians Chapter 3, it's stated that there is neither Jew nor Greek, neither male nor female.
Similarly, in Colossians Chapter 3, it says there is neither slave nor free, neither barbarian nor Scythian, but Christ is everything and in everyone.
Therefore, everyone is one in Christ Jesus.
Romans Chapter 10 notes that Christ is the end of the law.
Without the law, meaning without discipline, one becomes without Christ.
Therefore, those who lack teaching do not follow in Christ's footsteps.
In the times of the Gospel, it's inappropriate and unjust for God's servants to be without Christ, especially since the apostles were given the right to preach to all nations, as stated in Matthew Chapter 28.
The Gospel, like thunder, resounded throughout the world, and nations that didn't pursue righteousness attained it, as mentioned in Romans Chapter 9.
Those who were far off were brought near by the blood of Christ, as noted in Ephesians Chapter 2.
Those who were once not a people are now a holy people in Christ, as referenced in Hosea Chapter 2.
It's the acceptable time and the day of salvation, as stated in Second Corinthians Chapter 6, and the times of refreshing in the presence of the Most High, as recorded in Acts Chapter 3.
Each nation has a witness of the resurrection, as the Lord tells his disciples, "Behold, I am with you all the days, until the end of the age," as noted in Matthew Chapter 28.
So, let us not do anything without Christ, lest Christ becomes without us in the future.
Therefore, beloved, we should embrace the discipline of Christ with all devotion and be obedient to our leaders for Christ's sake.
Discipline is essential for adolescents and young people, and they should submit to the teachings of their elders with humility and reverence.
In the Old Testament, the Lord commanded the Levites to serve in the tabernacle from the age of 25 and to become guardians of the vessels at 50, as stated in Numbers Chapter 8.
The 25th year, when the flower of youth begins, signifies the battles of vices against each person.
The 50th year, which contains the rest of the jubilee, represents the internal peace of a disciplined mind.
The vessels of the tabernacle symbolize the souls of the faithful.
The Levites begin serving at the tabernacle from the age of twenty-five, and by fifty, they become guardians of the vessels.
This implies that those still battling personal vices shouldn't assume the responsibility of guiding others; instead, they should remain under the guidance of their elders.
Once they overcome temptations and attain inner peace and security, they can then care for souls, becoming learned participants in spiritual battles.
However, who can fully conquer these battles when even Paul, the most learned and formidable fighter, says:
"I see another law in my members, warring against the law of my mind and bringing me into captivity to the law of sin" (Romans Chapter Seven).
There's a clear distinction between bravely enduring battles and being easily defeated.
In these intense battles, the strength of youth is honed so it doesn't become arrogant; in weaker and disordered ones, it is completely extinguished, unable to endure.
Therefore, it's beneficial for young people to humbly serve their superiors while the vigor of youth flourishes.
For how can one expect to be served in old age if they refuse to obey their elders when young?
A young person who doesn't wish to submit to the discipline of their elders shouldn't expect respect from the younger generation when they're old.
This is why the ancient proverb states that those who refuse to serve will not want to be served.
Even the Lord Jesus Christ, when young and not yet a teacher, obediently served his parents.
He demonstrated honor, respect, and service to them in his youth to set an example of obedience and service for young people (Luke Chapter Two).
Just as sobriety and moral perfection are expected in the elderly, service, submission, and obedience are rightly expected from the young.
Therefore, in the commandments of the law, the first of those that pertain to people.
.
The command to honor one's father and mother is given in Exodus 20.
This applies even if the biological father has died or was unworthy; the idea is that children should still show honor to someone as a father figure until they reach maturity and are worthy of making their own decisions.
It is appropriate that, until they come of age, children are instructed to live under the guidance or discipline of their father or, if necessary, another trusted adult.
This is because someone without discipline and learning will never be a true disciple of Christ.
In Scripture, the term "father" is used in five different ways: by nature, by nation, by instruction, by age, and by adoption.
For a natural father, Jacob said to Laban: "If the God of my father Isaac had not been with me, you would have taken everything I own" (Genesis 31).
By nation, someone is called a father when God says to Moses from the burning bush: "I am the God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob" (Exodus 3).
By age and instruction, someone is called a father when Moses says in the song of Deuteronomy: "Ask your father and he will tell you; your elders and they will explain it to you" (Deuteronomy 32).
By adoption, we call God our Father when we say in prayer: "Our Father, who art in heaven" (Matthew 6).
So even if your biological father is no longer alive or has proven unworthy, young people must still show obedience to a wise and upright elder who instructs them.
For how can a person be worthy of honor in old age if they did not accept the burden of discipline in their youth?
Whatever a person sows, that is what they will reap (Galatians 6).
Discipline may not seem joyful in the moment; it feels like sorrow and hard work, not rest.
But later, it yields the peaceful fruit of righteousness for those trained by it (Hebrews 12).
Just as a tree cannot produce fruit if it never had buds or blossoms, so a person cannot rightfully receive honor in old age if they did not work hard in their youth to follow some good form of discipline.
And how can there be discipline without obedience?
A young person without obedience is a young person without discipline.
Why is that?
Obedience, which is the foundation and culmination of all virtues, requires a lot of practice to align with Christ the Lord, who was obedient to the Father, even to the point of death, willingly enduring the shame of the cross for everyone, as stated in
Philippians
Chapter 2.
However, the discipline enforced by Catholic teachers should be moderated so it doesn't harm those it is meant to heal and cure through excessive harshness.
Proud teachers tend to wound rather than correct, as Solomon points out: "In the mouth of a fool is a rod of pride"
Proverbs 14.
Indeed, proud teachers carry this rod of pride because they harshly strike when rebuking and lack the ability to be humbly compassionate and merciful.
Similarly, angry teachers can turn the discipline into cruelty through their rage, and instead of correcting, they end up causing harm.
Consequently, a furious leader punishes faults excessively because their heart, distracted by various concerns, isn't centered on the love of a single dignity.
A mind distracted by too many things isn't bound by the chain of charity, and when poorly focused, it acts wrongly at every chance.
Thus, every leader must be very careful in their actions towards those they lead, being mindful of the judgment they might face from Christ.
As it is written: "With the measure you use, it will be measured to you"
Matthew 7.
Therefore, anyone in a leadership position should manage their subjects' discipline with both authority and humility.
The virtue of humility must be present to prevent the lives of their subjects from falling into vice.
At the same time, authority must be evident to ensure that severity doesn't become excessive due to pride.
This is the true discernment needed in the priests of God, where they are neither overly proud in their freedom nor overly lax in their humility.
It's important to understand that not all subjects should be treated with the same approach; the teachings should vary according to their character.
Therefore, obvious sins should not be addressed with hidden corrections.
When people openly harm others, they should be corrected publicly.
This way, those who have followed their bad example can learn from the rebuke.
Correcting one person can lead to improvement for many.
It's better for one person to face consequences for the benefit of many, rather than for many to be led astray by one person's wrongdoing.
Therefore, it's important to address wrongdoers in a manner that considers their well-being.
Some respond to strong scolding, while others are better corrected with a gentle approach.
As the Blessed Ambrose, a highly respected figure in the Church of Christ, states:
"A person who is gently corrected respects the one correcting them. However, if they are upset by excessive harshness, they neither accept the correction nor achieve salvation."
The Blessed Isidore, an excellent teacher, says:
"Just as skilled doctors use different medicines for various illnesses, applying treatments based on the nature of the wounds, so should a church teacher offer appropriate doctrinal remedies to each person, considering their age, gender, and profession."
Sometimes, discerning teachers use harsh rebukes, but they always maintain love for those they correct.
Often, the Church's judgment may seem arrogant to the proud, and what the righteous do with good intentions is perceived as cruel by the wicked, because they fail to see the good spirit behind the actions.
Moreover, some perverse individuals, when accused of their wrongdoings, reject the words of their just leaders to avoid criticism, thereby leaving themselves to divine judgment, which will be harsher since they scorn temporary human judgment.
To the wicked, truth is unpleasant, and the discipline of justice is bitter. They find joy only in indulging their own weaknesses, unproductive in justice, barren in truth, blind to the light, and quick to see the error of darkness.
There are people so corrupt that, instead of addressing their own wrongdoings, they falsely accuse those who correct them.
They find solace in their crimes by making false accusations against good people.
This is why it is written in the Proverbs of Solomon: "The wicked turn good into evil and place a blemish on the chosen" Ecclesiasticus 11.
Many wicked individuals also defend others like themselves in wrongdoing and support the depraved against the correction of the good, so they avoid being corrected for what displeases them.
They add others' offenses to their own, making them guilty not only of their own wrongs but also of the crimes of those they defend.
Therefore, church discipline must be moderate and wise, to correct the negligent, strengthen the weak, and encourage the good to strive for greater gifts.
I urge you, my brothers and lords, to willingly accept the discipline of our Lord Jesus Christ, as conveyed by your leaders.
Do your utmost to follow their commands and prioritize their will over your own in all matters.
Let none of you say: Why should I accept my abbot's discipline when I am more learned and have a greater understanding of the Scriptures?
Or: Why should I submit to my leader's discipline when he is of humble birth, and I am the son of a more powerful and influential man?
Why should I follow his commands when he is more negligent in his conduct, and I live a holier life?
Do not, my beloved brothers, entertain such thoughts; for neither work, nor reason, nor knowledge, nor wisdom holds any value in the grave Ecclesiastes 9.
Let no one boast of noble birth, for on the day of the final judgment of our Lord Jesus Christ, nobility will not be able to help him.
No one should pridefully challenge their leader because of the holiness granted to them by God.
For many fasts, alms, vigils, tears, prayers, and other good deeds, if tainted with pride, become worthless to God.
Be humble and accept the guidance of your superior with full devotion.
It's better to be corrected or disciplined by a just person than to be deceived or flattered by a sinner.
As the Psalmist says:
"The just person will correct me with mercy and rebuke me, but the oil of the sinner will not anoint my head" from Psalm one forty.
The oil of the sinner is the praise of a flatterer.
So, the head is anointed with the oil of the sinner when the listener's mind delights in flattery.
In divine Scriptures, the mind is referred to as the head.
Willingly submit your backs to the whip to escape the torments of hell.
Don't consider it harsh to be whipped by the abbot's hand, so you may be counted among the martyrs in the heavenly court.
Isn't it better to be temporarily beaten with rods by your superior for your faults and negligence than to endure eternal torment in hell?
Isn't it much better and more tolerable to humbly bear the abbot's sentence in this world than, through pride and stubbornness, to suffer the punishment of eternal damnation with the devil and his angels in hell?
So, beloved ones, hold and keep the discipline of your shepherd with devotion, so you may be heirs of eternal happiness with him.
Respect the one who disciplines, love the one who corrects, honor the one who advises, thank the one who whips, offer obedience to the one who counsels good, and fully obey the regular and God-pleasing commands given.
Don't repay evil for good, don't respond to a blessing with a curse, don't argue with the preacher, and don't dishonor the one who rebukes.
In everything you do, present yourselves as servants and followers of God.
Despise earthly things and love heavenly ones.
Earnestly lament your sins and those of the people whose charity you benefit from.
Fear the punishments of hell, and desire the joys of eternal life, so that by following the footsteps of Christ without stumbling, you may reach the heavenly homeland with the abbot who leads you.
This is by the grace of Him who lives and reigns with the same Father and Holy Spirit in perfect Trinity, God, forever and ever.
Amen.
Chapter Seven: How Young People Should Avoid Idleness
It's important, my brothers and lords, that we come together to listen to teachings that concern our education and the whole Church, as spoken by Isidore, the teacher of the Spanish.
I believe God has given us his body so we might devoutly receive his most beneficial teachings and eagerly carry them out through good works.
Therefore, we should listen to his admonition as reverently as if he were speaking to us directly.
He says: Just as we desire to learn through reading the things we don't know, we should also strive to put into action the right things we've learned.
A diligent reader is more eager to act on what he reads than simply to learn what he doesn't know.
The law of God offers both reward and punishment to those who read it.
It rewards those who follow it by living well, and it punishes those who disregard it by living poorly.
It's a greater fault to know what you should do and choose not to do it.
As the Lord says in the Gospel: The servant who knows his master's will and does not do it will receive many blows.
And James says: For one who knows the right thing to do and does not do it, it is sin.
Therefore, a servant of God must continually read, pray, and work, lest the spirit of fornication stealthily enters a mind given to idleness and incites to sin.
Lust quickly overtakes a man it finds idle; however, a body tired from work is less tempted by shameful acts.
Consider King Solomon, who through idleness became entangled in many fornications and, through the vice of fornication, fell into idolatry.
Both are greatly commended before God as necessary: that prayer supports work, and work supports prayer.
Hence, Jeremiah also says: Let us lift our hearts with our hands to God.
He lifts his heart with his hands who raises his prayer with good work.
For whoever prays without working lifts his heart but does not lift his hands.
Whoever works without praying lifts his hands to God but does not lift his heart.
Since it's important to both work and pray, it's well expressed in both ways: Let us lift our hearts with our hands to God.
So, dear brothers, to avoid being criticized for neglecting the commandments while trying to achieve salvation through either prayer or work alone, it's essential that after doing a good deed, we offer tears of prayer.
This way, through humility, we can earn the merit of good actions by pleading.
Anyone who wants to please God in all they do should steer clear of idleness.
Sometimes they should focus on prayer; at other times, they should engage in work that benefits themselves and others.
Idleness breeds foolishness, but labor brings knowledge.
That's why, in all good work, we must be wary of deceit and desires.
We deceive God when we praise ourselves instead of God for our good deeds.
We act negligently when we sluggishly handle God's work due to laziness.
Every skill in this world has dedicated enthusiasts eager to pursue it, because it offers immediate rewards for their efforts.
However, the skill of divine fear has many followers who are sluggish, lukewarm, and frozen by laziness, because the reward for their labor is not immediate but delayed for the future.
As a result, since the reward doesn't come right away, they almost lose hope and weaken in their good work.
There is both inner and outer labor and idleness.
The labor of the inner person is the pursuit of knowledge, while the labor of the outer person is the exercise of action.
The labor of knowledge is divided into three parts: discipline, exercise, and teaching.
In childhood, there's the labor of discipline; in youth, the labor of exercise; and in old age, the labor of teaching.
This way, the one who doesn't know learns in childhood; the one who has learned applies it in youth; and what they have applied, they teach in old age.
There is also another type of inner work, involving thought and meditation, to achieve the peace of contemplation.
If something is hidden in doubt due to forgetfulness, it becomes clear through thought, clearer through meditation, and clearest through contemplation.
When something heavenly comes to mind, it starts as a confused thought, becomes clearer through meditation, and is finally recognized through contemplation.
Thus, thought is sparked by consideration, meditation is fueled by discernment, and contemplation is illuminated by understanding.
Thought is like smoke in the mind, meditation like a flame with smoke, and contemplation like a fire with a flame but without smoke.
However, when the mind tries to focus on heavenly things, thought is distracted by worldly matters, meditation is disturbed by leisure, and contemplation is interrupted by curiosity.
Sometimes this happens, causing the idle mind to become numb with pleasure and fall into vices.
When the inner self lies in the comfort of pleasure, numbed by laziness and distracted by curious dreams, it calls the outer self to listen to gossip, speak of trivial matters, wear soft clothing, eat early in the morning, and stop reading at the crow of the rooster.
When going to sleep, they meet the brothers rising for vigils; as others watch, they sleep, and as others return, they rise.
It might be better if they said nothing at all than if they chanted psalms with missing syllables or words.
This reflects the slowness of the idle, who do nothing on time but always linger.
They prefer eating outside the convent and rising later than the appointed hours.
These are those who wait with the donkey, not ascending the mountain with Isaac: carrying straw and a goad, which belong to the donkey, not fire and a sword, which belong to the sacrifice.
For Abraham said to the young men, "Wait here with the donkey; the boy and I will go over there, worship, and then return to you."
(Genesis 22)
The young men represent the childish senses of the mind, waiting with the donkey because they always prefer slowness.
There are said to be two types of people: those who are idle and those who are lukewarm, burdened by the desires of the flesh and the distractions of frivolity.
Abraham, whose name means "father of many nations," represents a mind full of thoughts. He went up with a boy, symbolizing a pure heart, carrying fire and a sword. Here, fire signifies love, and the sword represents the power of preaching. Therefore, the one who carries both fire and a sword fulfills what they love and communicates through their deeds.
He says, "I and the boy will return to you." This means that both reason and a pure mind must return to address the needs of the body, focusing on necessities rather than desires. The body always craves plenty and the luxury of idleness. However, what is necessary should be provided, not withheld. To avoid idleness while providing for the body, there should be discipline and labor. The rod signifies correction, and the burden represents work. Between discipline and labor, there is no room for idleness.
Therefore, one should work both internally and externally, applying themselves diligently, so they are not asked, "Why are you standing here all day idle?" Those who spend their lives avoiding good work and indulging in vanity are idle. A community of brothers is almost idle if the abbot doesn't encourage them to work, meaning engaging in a disciplined life through teaching and guidance. People remain idle if neither the bishop nor the archdeacons lead them to good work. The leaders should understand the reason for this idleness: "No one has hired us," they say.
Neither bishops nor priests guide the people, nor do abbots or priors lead their communities. Where do they lead them? Perhaps toward seeking temporal honor instead of spiritual work. Maybe they focus more on the king's court than the Lord's vineyard, valuing money over addressing guilt, and discussing wealth rather than cleansing sins.
Some great leaders hire workers for labor, teaching with words and leading by example.
People of all ages come to work: children, young people, and the elderly.
They arrive at different times of the day: morning, noon, and evening.
Children come in the morning, young people at noon, and the elderly in the evening.
In a manner of speaking, Maurus arrives in the morning, Paul at noon, and Tranquellinus or Gentianus in the evening.
We broadly include youth, encompassing not only adolescence but also mature age.
This is the ideal time for work because in the next life, no one will be able to work.
Night comes when no one can work, as noted in the Gospel of John, chapter nine.
During this time, Paul, wanting to make the most of it, devoted himself to both contemplation and action.
Let's consider the Patriarch Issachar as an example of exercise, perseverance, and perfection.
Issachar, meaning reward, represents the people bought by the Lord with His blood.
Issachar is described as a strong donkey in Genesis, chapter forty-nine, because pagan people were once like a brute animal serving idols.
Now, they are strong, submitting to the yoke of the Redeemer Lord and bearing the burden of evangelical discipline.
Lying between boundaries, Issachar saw that rest was good and the land was excellent, so he put his shoulder to carry and became a servant to tribute, as mentioned in Genesis, chapter forty-nine.
Therefore, beloved, we must journey from one land to another, from foreign lands to our homeland, from exile to home, from one nation to another, from the land of the dying to the land of the living, if we want to truly experience joy.
Let us also desire the land that Issachar saw and longed for.
For if he hadn't seen it, he wouldn't have known it; and if he hadn't known it, he wouldn't have desired it, as mentioned in the Gospel of John, chapter fourteen.
Because of this land, becoming a strong donkey, he willingly put his shoulder to carry and became a servant to tribute.
He suddenly felt as though he was worth much less, comparing himself to a donkey, often seen as one of the most worthless animals.
He deeply desired the land he saw and endured all sorts of hardships for it.
He realized that, compared to the beauty of that land, all our righteous acts were like a woman's menstrual cloth, as mentioned in Isaiah 64.
He also understood that the sufferings of this present time are nothing compared to the future glory that will be revealed in us, as stated in Romans 8.
In one sense, he felt worthless; in another, he found strength.
Humbled by one thing and strengthened by another, he willingly took on all labor, paying tribute to the heavenly king and seeking divine glory, not his own.
Do you want to hear about another who, in a similar way, felt worthless but also found strength for all labor?
"I was like a beast before you," says David in Psalm 73.
And elsewhere: "For your sake, we face death all day long" (Psalm 44).
See how he felt worthless, yet strong.
Worthless like a beast, but strong enough to mortify himself.
Issachar, a strong donkey dwelling between the boundaries, saw that rest was good and the land was excellent.
He almost, but not completely, grasped that land of the living, dwelling between the borders.
Content with the most worthless and fewest goods of this miserable earth, he held the outermost parts of this land.
Because he often tasted the goods of eternal life through frequent mental ecstasies, he touched the beginnings of that blessed land.
"I saw that rest was good," he says.
So, rest is good there, in the heavenly homeland, because if it weren't there, he wouldn't have seen it; and if it weren't good, he wouldn't have carried it on his shoulder.
"The meek," says the Prophet, "will inherit the land and delight in an abundance of peace" (Psalm 37).
See what kind of land it is: there is true rest, full peace, good rest, quiet peace, peaceful rest.
In that heavenly homeland, there is no labor, but it cannot be reached without labor.
For its sake, we toil in this life, but there, no one is required to labor.
True rest isn't found beyond this earth, because there's no labor there.
So, if we want to redeem the time like Paul and avoid the evil days, we need to regularly pray, work, and read in this life (Ephesians 5).
Just as Jacob returns to his homeland with Rachel and Leah (Genesis 30), Lazarus is brought back to life by the prayers of Mary and Martha (John 11).
Jacob returns with Rachel and Leah when someone, eager to do good works, embraces both active and contemplative life.
Lazarus, meaning "helped," is resurrected when someone is freed from the death of sin through good works and tears.
No one is exempt from labor-not children, not the young, not the old. Yet, it's the youth who carry the burden of the day and the heat. They bear the physical demands of labor and the moral challenges of desire.
The burden of temptations is overcome by manual labor; idleness only increases the temptation of vices. The body is disciplined by work, but idleness nourishes it. A young person in idleness is like an unyoked ox, running wildly through their own desires without the restraint of obedience in the community.
Therefore, I urge you, dearest brothers, to listen diligently. In that good and excellent land, our heavenly home, there is no labor, but no one can reach it without effort. It is said: Great rewards require great efforts. And again: No one will be crowned unless they have competed by the rules (Second Timothy 2).
The kingdom of heaven won't be given to the lukewarm, idle, and wandering, but to those trained in God's service, diligently fighting against vices and temptations.
So, lift your minds to that good and excellent land, and for its love, disregard all worldly things.
To inherit it, willingly shoulder the burden of discipline.
Follow your leaders wholeheartedly, so you may reach the heavenly homeland.
Willingly submit to the divine order.
For the love of Christ, set aside selfishness and find strength in serving God.
Focus beyond the present, desire future blessings, reject worldly temptations, cherish spiritual values, use material things only as needed, and yearn for eternal joy.
But my soul, not yet gathered for eternal joy, does not truly know what rest is.
Woe to me, a wretched one, still wandering and exiled on this earth!
I wander, driven by desire; I am exiled, avoiding misery.
Desire leads me astray, while misery makes me a fugitive.
Indeed, this earth is not a place of stability for the heart but rather a place of hardness and insensitivity of the mind.
Oh, how blessed is the one who could forget all evils, even for an hour, and enjoy inner peace or rest, even for a moment!
Equally blessed is the one who can gather the distractions of the heart and focus his desire on true happiness!
So let us, dear ones, journey with the patriarch Issachar in mind and deed, from misery to the best land, from a foreign place to our true home, from exile to homeland, from prison to court, from unhappiness to glory, from captivity to freedom, from death to life, from darkness to light, from the theater to the palace, from the workhouse to the kingdom, from the sewer to heaven, from the mire of vices to the company of angels, to which Jesus Christ may lead us, who lives and reigns with the Father and Holy Spirit in perfect Trinity, God, forever and ever.
Amen.
Chapter Eight: How the Old and the Young Ought to Serve God
I advise you, dearest brothers, for the sake of your salvation, to listen closely to the wise words of Solomon from the Book of Wisdom, Chapter 4: "Gray hair is the understanding of a person, and the age of old age is an unblemished life."
Therefore, one is not truly considered old because of advanced age, but because of perfect understanding.
Old age is honorable not due to its length or the number of years, but because of a life that is innocent and pleasing to God.
Childhood is not absent if one is young and frivolous in understanding.
Hence, it is said in the Book of Isaiah, Chapter 65: "Cursed is the child of one hundred years."
Although someone may be young in age, if they possess great understanding, they should be considered among the old, not the young.
It is written about Daniel: He was young in age, but old in wisdom and gentleness.
David, too, was a child in age, yet perfect in understanding; his heart and mind were set on the Lord, which led to his elevation as king.
Saul, despite his old age, was cast down from his royal throne due to his great wickedness and childish frivolity.
Our Lord and Savior was crucified by the elders and praised by children upon entering Jerusalem.
Even a tree of many years, if fruitless, is cut down; but if it is young and fruitful, it is nurtured to produce more fruit.
Therefore, dearest brothers, these comparisons are given so that none of you, whether young or old, may take pride in your virtue or trust in your works; but always remain mindful of displeasing God in any work and be cautious of being separated from Him forever.
What then? "Let the one who boasts, boast in the Lord," as stated in First Corinthians, Chapter 1, and not in themselves.
However, it should be known that in some things we must be like children, and in others, like the old.
Hence, the Lord in the Gospel says in the Book of Matthew, Chapter 18: "Unless you change and become like little children, you will never enter the kingdom of heaven."
And Peter the Apostle says:
Like newborn babies, desire the pure milk of the word
First Peter chapter two.
Similarly, Paul says:
Do not be children in your understanding, but in malice be like children; in understanding be mature
First Corinthians chapter fourteen.
Therefore, it is fitting for everyone to serve God diligently and cling to Him through good deeds, especially for the elderly, who are already near the grave.
It is even more fitting for those whose youthful years have passed to dedicate themselves to religion.
Just as a tree is deemed worthless if, after flowering, it does not produce good fruit for its gardener, so is a person considered unworthy if the bloom of youth has passed and they neglect to produce mature fruits of good deeds in their old age.
What can be more foolish or senseless than not striving for perfection when the whole body is weakened by old age and the person is nearing death?
When eyes grow dim, ears hardly hear, hair falls out, the face turns pale, teeth are lost, skin dries and wrinkles, breath no longer smells sweet, the chest is congested, coughing and wheezing persist, knees tremble, swelling affects ankles and feet, and the inner self, which does not age, is burdened by all these.
All these things announce the impending collapse of the body's house.
What remains, then, but to consider how to secure the prosperity of future access and evade the soul's dangers as this life's end approaches?
For the end of this life is uncertain for the young, but for the elderly, departure from this world is closer.
Therefore, two parts must be guarded in a person that do not age and lead the whole person to sin: namely, the heart and the tongue.
Because the heart never stops devising new thoughts, and the tongue eagerly speaks whatever the heart devises.
So, the old man shouldn't just say: I don't shed human blood, I don't set my neighbor's houses on fire, I don't steal other people's things.
Because if he doesn't remove unnecessary and, worse yet, harmful thoughts from his heart and doesn't guard his mouth, he will be found guilty before Christ, the strict judge, even for a careless word.
Therefore, old age should be cautious, so these youthful tendencies-namely, an uncontrolled tongue and a mind preoccupied with useless and vain thoughts-don't disrupt the whole harmony and mock the seriousness of the rest of the body with foolish matters, leading it to the torments of hell.
An old man who is close to death, who doesn't shun or fear its approach, stands, as it were, at the door of this world, strong and steadfast, but doesn't pay attention to leaving this life nor consider entering the next, alienates himself from the company of the righteous.
He hears the messengers of death and doesn't want to believe them.
For there are three messengers of death: accidents, illness, and old age.
Accidents announce uncertain death, illness serious, and old age certain.
From the uncertainty of death comes fear; from the severity of illness, pain; from the certainty of old age, not stubbornness, but humility and affliction should follow.
But perhaps the threefold cord that binds the old man is not easily broken.
As it is said in Ecclesiastes chapter four, the threefold cord of bad habit is a usage made of three parts: when thought is entangled with speech, and speech with action, by idle people.
For when pleasure has made a path in the old man's mind from childhood through thought, vanity in speech, and perversity in action, what else happens but that these three are twisted into habit?
Moreover, there is a snare in the rope, the sweetness of temporal things in habit; the encirclement of the rope is the hindrances of the flesh.
We are deceived by the sweetness of temporal things, bound by habit.
But he escaped the snare who said of himself and his companions: Our soul has escaped like a bird from the hunter's snare; the snare is broken, and we are set free (Psalm one hundred and twenty-four).
Absalom, caught by his hair in the oak tree, symbolizes the stubbornness of someone determined not to do good.
While fleeing from his father's army, his hair got tangled in a dense oak tree.
(Second Samuel, Chapter 18).
The name Absalom means "peace of the father," because his father endured him, even as he pursued him.
It's not called "peace of the son," because he refused to endure his father.
An oak is tougher on the inside, yet more fragile on the outside.
Absalom hangs from it, clinging to the stubbornness inside his mind, but outwardly showing the frailty of the flesh.
Hanging by his hair, he is suspended by the love of vanity.
The mule he was riding on passed by, leaving him hanging from the oak.
This signifies that while the luxury and deceit he served perished, the punishment for his sin remained.
His heart was pierced by three spears, representing greed, pride, and lust.
Thus, to this day, a large heap of stones is piled over him, symbolizing the weight of his numerous sins or punishments.
It's no surprise that it was a large heap of stones, as through stubbornness, he carried an unrepentant heart to the end.
There are also three types of stubborn people:
first, those who improve through correction;
second, those who become worse through warnings;
and third, those who promise to change but never do.
King Manasseh improved through correction.
(Second Chronicles, Chapter 33).
Nabal became worse despite warnings.
(First Samuel, Chapter 25).
Pharaoh became more stubborn through affliction.
(Exodus, Chapter 7).
Manasseh, imprisoned and bound with chains, came to know God, whom he had refused to acknowledge when free.
Some monks are like this; as long as they are their own masters, they live perversely.
But when they are confined in the monastery, as if imprisoned by chains of obedience and fear, and further restricted by not being allowed to wander outside, they sometimes come to love God, whom they previously despised, when corrected.
And those who turned freedom into servitude, turn necessity into virtue.
Those who are misled by their own freedom become devoted through the guidance of another's authority.
Nabal represents certain teachers who become worse after being corrected by their followers.
They deny food to David's young men because they refuse to share the word of God with those who seek to live purely.
They prepare a feast for their shearers because they prefer the idle chatter of flatterers.
Nabal accuses David, saying, "Today, many servants are running away from their masters." First Samuel chapter twenty-five. Corrupt leaders indeed feel troubled when they see the number of religious people increasing. They fear when they see David, meaning good subjects, being anointed as king, and Saul being deposed, meaning corrupt leaders being stripped of their authority. But why do they fear? Clearly, they worry about losing their own honors, fearing someone better might take their place.
Abigail told Nabal all the words she heard from David, and his heart died within him, and he became like a stone, when someone becomes hardened by eternal death. After Nabal's death, Abigail became queen because those who live well under a corrupt teacher can be elevated to lead souls, gaining a temporary kingdom with David and reigning forever with Christ.
David sent messengers to Abigail, and she followed them. Abigail follows David's messengers just as any faithful person imitates the life and conduct of the Church's teachers. Her five maidservants accompanied her. Her five maidservants are like the five senses of the body, which follow Abigail as they serve any righteous person through the purity of self-control.
Pharaoh, who promised to let Moses' people go but did not, represents those who promise to improve their lives but neither abandon their faults nor seek true contrition in the spirit of a dove. Instead, they seek delay in the voice of a raven. Their land is afflicted by various plagues but does not soften, becoming more hardened by the habit of sinning. Then the Lord turns the waters into blood when someone perceives things in a carnal way.
The earth produces frogs when someone talks too much and fills the air with empty chatter.
Flies and gnats are like a rush of thoughts and stubborn habits that swarm the mind.
The death of livestock symbolizes the end of thoughts that, lacking rational understanding, resemble livestock.
Just as a person is compared to senseless animals, they become like them, as mentioned in
Psalms
49.
The sixth plague occurs when blisters swell and insides decay, reflecting how inner thoughts swell with hatred and boil with anger.
The plague of hail on fruits represents obvious wickedness in actions.
The plague of locusts signifies the instability of a soul that harms with its words when it slanders and leaps towards carnal desires.
The plague of darkness represents the blindness of souls, which becomes tangible when the mind's evil thoughts are acted upon.
Indeed, that which can be touched by hand is tangible.
Notice that the plague of locusts is placed between the plague of hail and the plague of darkness.
From the wickedness represented by the hail, locusts leap towards the blindness of eternal damnation.
The final plague is the death of the firstborn.
The moral firstborn of the mind are indeed the will and intention of anyone acting.
When the will and intention are corrupted, they are struck down like the firstborn of the Egyptians.
These plagues afflict the stubbornness of an old man who delights in worldly things, enjoys chatter, bothers everyone,
is prone to vices like livestock, swells with anger, is obvious in doing harm, is unstable in everything, lacks the light of truth, and therefore gropes himself.
Once again, my dear ones, I speak with compassion about the stubborn old man.
An old man who is invited to good work in the morning, at the third, sixth, and ninth hours, that is, in childhood, adolescence, youth, and old age,
and refuses to come-what else does he await but the night of eternal damnation, in which he will no longer be able to do any good?
An old man who spends his days idle, refusing to endure life's challenges for God, is ultimately setting himself up for eternal punishment.
As the blessed John the Baptist stated:
"The axe is already laid at the root of the trees. Every tree that does not produce good fruit will be cut down and thrown into the fire."
(Matthew, Chapter Three).
Just like a barren tree is cut down and burned, a fruitless old man who stubbornly avoids doing good is eventually claimed by death and assigned to the fires of hell.
How can he expect to enter the eternal King's wedding feast when he hears the Lord's call but ignores it, avoiding the path of good deeds?
Indeed, everyone must persist in good works, especially the elderly, who are more aware of their limited time.
An old man indulging in frivolity and wrongdoing will be accountable not only for his own actions but also for leading others astray with his poor example.
Therefore, even if late, a negligent old man must return to his senses, break the chains of bad habits, and rescue his soul from danger by living righteously.
He should wholeheartedly submit to the Church's discipline, not pretending or delaying, but with the humility of a dove, correcting his past mistakes.
He must rid himself of frivolous attachments, casting aside excess, so that he doesn't cling to stubbornness and greed, ending up empty of good deeds and separated from God's chosen ones.
So listen, whoever you are, an idle and unproductive old man, listen to my words, heed my advice.
Stop adding to your sins and put an end to your wrongdoings.
It is time to reflect on who you are, why you were born, and the purpose of your creation in this world.
Did God Almighty create you in this life just to spend all your time idly?
Or rather, to know Him, serve Him faithfully, and ultimately reign with Him in heaven?
If so, why do you turn away from Him who created you and everything from nothing, and expose yourself to the flames of hell by living wrongly?
So, hurry for your own sake, dear soul, while you have the chance.
Otherwise, if you refuse now, there may come a time when you want to, but can no longer do so.
God is always ready to forgive our sins if we turn to Him with all our heart and pray with humility and sincerity.
Therefore, while He waits patiently, let us hasten to turn to Him by doing good, lest we provoke Him to anger by delaying.
He has indeed predestined some to punishment, but granted great benefits to others; and He did this not unjustly, but according to His wise counsel and judgment.
For Cain committed murder Genesis Chapter 4, and Job suffered as a friend of God Job Chapter 2.
Abel was killed by his brother Genesis Chapter 4.
Yet Job did not suffer indefinitely, nor was forgiveness offered to Ananias Acts Chapter 5.
Paul was not abandoned when beaten, as His grace made him strong Second Corinthians Chapter 12.
Judas was not received even when repentant Matthew Chapter 27, yet Peter was not deserted when weeping Luke Chapter 22.
Thus, the compassionate and merciful Lord separates the vessels of wrath from the vessels of mercy according to His high judgment.
Consider the unfortunate Judas, once a perfect vessel led to destruction, unable to contain the new wine of the Holy Spirit, and upon receiving it, he burst, for a completely broken vessel is useful for nothing!
I've shared these examples with you, dear elder, hoping for good things, so that you do not delay in turning to God.
Instead, as quickly as possible, humbly submit yourself to the yoke of service to Christ.
Hurry, then, while you still can, as God grants you the grace to live.
Lest, if you delay, He who did not spare the natural branches may not spare you either Romans Chapter 11.
Therefore, act now as you should.
Consider the end of your life daily.
Remember the inevitability of your death.
Decide not to sin anymore. Resolve not to stray again.
Be careful not to repeat your mistakes. Think about the future judgment.
Remember the eternal fires of hell.
Consider the terrible punishments of Gehenna.
Pray with tears constantly.
Pray continuously.
Ask God day and night to mercifully forgive your sins.
Confess your sins with tears, and hope without doubt for God's mercy.
Put aside injustice, and trust in God's goodness for forgiveness.
I want you to know again, dearest brothers, that the Son of God chose to die not only for the elderly but for everyone He predestined for eternal life.
Therefore, it's fitting for all children, adolescents, young people, the elderly, and all ages of the faithful to recognize Him as the one true God with the Father and the Holy Spirit.
To love Him with fear, and to fear Him with love.
To cling to Him with a pure and devoted mind, and to offer pleasing service to Him to the best of your ability.
So, diligently follow His footsteps as much as possible, so that you may be able to see Him reigning at the right hand of His Father.
By His grace, who lives and reigns with the same Father and Holy Spirit as God in perfect Trinity forever and ever.
Amen.
Chapter Nine: That Monks or Canons Should Not Presume to Frequent the King's Court
I ask and urge you, my brothers and lords, to carefully listen to the words of the Spanish teacher Isidore:
He says there are different commandments for those living a common life in this world and for those who have renounced it.
For all those living a common life, it is said they should manage their affairs well and justly;
for those who have renounced the world, it is commanded to leave everything behind for Christ.
Those, meaning all the faithful, are bound by general commandments;
these, that is, the religious, rise above these commandments by living more perfectly.
To them, it is said not to steal from others;
to these, to abandon what they have.
To them, it is commanded not to kill;
to these, not to hate anyone but to pray to the Lord for their enemies.
It is lawful for them to legitimately take wives;
for these, it is unlawful to even think about anything related to marriage.
They are commanded not to give false testimony against anyone;
these are told to guard their mouths.
All the faithful are commonly allowed to use worldly things well;
religious people are told to delight in living for God alone, having denied all else.
It is the way of secular people to go here and there through the streets of the city doing good;
it is the way of religious people to avoid the sight of others and enclose themselves within the walls of the cloister.
Therefore, those who renounce the world for fear of God but are still entangled in family matters, the more they involve themselves in worldly affairs, the more they separate from divine love.
Those who try to serve both earthly concerns and divine duties at the same time cannot manage both;
because two cares cannot coexist in the human heart, and it's difficult to please both masters when serving two.
Those who, after renouncing the world, long for the heavenly homeland with holy desires, are lifted from earthly intentions as if by wings and see where they have fallen through their lamentations;
and where they have reached, they look forward with great joy.
However, when someone is pulled away from the peace of contemplation and falls into the vices of this world, if they come back to their senses, they immediately groan.
No matter how peaceful the things they lost were, and how confusing the situation they've fallen into is, they recognize it by the difficulty of their struggle.
For what is more laborious in this life than being consumed by earthly desires, or what is more secure than not craving anything of this world?
Those who love this world are troubled by its chaotic cares and worries, but those who hate and do not follow them enjoy the tranquility of inner peace and begin to experience a glimpse of future peace here and now.
A monk is called such from the Greek etymology because they are solitary.
In Greek, "monas" means singularity in Latin.
So, if a monk is interpreted as solitary, what is someone who is alone doing in a crowd, and why are they among the people?
There are many kinds of monks.
The first kind is the cenobites, whom we can call those living in community.
A cenobium consists of many, resembling those holy ones who, during the times of the apostles in Jerusalem, sold and distributed all their possessions to those in need, living in a holy communal life, claiming nothing as their own but having everything in common, with one soul and one heart in the Lord, as described in the Acts of the Apostles.
From their institution and example, monasteries began under the guidance of the Holy Spirit.
The second kind is the hermits, who are said to withdraw far from people, inhabiting deserted and vast places, imitating Elijah and John the Baptist, who ventured into solitary retreats.
The third kind is the anchorites, who, having perfected the communal way of life, enclose themselves in cells, removed from human sight and rarely allowing anyone access to them, living solely in contemplation and conversation with the Lord.
The name "Abba" is Syrian and means father in Latin, as Paul explained when writing to the Romans, saying: In whom we cry: Abba, Father.
He uses two languages in one name, calling his father by a Syrian name and then again in Latin.
"Canon" translates to "regula" in Latin. So, those who live a religious and communal life in monasteries according to the rules set by the holy apostles are known as regular canons.
Monks and canons, out of love for Christ, renounce worldly life and separate themselves from its chaos.
Within the cloister walls, they dedicate themselves to avoiding even the slightest blemish from idle talk, humbly submitting to the judgment and governance of their superiors.
These monks and canons, while avoiding public attention, rejecting worldly conversations, and setting aside wealth and pleasures for the love of Christ, create a sort of desert among people by dedicating themselves day and night to prayer, reading, and divine contemplation.
There, they serve God more freely with psalms, hymns, and spiritual songs, with purity and care.
However, there are some monks and canons, whom we can only mention with heavy sighs, who, despite renouncing the world and living in monasteries under the guise of religion, refuse to stay within the cloister walls.
Instead, they prefer to frequent the courts of kings and princes.
As we are about to discuss the courtly monk, I must say we feel similarly about the canon or courtly convert.
Although their attire may differ, their religious devotion should remain the same: they should be known for their good morals, not their clothing.
When a monk or canon is described as courtly, it suggests a certain frivolity.
For if a monk were not drawn to frivolity, he would not expose himself to the conversations of kings.
Those who enjoy the company of worldly people, who willingly participate in the councils of princes and become privy to their secrets, can be considered courtiers.
If you know the questionable counsels of princes and act as their intermediary, I fear you might align with them and tarnish your soul.
The order of the cloister and the order of the court are quite different.
The cloister is peaceful, while the court is full of turmoil.
In the cloister, conversations are calm and beneficial, but life in the court is chaotic and dangerous.
The residents of the cloister please God by doing good deeds, whereas those in the court provoke His anger by engaging in unlawful activities.
In the court, there's secret plotting with the wealthy to harm the innocent Psalm 9; in the cloister, you hear: "I have not sat with false counsel, nor will I enter with those who do wrong" Psalm 25.
In the court, people lie in wait to seize the poor, ensnaring them Psalm 9; in the cloister, you say: "I have hated the assembly of evildoers, and will not sit with the wicked" Psalm 25.
In the court, your right hand is filled with bribes; in the cloister, you wash your hands among the innocent. There, the goods of the poor are taken by force; here, they are willingly offered by the leaders. In the court, the sinner is praised for his desires and the wicked is blessed Psalm 9; but in the cloister, the Lord blesses the righteous Psalm 5.
If you wish to be a monk or a courtly canon, you end up praising what you shouldn't, defending what's inappropriate, doing what's not allowed, and saying what's improper. However, there are two types of secular courts: those that build churches and those that destroy them. Although religious men are necessary in both, the involvement of courtly monks is useless and dangerous.
This is the court of David and that of Absalom. In both, the counsel of Hushai is necessary. I read that Ahithophel was once an advisor to David but left him to join Absalom Second Samuel 15. We have a place to discuss the example more thoroughly. There are indeed two courts, David's and Absalom's. In both, Hushai's counsel prevailed, not Ahithophel's. Hushai means silence; Ahithophel means the downfall of the brother Second Samuel 17.
A deceitful man will not be established in the land: calamity will overtake the unjust man in his destruction Psalm 139. But if you love to see good days, keep your tongue from evil and your lips from speaking deceit Psalm 34.
This is Hushai's counsel, not Ahithophel's.
The tongue is in slippery places, leading to the downfall of brothers.
Yet, in silence, peace is nurtured, preserving David so he does not die.
As written, Hushai was a friend of David in Second Samuel 15.
But how did he show his love?
"I became mute, humbled, and kept silent even from good things" as it says in Psalm 39. The righteous love the fruit of silence so much that they remain quiet even about good things. Hushai loves counsel so much that he guards his words, speaking only with permission. David sings a psalm for Hushai's words in Psalm 7.
The words of Hushai are words of silence; words of silence are words of mystery. There are three types of silence: the silence of the mouth, the tranquility of the mind, and the veil of mystery. The first silence is discreet, the second is secret, and the third reveals a mystery. Know the history, recognize the mystery, assign the moral.
Absalom pursued David, Judas pursued Christ, and the desires of the flesh pursued the spirit. Absalom burned with a desire for power. This is the root of all evil, greed, as mentioned in First Timothy 6, the source from which all vices stem. This is the hair that Absalom nurtured, weighing him down. He cut it only once a year, and then publicly weighed it at 200 shekels, as noted in Second Samuel 14.
Absalom means "father's peace," yet he is also like Judas, the betrayer. Listen to the father's peace: "The one who dips his hand with me in the dish, he will betray me" in Matthew 26. Listen to the son's peace: "The one I kiss is the man; arrest him" in Matthew 26. He promises peace with a kiss and betrays. He nurtured his hair. But how? He was a thief and held the money bag, as explained in John 12. Once a year, he cut it when he returned the thirty pieces of silver, throwing them into the temple. He weighed his hair at 200 shekels, the number of the unclean, because, led by repentance, he said, "I have sinned by betraying innocent blood" in Matthew 27.
If he understood the injustice of the weight, meaning the price of blood, he would not run to the noose, but humbly hasten to the cross of the Lord.
However, he measured with a public scale, not the sacred one: he placed a talent of lead where the devil sits, rather than a lighter weight of mercy where the Lord places his hand.
He chose the weight of despair over mercy because he possessed the former but lacked the latter.
Perhaps, in his reluctance to show mercy, he doubted he could seek mercy's pardon.
Listen to the sacred weight: I have sinned; I made my sin known to you, and I did not hide my injustice.
I said: I will confess my injustice to the Lord, and you forgave the wickedness of my sin.
Psalm Thirty-Two.
O just weight, full of mercy!
He reveals his sin, confesses his wrongdoing; and the more he uncovers his sin, the more God covers it.
Listen to the public weight of Cain; he said: My iniquity is greater than I can bear to deserve pardon.
Genesis Chapter Four.
He judged his wickedness heavier than God's mercy.
The desire of the flesh nurtures the hair, as it generates an abundance of thoughts.
This hair burdens the mind, while earthly dwelling overwhelms the senses with numerous thoughts.
Wisdom Chapter Fourteen.
When cut once a year, his hair weighs two hundred shekels, signifying the renouncement of desires once in a lifetime, ultimately denying bodily desires.
He is stripped of his possessions only when he is separated from earthly things by the finality of death.
He values earth more than heaven, preferring a clay house to one not made by hands, which is in heaven; choosing the temporary over the eternal.
This is measured with a public scale, not the sacred one, prioritizing earthly desires over the love of God.
Listen to the sacred weight, namely the weight of Paul: I desire, he says, to depart and be with Christ.
Philippians Chapter One.
Listen to the public weight: Woe to the inhabitants of the earth.
Revelation Chapter Eight; not to those who dwell in body, but to those who love with their hearts; not to those who physically live on earth, but in thought and longing converse in heaven; rather, to those intoxicated by earthly delights.
Let monks or canons embrace the advice of Hushai, which is the silence of the cloister.
They should turn away from the counsel of Ahithophel, steering clear of rulers' affairs and not seeking involvement in worldly matters.
They should adhere to the rules of the order, through which they can receive the gift of divine grace, and avoid courtly rumors and excessive speech.
Monks should prefer the company of humble brothers in the monastery over the company of proud soldiers in the king's palace.
They should find more joy in hearing God's praises with their brothers in the church than in idle chatter in the king's court.
It's more appropriate for a canon or a courtly monk to participate in divine services in God's house than to engage in secular affairs in the king's residence.
Canons and courtly monks, who disregard monasteries and unnecessarily mingle with secular crowds, frequenting rulers' courts and city streets, are mourned by the prophet Jeremiah, who says:
"How the gold has become dim, the finest color has changed, the stones of the sanctuary are scattered at the head of every street" (Lamentations Lamentations 4:1).
By gold, we understand religious men who are separated from worldly noise and engaged in God's service, illuminating the world through the wisdom and holiness granted to them by God.
The Lord says in the Gospel: "You are the light of the world" (Matthew 5:14).
Even of their wisdom, symbolized by gold, it is written in Solomon: "A desirable treasure rests in the mouth of the wise" (Proverbs 21:20).
Therefore, they must be wise and holy, so that through preaching, they may dispel darkness from others' hearts and guide them toward heaven by setting an example of good deeds.
Ecclesiastical men are rightly compared to gold; just as gold is more splendid than all metals, the order of clerics, with wisdom and discretion, shines as a light to all laypeople.
Thus, a wise man once said: "As far as heaven is from earth, so is the discretion of clerics from the discretion of laypeople."
The church's order should radiate holiness for all believers and be illuminated by the preaching of the Gospel.
This is why it is said:
"Let your light shine before others, that they may see your good deeds and glorify your Father in heaven."
(Matthew, Chapter Five).
If church leaders are the light of the world, as the Lord says, then why did Jeremiah previously state:
"How the gold has grown dim, the finest gold has changed"?
Undoubtedly, the prophet spoke truthfully about us and our times; because what he spiritually foresaw, we now see has come to pass.
Truly, today this prophecy is fulfilled in us when our lives are shown to be disgraceful through our actions.
The finest color of gold represents the habit of a religious life. Today, the gold has grown dim when religious men, who should be examples of good deeds, become examples of wickedness. The finest color of gold changes whenever the appearance of holiness is reduced to disgrace and scorn.
Indeed, the finest color of gold, which is the habit of religion, changes when a wolf hides in sheep's clothing. Then, the finest color of gold, which is the appearance of religious men, turns to contempt among onlookers when perverse actions are hidden within and not unnoticed by the public outside.
Brothers, dearest ones, do the people despise us without reason? By no means. We are rightly despised because we are one thing inside and another outside. We conceal one thing inwardly and show another outwardly. Inside, pride and empty glory are hidden, while externally humility is feigned. Inside lies the venom of hatred and discord, while outside appears the habit of holiness and innocence. Inside we hide the will to possess wealth, while outside we pretend voluntary poverty.
It follows:
"The precious stones of the sanctuary are scattered at the head of every street."
The precious stones of the sanctuary are religious men founded on the foundation of the Church.
The stones of the sanctuary are scattered at the head of every street when church leaders stray, chasing after vain and trivial pursuits.
Indeed, they are scattered everywhere-found in the market, in the city square, and even in the king's court.
These stones, representing the church leaders, are dispersed when those who should remain within, immersed in pure prayer and divine contemplation, venture out to satisfy their worldly desires.
Notice how, at the head of every street, they have become leaders of error instead of being mirrors of truth and examples of perfection.
Therefore, dear brothers, since by God's grace you have rejected the world and chosen the monastic life, I urge you not to frequent the king's court unless absolutely necessary.
For the love of God, stay within the cloister walls, read the Holy Scriptures diligently, dedicate yourselves to continuous prayer, observe silence at the appropriate times, devote yourselves to meditation and divine contemplation, and strive with all your might to experience the sweetness and grace of the Lord.
May vegetables in the refectory be sweeter to you than the lavish dishes in the king's court.
Let it be more delightful to study books of various subjects in the cloister than to admire the king's dogs and soldiers with falcons at the palace.
Cherish the companionship of your brothers in the house of the Lord more than the greetings of princes among the people.
Yet, if you truly wish to be courtiers, aim with all your heart for the court of the supreme King.
If you find joy in seeing soldiers of great nobility, strive to reach the palace of the eternal Emperor through good deeds, where the entire heavenly army serves the Emperor endlessly.
So, dear ones, free your hands from all burdens, shield your ears with the thorns of the fear of God, guard your mouth, and with all effort, cleanse the eyes of your heart from anger, envy, hatred, and all ill will.
This is so that after this life, you may reach the heavenly homeland and see the King of all saints reigning in His glory.
May He, in His gracious goodness, grant this.
He who lives and reigns as God in the perfect Trinity for all ages.
Amen.
Chapter Ten: That Monks or Canons Should Not Desire to Know the Secrets of Princes
I advise you, dearest brothers, to listen carefully to the words of our Lord Jesus Christ.
For He says: Whoever serves me must follow me; and where I am, my servant will also be John Chapter Twelve.
It is both fitting and very necessary to follow Christ and serve Him, because He ensures that His followers and servants reach Him.
What could be more honorable and joyful than to follow Christ with full devotion, knowing that He rewards His servants so nobly in the presence of Himself and God the Father?
What greater glory or happiness could there be for us than to be the servants and friends of that Emperor, who reigns above all emperors and crowns His soldiers with unfading crowns?
The higher our Emperor is in power and virtue, the more we should be diligent and observant of His commandments in holiness, justice, and humility.
Let us recognize and consider with all diligence the honor with which we should accept His mission.
If a mission came to us from a king, or a seal or message, would we not, immediately setting aside other concerns, willingly and with all devotion receive the letters and strive to fulfill them upon reading?
And behold, the King of kings and Lord of lords, indeed our Redeemer, has deigned to send His letters through the prophets and apostles; not to seek any necessary service from us, but to make known to us what can benefit our salvation and glory.
And He did not want to be content with this alone, but also, what is more wonderful and merciful, He deigned to come to us Himself and show us the straight path to reach Him.
Therefore, it is fitting that we follow Him with all our minds, with the steps of good works, and serve Him with full devotion; because if we are unwilling to do this, we will be in danger before His strict judge.
But what does it mean to serve Christ?
It means to diligently pursue good works out of love for Him without deceit.
But someone might ask: How are we cheating Christ?
Listen carefully to what the blessed Isidore says: We cheat God when we praise ourselves for good deeds instead of praising Him.
Some deceive Christ by boasting to themselves about their chastity and abstinence.
Those who give alms for the sake of vanity are also committing fraud.
Anyone who is arrogant about wisdom, seeks a reward for justice, turns any gift from God into self-praise, or uses it for bad purposes, is undoubtedly cheating Christ.
Those who turn virtues into sins do not serve Christ, because they prefer temporary praise from people over eternal reward from Christ for good deeds.
Therefore, such ministers are not rewarded by Christ but condemned, because they do good not for Him, but for temporary praise.
To them, He will say in judgment: Depart from me, you workers of iniquity; I do not know where you are from, as it says in the Gospel of Luke, Chapter Thirteen.
Therefore, let the children of the Church strive to serve Christ without deceit and pretense, not for vain human glory, but for eternal happiness.
Let them avoid being honored by people for empty glory.
Let them separate themselves from worldly gatherings and devote themselves to reading and prayer in the house of God.
Yet, sadly, some, after renouncing the world, love temporal things more than eternal ones, carnal things more than spiritual ones, prefer conversations with the rich over singing psalms, and choose riding to see worldly sights over reading in the cloister.
It sometimes happens that monks or canons who frequent courts listen to cases and seek judgments so that if their own cases arise, they can turn to the court more securely.
They defend not only their own causes but also those of others.
And because they love these things, they frequent them.
They prefer council decisions over the secrets of mysteries; instead of reciting psalms, they focus on decrees.
They become advocates in legal matters and use rhetorical flair.
They seek praise for speaking to many, but a monk or canon who talks too much displeases many.
They enter into unlawful marriages and sometimes break up lawful ones.
They often claim ancestors they don't actually know and recount family lineages.
They assert that someone descended from another, judge uncertain matters, and frequently testify about things they don't know.
If they sometimes enter unlawful marriages, they claim it's for the common good.
They promise peace for the churches, the people, and the country.
If things can't be resolved this way, a monk or canon lawyer plans a trip so what couldn't be done elsewhere can be done in Rome.
For a secular prince, they willingly endure the cold of the Alps and the heat of Italy, which perhaps they wouldn't endure as much for a spiritual leader, like an abbot.
Loaded with documents and backed by authorities, they return, set a date for the case, and bring in witnesses who, if you want, are ready to swear to the truth; and if you want, they'll swear again to what isn't true.
These are the affairs of princes.
Now listen again to John the Baptist's judgment in a similar matter: "It is not lawful for you to have your brother's wife" from the Book of Mark, Chapter 6.
What should I say?
Doesn't a monk prefer being a lawyer dining with Herod rather than being held in chains and prison with John?
At that banquet, even if he doesn't see John's head, he sees what is gained by spilled blood: the widow's cow and the poor man's pig.
In the prince's prison, the poor man dies, and yet, living off the poor man's substance, the monk or canon flatters the prince.
But I too, beloved, sometimes morally dine with Herod at the banquet, watch the dancing girl, and see John's head cut off on a platter.
For Herod symbolizes glory.
All the glory of the daughters of Zion is inward, but the glory of the daughters of the world is outward.
So, I'm sitting at a feast with Herod, seeking the empty glory that comes from the pleasures of sin.
I watch the daughter of Herodias dancing, and the vanity of curiosity captivates me.
These are the two things that lead to John's downfall: the delight in sin and the allure of curiosity.
John signifies "God's grace," and God is at the heart of this grace.
The separation of the head from the body happens when someone credits their good deeds to themselves instead of God; such people don't find grace with God because they aren't truly seeking it.
The proud seek God's grace with humility among people.
As Paul says, "By the grace of God, I am what I am" from First Corinthians, Chapter 15.
Let the canon or monk lawyer listen to the apostle who says, "Do not claim what is yours" from Luke, Chapter 6; let them hear and resolve disputes.
He advises not to claim it through argument or pursue it with aggravation; yet, if something is taken from them, they don't shy away from judgment; they don't avoid the risk of perjury when someone swears for themselves or another.
The Apostle laments that we don't want to endure fraud, that we argue in courts, that we seek vengeance in anger from First Corinthians, Chapter 6, saying, "Do not defend yourselves, beloved, but leave room for wrath" from Romans, Chapter 12.
Oh sorrow! Where can true religion, the integrity of perfection, the foundation of charity be found?
Perhaps among the cloistered, who judge themselves daily, fear the judgment of the highest judge, and with deep sighs cry out: "Do not bring your servant to judgment, Lord" from Psalm 142.
For the cloistered seek God's true judgments, not secular ones.
They uphold the law of the Lord by living, meditating, and loving.
Through living, they achieve purity of conscience; through meditating, fullness of knowledge; through loving, the perfection of charity.
The law of the cloistered also has its judges, witnesses, and advisors.
In the law of the Lord, there are two witnesses: life and conscience; two judges, meditation and knowledge; two advisors, love of God and neighbor.
Conscience is a witness before God, life before humans.
Harmony in judgments arises from knowledge and reflection, ensuring that actions and words are carefully considered.
All justice from the mentioned law depends on these two prior advisors.
On these two commandments rest all the law and the prophets.
Matthew twenty-two.
If there is any perfection to be found in this world, it exists in monastic life.
However, this perfection's integrity cannot be upheld unless poverty is embraced wholeheartedly.
For those who are wealthy, setting their hearts on riches burdens them with worries and entangles them in business.
Therefore, it is dangerously misleading to be swayed by vanity after renouncing worldly life, only to become entangled again in earthly concerns.
The higher one climbs, the more dangerous the fall.
One falls from a great height who, having tasted the sweetness of contemplation, returns to worldly matters without necessity.
Like a dog returning to its vomit, is a monk or canon reverting to secular business.
Thus, the Lord says in the Gospel:
No one who puts their hand to the plow and looks back is fit for the kingdom of God.
Luke nine.
A great misfortune befalls one who should ascend but descends.
A great misfortune befalls one who should have advanced to better things through spiritual practice but daily moves towards worse things through the desire for temporal glory.
Although God protects the lives of the chosen amidst the secular, it is impossible for anyone among worldly pleasures to remain untainted by vices.
We know of some who left the cloister and were immediately ensnared by vices, departing from the Creator's love and finding the damnation of their souls.
Therefore, anyone desiring to preserve an unblemished life should remain within the cloister's walls and not venture outside unless commanded by their abbot, remembering the words of the bride, the holy soul, to the calling bridegroom, Christ: I have taken off my robe, how can I put it on again?
I have washed my feet, how can I soil them again?
Song of Solomon five.
The bride's garment, which symbolizes her holy soul, has been removed because she has let go of all the external things that once adorned her.
She has shed her garment, choosing to renounce worldly pleasures and live solely for God.
The bride has also washed her feet because, while living in sacred leisure, she diligently reflects on her past actions.
When she finds any impurities through this introspection, she mourns with daily tears and sighs.
She has washed her feet to cleanse away past missteps, those careless actions she took while navigating this world, using her tears.
By cleansing her sins with tears, she wishes to appear pure in the eyes of her beloved.
She is careful not to soil her feet again because she fears that becoming entangled in worldly matters might stain her with the dust of the earth, making her seem worthless and rejected in the eyes of Jesus Christ, her bridegroom.
For this reason, she chooses to remain in spiritual leisure, distancing herself from worldly chaos to live more securely, as if safely positioned on the shore.
Therefore, beloved, practice these teachings, meditate on them diligently, and resist the urge to reclaim the earthly possessions you once set aside out of love for Christ.
Be cautious not to soil your feet again, which means avoiding the sins of your past that you have already washed away with tears and frequent sobs.
Avoid getting involved in the affairs of powerful figures, steer clear of disputes and arguments, and refrain from engaging in judgmental debates.
Thus says the Lord: Do not resist an evil person.
From the Gospel according to Matthew, Chapter Five: If someone wants to sue you and take your tunic, let them have your cloak as well.
Therefore, beloved, as disciples of Christ, demonstrate the discipline of Christ not only through words but also through good deeds.
Do not seek to defend yourselves, but allow room for wrath.
Why?
Because vengeance is the Lord's, who will repay each according to their deeds and deliver you from those who hate you.
I advise you, beloved, to focus more on uncovering the secrets of mysteries than on the decrees of councils.
It's better to sing psalms in the choir than to get caught up in legal disputes about worldly matters.
Spending day and night in the house of God, focusing on prayer, reading, and divine contemplation, is preferable to being involved in the business and conflicts of a ruler's house.
The former lifts the mind to heavenly things, while the latter pulls it away from God.
The former refreshes the soul with heavenly nourishment, while the latter entangles it in sins and vices.
The former satisfies the soul with spiritual delights, while the latter drains it of virtues.
In the cloister, a spiritual meal, namely divine reading, is offered to refresh the minds of God's servants.
They don't grow weary from spiritual hunger amidst life's dangers but are instead uplifted to the joys of the heavenly homeland.
At the table of the Holy Scriptures, newcomers or those with less understanding find milk, gentle and sweet teaching that nurtures them to do good.
The experienced, those trained in God's service or more perfectly instructed in divine knowledge, find bread for nourishment, higher teachings that deepen their dedication to serving God.
There, God's servant learns how to withdraw from worldly pleasures and begins to taste how sweet and gentle the Lord is.
They learn to despise the present age and understand the order in which to love God and neighbor.
They discover the cunning and temptations of the ancient enemy and how to resist the desires of their own flesh.
They find the good they should pursue and the evil they should avoid, how to renounce vices and cling to virtues, forgetting what is behind and reaching forward to what lies ahead.
They learn to guard their mouth, close their ears to avoid hearing evil, and turn away their eyes from vanity.
They learn not to repay evil for evil, not to impose on anyone what they do not wish to suffer, and to do for others what they wish for themselves.
But above all, at this spiritual table, they find the way to reach the heavenly homeland.
Therefore, beloved friends, approach this spiritual table more diligently than usual.
Draw your spiritual nourishment from it according to the understanding given to you by God, so that you do not grow weary from a lack of God's word on this journey.
As humans, we do not live by bread alone, but by every word that comes from the mouth of God.
Matthew Chapter 4.
Holy Scripture adapts to the understanding of each reader, much like how manna provided different flavors to the people of old according to each person's taste.
The Lord's word aligns with each individual's capacity for understanding, or intelligence.
While it varies for each person's comprehension, it remains unified in itself.
Therefore, dearest ones, disregard the external and strive for the internal.
Reject the visible and love the invisible.
Avoid visiting the court of an earthly ruler unless absolutely necessary.
Instead, hasten to the palace of the eternal king with steps of good deeds.
To see your Redeemer reigning at the right hand of the Father, pour out tears incessantly with a deep sigh from the heart.
May He graciously grant this, who lives and reigns with the same Father and the Holy Spirit in perfect Trinity, God, forever and ever.
Amen.
Chapter Eleven: On the Acts of the Apostles
Luke, the evangelist and recorder of apostolic history, was a Syrian by birth and a doctor by profession.
He was skilled in Greek, a disciple of the apostle Paul, and his inseparable companion on his journeys.
With the help of the Holy Spirit's grace, he remained very chaste from childhood.
At the beginning of the emerging Church, he addresses Theophilus, his fellow disciple and bishop, saying:
"In my first book, I wrote about everything, O Theophilus, that Jesus began to do and teach, up until the day he was taken up to heaven, after giving instructions through the Holy Spirit to the apostles he had chosen."
It's noteworthy that he first mentioned "what Jesus began to do," and then added "to teach," because, as a perfect teacher, Jesus first did what he later taught.
He lived without fault and taught without deceit.
He committed no sin throughout his life and preached nothing that could be rightfully criticized.
He lived innocently among the Jews and taught the people who came to him truthfully.
Therefore, it's fitting that Luke first said he intended to write about what Jesus began to do and teach, because Jesus gave his disciples, whom he was about to send to teach all nations, indeed to all leaders of the Church, a model of perfection.
This is the form of ecclesiastical religion: each preacher should first strive to live well, and then to teach well, so that those whom he brings to faith with words, he may nurture with examples.
Thus, the Son of God and man lived incomparably in this world and taught the crowds who came to him beneficially, sufficiently feeding them with the bread of the heavenly word.
Until the day when, instructing the apostles he had chosen through the Holy Spirit to preach the gospel to every creature, he was taken up to heaven, from where he had descended.
He chose a few, through whom he acquired many. He chose the poor, through whom he subdued the rich and powerful; he humbled the proud, restrained the arrogant, overthrew tyrants, and subjected all those predestined for eternal life to the yoke of his faith.
He chose those who were uneducated and fearful, and through them, He taught the Holy Spirit, as foretold, to preach and strengthened them to endure the persecutions of the wicked.
Indeed, the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ were afraid, not daring to preach or even step outside the house for fear of the Jews.
How could they preach unless divine grace enlightened them, especially since they were unfamiliar with letters and the languages of the nations?
The early Church was indeed tender, timid, and unlearned among those same apostles, as Solomon had foretold long before in the Song of Songs under the guise of the bridegroom, namely Jesus Christ.
He said, "Our sister is little and has no breasts" (Song of Songs 8).
Christ calls the Church a sister, as He said of these apostles: "Go, tell my brothers to go to Galilee, there they will see me" (Matthew 28).
The Church was a little sister and had no breasts when it consisted only of the apostles, because it could not nourish itself or others with the milk of preaching.
What could Peter preach to others when he denied being a disciple of Christ by cursing and swearing at the voice of a single maidservant?
(Matthew 26).
Therefore, the Church was little and had no breasts because, after Christ's resurrection, it was enclosed in one house, fearing not only to preach but even to be seen among its persecutors.
Again, the Son of God and the Virgin adds, saying: "What shall we do for our sister on the day she is spoken for?" (Song of Songs 8).
Christ spoke to this same sister when He sent the Holy Spirit upon the apostles, teaching them all the languages of the world with manifold distribution, and strengthening them to endure adversity.
Indeed, one cannot be a perfect preacher if he fears to preach the good things he has learned, just as the unlearned cannot presume to preach what they do not know.
Therefore, the Son of God strengthened and taught His disciples, that is, His Church, to boldly preach good things and patiently endure evil.
Jacob, the patriarch, spoke prophetically when he blessed his son Zebulun:
"Zebulun will live by the seashore and be a haven for ships"
(Genesis 49).
Zebulun, meaning 'dwelling of strength,' symbolizes the Church, which is resilient in facing suffering.
It is positioned by the seashore, serving as a safe harbor for believers, offering a beacon of true faith to those in peril.
It remains steadfast against all the world's storms, witnessing the downfall of Jews and heretics,
and the chaos of surrounding events.
When waves crash against it, it withstands them without breaking.
It does not succumb to the storms of heresy nor to the winds of division.
It reaches Sidon, symbolizing its extension to the nations.
The Gospel also notes that some apostles were chosen from there, and the Lord frequently taught in those areas.
As the Psalm says:
"The leaders of Judah, their commanders; the leaders of Zebulun, the leaders of Naphtali"
(Psalm 68).
It's as if to clarify: The leaders of Judah, their commanders, refer to the leaders of faith, namely, the holy apostles, who lead the Church.
And the leaders of Zebulun represent leaders of hope; and the leaders of Naphtali symbolize charity, known as expansion,
as some were even moved to pray for their enemies.
It continues:
"Command, O God, your strength: confirm, O God, what you have worked in us"
(Psalm 68).
This suggests: Command, O God, your strength, meaning let converted believers bless you through the apostles in the churches.
It's like saying: O God the Father, command, or entrust, your strength, referring to your incarnate Word, which is your power.
As Paul says:
"Christ is the power of God and the wisdom of God"
(First Corinthians 1).
Or command your strength to bless, so that through your might, all blessings may be fulfilled.
Command your strength, which is the love you had for people, since while we were still sinners, Christ died for us.
Again, it says: Strengthen, O God, what you have worked in us, as stated in Romans Chapter Five.
Strengthen the grace you have given us; make it firm for us and the nations, starting from your temple in Jerusalem, where the word of God was first preached.
However, because the blinded Jews refused to humbly accept it, the preachers, namely the holy apostles, turned to the Gentiles.
Strengthen, O God, what you have worked in us; for if you strengthen it, the kings, that is, your apostles, will bring you gifts.
Peter will offer you converts from the circumcised, Paul from the uncircumcised, Thomas the Indians, James the Spaniards, Matthew the Ethiopians, John the Asians, Mark the Egyptians, and each will bring their own to whom they will preach.
Alternatively: The leaders of Judah are their guides; the leaders of Zebulun, the leaders of Naphtali.
Cassiodorus indicates Christ and his apostles through these tribe names.
Augustine suggests that perhaps the apostles were from these tribes, and they are the leaders of those who bless God in the churches.
But the pleasing meaning is the one gathered from the interpretation of the names, which fits the Church.
For Judah means confession, Zebulun a dwelling of strength, and Naphtali expansion, which fits the leaders of the Church.
In martyrdoms, confession comes first, for which whatever happens must be endured bravely.
Then, after the trials are over, expansion follows as a reward; and it is: There are the leaders of Judah, that is, of confession; leaders of Zebulun, that is, of strength; and leaders of Naphtali, that is, of expansion.
Or in such a way that it refers to the three virtues, which are signified by these name interpretations; because confession is in faith, strength in hope, and expansion in love.
Bless God, I tell you, those who have drunk from the springs of Israel, meaning those who have embraced the teachings of the apostles, as is fitting.
For there are the leaders of Judah, Zebulun, and Naphtali, which symbolize the leaders of faith, hope, and charity, and these are the leaders within the Churches.
Through this, each is like Benjamin, the son of the right hand; a young man who has set aside old malice and is in a state of mental ecstasy, with an uplifted mind.
There, Benjamin is a young man in a state of mental ecstasy.
Cassiodorus says that among the fountains of living water, among the apostles or in the Churches, is Benjamin, the last of the apostles.
A young man, freshly taken up, from the tribe of Benjamin.
Therefore, it is said: Benjamin is a ravenous wolf; in the morning he will devour the prey, and in the evening he will divide the spoils.
Genesis Forty-Nine.
This refers to Paul, who in the morning of his life persecuted the saints, but in the evening, after his conversion to God, divided the spoils taken from the devil through various roles.
Augustine describes being in a state of mental ecstasy, with the mind distracted from bodily senses, as when he was caught up to the third heaven, or in a state of mental awe.
Our Lord Jesus Christ, coming into this world, broke the power of the devil and chose disciples from humble backgrounds to teach his Church.
Initially, he taught the synagogue through patriarchs, prophets, and teachers of the law; but ultimately, he taught the holy apostles and their successors.
After defeating the prince of death and granting eternal peace, he taught the holy Church.
Hence, the prophet Micah introduces the Lord speaking, foretelling peace for the holy Church and the easy defeat of the devil at Christ's coming.
Therefore, let Almighty God, who is three in persons and one in deity, proclaim.
He says, we will raise up over the Assyrian seven shepherds and eight princes.
And they will feed the land of Assyria with the sword and the land of Nimrod with their spears, delivering his people from Assyria; and there will be peace on earth when he comes.
Micah Five.
Imagine God the Father saying: Along with my beloved Son, who is co-eternal with me and whom I brought forth before all ages, and the Holy Spirit, who shares the same essence as us, I will raise seven shepherds against Assyria.
These are all the patriarchs, prophets, and saints of the Old Testament, where the Sabbath was celebrated, and eight leaders, including the apostles and evangelists, and other teachers of the New Testament.
They will nourish the land, meaning they will tear apart and devastate Assyria with the sword of divine speech, sent to earth to divide and transform.
They will also devastate the land of Nimrod with spears, symbolizing the preaching of Christ, who is our peace.
He will deliver his people from Assyria, representing the devil.
Nimrod is interpreted as a tyrant or descending temptation.
He was the first to seize oppressive power among people and attempted to build a tower against God, representing the one who said: I will place my throne to the north and be like the Most High Isaiah fourteen.
Nimrod also symbolizes a descending temptation and represents the one who fell from heaven like lightning Luke ten, always roaming like a hunter among beasts.
He inspects barren trees and forests, signifying people lacking in good works.
However, the holy teachers of the Old and New Testaments-patriarchs, prophets, apostles, and evangelists sent by God-devastate the land of the devil who accuses and tempts.
Thus, God liberates his people from Assyria, representing the devil who seeks to trample the boundaries of Israel, the holy Church.
And because this wicked enemy strives to destroy the family of God, he is wounded and bound by Christ and his ministers, according to the Gospel, in his own house.
It also says: And the remnant of Jacob shall be in the midst of many peoples like dew from the Lord, like drops upon the grass, which does not wait for man and does not expect the sons of men Micah five.
What we read as having happened literally with the three young men in the Book of Daniel, the teaching of the apostles has brought about universally among all nations.
It is written, "Like dew upon the grass," and this grass does not wait for man meaning it does not depend on human help but only on God. It does not look for the sons of men, but for the Son of God from heaven.
So when we are freed from Assyria that is, from the power of the devil by God, who raised up against him seven and eight shepherds (that is, the patriarchs and prophets, apostles and evangelists), then the remnant of Jacob meaning the apostles and the early Church, which began among the Jews will be like dew among the people, putting out the fiery darts of the devil in the hearts of men.
It continues: "And the remnant of Jacob shall be among the nations, in the midst of many peoples, like a lion among the beasts of the forest, and like a lion's cub among the herds of pigs."
It is as if to say: the apostles will be strong and unshakable in suffering, like a lion's cub among pigs. Christ, the Lion and the Lion's Cub, gave this strength to the apostles that just as no one can stop a lion from snatching away animals or sheep, so also the apostles, freed from the hand of the Assyrian (meaning the devil), will snatch away and separate from the unbelievers the "beasts," that is, the simple-hearted, so that they may be saved.
These invincible soldiers of Christ namely the holy apostles and martyrs were prefigured by Gideon, the mightiest among men, who defeated the Midianites not with weapons, but with jars, torches, and trumpets (Judges 7).
Gideon, when he was preparing to fight against the Midianites and gathered a large army for battle, removed from the fight all those whom he saw kneeling down to drink water.
He remained with only 300 men those who stayed standing and scooped up water with their hands.
With these men, Gideon went to battle, equipping them not with swords, but with trumpets, jars, and torches.
As it is written, they put the lit torches inside the jars, held the trumpets in their right hands and the jars in their left, and as they approached the enemy, they blew the trumpets.
The torches appeared, and their enemies were struck with fear.
And from here, the enemies, frightened by the sound of trumpets and the flashing of lamps, turned to flee.
What does it mean that such a battle is brought forth through the prophet?
Did the prophet mean to show us that the coming of our Redeemer was symbolized by that battle led by Gideon against the devil?
Indeed, these events, which seem far from ordinary warfare, are deeply connected to the mystery of prophecy.
Who has ever gone into battle with jars and lamps?
Who, facing weapons, has chosen to leave weapons behind?
These actions might seem absurd to us, yet they were terrifying to the enemies.
This victory teaches us not to dismiss these actions as insignificant.
For Gideon going into battle signifies the coming of the Redeemer, as it is written: "Lift up your heads, O you gates, and be lifted up, you everlasting doors, and the King of glory shall come in" Psalm 24. And again: "Who is this King of glory? The Lord, strong and mighty, the Lord mighty in battle" Psalm 24. This prophecy reveals our Redeemer not only in action but also in name.
For Gideon means "one who goes around in the womb." The Lord, with His majestic power, encompasses everything, and yet through divine grace, He entered the womb of the Virgin.
What does "one who goes around in the womb" mean, if not that the almighty God, Christ, was present in the womb in His human weakness, yet remained outside the world through His divine power?
Midian means "the judgment of God." His enemies were to be repelled and destroyed, not because of the fault of the one doing the repelling, but because of the judgment of the one judging. Therefore, the Midianites are called the judgment of God because they, being outside the grace of the Redeemer, embody a just cause for condemnation even in their very name.
Against the enemies, Gideon goes to battle with 300 men. It's common to interpret the number 300 as representing complete perfection. What then is signified by the number 300, if not the perfect understanding of the Trinity?
With these, indeed, our Redeemer defeats the adversaries of faith.
He enters the battles of preaching with those who can understand divine matters, those who can fully grasp what is said about the Trinity, which is God.
It's important to note that the number three hundred is represented by the letter Tau, which has the shape of a cross.
If something were added above the transverse line, it would not just be the shape of a cross, but the cross itself.
Therefore, because this number three hundred is represented by the letter Tau, and as we've mentioned, the shape of the cross is shown through it, it's fitting that those who followed Gideon with these three hundred are marked, to whom it is said:
"If anyone wants to come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me" (Matthew 16).
Those who follow Christ truly take up the cross when they discipline themselves harshly and are moved by compassion and love for their neighbors.
Thus, through the prophet Ezekiel, it is said:
"Mark a Tau on the foreheads of those who sigh and mourn" (Ezekiel 9).
Certainly, within these three hundred, represented by the letter Tau, it is shown that the iron of the enemies is conquered by the wood of the cross.
They were led to the river to drink water, and those who drank on bended knee were excluded from the military expedition.
In water, the doctrine of wisdom is understood, and the upright actions of those standing are represented.
Those who knelt while drinking were the ones who didn't draw doctrine with right actions.
But those who drew from the streams of doctrine without bending carnally into wicked deeds, these, with Christ as their leader, go to battle against the enemies of faith.
They go with trumpets and jars because this was the order of battle.
They sounded the trumpets, placed lamps inside the jars, and when the jars were broken, the lamps revealed their bright light, terrifying the enemies and causing them to flee.
Therefore, the sound of the trumpets symbolizes the cries of preaching by the apostles, evangelists, and holy martyrs.
The lamps signify the brightness of miracles, while the jars represent the frailty of our bodies.
Our leader, Jesus Christ, led these soldiers into battle.
They disregarded the safety of their bodies and overcame their enemies by dying, not with weapons, but with patience.
Our martyrs went into battle under their leader with trumpets, jars, and lamps.
They sounded the trumpets when they preached.
They broke the jars when they exposed their bodies to suffering and destruction by the enemy's swords.
The lamps shone brightly when, after their bodies perished, they dazzled with miracles.
The enemies soon fled because when they saw the bodies of the dead martyrs shining with miracles, they were overwhelmed by the light of truth, which they had attacked.
The trumpets were sounded so that the jars would break.
The jars were broken so that the lamps would appear.
The lamps appeared to turn the enemies to flight, meaning the martyrs preached until their bodies dissolved in death.
Their bodies dissolved in death so they could dazzle with miracles, striking down their enemies with divine light.
It's important to note that the enemies stood firm before the jars but fled before the lamps because, indeed, the persecutors of the holy faith resisted the preachers while they were alive.
But after their bodies perished and miracles appeared, they fled, ceasing their persecution of the faithful, shattered by fear.
It's also worth noting what's written: they held the trumpets in their right hand and the jars in their left.
This shows that the martyrs of Christ valued the grace of preaching greatly and the usefulness of the body very little.
Whoever prioritizes the body's usefulness over the grace of preaching holds the trumpet in the left hand and the jar in the right.
If the grace of preaching comes first and the body's usefulness second, it's certain that the trumpets are held in the right hand and the jars in the left.
As we mentioned before, the soldiers of Christ, like the apostles and martyrs, overcame the Church's persecutors not by inflicting harm, but by patiently enduring hardships and performing miracles.
Divine grace led them to be expelled from Judea, prompting them to spread to other nations.
This is similar to what the blessed Job reflects on when contemplating the great and indescribable works of God, saying:
"He moves mountains without their knowing it." (Job 9:5)
Gregory points out that in sacred Scripture, the term mountains symbolizes the greatness of preachers.
As the Psalmist says:
"The mountains will bring peace to the people, and the hills righteousness." (Psalm 72:3)
Indeed, the chosen preachers of the eternal homeland are fittingly called mountains because of their lofty way of life.
They rise above the mundane concerns of the earth and draw closer to heaven.
God moved these mountains, or preachers, taking them away from the stubbornness of Judea.
Therefore, the Psalmist rightly says:
"The mountains are moved into the heart of the sea." (Psalm 46:2)
The mountains were indeed moved into the heart of the sea when the apostles, pushed away by the faithlessness of Judea, turned to the Gentiles.
They themselves declare in their Acts:
"It was necessary that the word of God should be spoken to you first; but since you reject it and judge yourselves unworthy of everlasting life, behold, we turn to the Gentiles." (Acts 13:46)
However, those who were cast down in the Lord's wrath did not comprehend this movement of the mountains.
When the Hebrews expelled the apostles, they mistakenly believed they benefited by losing the light of preaching.
Blinded by rightful judgment, they saw the loss of this light as a cause for celebration.
But after the apostles were rejected, Judea was soon destroyed by the Roman leader Titus and its people scattered among all nations.
Thus, with the mountains moved, it's fittingly added:
"He shakes the earth out of its place, and its pillars tremble." (Job 9:6)
The earth truly felt the impact when the people of Israel were torn from the borders of Judea and submitted to nations, refusing to submit to their Creator.
This land, once strong with its foundation of priests, leaders, teachers, and Pharisees, rose up in defiance and then fell.
They held the structure of the letters, and during times of peace, they carried the burdens of sacrifices like a building on top.
But when the mountains moved, the foundations shook because when the apostles left Judea, those who expelled the preachers of life couldn't remain there.
It was only fitting that they lost their earthly homeland since they, in their love, didn't fear attacking the soldiers of the heavenly homeland.
With the holy teachers gone, Judea withered, and by the just judgment of the ultimate judge, their minds were closed to the light, trapped in darkness and error.
Thus, it is further stated:
"He commands the sun, and it does not rise; He seals off the stars" (Job 9).
In sacred speech, the preachers are sometimes symbolized by the sun, as John says: "The sun became as black as sackcloth of hair" (Revelation 6).
At the end of times, the sun appears as black as sackcloth because the once bright life of the preachers is seen as harsh and despised by the wicked.
They are also represented by the brightness of the stars because, as they preach righteousness, they illuminate the darkness of our night.
Thus, when the preachers are removed, the prophet says: "The stars of the showers were withheld" (Jeremiah 3).
Literally, the stars of the showers are Orion, Arcturus, and the Hyades, which generate rain.
Because the sun shines during the day and the stars illuminate the night, in sacred speech, the day often symbolizes the eternal homeland, while the night signifies the present life.
Therefore, the holy preachers are like the sun to our eyes when they open up the contemplation of true light for us.
They shine like stars in the darkness when, through active life, they manage earthly matters for our needs.
They shine brightly like the sun during the day when they elevate our minds to contemplate the homeland of inner brightness.
They sparkle like stars at night because even when dealing with earthly matters, they guide our work with the example of their righteousness.
However, when the preachers were driven out, there was no one to show either the brightness of contemplation or the light of active life to the Jewish people, who remained in the night of their disbelief.
The truth, which left them due to this rejection, rightfully blinded them to their wickedness by removing the light of preaching.
Thus, it is rightly said: "He commands the sun not to rise, and seals up the stars." Indeed, He did not allow the sun to rise for those from whom He turned away the minds of the preachers. And He sealed up the stars as if under a signet; because by keeping His preachers silent, He hid the heavenly light from the blind senses of the wicked.
It's worth considering that we seal something up so it can be revealed when the time is right. From sacred testimony, we learn that Judea, now abandoned, will be gathered back to the embrace of faith in the end. Thus, it is said through Isaiah: "Though the number of the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, only a remnant shall be saved" (Isaiah 10).
And Paul says: "Until the fullness of the Gentiles has come in, and so all Israel will be saved" (Romans 9).
Therefore, He who now takes the preachers away from Judea's eyes will later reveal them again, as if sealing up the stars, so that even though hidden at first, with the shining rays of spiritual stars, they will not see the night of their disbelief now when rejected, but will understand when enlightened later.
This is why two eminent preachers were taken away with their deaths delayed, so they may be called back for preaching at the end: they are the two olive trees and the two lampstands standing before the Lord of the earth (Revelation).
In Matthew seventeen, it is promised that Elijah will come and restore everything.
It's as if they are hidden under the sign of the star: hidden now, but later they will appear to bring benefit.
However, the people of Israel, who will be abundantly gathered at the end, are initially hardened against the beginnings of the holy Church; they reject the preachers of truth and scorn words of help.
This happens by the wondrous plan of the Creator so that the glory of the preachers, which could have remained hidden within one people, spreads among all nations when rejected.
Therefore, the teaching of the Gospel went out to all nations through the apostles; like good seed, it filled the whole world:
As the prophet Micah predicted long ago: From Zion, he says, the law will go out, and the word of the Lord from Jerusalem.
Zion is interpreted as "watchtower."
The holy Church is called Zion because by contemplating heavenly things, doing good, and avoiding adversities, it constantly watches for the entrance to the heavenly kingdom.
Thus, let this holy prophet say: From Zion, that is, from the early Church where the teacher and high priest is the Son of God and the Virgin, a spiritual law will go out through the apostles to the nations:
And the word of the Lord from Jerusalem, meaning the word of preaching throughout the world.
Hence, it is said: Their sound has gone out into all the earth, and their words to the ends of the world.
It continues: And they will beat their swords into plowshares, and their spears into pruning hooks.
Allegorically, through faith in Christ, unrestrained anger and insults are set aside so that each person may put their hand to the plow, as the apostles advise, not looking back, so that with the weapons of persecution and insults broken, Christ may harvest spiritual grain through angels.
No one intends to overthrow listeners or prohibit preachers, namely apostles, because it is a time for planting.
It further adds, saying: Nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war anymore.
A man will sit under the vine to press the wine of spiritual understanding that gladdens the heart, and under the fig tree to gather the rich fruits of the Holy Spirit.
Before the birth of Christ, the world was engulfed in bloodshed, with Rome itself torn apart by civil wars.
However, after Rome embraced a unique empire under Christ's command, the world became a pathway for the apostles, with city gates opening to them.
An extraordinary empire was established for preaching about the one God.
Almighty God, through His beloved Son, sent apostles throughout the world, mercifully calling all nations to His knowledge and love, as foretold by the prophet Zechariah.
He said, "I will whistle for them and gather them, for I have redeemed them, and I will multiply them as they once were multiplied.
I will sow them among the peoples, and they will remember Me from afar; they will live with their children and return.
I will bring them back from the land of Egypt, and I will gather them from Assyria and bring them to the land of Gilead and Lebanon, and there will not be found a place for them."
Zechariah chapter ten.
Allegorically, for those captive in sins, the Lord signifies through His mercy that they will be gathered to Him, like to Redemption, saying, "Take my yoke upon you," etc. (Matthew chapter eleven).
He multiplies these saints, namely the apostles, not with physical but spiritual blessings.
They are sown among the peoples, to whom it is said, "Go, therefore, and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit." (Matthew chapter twenty-eight).
Through these disciples of Christ, sown among all nations, the people distanced by idolatry will remember the Lord, and all families of the nations will worship in His presence.
They will live with their children, whom they have won for the Lord through preaching, and they will return, so that those once dead in unbelief may live spiritually.
These are the children to whom Paul fed milk.
I will bring them back from the land of Egypt and Assyria; from the realm of King Pharaoh, who proclaimed, "The rivers are mine, and I made them."
Ezekiel chapter twenty-nine.
And from the land ruled by the Assyrian king, the great intellect, symbolizing the proud devil who claims greatness, and is known for arguing and convincing; such individuals are guided to the land of Gilead, transitioning from earthly matters to spiritual ones.
Gilead indeed signifies testimony of migration.
The faithful are also led by the apostles to Lebanon, meaning purification, so that, drawn out of this world's darkness, they are cleansed; and then, no place will confine them, for they will not be limited by the earth's narrowness but will enjoy the vastness of heaven.
Through these apostles, God poured into the hearts of the faithful the sweetness of His kindness, as the prophet Joel, exulting and speaking figuratively, foretold.
He said, "On that day: the mountains will drip sweetness, and the hills will flow with milk; and through all the streams of Judah will go waters."
Joel chapter three.
After the Lord's resurrection and ascension to the heavens, the mountains, representing the apostles, and subsequently the high-minded teachers of the Church, will be filled with the sweetness and delight of wisdom and divine speech; and spiritual graces will flow from them.
And the hills, those without such fullness of understanding, will produce milk, nourishing the infancy of the Church.
And through all the streams of Judah, over the believing children of the Church, waters, namely the preachings of the apostles and evangelists, and the gifts of grace, will abound, ensuring nothing remains dry.
It continues: "And a fountain will go out from the house of the Lord and will water the valley of the acacias."
From the house of the Lord, meaning the early Church, will emerge the fountain of baptism and spiritual teaching, which nourishes the hearts of the Gentiles, previously pierced by the thorns of vices and evil thoughts, so that flowers of virtues may bloom where once the pricks of vices existed.
This spring emerged from the house of the Lord when He instructed His disciples:
Go, teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
At that moment, the mountains and hills overflowed with sweetness, representing the honey of wisdom and spiritual understanding, and the hills with milk, symbolizing the teachings that nurture the little ones of the Church in the knowledge of God.
The holy apostles and their successors, through their words, examples, and the true writings of the Gospels and Epistles, nourished the entire Church.
This is akin to what the prophet Zechariah foresaw in spirit about Christ's resurrection and ascension, when he joyfully proclaimed:
On that day, living waters will flow out from Jerusalem: half toward the western sea and half toward the eastern sea, in both summer and winter.
As if he were describing the first coming of Christ and His Church more clearly: On that day, known only to God, living waters will flow out from Jerusalem.
The waters are called living because they grant life through Christ's grace.
It is as though there is one continuous day and time from Christ's first coming to His second.
Half of them flow to the western sea, which is called dead because it kills living things, or because nothing can live in its waters.
The other half flows to the eastern sea, known as the great sea.
The two seas are allegorically understood as the two Testaments, which, unless sweetened by the river of spiritual understanding, are bitter with the letter that kills and the spirit that does not give life.
In summer and winter, meaning the waters from Jerusalem, or the Church, will neither dry up from heat nor freeze in winter.
The waters flowing from Jerusalem, representing the Church, are the teachings of the Savior, namely baptism; one part reaches the western sea, symbolizing the people of circumcision, chosen through the apostles;
and the other part flows to the eastern sea, representing those from the east and west who will join Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven.
These waters will not cease in times of prosperity nor in times of persecution.
It follows: And the Lord will be king over the whole earth.
This means that when such waters have reached both seas and turned the bitter waters sweet,
the Lord, specifically Christ, will reign over the entire earth.
Then, that most powerful king will be acknowledged, as it is said: O Lord, our Lord,
how wonderful is your name throughout the earth!
(Psalm 8).
Furthermore, it adds: On that day, the Lord will be one, and his name will be one, and the
whole earth will be restored, reaching as far as the desert, from the hill Adremon to the south,
and Jerusalem will be elevated and will occupy its place, meaning it will be rebuilt in its
original location, specifically from the gate of Benjamin to the site of the former gate, and
up to the gate of the corners; and from the tower of Hananael up to the king's winepresses.
And they will live there, and no curse will remain.
When the Lord Jesus Christ is king over the entire earth, there will be one Lord, about
whom it is written: Know that the Lord himself is God; he made us, and not we ourselves.
(Psalm 79).
And there will be one name of the Lord, with the false religion of idols crushed.
Then the whole earth will be restored, where the Jews have lived, reaching the desert, which
signifies the people of the nations; who were once deserted because they lacked the knowledge
of the law, and from the hill to Adremon, meaning to the high place, because from the land and
desert to the hills, and from the hills to the mountains we will ascend; and from there to the
south full of light, and thus ascending, the Church will be elevated and will reside in the
place about which it is written: In a place of pasture, he placed me there.
(Psalm 23).
And from the gate of Benjamin, starting from the strength symbolized by the right hand, it
will reach the former gate, allowing entrance to others through it.
Next is the gate of the corners, where the cornerstone is, namely Christ, who unites two
walls into one.
Following that is the tower of Hananael, which is considered most pleasing to God.
Regarding this tower, David says to God: You are my hope; a tower of strength against the
enemy.
(Psalm 60).
For those seeking God amidst life's challenges, nothing is more comforting than this tower.
From here, one can reach the king's winepresses and drink the wine that brings joy to the heart, having been welcomed into God's wine cellar, where the wine of the Gospel's teachings is found.
Those who become filled with this wine will inhabit the heavenly Jerusalem, where there is no curse, meaning no separation from God, but a place of secure rest for those who trust in Him.
As mentioned earlier, living waters flowed out of Jerusalem because the holy apostles spread the teachings of the Gospel throughout the world.
These apostles of Christ were symbolized by the patriarch Jacob when he blessed his son Naphtali, calling him a dispatched deer.
Naphtali, meaning "expansion," represents the apostles and other preachers whose teachings reached across the globe.
From this tribe came the apostles, who are leaders of the Churches. Also, what is read in the Psalms about the leaders of Zebulun and Naphtali undoubtedly refers to the apostles (Psalm 68).
They are the sons of those who were sent, meaning the prophets, who, in the hand of Almighty God, like arrows shot forth, reached the ends of the earth.
Thus, it is fitting that Naphtali is described as a dispatched deer because the apostles and other preachers, like swift deer, rise above worldly entanglements.
In doing so, they contemplate lofty and sublime words, preaching the grace of God the Savior to all nations.
God expanded the reach of the holy apostles throughout the world, revealing His name to all nations, as the blessed Job predicted while speaking about the omnipotence of God.
He said, "He alone stretches out the heavens and treads on the waves of the sea" (Job 9).
Gregory: What else is symbolized by the heavens, if not the heavenly path of the holy apostles and the other preachers?
The psalmist speaks of them, saying:
"The heavens declare the glory of God, and the firmament proclaims the work of His hands."
Psalm Nineteen.
These heavens are referred to as the sun.
The heavens protect through intercession, while the sun reveals the power of light through preaching.
The heavens extend as, when Judea raged with persecution, the Lord expanded the apostles' reach to the knowledge of all nations.
Judea, by a just judgment, was scattered across the world as captives, while these apostles, by grace, are honored everywhere.
The heavens were once narrow when one nation held so many distinguished preachers.
Who among the Gentiles would have known Peter if he had only preached to Israel?
Who would have recognized Paul's virtues if Judea hadn't sent him to us through persecution?
Now, those who were rejected with scourges and insults by Israel are honored throughout the world.
The Lord alone extends the heavens, allowing His preachers to be oppressed in one nation and causing them to spread to the corners of the world through His secret counsel.
Even this very Gentile world, devoted to the present, accepted the words of life when the apostles' tongues reproved its faults.
It immediately swelled with the arrogance of contradiction and stirred itself to cruelty in persecution.
But the world's bitterness, which seeks to oppose preaching, is quickly tempered by the admiration of signs.
Hence, it is fitting to add in praise of the author: "And He walks on the waves of the sea."
What does the sea represent but the bitterness of this world raging to destroy the good?
The psalmist says: "He gathers the waters of the sea like a bottle."
Psalm Thirty-Three.
The Lord gathers the waters of the sea as if in a bottle, arranging all things with marvelous moderation, restraining the threats of the carnal, locked in their hearts.
The Lord walks on the waves of the sea because when storms of persecution rise, they are broken by the astonishment of His miracles.
He who calms the swells of human madness treads the wave as though standing on a mound.
When the pagans saw their customs being destroyed by new ways of living, the wealthy noticed the actions of the poor challenging their pride, and the wise of the age viewed the words of the uneducated as opposition, they quickly reacted with a storm of persecution.
However, those who are troubled by words and leap into persecution are held back by the marvel of signs.
The Lord walked on as many waves as the proud persecutors to whom He showed miracles.
Thus, it's fittingly said by the Psalmist: "The roaring of the seas is wondrous; the Lord is wondrous on high" (Psalm Ninety-three).
When the world rose dramatically against the chosen ones with waves of persecution, the Creator of the heavens subdued it even more wonderfully through the powerful preaching of His followers.
He showed that His ministers could perform miracles, which enraged earthly powers.
This is vividly narrated by the Lord through Jeremiah, revealing the exterior and denouncing the interior: "I have placed the sand as a boundary for the sea, an everlasting decree, which it cannot pass; though its waves toss, they cannot prevail; though they roar, they cannot cross it" (Jeremiah Five).
Indeed, the Lord set sand as a boundary for the sea because He chose the lowly and poor to break the glory of the world, whose waves swell when the powers of the age and the turmoil of persecution arise.
But they cannot pass the sand because they are stopped by the miracles and humility of the despised apostles and martyrs.
While the sea rages and rises through its madness, and is subdued by the display of inner strength, the holy Church progresses and ascends to its rightful order as time goes on.
Indeed, the apostles of Jesus Christ and the holy martyrs, through preaching the Gospel and shedding their own blood, have called the world back to the worship of God.
Like farmers, they continue to yield the sweetest fruit to God from the cultivated earth to this day.
The prophet Amos, inspired by the Holy Spirit, joyfully proclaimed:
"Look, the days are coming," says the Lord, "when the plowman will overtake the reaper, and the treader of grapes the one sowing seed. The mountains will drip with sweetness, and all the hills shall be cultivated."
(Amos chapter nine).
These words illustrate the order of preachers, namely the apostles and church leaders.
Allegorically, it suggests that after the resurrection and ascension of the Lord, the plowman-representing the order of teachers, specifically the apostles and other educators-will cultivate hearts with faith and love, bringing forth the fruit of good deeds by removing disbelief's hardness.
These plowmen, the holy apostles, will surpass the reapers, those who, through preaching God's word, draw people away from worldly concerns to bring them into the holy Church.
The grape treader symbolizes the apostles and holy martyrs, who, by conquering death and the devil, suffer for Christ's name, shedding their blood to set examples of virtue for others.
God sends all these into the Church to sow the seed of His word in the hearts of the chosen, to separate them from worldly distractions, and to lay down their lives for the flocks they are entrusted with.
One follows another because each succeeds the other.
As mentioned, the Son of God and the Virgin foretold His resurrection through the prophets and revealed it through the apostles.
Thus, through the prophet Zephaniah, He speaks to His Church, saying:
"Wait for me on the day of my resurrection in the future, for my judgment is to gather the nations, namely to faith, and to collect kingdoms, specifically the leaders of perverse doctrines, who will be consumed by divine fire; and I will pour out my indignation on them, all my fierce anger."
(Zephaniah chapter three).
Imagine the Son of God and the Virgin speaking directly to His holy Church, His bride, more openly:
"Wait for me by rejecting idols, and on the future day of resurrection, when I rise from the death I will suffer for your redemption, I will renew you to eternal life through baptism.
I will enlighten the eyes of your heart with the Holy Spirit so you can know me.
I will strengthen you with the bread of the heavenly word and intoxicate you with the wine of the Gospel's preaching.
So, bride, wait for me, so you may rightly say with the Prophet: 'My heart is ready, God, my heart is ready: I will sing and give praise in my glory'
(Psalm Fifty-Seven).
These words can be understood allegorically about the first coming, when the demon was defeated, all errors were removed, earthly works were destroyed, and the apostles spoke in all languages.
It was also when God seemed to rise in us after vices and sins, and everyone was gathered to faith, kindled by the fear of God's wrath and divine fire, which consumed all earthly works within them.
Again, the Lord speaks, saying: 'For in the fire of my zeal, the whole earth will be consumed.
For then I will give the peoples purified lips, so they may all call upon the name of the Lord and serve Him with one shoulder'
(Zephaniah Three).
It is said that one language will be restored to all, so each person, abandoning their error, may return to the ancient speech of God's confession.
With one mouth, they will call upon God, confessing that the Lord Jesus Christ is in the glory of God the Father, in whose name every knee should bow, in heaven, on earth, and under the earth
(Philippians Two).
This can also be said about the second coming when, after the vices of the present age, with the Church awaiting the coming of the bridegroom, the nations will be gathered for judgment, and kings will be collected in the place of punishment.
Then God's wrath will be poured out, punishing all evil, where the mighty will endure mighty torments, and those who sinned less will quickly deserve pardon.
"
"In the fire of my zeal," he says, "the earth will be devoured."
When the nations are gathered for judgment, and kings face punishment, everything earthly will be consumed worldwide.
All things related to the works of the flesh will also be consumed, so that, when all are saved and the thorns and briars are burned away, each may return to the ancient word of confessing and praising God forever.
With united effort, they will serve him diligently in his temple.
It is fitting that thanks and praises be given to him, not only in this life but also in the life to come, by both angels and humans.
Even though unworthy-that is, the entire Church-he mercifully continues to call us to himself through prophets and apostles.
He shows the sweetness of his love and kindness through the prophet Hosea, speaking to his Church, saying:
Hosea Chapter 2, "I will betroth you to me forever; I will betroth you to me in righteousness and justice, and in mercy and compassion."
Circumcision given to Abraham was a sign between God and his descendants.
It continues, "And I will betroth you to me in faithfulness, and you will know that I am the Lord."
Note the mercy of God.
A prostitute, long engaged in fornication, returns to her husband and is not merely reconciled, but betrothed.
Note the difference between the marriages of God and humans; humans corrupt virgins, while God, joined to prostitutes, makes them virgins again.
Again he says, "And it will be on that day: I will answer," says the Lord, "I will answer the heavens, and they will answer the earth. And the earth will answer the grain, the wine, and the oil."
It's as if to say: On that day, specifically when I pledge myself to you in faith, I will hear the heavens, meaning the apostles, and they will hear the earth, from which truth has risen.
In this earth, Christ, the head of the household, sows good seed, which will be watered by the heavenly word like rain.
The earth will listen to the wheat, the wine, and the oil; this particularly refers to the apostles, who, starting their preaching from Jerusalem and performing miracles, make the hearts of those who hear them bear fruit everywhere.
They are the seed when they receive from the Lord, and they are the sowers when their message spreads across the earth.
It continues: And I will betroth you to me forever, he says.
First, God the Father betrothed her to himself in Abraham, or when he led her out of Egypt, intending for her to be his eternal wife.
Second, on Mount Sinai, he gave her the justice and judgment of the law as a dowry, combined with the mercy of the law, so that if she sins, she is captured, but if she repents, she is brought back.
Third, he betrothed her at the coming of his Son, which is in the faith of the Holy Trinity, where those who believe immediately recognize him as the one they once denied.
This woman, who was first joined in the everlasting embrace of a husband because she worshiped idols in Egypt, is again taken through the law.
Because she transgressed, after the prophets, almost like the companions of a bridegroom, were killed, the Son came a third time.
When he was crucified and rose from the dead, the Church is betrothed, no longer in the justice of the law, but in the faith and grace of the Gospel, and the knowledge of the truth.
Jerome: According to the letter, it can be understood that at the coming of Christ, temporal goods are promised to believers, so that through him, who is the seed of God, everything functions in its order as established from the beginning, serving the benefit of humankind.
And yet the Jews, after so many goods, still expect the Antichrist in the flesh.
Spiritually: the heavens, which declare the glory of God, have been heard, praying for the Canaanite woman (Matthew 15), and for Peter's mother-in-law (Luke 4).
The heavens, representing the apostles, listen to the earth, which symbolizes the people who form the Church.
Though not yet perfect, they strive to keep God's commandments.
The earth, or the Church, hears the wheat, signifying that it provides spiritual understanding of the Old and New Testaments.
This understanding brings joy to the listeners, adapting the teaching to each person's ability.
Both heaven and earth, meaning the apostles and the universal Church, will hear Israel.
They will bring the seed of God's word to the fruition of works, so that one seed may yield a hundredfold, another sixtyfold, and another thirtyfold.
Matthew Chapter 13.
The seed, representing the apostles' doctrine, produced a hundredfold harvest because their preaching led many nations and some Jews to faith in Christ.
In the passion and resurrection of the Son of God and the Virgin, despite witnessing countless signs and miracles, some Jews remained obstinate, while others embraced the grace of baptism.
These were symbolized by two baskets that the Prophet Jeremiah said the Lord showed him before the temple of the Lord: Behold, two baskets full of figs stood before the temple.
One basket contained very good figs, while the other had very bad figs, which were inedible.
Jeremiah Chapter 24.
Some interpret the two baskets of good and bad figs as representing the law and the Gospel, the Synagogue and the Church, the Jewish people and Christians, hell, and the kingdom of heaven; one relating to the punishment of sinners, and the other to the dwelling of the saints.
But we, following the Apostle, acknowledge that the law is good and holy, and the commandment is good and holy, and that there is one God for both Testaments.
We refer this to the Jews who believed or did not believe at the coming of the Lord.
Romans Chapter 7.
To those who cried out to Pilate, saying: Crucify, crucify him.
Matthew.
There are twenty-seven baskets of bad figs, but those who believed are counted among the good figs in the best basket.
This basket includes Peter and Paul, John and James, Andrew and Thomas, along with the other apostles and all disciples who spread the word of life throughout the world.
The basket of bad figs includes Caiaphas, Annas, and other non-believers who condemned themselves and their descendants before they were born, saying: "His blood be on us and on our children." (Matthew 27:25).
The sweetness of good figs represents the pleasantness of the Gospels, while the bitterness of bad figs, which couldn't be eaten, indicates the deceit and disbelief of the Jews.
In the Church of Christ, the baskets of good figs were the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ, who bravely resisted His adversaries and willingly shed their blood to lead it to righteousness.
Mystically, Gedaliah, whose name means magnified by the Lord, prefigured these noble preachers of the Church, who are accomplished by the will of the Lord, so that those who fear the Lord may find refuge and comfort.
These men laid down their lives for their people and raised shields of protection against the faithless, following the example of their master, Jesus Christ.
Faithfully persisting in their duty until death, they are persecuted by the wicked, just as innocent Gedaliah was killed by the treacherous Ishmael.
God established the holy Church for the praise and glory of His name, placing the holy apostles in it for its protection and defense.
He gave it glorious martyrs as examples of virtue and provided illustrious teachers of the Old and New Testaments to adequately water it with the showers of heavenly doctrine once the time of persecution had passed.
Regarding all of these, blessed Job praises God in His works, speaking figuratively as if about the heavenly stars, saying: "He who made the Bear, Orion, and the Pleiades, and the chambers of the south." (Job 9:9).
Gregory: The words of truth certainly don't follow the empty fables of Hesiod, Aratus, and Callimachus.
It's as if naming Arcturus, the last of the seven stars, refers to the tail of the bear, and as if Orion holds a sword like a mad lover.
Indeed, these star names were invented by those devoted to worldly wisdom.
But Holy Scripture uses the same names to convey its messages, using familiar terms.
If it spoke of the stars by names unknown to us, the people for whom this Scripture was made wouldn't understand what they heard.
Thus, in sacred discourse, the wise of God borrow words from the wise of the world.
Just as, for humanity's benefit, God, the creator of all, takes on the voice of human passion.
For instance, it says: "I regret that I have made humans on the earth" from the Book of Genesis, Chapter 6.
Even though it's clear that He, who sees all things before they happen, does not regret or change His mind after doing something.
What wonder is it, then, if spiritual men use worldly words, when the ineffable Spirit and creator of all, to draw us closer to His understanding, adopts human language Himself?
Therefore, when we hear the familiar names of stars in Holy Scripture, we recognize which stars are being discussed.
And when we consider the stars being mentioned, it remains for us to rise from their movements to the mysteries of spiritual understanding.
It's not surprising in the literal sense that God made Arcturus, Orion, and Hyades, as it's certain that there's nothing in the world He didn't make.
Thus, the holy man says the Lord made these things, understanding that they signify those things which are spiritually conducted.
What, then, is expressed by the name of Arcturus, which shines with the rays of seven stars set in the axis of the sky, if not the universal Church?
Which is symbolized in John's Revelation by the seven Churches and seven lampstands, as found in Revelation Chapter 1.
These gifts, containing the sevenfold grace of the Spirit, are illuminated by the brightness of supreme virtue and shine as if from the axis of truth.
Consider that Arcturus always revolves and never sets, just as the holy Church constantly endures the persecutions of the wicked, yet persists without failure until the end of the world.
Often, those who have tried to destroy it believed they had extinguished it completely, but it returns stronger, having struggled to survive in the hands of its persecutors.
As Arcturus revolves and rises, so too does the holy Church, becoming stronger in virtue when it is tested for the truth.
Appropriately, Orion follows Arcturus; Orions rise during the winter and stir up storms with their rising, disturbing both seas and lands.
What does Orion signify after Arcturus, if not the martyrs?
As the holy Church rises to preaching, these martyrs face the troubles of their persecutors, as if arriving in winter.
When they arrive, the sea and land are disturbed, because as the strength of the saints appears, the gentiles, upset over the destruction of their customs, raise not only the angry and turbulent, but even the calm, against them.
With the Orions, winter shudders, as the constancy of the holy apostles and martyrs shines, stirring the cold minds of unbelievers to the storm of persecution.
The sky brought forth Orions when the holy Church sent forth martyrs.
These martyrs dared to speak rightly to the unlearned and endured adversity from the cold.
Moreover, the Hyades are aptly added immediately, appearing in the sky with the youthful spring and revealing themselves when the sun already exerts its heat.
They cling to the beginnings of the sign called Taurus, from which the sun begins to rise more fervently, extending the length of the day.
What, then, are the Orions, by the name of the Hyades, if not the teachers of the holy Church who emerged into worldly knowledge at a time when it shone even brighter?
With the winter of unbelief dispelled, the sun of truth burns more intensely in the hearts of the faithful.
With the storm of persecution gone, after the long nights of unbelief had passed, they rose in the holy Church when the brighter year of belief's springtime began.
It's fitting that the holy teachers are marked by the name of the Hyades.
In Greek, hyetos means rain, and the Hyades are named for the rains because, without a doubt, they bring showers when they rise.
The name of the Hyades aptly describes those who, as if descending from the heavens, shower the rain of evangelical teaching over the dry land of the human heart for the well-being of the universal Church.
If the sermon of holy preaching weren't like rain, Moses wouldn't have said: "Let my speech be awaited like the rain" (Deuteronomy, chapter thirty-two).
And the Lord, through Isaiah: "I will command the clouds not to rain upon it" (Isaiah, chapter five).
And again: "The stars or drops of the rains are prevented" (Jeremiah, chapter three), namely, Arcturus, Orion, and the Hyades, which generate rains.
Therefore, when the Hyades come with rains, the sun rises higher in the sky, because with the appearance of the teachers' knowledge, as our minds are nourished by the rain of preaching, the warmth of faith grows.
The watered earth advances to fruitfulness when the light of the ether ignites, because we produce the fruits of good work more abundantly as our hearts burn brighter with the flame of sacred instruction.
As celestial knowledge is revealed more each day through them, it's as if the springtime of our inner light opens to us, allowing a new warmth to shine in our minds, and by their words, known to us, it sparkles brighter every day.
Indeed, as the end of the world approaches, heavenly knowledge advances and grows more abundantly over time.
Hence, it is said through Daniel: "Many shall travel back and forth, and knowledge shall increase" (Daniel, chapter twelve).
In the beginning of this revelation, the angel tells John:
"Seal up the things which the seven thunders have spoken."
(Revelation 10).
However, by the end of the same revelation, he instructs:
"Do not seal the words of the prophecy of this book."
(Revelation 22).
The earlier part of the revelation is to be sealed, while the latter part is not;
because what was hidden at the beginning of the holy Church is revealed more and more each day.
Some people believe the Hyades are named after the Greek letter 'Y'.
If that's true, it aligns with the meaning we've discussed;
for these stars, named after letters, fittingly represent teachers.
Although the Hyades visually resemble that letter,
'Hyetos' certainly means rain, and these stars bring rain when they rise.
Let's listen to what the blessed Isidore, the teacher of the Spanish and our patron, says about these stars:
"The first constellation is the Bear, fixed on the axis, rotating with seven stars around it.
The name is Greek, but in Latin, it's called Ursa; because it turns like a wagon, our people call it the North.
Oxen, used for plowing, are called 'triones' because they tread the earth, like 'teriones'.
The North stars do not set because their proximity to the axis keeps them fixed."
Arctophylax is named because it follows the Bear, or Helice.
He's also called Bootes, as he is attached to the wagon; a constellation visible with many stars, including Arcturus.
Arcturus is a star behind the tail of the Great Bear, located in the sign of Bootes, hence its name, as if from 'e yoypa', because it is near Bootes' heart.
It rises in the autumn.
Orion shines before Taurus' footsteps and is named Orion from 'urine', meaning the flooding of waters.
In winter, when it rises, it stirs the sea and land with water and storms.
The Latins call it Jugulum because it's armed like a sword, and its starry light is terrifying and bright; when all its stars shine, it signals calm; if its brightness dims, a storm is on the way."
The Hyades are named from the Greek word hyein, meaning moisture and rains.
In Greek, rains are called hyetos.
When the Hyades rise, they bring about rain, which is why the Romans also called them Suculae.
As Virgil mentioned, "Arcturus and the rainy Hyades." There are seven stars on the forehead of Taurus, which rise in the springtime.
With the teachings of the blessed Isidore in mind, let's return to what we previously left behind. Saint Job, reflecting on the order of our redemption and considering the various roles of teachers, apostles, evangelists, martyrs, and confessors, marvels and exclaims: "He who stretches out the heavens alone, who makes Arcturus, Orion, and the Hyades."
Gregory states: "Indeed, with the heavens stretched out, the Lord formed Arcturus, as he guided the apostles with honor, establishing the Church in heavenly conversation. After forming Arcturus, he made Orion, because with the universal Church's faith strengthened, he brought forth martyrs against the world's storms. After bringing forth Orions, he produced the Hyades, as the martyrs grew stronger against adversities. He bestowed the teaching of masters to pour into the dryness of human hearts. These are the spiritual stars, which, while shining with the highest virtues, always shine from above. After these things, what remains except for the holy Church to receive the fruit of its labor and arrive at viewing the inner parts of the heavenly homeland? Hence, it is fitting that he said: 'Who makes Arcturus, Orion, and the Hyades;' immediately adding: 'and the inner parts of the south.'"
Here, what does the name of the south indicate except the fervor of the Holy Spirit? When anyone is filled with this, they ignite with love for the spiritual homeland. Hence, it is said in the voice of the bridegroom in the Song of Songs: "Awake, north wind, and come, south wind, blow upon my garden, and let its spices flow out" (Song of Solomon 4).
When the south wind comes, the north wind rises and retreats, as the ancient enemy is expelled with the coming of the Holy Spirit, leaving the mind it had bound in lethargy.
The bridegroom's garden is stirred by the south wind, allowing the spices to flow.
Similarly, when the Holy Spirit fills the holy Church with His gifts, it spreads the fragrance of good works far and wide.
The depths of the south wind represent the hidden orders of angels and the secret corners of the heavenly homeland, warmed by the Holy Spirit.
To this place, the souls of the saints, freed from their bodies and later restored, arrive and are hidden like stars.
Here, during the day, as if at noon, the sun's fire burns intensely.
The Creator's brightness shines more clearly, and like a ray of light, ascends to higher realms as the truth subtly illuminates us.
In this realm, the light of inner contemplation is seen without change; the warmth of the highest light remains clear, without dullness.
The invisible choirs of angels shine like stars, unseen by humans now, as they are deeply infused by the true light.
It's truly remarkable how the Lord expanded the heavens by sending the apostles, calmed the storms of persecution, established the Church by setting Arcturus, strengthened the martyrs like Orions, and provided peaceful teachers like the Hyades.
Yet, after all this, it is even more admirable that He has restored to us the embrace of the heavenly homeland, akin to the depths of the south wind.
Everything seen under divine dispensation is beautiful, but it is far more beautiful and incomparable there.
Thus, the bridegroom fittingly praises his bride: "How beautiful you are, my friend, how beautiful you are! Your eyes are doves, apart from what lies within" (Song of Solomon chapter 4).
He describes her as beautiful and repeats it, acknowledging the beauty of her character now and the beauty of her future rewards when elevated by her Creator's presence.
The members, all the chosen ones, are called his dove-like eyes because they approach everything with simplicity, shining brightly and displaying miraculous signs.
However, no matter how great the visible miracle is, the unseen miracle within is even more wondrous, which is fittingly mentioned as, apart from what lies hidden inside.
Blessed Job hints at this when he praises the innermost parts of the south.
With the Bridegroom absent, the holy Church groans amidst the troubles of the present world, as Jeremiah laments: "They have heard that I groan, and there is no one to comfort me" (Lamentations Chapter One).
It's as if the holy Church is openly saying: "My enemies have heard that I groan, with Jesus Christ the Bridegroom absent, and there is no one to comfort me, as the Holy Spirit is driven away."
Allegorically, the Church laments its own and its people's miseries, such as persecutions and martyrdoms.
The letter Sin is prefixed, sounding like teeth: this refers to the weeping of teeth, as it is read in the Song of Songs: "Your teeth are like a flock of shorn sheep" (Song of Songs Chapter Four).
These are those who no longer need the milk of infancy but eat solid bread, as it was said to Peter: "Kill and eat" (Acts Chapter Ten).
It's as if it were said: "I have set before you not only bread to eat but also reptiles."
For such people, with the sharpness of doctrine, know how to kill vices and convert reptiles, meaning people of various nations, into the body of Christ.
However, the duty of teeth varies; some divide, some grind, some form voices.
Thus, mystical teeth, some are like flocks of shorn sheep, stripped of old age, providing their offspring with the milk of doctrine and the garments of virtues; others, whiter than milk, are adorned with the beauty of office, ministering the word to listeners with utmost subtlety.
Hence the Apostle: "Solid food is for the mature, who have their senses trained" (Hebrews Chapter Five), referring to the holy apostles and the teachers of the Church.
He says: "They have heard that I groan, and there is no one to comfort me."
The enemies hear the bride, which is the holy Church, crying because she feels the bridegroom is absent.
Even though he is always present through his majesty, he allows the bride to be tested by temptations to keep her alert and cautious, so she doesn't fall for the corrupter's suggestions.
They heard, he says, that I groan, something they always wished for but never really expected.
There's no one to comfort her because the Holy Spirit does not dwell in a body subjected to sins, and my troubles grow daily, especially the temptations faced by my children and the dangers of the present age.
Again, it says: All my enemies heard of my trouble, and they were glad.
From the Book of Lamentations, Chapter One.
The Church's enemies include demons, heretics, false Christians, and pagan persecutors.
Even the Jews severely afflicted her through their leader, Christ, and in his members, meaning the apostles, martyrs, and other faithful.
While some were killed, others were driven out of their homes.
Therefore, let the bride of Christ, as if complaining about her enemies, say to her bridegroom:
All my enemies heard of my trouble, meaning demons and other persecutors heard of the apostles' persecutions, Stephen's sufferings, and the afflictions of my members.
They were glad because you allowed it to happen, by your just judgment.
Hence it is said: I am the Lord, creating peace and causing evil.
From the Book of Isaiah, Chapter Fifty-Five.
This means permitting by just judgment.
He allowed this so the Church would face hatred on earth because of its name from adversaries, to be more gloriously crowned by him in heaven.
It continues: You brought the day of consolation, and they will become like me.
From the Book of Lamentations, Chapter One.
As if the bride of Christ, meaning the holy Church, expects to be comforted by the same heavenly bridegroom and doesn't doubt that her adversaries who afflicted her will be punished by him, she speaks, saying:
You brought the day of consolation, meaning you will bring the day of judgment, and those who persecuted me will become like me, that is, captives and afflicted, just as I was.
This message is more fitting for the Church because, after the final captivity, there is no consolation left for the Jews and other persecutors of the Church.
On the day of judgment, the Lord will provide comfort to the good and punishment to the wicked.
In this present life, the soul mourns the loss of virtues, saying: They have heard that I am groaning, namely, enemies in the troubles I endure.
It says, there is no one to comfort me; the pain of an anxious soul increases because help is delayed where it is hoped for.
It also grieves deeply that invisible enemies, who once flattered, now mock.
Furthermore, conscience accuses more harshly, and sins, which once seemed sweet, are revealed as bitter; for those who seemed friends before, who ought to have sympathized, if they know of any crimes, mock like enemies.
As David says: Those who watched over my soul made plans together, saying: God has abandoned him
Psalm Seventy.
Cassiodorus: A burden is heavier when it is not shared.
They agreed, saying: God has abandoned him, pursue and seize him.
As if to say among themselves: The God whom he claims for himself has abandoned him.
Seeing him worn out by misfortunes, they think he has been abandoned by God.
So, pursue him as slow, and seize him as weak; because there is no one to rescue him once captured.
But every servant of God overcomes all the adversities of the present world with God's help.
Therefore, the soul, as mentioned before, has teeth, namely virtues and discerning thoughts, which can divide prosperous and adverse things, seek the comforting Holy Spirit, and hope for God's mercy.
Hence it adds: You have brought the day of consolation, etc.
For the faithful soul knows that after distress, pardon is given to the repentant, and punishment is returned to the mocking.
Therefore, God the Father, from the beginning through His co-eternal and consubstantial Word, has continually chosen prophets and apostles, and through them, comforted His Church and separated it from the unbelievers.
The Word, coeternal with God the Father, came to the prophet Jeremiah from the Lord, urging the apostles and teachers to preach, saying:
"Listen to the words of this covenant, and speak to the people of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem" Jeremiah chapter eleven.
It's as if He were saying more clearly: listen to the Word that was in the beginning with God, and the Word was God.
It's as if God the Father were speaking to the prophets, apostles, and other teachers of the Church, saying:
Listen to the words of this covenant, namely, my only-begotten Son, sent by me for your salvation.
Therefore, obey Him in all things, whatever He tells you.
About this, Moses says:
"The Lord your God will raise up for you a prophet from among your brothers, like me; you shall listen to him in everything he tells you" Deuteronomy chapter eighteen.
Also, God the Father spoke to the three disciples, Peter, James, and John, who saw Him transfigured on the mountain, saying:
"This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased; listen to Him" Matthew chapter seventeen.
It's as if He were saying: keep and do everything He tells you; for preaching is beneficial if the Word of God reaches every individual.
For what good is it for me to have come into the world if I do not have that Word which was given to the prophets?
And to the disciples, He said:
"Behold, I am with you always, even to the end of the age" Matthew chapter twenty-eight.
Therefore, let God the Father say to the prophets, apostles, and ecclesiastical men:
Listen to the Word of this covenant, that is, of the great counsel: and speak to the people of Judah, that is, the Christians, who truly are the confessors of Christ:
And to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, meaning the Church, which is the city of the great King, and the vision of peace.
For peace in it is multiplied and seen through the same Christ, who is the Word of the Father.
Jews are interpreted as confessors from Judah the patriarch, from whose tribe the Lord arose, about whom it is truly said:
"Judah, your brothers shall praise you; your hand shall be on the neck of your enemies" Genesis chapter forty-nine.
So, when the call to preach is directed to the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, it's really meant for Christians who are true followers of Christ.
Let the prophets and apostles share the word of the Lord's covenant:
Here's what the Lord God of Israel says:
Cursed is the person who doesn't listen to the words of this covenant, which I commanded your ancestors on the day I brought them out of Egypt, from the iron furnace, saying:
Listen to my voice, do everything I command you, and you will be my people, and I will be your God.
Jeremiah eleven.
In other words: It's not by birthright, circumcision, or observing the Sabbath, but through obedience, that I become the God of Israel, and they become my people.
And here in the law, He speaks to servants, but in the Gospel, He speaks to friends: You are my friends if you do what I command you.
John fifteen.
And again: I no longer call you servants, but friends; because a servant doesn't know what his master is doing.
But when they become friends, they move from being friends to becoming children.
To all who received him, he gave the power to become children of God.
John one.
He instructs friends and children, saying: Be perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect.
Matthew five.
When he calls for perfection, he doesn't mean equality, but resemblance.
In the law, obedience to commandments is required, but in the Gospel, the likeness of God is promised to the children of the Church.
Cursed, He says, is the person who doesn't listen to the word of this covenant.
Thus, the Jews are cursed for not listening to the covenant of God when He brought them out of Egypt.
But we who believe in Christ obey His covenant, which is handed down through Moses; because in the seed of Abraham, that is, in Christ, we are blessed.
For this purpose, the Son of God chose the holy apostles and sent them to preach throughout the world, so that the words of this covenant might fill the hearts of all nations under heaven, like rain from clouds;
that is, so they would believe Him to be the one true God with the Father and the Holy Spirit.
Christ also commanded his disciples to preach deep and mysterious teachings to those who were more spiritually mature, but to speak more plainly to beginners; to those who understood less.
That's why the blessed Job, praising God through His works, says: "He binds up the waters in His clouds so they do not burst forth all at once" (Job 26).
Gregory the Great explains this by asking: What is meant by "water" here, if not knowledge? And what are the "clouds," if not the preachers; that is, the holy apostles?
We know that in Scripture, water sometimes stands for knowledge. Solomon confirms this when he says: "The words from a man's mouth are deep water; and the fountain of wisdom is a flowing stream" (Proverbs 18).
David the prophet also affirms that water symbolizes knowledge, saying: "Dark water was in the clouds of the air" (Psalm 18).
This means hidden knowledge was in the prophets.
Before the coming of the Lord, the prophets carried deep mysteries hidden within them, and their meaning was not clear to those who looked on.
So in this passage, the "clouds" represent the preachers; the holy apostles; who were sent throughout the world. They knew how to rain down words, flash with miracles, and stir fear with warnings.
Isaiah, foreseeing this long before, said: "Who are these that fly like clouds?" (Isaiah 60)
Because of this, blessed Job; filled with the prophetic spirit; in speaking these words to praise God, is longing for the beginning of the Church to arise.
He is eager to describe its order, starting from the preaching of the apostles.
The apostles were careful to preach simple and understandable truths to new believers, not high and difficult teachings.
If they had poured out all the holy knowledge (represented by the water) from their hearts into their speech, as they received it through the Holy Spirit, they would have overwhelmed their listeners rather than nourished them.
So the knowledge was kept inside, held back, so that it wouldn't burst forth all at once.
Instead, the cloud; the apostle; nurtured his listeners with a gentle drizzle of words.
He said, "I could not speak to you as to spiritual people, but as to those who are worldly. As to infants in Christ, I gave you milk to drink, not solid food" (1 Corinthians 3).
Who could have endured it if, taken to the third heaven and into paradise, they heard secret words not meant to be spoken by humans, revealing such vast heavenly knowledge?
Whose strength as a listener wouldn't be overwhelmed if the depth of this wisdom, absorbed internally, overflowed as much as the tongue could handle?
But for listeners who are unlearned, it's better to benefit from a moderate stream of preaching rather than a flood of knowledge.
God controls the waters in the clouds so they don't pour out all at once, tempering the teachings for listeners to grow stronger, nourished by the teachers' words.
This concept is well illustrated in the mystical story from the Gospel, where it says: Jesus got into Peter's boat and asked him to move it a little away from the shore, and sitting down, He taught the crowds.
From the Gospel of Luke, Chapter Five.
What else does Peter's boat symbolize but the Church entrusted to him?
The Lord, to preach to the gathering crowds, commands the boat to be moved a little away from the land.
He doesn't ask for it to be taken into the deep, yet He wants it moved from the land, clearly indicating that His preachers shouldn't speak of heavenly matters too high for the unlearned, nor preach earthly matters.
Therefore, the water is restrained in the clouds because the knowledge of preachers speaking to the weak is limited to what they can understand.
Often, if the vastness of the word corrupts the listeners' hearts, the teachers' indiscretion is punished.
Thus, it is written: If someone opens a pit and digs it without covering it, and an ox or a donkey falls in, the owner must pay for the animals.
From the Book of Exodus, Chapter Twenty-One.
What does it mean to open a pit if not to delve into the secrets of sacred Scripture with deep understanding?
And what do the ox and the donkey represent, as clean and unclean animals, if not the faithful and the unfaithful?
If someone digs a pit, they should cover it to prevent an ox or donkey from falling in.
This suggests that if someone understands the deep meanings in sacred teachings, they should keep those profound insights hidden from those who can't grasp them, to avoid causing mental distress or leading a faithful child or potential believer into harm.
For the loss of animals, compensation is required because it was allowed to happen, and the person responsible is held accountable and must repent.
Therefore, the pit should be covered, just as deep knowledge should be concealed from immature minds, to prevent the weakness of the listeners from faltering while the teacher's heart is lifted to great heights.
It is rightly said: "He binds the waters in the clouds so that they do not all burst out at once."
The waters would indeed burst out at once if the speaker were to reveal all his knowledge before weak listeners.
If the entire fullness of preaching were poured out at once, nothing would be held back for those who are advancing.
It is important for the preacher to consider the capacity of the listener so that the teaching grows with the listener's progress.
Every preacher should act as divinely arranged: not revealing everything they understand to the weak, because as long as they remain in the frailty of mortal flesh, they cannot understand all heavenly things.
Therefore, one should not preach to the unlearned as much as they know, because even they cannot understand the fullness of heavenly mysteries.
Preachers of the holy Church, as mentioned, should preach according to the capacity of their listeners, so they can cut out vices, nurture virtues in their hearts, impose the standards of the Christian religion, and prepare them to be fit for the building of the heavenly Jerusalem.
God has given a measure for preaching to the teachers of both the Old and New Testaments, as the prophet Ezekiel figuratively speaks, saying: "I saw a man standing at the gate, who had a measuring rod in his hand, and he measured the building and its gates, and he measured the threshold of the gate, according to the vestibule of the inner gate, with one rod" (Ezekiel 40).
This man is Christ, who holds a measuring rod in his hand, symbolizing the authority of sacred Scripture.
With it, he measures both the inner and outer thresholds, meaning he organizes the lives of the saints from both the Old and New Testaments.
Through them, he guides the behavior of all the faithful and corrects their faults.
Gregory says: The outer threshold represents the Fathers of the Old Testament, whose preaching punished corrupt actions.
The inner threshold represents the teachers of the New Testament, whose teachings restrain the mind from unlawful thoughts.
Those who were outside did not see Christ in the flesh but were not separated from the holy Church because they held the sacraments of faith in their minds, actions, and preaching.
Just as we are saved by Christ's past suffering, they were saved by faith in the same event to come.
They were outside, not outside the mystery, but outside the time.
However, bad shepherds were never inside; they were always outside and therefore rejected by the Lord.
The Lord decided to remove the shepherds of the Synagogue, whom I do not call shepherds but transgressors of the law, namely the scribes and Pharisees, from his presence due to their iniquities, and replace them with the apostles.
Through the prophet Jeremiah, he made this known to them, saying: You have scattered my flock, driven them away, and not attended to them; and because you have done this, behold, I will attend to you for the evil of your doings, says the Lord.
Jeremiah Chapter Twenty-Three.
Since all hope of the Jewish kingdom had failed, the Synagogue, along with its shepherds, was abandoned and condemned, transitioning to the leaders of the Church.
The message turns to the apostles, about whom it is said: I will raise up shepherds over them, etc.
Behold, he says, I will gather the remnant of my people from all the lands where I have driven them, and I will bring them back to their fields; and they will increase and multiply.
Jeremiah Chapter Twenty-Three.
It's like saying: "Look, I alone will gather the remnants of my flock, specifically the Gentile people who have wandered far and wide in sin, from all the lands to which, because of their sins, I had cast them."
"I will bring them back to their fields, that is, to the holy Church, so they can be nourished on the green pastures of the holy Scriptures."
"There will be one flock and one shepherd, and they will grow in virtues and multiply spiritually with new offspring."
Again, he says: "And I will raise up shepherds over them, and they will feed them."
With the shepherds of the Synagogue, that is, the Scribes and Pharisees, cast out, I will appoint new shepherds over my people, namely apostles and church leaders; and they will feed them with the bread of the word of God.
We can understand this in a moral sense regarding the leaders of the Church who do not rule the Lord's sheep worthily.
When they are cast out and condemned, the people are saved, entrusted to good shepherds, and the remnants are preserved.
Shepherds who teach heresy lead the sheep astray, tear apart, and scatter them by causing divisions, unjustly cast them out of the Church by persecuting, and act arrogantly.
They do not visit the weak in faith, holding back their hand from the repentant.
The Lord has mercy on all of them, restoring the former pastures and removing the bad shepherds.
Good shepherds refresh the holy creatures, that is, the faithful people, with their preaching, like angelic feasts.
Thus, the teaching of the holy Fathers is a table of heavenly sweetness.
Therefore, the prophet Ezekiel speaks symbolically in a vision shown to him by divine power, saying: "I saw in the vestibule of the inner gate two tables on this side and two on that side; that the burnt offering for guilt and sin might be offered on them" (Ezekiel forty).
Gregory: "Our gate, that is, the catholic faith, in the inner vestibule has four tables, because the holy Church for the instruction of the faithful has received four orders of rulers."
Therefore, the most blessed Paul speaks, saying: "He, that is, God, gave some as apostles, some as prophets, others as evangelists, others as pastors and teachers" (Ephesians four), who are one order.
So, these people, while preaching, nourish the Lord's flock, meaning the faithful people, with spiritual sweetness.
The outer gate also has four tables: the Synagogue, the chief priests, the leaders of the people, the scribes, and the Pharisees.
The Pharisees were known as teachers of the law.
At each gate, there are two tables on one side and two on the other, because the holy Church at its beginning had apostles and prophets, who emerged after the apostles.
Now, however, it has evangelists and teachers.
Evangelists are those who bring the joys of the heavenly homeland to the people.
The tables of the inner gate, that is, of the holy Church, hold the burnt offering because in the hearts of the apostles and prophets, or in the minds of the evangelists and teachers, the fire of the Holy Spirit blazed and continues to burn, consuming every intention and thought.
The flame of the love of God, like a whole burnt offering, consumes everything it encounters.
These tables are made of squared stones because as they meditate on the words of sacred scripture daily, they are built like squared stones to offer the burnt offering of prayer to the Lord.
The words of holy Scripture are like squared stones, standing firmly everywhere, never criticized.
For everything they narrate about the past, everything they predict for the future, everything they interpret spiritually, everything they announce morally, they hold a position as if on different sides.
Thus, the hearts of the saints are God's tables for burnt offerings, constructed of squared stones, because those who always contemplate the words of the Lord sacrifice themselves to the Lord from a carnal life.
Hence it is said: "The law of his God is in his heart" (Psalm 37).
Cassiodorus: "The law of his God," meaning the commandments of God, are in his heart, and like a heart, resonate with the tongue. And what benefit does this bring him? It means his steps will not be overthrown. To overthrow is to lay a trap of deceit underfoot. The meaning is: The word in the heart frees from the snares of the sinner, so that the steps of the person praising God are not overthrown.
Without a doubt, anyone who meditates on the Lord's law day and night can echo the words of the Prophet:
I have hidden your words in my heart so that I will not sin against you.
(Psalm one-nineteen)
It's as if they're saying: I have sought out your commands and even committed them to memory.
This is what it means to hide your words in my heart, keeping them away from those who wouldn't appreciate them.
Cassiodorus says: It is a kind of sin to preach to the stubborn, and so I have hidden your words to avoid sinning against you, who say:
Do not give what is holy to dogs, nor cast your pearls before pigs.
(Matthew seven)
It is a fault to reveal secret mysteries to the unworthy, like showing the treasures of the Lord's house to the Babylonians.
This might be done out of flattery, to please someone; or out of greed, to gain something; or out of pride, to seem more knowledgeable; or through careless talk, when a word once spoken cannot be taken back.
Therefore, the discipline of silence should be adopted, so that one remains silent before speaking.
Hence it is said: Let every person be quick to listen, slow to speak, and slow to anger.
(James one)
When the Lord told Isaiah to cry out, he didn't do so until he knew what to say, asking: What shall I cry?
(Isaiah forty)
The Lord also compares the kingdom of heaven to a treasure hidden in a field in the Gospel.
This is the treasure of wisdom and knowledge, which, when found, is hidden in the heart and not revealed.
(Matthew thirteen)
Just as Mary kept all the Lord's words, pondering them in her heart.
(Luke two)
So, as mentioned before, the hearts of the saints are God's tables, where they meditate on the Lord's words continuously, nourishing the children of the Church.
About these stones, Isaiah says: The bricks have fallen, but we will build with dressed stones.
(Isaiah nine)
In clearer terms: The bricks have fallen, referring to the Jews; but we will build with dressed stones, referring to the holy apostles, martyrs, and Church teachers, with whom the heavenly Jerusalem is built from living and chosen stones.
The Christian faithful hold fast to four key principles: faith, righteous living, patience, and kindness, drawing inspiration from the lives of the saints.
God alone is to be worshiped, glorified, and loved above all by humans and the blessed spirits in heaven.
Through His beloved Son, Christ, He restored everything among angels and holy people.
On this, the prophet Jeremiah, guided by the Holy Spirit, said:
"He made the earth by His power, established the world by His wisdom, and by His understanding stretched out the heavens" (Jeremiah 10:12).
It's as if he's saying: God the Father made the earth by His power, transforming sinners into the righteous and holy.
He prepared the world to serve Him with His wisdom, found in the Son, who is His strength, power, and wisdom.
By His understanding, He stretched out the heavens, spreading the teachings of the apostles across the world.
For He spoke, and it was done; He commanded, and they were created (Psalm 148:5).
Thus, speaking to the Son: "Let us make man in our image, after our likeness" (Genesis 1:26).
The prophet rightly adds: "When He utters His voice, there is a multitude of waters in the heavens, and He raises the clouds from the ends of the earth" (Jeremiah 10:13).
All the Lord's teachings flow from the heavens.
As it is said: "The earth trembled, and the heavens dripped from the presence of God at Sinai, from the presence of the God of Israel" (Psalm 68:8).
Augustine: The earth trembled, meaning those on earth were moved to faith in Christ; but why?
Because the heavens, or the apostles, poured down rain, symbolizing grace; and this came from the presence of God, meaning not from themselves, but from God within them.
It follows: Mount Sinai from the presence of the God of Israel, meaning, it dripped from the face of God and above others.
Another interpretation: Mount Sinai dripped from the presence of the God of Israel: that is, Paul, the apostle to the nations, who poured out more teachings than anyone else, is well represented by Mount Sinai, because he was first subjected to the law, which was given on Mount Sinai.
According to the same letter, Mount Sinai dripped from the presence of the God of Israel.
The heavens and mountains are the same, meaning the apostles are symbolized by the heavens and mountains.
However, it doesn't say "mountains" but "mountain," signifying the same thing in singular as in plural, just as elsewhere it is said: "The heavens declare, and the firmament announces"
Psalm 19.
It signifies the same through the heavens and the firmament.
The meaning is: Mount Sinai, that is, the apostles, dripped from the presence of the God of Israel.
However, some Greek and Latin books do not have such a letter, specifically, "Mount Sinai from the presence of the God of Israel," but have "from the presence of the God of Sinai, from the presence of the God of Israel."
The meaning is: The heavens, that is, the apostles, dripped from the presence of God.
Which God? The God of Sinai, the God of Israel; that is, the one who gave the law to the people of Israel.
For the one who gave the law through Moses to instill fear also gives through the apostles the blessing to liberate.
What did the heavens drip? Rain, meaning the doctrine of the grace of the Holy Spirit, given voluntarily, without merit, solely by the will of God.
Indeed, he gave birth to us voluntarily by the word of truth
James 1.
You will separate this rain, God, for your inheritance, meaning for the faithful in whom the rain descends with abundant irrigation.
That inheritance was weakened, meaning it recognized itself as nothing by itself; but you completed it, for strength is perfected in weakness
Second Corinthians 12.
Alternatively: You will separate voluntary rain, God, for your inheritance.
And how will this happen?
For the heavens dripped, that is, the apostles will drip from the presence of the God of Sinai, meaning from the knowledge of the God who gives the law in Sinai, from the presence of the God of Israel.
I say Israel, not according to the flesh, but the true Israel receiving grace, and not relying on fleshly observance.
For this reason, the law was given, to instill fear in those who rely on themselves; and the blessing was given to liberate those who hope in him.
Therefore, let King David and the prophet say: You will separate voluntary rain, God, for your inheritance, the heavens, he says, will drip.
And what will they drip?
The rain, specifically voluntary rain, represents the word of God given freely, not based on human merits, which you, God, will provide to your inheritance, meaning your chosen ones.
You will commend this rain because not everyone has faith, and the inheritance is weakened by acknowledging its sins and feeling that it has nothing to boast about.
It is weakened, but you, in truth, have made it perfect.
As the Apostle says, "I was, he says, a persecutor and blasphemer, but I obtained mercy" from First Timothy Chapter 1.
Or put another way, the inheritance is weakened in itself to endure tribulations, but you strengthened it and thus made it perfect.
Therefore, let Jeremiah speak of God's omnipotence: "From His voice, He gives a multitude of waters in the heavens and raises clouds from the ends of the earth" from Jeremiah Chapter 10.
As if saying more clearly, from His voice, God gives in heaven, that is, in the Church, a multitude of waters, meaning the abundant holy teachings of the Scriptures.
Hence, it is said, "In the voice of your waterfalls" from Psalm 42, meaning the apostles and prophets.
And it says He raises clouds from the ends of the earth because He chose not the proud but the humble, not the rich but the poor as preachers, specifically the apostles who were humble fishermen, to dismantle the swelling arguments of heretics and philosophers.
Hence, it is said, "God chose the weak things of this world and the contemptible things to shame the strong" from First Corinthians Chapter 1.
Therefore, whoever raises their mind in pride should not presume to preach to others.
The one who can worthily declare the Lord's righteousness to others is the one who is grounded in humility.
Hence, it is said, "Whoever wants to be first among you must be the last of all" from Mark Chapter 9.
Otherwise, no one will be able to be a cloud, that is, suitable for watering the hearts of listeners with the teaching of heavenly rain.
Isidore: A cloud is named so because it covers, that is, it covers the earth, or because when it moves, it creates clouds.
For damp valleys exhale mists, and they become clouds; hence clouds and snow.
However, clouds descend when it is clear; they rise high when it is cloudy.
Therefore, as it is said, the Lord raises clouds from the ends of the earth.
By clouds, I mean those who know when to release rain and when to hold it back; namely, the holy apostles and their successors, who, with the grace and authority given to them, nourish the hearts of the faithful with spiritual rains.
They know well when and to whom they should share the word of preaching.
About them, it is said: "I will command my clouds not to rain on it." This means not to bring the doctrine of salvation to a sinful nation. Again, to those who do God's will, it is promised: "I will give you rains in their season."
Moses, like a cloud, poured down rain when he said: "Let my teaching fall like rain, and my words descend like dew on the grass." And Isaiah: "Hear, O heavens, and give ear, O earth, for the Lord has spoken."
God does not bring forth the rain of heavenly doctrine from proud counselors, nor from leaders, nor from the rich, but from the humble hearts of preachers, namely apostles and teachers. Because blessed are the poor in spirit, for to them is entrusted the guidance of the holy Church, which is called the kingdom of heaven.
Therefore, in the Gospel, glorifying God the Father, the Lord said: "I thank you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, for you have hidden these things from the wise and learned, and revealed them to little children." That is, to the humble and simple who rely not on themselves, but on your mercy.
Again, Jeremiah adds in praise of the Creator, saying: "He makes lightning for the rain, and brings forth the wind from His storehouses." God makes lightning for the rain when He terrifies and satisfies the parched hearts of people with His brilliant doctrine.
It is said that lightning is generated from the collision of clouds, just as fire sparks from the strike of hard flints. Moses and Joshua were clouds, because when they spoke to each other, lightning flashed from their words. Jeremiah and Baruch, speaking to each other, also sent forth radiant lightning.
The Psalmist, reflecting on the omnipotence of God, said:
"He brings clouds from the ends of the earth; He turns lightning into rain"
Psalm One Hundred Thirty-Five.
Augustine noted that God sends these clouds not only from Israel but also raises them from the ends of the earth and sends them to the ends of the world.
So, what does He do with these clouds? Clearly, He turns lightning into rain, meaning He turns threats into mercy, watering from terrors.
Preachers both frighten and soothe.
They frighten by warning of eternal punishment; they soothe by promising eternal joy.
And thus, it is written that manna melted in the sun and hardened in the fire
Exodus Sixteen,
Wisdom Sixteen.
Manna, given from heaven, symbolizes divine words;
it melts in the sun, glorifying the minds of the faithful with the promise of future brightness when it is said:
"The righteous will shine like the sun in the kingdom of my Father"
Matthew Thirteen.
However, manna hardens in the fire, warning the minds of sinners unaware of future punishment, saying:
"Every tree that does not produce good fruit will be cut down and thrown into the fire"
Matthew Three.
Therefore, in the old law, on the robe of the high priest, there was double-dyed scarlet, which resembles fire
Exodus Twenty-Eight.
Fire indeed does two things: it burns and it gives light;
because the preacher should burn the heart of sinners with lightning and the terror of threats, and comfort the minds of the righteous with the promise of eternal light.
This is why the staff of the bishop has a lower part that pricks and an upper part that extends forward;
because the preacher should prick the vices of the flesh and guide the strength of the mind forward;
yet he should always return to self-reflection, lest after preaching to others, he himself becomes disqualified
First Corinthians Nine.
At the beginning of his sermon, he should be his own accuser, so that he does not see the speck in another's eye while carrying a beam in his own
Matthew Seven.
Therefore, as promised, God turns lightning into rain, because in the preaching of the humble, He satisfies the hearts of listeners with spiritual teaching and instills fear of punishments.
He soothes with the promise of rewards and terrifies with the announcement of punishments.
Isidore: Clouds are named because they cover and conceal the sky.
In a similar way, brides are called this because they veil their faces.
Likewise, Neptune is named for covering both the sea and the land.
A cloud forms from the density of the air.
The winds gather the air, creating clouds; hence the saying: "And the air is gathered into a cloud."
Thunder gets its name because its sound is frightening; "tonus" means sound.
Sometimes it shakes everything so violently that it seems like the sky has split.
This happens when a fierce storm of winds rushes into the clouds, gaining strength and looking for an exit.
It cuts through the cloud with great force, reaching our ears with a terrifying crash.
It's not surprising, as even a small animal bladder can make a loud noise when it bursts.
Lightning appears at the same time as thunder, but we see lightning more quickly because it's bright, while thunder reaches our ears more slowly.
The light that appears before the thunder is called "fulgetra"; we see it first because it's bright.
"Fulgur" and "fulmen" are named from the strike of a heavenly javelin.
To flash is to strike and hit.
"Fulmen" occurs when clouds collide; collisions create fire, as we see with stones, the friction of wheels, or in the woods with trees.
Similarly, fire is made in the clouds; thus, there are clouds first, then fires.
It's said that lightning is created in the clouds from wind and fire, emitted by the force of the winds.
The fire of lightning penetrates more powerfully than the fire we use because it's made from more subtle elements.
It has three names: "fulgur," "fulgor," and "fulmen."
"Fulgur" because it touches, "fulgor" because it ignites and burns, and "fulmen" because it splits, depicted with three rays.
The prophet Jeremiah adds about the works of Almighty God, saying: "And he brings out the wind from his storehouses" (Jeremiah 10).
This means he brings forth the wind of wisdom from the hearts of the humble, sending those simple and humble ones to proclaim the teaching of his faith.
Within them lie the hidden treasures of God's wisdom and knowledge.
God brings forth the wind from his treasures, and through humble ones-like the apostles, evangelists, and other teachers-he reveals the mysteries of his secrets to all the peoples of the world.
The winds that sweep across the lands symbolize these spiritual winds.
This is similar to what the Psalmist says: "He brings forth the winds from his treasures" (Psalm one hundred thirty-five).
Preachers are like clouds and winds; clouds because of the flesh, winds because of the spirit.
Clouds are seen, while winds are felt but not seen.
And since flesh is from the earth, it's said that he stirs up the clouds from the ends of the earth, yet the spirit of man is unknown from where it comes.
Thus, it is aptly said: "He brings forth the winds from his treasures."
The apostles are called winds for another reason, namely because they swiftly travel the whole world.
As the blessed Isidore says: "The wind is air that is moved and stirred, receiving different names depending on the parts of the sky."
It is called wind because it is strong and forceful.
Its power is so immense that it not only uproots rocks and trees but also stirs the sky and earth, and agitates the seas.
There are four principal winds: from the east is Subsolanus, from the south is Auster, from the west is Favonius, and from the north is the wind of the same name, with twin spirits on either side.
Subsolanus has Vulturnus on the right side and Eurus on the left; Auster has Euroaustrum on the right and Austroafricum on the left.
Favonius has Africus on the right side and Corus on the left.
Similarly, Septentrio has Circius on the right and Aquilo on the left.
These twelve winds encircle the globe, each named for specific reasons.
Subsolanus is named because it arises under the rising sun.
Eurus is called so because it blows from Eos, meaning from the east, and is joined with Subsolanus.
Vulturnus gets its name because it thunders loudly; as Lucretius says: 'Loud-thundering Vulturnus, and Auster powerful with lightning.' (Lucretius, Book five, line seven hundred forty-four).
The south wind is called Auster because it draws up water, thickening the air and feeding clouds.
In Greek, it is known as Notos because it can sometimes corrupt the air.
Auster spreads disease through the air, born from its corruption, to other areas.
However, just as Auster creates disease, Aquilo drives it away.
The wind called Euroauster is named because it has Eurus on one side and Auster on the other.
Austroafricus gets its name from being joined by Auster on one side and Africus on the other.
It is also known as Libonotus because it has Libs on one side and Notus on the other.
Zephyrus is called by its Greek name because its breath revives flowers and buds.
In Latin, it is Favonius because it nurtures new growth.
Flowers bloom with the south wind, but they come to life with Zephyrus, or Favonius.
Favonius is named for its nurturing effect on crops and flowers.
In Greek, it is Zephyros as it often blows in spring.
Thus the saying goes: "And the loose soil crumbles under the west wind." Virgil, Georgics, Book One, Line 43.
Africus is named after its region because it starts blowing from Africa.
Corus is the summer west wind, called Corus because it completes the circle of winds, almost like forming a chorus.
Septentrio is named for the circle of seven stars, which seem to be carried with their heads turned as the world turns.
Circius is named because it is connected to Corus.
The Spanish call this wind Gallecum because it blows to them from Galicia.
Aquilo is named for tightening the waters and scattering clouds; it is a cold, dry wind.
It is also called Boreas because it blows from the Hyperborean mountains.
This origin makes it cold.
Northern winds are cold and dry, while southern winds are moist and warm.
Of all the winds, two are cardinal: Aquilo and Auster.
After briefly discussing the nature and diversity of winds by the blessed Isidore, we must return to the topics we previously omitted.
So, the winds that blow over the earth aren't part of God's treasures because their nature is obvious.
However, there are treasures of winds, which refer to spirits: the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and strength, the spirit of knowledge and piety, and the spirit of the fear of the Lord (Isaiah eleven).
These treasures are fully hidden in Christ, the source of all good things, and are also found to some extent in the hearts of His servants.
From the fullness of this greatest treasure, we see that one person is wise, another is faithful, one is humble, another is chaste, one is full of love, another is sober, one is dedicated to prayer and divine contemplation, another is generous in almsgiving, one focuses on hospitality and works of mercy, another patiently endures the challenges of this world, and yet another despises riches and willingly embraces poverty for the sake of eternal reward.
The prophet Jeremiah talks about the strength, wisdom, and prudence of God the Father.
He says, "He made the earth by His power, prepared the world by His wisdom, and stretched out the heavens by His understanding." Here, the prophet highlights three virtues: strength, wisdom, and prudence, and assigns each its own works: the earth to strength, the world to wisdom, and heaven to prudence.
Therefore, in our earthly existence, of which it was said: "You are dust, and to dust you shall return" (Genesis three), we need the strength of God, without which it's impossible to overcome the flesh.
As the Apostle says, when our earthly members are put to death (Colossians three), the flesh will then obey the spirit's will.
The deeds of the flesh are put to death by the spirit, because, as written in Job, God set the earth on nothingness; which shows that by His strength, the balance of the earth is maintained in the middle of the world.
"He stretches out the north over empty space, and hangs the earth on nothing" (Job twenty-six).
Gregory: In sacred scripture, the devil is often referred to as the one from the north, who aims to chill and harden the hearts of nations with cold indifference.
He said, "I will sit on the mount of the covenant on the sides of the north."
Isaiah 14:13.
He spreads over emptiness because he occupies hearts that lack the grace of divine love.
However, Almighty God can fill even the devil's empty vessels with His grace and instill divine fear in those not yet strengthened by righteousness.
Thus, it is fittingly said: "He hangs the earth over nothing."
What does the name "earth" signify if not the holy Church?
When it receives the words of preaching, it bears the fruit of good works.
Moses spoke of this: "Let the earth hear the words from my mouth."
Deuteronomy 32:1.
And again: "Let my words fall like rain."
Deuteronomy 32:2.
What does "nothing" mean if not the Gentile nations?
About whom Isaiah said: "All the nations are regarded by Him as nothing and emptiness."
Isaiah 40:17.
Therefore, the earth is suspended over that nothingness where it was once held by the north, because the hearts of the Gentiles are now filled with God's love, which were once oppressed by the devil's numbness.
So, let us mortify our earthly members, meaning the vices of the flesh, and let virtues come alive through God's grace within each of us, so that our hearts may be closed to the devil and open to Christ.
Indeed, this emptiness can also symbolize the unbelief of the Jews, and the earth, as we said, represents the fruitfulness of the holy Church.
Therefore, let the holy person observe the plight of the perishing Jews and recognize the merits of the Gentiles returning to grace; and let him proclaim: "He stretches the north over emptiness, and hangs the earth over nothing."
For the hearts of the Jews are empty of faith and subjected to the devil, he stretches the north over emptiness.
But because, with no merits existing, the Lord established the Church among the nations, who were once considered nothing before their conversion through the Prophet, it is fittingly stated: "He hangs the earth over nothing."
This fits well with what the Psalmist said:
"You will save them for nothing" (Psalm Fifty-Five).
So, as mentioned earlier, if we mortify our earthly members, the north wind will be driven further from us.
We will be counted among the Church's members, and our soul will be inhabited by the Holy Spirit.
In Greek, the world is called ciromines, meaning "inhabited."
I know a soul that is inhabited, and one that is abandoned.
For if it doesn't have God the Father and the Son saying:
"I and the Father are one" (John Chapter Ten),
and "we will come to him who loves me and make our home with him" (John Chapter Fourteen),
and the Holy Spirit who proceeds from both, it is truly deserted.
However, a soul is inhabited when it is full of God and has Christ and the Spirit of the Lord.
Thus, David in the Psalm of confession says:
"Uphold me with a willing spirit. Renew a right spirit within me.
Do not take your Holy Spirit from me" (Psalm Fifty-One).
We mention these to prove that the inhabited world is made in the wisdom of God.
As it's written:
"Wisdom helps the just more than ten rulers in the city" (Ecclesiastes Chapter Seven).
Indeed, whoever rejects wisdom and discipline is unfortunate, with vain hope,
senseless efforts, and useless works (Wisdom Chapter Three).
Therefore, let's strive, dear brothers, for our soul to be inhabited by God the Father, His Son, and the Holy Spirit,
and be uplifted by His wisdom.
We fell from on high into this pit of misery when we sinned.
In fact, whoever is in this world fell before correction.
We all fell through sin into the world, but the Lord lifted the fallen,
and in His wisdom, He stretched out the heavens, meaning the minds.
Strength was not assumed in the stretching out of the heavens, nor was wisdom.
Hence it is said:
"The Lord founded the earth, and prepared the heavens with wisdom" (Proverbs Chapter Three).
Therefore, do not seek God's wisdom outside of Christ,
because everything of God is Christ (Colossians Chapter Three).
He embodies wisdom, strength, justice, and holiness, and his prudence is clear to see.
Though it is one in substance, it is referred to by different names based on its various meanings.
Wisdom represents one aspect, while justice represents another.
When wisdom is mentioned, it teaches us about both human and divine matters.
When justice is mentioned, it signifies the one who distributes and judges merits.
So, understand his prudence here as the doctrine and demonstration of good, evil, or both.
It is said that he stretched out the heavens in his prudence.
This is why it is said: "I have extended my words, and you did not pay attention" (Proverbs 1).
This suggests a certain extension of words, much like the heavens.
Therefore, this: "He stretches out the heavens like a tent; he covers its upper areas with water" (Psalm 104).
As if to say: You are God, stretching out the heavens.
Literally, God stretched out the heavens like the roof of the world.
He makes the firmament broad to cover the earth, as effortlessly as one stretches a skin, not with any labor, as you would stretch out your roof, but as easily as stretching a skin.
By saying "like a skin," he also indicates himself as the creator of all things surrounding everything.
Mystically, it can also be interpreted and relates to the earlier statement that he clothed himself with the Church.
But how he accomplished this is explained by saying: You are stretching out the heavens like a skin.
He explains with figurative sacraments when the Church is made a light, without spot or wrinkle.
For sacred Scripture is perceived as the heavens; by the skin, which comes from dead animals, the mortality of the preachers is understood.
Thus, our first parents, Adam and Eve, after their transgression, became mortal and were clothed in skins.
Yet the Word of God is eternal, and God is with God.
And because the world did not know God through God's wisdom, through the foolishness of preaching, that is, through mortal preachers who seemed foolish, God saves those who believe, and in a mortal man, he makes the immortal Word known (First Corinthians 1).
Preachers can be likened to skins because, just as the skins of dead animals serve a purpose, the word of God became more widely known through preachers, even more so after their time.
The prophets and apostles may have passed away, but their words endure.
Now, their words are often seen as the words of the departed, gaining greater recognition after their deaths.
While Judea was the only place with living prophets, all nations now have access to the words of the deceased prophets, allowing us to read them until the end of time.
The idea here is: When you make something to cover.
See, you are like God stretching out the heavens-symbolizing the Holy Scripture-to encompass the entire world, through which the eternal word of God is revealed.
I describe this stretching like a skin, meaning through mortal preachers.
The word of God was always present, but the world did not recognize it, as stated in John, chapter one.
It began to be known through mortals, and after them, it became even more widely recognized.
Consequently, our soul expands from where it was once confined.
Those who embody the heavenly man belong to heaven.
But if it is said to the sinner: You are dust, and to dust you shall return, as in Genesis, chapter three, why is it not said to the righteous: You are heaven, and to heaven you shall go?
Or if, due to earthly existence, it is said to one who bears the image of the earthly man: You are dust, and to dust you shall return, why is it not said to one who bears the image of the heavenly: You are heaven, and to heaven you shall go?
Each of us carries either heavenly deeds or earthly ones.
Earthly deeds lead to earth, aligning with earthly treasures, while heavenly deeds guide the treasurer to realms fitting them.
Thus, God the Father sent, through His beloved Son, the holy apostles to all corners of the world, to transform the earthly into heavenly, the carnal into spiritual, the sinners into righteous, and to guide their ways to serve God spiritually.
As the blessed Job, foreseeing in spirit the apostles' rejection from Judea, said: The children of the taught did not walk there, nor did the lioness pass through it.
Gregory: In all the Latin manuscripts, we found the word "teachers," but in the Greek ones, we found "merchants." From this, we can understand that those who wrote "teachers" instead of "merchants" did so out of ignorance.
We call merchants "traders" because they are engaged in their work. Even though the terms sound different, they mean the same thing, because everyone who helps shape the morals of the faithful is engaged in spiritual business.
When they provide preaching to their listeners, they hope to receive faith and good works from them, as it is written about the Holy Church: "She makes linen garments and sells them" (Proverbs Chapter Thirty-One).
And shortly after, it adds: "She sees that her trading is profitable."
So, who are the merchants in this passage, if not the holy prophets who took care to shape the morals of the Synagogue through prophecy?
Their spiritual descendants are called the holy apostles, who, through their preaching, brought others to the same faith, to believe in God as human.
About them, it is said through the Psalmist about the Holy Church: "Instead of your fathers shall be your sons; you will make them princes in all the earth" (Psalm Forty-Five).
Cassiodorus: Here, he is saying how much the bride, that is, the Holy Church, has grown.
He commends the offspring, as if to say: "They will be brought," for instead of your fathers, the ancient idol-worshiping fathers, you have sons born to you, that is, the apostles, the leaders of preaching.
Augustine: "Instead of your fathers shall be your sons," that is, after the prophets, the apostles, and after the apostles and for the apostles, bishops, and other teachers whom the Church has brought forth and placed in the seat of the Fathers.
Hence it follows: "You will make them princes in all the earth," etc. Therefore, for the patriarchs and prophets of the Holy Church, sons were born, that is, the holy apostles.
But because they were rejected by the Jews and left the boundaries of the Synagogue, it is rightly said now: "The sons of the merchants did not tread on it," namely the Synagogue.
If the holy preachers used the strength of virtue to trample on the vices of the Synagogue, they would indeed tread on it.
If we consider the merchants to be the preachers of the holy Church, then the sons of these merchants are the pastors and teachers who followed the apostles' path.
It's easy to understand that they didn't tread on the Synagogue because when their fathers, the apostles, were rejected by it, they too stopped returning there.
Therefore, the Synagogue was not traversed by the lioness because the holy Church, focused on gathering the nations, didn't spend much time with the Jewish people.
The Church is aptly called a lioness because it destroys those living in sin through the power of holy preaching.
Thus, the first preacher is told, as if to the mouth of this lioness: "Kill and eat" Acts chapter 10.
What is killed is taken from life to death.
What is eaten is transformed into the body of the one eating.
So, "Kill and eat" means to destroy the sin in which they live and to transform them into your members.
And because this Church is the body of the Lord, the Lord himself is also called a lion by Jacob and a lioness by the body, when it is said to him under the guise of Judah: "You have gone up to the prey, my son" Genesis chapter 49.
"You lie down as a lion, and as a lioness; who will rouse him?"
Therefore, this lioness is not said to have not passed through Judea, but rather not to have completely passed over it.
Blessed Job says, "The lion has not passed over it" Job chapter 28.
With the apostles preaching, first three thousand, and later five thousand from Judea believed Acts chapters 2 and 4.
Thus, the lioness, the Church, passed through the Synagogue but didn't completely pass over it, because it brought some to faith but didn't utterly destroy that unfaithful people.
As we've often said, the lioness, the early Church, turned away from the unbelief of the Jews and moved toward the calling of the Gentiles.
Hence, of the same lioness, the holy Church, it is said: "He stretches out his hand to the rock; he overturns the mountains by the roots" Job chapter 28.
The lioness extends her paw to the rock, symbolizing the Church reaching out with its preaching to the hardened nations.
Thus, the blessed Job foresaw that the story of his suffering would be woven into us, the Gentiles, when he said:
"Let these words be written with an iron pen on a lead plate, or carved into rock" Job chapter nineteen.
In this context, what do we understand by mountains if not the powers of this world, who are puffed up with pride over earthly wealth?
About these, the Psalmist says: "Touch the mountains, and they will smoke" Psalm one hundred and forty-three.
Cassiodorus explains: "Lord, by your grace, touch the mountains, meaning the great figures of the earth, the proud; and they will smoke, meaning they will confess their sins."
Gregory says: "Mountains have been uprooted because, with the preaching of the holy Church, the highest powers of this world fall into worship of the omnipotent God from their innermost thoughts.
The roots of the mountains are the innermost thoughts of the proud; and the mountains fall from their roots because the powers of the world are brought down from their innermost thoughts to worship God.
Thus, let the blessed Job speak of the lioness, meaning the early Church: 'She extends her hand to the rock and uproots the mountains from their roots.'
For, while the holy preaching of the apostles sought the hardness of the nations, it completely uprooted the pride of the arrogant.
The Son of God sent his disciples for this purpose, to cut away the vices of both the high and the low of this world with the sword of God's word, to shape their morals, and to uproot from their hearts useless and perverse thoughts.
Hence, Jeremiah says: 'Cursed is the one who withholds his sword from blood' Jeremiah forty-eight.
As if to say: Cursed is the one who neglects to cut away fleshly vices with the word of God, both in himself and in those he leads.
Thus, blessed Gregory says: 'To withhold the sword from blood is to hold back the word of preaching from the killing of a carnal life.'
Of this it is said: 'My sword shall devour flesh' Deuteronomy thirty-two.
Paul also says: 'I declare to you today that I am innocent of the blood of all people.
For I did not shrink from declaring to you the whole counsel of God' Acts twenty.
This applies to those living a worldly life, indulging in luxuries and neglecting to discipline their bodies and bring them into submission.
As it is written: "Those who belong to Christ have crucified the flesh with its passions and desires" from the book of Galatians, chapter five.
For without the shedding of blood, there is no forgiveness of sins from the book of Hebrews, chapter nine.
Flesh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God from First Corinthians, chapter fifteen.
Cursed is the one who prevents the sword, meaning the word of God, from shedding the blood that revives the material of sins.
It's important to understand that whatever is carnal and earthly in us must be cut away with the sword of the word of God.
What's truly sorrowful is that some churchmen willingly speak useless things and neglect to say what could benefit many listeners.
For the love of God and neighbor, they should refrain from unnecessary words and speak what is good.
Voluntarily, indeed, he who said, "I have proclaimed your righteousness in the great congregation; I do not restrain my lips, Lord, you know" from the book of Psalms, chapter thirty-nine, preached God's commandments to the people.
It's as if he were saying: I have proclaimed.
He says this as if speaking through the members; first through himself, then through others, proclaiming that your righteousness is from you.
I have proclaimed your righteousness in the great Church, which is now worldwide, not small as before; if anything arises, fear will not stop me from speaking, meaning I will not restrain my lips.
It's as if he were saying: I don't keep this to myself out of fear.
He says this against worldly fear, meaning he will speak without pretense, because, Lord, you know my heart.
It's as if he says: My lips speak to people, but you, Lord, know my heart.
This is to ensure the proclamation is not only on the lips, for it is with the heart that one believes unto righteousness, and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation from the book of Romans, chapter ten.
And he says this against pretense.
Or thus: O Lord, I will not restrain my lips: you know that fear does not stop me from speaking.
I won't hold back my words, and that's because of you, Lord, because you knew it; meaning, you destined it to happen.
And for this, I am not idle, because I didn't hide your righteousness in my heart, but I spoke of your truth and salvation.
I didn't keep your righteousness, or my own, hidden in my heart when I could help others; that is, I confessed my faith.
I didn't hide your salvation.
Augustine: Or I spoke your truth and salvation, meaning Christ, that is, I preached, and I didn't stop despite many who might oppose.
Therefore, men of the Church, as mentioned earlier, should eagerly preach the righteousness of God to the people and take great care not to speak out of ignorance or withhold necessary truths from their listeners.
In all things, they should strive to follow the standard of apostolic teaching.
These chosen preachers from the nations were foreshadowed by Hiram from Tyre, the craftsman, whom King Solomon took as a helper for his work, as mentioned in First Kings chapter seven and Second Chronicles chapter two.
His mother, a widow, represented the present Church, for whom the Son of God and the Virgin mercifully gave his life, and ascending to heaven, left her wandering on earth like a widow, whose sons are the preachers chosen after the apostles.
Hence, it is said: Your sons are born to you instead of your fathers, as in Psalm forty-five.
And Hiram made two bronze pillars, eighteen cubits high, and a line of twelve cubits surrounded each pillar, as mentioned in First Kings chapter seven.
Therefore, the line of twelve cubits that surrounded each pillar is the apostolic doctrine.
Thus, the standard of apostolic teaching surrounds each pillar when holy teachers, commanded to preach to Jews or Gentiles, make sure to do and teach only what the Church received and learned through the apostles.
For anyone who wishes to live or teach otherwise, and to scorn apostolic doctrine, is not a pillar in the temple of God.
Because when they disdain to follow apostolic statutes, whether due to laziness or pride, they do not fit the twelve-cubit line.
The two columns, therefore, symbolize the apostles and all the Church's teachers who are strong in faith and action, elevated by contemplation.
They serve to introduce both the circumcised and the uncircumcised into the Church through preaching.
God, who wished to build a temple for the glory of His name through both Jews and Gentiles, chose distinguished teachers from the Gentiles after the apostles to construct His Church.
As blessed Job, praising God, says:
"He removes the stars of the rain and pours down showers like floods from the clouds."
Job
36.
Gregory says: In this life, there are two kinds of righteous people. Some live well but do not teach, while others live rightly and teach those same principles. Just as in the sky, some stars appear after which a thousand rains follow, while others pour heavy rains on the dry land, like Arcturus, Orion, and the Hyades.
So, whenever certain individuals live rightly in the holy Church but do not know how to preach that same righteousness, they are like stars born in the dry air. Through their example of good living, they can shine for others, but they cannot rain the word of preaching.
But when in the Church some live rightly and also spread the same righteousness to others through preaching, stars are created in the sky to bring forth rains. These stars shine by the merits of their life and also rain down through the word of preaching.
Wasn't Moses a rain star in this sky? When he shone from on high, he infused the hearts of sinners-like dry land below-with the rain of holy exhortation to produce abundance.
Wasn't Isaiah shown to be a rain star, who, by holding the light of truth with foresight, watered the dryness of the unbelievers by announcing prophecy?
Were not Jeremiah and the other prophets, as if placed in the sky, rain stars? Elevated to the height of preaching, they boldly rebuked the wickedness of sinners, pressing down the dust of human blindness by watering it with drops of words.
Their souls, taken from this corruptible flesh and removed from this life to heavenly judgments, are like stars hidden by rain from the sky.
Secretly, the stars return when the souls of the saints, having completed their journeys, are stored in the treasures of the inner spirit.
If the earth would dry up with the stars withdrawn and the heavenly rains ceased entirely, it would be like the ancient fathers being removed and the teachings of the law silenced.
So, he hides the stars of the rain and pours out showers like floods.
When he brought the preachers of the law to the secret inner places, a more abundant force of preaching flowed out through the words of their persecutors.
The holy Apostles can also be seen as the stars of the rain, of whom it is said regarding rejected Judea through Jeremiah: "The rain stars have been forbidden, and the latter rain was not" (Jeremiah 3:3).
So, the Lord removed the stars of the rain and poured out showers like floods, because when he took away the apostles who preached in Judea, he watered the world with the teachings of new grace.
These events can also be understood to have happened in the Church; as when he transferred the souls of the apostles, releasing them from their bodies to the secret places of the heavens, he hid the stars of the rain from the sky.
But with the stars of the rain taken away, he gave showers like floods because even when the apostles returned to the heavenly places, he revealed through a more generous outpouring the streams of divine knowledge long hidden, through the tongues of the interpreters who followed.
What the apostles spoke briefly, these interpreters assert by expounding in many ways.
Thus, this very preaching of the interpreters is compared to floods; because while they gather the sayings of many predecessors, they themselves expand more deeply on what they assert.
As they join testimonies to testimonies, they create floods from floods; their words teach the nations daily, and the minds of sinners receive heavenly knowledge, like water on the earth showing floods.
Even though they don't claim to surpass the apostles in knowledge, they often provide more detailed explanations.
They must always remember through whom they received these insights.
That's why it's fitting to say: They flow from the clouds.
These streams come from the clouds because without the apostles' understanding, a more abundant flow of wisdom wouldn't come from teachers today.
In sacred Scripture, clouds can symbolize different groups: sometimes people, sometimes prophets, or apostles.
Clouds signify the changing nature of the human mind, as Solomon says: Whoever watches the wind will not sow, and whoever looks at the clouds will not reap.
Ecclesiastes eleven.
The wind undoubtedly refers to the unclean spirit, and the clouds symbolize the people influenced by it.
They are swayed by temptations as these gusts of suggestions move through their hearts.
So, whoever watches the wind will not sow because fearing coming temptations stops them from focusing on good works.
And whoever considers the clouds will not reap because fearing human unpredictability prevents them from gaining eternal rewards.
Prophets are also depicted as clouds, as the Psalmist says: The dark water in the clouds of the air.
Psalm eighteen.
Augustine explains that the dark water in the clouds represents the obscure doctrines taught by prophets and preachers, who, elevated above earthly matters, deliver God's Word to those below.
This is obscure compared to the brightness that will appear in His presence, or in His revelation.
For now, we see through a mirror, but then face to face.
First Corinthians thirteen.
Cassiodorus adds that no one should assume they will be part of the future light just because they understand Scripture well.
He continues: The clouds have passed.
This suggests that the preachers of the divine word, symbolized by these clouds, have moved to the nations beyond Judea.
Another interpretation is that he bent down the heavens, symbolizing how he humbled the preachers from a contemplative life to active ministry, similar to how Rachel gave her husband to Leah in the Book of Genesis, Chapter 29.
Through their teachings, he reaches the understanding of simple people who cannot grasp more complex ideas.
Thus, when he said he descended or bent down the heavens, it means he humbled the preachers to endure hardships, and he himself, the bridegroom of the Church, suffers with those he is united with.
As the blessed Gregory noted, the apostles are also represented through the clouds, as mentioned in Isaiah: I will command the clouds not to rain on it, from the Book of Isaiah, Chapter 5.
They shine like stars through the merits of their lives; they are the clouds because they water the dry lands of our hearts with heavenly understanding.
If there were no clouds, the prophet would not have looked upon them and said: Who are these who fly like clouds?
from the Book of Isaiah, Chapter 60.
The torrents of rain flow from the clouds because the profound teachings originate from the understanding of the holy apostles.
They, as disciples of the ultimate truth, began preaching after their glorious master, Christ.
They were told: Go into all the world and preach the Gospel to every creature, from the Book of Mark, Chapter 16.
They were commanded to baptize all nations in the faith of the supreme and indivisible Trinity, from the Book of Matthew, Chapter 28.
What they heard in secret, they preached openly; and what they learned in darkness, that is, in private, from the Lord, they announced in all cities and to all nations throughout the world.
These men sowed the chosen seeds of the word upon the rational earth, meaning upon the hearts of humankind, and brought back to God the fruit a hundredfold, namely, holy souls.
To them, the Son of God and the Virgin, when going on a journey, that is, ascending to heaven, divided his goods for trading, giving the gifts of the Holy Spirit, so that when he returns to settle accounts, that is, at the judgment, he may see how much each has gained.
As faithful and devoted servants, they shared the talents given to them with all nations under heaven, bringing back great rewards of holy souls to their master.
This same beloved Teacher foretold that they would join Him at the end of the world to judge the twelve tribes of Israel.
So, dearest brothers, let us follow in the footsteps of these holy apostles, as divine grace permits, so that, with their merits and prayers, we may be worthy of eternal joy.
Through the One who, in perfect Trinity, lives and reigns as God, forever and ever.
Amen.