On the Prophet Zechariah
by Haymo Bishop of Halberstadt
Zacharias, son of Barachias and grandson of Addo, was among the last of the twelve prophets and a contemporary of Haggai.
They both prophesied during the second year of Darius's reign.
However, Zacharias started prophesying in the eighth month, which is November for the Hebrews, while Haggai began in the sixth month, which is September, on the first day.
Therefore, Haggai is rightfully placed as the tenth prophet, and Zacharias as the eleventh.
This Darius was the son of Hystaspes and the fourth ruler over the Persians and Medes after Cyrus.
Cyrus had destroyed the Chaldean empire and transferred it to the Medes and Persians.
In the first year of his reign, as Isaiah had predicted, he released almost fifty thousand captives from Babylon to Judea.
He also returned the vessels of the Lord's temple, which Nebuchadnezzar had taken, and ordered the temple to be rebuilt in Jerusalem under Zerubbabel and Joshua, the high priest.
This Cyrus was killed by Tomyris, queen of the Massagetae, who threw his head into a vessel full of blood, saying, "Drink the blood you always thirsted for!"
His son Cambyses succeeded him, followed by two magician brothers.
After they were killed, Darius, son of Hystaspes, was made king of the Persians.
In the second year of his reign, Zacharias began to prophesy.
Therefore, from the first year of King Cyrus to the second year of Darius, forty years are counted, during which only the altar was built, and the foundations of the temple were laid, as neighboring nations, by order of King Cambyses, prevented them from building the temple or the city.
Chapter One
In the eighth month of the second year of King Darius, the word of the Lord came to Zechariah, the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, the prophet.
Note that Zechariah is referred to as the son of both Berechiah and Iddo.
This Iddo is the same one sent to the wicked King Jeroboam, as mentioned in the book of Kings, when the altar was destroyed, and the king's hand withered but was restored when the man of God prayed.
Allegorically, the eighth month, which is November for the Hebrews, marks the beginning of winter and has no festival.
Since the people had not fully returned from captivity and the temple of God was not yet built, the prophet is said to have prophesied during a month with no festival or joy.
However, they remembered the Lord and the former temple and religion.
This is shown by Zechariah, whose name means "the memory of the Lord." Therefore, they were worthy of the Lord's blessing, which is Berechiah, meaning "the blessing of the Lord," and had testimony of their devotion, which is Iddo, meaning "the testimony of the Lord."
Anyone who strives to remember the Lord is rightly called the son of Berechiah, that is, the blessing of the Lord, and the son of Iddo, that is, the testimony of the Lord. Whoever confesses Christ before men will also be confessed before God the Father, who is in heaven.
The Lord was very angry with your ancestors, and you shall say to them: This is what the Lord God of hosts says: Turn to me, says the Lord of hosts, and I will turn to you, says the Lord of hosts. Do not be like your ancestors, to whom the former prophets cried out, saying...
When it is said that he is angry, it should not be thought that any disturbance of mind befalls him. Rather, it implies that those to whom this is said are deserving of anger and vengeance. He does not avenge in anger but rebukes to amend. Hence, it also follows, Turn. For if he is truly angry, why does he urge them to turn back?
He commanded those who had returned from Babylon to change their ways, so that the children would not endure what their fathers had endured.
The Lord of hosts, which in Hebrew is called Sabaoth, is named because He commands the armies of the heavenly militia.
Both Haggai and Zechariah frequently call the Lord "the Lord of hosts" to give confidence to those who, despite the power of the Persian empire and the opposition from Cyrus, were building the temple of the Lord.
This is what the Lord of hosts says: Turn from your evil ways and your wicked thoughts, but they did not listen or pay attention to me, says the Lord. Where are your forefathers now and the prophets? Do they live forever? But my words and decrees, which I commanded my servants the prophets, did they not reach your forefathers? And they repented and said: As the Lord of hosts intended to do to us according to our ways and our deeds, so He has done to us.
These words depend on the previous chapter, where it says: Do not be like your forefathers, to whom the earlier prophets cried out, saying: This is what the Lord of hosts says: Turn from your ways, etc. Therefore, Zechariah does not say this on his own behalf, but from the preceding prophets, who cried out with the voice of the Lord, saying: Turn, etc. Isaiah, Hosea, Jeremiah, and the others in order cried out for them to turn from their evil deeds and wicked thoughts, but hardened and almost desperate, they did not listen; as even Saint Daniel confessed the same thing, praying to the Lord for the liberation of his people.
On the twenty-fourth day of the eleventh month of Shebat, in the second year of the reign of Darius, the word of the Lord came to Zechariah, son of Berechiah, son of Iddo, the prophet. The eleventh month Shebat is called February by us. Shebat is interpreted as "rod" because of the harshness and rigor of the winter season. On the twenty-fourth day, when the moon is already faintly shining and nearly waning.
Since the prophet Zechariah was speaking to the people who were mostly still exiled in Assyria, it's fitting that he prophesied in the second year and eleventh month, on the twenty-fourth day, when the moon was waning and darkness was growing.
He is said to have prophesied the following things:
I saw during the night, and behold, a man riding on a red horse, standing among the myrtle trees in the deep, and behind him were red, spotted, and white horses.
He says he saw it at night, not during the day, like Moses, when God spoke to him face to face, and like Isaiah who said: I saw the Lord seated on a high throne.
Because the people were still held in the darkness of servitude, as if it were night.
Therefore, the prophet says he saw these things for them at night.
Spiritually, the night in which the vision is seen signifies the obscurity of the mystical vision.
Hence the Psalmist says, He made darkness his secret place.
And behold, a man riding on a red horse, standing among the myrtle trees in the deep.
The Hebrews literally understand the rider on the red horse to be the archangel Michael.
He was red because he is the avenger of the iniquities of the people over whom he presides.
The myrtle trees in the deep are said by prophets and saints to be those who dwelt among the captive people.
The red, spotted, and white horses that followed the man, who is Michael, represent kingdoms or angels who preside over those kingdoms, though in a different order.
The white horses represent the Medes and Persians, who were kind to the Jews, and under whom the captivity ended and the temple was rebuilt.
The spotted horses represent the Macedonians, some of whom were kind to the Jews, while others persecuted them.
The red horses signify the Roman Empire, cruel and bloodthirsty, which destroyed the temple and annihilated the nation.
Some people interpret the four kingdoms mentioned here in the order they are listed: the red horse, on which a man was sitting, and the red horses that followed him.
They believe these represent the Assyrians and the Chaldeans, who were bloodthirsty and cruel.
The Assyrians captured the ten tribes under Shalmaneser, and the Chaldeans took two tribes under Nebuchadnezzar, burning Jerusalem and destroying the temple.
The third and fourth horses, variegated and white, are thought to be the Medes and the Persians.
Some of these were merciful, like Cyrus, Darius, and Ahasuerus, while others were cruel, like Cambyses.
And I said, "What are these, my lord?" And the angel who spoke to me said, "I will show you what these are." The man who stood among the myrtle trees answered and said, seeing horses of different colors, he asked what they were. For he knew that something else was signified by the appearance of the horses. Then the angel who spoke in him promised to explain. But while he remained silent, the man who stood among the myrtle trees explained what he had asked: "These are the ones whom the Lord has sent to walk throughout the earth and to subject it to his power." And they answered the angel of the Lord, who stood among the myrtle trees. The angels who presided over the individual kingdoms came to the man who stood among the myrtle trees, or to the angel. They said, "We have walked throughout the earth, and behold, all the earth is inhabited and at rest." As if to say: "All your kingdoms are peaceful, and none are oppressed by distress."
And the angel of the Lord responded and said, "Lord of hosts, how long will you not have mercy on Jerusalem and the cities of Judah, against which you have been angry? This is now the seventieth year." From this response, the angel who interceded for Israel took the opportunity to plead with the Lord for the people and said, "O Lord, when all the earth is securely inhabited, why do you not have mercy on Jerusalem and the cities of Judah, especially since according to your promises the time of captivity has been completed?" And the Lord answered the angel who spoke to me with good words, promising things to come; comforting words, addressing present needs. This according to the letter.
Allegorically, the man who rides a red horse is the Lord and Savior.
The red horse represents the mortality of our flesh that He took on for us.
As it is said through Isaiah:
"Why are your garments red?"
It's noteworthy that the one described here as sitting on the red horse appeared in the Revelation of John wearing a white robe and sitting on a white horse. He was red in His passion but white in His resurrection. Hence, the Church in the Song of Songs says,
"My beloved is white and ruddy."
The myrtle trees in the depths, among which the man is described as standing, represent the angelic powers who also assisted and ministered to Him when He was in the flesh. By the red, speckled, and white horses, we should understand the apostles and apostolic men who traveled throughout the world preaching. Some of them are red because they were crowned with martyrdom. Others are speckled because they were distinguished by their teachings, works, and the diversity of signs. Others are white because they were renowned for the purity of their virginity, the integrity of their faith, and the purity of their hearts. These were sent by the Lord to fill the whole world with the preaching of the gospel. Hence, the Lord says to Job:
"Can you send out lightnings, that they may go, and say to you, 'Here we are'?"
The man stood among the myrtle trees, or as another translation says, among the mountains, meaning Christ distinguishing between the people of both callings: those to be saved and those to be damned. Hence the Apostle:
"We are the pleasing aroma of Christ among those who are being saved and those who are perishing."
That the angel asks God to have mercy on the people because it was already the seventieth year signifies that Jerusalem, meaning the Church, will not achieve perfect freedom until the true Sabbath, meaning rest, is fulfilled, which the seventieth year represents. This number is completed by multiplying ten by seven. This peace begins in the present when we rest from the wars of vices and will be perfected in the future when we reach the vision of the Creator.
And the angel speaking with me said: Cry out, saying: This is what the Lord of Hosts says:
I am very jealous for Jerusalem and Zion, and I am very angry with the wealthy nations, because I was a little angry, but they added to the harm.
These were the good and comforting words that the Lord previously answered.
Here, the prophet is commanded to cry out:
I am jealous for Jerusalem not just a little, but with great zeal.
This zeal is taken for fury and indignation.
And because Jerusalem and Zion, being one, had committed great sins, they incurred the great wrath of God.
But now, He says, I will be very angry with the wealthy nations, who rest in long peace and overflow with all good things, whom the red, variegated, and white horses above represented.
He also explains the reason for such great wrath, saying: Because I was a little angry, but they added to the harm.
For God handed the Jews over to the nations for correction, like a son to a tutor, but they showed no mercy; instead, they raged against them with all cruelty.
Therefore, this is what the Lord says: I will return to Jerusalem with mercy, and my house will be built in it, says the Lord of Hosts.
Under Zerubbabel and Jesus, the measuring line, that is the line of the masons, will be stretched over Jerusalem.
Spiritually, Jerusalem is the Church, seeing peace and concord; it is also Zion, which turns into a watchtower, contemplating not humble or earthly things, but heavenly things.
If it sins, or if its charity cools, the Lord hands it over to persecutors for purification, like gold or silver in the furnace.
The adversaries, to whom it is handed over for testing, add to the harm, because they use cruelty instead of discipline.
Therefore, He threatens them with wrath but promises peace and mercy to His Church, and says that the measuring line or cord will be extended in it, meaning He distributes the measures and orders of each member of the Church in their places and times according to the quality of their merits.
Cry out again, saying: This is what the Lord of Hosts says.
My cities will once again overflow with good things, and the Lord will comfort Zion and choose Jerusalem once again.
The prophet is commanded to cry out, not with a loud voice, but with the intention of the mind.
He says, "My cities, which you now see burned by the fire of the Chaldeans, will once again be filled with all good things, so that the present happiness will console the past misery."
But also, mystically, good things are promised to the Church, of which the Psalmist says: "I believe that I shall see the goodness of the Lord in the land of the living."
And I lifted my eyes and saw, and behold, four horns. And I said to the angel who spoke with me, "What are these?" And he said to me, "These are the horns that scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem."
The four horns that scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem, the Lord himself explains as four nations, saying: "These are the horns," etc. Daniel also, under the figure of a lioness, a leopard, a bear, and another beast, which he does not name specifically, clearly describes four kingdoms: the Babylonians, the Medes, the Persians, and the Romans.
In sacred Scripture, it is very common to use horns to signify the power of a kingdom, as in "He will exalt the horn of His anointed." Also, "He has raised up a horn of salvation for us." These horns scattered or dispersed Judah. For the Jews suffered many evils from these nations, especially from Antiochus, surnamed Epiphanes, which means "the manifest one," because he wanted to be called a god.
Ultimately, the Romans devastated them with such a great slaughter that they almost dispersed them man by man, so that no one of them could lift their head, pressed down by the heavy burden of their adversities.
And the Lord showed me four craftsmen, and I said, "What are these coming to do?" He said, "These are the horns that scattered Judah man by man, so that no one could lift their head, and these have come to terrify them, to cast down the horns of the nations that lifted up a horn against the land of Judah to scatter it."
Who are the craftsmen, and what is their purpose? The Lord Himself explains it.
The prophet didn’t see them directly; the Lord revealed them to him.
These craftsmen are understood to be angels following God's command, coming to rebuild what the nations had destroyed.
The angels came to blunt the horns, meaning to dull them so they could no longer oppress Judah.
Some manuscripts say "to terrify them," meaning to instill fear in the horns, making them abandon cruelty and submit to Christ.
Notice he says "they lifted up a horn" in the singular, even though he mentioned four horns earlier. This is because, although the kings of the four kingdoms didn’t reign simultaneously but succeeded one another, they collectively lifted up one horn against the people of God. When the prophet said he lifted his eyes to see what was shown to him, it indicates a spiritual understanding, as the Lord says in the Gospel: "Lift up your eyes and see who created these things." The four horns represent spiritual evils and opposing forces that severely persecute the Church.
The Apostle says, "We do not wrestle against flesh and blood, but against principalities and powers, against the rulers of the darkness of this world." The Psalmist describes these four horns as beasts, addressing a holy man: "You will tread on the asp and the basilisk, and you will trample the lion and the dragon." The devil, when he rages against the chosen, is like an asp because he strikes secretly, a basilisk because he sometimes spreads open poison of envy, a lion because he persecutes the innocent, and a dragon because he devours those he can with impious voracity.
The four horns can also be seen as four disturbances of the mind: two from perceived goods and two from perceived evils—namely joy and hope, fear and sorrow. Against these passions, there are four virtues of good craftsmen: prudence, justice, fortitude, and temperance. These good craftsmen rebuild whatever those horns destroy.
But the saints who possess these virtues are spiritual builders.
For the Apostle says about himself, "As a wise architect, I laid the foundation," and the Lord himself, the creator of all, is called the son of a carpenter.
Chapter Two
And I lifted my eyes and saw, and behold, a man with a measuring line in his hand.
And I asked, "Where are you going?" He replied, "To measure Jerusalem, to see how wide and how long it is."
Prophetic Scripture always follows sorrow with joy. The one who first lifted his eyes to see sorrow now lifts his eyes again to see the man measuring Jerusalem.
This is the man of whom it is written: "Behold, a man whose name is Branch;" he is described in the book of Ezekiel.
Holding a measuring line and a reed in his hand, he measures the city of God, Jerusalem, whose architect and builder is God.
This is the holy Church, the mother of saints, which began to be built in the passion and resurrection of the Lord, and is built daily to grow in the increase of faith.
The one who holds the measuring line and the reed measures because he dispenses the measures and merits of each person.
He also sees how wide the charity is in each person, and how long their hope and patience are.
And behold, the angel who spoke with me was going out, and another angel was coming to meet him.
He said to him, "Run, speak to this young man, saying: 'Jerusalem will be inhabited without walls because of the multitude of people and animals in it.'"
The Hebrews understand the angel who spoke in the prophet as Michael; they believe the angel who met him to be Gabriel. Gabriel joyfully tells him to run and speak to the prophet about the great abundance that Jerusalem will have. Though it seemed destroyed to ashes, it will be without walls because of the multitude of people and animals, and the multitude of peace.
A little later, it is explained why it will be without walls: 'And I will be to her,' says the Lord, 'a wall of fire around her; and I will be the glory in her midst.'
These things can also be said spiritually about the Church, which is the city of God, about which the Psalmist said, "Glorious things are spoken of you, city of God."
This city is without a wall, not needing mortal protection, because the Lord is a wall of fire around it, and He is in its midst in glory.
This city has people and animals, representing both kinds of people.
The Jewish people, who lived according to the law and used reason, having the knowledge of God, are designated as people.
The Gentiles, who did not know God, are rightly called animals.
Some understand "people" to refer to the wise and learned, and "animals" to the simple ones in the Church, as the Psalmist says, "You save both people and animals, Lord."
Therefore, the Lord is a wall of fire around the Church, warming it with the fire of love and making it fervent with the Spirit. He is in its midst in glory, glorifying it with His presence and defending it from adversaries like a wall of fire.
O, flee from the land of the north, says the Lord, for I have scattered you to the four winds of heaven, says the Lord.
O Zion, flee, you who live with the daughter of Babylon.
The Assyrians and Chaldeans, who had captured God's people, are in the northern region. The prophet Jeremiah, when describing a boiling pot facing from the north, immediately added: From the north, disaster will be poured out on all the people of the land.
Therefore, the prophet urges, and not just once but repeatedly warns, calling for them to flee from the land of the north, where they still largely remained, and return to their own places.
Spiritually, it is commanded to us that those of us who lived in the north, in the coldest wind, in a time of unbelief, without the warmth of divine heat, and involved in the confusion of vices, should flee to Zion, the Church of the Lord. We should leave behind earthly and lowly things, ascend to the height of contemplation, and stand in the loftiness of spiritual teachings.
Because this is what the Lord of hosts says: after glory, He sent me to the nations that plundered you.
The voice of the Lord is the Savior's, and He says that He was sent by God the Father, not because He is almighty and equal to the Father, but because He is human and lesser than the Father.
Therefore, He also says that He was sent after the glory He had when He was with the Father, even though He never left the Father.
Hence, He says to the Father, "Glorify me, Father, with the glory I had with you before the world existed." And the Apostle says, "Who, being in the form of God, did not consider it robbery to be equal with God."
The Son of God was sent after the glory of divine majesty to the nations that had plundered God's people, so they would become prey to those they had previously plundered. For whoever touches you touches the apple of my eye. We should understand "touched" as vexation and injury, according to the saying, "Do not touch my anointed ones." For the saints are like the eyes of God, to whom it is said, "You are the light of the world." Whoever harms them, it is as if they touch the apple of God's eye and wish to deprive Him of clear sight.
Because, behold, I raise my hand over them, and they will be plundered by those who served them, and you will know that the Lord of hosts has sent me. And the Lord raised His hand then to strike the nations and bring His people back to Zion. He raises His power daily to call His people (that is, Christians) back to the Church through repentance, having struck down the adversaries, that is, spiritual enemies, who do not cease to attack Him.
Rejoice and be glad, daughter of Zion, for behold, I come and will dwell in your midst, says the Lord.
And many nations will be joined to the Lord on that day, and they will be my people, and I will dwell in your midst, and you will know that the Lord of hosts has sent me to you.
And the Lord will possess Judah as His portion in the holy land, and will again choose Jerusalem.
The Lord Himself still speaks and encourages the people liberated from captivity to rejoice and be glad.
However, the Church, also known as the daughter of Zion, which represents the heavenly city consisting of angels and holy men, is commanded to rejoice because they have been freed from the slavery of the devil.
Their Lord dwells among them, and many nations will believe in Him, as He said when He was about to leave the apostles bodily:
"Behold, I am with you always, even to the end of the age."
He also promises that He will possess Judah, meaning the people who confess Him, and He will be their portion in the sanctified land, which is the Church. He will still choose Jerusalem, those who seemed to be rejected during persecutions. Let all flesh be silent before the Lord, for He has risen from His holy dwelling.
Therefore, since the Lord will possess Judah as His portion and will choose Jerusalem, let all flesh—all mankind—be silent, fear, and stand in awe of His coming, for He has risen for vengeance, to render to each according to their deeds. God is said to rise when He is stirred to vengeance. But all flesh, meaning every human being, not mute animals, should be understood as:
"To you all flesh will come," meaning every human being.
Chapter Three
And the Lord showed me the high priest Joshua standing before the angel of the Lord, while Satan stood at his right hand to oppose him.
The Hebrews interpret the high priest Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, literally in this context.
Satan, meaning his adversary the devil, stood at his right hand to accuse him.
He stood at his right hand because he had a valid accusation against Joshua, who, like others, had taken a foreign wife.
And the Lord said to Satan: "The Lord rebuke you, Satan! The Lord who has chosen Jerusalem rebuke you!"
The Lord says this twice to hint at the Father and the Son, as it is written elsewhere, The Lord rained fire and sulfur from the Lord out of heaven on Sodom.
Surely this is a brand plucked from the fire.
The meaning is that since the Lord has chosen Jerusalem from all the cities of Judah, He does not count its sins against it.
So why are you trying to overwhelm Joshua with accusations, who has survived the Babylonian captivity as a half-burnt brand?
A half-burnt brand is a piece of wood commonly called a cinder.
And Joshua was dressed in filthy clothes and stood before the angel.
He wore filthy clothes for one of three reasons: either because he had taken a foreign wife, because of the people's sins for which he was responsible as a priest, or because of the filth of captivity.
And he answered and said to those standing before him.
The angel before whom Joshua stood commanded the other angels on behalf of the Lord, saying: "Take away the filthy garments from him."
And when they had carried out the command, the angel said to Joshua: "See, I have removed your iniquity from you."
This shows what the filthy garments were, and I will clothe you with festive robes, meaning I have joined an Israelite wife to you.
The Septuagint translated 'festive robes' as a long tunic reaching to the feet.
And he said, with the angel understood: "Put a clean turban or mitre on his head."
And they put a clean turban on his head and clothed him with garments.
Through the mitre, which is the priestly cap, the dignity of the priesthood is symbolized.
This signifies that once the stains of sins are removed, the priesthood becomes pure.
Mystically, Jesus is the great priest to whom it is said, You are a priest forever.
The Lord revealed him to the prophet because he cannot be seen by himself.
He stood before the angel of the Lord, meaning he is the mediator between God and humans.
He stands before the angel, and in doing so, he stands before himself.
In Christ, there are the different natures of God and human in one person.
He was dressed in dirty clothes because he carried our sins.
Satan stood at his right side as he willingly faced temptation from the devil, who wanted to test if he was truly the Son of God, especially after seeing him hungry from fasting.
What follows: May the Lord rebuke you, Satan, is said by the Son to the Father.
This is not because he himself couldn't rebuke Satan, but because of the unity of their nature.
When one rebukes, it is understood that the other also rebukes.
For God the Father and the Son share the same substance, even though one is the Father and the other is the Son.
He chose Jerusalem, symbolizing the Church.
The brand plucked from the fire represents Christ in his humanity, who, in the confusion of the world, was not burned by the flame of any sin, just as the bush was not consumed by the fire.
Jesus wore dirty clothes because he, who did not sin, took on our sins as a sacrifice.
He carried our weaknesses, and these dirty clothes were removed when he erased our sins.
This is why he was dressed in dirty clothes, so that we could receive pure garments in baptism, and it would be said to us, now cleansed: May your clothes always be white.
The clean mitre on his head signifies the splendor of his divine majesty.
For the head of Christ is God.
He is both God and human, so the clothing represents humanity, and the mitre represents the clarity of divine majesty.
And the angel of the Lord stood and addressed Jesus, saying:
"Thus says the Lord of Hosts: If you walk in my ways and keep my commandments, you will also judge my house and guard my courts."
According to Hebrew tradition, the angel speaking to Jesus does so after he was stripped of dirty clothes and dressed in clean garments.
These things are quite clear by themselves and do not need explanation.
However, interpreting this spiritually is more challenging.
If what is said to Jesus, the son of Josedech, is, "If you walk in my ways and keep my commandments," it is well known that Christ and the Church are the head and the members.
Therefore, let's understand this as applying to the members, for what is said to him is certainly said to his members.
Thus, it is promised to his members that if they walk in the ways of the Lord and keep his commandments, that is, his precepts, they will judge his house, which is the Church.
About which the Apostle says, "Christ is like a son over his own house, which house we are."
Similarly, to Timothy, "So that you may know how one ought to behave in the house of God, which is the Church of the living God, the pillar and foundation of the truth."
Therefore, Jesus judges the house of God according to the merits and words of each individual, appointing one over ten cities, another over five, making some teachers, some pastors, giving to some the power to perform miracles, making some the eyes in his body, others the hands, others the feet.
And I will give you those who walk among these who now stand here.
The Lord gave to his Son ministers from among the angels because he made his saints, still in the flesh, similar to angels.
Hence the Apostle said: "Our citizenship is in heaven."
For the virgins, the company of angels is promised, with the Lord saying: "They will neither marry nor be given in marriage, but will be like the angels of God in heaven."
He promises to reward those who assist because they remain unwavering, stable, and constant in the Church of God, just like the apostles who stood firm with the Lord.
These individuals are worthy of becoming companions of angelic dignity.
Listen, great priest Joshua, you and your friends who stand before you, for they are men who are a sign.
Behold, I will bring my servant, the branch.
Here, we take Joshua literally, the son of Josedech, to whom the coming of the Son of God is promised.
Previously, we mentioned that this priest Joshua was a type of Christ.
Now, we take him literally.
Let's see what the angel, speaking on behalf of God, says to Joshua: Listen, great priest Joshua, you and your friends, that is, the other prophets.
Joshua was also a prophet because he foreshadowed Christ not just by words, but by name and actions.
A prophet is not only someone who foretells Christ by words but also someone who signifies Him through figures and symbols.
Therefore, Joshua is commanded to listen, and his friends, the other prophets, are also commanded to listen.
It is said: Behold, I will bring my servant, the branch.
Behold the stone that I have laid before Joshua, on one stone are seven eyes.
These men are to be heard because they are a sign of things to come.
They are called portending because they announce future events far in advance.
Behold, he says, I will bring my servant, the branch, the one of whom it is said: Behold, the man whose name is the branch; and elsewhere: But for you who fear my name, the sun of righteousness will rise.
Also in the Gospel: The sunrise from on high has visited us to shine on those who sit in darkness and the shadow of death.
The prophet calls him my servant, taking on the form of a servant, as it is said: Behold my servant, I will uphold him.
He is also the stone laid before Joshua, announced and promised by the prophets.
This is the cornerstone that joined two walls coming from different directions, rejected by men but chosen and honored by God.
On this stone, there are seven eyes, representing the seven gifts of the Holy Spirit that rest on Christ, as the prophet Isaiah lists:
"The Spirit of the Lord will rest on him—the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and might, the spirit of knowledge and piety, and he will be filled with the spirit of the fear of the Lord."
"Behold, I will engrave its inscription," says the Lord of hosts, "and I will remove the iniquity of that land in one day."
Since he previously mentioned the stone, he continues the metaphor by saying, "Behold, I will engrave its inscription," referring to the stone's engraving. This prophecy clearly points to the Lord's passion. The engraving of the stone symbolizes the wounds he received on the cross. "I will engrave its inscription," he says, meaning he will be wounded by nails and a spear. This is what God the Father did when he gave him up for death for all of us.
Then the iniquity of that land will be forgiven. Through his passion, iniquity was forgiven, and justice was restored in one day, about which the Psalmist says, "This is the day the Lord has made."
On that day, says the Lord of hosts, a man will call his friend under the vine and under the fig tree.
From the time of Christ's passion, the Gospel began to be proclaimed. An apostolic and perfect man, who can now ascend to higher things, calls his friends—believers, or certainly the Gentiles—under the vine, meaning Christ, who says in the Gospel, "I am the true vine, whose fruit gladdens the heart of man." And under the fig tree, representing the glory of the Holy Spirit, whose fruits are the sweetest, so that under such a shade they may rest in eternal peace.
The prophet Micah also foretold this in almost the same words: "On that day," he says, "each one will call his neighbor and brother under the fig tree and the vine, and there will be no one to make them afraid."
Chapter Four
And the angel who was speaking with me returned and woke me up, like a man who is awakened from his sleep.
What does it mean when it says: The angel returned?
Where had he gone who was speaking in the prophet?
It should be understood that when human frailty is left to its own weakness, God is absent from man with the help of angels.
Therefore, the prophet, astonished by the great vision, was dazed and, as if in a mental stupor, could not see the true light.
Hence, the angel who had left him for a moment and seemed to have departed from him, returned and woke him up so he could see what he could not see before with the eyes of his heart closed.
We can also take the prophet’s sleep in a good sense, according to what Solomon says: If you sleep, you will not be afraid; you will rest, and your sleep will be sweet.
Therefore, he who sleeps from the cares and disruptions of the world and can say with the bridegroom: I sleep, but my heart is awake, deserves to be awakened by the angel and to enjoy an angelic vision and conversation.
And he said to me: What do you see?
And I said: I saw, and behold, a whole golden lampstand, and its lamp on top of it, and its seven lamps on it, and seven pipes to the lamps, which were on top of it, and two olive trees by it, one on the right side of the lamp and one on the left side of it.
And I answered and said to the angel who was speaking with me, "What are these, my lord?" And the angel who was speaking with me answered and said to me: Do you not know what these are? And I said: "No, my lord."
And he answered and said to me: In this place, the Hebrew tradition is as follows: The whole lampstand made of solid gold represents the law; the lamp, that is, the flame shining at the top of the lampstand, represents Christ, who is the head of the law, and who enlightens the whole world; the seven lamps on the lampstand represent the seven gifts of the Holy Spirit as previously listed.
These lamps on the candlestick are there because the law was written under the guidance of the Holy Spirit.
The seven reservoirs, which are the small vessels containing the oil that is poured into the lamps, shine on the candlestick.
They signify that these seven graces come down to humans from heaven through the law.
The two olive trees on the candlestick, one on the right and one on the left, with the middle lamp shining between them, represent the law and the prophecy.
When the prophet described the vision to the angel, he asked the angel what the vision meant.
The angel responded: Do you not know what these are?
When he replied, I do not know, the angel explained: This is the word of the Lord to Zerubbabel, saying: Not by might, nor by power, but by my spirit, says the Lord of hosts.
The people were brought back from captivity and will be brought back more fully, and their adversaries will be devastated.
Who are you, O great mountain?
Before Zerubbabel, you will become a plain.
The people of the Jews, who did not want them to prosper and rebuild the temple, will be leveled, and their pride will be brought down, humbled under the feet of Israel.
He will bring forth the cornerstone, that is Christ, who has always been a help to the people of Israel from ages past.
He will match grace with grace, that is the stone.
This clearly means: He brought out his grace from captivity and will match this grace with the grace he showed to their fathers, extending similar mercy to these.
This is the tradition of the Hebrews.
But the church doctors explain this passage in this way: The entirely golden candlestick is the holy Church, which in the divine Scriptures seeks the sense more than the words.
The lamp on the candlestick designates the Lord Christ, who illuminates the Church, and who says of himself: No one lights a lamp and puts it under a bushel basket, that is, under the measure of the law, but on a candlestick, that is, in the freedom of the Gospel, by which the Church is enlightened.
Seven lamps and their pourers symbolize the grace of the Holy Spirit, through which the Church receives the oil of divine mercy and all virtues.
The two olive trees are Moses and Elijah, who appeared on the mountain with the transfigured Lord and spoke of what He was to endure in Jerusalem.
Some interpret the two olive trees on the right and left as the Gospel and the law, with the olive tree on the right representing the Gospel and the one on the left representing the law.
The great mountain before Zerubbabel represents the devil or the Antichrist, who rose up against Zerubbabel, from whom Christ was to be born.
To Christ Himself in the Gospel, when shown the kingdoms and honors of the world, the devil dared to say, "All this I will give you, if you fall down and worship me."
And the Lord Himself calls the devil a mountain in the Gospel, saying, "If you have faith the size of a mustard seed, you will say to this mountain, 'Move from here,' and it will move."
This pride must be leveled and humbled to the dust.
The cornerstone is the one about whom John wrote: "In the beginning was the Word."
What follows, "grace for grace," is explained by the Apostle: "We have all received from His fullness, grace upon grace," the grace of the Gospel for the grace of the law, so that both the believers from Israel and the Gentiles coming to faith receive equal glory.
Hence, John says, "The law was given through Moses; grace and truth came through Jesus Christ."
And the word of the Lord came to me, saying: "The hands of Zerubbabel have laid the foundation of this house, and his hands shall complete it."
Then you will know that the Lord of hosts has sent me to you.
Anyone who reads the prophet Ezra will find that the temple was indeed founded by Zerubbabel and brought to its highest pinnacles.
For who has despised the day of small things?
This is taken to mean the royal power, which at that time Zerubbabel's adversaries despised and considered insignificant.
He advises Zerubbabel and Jeshua, along with all the people building, not to fear their adversaries who try to stop them from building, but rather to listen to the Lord, who encourages them and promises His help.
It follows: And they will rejoice, meaning that despite the contempt of a few days, they will be filled with greater joy.
This can be understood as: It is rare for someone to despise the short days of this age because many people delight in this world so much that, if they could, they would always want to live here.
Therefore, when we see the lovers of this world shining in gold, adorned with purple and gems, surrounded by the services of attendants, we can take this and say: Who has despised the small days?
For all the days of the present life are short, no matter how long they may extend.
Hence, Jacob said: My days are few and evil.
And they will see the stone of tin in the hand of Zerubbabel.
These seven are the eyes of the Lord, which range throughout the whole earth, that is, the help of the Savior, who is born from the lineage of Zerubbabel.
The stone is called so because of its unsurpassable strength.
But why is it called the stone of tin?
They say the nature of tin is to protect other metals from fire.
For although copper, iron, and other metals are naturally harder, if they are put into the furnace without tin, they burn.
Similarly, the strength of angels and humans is fragile and weak if it does not have divine help.
Therefore, the stone of tin is called Christ because just as tin separates mixed and adulterated metals, so does the Lord Savior, of whom the prophet says, He will sit refining and purifying silver, separating the silver and gold of good works from the bronze and lead of vices, so that pure gold and silver remain.
And I answered and said to him: What are these two olive trees on the right and the left of the lampstand?
And I answered again and said to him: What are these two olive branches beside the two gold spouts from which the golden oil pours?
And he said to me: Do you not know what these are?
And I said, No, my lord.
And he said to me: These are the two sons of oil, of splendor, who stand by the Lord of all the earth.
The prophet asks about the meaning of the two olive trees on the right and left of the lampstand.
But the angel, speaking on behalf of the Lord, did not answer him.
This could be because the prophet had previously heard about the olive trees and did not remember, or perhaps he sought knowledge beyond his understanding.
The angel's silence serves as a rebuke.
According to the Hebrews, the angel did not respond because the prophet did not ask the right questions or seek all that he should have.
He inquired about the olive trees but did not ask about their ears, golden beaks, or infusers.
The ears of the olive trees refer to the trees themselves, using a metaphor, as they stand straight like ears of grain.
Just as ears are surrounded by bristles, these trees rise straight up, forming a barrier of branches and leaves.
Some interpret the two ears of olive trees as the two Testaments, the Gospel, and the Law, calling them the sons of splendor who stand by the Lord of all flesh.
Others see them as representing the priesthood and the Law, or Elijah and Enoch—one pleasing God in uncircumcision, the other in circumcision.
Chapter Five
I turned and lifted my eyes and saw a flying scroll.
And he said to me, "What do you see?"
And I said, "I see a flying scroll. Its length is 20 cubits and its width is 10 cubits."
And he said to me, "This is the curse that goes out over the face of the whole earth."
The prophet turned from one vision to another, shifting from joyful and prosperous visions to sad ones, lifting the eyes of his mind.
So that his heart would not be lifted up, since he was announcing all things happy and full of joy, he also sees those that are sad.
Therefore, he sees a flying scroll, on which the deeds of all are written.
This scroll represents the nature of both Testaments.
By the 20 cubits of length, the Gospel is represented; by the 10 cubits of width, the Decalogue of the law is understood.
Twenty to ten is double to single, because in the Decalogues, the sins of deeds are forbidden, but in the Gospel, the sins of thoughts are cut off.
For example: the law prohibits murder, the Gospel prohibits anger;
adultery is condemned in the law, in the Gospel, lust is punished, because whoever looks at a woman to lust after her, etc.
In the law, robbery makes one guilty, in the Gospel, greed subjects one to the flames of hell.
The seventy translators for the scroll said "sickle," having the same measure of length and width. This sickle signifies the severity of divine judgment:
just as a sickle encompasses all around its circuit outwardly and cuts inwardly, so the power of divine judgment encompasses all outwardly and separates and discerns inwardly, judging deeds and thoughts.
Because every thief, as it is written there, will be judged, and everyone who swears falsely by my name will be judged likewise.
"I will bring it forth," says the Lord of hosts, "and it will enter the house of the thief, and the house of the one who swears falsely by my name,
and it will remain in the midst of his house and consume it, with its timber and stones."
Many people think theft and perjury are minor or insignificant crimes.
They don't realize that the curse of this book is said to come to the house of the thief and the one who falsely swears in the name of the Lord.
This curse consumes both the wood and the stones, representing the severe and serious sins of that person.
So, what will happen with even graver sins, such as murder, adultery, and other works of the flesh, if theft and perjury are punished with such a severe penalty?
And the angel who spoke with me went out and said to me, “Lift your eyes and see what is going out.
” I asked, “What is it?
” And he replied, “This is a basket going out.
” The angel who spoke to the prophet went out to show him another vision.
He commanded him to lift his eyes to behold great things and see the basket, which signifies that the measure of the sins of the people of Israel is complete and full.
The basket, called an ephah or ephi in Hebrew, represents the fullness of sins.
The angel also names the basket, saying, “This is their eye in all the land,” meaning the manifestation of all sins.
When the measure of sins is full, as the Lord says to the Jews, “Fill up the measure of your fathers,” and in Genesis: “The sins of the Amorites are not yet complete,” it means there is an eye, representing the manifestation and just vengeance of God’s wrath.
Likewise, the sins of that people had been hidden when they were not yet complete.
But now that they were complete, they were revealed to all and shown to all nations, showing how they had been in their land.
And behold, a talent of lead was being carried, and a woman was sitting in the middle of the basket.
The angel said, “This is wickedness.
” He threw her into the middle of the basket and placed the lead weight on its mouth.
As the angel explained, it was called wickedness, meaning idolatry and the denial of God.
The talent of lead signifies a heavy mass.
It was carried either by its own force through the air or by the command of God.
This talent or mass of lead represents the very heavy weight of sins by which those people were oppressed.
The angel of the Lord then threw the seized woman into the middle of a jar, so that in the fullness of her sins, she would be carried to Babylon.
As stated, she was taken there to be oppressed by the weight of captivity.
Because she gloried in her crime, the angel put a talent, or mass, of lead into her mouth—that is, the jar—to seal her wickedness.
With her mouth closed, she would no longer boast of her crime but would fall silent in eternal silence.
And I lifted my eyes and saw, and behold, two women coming out, and the wind was in their wings.
These two women represent the ten tribes called Israel and the two called Judah.
The ten tribes were captured by the Assyrians, and the two by the Chaldeans.
The spirit in their wings symbolizes the powers of the devil, who is called an unclean spirit in the Gospel, and about whom Solomon said: "If the spirit of the ruler rises against you, do not leave your place." So, by this spirit, like the breath of the wind, these women were carried swiftly to all wickedness.
They had wings like the wings of a kite, a very predatory bird, always preying on domestic birds. This bird aptly represents these women of Judah and Israel, who, due to their excessive sins, were handed over to the power of demons and led into captivity by them. They lifted the jar, in which was wickedness, and the mass of lead enclosed, between the earth and the heaven. And I said to the angel who spoke to me.
The prophet no longer asks who these women are, for he knew by prophetic spirit, nor what they carry, because he had learned from the angel, but where they carry it, saying: "Where are they taking the jar?" And he said to me.
The angel replied: "To build a house for it in the land of Shinar, and to establish it, and place it there upon its base." Shinar is the plain of the Chaldeans, where after the flood, the sons of Adam tried to build the tower of pride, but the Lord confused the language which was one for all. Hence, the city itself was called Babylon, that is, confusion.
An amphora filled with wickedness was being carried to Babylon to be placed on a base, a stable seat, where it would remain forever.
Sennaar means the shaking of teeth or their stench.
So, this amphora of wickedness is taken to the land of Sennaar, where a permanent place is prepared for it.
The devil, the author of wickedness, resides in the hearts of the reprobate, those possessed by wickedness or the stench of lust.
The name Sennaar, meaning the shaking of teeth, indicates that the reprobate have lost and ruined teeth.
These teeth should have been used to grind the words of God, meaning to meditate on them.
They perish because they don't internalize the divine words into their memory.
In a spiritual sense, these two women represent heretics and Jews, who turn away from the Lord and are led by an uncertain spirit of error, enjoying quarrels and disputes.
They bear the weight of wickedness, and in Babylon, which symbolizes confusion, they build a home for themselves.
Chapter Six
I turned, looked up, and saw four chariots coming out from between two mountains, and the mountains were made of bronze.
The first chariot had red horses, the second chariot had black horses, the third chariot had white horses, and the fourth chariot had dappled, strong horses.
I asked the angel who was speaking to me, "What are these, my lord?" The angel answered me and said,
The prophet shifts to another vision and looks deeper into his heart to see four chariots emerging from between two very strong bronze mountains that cannot be worn out by time. In the second chariot, the black horses represent the deadly kings of Persia and Media because of Ahasuerus, who, during his reign, at Haman's request, condemned all the Jewish people to death by public decree.
In the third chariot, the white horses represent the Macedonians, under whose king Antiochus, the victory of the Maccabees is described.
In the fourth chariot, the strong dappled horses represent the Roman kings. They are dappled because some were kind to the Jews, like Claudius, while others persecuted them, like Caligula, Nero, and Vespasian.
When the prophet asked what these visions meant, the angel replied, "These are the four winds of heaven, meaning the regions or directions, which go out to stand before the Lord of all the earth. The kingdoms of the earth can do nothing without God's permission and will."
The chariot with the black horses went to the northern land, the white ones followed them, and the dappled horses went to the southern land. The strongest ones set out and wanted to go and roam the earth. The angel said, "Go and patrol the earth," and they patrolled the earth.
Then he called me and spoke to me, saying,
Therefore, the prophet does not mention the first chariot with the red horses, because the Babylonian kingdom had already fallen, and the Medes and Persians ruled all of Asia. Under their king Darius, Zechariah saw all these things.
So, the chariot with black horses went out to the north, where, by the Lord's command, the empire of the Chaldeans would be destroyed.
White horses also followed, representing the Macedonians who, after the Medes, brought the Chaldean kingdoms under their own rule.
The fourth group, the strong and varied Romans, went out to the south and were instructed to traverse the entire land.
The power of the Romans expanded their empire to the four corners of the world.
Then the angel turned to the prophet and said, "Behold, those who are going to the land of the north have brought rest to My Spirit in the land of the north." He is referring to the third chariot with white horses, symbolizing the Macedonians, who also went to the north after the black horses. They brought rest to the Lord's Spirit in the land of the north by fulfilling God's vengeance and overthrowing the empire of the Medes.
For Alexander, the king of the Macedonians, killed Darius, the king of the Persians and Medes, and transferred his kingdom to the Macedonians. This brought rest to the prophetic Spirit, God's Spirit, in the land of the north because they executed God's vengeance on His people’s enemies and fulfilled His will in their destruction. It is a great consolation for those who are oppressed to know that their enemies will soon perish.
Some interpret the four chariots spiritually as the four Gospels, with the horses representing God's chosen ones, each possessing different graces in their diverse colors. Some are red, signifying martyrdom; some are black, darkened by the gloom of penance or those who penetrate the obscure mysteries of Christ. As it is written, "He made darkness His hiding place." Others are white, shining with the brightness of virginity or cleansed in baptism. Some are varied, strong, and possess the grace of various healings and virtues.
The saying, "Those who go out to the land of the north have made my spirit rest in the land of the north," means that through the preaching of the gospel, the people who were in the north—cold in unbelief and under the power of the devil, who said, "I will place my throne in the north"—believed, and the Spirit of the Lord rested upon them.
Then the word of the Lord came to me, saying: Take from the exiles, from Heldai, Tobiah, and Jedaiah, and on that day, go to the house of Josiah, son of Zephaniah, who came from Babylon. Take gold and silver and make crowns, placing them on the head of Joshua, son of Jehozadak, the high priest.
Speak to him, saying: This is what the Lord of Hosts says: Behold, the man whose name is the Branch. He shall branch out from his place and build the temple of the Lord.
The order of the words is a bit confusing, but it means: Take from Heldai, Tobiah, and Jedaiah, who came from Babylon, and from them, take the offerings of gold and silver. Enter the house of Josiah, son of Zephaniah, and there, make crowns adorned with gold and silver. Place one of them on Joshua, son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and say to him: Behold, the man whose name is the Branch. He shall branch out from his place, sprouting like a seedling.
This signifies Zerubbabel, who rose from a humble and captive status to become the leader of the people and built the temple of the Lord. As it says: And he shall build the temple of the Lord. He shall bear the glory, symbolized by the other crown. He shall sit and rule on his throne. There shall be a priest on his throne, and there shall be a council of peace between the two of them.
The crowns shall be for Heldai, Tobiah, Jedaiah, and Hen. Up to this point, it has been about Zerubbabel. Now it repeats again about Joshua the priest, whom it had previously mentioned.
But also, the high priest Jesus will sit on his throne, which is the priestly throne, and there will be peace between those two—between Zerubbabel, who was of royal lineage, and Jesus, who descended from the Levitical tribe—so that both the priesthood and the kingdom can jointly govern God’s people.
The crowns, after being placed on the heads of Jesus son of Jozadak and Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, will be consecrated in the temple in the names of those who offered them: Helem, Tobijah, Jedaiah, and Hen.
The son of Zephaniah will serve as a memorial in the temple of the Lord.
Those who are far off will come and build in the temple of the Lord, and you will know that the Lord of hosts has sent me to you.
This will happen if you diligently listen to the voice of the Lord your God.
Once the crowns are placed in the temple of the Lord and consecrated for eternal memory, people from all over the earth will come and build in the temple, and you will know that the Lord has sent me to you.
It should be noted that while three men were previously mentioned—Holdai, Tobiah, and Jedaiah—the first name has now been changed: instead of Holdai, Helem is mentioned.
Additionally, a fourth name has been added, which was not mentioned before: Hen.
Holdai means "the Lord's supplication," Tobiah means "the Lord's goodness," Jedaiah means "the Lord's knowledge," and Hen means "grace." Helem, which is used instead of Holdai, means "dream."
The Hebrews say that these three, Holdai, Tobiah, and Jedaiah, are the three young men—Hananiah, Azariah, and Mishael—who came from captivity and offered these gifts of gold and silver in the temple of the Lord. The fourth, which was not mentioned before, that is, Hen, they say is Daniel, who also came with a gift. They say Helem is used instead of Holdai because Helem means "dream," to show from the interpretation that Daniel and the three young men understood the mysteries of the royal dream in Babylon.
This Josiah, to whom the prophet is ordered to go and for whose sake the crowns are said to be by the Seventy translators—because they were kept with him—was the temple keeper, that is, the guardian of the Lord’s temple. This is according to the literal sense, as the Hebrew tradition holds.
Spiritually, the prophet is commanded to take gold and silver from the exile.
The exile of the Jewish people, those confessing God, represents the vices and sins.
When someone begins to abandon and repent for these sins and desires the homeland, the heavenly Jerusalem, they offer gold and silver in the temple of the Lord by understanding and speaking, confessing the Lord.
From this gold and silver, crowns are made in the temple of Josiah, who is interpreted as "saved," and is a son of the salvation of the Lord. The house is the Church, where the people are saved by the Lord, who is the son of the visitation of the Lord. The Lord visited those who were seriously ill, lying in the weakness of sins.
These crowns are placed on Jesus, son of Josedech, the high priest. This signifies that when we are freed from the captivity of the devil and progress through each of our virtues, the Lord is crowned, or rather, He receives the crowns in us. Rightly is he called the son of Josedech, which is interpreted as "the Lord of righteousness," meaning that God the Father of the Lord Savior will justly restore to each according to their merits. Hence, the Apostle confidently said: "The crown of righteousness is laid up for me," etc.
Therefore, the prophet is commanded that after placing the crowns on the head of Jesus, son of Josedech, the high priest, he should say to him: Behold the man whose name is the Branch. Christ, who is called Jesus, who saved the world, is now called the Branch because in his days righteousness arose.
And under him will arise, you understand, a multitude of believers. He will build the temple of the Lord, which is the Church. He will rule on his throne because when he comes to judgment, he will sit on the throne of his majesty. He will be a priest on his throne, because he himself is king and high priest, and he will sit on both the royal and priestly thrones.
And the counsel of peace will be between both of them, so that neither royal dignity may depress priestly dignity, nor priestly dignity royal dignity, but both may agree in the glory of one Lord Jesus.
Chapter Seven
In the fourth year of King Darius, the word of the Lord came to Zechariah on the fourth day of the ninth month, which is Kislev.
They sent Sarasar and Rogommelech, along with the men who were with them, to the house of God to seek the Lord's favor and to speak to the priests of the house of the Lord of hosts and the prophets.
The ninth month, which the Hebrews call Kislev, we call December.
On the fourth day of this month, they went to the temple of the Lord, which had already been restored.
They sent Zerubbabel and Joshua, along with Sarasar and Rogommelech, who (as the Hebrews believe) were Persian princes who feared the Lord.
Since they had heard that the temple was restored, they asked the priests and prophets whether they should continue to weep and fast as per their old custom or turn their mourning into joy and happiness.
They asked, "Should I weep in the fifth month?" In the fifth month, which the Romans call August, Jerusalem was destroyed by Nebuchadnezzar. For this reason, they had fasted until that time, consoling the desolation of the temple with mourning and sorrow. Now, seeing the temple rebuilt and no reason for sadness, they asked whether they should continue this practice. They questioned, "Should I sanctify myself as I have done for many years?" They called fasting a sanctification because, in fasting, they abstained from all pleasures and devoted themselves to good works and almsgiving. Therefore, the prophet also says, "Sanctify a fast." To sanctify a fast is to abstain from vices while performing other good deeds.
After the Persian princes asked through the envoys they sent, the word of the Lord came to the prophet, commanding him to speak to all the people. He also spoke to the priests about what they should respond. And the word of the Lord of hosts came to me, saying: "Speak to all the people of the land and to the priests, saying, 'When you fasted and mourned in the fifth and seventh months for these seventy years, did you fast for me?'"
In the fifth month, they fasted because that was when Jerusalem was destroyed by the Chaldeans.
In the seventh month, they fasted because that was when Gedaliah, appointed by the king of Babylon over the land, was killed, and the remaining people were scattered.
So the Lord says: What benefit was it to Me that you fasted and mourned for seventy years during the desolation of Jerusalem, when you were fasting for yourselves, not for Me?
And when you ate and drank at your festivals, wasn't it for yourselves that you ate and drank?
God is not pleased with these things, but with good deeds, in judgment, justice, and truth.
Food does not commend us to God.
Are these not the words that the Lord spoke through the earlier prophets, when Jerusalem was still inhabited and prosperous, both it and the surrounding cities, and when the Negev and the lowlands were still inhabited?
When He says, Jerusalem was still standing, abundant in all good things, and enjoyed perfect peace, the earlier prophets spoke these same words to you.
What those words were will be revealed in what follows.
And the word of the Lord came to Zechariah, saying, This is what the Lord of hosts says: Judge true judgment, and show mercy and compassion to each other.
Do not oppress the widow, the orphan, the foreigner, or the poor, and do not think evil in your hearts against each other.
But they refused to listen, turned their backs, and stopped their ears from hearing.
They made their hearts as hard as stone so they would not hear the law and the words that the Lord of hosts had sent by His Spirit through the earlier prophets.
Therefore, great wrath came from the Lord of hosts.
And just as He had spoken and they did not listen, so they will cry out, and I will not listen, says the Lord of hosts.
And I scattered them among all the nations they did not know, and the land was desolate after them, with no one passing through or returning, and they made the pleasant land desolate.
This pleases me more than fasting on the fifth and seventh months.
Because you did not do this, you were handed over to captivity and disgrace.
Show mercy and compassion.
Showing mercy means giving alms to the poor; showing compassion means forgiving debtors.
This is expressed in the prophet Isaiah as, "Break your bread for the hungry."
Behold mercy.
And a little further, "Loose the bonds of wickedness, undo the straps of the yoke."
Behold compassion.
The most correct order is that mercy follows judgment, especially for brothers whom either blood or the same faith connects us in affinity.
For what is said in the law, "You shall not show pity in judgment," means that during the act of judgment, pity is not to be shown, but to one convicted and confessing their guilt, mercy is to be extended.
The Lord also commanded concerning widows and orphans: "Be a father to the orphans and a husband to their mothers."
He also commanded not to oppress the stranger and the poor, for one is humbled by being a stranger, the other by poverty.
When the Lord commanded these and other things, they did the opposite, turned their backs to him, and retreated.
That is, they turned away their shoulders and hardened their ears, like deaf asps.
Therefore, for great sins, there was great indignation from God, and they were scattered through kingdoms they had not known before: Assyria, Media, and Persia.
The land that flowed with milk and honey was turned into a wasteland.
These things can also refer to those who, placed in the Church, are proud of their abundance of virtues, and do not give thanks to God their teacher.
Therefore, by the just judgment of God, they are allowed to be tempted by the devil and are taken captive under the law of sin.
Their land, that is, the soul once the dwelling place of the Trinity, is made desolate, abandoned by God the inhabitant.
Chapter Eight
And the word of the Lord of hosts came to me, saying:
Thus says the Lord of hosts: Speak about Jerusalem as a man speaks about an adulterous wife.
For God loved the people of Israel and joined them to Himself with pure love and the dowry of faith, as the prophet Ezekiel declares.
Later, having forsaken God, they committed adultery with the idols of various nations.
Because of this, they were handed over into captivity.
They repented, saying, "I will return to my former husband, because it was better for me then than now." Merciful God, receiving them and not counting their sins, says: "I have been zealous for Zion with great zeal, and with great anger, I have been zealous for her."
Thus says the Lord of hosts: "I have returned to Zion, and I will dwell in the midst of Jerusalem, and Jerusalem will be called the city of truth, and the mountain of the Lord of hosts, the holy mountain."
Because He says, "Zion, which is Jerusalem, has left me, followed many lovers, and has been disgraced by them. I have been zealous with great zeal according to the magnitude of the crimes. But she has returned to me, repenting, and I have returned to her with greater mercy. Build me a temple, and I will dwell in your midst, and the city will be called the city of truth, which was once called the city of lies. It was also called the holy mountain and the mountain of the Lord."
These things can spiritually refer to the soul, which ought to have been Jerusalem, that is, the vision of peace, and Zion, that is, the watchtower by contemplating God. When it sins, it is handed over to the power of the devil and subjected to the captivity of vices. But if it repents and seeks to appease the offended God, God will return to it, and it will be the holy mountain and the city of God. He will dwell in its midst, and it will be said to it: "Great is the Lord and greatly to be praised," etc.
Thus says the Lord of hosts: "Old men and old women will still dwell in the streets of Jerusalem, each man with his staff in his hand because of the multitude of days, and the streets of the city will be filled with boys and girls playing in its streets."
He says, "While I am living in Jerusalem, there will be so much prosperity and peace that no one will die young. People of both sexes will live to a ripe old age, supported by a staff due to their many years. The streets will also be filled with boys and girls playing."
Spiritually, the streets, called 'broad' because of their width, represent virtues in which the saints walk and act confidently. The Psalmist calls the commandment of God broad. In these streets, elderly men and women, accomplished in virtues, sit. Old age is indeed venerable. These streets will be filled with boys and girls, referring to those who receive the basic teachings of God's word. John says, "I write to you, young men, because your sins are forgiven for His name's sake," fulfilling what the Psalmist says, "Young men and maidens, etc."
This is what the Lord of hosts says: "If it seems difficult in the eyes of the remnant of this people in those days, will it be difficult in my eyes?" says the Lord of hosts. Because great and almost unbelievable things were promised to Israel, they might have doubted due to the magnitude of the promises. Therefore, the prophet now speaks in the person of the Lord. "If it seems difficult for you, O remnant of my people, what I am promising, will it be difficult for me who am omnipotent?"
In a similar manner, it seemed impossible to the saints during times of persecution, when the Church was afflicted in various ways, that peace would ever be granted to them. But now the kings of the world and princes have bowed their necks to Christ, and the emperor's knees bend before the tomb of the fisherman.
This is what the Lord of hosts says: "Behold, I will save my people from the land of the east and from the land of the west, and I will bring them, and they will dwell in the midst of Jerusalem. They will be my people, and I will be their God in truth and in righteousness."
These things were partially fulfilled under Zerubbabel and Joshua when God's people returned from captivity and lived in Jerusalem, and the Lord was called their God.
Now, they are more fully realized under the Lord Savior in the Church, which is the true Jerusalem, as people from all parts of the world come to faith, just as the Lord says in the Gospel:
"Many will come from the East and the West," etc.
The phrase "In truth and righteousness" signifies that with the passing of the shadow and figure of the law, the truth of the Gospel takes its place.
The Lord of hosts says:
Let your hands be strong, you who hear these words today from the mouths of the prophets, on the day the house of the Lord of hosts was founded, so that the temple may be built.
For now, they saw the temple being constructed as the prophets Haggai and Zechariah had predicted.
The Lord encourages the people to have faith in the promises for the future based on the truth of the former promises, and to strengthen their hands, not fearing those who wanted to hinder them from building.
Indeed, before those days, there was no payment for men or animals, and there was no peace for those coming or going because of tribulation.
I let everyone go, each against his neighbor. Before the temple of the Lord was founded and built, all their labor was in vain, and both men and animals were frustrated in agriculture and various works, with their efforts thwarted.
There was no peace for those coming or going, with internal strife and external adversaries disturbing them.
The same happened in the Church, because before the Lord's temple was spiritually founded in people, and before it was said to them:
"You are the temple of the living God," there was no reward for men, meaning those who are rational, or for irrational animals before God.
But after they converted and God began to dwell in them, they heard from the Apostle:
"Each will receive his own reward according to his labor."
Now, however, I will not do as in former days for the remnant of this people, says the Lord of hosts, but there will be a seed of peace.
The vineyard will yield its fruit, the earth will produce its crops, and the heavens will give their dew.
I will make the remnants of this people possess all these things.
When the temple was founded, I did not afflict this people as I did before.
Instead, I will give them peace and compensate for the past famine with future abundance.
Similarly, the virgins of the heretics, the abstinence of the philosophers, and the observance of the Jews have no reward.
This is because whatever good they do, they do not do it in the name of the Lord, nor do they build the house of the Lord within themselves.
However, once they turn to God, are freed from the captivity of the devil, and begin to build the temple of the Lord within themselves, a multitude of peace will arise in them.
The vineyard mentioned in the Gospel, I am the true vine, will yield its fruit, and the good earth will yield its fruit a hundredfold, sixtyfold, and thirtyfold.
The heavens will also give the dew of preaching, as it is written: The heavens declare the glory of God.
And it will be, as you were a curse among the nations, O house of Judah and house of Israel, so I will save you, and you will be a blessing.
Do not fear.
Let your hands be strong, for thus says the Lord of hosts: Just as I planned to afflict you when your fathers provoked me to anger, and I did not relent, so I have now turned and planned in these days to do good to Jerusalem and the house of Judah.
These are the open promises and consolations of the Lord who strengthens his people.
The house of Judah refers to the two tribes, Judah and Benjamin; the house of Israel refers to the other ten tribes, to all of whom he promises to show mercy.
This consolation can be referred to the Church afflicted by persecutions.
Those who are cast out of the Church and taken captive by the devil due to their sins, if they repent, will return to their former state.
They will see the peace of the Lord and possess the glory of their confession.
Do not fear.
These are the words you should do: Speak the truth, each one with his neighbor.
Judge truthfully and make fair decisions within your communities.
Do not harbor ill thoughts against your neighbor, for I have promised you good things, and my promise will stand.
Follow my command: speak the truth to your neighbor.
Let's consider everyone our neighbor because we all come from one origin.
If we are commanded to speak the truth only to our immediate neighbors, does that mean it's acceptable to lie to strangers and foreigners?
Judge truthfully and fairly in your communities, ensuring that truth and justice come first, followed by mercy.
The goal of judgment should be to reconcile discord.
Regarding "in your gates," it was customary for judges to sit at the city gates and resolve individual cases. That's why the Psalmist says about the righteous person: "He will not be put to shame when he speaks with his enemies at the gate," and the prophet says: "They hate the one who rebukes in the gate." Judges held court at the gate so that farmers wouldn't have to enter the city and incur a loss, and both city dwellers and country folk could hear the judges' decisions and then return to their places.
As for "do not think evil," this can be understood in two ways: causing affliction or causing sin. Therefore, a holy person should neither think of afflicting anyone nor causing them to sin. And do not love false oaths. When it says "false oaths," it doesn't forbid swearing truthfully. However, in the Gospel, swearing is completely abolished by the Lord who said: "I tell you, do not swear at all." For one who does not swear can never lie under oath. These are the things I hate, says the Lord.
And the word of the Lord of Hosts came to me, saying: This is what the Lord of Hosts says: The fasts of the fourth, fifth, seventh, and tenth months will become times of joy, gladness, and cheerful feasts for the house of Judah. Therefore, love truth and peace.
To the questions previously asked by the Persian leaders through their envoys—whether they should fast in the fifth and seventh months, or if they should end the fast and lay aside mourning after the temple's construction—the prophet, placing many things in the middle that they should follow and prosper in, responds in the person of Christ.
The fast of the fourth month, understood implicitly, and of the fifth and seventh, understood in common, that is, from the common month.
The fourth month among the Hebrews is called July by us, in which Moses, descending from the mountain and seeing the people playing before the golden calf they had made, threw down the tablets of the covenant he had received from God and broke them at the foot of the mountain, and twenty-three thousand idolaters were slain.
In this same month (as we read in Jeremiah), the walls of the city of Jerusalem were breached by the Chaldeans.
For this reason, the Jews always fasted in the fourth month.
Their fifth month is called August by us.
In this month, the Jews suffered many adversities.
When they were in the desert, a rebellion arose because of the scouts who, having returned, caused the people to murmur.
Because of this, the Lord, being angered, forbade them from immediately entering the promised land, but made them wander in the desert for forty years until all who were twenty years old and above, who had left Egypt, died, except for Caleb and Joshua.
In this same month, the temple was destroyed and burned by Nebuchadnezzar first, and after many ages by the Romans, for which reasons they imposed a most severe fast on themselves every year.
The Hebrews' seventh month is called October by us, in which Gedaliah was killed by Ishmael, as mentioned above, and the remnants of the Jews were scattered.
This is the reason for the fast of the seventh month.
Their tenth month is called January by the Romans.
In this month, the prophet Ezekiel and the entire population of captives who were in Babylon heard in the fifth month that the temple had been destroyed.
Therefore, in this month, they fasted every year.
The meaning is this: The days of fasting you have observed in sorrow will now turn into joy, as I, the Lord, bring you prosperity, provided that you love truth and peace.
This is what the Lord of Hosts says: There will come a time when people from many cities will gather and go from one person to another, saying, "Let's go and seek the Lord of Hosts and pray to Him."
The fasts of the fourth and fifth months will be turned into splendid celebrations, and the cities of Judah, once deserted, will be filled with many citizens. One city will go to another, encouraging each other, because for seventy years no one came to the Lord's temple; the roads to Zion were in mourning and desolation.
Now that peace has been restored, let us go to Jerusalem to celebrate the festivals prescribed by the law each year. One city will say to another, "I will also go." Many people and strong nations will come to seek the Lord of Hosts in Jerusalem and pray to the Lord, offering sacrifices and praying to Him.
In a deeper sense, the face of the Lord is the Son of God the Father, for through Him, as through a face, the Father God is known. As the Son Himself says, "I have made Your name known to the people."
Therefore, all believing people gather at the Church, and there they pray to the Son of God, offering sacrifices of praise to God.
This is what the Lord of Hosts says: In those days, ten men from all languages of the nations will grasp the hem of a Jewish man, saying, "We will go with you, for we have heard that God is with you."
Although the Jews refer this to the end times of the Antichrist, we say it happened at the coming of the Lord when He was born of the Virgin Mary. These ten men represent the Church spread throughout the world, as ten is a perfect number, the end of the sequence of numbers. The letter iota in Greek, from which the name Jesus begins, also represents ten.
The Lord sought these ten men from Abraham, saying, "If I find ten there, I will not destroy the city for the sake of the ten."
The churches represented by the number ten are shown by John in the Book of Revelation with the number seven, where he saw the Son of Man in the midst of the lampstands, symbolizing the churches described under the names of cities.
It is also said in Isaiah: "Seven women will take hold of one man in that day."
The Apostle Paul wrote to seven churches: the Romans, Corinthians, Galatians, Ephesians, Philippians, Colossians, and Thessalonians.
Therefore, the churches marked by the number seven, due to the gifts of the sevenfold Spirit, are expressed by the prophet Zechariah with the number ten for perfect completeness.
And ten men, that is, churches that have reached spiritual maturity, will take hold of the hem of a Jewish man's garment, that is, the Lord Savior, of whom it is written: "Judah, your brothers will praise you;" and in the psalm: "Judah is my king."
The churches will take hold of the hem of this Jewish man, meaning they will believe in the mystery of his incarnation.
Through the hem, which is the smallest part of the garment, the humility of his incarnation is suggested.
This is what the woman with the issue of blood touched and was healed.
Thus, they will take hold of him, desiring to follow in his footsteps.
Therefore, all who are called by the Christian name and have reached spiritual maturity are included in these ten men, striving to be imitators of Christ by faithfully believing in his incarnation.
We can also specifically interpret the hem of the Jewish man as the Apostle Paul, who described himself as the least of the apostles, not worthy to be called an apostle.
Therefore, the hem of the Jewish man is Paul, the apostle of our Lord.
This hem is taken hold of by ten men, that is, all who believe in Christ and follow his teachings, as he himself says: "Be imitators of me."
Chapter Nine
The burden of the word of the Lord in the land of Hadrach and Damascus, his resting place.
This prophecy is about the construction of the holy Church, which consists of both Jews and Gentiles.
The order of the words is: For the burden is the weight of the word of the Lord, sharp and soft, sharp against sinners, soft towards the righteous.
"Had" in Hebrew means sharp, and "rach" means soft. Therefore, the weight of the word of the Lord is very heavy for sinners, but soft for the righteous.
In the land of Hadrach, let us understand the Jews: through Damascus, the Gentiles.
Therefore, the burden of the word of the Lord is in the land of Hadrach, representing the people of the Jews, upon whom the Lord exercised both severity and mercy—severity on those who did not want to believe, and mercy on those who turned from unbelief to faith.
Damascus is called the resting place of the Lord, because the Lord rested in the faith and devotion of the Gentiles, according to what was foretold through Isaiah about Christ:
Before the boy knows how to call his father or his mother, he will take the wealth of Damascus and the spoils of Samaria.
Rightly, however, Damascus is interpreted as drinking blood or the blood of sackcloth, because the Gentiles, first stained by idolatry, were wounded by the blood of sinners. Later, they sought to cleanse the blood of wickedness with the sackcloth of repentance.
Because the Lord is the eye of man and of all the tribes of Israel.
Therefore, he says, the house of the Lord, that is, the Church, is built from both peoples—from the land of Hadrach and from Damascus—because whoever looks to the Lord, whether from the Gentiles or from the Jews, believes and hopes in him.
For the eye is the sight of contemplation.
Hamath also, in its borders, and Tyre and Sidon, have assumed for themselves great wisdom.
And Tyre built its fortification, and heaped up silver like dust, and gold like mud in the streets.
Behold, the Lord will possess her, and will strike her power in the sea, and she will be devoured by fire.
Hamath is a city of Coele-Syria. Because it was rebuilt by Antiochus Epiphanes, it was called Epiphania.
For Hamath means indignation.
So, these cities—Tyre and Sidon—will be within the borders of Damascus, or within the land of Hadrach, so they too might believe in the Lord Savior, to whom the prophet says in the psalm:
"Ask of me, and I will give you the nations," etc.
Emath, which means indignation, and Tyre, which means distress, and Sidon, which means futile hunting, represent the peoples of the nations. Initially, they were indignant at the preaching of Christ's name, distressed by sins, and hunted by the devil, much like Nimrod, a mighty hunter before the Lord.
But these cities, or rather the peoples they signified, were the most eager to believe. The Lord shows this in the Gospel, saying:
"Woe to you, Chorazin, woe to you, Bethsaida, for if the miracles done in you had been done in Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago."
Therefore, they pursued great wisdom, including sophisms and clever tricks of dialectics.
Tyre also built her fortifications—strong arguments—with which the Gentiles, once fortified as if by a wall, could not be overcome by any teacher of truth.
They amassed silver, representing the eloquence of rhetoric, and gold, symbolizing the sense of morals and allegories.
But how worthless and contemptible these things are is shown when he compares this silver and gold to the mud of the streets.
They gathered these things to fortify the kingdom of idolatry and to make it invincible.
Therefore, the Lord took possession of Tyre and Sidon when he struck down their strength in the turbulent sea of this age, destroyed all their secular wisdom, and refined and purified their gold and silver with that fire of which he himself says in the Gospel:
"I have come to cast fire upon the earth," etc.
Ashkelon will see it and be afraid, Gaza will tremble greatly, and Ekron will be ashamed of her hope.
The king will perish from Gaza, and Ashkelon will no longer be inhabited.
And a separator will sit in Ashdod.
When Ascalon, Gaza, and Accaron—cities of the Philistines—see that Emath is within the borders of Damascus, and that Tyre and Sidon have come under its control, and see them possessed by the Lord, they will grieve and be filled with fear because they will realize that the hope they placed in idols was in vain.
Ascalon means "ignoble fire" or "weighed"; Gaza means "strong" or "rule"; Accaron means "barren" or "uprooted"; Azotus means "generating fire," "uncle's fire," or "breast fire."
Jebusite, which means "trampled down," represents souls deceived by the devil in this way. Ascalon, where the devil had been—the ignoble fire that had reached the weight of sins, that is, the people of the nations—was filled with such terror.
Gaza, which had been strong and believed it ruled through idolatry, grieved deeply, repenting for its past crimes.
Accaron, barren and without knowledge of God, not having spiritual children, was uprooted from the error that held it firmly.
When these cities, which represent the nations, are terrified and grieve because their hope is thwarted, then the separator will sit in Azotus—that is, the Lord Savior, who separates the wheat from the chaff, the bad fish from the good, and who will separate the sheep from the goats in judgment.
He will sit in Azotus, where the fire of the Spirit of God generates adopted children, where is the uncle's fire—that is, our Lord Jesus Christ, who deigned to take flesh from us, and of whom Isaiah said: "I will sing to my beloved a song of my uncle, my vineyard." There, too, is the fire of the breast, that is, the desire and fervor for drawing the milk of spiritual doctrine.
For the two breasts of the Church are the two Testaments, as the bride indicates in the Song of Songs: "My beloved is to me a cluster of henna blossoms in the vineyards of En-Gedi; he will lie between my breasts."
And I will destroy the pride of the Philistines, and remove his blood from his mouth, and his abominations from between his teeth. And even he will be left for our God and will be like a leader in Judah.
The Philistines, interpreted as those who fall by the cup, were drunk from the cup of demons and fell.
They are seen as the evocations of the nations—blasphemies or the eating of things sacrificed to idols.
By removing these, they may turn to our God, rejecting the care of many and beginning to worship only one God, becoming a leader in Judah.
Just as the former people, marked by Judah, turned into a tail, the last who was a tail became the head.
Accaron, once barren and uprooted, representing the Gentiles, will be like the Jebusites, or Jerusalem, which was known by three different names at various times.
First, it was called Salem.
When possessed by the Jebusites, it was called Jebus.
Combining the names Jebus and Salem, it became Jerusalem.
Accaron will be like the Jebusites because the nations will receive the grace that the inhabitants of Jerusalem once had when they believed in God.
And I will surround my house, the Church, with those who serve me, going and returning—the angels who serve me in various ministries for the sake of those who inherit salvation.
By their protection, the Church is fortified, as the Psalmist says: The angel of the Lord encamps around those who fear him.
The oppressor, the devil, will no longer pass over them, as Isaiah says: How the oppressor has ceased, the tribute has ended.
I have seen with my own eyes, meaning I have made my prophets see.
They are the eyes of the Lord, through whom he announced the calling of the nations and the safety of the Church.
Rejoice greatly, daughter of Zion, shout, daughter of Jerusalem.
Behold, your king will come to you, righteous and a savior, humble and riding on a donkey, on a colt, the foal of a donkey.
This prophecy, as Matthew the evangelist explains, was fulfilled in the Savior when he came to Jerusalem, sitting on a donkey's colt, and was received by crowds with palm branches, shouting divine praises to him.
Therefore, it is said: Rejoice greatly, daughter of Zion, shout, daughter of Jerusalem, which is one city.
Behold, your king, promised by all the voices of the prophets, comes to you, meaning for your sake, to free you.
Righteous and savior, he is called Jesus in Hebrew, because he will save his people from their sins.
He himself, though rich, became poor for us.
He rides on a donkey and a colt, the foal of a donkey, representing both peoples.
The donkey symbolizes the synagogue, which had borne the heavy yoke of the law.
The colt, however, represents the playful and free people of the Gentiles, who have no ruler, master, or law.
The Lord sits on both peoples and enters Jerusalem, and from the present Church, he guides them to the vision of true peace.
I will destroy the chariot from Ephraim and the horse from Jerusalem, and the bow of war will be broken.
He will speak peace to the nations, and his dominion will be from sea to sea, and from the rivers to the ends of the earth.
The voice of God the Father, who commanded the daughter of Zion to rejoice and the daughter of Jerusalem to shout for joy, still speaks, declaring what he will do.
"I will destroy," he says, "the chariot," meaning there will be no battles in the whole world at the coming of Christ, the peacemaker.
Allegorically, Ephraim, which means abundance, represents heretics, who boasted in chariots, that is, in the pride of their knowledge.
About whom the Psalmist says: "Some trust in chariots and some in horses," etc.
And elsewhere: "The sons of Ephraim, armed with bows, turned back on the day of battle."
He will also destroy the horse from Jerusalem, meaning all fleshly pride and pleasure, which is represented by the horse.
Hence the Psalmist says: "Do not be like the horse or the mule."
Then also the bow of war will be broken, meaning all instruments of battle will cease, with peace flourishing throughout the world.
Or the bow of war will be broken so that no more fiery arrows will be shot that could wound the hearts of the carnal.
He will speak peace to the nations, about whom it is said: "He will be the hope of the nations."
To these nations, he will speak peace made between God and men through his blood.
And his dominion will be from sea to sea.
For his dominion is over the whole world, and Christ is worshiped and revered everywhere.
Here the Psalmist says:
He will rule from sea, meaning the Indian Sea, to sea, meaning the Ocean, and from the Jordan River, where he was baptized and began to preach, to the ends of the earth.
You too, in the blood of your covenant, freed your prisoners from the pit where there is no water.
Now the prophet makes an apostrophe, or rather God himself speaks to Christ his Son, and says:
You too brought out your prisoners, that is the saints who were held in bonds, from the pit where there is no water; that is, you freed them from hell, where there is no mercy.
Finally, at the resurrection of the Lord, many of the saints who were held in hell by the bonds of original sin rose with him, came to the holy city, and appeared to many.
About this blood of the covenant, he himself said to the apostles at the Last Supper:
This is the cup of the New Covenant in my blood, which will be shed for you.
Return to the stronghold, prisoners of hope.
Today I also announce that I will repay you double.
Again, the speech turns to us, who were prisoners, and to be freed by God's mercy.
You (he says) who are now prisoners in the terrible prison of hell, and hope for release from hell at the coming of Christ, turn to the stronghold, that is, to the confidence of divine protection, and say with the Psalmist: Be my protecting God.
Or, turn to the stronghold, that is, remember the paradise which you now have in hope, but from this time you will possess it in reality; there will be your stronghold and secure tranquility, when you will no longer fear the rule of any enemy.
Today I also announce that I will repay you double, that is, from this time I am announcing this, I will repay you double, so that for a short time of tribulation you may receive eternal rewards.
For, as the Apostle says:
Everything in the world is temporary and brief in tribulation, but it works in us an exceedingly great and eternal weight of glory, not looking at what is seen, but what is unseen.
What is seen is temporary; what is unseen is eternal.
Since I have stretched out Judah for myself like a bow, I have filled the land of Ephraim.
Judah is Christ the Lord, who was born from the royal tribe.
God the Father stretched Him out for Himself like a bow when He wanted Him to take flesh from the virgin.
He is the bow, He is the arrow, and He is the archer.
The bow, indeed, as it says here, "I have stretched out Judah for myself like a bow"; the arrow, as He speaks through Jeremiah about God the Father: "He made me a chosen arrow, and hid me in His quiver"; and the archer, as it is said to Him in the Psalms through David, "Your arrows are sharp, peoples fall under you."
This arrow has filled Ephraim, that is, the assembly of heretics armed against the Lord and ready for battle, so that they too may be wounded by the Lord's arrows for salvation and say with the Church, "I am wounded with love."
And I will stir up your sons, Zion, against your sons, Greece, and make you like a warrior's sword. If by Ephraim the heretics are understood, then rightly by the sons of Greece the teachers of worldly philosophy are understood.
Therefore, the Lord has filled Ephraim with arrows and stirred up the sons of Zion, that is, the sons of the Church, against the sons of the Greeks, that is, the philosophers, because when the apostles preached, all the leaders of perverse doctrines and all the assertions of the philosophers, who especially thrived in Athens, were destroyed by the sword of the word of God, indeed by Christ Himself who is the sword of the mighty, about whom the Psalmist says: "Gird your sword upon your thigh," and another prophet says: "And you Ethiopians shall be slain by my sword"; and the Apostle says: "The word of God is living and effective, and sharper than any two-edged sword."
And the Lord God will appear over them, and His arrow will go out like lightning. And the Lord God will blow the trumpet and will march in the storms of the south. When, He says, the heretics and the wise of the nations have been slain by the bow and sword of the Lord by the sons of Zion, the glory of the Lord will appear over them; this is what it means when it says: "The Lord God will appear over them, and His arrow will go out like lightning," shining with the brilliance of miracles.
Another prophet says: "They will go in the light of your arrows, in the brightness of the flashing spear." This brightness and these flashes are called the trumpet or clangor, so that those illuminated by the brightness may be awakened by the sound of the trumpet to listen, and such a person can say with the prophet: "The Lord God has opened my ear." He awakens me morning by morning, he awakens my ear to listen as a disciple. The Lord also sees in the whirlwind of the south, that is, in the movement of threatening, which is therefore called punishments, so that he may have mercy. Hence it follows: "The Lord of hosts will protect them," whom he had terrified with his threats. And they will devour and subject them to sling stones, the sons of Zion protected by the Lord, that is, the men of the Church, will devour – you understand the adversaries, who are understood by the sons of Greece – and will subject them to sling stones, subjecting them to the threats of the Scriptures, and by the rotation of the sling, that is, by the testimonies and examples of divine sayings. They will be intoxicated as if with the fullest knowledge of the Scriptures, to which Wisdom invites us: "Eat, friends, drink and be intoxicated, beloved." And so, their intoxication will be pleasing to God, as if the libation of a sacrifice, and like the horns of the altar, that is, the four corners, which once a year the high priest, having entered the Holy of Holies, touched with his finger dipped in blood. And drinking, they will be intoxicated as if by wine, and they will be filled like bowls, and like the horns of the altar; and the Lord their God will save them on that day as the flock of his people, because the holy stones are lifted up over his land. Because the holy stones, that is, the chosen ones, will also be lifted up over his land, light and having no weight of sin at all, nor will they wait to be lifted by the builders, but they will lift themselves up, and they will hasten to be placed on the foundation of Christ, and to be contained by the cornerstone. Of these stones Peter speaks: "Coming to him, a living stone, you also, like living stones, are being built up." For what is his goodness and what is his beauty, unless the grain of the chosen ones, and the wine that causes virgins to flourish?
The chosen grain and wine that nurtures virgins, in a more sacred sense, is the Lord and Savior, who says of himself:
"Unless a grain of wheat falls to the ground and dies, it remains alone."
From this wheat, ground by the mill of passion and baked by the fire of death, the bread that came down from heaven and gives life to the world is made for us. He who is the bread is also the wine that gladdens the heart of man.
This wine is drunk by those virgins who, according to the Apostle, are holy in body and spirit, and, intoxicated, say with the bride:
"The king brought me into his wine cellar, and he ordered charity in me."
This wine nurtures virgins because those who are intoxicated by the love of Christ scorn all the pleasures of the world, and, as if drunk and insensitive to the world, love only Christ and say with the Apostle:
"So from now on we regard no one from a worldly point of view."
Chapter Ten
Ask the Lord for rain in the late season, and He will bring snow and rain showers, providing each of us with grass in the field.
The Lord encourages believers in Christ to seek this late rain, symbolizing the fullness of spiritual grace at the end of the age.
During these times, the more the Church is afflicted, the stronger it becomes, filled with greater hope and perseverance.
In each person's heart, the green grass of virtues will flourish, allowing them to say with the Psalmist: The Lord is my shepherd, etc.
The idols have spoken uselessly, the diviners have seen lies, and the dreamers have spoken in vain, offering empty consolation.
Consequently, they have been led like a flock and are afflicted because they have no shepherd.
This refers to heretics, who will especially proliferate at the end of the world.
They deceive people under the guise of Christianity, paying attention to spirits of error and demons, and speaking lies in hypocrisy, offering false consolation.
What they promise themselves and others are lies; because of their actions, they are led and captivated by the devil, delivered to Satan for the destruction of the flesh, and afflicted because they do not have Christ as their shepherd, despite their false claims.
All these things, except for the part where it says: I extended Judah to myself like a bow; I filled the land with Ephraim, refer to the times of the Maccabean leaders.
These leaders defeated the Macedonians and cleansed the temple defiled by pagans after a period of three and a half years.
As for the saying: They will be drunk as if with wine, and filled like bowls, it is interpreted as follows: Those who fought with Judas Maccabeus fought with such desperation, as if drunk, forgetting their own safety, caring only for victory.
Here's the translation:
The phrase "What is good, what is beautiful, except the grain of the chosen and the wine, producing virgins" is understood like this: The Maccabees did great things and willingly faced death to defeat their enemies, purify the temple, observe the commandments of the law again, and inspire people to believe in one God. They would once again have learned individuals who follow the divine law. They would ask the Lord for the late rain because the prophets had ceased, and the world was approaching its end. Ultimately, Christ would come and fulfill what the prophets had foretold.
"My anger is kindled against the shepherds, and I will punish the goats, for the Lord of hosts has visited His flock, the house of Judah, and has made them like His majestic horse in battle." Often, the sins of the shepherds cause the people to suffer and be handed over to adversaries. For instance, when David sinned, many thousands of the Jewish people were struck by pestilence. The prophet says the Lord is angry with the shepherds and visits His anger upon the people, because they follow their leaders in sin. Yet afterward, when He has avenged these sins, He will visit His flock, the house of Judah, in goodness. Those who confess God in word and deed will be set like His majestic horse, as He presides over them and rules them, appearing marvelous among them.
About these horses, the prophet says: "You ride on Your horses, Your chariots of salvation." From Him, who sets them like His majestic horse, will come the cornerstone, someone perfect who, like a cornerstone, will hold together and strengthen those in the struggle. From Him will come the peg, a humble one in the Church, who, through patience, supports the rest like an outstretched tent. And from Him will come the battle bow, the preacher, sending arrows of warning to sinners.
From him will come every taskmaster who will compel the unwilling and demand they submit to Christ, frightened by the fear of judgment when they hear about the great punishments prepared for the unbelievers.
They will be like strong men, trampling the mud of the roads in battle, fighting because the Lord is with them.
When crowned with martyrdom for Christ, they will say with the Psalmist:
"Though an army besiege me," etc.
Here, the Hebrews explain that the persecution that happened to the Jews under Antiochus occurred because of the fault of their leaders. It was visited upon the goats, that is, the people, and they were handed over to the nations. Later, He visited His flock, the house of Judah, by raising up Judas Maccabeus and others who were like a horse of glory.
Regarding the phrase "From him the cornerstone, from him the tent peg," they interpret the cornerstone as royal power, which holds two walls together, and the tent peg as the priesthood. From him the taskmaster, meaning all other lesser dignities, so the meaning is: there will be no dignity not appointed by him, that is, Judas Maccabeus.
The riders on horses will be put to shame. I will strengthen the house of Judah, and I will save the house of Joseph. I will bring them back because I will have mercy on them, and they will be as if I had not cast them off. For I am the Lord their God, and I will hear them.
These things are to be understood as above, when the Lord will strengthen His martyrs in persecutions and grant help to the desperate. Then the riders on horses, meaning the proud persecutors, will be put to shame. He will strengthen the house of Judah, those who confess the Lord, and the house of Joseph, which means "increased" or "blessed."
They will be like the mighty men of Ephraim, and their hearts will rejoice as with wine. Their children will see and be glad; their hearts will exult in the Lord. Ephraim, meaning "abundance," so they may be worthy of that name. They will rejoice when they drink the wine of the true vine, that is, when they are companions in the sufferings of Christ.
The children of those to whom the Apostle speaks:
"My dear children, for whom I am again in the pains of childbirth,"
and to whom the Psalmist says:
"Come, children, listen to me."
They will rejoice, and their hearts will be glad in the Lord, saying with the Apostle:
"The sufferings of this present time are not worth comparing to the glory that will be revealed in us."
Nevertheless, this is also referred by the Hebrews to the Maccabees, that, having overcome the enemies of the house of Judah—that is, the two tribes—and the house of Joseph—that is, the ten tribes—they will be saved and will rejoice as if drunk with wine.
Then also the two and ten tribes, which had been separated from each other under Jeroboam, will be reunited, and they will be as they were before the Lord cast them off. The children of these people, seeing the triumphs of their parents, will rejoice in the Lord.
"I will whistle for them and gather them, for I have redeemed them, and they will increase as they once increased, and I will sow them among the peoples."
In a more sacred sense, the Lord will whistle, that is, make a sign to those who were scattered due to sins, so that they may return to Him. And He speaks in the Gospel:
"Come to me, all you who are weary and burdened."
They will be gathered because the Lord has redeemed them with His precious blood. They will increase, as they once increased, that is, according to what was said to Abraham:
"In your seed, all the nations will be blessed."
And the Apostle:
"Those who have faith are children of Abraham."
They are also sown among the peoples to announce Christ to all nations, as He Himself commanded:
"Go into all the world and preach the Gospel to all creation."
And they will remember me from afar. By these words, it is implied the nations, which were far from God due to unbelief; of which the Psalmist says:
"They will remember and turn to the Lord,"
and those who were dead in sins. And they will live with their children, those, namely, whom they have begotten for Christ by preaching. To such people, the Apostle says:
"As infants in Christ, I gave you milk to drink, not solid food."
And they will return, and I will bring them back from the land of Egypt, that is, from the darkness of ignorance, where the devil reigns. And I will gather them from Assyria, from the proud sense of the false doctrine of heretics.
I will bring them to the land of Gilead and Lebanon, where no place will be found for them.
Gilead means the testimony of migration, and Lebanon means whitening.
So, they will be brought back to Gilead, symbolizing those who move from the physical to the spiritual, and from the earthly to the heavenly.
They will be brought to Lebanon, representing those who, after shedding the darkness of sins and being whitened by baptism, will receive the white robe of immortality.
They will pass through the sea's strait, and the waves will crash in the sea, causing all the depths of the river to be confused.
The pride of Assyria will be humbled, and the scepter of Egypt will be taken away.
I will strengthen them in the Lord, and in His name, they will walk, says the Lord.
According to the literal tradition of the Hebrews, the Jews captured by the Assyrians and Chaldeans were not only handed over to the Medes and Persians or to Babylon but also to the northern region and the Bosphorus.
Later, some were called back from there, with God's mercy upon them.
This is what is meant here: They will pass through the sea's strait, specifically the narrow sea of Propontis, where the strait divides Chalcedon and Byzantium.
The Lord will strike the waves in the sea, going before His people, causing the depths of the rivers to be confused, just as the Red Sea was divided and the Jordan dried up.
Then the pride of the Assyrians will be humbled, and the scepter of Egypt will be taken from them.
God's people will be freed, strengthened in the Lord, and will walk in His name, returning to their land.
These things are said according to the tradition of the Hebrews.
According to the mystical sense, we also pass through the narrow sea of this world, which is full of dangers for the saints.
But for those who love this world, it is very wide, because the wide road leads to death, while the narrow one leads to life.
In this narrow and turbulent sea of the world, our Redeemer first passed through, followed by the apostles, of whom it is said: Those who go down to the sea in ships have seen the works of the Lord.
Then the pride of Assyria, which means the devil, will be humbled, and the power of Egypt, which represents darkness and the powers of the air, will fade away.
When the last enemy, death, is destroyed, and the one who held the power of death is locked in the prison of hell.
But the saints will be strengthened in the Lord and will say: My strength and my praise.
And they will walk in His name, which means in the name of Christ, from whom Christians are named.
Under the dignity of this title, they will walk from strength to strength until the God of gods is seen in Zion.
Chapter Eleven
Open your gates, Lebanon, and let the fire consume your cedars.
Lebanon is a mountain in Phoenicia, marking the northern boundary of Judea.
Here, the temple is called Lebanon because it was built from Lebanese wood.
The prophet predicted that the temple, recently constructed by Zerubbabel and Joshua, would be destroyed by Vespasian and Titus, leaders of the Romans.
Open Lebanon, your gates to receive the invading enemies.
When he mentions Lebanon, he continues the metaphor, saying, let the fire devour your cedars.
By cedars, fir trees, oaks of Bashan, and the wooded forest, he refers to the leaders, priests, and people of the Jews.
Let the fire consume your cedars, he says, so that everything is either destroyed by fire or hostile rule, consuming both leaders and people.
Wail, fir tree, because the cedar has fallen, for the mighty have been devastated;
wail, oaks of Bashan, because the fortified forest has been cut down.
In mutual lamentation, he says, priests, leaders, and people, mourn your demise.
If you wonder what the cedars, fir trees, and oaks signify, he clarifies that he is speaking about people, because the mighty have been devastated.
Bashan means confusion, and the oaks of Bashan refer to people of confusion and disgrace, because the fortified forest has been cut down.
By the fortified or wooded forest, he means the temple itself, built with unassailable strength by various kings, and finally by Herod.
Metaphorically, he says it will be cut down, meaning devastated by the fighting Romans.
The sound of the shepherds' wailing, because their magnificence has been devastated.
Those he previously called cedars, fir trees, or oaks, he now explains as shepherds, meaning their priests and leaders.
The wailing is heard because their magnificence and pride, namely the temple in which they greatly gloried, has been burned and destroyed.
The sound of the lions' roar, because the pride of the Jordan has been devastated.
Those whom he previously referred to as trees or shepherds, he now calls lions.
Just as he previously compared the height of the temple to the height of Mount Lebanon, the highest and densest in the promised land, he now links the roar of lions to the pride of the Jordan River.
In that region, the Jordan is the largest of all rivers.
Lions dwell near it, either to quench their thirst with its waters or because it is close to the desert and vast wilderness.
Thus the prophet says: The voice of the roaring lions, meaning the nobles and princes, is heard.
Because the pride of the Jordan is devastated, that is, the dignity of the temple is destroyed, from where help was hoped for.
This is what the Lord my God says: Feed the sheep destined for slaughter, those who owned them killed them and did not grieve, and sold them.
The voice of the Lord to the prophet.
Now, he says, let the flock be nourished and grow, which will later be captured by enemies.
The Romans, who possessed these sheep by right of conquest, killed them and did not grieve, nor did they show mercy.
Those they preserved for life, they sold and rejoiced, saying: Blessed be the Lord, we have become rich.
Anyone who reads the history will find that these things happened.
These can be tropologically referred to the bishops and priests of Christians.
Evil shepherds feed the flock destined for slaughter, whose negligence causes the Lord's flock to perish.
They see those under them going astray in vices and do not correct or amend them, fearing to lose temporal advantages which they love.
Thus, they feed them not for life, but for slaughter, and they cannot say with the Apostle: Who is scandalized, and I do not burn?
They also sell the submissive people when they make wealth for themselves from their destruction.
They favor sinners, praising those who plunder the poor, and blessing the wicked.
And their shepherds did not spare them, and I will no longer spare the inhabitants of the land, says the Lord.
Because, he says, the shepherds did not spare the flock, but they themselves first devoured my people, therefore I will no longer spare the inhabitants of the land, meaning Judea.
This literally refers to the land of the Jews, not the whole world.
He says, "I will not spare anymore, but will take revenge immediately and hand them over to their enemies." This was fulfilled in the forty-second year after the Lord's passion, which was the time given to them for repentance.
"Behold, I will hand over men, each to the hand of his neighbor and to the hand of his king, and they will devastate the land, and I will not rescue it from their hands. I will feed the flock of slaughter because of this, O poor flock." He says, "I will let men go so that they kill each other."
Let us read Josephus, and we will find that during the siege of Jerusalem, there was so much discord and sedition among the Jews that the people were divided into three parts and fought against each other. And he says, "The Romans will devastate the land."
When he says "their king," at that time the Jews did not have a king, but he refers to a protector and leader as a king. He shows what that eternal desolation is when he says, "I will not rescue them from their hands," that is, from the Romans, because it is God's judgment that it should be so.
"O poor flock, the just of Israel, who believed in the Lord God, hear and understand what is said." And I took two staffs for myself; one I called Beauty, and the other I called Bonds, and I fed the flock.
The Creator and Shepherd, the Lord God, took two staffs for himself, that is, two peoples. He had the first staff, the whole human race under Noah, which he called Beauty, because in the world recently restored after the flood, humans had not yet become tainted with crimes. Nothing is more just than calling the Creator of all equally, since He created all with equal condition; the other he called Bonds, by choosing the Israelite people under Abraham.
For when the Most High divided the nations, etc. And he says, "I fed the flock, either Israel or the whole human race. And I destroyed three shepherds in one month, and my soul grew weary of them; indeed, their souls also varied towards me, and I said."
We must acknowledge three shepherds: Moses, Aaron, and their sister Miriam.
Miriam died in the desert of Sin during the first month, which they call Nisan and the Romans call April.
In the same month and place, Moses and Aaron were condemned not to enter the Promised Land because they did not sanctify the Lord at the Waters of Contradiction.
Thus, three shepherds were cut off in one month: Miriam by present death, and Moses and Aaron by the sentence of future death.
And my soul was distressed with them, meaning I was somewhat indignant over those three shepherds whom I had appointed over my flock.
Indeed, their souls wavered by doubting me because they did not glorify me before the children of Israel at the Waters of Contradiction.
If we want to refer this to the people, the meaning would be: I was indignant because their souls, that is, the people's, wavered in me, fluctuating between me and idols and opposing me in various ways.
Therefore, I angrily said: I will not feed you; and to Moses, I said: Leave me so that I may destroy them.
I was indeed angry, but I was still waiting, for when I say, leave me, I provoke him to ask me, showing that I can be restrained.
Let that which dies, die; and that which is cut off, be cut off by death, and let the rest devour each other’s flesh.
He said: Let the bodies of all fall in the desert, and let the rest devour each other’s flesh.
Let them turn into rebellion, and like beasts, let them be torn apart by mutual bites, and let none enter their Promised Land.
And I took my staff called Beauty, and cut it apart.
After the assumption of Israel—this is the second staff, called "cord"—the Lord took the first staff, called "beautiful," representing the nations of the world because they abandoned God and followed idols. As the Psalmist says: "They have all turned aside," and, as if explaining what this staff was, he added: "To annul my covenant, which I made with all the peoples, and it was annulled on that day. Then the poor of the flock who watched me knew that it was the word of the Lord."
As soon as Israel was taken up, the multitude of nations was cast aside, and the covenant I made with all nations was annulled. The poor of the flock, that is, the faithful from Israel who keep my commandments, knew that it was the word of the Lord. This is the will of the Lord: that the nations be rejected and Israel be chosen in Abraham.
And I said to them: If it is good in your eyes, bring my reward; and if not, refrain. I said (he says) to them, that is, to the poor of the Israelite flock, after they knew it was the word of the Lord, that it was the will of the Lord that, with all the nations rejected and their errors with their promises, the nation of Israel be chosen.
If it is good in your eyes, that is, if it pleases you, for you have the free will to choose what you want, in exchange for this assumption by which all nations are rejected and you are chosen as my special people, give me my reward, that is, keep my commandments.
But if you do not want to be counted by my name or do what I command, then openly do what you want.
But then, when these things were said to them, they responded to Moses: "All that the Lord our God has commanded us, we will do." However, at the end of times, for all that I did for them, freeing them from Egyptian slavery and taking them as my special people.
They weighed out my wages, giving thirty pieces of silver for my blood to Judas the betrayer.
The Lord said to me, the Savior, Throw it to the potter, referring to the creator or potter, whom we recognize as the shaper of all things, so that the judgment of this creator would weigh those given wages.
Seeing the Creator and Lord of the world valued at such a low price of thirty pieces of silver, He said ironically, What a fine price they have appraised me at.
As if to say with a certain indignant sarcasm, Look at the price my people, whom I specially loved and adopted as my children, have judged me to be worth.
The Prophet said, I took the thirty pieces of silver and did not put them away, but threw them into the house of the Lord to the potter, meaning I made the betrayer take that price into the house of the Lord and give it to the priests, admitting himself, I have sinned by betraying innocent blood.
But they did not want to put it into the treasury, so they bought the potter's field with it for the burial of strangers.
This act signified us, who were strangers to God's covenant but redeemed by the precious blood of His Son, resting in the potter's field, the creator and maker of all, at the price of Christ's blood.
I cut my second staff, which was called Union, to break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel.
After the Lord was appraised at thirty pieces of silver, and the price was used for the burial of strangers, meaning the Gentiles who were alien to God, the Lord said, I cut my second staff, meaning I cast away that people I loved, to break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel, separating the believers from the non-believers—namely the apostles and those who repented, called Judah, from those who cried out, Crucify him, and We have no king but Caesar, choosing to remain in their unbelief.
And this is what He says: Do not think that I have come to bring peace to the earth, etc.
And the Lord said to me:
"Take the gear of a foolish shepherd for yourself, because I am going to raise up a shepherd in the land who will not care for the lost, seek the scattered, heal the injured, or feed the healthy.
Instead, he will eat the meat of the fat sheep and tear off their hooves.
This foolish and unskilled shepherd is the Antichrist, who is said to come at the end of the world.
The gear of the foolish shepherd refers to his clothing and other symbols like the bag, staff, pipe, and whistle.
Just as Isaiah walked naked and barefoot to show the future captivity with his appearance, Zechariah is commanded to take on the appearance of the foolish shepherd to show the one he announced as coming."
Because earlier the good shepherd, being angry, had said,
'I will not feed you,'
it is therefore foretold that a foolish shepherd will come, who will be so foolish that he will sit in the temple of God, showing himself as if he were God.
He will not come to heal but to destroy the flock of Israel.
The Jews will accept this foolish shepherd by the just judgment of God because they did not want to believe the truth, they will believe the lie.
The prophet clearly describes what he will be like, showing that he will act entirely contrary to Christ.
'O worthless shepherd, abandoning the flock!
A sword will strike his arm and his right eye. His arm will wither completely, and his right eye will be totally blinded.'
After describing this foolish and wicked shepherd, there is an address to him, saying,
'O worthless shepherd.'
For he shows him to be so wicked that he calls him not just a worshiper of idols, but the idol itself, since he wants to be worshiped by everyone as God.
He abandons the flock to be devoured by beasts, which the Lord had protected for so long.
The sword upon his arm means clear retribution, so that all his strength and power will dry up, and upon his right eye, so that all his knowledge and understanding, which he boasted about, will be obscured by eternal darkness.
This sword can also be understood as the one mentioned elsewhere:
'My sword is drunk in heaven.'
This sword, specifically the word of God, penetrates everything and will cause the strength of the Antichrist to wither.
His eye, or the sharpness of his mind, with which he thought he could see the mysteries of God most acutely,
will condemn him to perpetual blindness.
Chapter Twelve
The word of the Lord concerning Israel.
The Lord, who stretches out the heavens, lays the foundation of the earth, and forms the spirit of man within him, said:
Look, I will make Jerusalem a threshold of drunkenness for all the surrounding peoples.
Even Judah will be besieged along with Jerusalem.
And on that day, I will make Jerusalem a heavy stone for all the people.
All who try to lift it will be severely injured, and all the kingdoms of the earth will gather against it.
The Lord stretched out the heavens like a tent, or as the Psalmist said, like a skin.
Just as skin covers the body of an animal on all sides, the sky encompasses everything.
He founded the earth, which is the center and lowest part of all elements, making it immovable and standing in its mass.
He formed the spirit of man within him, meaning He placed the soul in the human body, creating one being from both soul and body.
Here, "spirit" stands for "soul."
Therefore, this Creator and Lord of the universe says, literally, that He will make Jerusalem a threshold of drunkenness for all the surrounding peoples. Whoever touches its threshold will become drunk and fall, or the threshold itself will fall on whoever touches it.
Even Judah, captured by enemies and joining their side, with their city Jerusalem besieged, will be forced to besiege their own city.
The Lord will also make Jerusalem a heavy stone for all the people, and whoever tries to lift it will be severely injured.
According to the blessed Jerome, in the cities of Palestine, very heavy round stones are placed in castles and villages. Young men use these stones to train, lifting them according to their strength: some to their knees, others to their navel, some to their shoulders and head, and a few raise them above their head with their hands joined and extended, testing their strength in this way.
So the meaning is: I will make Jerusalem like a very heavy stone for all nations. Just as they gather to lift a stone for sport, they will gather to capture it and show their strength.
But as the stone is lifted, meaning as Jerusalem is attacked, those lifting it will inevitably suffer some cuts or scrapes.
On that day, says the Lord, I will strike every horse with panic and its rider with madness.
I will watch over the house of Judah and strike every horse of the peoples with blindness.
On that day, when Jerusalem is besieged, causing Judah to also be involved, the Lord will strike the adversaries' horses with panic.
This means that all who witness this will be astonished.
He will strike them with such panic that they become senseless, and their riders with madness, meaning they will be so overwhelmed with fear that they lose their sanity.
For the house of Judah, who are forced to act against their own city, the Lord will open His eyes in mercy, making them worthy of His sight and illuminating them with His light.
Spiritually, horses, when taken in a negative context, signify the lustful and the proud.
Their riders are demons or teachers of false doctrines, who will all be turned to panic and madness, showing they lack true knowledge.
They will be oppressed by palpable darkness, much like what happened in Egypt.
But for the house of Judah, those confessing the Lord, He will open His eyes and show mercy to those calling out to Him: Look upon me and have mercy on me.
The leaders of Judah will say in their hearts: Let the inhabitants of Jerusalem be strengthened in the Lord of hosts, their God.
When the Lord shows mercy on Judah, the leaders of Judah, who were besieged by enemies, will make vows in their hearts, unable to speak freely, so that over Jerusalem, which they besiege, and Judah itself, will prevail with its citizens.
Tropologically, the leaders of Judah are the apostles, apostolic men, and other teachers who lead the armies of Christ.
They do not want any other helpers except the inhabitants of Jerusalem, that is, orthodox and catholic men.
They wish for these people to be strengthened in the Lord their God.
One of these leaders was Peter, who found Mark, an inhabitant of Jerusalem.
Paul, an excellent leader himself, had Timothy, Titus, and Luke, true inhabitants of Jerusalem.
With them, he conquered the world for Christ.
On that day, I will make the leaders of Judah like a fire stove among wood, and like a flaming torch among straw.
They will devour all the surrounding peoples to the right and to the left, and Jerusalem will be inhabited again in its place in Jerusalem.
The Lord will save the tents of Judah first, so the glory of the house of David and the glory of the inhabitants of Jerusalem will not be magnified against Judah.
When, he says, the leaders in Judah, who were necessarily with the enemies against Jerusalem, made these vows, then I, the Lord, will give them such strength that they will devour all their adversaries around them like firewood and a flaming torch among straw.
Once the victory is achieved, Jerusalem will be inhabited again, and the tents of Judah will be restored—that is, the castles, villages, and towns that were devastated.
The house of Judah, that is, the royal family descending from David, and the illustrious and powerful ones from Jerusalem, will not boast against Judah, as if it were governed by their rule and counsel.
They will know that the Lord is their king and victory.
According to the allegory, when the Lord gives peace to the Church and turns its enemies into stupor and madness, the leaders of the Church will be like fire among wood and like flaming torches among straw, purging all vice and unfruitful trees.
That is, all perverse doctrines will be consumed, and they will devour on the right and on the left those who did not want to follow the middle path of virtue.
For every virtue is in the middle.
On the right and on the left are those who either understand more or less than they should.
Then the Church will regain its former glory, and the gatherings of the faithful will be restored throughout the whole world.
The teachers will not claim this glory for themselves, as if the Church's peace came through them.
Instead, all joy and prosperity of the faithful will be attributed to the Lord.
On that day, the Lord will protect the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and anyone among them who stumbles will be like David.
The house of David will be like God, like the angel of the Lord before him.
When the Lord helps Judah to gain victory, He will also protect the inhabitants of Jerusalem who were besieged, and everything will change for the better.
The one who offends God and is thought to be the least will be like David, like the royal family.
The one from the royal house will be like the house of God, like the messenger of the Lord before those who see them at that time.
In a higher sense, when the Lord delivers His Church from the hands of persecutors, those who stood firm during the persecution will be so glorious among all that the least of them, even someone who has offended God, will be in the rank of teachers.
The teachers will be like the house of God and like an angel transformed into evangelical dignity.
And on that day, I will seek to crush all the nations that come against Jerusalem.
What is said about seeking to crush all nations should be taken in a positive sense.
The Lord crushes not for destruction but for correction, so that they stop persecuting Jerusalem and turn from enemies into sheep.
And I will pour out on the house of David and on the inhabitants of Jerusalem the spirit of grace and supplication.
By showing the abundance of the outpouring, He indicates that God gives the grace of the Holy Spirit, about which Paul says: "The love of God has been poured out in our hearts." Another prophet says: "I will pour out my Spirit on all people." And rightly, after saying the spirit of grace, He added supplication, because those whom the Holy Spirit fills are immediately set on fire to worship.
These things were fulfilled in the resurrection of Christ and are fulfilled daily in the Church.
They will look at me, whom they have pierced, and they will mourn for him as one mourns for an only child, and they will grieve for him as one grieves over the death of a firstborn.
The prophet introduces the very Son of God, speaking clearly about himself: They will look at me whom they have pierced.
This can refer both to the time of the Lord's passion and to the day of the final judgment.
When the Lord was placed on the cross, the pious and faithful surely looked at him and were deeply moved with sorrow for him.
But in judgment, they will look at him coming in the glory of his majesty, whom they pierced on the cross with nails, and they will mourn and grieve with great lamentation and sorrow, just as one does for the death of an only child, whose bitter funeral causes immense grief to the parents.
Therefore, the Jews will mourn as if for an only child, or, as the Septuagint translated, a firstborn.
For Christ is the only begotten according to the nature of his being: by divinity, the only one of the Father; by humanity, the only one of his mother.
He is also the firstborn, as John says: He is the firstborn of the dead and the ruler of the kings of the earth.
On that day there will be great mourning in Jerusalem, like the mourning of Hadad-Rimmon in the plain of Megiddo, and the families of the earth will mourn, each family separately:
the family of the house of David separately, and their women separately;
the family of the house of Nathan separately, and their women separately;
the family of the house of Levi separately, and their women separately;
the family of Shimei separately, and their women separately.
Hadad-Rimmon is a city near Jezreel, now called Maximianopolis, located in the plain of Megiddo, where King Josiah, the most righteous, was killed by Pharaoh Necho, over whom Jeremiah made great lamentation.
He also mentions this in the book of Lamentations, saying: The breath of our nostrils, the Lord's anointed, was captured in their pits, of whom we said: Under your shadow we shall live among the nations.
Although this, according to the spiritual sense, refers to the Lord the Savior.
Just as there was great mourning in the city of Hadadrimmon back then, there will also be great mourning in Jerusalem when the Savior is killed.
The phrase, "the families will mourn separately," signifies that during times of tribulation, those with wives should refrain from marital duties. As written in Genesis, when the flood was imminent, Noah was instructed, "Enter the ark, you and your sons, and your wife and your sons' wives with you"; placing the father with his sons first, and then separately, the father's wife and the sons' wives.
Similarly, the family of David, the family of Nathan, the family of Levi, and the family of Shimei are separated from their wives to mourn the only-begotten Christ, against whom they cried, "His blood be on us and on our children."
In David, we see the royal house, which is the tribe of Judah; in Nathan, the prophecy; in Levi, the priestly order, since the priesthood of that family came from Levi's lineage; and in Shimei, the teachers, because the tribe of Shimei held the privilege of teaching and instruction.
The phrase, "All the families, the remaining families, and their women separately," includes all other families by name that do not have any privileged status. These interpretations are according to Hebrew tradition.
Now, let's explain how the Church's teachers refer to the Day of Judgment. On that day, when Jesus Christ comes in His majesty, showing everyone the wounds of His passion on His body, and making the cross carried by angelic hands visible to the whole world, there will be incomparable mourning. Everyone will lament that their Lord and Creator endured such great and unworthy suffering for the unworthy and for sinners.
There will be four groups of mourners:
The first group is from the family of the house of David, representing royalty and all worldly dignitaries.
Within this group, some individuals will be righteous and chosen, having governed the people entrusted to them according to God's will.
These are indicated by the men.
The second group is from the family of the house of Nathan, representing the teachers of the Church.
Nathan was a prophet during David's time, and through him, teachers are understood, whom the apostle Paul calls prophets.
In this group, some individuals preach the word of God sincerely, represented by men, while others seek praise or rewards from people, represented by women.
The third group is from the family of the house of Levi, representing the priestly order and all ecclesiastical ranks.
Among these, some are pleasing to God and diligently work to save souls, while others, living weakly like women, care little for the salvation of souls.
The fourth group is from the family of the house of Shimei, representing the lay order.
Shimei lived among the people and took care of his household, symbolizing those who live secular lives.
In this group, there are good people, referred to as men, and the unworthy, referred to as women.
Thus, at the judgment, each person will be placed according to the quality of their merits.
Some will be on the right to be crowned, while others will be on the left to be condemned.
All will mourn, but the mourning of the righteous will turn into eternal rejoicing, while the mourning of the unworthy will turn into endless weeping.
Chapter Thirteen
On that day, a fountain will be opened for the house of David and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, for cleansing from sin and impurity.
According to Blessed Jerome, this fountain represents the knowledge of the Scriptures, accessible to the house of David, meaning the entire Church.
The Church is indeed the house of David because it embodies strength and the desired vision.
The prophet Ezekiel saw this fountain flowing out of the temple, growing into a great river, and reaching the wilderness of the nations to irrigate it with divine knowledge.
This fountain is open for the cleansing of sinners and the impure, so that, by receiving faith, we may be reborn in Christ, and our sins washed away in the waters of baptism.
According to Blessed Gregory, this fountain is the boundless mercy of God, open to the house of David, which is the entire Church, for cleansing the impure and those who have committed sinful deeds, whom he calls sinners, and those who have conceived evil in their minds but have not yet acted on it, whom he calls impure.
The impure woman may not touch another's flesh but is polluted by her own.
Similarly, the soul can be stained by vices and the filth of evil will.
Therefore, God's mercy is open to all.
And it shall come to pass on that day, says the Lord of hosts: I will remove the names of the idols from the land, and they shall no longer be remembered.
I will remove the false prophets and the unclean spirit from the land.
When Christ saves His Church, He will destroy the names of idols, whether they are crafted by artisans or represent corrupt doctrines made by heretics.
Just as idols are crafted by artisans, so are the perverse doctrines of heretics, who, instead of Christ, worship the Antichrist.
He will also remove the false prophets, the priests of idols, whom pagans call prophets or seers.
He will remove the unclean spirit that resides in the hearts of the impure, so it can no longer deceive anyone through fanatics and diviners.
When someone continues to prophesy, their parents will say to them, "You will not live because you have spoken lies in the name of the Lord." These parents will pierce their child when they prophesy.
Once these events have occurred and the false prophets and unclean spirits are removed, if anyone tries to prophesy in the name of the Lord again, their parents, forgetting their parental affection to fulfill God's will, will pronounce a death sentence against their child. There will be no public judgment; they will be condemned by their own relatives for daring to prophesy.
On that day, prophets will be ashamed of their visions when they prophesy, and they will not wear a sackcloth cloak to lie. When a prophet is found to have spoken falsely in the name of the Lord, they will be ashamed of their false vision and will not wear the sackcloth cloak, which was traditionally worn by prophets to announce repentance, as the prophet Isaiah did. Therefore, the false prophet will not dare to wear this attire and pretend to be a prophet.
Instead, they will say, "I am not a prophet; I am a farmer, for Adam has been my example since my youth." They will claim to be a farmer, plowing the land and subject to the same sentence that was issued to Adam when he sinned, as the Lord said, "In the sweat of your face," etc.
When they profess that they are not a prophet but a farmer, someone will ask, "What are these wounds in the middle of your hands? Why were you pierced with nails?" For it was said earlier that their parents pierced them when they prophesied. If they are not a prophet, what did they do to deserve this punishment?
Because of this, perhaps the Jews judged Christ the Lord to be worthy of the cross, as if He were a false prophet.
They said, "We have a law, and according to the law, He must die." The law is not only those five books of Moses, but also the prophets and the Psalms are called law. Hence, the Lord in the Gospel says: "Is it not written in your law, 'I said, you are gods,' even though this is written in the Psalms?"
He will respond and say: "I was wounded in the house of those who loved me." By this response, He showed at that time the future defense of the truth, so that not even the one condemned by his own fault would dare to lie but would rightly confess to having endured all things. He says: "These are the wounds or scars I received in the house of my parents, who loved me; condemned not by the judgment of those who hated, but by those who loved me."
"Awake, O sword, against my shepherd, and against the man who is close to me," says the Lord of hosts. "Strike the shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered; and I will turn my hand against the little ones." The sword, or rhomphaea, that is, a double-edged sword, although some want to take it as a spear.
Therefore, the Lord commands the sword to be awakened against the shepherd, whom no one doubts to be Christ. For God the Father, because of the great love with which He loved the human race, preordained before the ages to redeem the world through the death of His Son, and in the fullness of time hastened to fulfill the work of His mercy. Therefore, He commands the sword, which we can take to mean the pain of suffering, or death, or certainly the very malice of the Jews, about which He Himself speaks to the Father: "Deliver my soul from the sword."
This sword is awakened against the shepherd Christ by the command of the Father, to whom it is said: "They persecuted the one whom you struck." It is awakened also against the man who is close to Him, that is, to God the Father: for the Son is always close to the Father, as He Himself says: "I am in the Father, and the Father is in me." But He is close to Him not by conjunction, but by the unity of the same substance.
And it should be noted that here the Father is introduced as the one commanding, but in the Gospel, the Lord Himself is introduced as speaking: "I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered."
So, after the good shepherd was struck, and the man close to God was suspended on the cross, the sheep, the apostles, were scattered, along with whoever else was among the believers.
Then He turned His hand to the little ones, to whom He had said: "Do not be afraid, little flock," etc.
The little ones were the apostles and the other followers of the Lord, who were simple, innocent, and small in malice, or who still seemed very few compared to the innumerable unbelievers.
He turned His hand, meaning His action, towards them to save them and to complete the benefit and fruit of His passion in them.
Hence it follows: "And in all the land," says the Lord, "two parts in it shall be cut off and die, but the third part shall be left in it."
The two parts are the Jews and the Gentiles, who perished and failed together, fulfilling what is said in the Psalms: "Save me, Lord, for the godly one is gone."
But the third part is the believers, both from the Jewish and Gentile peoples, who are left for life and salvation.
"And I will bring the third part through the fire, and will refine them as silver is refined, and will test them as gold is tested."
That third part, which will be left in the land, will be brought through the fire of tribulation, and will be tested and afflicted; not to be consumed, but to be tested like gold and silver, so they may be able to say with the Psalmist: "You tested us, God," etc.
Or they will be brought through the fire which the Lord sent on the earth, and of which it is said: "He will baptize you with the Holy Spirit and fire."
So they will be brought through the fire of the Holy Spirit, so that whatever in them is fragile and fluid may dry up and be solidified, so that no adversities can overcome them.
"He will call on my name, and I will answer him. I will say: You are my people; and he will say: The Lord is my God."
When He says, "The children have been proven and the Lord has turned His hand to them," and through them the whole crowd of nations has believed, then the people who believe in Him will call.
That is, they will call Christ by His name, which is Jesus, meaning Savior. This is the holy name, called Jesus, the savior of all ages.
God Himself, showing that their faith and devotion are pleasing to Him, will say, "You are My people, whom I have known by name," and the people will reply, "The Lord is my God."
Chapter Fourteen
Behold, the days of the Lord are coming, and your plunder will be divided in your midst.
I will gather all nations to Jerusalem for battle.
The city will be captured, the houses plundered, and the women violated.
Half of the city will go into captivity, but the rest of the people will not be taken from the city.
After the prophet introduced the words of God the Father about the passion of the Lord, he then speaks about the destruction of Jerusalem from the voice of the same Lord, to show that this destruction happened because of the Lord's death.
The days he warns about refer to the time Isaiah mentions:
"The day of the Lord is full of indignation, and wrath and fury to make the nations desolate," clearly referring to the time of the final captivity.
When it says, "The plunder will be divided in the midst of the captured city," it means not only will Jerusalem be taken, but all sorts of atrocities will be committed there.
The houses of the inhabitants will be plundered, and the women violated, causing greater pain to their husbands who could not help their wives, which is the most brutal act of hostile cruelty.
The Lord will go out and fight against those nations, as He fought in the day of battle.
His feet will stand on that day on the Mount of Olives, which is opposite Jerusalem to the east.
When we hear about God going out or standing, or anything like that, we should not imagine a body or any physical movement.
God is incorporeal, as the Apostle says: "To the King of ages," etc.
And in the Gospel, the Lord says: "God is spirit."
So when the Lord is described in the Scriptures as standing or walking, or having human limbs, it should be understood according to the variety of causes.
He is said to go out or rise up when He delivers the saints placed in tribulation or when He condemns their persecutors with just vengeance.
Therefore, the Prophet says, "The Lord will go out," meaning He will reveal His mercy and gentleness, which He has by nature, by forgiving sins.
Since He is naturally sweet, He becomes bitter because of our faults, as He seems bitter to us who suffer evil for our sins.
The Lord, who is always the same, speaks through the Prophet: "I am God, and I do not change." He is now said to go out and fight as in the day of battle, when He fought for the people of Israel and drowned Pharaoh.
And His feet will stand. Standing implies fighting and helping. Therefore, the feet of the Lord will stand for and with those for whom He fought. He also walks and moves for those He is angry with, as we read about Adam, after whose sin the Lord was walking in the breeze after noon. However, He stood not in the valley, but on the Mount of Olives, a place of light, peace, and mercy, which also gets its name from mercy.
This mountain is also to the east of Jerusalem, from where the sun of justice rises for us. Hence the prophet says: "For you who fear my name, the sun of justice will rise, and healing will be in its wings." This Mount of Olives is Christ, planted with those olives, about which it is said in the psalm: "Your children are like young olive plants." He Himself is the rising splendor of the Father.
For just as He is the door and the doorkeeper, the way through which we come to Him, so He is the one who stands, the mountain on which He stands. And the Mount of Olives will be split in half from the east to the west by a very large valley, and the middle of the mountain will be separated to the north and to the south. The Mount of Olives, which we said signifies Christ, though always being the same, will be split, that is, it will make a division of two peoples through the middle; the part that is split to the east represents the Church, in which olives from the nations are planted, one of which says: "But I am like a green olive tree," and so on.
The other middle part, split to the west, with a large valley, represents the people of circumcision, following the letter to the west. And it is not simply said to be split, but it is added: "by a very large valley," which is a great chasm of perdition; about which the prophet Micah says: "I will take away its stones into the valley," meaning Jerusalem, "and I will uncover its foundations."
And the middle of the mountain will split toward the north, and its middle toward the south.
When the Mount of Olives is split by a great chasm, one part of the chasm will face north and the other part will face south.
Suddenly, in that same chasm, another chasm will break open, splitting one part to the north and the other to the south, forming a four-sided chasm that extends in four directions of the world.
You will flee to the valley of their mountains, because the valley will reach the nearest point.
There were two mountains, the Temple Mount and Mount Zion, called the mountains of God.
This means you will flee to the valley of their mountains.
The next part, "Because the valley of the mountains will reach the nearest point," shows how the valley, split by mountains on both sides, will extend to the Temple Mount, which is holy, drawing its chasm there.
You will flee as you fled from the earthquake in the days of Uzziah, king of Judah. This refers to the time when Uzziah, also called Azariah, tried to unlawfully claim the priesthood. Because of this, he was struck with leprosy and expelled from the temple by the priests; due to this impiety, an earthquake occurred.
The prophet Amos mentions this earthquake at the beginning of his book, saying: The words of Amos, who was among the shepherds of Tekoa, which he saw concerning Israel in the days of Uzziah, king of Judah, two years before the earthquake. According to the literal tradition of the Hebrews, they believe all these events will be fulfilled at the coming of Christ. Now, let's see what the spiritual understanding of the Church's teachers contains: we have said that the Mount of Olives signifies the Lord Christ. When this mountain is divided into east and west, it means the nations (designated by the east) are chosen, and the Jews (understood by the west) are rejected.
Another split will occur between the northern and southern parts, with the north joining the west and the south joining the east.
Circumcision will stand on the left, and the Christian people on the right.
Through the left, the coldest north and icy wind, the devil is understood as the head of all the reprobates, who are to be placed on the left in judgment.
On the other hand, the south, which is the right, is always illuminated by the light and heat of the sun.
The saints are depicted as being fervent in charity and shining with the grace of the true sun, and they are to be placed on the right of the judge.
Hence, the Bride in the Song of Songs says: "Rise up, north wind, and come, south wind," desiring the cold north, that is, the devil, to depart, and the south, that is, the fervor of love, to come. And it is said through Habakkuk: "God will come from the south."
Therefore, when there has been such a division of two peoples, and some are separated to the east and south, others to the north and west, we are commanded to flee to the valley of the mountains of God, that is, to the two Testaments. The valley, which was first made of both mountains, will be joined to the nearest one, or, as the Seventy translated, to the house of God, namely paradise, and the heavenly Jerusalem.
"Up to the nearest" signifies that the two Testaments are joined to each other, but not completely one in all things, but rather close. We have lost much from the old law, nor do we observe it in the New. Just as the earthquake under King Uzziah terrified the hearts of mortals, so too will the separation of the east and the west, Gentiles and Jews, and again the association of those believing in vain faith, which the conjunction of the division of the east and south designated, turn the minds into amazement and fear, admiring the unfathomable abyss of God's judgments.
But when this has happened, and Jews and Gentiles have been united as one, then the Lord my God will come to judgment and all the saints with him. And it will be on that day, there will not be light, but cold and frost, and it will be one day known to the Lord, neither day nor night, and in the evening time there will be light.
When the Lord comes for judgment, as John says in Revelation:
"Behold, he will come with the clouds," meaning with his ministering angels, apostles, and prophets.
On that day, there will be no light, only cold and frost, as the love in everyone grows cold and the warmth of faith fades.
Once all the damned have carried their cold and frost into Hell, there will be one perpetual day for the saints, neither day nor night, with no alternation.
This day is known to the Lord, for the Lord is the light for all the elect, as Isaiah says:
"The sun shall no longer be your light by day, nor will the brightness of the moon shine on you, but the Lord will be your everlasting light."
And the Psalmist says: "Better is one day," etc.
In the evening, there will be light; when evening and darkness obscure all the damned, there will be light for God's holy elect.
Therefore, that day is known to the Lord; he cannot be unaware of what he created. But when it says: "Known to the Lord," it means it is unknown to men and even to the angels, as the Lord says: "Of that day no one knows, neither the angels."
On that day: "Living waters will flow out of Jerusalem; half will go to the eastern sea, and half to the western sea, in summer and in winter."
And the Lord will be king over all the earth.
The eastern sea, according to the letter, is called the Dead Sea, which in Greek is "λίμνη ἀσφάλτου", meaning the lake of asphalt, and we call it the Dead Sea because nothing can live in it.
The western sea is called the Tyrrhenian Sea, which leads to Egypt and borders Palestine.
This means that the waters flowing out of Jerusalem, half will go towards the east into the Dead Sea, into which the Jordan flows; the other half will flow into the western sea, known as the last sea, because it marks the end of Judea.
In summer and winter, these waters will neither freeze from the winter's frost nor dry up from the summer's heat, but will always flow abundantly.
When this happens, the Lord will be king over all the earth.
According to the mystical sense, the waters that flow from Jerusalem, which is from the Church, represent the teachings of the Savior.
As the Prophet says, "From Zion shall go forth the law," etc.
Half of these waters will go to the eastern sea, which refers to the Jewish people who first received the light of divine knowledge from the apostles and through them were led to faith.
The other half will go to the western sea, meaning the nations of the Gentiles.
By these regions of the east and west, we understand all parts of the world where the waters of divine knowledge have spread.
Hence the Lord says, "Many will come from the east and the west and will recline at the table with Abraham," etc.
We can also interpret the eastern sea and the last sea as representing both the Testament of the Law and the Gospel, which must be sweetened by the river of the Savior, meaning the spiritual sense, and lose the bitterness of the western letter.
These waters will be present in summer and winter, because the heavenly doctrine does not stop flowing either in prosperity, represented by summer, or in the adversity of persecution, represented by winter.
It should be noted that in the Septuagint it is not "in winter," but "in spring and in summer," and therefore some refer the living waters to baptism, which is generally celebrated by the whole Church in spring and summer, that is, at Easter and Pentecost.
On that day, the Lord will be one, and His name one: and the whole land will return as far as the desert, from the hill of Rimmon to the south of Jerusalem: and it will be exalted, and will dwell in its place from the gate of Benjamin to the place of the first gate, and to the corner gate: and from the tower of Hananel to the king's winepresses.
And they will dwell there, and there will no longer be a curse, but Jerusalem will dwell securely.
All these things about the construction of earthly Jerusalem and the flow of waters to both seas, the Jews and the heretical Judaizers, whom they call Chiliasts, promise themselves from the number of 1,000 years, during which they think they will reign happily with their Christ at the end of the world.
It is said that when Christ reigns in Jerusalem, adorned with gold and gems, there will no longer be idols or diverse worship.
There will be one Lord, and He alone will be named.
The whole earth will return to its ancient state, with all the land uncultivated and deserted.
Places are mentioned, from where Jerusalem is to be built, from the hill of Rhemmon to the south of Jerusalem.
It will be exalted as before, from the gate of Benjamin to the gate of the corners, and from the tower of Ananehel to the king's winepresses.
There will be no curse, no fear, no enemy attack; Jerusalem will sit secure and at peace.
The word "anathema" is Greek, and in Latin, it means alienation. The term comes from things that people, making vows, would attach to temples, alienating them from themselves from placing "above" or "suspending."
These events are suspected to happen literally, but let us explore the mystical sense. Interpret what they fabricate about the earthly Jerusalem as referring to the heavenly and celestial one. When the Lord Jesus is King over all the earth and His name is one, He alone will be invoked and worshipped as God, with all false religion removed. What the Psalmist says to the Lord will be fulfilled: "O Lord, our Lord." The whole earth will return to the desert. The unbelieving Jewish nation will be as the nations once were, called the desert, without the knowledge of God. But the nations believing in Christ will have the place with God that the Jews once had.
Thus, it is said through Isaiah: "Lebanon will be turned into Carmel, and Carmel will be counted as a forest." It will return from the hill of Rhemmon to the south of Jerusalem.
Rhemmon means "high" or "pomegranate," symbolizing that the Church, which is Jerusalem, will rise from the desert to the hills and from the hills to the heights, advancing from strength to strength.
Not stopping there, it will reach the southern region, where the warmth of love and the splendor of eternal divine vision reside. As the Psalmist says: "I will be satisfied when your glory is revealed."
Rhemmon also means "pomegranate," a tree with beautiful fruit full of seeds contained in various cells with membranous divisions and a red rind.
It is said to heal stomach heat, cleanse a corrupted stomach, and benefit all the internal organs.
This beauty of the fruit represents the Church in the blush of modest chastity, in the order of the seeds, and in the ranks and members of the entire ecclesiastical body distributed by each office.
From the hill of Rhemmon, the boundaries of the Church begin, starting from humility and the lesser, so that the ecclesiastical order is built with certain advancements.
It will rise, starting from the hills, and will dwell in its place in the station of perfection.
About this place, the Psalmist says: "In the place of pasture, there he put me."
It follows: from the gate of Benjamin to the place of the former gate.
Benjamin means "son of the right hand," because the holy Church begins with virtue, which the right hand signifies, and reaches the former gate, that is, faith, so that through it we may enter the remaining virtues.
Immediately, the gate of the corners appears, representing Christ the cornerstone, which joins two walls.
On this stone are built other cornerstones, namely the apostles and apostolic men, containing the remaining corners of the Church, to whom Paul speaks: "You are fellow citizens with the saints and members of the household of God."
The Church is also built from the tower of Hananel, which means "most pleasing to God," the foundation of faith, hope, and charity. The Psalmist rejoiced to have reached this place, saying: "You led me because you became my hope, a tower of strength from the enemy's face."
Nothing pleases God more than this tower.
From here, the construction reaches the king's wine presses, where the harvest of Christ, which He first trod, is pressed.
As Isaiah says, "I have trodden the wine press alone." In these wine presses, the clusters of the martyrs, who follow in the footsteps of Christ's suffering, are trodden. Just as He laid down His life for them, they too do not fear death out of love for Him. Therefore, when the city of God, built up, reaches the wine presses of Christ the King, there will no longer be an anathema, that is, a curse or alienation, but Jerusalem will be secure and confident: for "Blessed is the man who trusts in the Lord."
And this will be the plague with which the Lord will strike all the nations that fought against Jerusalem: the flesh of each person standing on their feet will rot away, their eyes will rot in their sockets, and their tongue will rot in their mouths. It clearly shows that all the opinions the Jews have about earthly Jerusalem are in vain. For the Romans, who fought against Jerusalem most recently, utterly destroyed it and suffered nothing like this. However, we can say about the persecutors of the Church, who fought against it with all their might, that these things have often been fulfilled in them even physically. Without mentioning the torments they endured in hell after death, even in this life, the flesh of many rotted away, their eyes decayed in their sockets, and their tongues dissolved into stench and pus.
Spiritually, those who stand on their feet and say with the Psalmist: "The Lord set my feet upon a rock," have their carnal vices washed away, so that spiritual virtues may arise. The eyes, which once wandered through lust, fall so that better ones may be placed, and they may say: "To you I lift up my eyes, you who dwell in the heavens." The blasphemous tongue against God will fail, so that it may be reborn to glorify God. Thus, the scourges of God are proven not to be of cruelty, but of mercy, so that, with the evils uprooted, good may grow.
In that day, there will be a great commotion from the Lord among them.
A man will seize the hand of his neighbor, and his hand will be raised against the hand of his neighbor.
These things that the Jews and Judaizing heretics take literally, we should spiritually interpret as referring to the happiness of the Church.
When their enemies are subdued and accept faith in Christ, there will be a commotion and amazement at such a sudden change of events.
Then a man will seize the hand of his neighbor, and their hands will join together, as they give each other the right hand of mutual fellowship in the faith of Christ.
As new recruits, they will swear to remain steadfast in His worship and religion.
What follows: "But Judas will fight against Jerusalem," signifies that many of those who previously confessed the name of Christ, compelled by the necessity of persecution, will act against the Church. Although in the Septuagint interpreters it is not written as "He will fight against Jerusalem," but "He will be prepared in Jerusalem," meaning that those confessing the Lord will be prepared in the Church to fight against its adversaries. Then the wealth of all the nations around will be gathered, understood as being in the Church: gold, which means wisdom, and silver, which means speech; and many garments, representing the diversity of virtues with which the Church is adorned.
And thus, there will be the downfall of the horse, mule, camel, donkey, and all the animals that were in those camps, just like this downfall. All the evils that previously fought against the Church are foretold to fall, so that good things may suddenly arise. The one who was previously an impatient horse for lust, in him lust falls, and chastity rises, and he begins to have the Lord as his rider. Those who were previously sterile mules, not having children of good works, are overturned and produce spiritual offspring, and it is said to them: "Your sons will be like new olive plants." Camels, who are weighed down by a heavy hump, chew the cud but do not divide the hoof, signify those who are oppressed by serious sins.
They read the Scriptures but neglect what is written there.
They point out the Jews, who meditate on the law of God but do not divide the hoof because they do not believe in the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
They are unclean like donkeys, not resisting the passions of their flesh.
It is good for all of these that what was wrong in them should fall, so that, rising up, they may receive the gentle God within themselves, who will lead them to the heavenly Jerusalem.
And all who are left from all the nations that came against Jerusalem will go up year by year to worship the King, the Lord of hosts, and to celebrate the Feast of Tabernacles.
The Feast of Tabernacles, which is called scenopegia in Greek, was celebrated in the seventh month, on the fifteenth day, in memory of the time when they lived in tents in the desert for forty years, where there were no houses.
And we, mystically: as long as we are in the struggle and know we are strangers and guests on the earth, we live in tents, confessing that we do not have a lasting city here, but we seek the one to come.
We long for it with all our heart, saying with the Psalmist: "Woe to me, for my sojourning has been prolonged."
But when we reach our homeland, we will be able to say: "Blessed are those who dwell in your house," and: "One thing I have asked of the Lord, this I will seek," etc. Then it will be fitting to celebrate the Feast of Tabernacles, always remembering the time of our liberation and that eternal rest, which is promised to us after the ages of the world as in one Sabbath.
Taking for ourselves branches of the most beautiful trees, that is, the wisdom, into unfading greenery, in whose praise it is said, "It is a tree of life to those who take hold of it." Also, branches of palm trees, in which the sign of victory and reward is contained. Branches of trees with thick foliage, which the Jews think is myrtle, so that we may mortify in ourselves the incentives of vices, which is also signified by the willows of the brook, which we are likewise commanded to take.
Doctors say that if anyone drinks a mixture of willow flower and water, it will cool down their natural heat and dry up the poisons of lust, so they will no longer reproduce.
But whoever wants to celebrate the Feast of Tabernacles should make shelters from such trees.
And it is said that anyone from the families of the earth who does not go up to Jerusalem to worship the King, the Lord of hosts, will receive no rain.
The heavenly Jerusalem is the city of our Lord Jesus Christ, of which the Apostle says: "The Jerusalem above is free, and she is our mother." Anyone who wishes to come to this city must ascend, for it is situated on a high mountain, not in a low place. The Lord says, "A city set on a hill cannot be hidden."
Therefore, the citizens of Jerusalem go up to worship the King, the Lord of hosts. But those who are not citizens, but from the families and tribes, such as the Jews and heretics, have not gone up, and therefore the rain of apostolic preaching has not come upon them. About them, it is said: "I will command the clouds not to rain on it."
And if the family of Egypt does not go up and does not come, there will be no rain upon them. Instead, there will be the plague with which the Lord strikes all the nations that do not go up to celebrate the Feast of Tabernacles. Egypt means darkness or sorrow. Therefore, whoever is in Egypt, that is, established in the darkness of ignorance of God or of crimes, cannot go up to Jerusalem, not having the guiding light, which says: "Walk while you have the light." They cannot have joy from the hope of future things. Therefore, the rain of heavenly blessing will not come upon them. This will be the sin of Egypt and the sin of all the nations that do not go up to celebrate the Feast of Tabernacles.
It is designated that the Ammonites, Moabites, Assyrians, Chaldeans, and other nations who choose to remain in errors and do not want to leave their land to come to the fellowship of the Church and become Israelites and citizens of the heavenly Jerusalem.
The following day will be holy to the Lord, even what is on the horse's bridle.
The Hebrews, according to their custom, say that after their king comes with justice and rules in golden Jerusalem, with peace prevailing, there will be no need for horses or cavalry.
The bridles and adornments of the trappings will be dedicated to the worship of the Lord.
When it says: on the horse's bridle, we should understand all warlike adornments.
In a mystical sense, the bridle represents the discipline of heavenly teaching, which restrains raging lust and wantonness.
The Psalmist says: With bit and bridle, restrain their jaws.
This bridle is placed in the horse's mouth so that, leaving behind the winding paths of error, it walks the straight path and offers gentle backs for the Savior to sit on.
Such adornments and such a bridle, decorated with gold and silver—that is, with sense and eloquence—are holy to the Lord and specially consecrated to His worship.
Indeed, what is read in the little book of the discovery of the Holy Cross: that this was fulfilled when Helena Augusta, mother of Emperor Constantine, ordered the nails of the Lord's cross to be made into bits for the bridle of the king's horse.
Blessed Jerome says this with a pious sense, but it is laughable.
And the pots in the house of the Lord will be like the bowls before the altar.
Every pot in Jerusalem and Judah will be holy to the Lord of hosts.
Pots, that is, bronze vessels in which the meat of the sacrifices was cooked, will be as holy and worthy of reverence as the golden bowls in which libations and spices were offered to the Lord.
This shows that all carnal tradition and observance of the Jews should be converted to spiritual, and the virulence of the flesh should be replaced by the spices of spiritual understanding.
About these bowls, John says he saw twenty-four elders having harps and bowls full of incense, which he says are the prayers of the saints.
And in the Song of Songs according to the Seventy: My beloved went down to his garden to the bowls of spices, to feed in the gardens and to gather lilies.
The bowls are containers of the souls of the saints, filled with virtues and the scents of pure prayers, from which a good aroma spreads daily to the Lord.
When the pots are turned into bowls, and the carnal is transformed into the spiritual, then every pot will be consecrated to the Lord in Jerusalem and in Judah, which symbolize the Church, the vision of peace, and where those who praise the Lord are.
All those who offer sacrifices will come, take from them, and cook in them.
There will be no merchant in the house of the Lord of hosts on that day.
When the pots are turned into bowls, and carnal sense is transformed into spiritual understanding, all those making sacrifices to the Lord will come, making themselves an acceptable burnt offering.
They will cook the flesh of the sacrifices, so that whatever is carnal and fleeting will be cooked away by the fire of the Holy Spirit.
The law forbids us to eat the raw meat of the Passover lamb, meaning we should not celebrate Passover carnally with the Jews.
A fragrance of good aroma will emanate from the bowls, so much so that no one will dare to do business in the house of the Lord or sell oxen, sheep, and doves there.
They will fear that just as He drove everyone out of the temple with a whip of cords, He may now, coming spiritually, exclude wicked merchants from the temple of the heavenly Jerusalem.