Letter One to Bishop Paternus
On the judgments, accusations, and defenses of sacred orders. 1.
Those who criticize or support enemies should be excluded from episcopal accusations.
2.
Individuals of lower rank should not accuse those of higher rank.
3.
In uncertain matters, definite judgments should not be made against a cleric in the province.
4.
Clerics should carry out their duties responsibly.
5.
Leaders should behave appropriately with an accused bishop.
6.
Church judges should not deliver judgments without the presence of the person involved, and the deceitful words of a traitor should not be considered.
To my dearest and most beloved fellow bishop Paternus, Bishop Felix sends greetings in the Lord.
Your writings have filled me with great joy in the Lord, as they clearly demonstrate your deep love for the Catholic faith and your strong aversion to heretical errors.
Heresy is indeed very impious and an enemy of the gospel truth, attempting not only to damage a part but to undermine the very foundations of the Christian religion.
Whoever it ensnares falls not only into this vice but into many others as well.
With the persuasion of the ancient enemy, they become not only persecutors of the Church but also of its priests.
Therefore, let us unite in our efforts to correct and confront such individuals, striving to liberate the Church, its faithful, and the priests of the Lord from their enemies.
Our almighty redeemer will grant us the strength to love and pursue justice.
He will provide us with unity of Spirit, even to those far from him, through whose craftsmanship the Church is built like an ark.
With its four sides of the world, bound by the framework of incorruptible wood and the pitch of charity, it remains undisturbed by any adversity or external force.
However, just as it's important to seek the grace of governance to keep external disturbances at bay, it's equally crucial, dear brother, to pray earnestly for Providence to clear away our inner burdens.
The adversary, the devil, who rages against the humble, prowls around like a roaring lion, looking for someone to devour.
First Peter five.
As we observe, he no longer merely circles the sheepfolds but fiercely attacks some vital members of the Church.
There's no doubt that unless the entire group of wise shepherds, united by the Lord, comes together, the whole fold could quickly be torn apart, though we hope this never happens.
Therefore, we remove from episcopal accusation those detractors who should be eradicated by divine authority, along with the supporters of enemies.
Likewise, let no one in high positions be disturbed or destroyed by the accusations of the lesser.
Hadrian, column 19.
Nor should a fixed sentence be judged in a definite matter.
Saint Gregory, letter 30, book 8.
Nor should any judgment be considered valid unless it is carried out in an orderly manner.
If anyone believes a cleric should be accused of any crimes, they should present their case in the province where the accused resides.
Hadrian, column 8.
The accused shouldn't be dragged elsewhere or farther for judgment.
If the accused finds the judges suspicious, they may appeal to the primates.
The primates, when examining the accused bishop, shouldn't issue a condemnation before consulting apostolic authority, unless the accused admits his guilt or is convicted by innocent and canonically examined witnesses.
Anastasius in the constitution, book 9, title 40, code Theodosian, 11, question 3, "It is null for the bishops."
Otherwise, we consider the condemnation of bishops to be null and unjust, and therefore it should be reconsidered by the synod so that those oppressed in any case may receive support from all.
Let the judges of the Church take care not to pronounce a sentence in the absence of the person whose case is being discussed, for it will be null.
They will also be accountable for the actions of the brothers in their presence.
Council of Carthage, 4th, chapter 28.
The voice or accusation of a traitor should not be considered.
No one knows a debtor better than someone who has suffered their injury and wickedness.
Theodosian Code, constitution three, title ten, book ten.
Those who wish to live piously in Christ must endure reproach from the wicked and be seen as fools or insane.
Prosper, sentence thirty-two, from Augustine on Psalm one hundred twenty-two.
They lose present goods to gain invisible and future ones.
The scorn and mockery from such people will eventually be turned back on those who attack them.
Their abundance will turn into poverty, and their arrogance into shame.
The adversities faced by the just are not punishments for wrongdoing but tests of virtue.
Just as gold is refined to become better, the just person becomes purer and dearer to God through patient endurance of affliction.
As Truth itself says in the Gospel of Matthew, chapter five:
Blessed are those who are persecuted for righteousness' sake, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.
The Lord speaks of such people through Isaiah, saying, Isaiah, chapter sixty-six:
Hear the word of the Lord, you who tremble at His word.
Your brothers who hate you and cast you out for My name's sake said: Let the Lord be glorified, that we may see your joy; but they shall be ashamed.
A voice of the people from the city, a voice from the temple, a voice of the Lord rendering recompense to His enemies.
Before she was in labor, she gave birth; before her pain came, she delivered a male child.
Who has ever heard of such a thing?
And who has seen anything like this?
Shall the earth be made to give birth in one day?
Or shall a nation be born at once, since Zion has labored and brought forth her children?
Shall I bring to the point of birth and not cause delivery?
says the Lord.
Shall I, who cause others to give birth, be barren?
says the Lord your God.
Rejoice with Jerusalem, and be glad with her, all you who love her.
Rejoice with her, all you who mourn over her, so that you may nurse and be satisfied from her comforting breast.
Drink deeply and delight in her glorious abundance.
For this is what the Lord says:
"I will extend peace to her like a river and the wealth of nations like an overflowing stream.
You will be nursed, carried on her arm, and bounced on her knees.
As a mother comforts her child, so will I comfort you, and you will be comforted in Jerusalem.
You will see this, and your heart will rejoice, and your bones will flourish like grass.
The Lord's hand will be made known to his servants, and his indignation will be shown against his enemies.
For see, the Lord will come with fire, and his chariots are like a whirlwind, to unleash his anger with fury and his rebuke with flames of fire.
For the Lord will execute judgment by fire and by his sword on all flesh, and those slain by the Lord will be many.
Those who sanctify and purify themselves to go into the gardens, following one who is among them, eating pig's flesh, detestable things, and mice, will all perish together," declares the Lord.
"And I, knowing their works and their thoughts, am coming to gather all nations and tongues, and they will come and see my glory.
I will set a sign among them, and I will send those who survive to the nations: to the sea, to Africa, to Lydia, skilled in archery, to Italy, and Greece, to distant islands that have not heard of me or seen my glory.
They will proclaim my glory among the nations, and they will bring all your brothers, from all the nations, as an offering to the Lord on horses, in chariots, in litters, on mules, and on camels to my holy mountain Jerusalem," says the Lord.
"Just as the Israelites bring their offerings in clean vessels to the house of the Lord, I will also select some of them to be priests and Levites," says the Lord.
"For as the new heavens and the new earth that I will make will endure before me," declares the Lord, "so will your descendants and your name endure.
From one new moon to another and from one Sabbath to another, all mankind will come and bow down before me," says the Lord.
They'll go out and see the bodies of those who have rebelled against me.
Their worm will not die, and their fire won't be extinguished, making them a spectacle for everyone to see.
What else do the detractors do,
Saint Gregory, letter forty-five, book eight,
but blow dust into the air and throw dirt into their own eyes?
The more they spread their gossip, the less truth they perceive.
However, such people, dearest brother, must be endured and corrected because they are blind guides leading the blind,
Saint Matthew, chapter fifteen.
I've briefly answered your questions, dearest brother, which we command you and all bishops to follow regularly.
Yet, brother, we urge you to work diligently for the stability of the Church and its priests,
to uphold the order of the holy Roman and apostolic Church in all things, and not to allow the decrees of the saints to be violated.
Instead, instruct all those you can, so that you may present fruitful harvests to the Lord.
Farewell.
Given on the fifth of June, in the year of the consuls Claudius and Aurelianus.
Letter Two: On the Authority of the Judge of the Apostolic See, and on Accused Bishops
Bishop Felix to all bishops established throughout the provinces of Gaul, greetings in the Lord.
There's no doubt that God is the source of good works and spiritual endeavors, as Saint Leo mentions in letter thirty-two.
He inspires our minds and supports our actions.
Therefore, your writings brought me joy, reflecting your strong efforts and the integrity of your faith and devotion.
However, your affliction and deep sorrow have greatly saddened me.
I read your letters with sadness and went through your sorrowful writings with appropriate grief.
Just as the peace of the Churches, the harmony of the priests, and the tranquility of the people bring us joy, the suffering of our brothers deeply affects us.
But do not be overly sorrowful, as Saint Gregory advises in letter forty-five, book eight.
As Truth itself says: If you were of this world, the world would love what is its own; but because you are not of this world, but I have chosen you out of the world, therefore the world hates you, meaning, the lovers of the world.
This is from the Gospel of Saint John, chapter fifteen.
No matter what others say or do against you, always keep your faith intact and maintain a pure conscience, so that your spirit and soul may be preserved on the day of the Lord, as written in First Thessalonians, chapter five.
We have called upon more than seventy of our brothers and fellow bishops to support you, and we have decided to regularly address these matters, which are detailed below.
Your letters, read aloud for everyone, contained many complaints and grievances, as you know, and regarding your decrees about the accusations against bishops, the holy synod stated:
These are the rules we want to firmly uphold in the future to protect against the plots of malicious people who indiscriminately attack the Church and its clergy, and we intend to preserve them:
If a bishop is accused by credible accusers, after he has been approached in a charitable manner to amend the issue, and he refuses to correct it, the case should not be immediately advanced.
Instead, it should be brought canonically to the highest leaders who must regularly convene a council in a suitable location within the same province, at an appropriate time, either in autumn or summer, so that all the bishops of the province can hear it.
If he is regularly summoned, unless illness or another serious necessity prevents him, he must attend, because it is not permitted to accuse beyond the province's boundaries before the hearing is requested.
If he has been stripped of his or the Church's resources entrusted to him, or God forbid, expelled from his see or kept away from his flock in any manner:
Then, canonically, before he is restored to his former state with all the privileges of his honor, and all possessions taken from him through his enemies' plots are restored by law, he cannot be summoned or judged, unless he chooses to come willingly for his own reasons, but not to be judged.
Let no one be asked to respond until everything lost due to his enemies' suggestions is fully restored to his authority by the honorable council in a legal manner.
The bishop should be returned to his former position with all honor, and once everything is organized and settled, he should handle his own affairs freely and securely for a long time.
Then, within four, five, or seven months, depending on what's possible for him, and not before, he should be summoned to the council at the right time in a legitimate and canonical manner to address the issue.
If it seems fair, he should respond to the accusations.
It's crucial to ensure he's not forced to respond before these conditions are met, as disputes should always be avoided.
Depriving a bishop of his bishopric, as noted in the Council of Africa, chapter eighty-seven, before the outcome of his case is clear, cannot be considered just by any Christian because such presumption is sacrilege, and the author of such acts is sacrilegious.
If the bishop is ill or held back by some serious necessity, he should send a representative to the synod on his behalf.
He should not be suspended from communion if accused of a crime, as stated in the Council of Carthage three, canon seven, unless he is summoned by letter to present his case on a specified day by elected judges and fails to attend, unless some necessity prevents him within the aforementioned months or longer, as dictated by the case.
If both parties come to present their case, since one should not be heard without the other, it must be inquired in judgment about the character, faith, and suspicion of the accusers or their intention in doing so.
They should not be admitted unless they are men of good character and correct faith, those who are free from all suspicion and are clearly of good life, and not notorious.
If the accusers' character, as referenced in the third question, is found to be blameworthy by the bishops, as noted in the same Council of Carthage, they should not be admitted to argue, unless they want to assert their own causes, though not criminal ones or ecclesiastical ones.
A person with a bad reputation cannot serve as a manager or representative.
If the opponent is absent, the accuser should not be heard, and no verdict given by the judge in the absence of the other party will be valid.
No one can accuse or be accused by someone else without being present, and relatives cannot be admitted for this purpose.
Therefore, no one should be moved from one province to another or to a county unless the judge handling the appeal reports it, meaning the authority should always follow the forum.
If anyone feels that a judge is biased against them, they should voice their appeal, which should not be denied to anyone.
We generally prohibit foreign judgments because it is inappropriate for locals to be judged by outsiders when they should have judges from among themselves whom they have chosen.
These decisions, brothers, have been unanimously agreed upon in the synod for your benefit and the protection of all co-bishops, so that if some misguided individuals, deceived by falsehoods, wish to accuse you, they may read or hear these rulings, repent, and return to unity.
And what was once a matter of revenge will turn into glory.
For undoubtedly, there are many who, as the apostle says, turn away from the truth because their ears itch for new stories and they gravitate towards harm.
The same apostle speaks of the ignorance of unbelievers: If they had known, they would never have crucified the Lord of glory.
Similarly, if they had known and loved the Lord perfectly, they would never have disturbed His servants, nor persecuted them with words or deeds.
Reconciled to God through the death of His Son, why do we pursue our brothers?
Why do we disrupt the peace of God's Church and trouble those who should be serving it?
The martyrs suffered, as mentioned in the same Council, yet their souls remained unharmed despite the suffering of their bodies.
The mouth of Truth assures us: "Do not fear those who kill the body but cannot kill the soul" (Matthew, Chapter 10).
We must understand that if the souls of martyrs cannot be extinguished by suffering, even when their bodies are destroyed, then neither should the souls of preachers and teachers be persecuted or distracted from serving God, for they too do not perish with the body.
These disruptors of the Church not only commit these wrongs but also curse the memories of the martyrs (Council of Gangra, Chapter 20, interpretation by Dionysius).
Therefore, in the aforementioned synod, we decree and command you and all Churches to celebrate Masses in honor of the martyrs.
This ensures that their memories cannot be erased by such people, nor can their veneration be hindered.
But you, brothers, do not be greatly troubled or distressed; rather, be strengthened in the Lord and in the power of His glory (Ephesians, Chapter 6).
Meanwhile, hold on to these decrees for your support, with apostolic authority.
Know that we are always ready to provide whatever you may need, with the Lord's help, even unto death if necessary.
However, those who oppose, with God as the author, will perish, and you will stand firm if your labor is not in vain but full of faith and charity.
"Woe," said the prophet, "to him who gives his friend a drink, mixing in his own poison" (Habakkuk, Chapter 2).
And again, the wise Solomon says, as cited in the letter of Felix the Second to the Egyptians, "He who speaks iniquity cannot hide, nor will the judgment that corrects him pass him by."
Therefore, in the minds of the wicked, there will be questioning.
But the hearing of his words will reach the Lord and lead to the correction of his iniquities.
For the ear of jealousy hears all things, and the tumult of murmurs will not be hidden (Wisdom, Chapter 1).
If they had embraced these teachings with true understanding, they wouldn't have fallen into a depraved state of mind.
By speaking with caution and reverence for God, they could have preserved the holy teachings of the fathers without causing any harm.
The sacred scripture says: "Good advice will protect you, and a good mind will guard you" (Proverbs, chapter two).
Such accusations and slanders do not come from the life-giving sources meant to lead us to eternal life.
Therefore, the blessed Apostle Paul wisely advises us: "You should not think of yourself more highly than you ought, but rather think of yourself with sober judgment" (Romans, chapter twelve), staying firm in the path of piety.
Those who ignore these teachings not only harm themselves by losing their strength, but they also leave behind a memory of their folly in their homes, unable to hide their sins.
For glory and disgrace come through speech (Ecclesiastes, chapter five), and a man's downfall lies in his words.
It is fitting that this demonstration of their reproaches be reflected in our actions, so that you no longer suffer from those who sow discord and scandals, but instead find joy in your duties and teachings.
Let them be ashamed and hasten to remove such blasphemy, unless they wish to be separated from our priestly community and cut off from the society of the entire Christian people.
Although we could have said and written more on these matters, which are found in the decrees of the apostolic see and established by the apostles and their successors, our predecessors, we decided to conclude the letter with a prayer.
Almighty God and His only-begotten Son, our Savior Christ, grant you this encouragement, so that you may assist all our brothers and fellow bishops who are struggling with various tribulations with all your strength.
By sharing in their suffering, you carry the cross of the same Lord and Savior, revealing yourselves as His true disciples before everyone.
In this way, both you and those with you may possess better things here and in the future, things which no eye has seen, nor ear heard, nor have entered into the heart of man, which God has prepared for those who love Him First Corinthians chapter two.
Through our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom and with whom there is glory to Almighty God forever and ever.
Amen.
I wish you well, dearest brothers.
Given on the ninth day before the Ides of August, in the consulship of the most illustrious men Claudius and Paternus, in the year of Christ two hundred sixty-nine, with Dionysius not yet dead.
Letter Three to Bishop Benignus
First, those who claim that the Son cannot see the Father because no one has ever seen God are mistaken.
Second, those who assert that the Son is lesser than the Father because the Father is invisible and the Son is visible are also mistaken.
To my dearest brother, Bishop Benignus, Bishop Felix sends greetings in the Lord.
Upon receiving your letters of brotherhood, in which you asked about points of faith that differed from the true faith's sacraments, I responded without hesitation, out of love for our brotherhood, as the Lord has given us.
Indeed, in times of doubt and major issues, it has always been customary to seek guidance from this holy see, instructed by the apostles through their teachings.
Therefore, you have done well to seek advice from this holy see, wanting it to strengthen and instruct you and others.
Your letters, and those of your brothers, mentioned that some people claim the Son cannot properly see the Father because it is written: "No one has ever seen God" (John, chapter 1).
Others falsely assert: "Therefore, the Son is lesser than the Father, because the Father bears witness to Him."
Some also argue that the Son is lesser than the Father because the Father is described as invisible, while the Son is proved to be visible.
These people, ignorant of the divine Scriptures and the teachings of the apostles, create such ideas from their own or distorted understanding and seek to mislead the hearts of the faithful.
Let us return to the original source, from which we teach with clearer testimonies from the writings of the Old and New Testaments that the Son has always been able to see the Father.
Solomon says: "With you is wisdom, which knows your works, which was present with you when you made the world, and knows what is pleasing in your eyes."
And the Lord in the Gospel says: "No one knows the Son except the Father, and no one knows the Father except the Son, and those to whom the Son chooses to reveal him."
And again: "No one has ever seen God, except the only begotten Son, who is in the bosom of the Father; he has made him known."
And again, he said to the Jews: You do not know him, but I know him.
If I were to say that I do not know him, I would be like you, a liar.
Also there: Whoever is from God knows him.
And again: I know him because I am from him.
See, we have taught that the Son always sees the Father.
How do they assert that the Father cannot be seen when he is known to remain in his embrace?
If you calmly consider the divine Scriptures, you will find not only the Father bearing witness to the Son, but also the entire inseparable Trinity, as the Lord himself declares, who says: I am the one who bears witness about myself, and the Father who sent me bears witness about me.
Saint John, chapter eight.
And again: If I bear witness about myself, my testimony is true because I know where I come from and where I am going.
And about the Holy Spirit: When the Advocate, the Spirit of Truth, comes, he will bear witness about me.
Saint John, chapter fifteen.
Pay attention, please, pay attention because, in these cases where the power of testimony is shown to be one, no one is judged to be greater or lesser than another.
We have said these things often because the Son is said to be visible according to the form of a human, but according to the substance of deity, he is proclaimed invisible, as testified by the Apostle Paul: Oh, the depth, he says, of the riches of the wisdom and knowledge of God!
How unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways beyond tracing out.
Romans, chapter eleven.
And in Isaiah: To whom will you compare him, since he is himself invisible?
Isaiah, chapter forty.
And also the Apostle: To me, the least of all the saints, this grace was given to preach to the Gentiles the unsearchable riches of Christ, and to enlighten everyone about what is the plan of the mystery hidden for ages, in which he created everything.
Ephesians, chapter three.
Also, he says: He is the image of the invisible God.
Colossians, chapter one.
To the Colossians, I, Paul, a minister, now rejoice in my sufferings for you.
I fill up what is lacking in Christ's afflictions in my flesh for his body, which is the Church, of which I became a minister according to the stewardship of God in the ministry of Christ, which was hidden for ages and generations.
Also there, so that their hearts may be comforted in love, in all the riches of full understanding, in the knowledge of the mystery, which is Christ, in whom all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge are hidden.
In the Book of Psalms, Chapter Seventy-Six: Your way was through the sea, your paths through the mighty waters, yet your footprints were unseen.
And in Ecclesiastes: Who can search out the wisdom of God that surpasses all things?
Also there: To whom has the root of wisdom been revealed?
And who has recognized its subtleties?
Also there: To whom has the discipline of wisdom been made known, and who has understood the vastness of its progress?
Also there: For the works of the Lord alone are marvelous, glorious, and hidden, and his works are invisible to men.
Behold, just as the Father is invisible, so also is the Son.
How then, by those who say what you have commanded, is he judged inferior to the Father because he deemed himself worthy to be seen by us in the flesh?
Do not believe such people, and teach others to turn away from their views.
Therefore, serve the Lord with fear, and rejoice with trembling.
Take hold of discipline, lest you stray from the right path.
This indeed, from the right faith, is the living tradition of the apostles.
This is true love, which is to be preached, truly loved and cherished, and confidently held by all.
This is the holy and apostolic mother of all churches.
Letter from Agatho to Emperor Constantine, Act Four of the council.
The Church of Christ, by the grace of Almighty God, has never been proven to have strayed from the path of apostolic tradition during the six ecumenical councils, nor has it succumbed to the corruptions of heretical innovations.
Instead, as it received the rule of the Christian faith from its founders, the chief apostles of Christ, it remains unblemished to the end, in accordance with the divine promise of the Lord Savior himself, who spoke to the chief of his disciples in his gospels:
"Peter," he said, "Satan has asked to sift you all like wheat. But I have prayed for you, that your faith may not fail; and when you have turned back, strengthen your brothers" (Luke twenty-two).
So let your excellent wisdom consider how good it is to persist in the mission entrusted to you, to uphold the true faith, to oppose heretics and those who are enemies of Christ, and never turn away from the path of truth.
For the Lord and Savior of all, whose faith it is, who did not hesitate to die for us, and redeemed us with his own blood, promised that the faith of blessed Peter would not fail, and urged him to strengthen his brothers: something that the apostolic pontiffs, my predecessors in humility, have confidently done, as is known to all.
Even my own smallness, though unequal and least, desires to follow in their footsteps, having received this ministry by divine favor.
Woe indeed will be to us, who have taken on the burden of this ministry, if we neglect to preach the truth of our Savior Jesus Christ, which the apostles proclaimed.
Woe will be to us if we suppress the truth in silence, which we are commanded to distribute to the money changers, that is, to teach and instruct the Christian people.
What will we say in the future judgment of Christ, if we are ashamed to preach the truth of his words?
What will become of us when Christ our God, the just judge, demands a strict account of the souls entrusted to us and of the office we have undertaken (First Corinthians nine; Matthew twenty-five)?
Therefore, brothers, I urge your love (Epistle of Saint Leo against...
I strongly urge you to be vigilant in investigating heretics and enemies of the holy Church of God as much as you can and should.
Use whatever severity is necessary to remove this plague from healthy minds, so it doesn't spread further.
Just as someone who diligently works for the salvation of the people entrusted to them will receive a worthy reward from God,
so too will they be unable to excuse themselves before the judgment seat of the Lord for negligence if they fail to protect their people against those who promote sacrilegious ideas.
This was given on the fifth of February, during the consulship of Claudius and Paternus, distinguished men.
In the year two hundred sixty-nine, with Felix not yet elected.
Letter Four to Bishop Maximus and the Clergy of Alexandria
A fragment on the divinity and humanity of Christ.
Regarding the incarnation of the Word and faith, we believe in our Lord Jesus Christ, born of the Virgin Mary, because he is the eternal Son of God.
The Son of God did not take on a man to be someone separate from himself.
Instead, being a perfect God, he also became a perfect man, incarnate from the Virgin.
Concerning the incarnation and our faith, we affirm our belief in our Lord Jesus Christ, born of the Virgin Mary, as the eternal Son of God and the Word.
He was not a man taken by God to be someone other than himself.
For the Son of God did not take on a man to be someone other than himself; but, being a perfect God, he also became a perfect man, incarnate from a virgin.