Predestined or the Heresy of the Predestinarians, and the Refutation of the Books Wrongly Attributed to Saint Augustine, distributed in three books
BOOK ONE.
This is a summary of the writings of Hyginus against the heresiarchs, the categories of Epiphanius against the sects, and the expositions of Philaster, who translated these from Greek to Latin, published when the Arians were condemned.
First Hyginus, then Polycrates, Africanus, Hesiod, Epiphanius, and Philaster; these men wrote about various heresies at different times.
The first heresy began with Simon, who claimed that chastity does not pertain to God, that God did not create the world, and other such things.
He was publicly defeated by the blessed and holy apostle Peter, to the point that he fell at Peter's feet and could not rise again.
The second heresy was that of Menander of the Menandrians, who claimed that the world was made not by God, but by angels.
Saint Linus, the second bishop after the apostle Peter, expelled them from our community and condemned them to eternal damnation.
He taught rationally, according to the holy Scriptures of the Old Testament, that the God who spoke with Moses is the creator of all things, and that there is nothing in all creation that is inherently blameworthy.
All things that are judged blameworthy are blamed for their actions, not their nature.
The third heresy was that of Basilides of the Basilidians.
They claimed that there are 365 heavens, opposing Moses, and they called the god of these heavens Abrasax.
This name, according to the Greek system of letters, sums up to this number: ΑΒΡΑΣΑΞ.
The letters are: Α equals 1, Β equals 2, Ρ equals 100, Α equals 1, Σ equals 200, Α equals 1, and Ξ equals 60.
When added together, they total 365.
The Church, considering these individuals possessed, did not condemn them through argument, but rather through expulsion.
The fourth heresy, that of the Nicolaitans, was invented by Nicolas, one of the seven deacons ordained by the apostles.
When he was reproached for his jealousy of his beautiful wife, he began to teach that one should use wives indiscriminately, not only lay people but even those who performed the duties of the priesthood.
Saint John the Apostle and Evangelist condemned these people and ordered that anyone who even spoke with them should be excluded from communion.
He taught that from the beginning of the world, chastity has greatly pleased God.
Furthermore, Christ, the Son of God, dedicated the glory of chastity to Himself, having a virgin mother and remaining a virgin Himself.
He did not permit any of His disciples to marry, even lawfully, saying: "If anyone wants to come after me, let him deny himself, take up his cross, and follow me" (Matthew 16:24).
The fifth heresy is that of the Saturninians, named after Saturninus.
He taught that seven angels made the world and introduced lust into it to perpetuate the world through sexual desire.
Blessed Thomas the Apostle of Christ condemned these teachings, reasonably asserting that the world had a beginning and thus will have an end.
Angels do not possess omnipotence and therefore could not have created the world.
Rather, the Creator of the world is the one God, whom Moses proclaimed made the heavens and the earth, the sea, and all that is in them.
The sixth heresy is that of the Gnostics, who called themselves Gnostics as if they had superior knowledge, but were considered more wretched than those previously mentioned.
Blessed Paul the Apostle reasonably taught that they do not serve God but their own belly and lust.
They are puffed up with pride, know nothing, and are sick with disputes and arguments about words.
The seventh heresy is that of the Carpocratians, founded by Carpocrates, who taught that the powers of darkness cannot be overcome except by those who have indulged in every kind of depravity.
They claimed that our Lord Jesus was born of both sexes but received a soul that knew the heavenly realms.
Denying the resurrection of the body, they condemned the prophets of the Old Testament.
They had a certain Marcellina who displayed images of Jesus, Paul, and the philosopher Pythagoras among those she was deceiving.
She made them honor these images as if they were divine and offer incense.
Blessed Barnabas, a disciple of Christ, condemned these people in Cyprus, teaching that they were ministers of Satan and that Christians should have no association with them whatsoever.
Eighth heresy: the Cerinthians, from Cerinthus.
They claimed the world was made by angels, that circumcision of the flesh was necessary, and that the precepts of the Old Testament should be followed literally.
They said Jesus was merely a man, had not yet resurrected, but would resurrect in the future.
Blessed apostle Paul condemned these people with an eternal curse in Galatia.
He also addressed them in his Epistle to the Galatians.
Ninth heresy: the Nazarenes.
They acknowledged the Son of God but kept all the rites of the Old Testament in the Jewish manner.
Blessed apostle Paul taught them to interpret the Scriptures spiritually; he found them in the churches of Galatia and declared them anathema because they did not agree with his doctrine.
Tenth heresy: the Ebionites.
They asserted that Jesus Christ was just a man and that the commandments of the law should be observed in the Jewish manner.
Luke the evangelist, finding them in the church at Antioch, condemned them, teaching that an angel had said to Mary:
"The Holy Spirit will come upon you, and the power of the Most High will overshadow you. Therefore, the holy one to be born will be called the Son of God" (Luke 1:35).
Eleventh heresy: the Valentinians, from Valentinus.
These people were spread throughout the East and severely harmed the Church of God, saying that the deep and the high were mixed together.
From these two, as from a marriage, the world emerged: they called the high one the Father and the deep one the Son, claiming He took nothing from the Virgin Mary, but passed through her like water through a stream or pipe without taking on any flesh.
They completely denied the resurrection of the flesh.
These were condemned by the blessed Zacchaeus, bishop of Caesarea.
He taught that our Lord Jesus Christ, true God and true man, passed through the virginal mysteries, from the seed of David according to the flesh.
He was truly born as a man, truly suffered, truly died, truly rose from the dead, and truly ascended into heaven.
Twelfth heresy: The Secundians.
They differ from the Valentinians only in that they add to this sect the disgrace of the body, which the so-called false chaste ones pretend to avoid.
These were condemned by Diodorus, bishop of Crete.
Thirteenth heresy: The Ptolemites, followers of Ptolemy, a disciple of Valentinus, who spread this same heresy more vigorously through debate.
He was condemned by the holy Zacchaeus, bishop of Caesarea, mentioned earlier.
However, he spread this very bad heresy through many regions of the East.
Fourteenth heresy: Invented by a certain Marcus, who denied the resurrection of the flesh and tried to establish that Christ did not truly suffer but only seemed to.
Saint Clement, bishop of Rome and a most worthy martyr of Christ, refuted him with clear and complete assertions.
He exposed Marcus before all the people in the church and condemned him to eternal damnation.
He taught that our Lord Jesus Christ was truly born and suffered, not doing anything in fantasy, and showed clearly that truth, being the enemy of falsehood, could not contain anything false.
Just as light cannot contain darkness, nor can a blessing contain a curse, nor sweetness contain bitterness.
And if these could be mixed, he taught that it is impossible for God to be mixed with lies.
Fifteenth heresy: The Colorbasians, invented by Colorbasus.
He tried to establish that all human life is placed in seven stars, and these seven Churches and seven golden lampstands.
Saint Theodotus, bishop of Pergamum, anathematized him in a synod of seven bishops.
He taught that the seven Churches are consecrated in the sevenfold spirit.
"There is one form," he said, "when it is recalled in the form that the first man had lost."
The second, when the sinner who was immaculate becomes so."
Third, when a dead body is raised from the earth.
Fourth, when a soul is freed from the confines of hell.
Fifth, when the soul rejoices in the dwelling of paradise until it receives its incorruptible body.
Sixth, when it transforms the children of Adam into children of God.
Seventh, when it makes a person a participant in the kingdom of heaven.
These are the forms of the Holy Spirit placed in the seven churches, the seven eyes, and the seven golden candlesticks.
Sixteenth, the heresy of the Heracleonites was invented by Heracleon.
It taught that a baptized person, whether just or sinful, should be considered sacred, and it claimed that sins do not harm the baptized.
It said that just as fire does not receive cold in itself, the baptized do not receive sin.
Just as fire melts snow by its presence, no matter how much snow is near, one who is baptized does not receive the guilt of sins, even if their deeds are mixed with many sins.
Heracleon began to teach this in parts of Sicily.
Against him, the bishops of Sicily, Eustachius of Lilybaeum and Theodorus of Panormus, took up the challenge.
They called for a synod of all the bishops throughout Sicily, decided to hear him out, and directed all his assertions to holy Alexander, bishop of the city.
They asked him to arrange something to refute him.
Then holy Alexander, drawing each sword of the Word of God from the sheath of divine law for each head of the hydra, composed a book against Heracleon.
He sent the fervent priest Sabinianus, who would refute him with both the writings of the bishop and his own assertions, so thoroughly that Heracleon fled in the middle of the night with the help of a ship, and no one ever knew where he ended up.
Seventeenth, the heresy of the Ophites.
They were named after the serpent.
For serpent, in Greek, is called ophis.
They have a serpent accustomed to licking their bread with its tongue, thereby supposedly sanctifying it as if it were the Eucharist.
This serpent they call their Christ.
Against these heretics, the priests of the provinces of Bithynia, namely the bishops Theocritus and Evander of the cities of Chalcedon and Nicomedia, took a stand.
They publicly refuted and overcame them, intervening in their gatherings in Bithynia, as I mentioned, secretly where they were conducting their activities.
They eliminated their priests, killed their snakes, and, by informing all the people, freed the majority of the populace from this danger.
Eighteenth Heresy: Cainites.
They are called this because they honor Cain, claiming he possessed the greatest virtue.
They also believe Judas the betrayer was divine in some way and view his crime as beneficial, asserting he foresaw how much Christ's passion would benefit humanity, and therefore handed Him over to the Jews to be killed.
Priests of the Mesopotamian Churches of Syria wrote to their fellow bishops about them.
Thirty-two bishops residing in Antioch, along with the bishop of the same city, Theodore, condemned them in person, quoting what the Holy Spirit spoke through the prophet:
"Woe to those who call evil good and good evil; who put darkness for light and light for darkness" (Isaiah 5:20).
Therefore, it is clear that you are condemned by your own actions, as you wish to call great and just those whom God has destined to the eternal fire of Gehenna due to their deeds.
Nineteenth Heresy: Sethians.
They are named after Adam's son, Seth.
They boast that he was born from a heavenly mother, whom they say united with a heavenly father, from whom a divine seed was born, from which God would choose the just and call them His children.
They originated in the regions of Achaia.
Saint Perigenes, the bishop of the city of Argos, opposed them, showing them that from one holy and true Isaac, two twins were born from the same womb: one ascended to the heights of divine grace, while the other descended to the depths of hell.
Therefore, he says, of the two possibilities, either the children are of a bad nature and both are damned for what they have been born as; or they are of a good nature, and according to their actions, one is justly blessed while the other is condemned.
With Saint Perigene asserting these and similar ideas, some believers turned away from this terrible error.
However, those who neither believed nor converted were cut off by the sword of excommunication.
The twentieth heresy among the Archontics in Crete got its name from the princes.
They claim to worship the princes who, they say, created this world.
Saint Dioscorus, bishop of Crete, condemned them, teaching that the one true God cannot be divided into substantial parts.
This is the God who revealed Himself to the prophets and delivered believers like Noah, Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, the sons of Israel, Jonah, Susanna, and the three youths from all dangers.
God showed countless signs of power to those who believed in Him, proving Himself to be the only God.
He accepted those who agreed with the truth but punished those who disagreed with eternal abomination.
The twenty-first heresy originated from Marcion.
He affirmed that there were two principles: good and evil.
Epiphanius said he taught three principles: good, just, and wicked.
However, Eusebius wrote that a certain Syrinus, not Marcion, was the author of the three principles and natures.
When the Marcionites defiled the universal Church of the East, they were overcome by Origen, who refuted and condemned them in each city.
After some years, although already defeated and exposed, they began to resurface in the African regions, but Tertullian overcame them in all ways, making them publicly denounce their own sect.
The twenty-second heresy is of the Apellites, led by Apelles, who introduces two gods but acknowledges one principle: that from that one principle, another was made.
When it was recognized as evil, it was rejected by the good, specifically by the good principle.
This principle, acting against the will of the good principle, created the world in its own evil.
This explains why we are naturally more inclined towards evil than good, and why we find more pleasure in vices than in virtues.
They claim that our Lord Jesus Christ took on flesh from the elements and returned it to the air when he ascended, entering heaven without it.
Origen overcame these people so effectively that he became a traveling preacher, moving through each city in the East to spread his message.
Because his volumes of treatises are countless, the heretics, having been defeated, altered the books with very cunning reasoning to fit their own desires, so they could deceive others by claiming Origen had defined things in his expositions.
Therefore, anyone reading Origen today, if they can distinguish with prudent recitation, will detect the parts tainted by the heretics.
Saint Pamphilus the martyr affirmed this in his Apology.
The twenty-third heresy of the Cerdonians began with Cerdo, who taught two opposing principles and claimed that the God of the law and prophets was not the Father of Christ, nor was He a good God, but a just one, while the Father of Christ was good.
He also claimed that Christ was neither born of a woman, nor had flesh, nor truly died or suffered anything, but only pretended to suffer.
Saint Apollonius, bishop of Corinth, opposed him and, along with the entire Eastern synod, condemned him, reasoning that this God is the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, about whom Moses says at the beginning of his book: "In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth" (Genesis 1:1).
He approved all the irreproachable ones of the Old Testament according to the Apostle, saying: "Who will bring any charge against those whom God has chosen? It is God who justifies. Who then is the one who condemns?" (Romans 8:33).
These and similar things condemned the heretics for this reason.
The priests, with reasonable words, either tried to call them back from the precipice or to show that they condemned the sects, not the people.
However, the people condemned themselves by embracing the condemned sects and departing from the truth.
The twenty-fourth heresy is that of the Severians, who arose from Severus.
They do not drink wine because they claim, with a fabulous vanity, that the vine sprouted from the seed of Satan.
They also reject the resurrection of the flesh along with the Old Testament.
Saint Euphranon, the bishop of Rhodes, condemned them; for their superstition arose in Rhodes.
He refuted them with the reasoning of the Holy Scriptures, which read that God brings forth bread from the earth to strengthen the heart of man and wine to gladden.
(Psalm 104:15-16).
The use of wine is not necessary, but excess is harmful to health and should be blamed.
The resurrection of the flesh was promised by Him who raised the dead in the present; if He had lied, He could not have raised the dead.
He clearly taught that the saints are the pillars of the Old Testament, like the foundations of a house, saying:
The foundations of the house are placed in dirty places so that the upper parts do not suffer any insult from the filth.
Therefore, the upper parts of the house are adorned with gilded ceilings, painted walls, and various marbles.
The lower parts, close to the earthly moisture, support all the upper parts.
What then shall we do now?
If we remove the lower parts, the upper parts will collapse.
However, if the lower parts were to be destroyed, no one could do this except the Son of God.
Let us see, therefore, whether He Himself destroyed what we say remains:
Do you think, He said, that I have come to destroy the law or the prophets?
I have not come to destroy the law, but to fulfill it.
(Matthew 5:17).
With these and similar words, Saint Euphranon, the bishop, converted many; those who persisted in error he deprived of communion by perpetual sanction.
The twenty-fifth heresy is that of the Tatianists, instituted by a certain Tatian, who are also called Encratites.
These people condemn marriage, equating it entirely with fornication and other corruptions.
They refuse to accept anyone who is married, whether male or female, into their ranks.
They do not eat meat and completely abhor it.
Saint Epiphanius, the bishop of Ancyra in Galatia, opposed them, citing the first letter of Paul the Apostle to Timothy:
Because they have a seared conscience, forbidding marriage and teaching to abstain from foods which God created to be received with thanksgiving by those who believe and know the truth: for every creature of God is good, and nothing is to be rejected if it is received with thanksgiving; for it is sanctified by the word of God and prayer.
First Timothy 4:2-5.
We, however, commend our Catholic abstainers because when they do not take food, they do not say it is evil to take it.
Instead, they call it good and excellent, asserting that they are unworthy to receive it.
Thus, the statute of the Apostle is also observed, which says: "Let not him who eats despise him who does not eat, and let not him who does not eat judge him who eats."
Romans 14:3.
For they do not accuse the creature but declare themselves to be unworthy of being refreshed by this feast.
Twenty-sixth Heresy: The Cataphrygians arose, named after the province, not the doctrine; their founders were Montanus, Prisca, and Maximilla.
These people claim that the coming of the Holy Spirit promised by the Lord was returned to them rather than to the apostles.
They regard second marriages as fornication and say that the apostle Paul allowed them because he knew in part and prophesied in part.
For what is perfect had not yet come.
However, they deliriously believe that this perfection came in Montanus and his prophetesses whom we mentioned above.
So far, I have spoken about the Cataphrygians.
I pass over the other things said about them as uncertain.
Regarding the claim that they take the blood of infants, we mention it so as not to seem ignorant of everything said about them: for those who wrote against them did not mention anything at all about this.
Books were written against them by Saint Soter, the Pope of Rome, and Apollonius, the bishop of Ephesus.
In response, Tertullian, a presbyter of Carthage, wrote against them.
While Tertullian's writings were generally excellent and incomparable, he was criticized for defending Montanus.
He argued against the aforementioned Soter, the Pope of Rome, claiming that the accusations about the blood of an infant, the Trinity in the unity of the Godhead, repentance for the fallen, the same mysteries, and one Passover with us were false.
He stated, "This is the only thing we differ on: we do not accept second marriages, and we do not reject Montanus' prophecy about the future judgment." Some people object to Tertullian, saying he claimed the soul is generated from the soul, just as the body is from the body, which the Catholic faith strongly opposes.
The twenty-seventh heresy is of the Pepuzians, named after a certain place. Epiphanius says this deserted city is called Jerusalem by them because they consider it divine. They give such prominence to women that they even honor them with the priesthood. They claim two churches, one of Quintilla and one of Priscilla, in the same city of Pepuza. They are associated with the Cataphrygians. They are looked down upon because these Pepuzians consider themselves better than others. They say that this village of Pepuza was the home of Montanus, Priscilla, and Maximilla, and because they started preaching there and lived there, they called the place Jerusalem. And because they are the inhabitants of the place, they consider themselves superior to others. Apollonius, the bishop of Ephesus, overcame them.
The twenty-eighth heresy calls its followers Artotyrites, named after their offering. They offer bread and cheese, claiming that the first people celebrated offerings to God from the fruits of the earth and sheep. Epiphanius connects them with the Pepuzians, against whom no one has deemed it worthy to even speak.
The twenty-ninth heresy is of the Tessarescaedecatites, named because they celebrate Passover on the fourteenth moon, regardless of the day of the week. And if it coincides with Sunday, they fast and keep vigil on that day.
The only difference between them and us is this, and nothing else.
Saint John, the bishop of Constantinople, achieved unity in many cities using this method.
He visited with his clergy and celebrated Easter with them, saying:
"Just as we celebrated Easter with you, come and celebrate with us too."
When they agreed, they began to think the same way and celebrate the day with us.
They realized that we share the same faith and believe just like them.
Thirty.
The thirtieth heresy is the Alogi.
They are called this because they refuse to accept that the Word of God is the Son; they even claim the Gospel of John is not his, nor do they accept the Revelation of John.
What more can be said?
They agree with us on everything else but completely reject the idea that the Word of God is the Son of God, considering it blasphemy.
Bishop Philo often defeated them.
Thirty-One.
The thirty-first heresy is the Adamites, named after Adam, whose nakedness in paradise they imitate, just as it was before sin.
They reject marriage because Adam did not know his wife before he was expelled from paradise.
They believe that marriages would not have existed if no one had sinned.
Thus, men and women meet naked, listen to readings naked, pray naked, celebrate the sacraments naked, and consider their church to be their paradise.
Saint Polycarp, the priest, discovered them, overcame them, and eliminated them.
Thirty-Two.
The thirty-second heresy is the Helcesites.
A false prophet named Helchi deceived them, and from his lineage, two women were worshipped by them as goddesses.
The rest of their beliefs are said by Epiphanius to be similar to those of the Ebionites.
Papias, the priest of Achaia, overcame them.
Thirty-Three.
The thirty-third heresy is held by the Theodotians, founded by Theodotus, who claimed that Christ was only a human being, the Son of God.
It is said that Theodotus taught this because, during persecution, he fell and thought he could avoid disgrace by claiming he had not denied God but only a man.
Craton, the bishop of the Syrians, overcame them.
Thirty-Four.
The thirty-fourth heresy was discovered by the Melchizedekians.
Melchizedek, the priest of the Most High God, is believed not to have been a human but rather a power of God, following that passage in the Epistle to the Hebrews where it says, "without father, without mother, without genealogy" Hebrews 7:3. Dionysius, the bishop of Jerusalem, countered this by saying that he did have both a father and a mother. He explained that the Apostle said this because neither his genealogy nor his maternal or paternal ancestry was included in the order prescribed by the law of the Hebrews, even though the generation of the Hebrews was certainly pleasing to God.
Heresy thirty-five is that of the Bardesanites, named after a certain Bardesanes who went astray. It is said that Bardesanes was originally a perfect Catholic but later fell into error through a disciple of Valentinus, claiming that the creation of human flesh was evil, but the soul was good. Theocritus, the bishop of Cappadocia, condemned him, teaching that God made both good, joined both together, and that it was the transgression, not the nature of human flesh, that should be blamed.
Heresy thirty-six is that of the Noetians, who say that Christ is the same as the Father and the Holy Spirit: not by substance, as we understand it, but by person, so that the Holy Spirit is said to be only seemingly, not truly. He was condemned by Tranquillus, the bishop of the Chalcedonians in Syria. Tranquillus showed that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are all true: one God by one substance, but believed to be three persons by distinction.
Heresy thirty-seven is that of the Valesians, who unhappily castrate both themselves and their guests. They claim that this is in fulfillment of the saying, "Those who have made themselves eunuchs for the kingdom of heaven" Matthew 19:12. They are also said to teach other heretical and shameful things, but neither Epiphanius himself mentions them, nor have I been able to find them anywhere. They were condemned by a synod in Achaia.
Heresy thirty-eight is that of the Cathars, who arrogantly call themselves by this name as if for purity. They do not admit second marriages. They deny penance. They follow the heretic Novatus, and thus are also called Novatians.
Against the blessed Sixtus, martyr and bishop, and the venerable Cyprian, martyr of Christ and bishop of Carthage, a book was written against Novatus on the Lapsed.
It stated that those who have fallen can recover the grace they lost through repentance, which Novatus claimed was absolutely impossible.
The thirty-ninth heresy is that of the Angelics.
They wanted to be called Angelics and believed that angels should be worshiped and honored in spirit.
They thought prayers should be offered to angels so that, knowing who has more power than themselves, they would fulfill human wishes and petitions.
Epiphanius testifies that they were completely defeated by Theophilus, bishop of Apamea.
In the fortieth place appeared the Apostolics, who arrogantly wanted to be called by this name.
They do not accept into their communion those who use marriage and possess personal property, such as the Catholic Church does, including many monks and clerics.
These are considered heretics because, separating themselves from the Church, they believe that those who use these things, which they lack, have no hope.
The Church counters them with the testimony in which the Apostle says: Even if I give my body to be burned, but have not love, it profits me nothing First Corinthians 13:3.
The forty-first heresy is that of the Sabellians, which arose from Sabellius, who confessed that the same person is Father, Son, and Holy Spirit.
They are also called Praxeans, after their initial teacher Praxeas, and Hermogenians, because they had Hermogenes in their company with Sabellius.
They were countered by Dositheus, bishop of Seleucia, who taught that they deny the whole Trinity while thinking they are defending unity.
For the Father is unbegotten, the Son begotten, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father, equal in all things to the Father and the Son.
Divinity thus maintains unity of substance without losing the distinction of persons.
The forty-second heresy of the Origenists began with a certain Origen, not the well-known one, but another extremely wicked Syrian.
Epiphanius says that this man taught such shameful things that they shouldn't be recorded for our descendants.
The forty-third heresy of the Origenists followed immediately after, as Epiphanius also notes.
They deny the resurrection of the dead, claim that the Holy Spirit is a creature of Christ, and interpret paradise and the heavens allegorically.
These two Origens wrote many corrupt things.
Heretical and perverse teachers mixed these writings with those of our Catholic writer Origen, fulfilling what the Lord says in the Gospels: "Did you not sow good seed in your field? Where then did these weeds come from?" He replied, "An enemy did this" Matthew 13:27.
That is why, when we read Origen, we find a Catholic who fights against heresies and wins; yet, at the same time, we find a heretic who contradicts the faith. Written words convey both the letter and the meaning: if they could also show the faces of the speakers, no one could mistake the identity of the teacher.
It must also be noted that a certain Ampullianus, a heresiarch from Bithynia, who taught after Origen in the Church of God, fell into such heresy that he claimed all criminals, along with the devil and demons, would be boiled in hell until they became pure and could emerge from there clean and spotless, to be restored to their creator as they were before their guilt.
When he was condemned by the universal Church, he began to produce books of Origen that he himself had corrupted, saying, "See, this is what Origen believed," especially in the four books of "Periarchon." But anyone of sound mind and clear vision can see the evil additions to Origen's works and recognize them, just as one would notice white or differently colored patches sewn onto a scarlet cloak.
What Saint Pamphilus, the holy martyr, teaches us is true.
Before he received the crown of martyrdom, he held the bishop's chair blamelessly and shared sound doctrine with God's people.
He wrote an Apology and refuted all the false claims made by ignorant Catholics about Origen.
He showed that the works found objectionable in Origen's writings were not his, but those of others whom he had surpassed.
The entirely erroneous works, however, belonged to two other heretics who used Origen's name without sharing his faith or conscience.
Heresy 44, the forty-fourth heresy, was created by Paul of Samosata and led to the formation of the Paulian community.
They claimed that Christ did not always exist but began with Mary and that he was nothing more than a man.
This heresy previously belonged to Artemon.
When it faded, Paul of Samosata revived it.
Later, the Church opposed this heresy, and although many years passed, when its faulty defense by its proponents failed, it was renewed by our bishop Photinus, leading to the Photinian community.
Therefore, whether you hear of the Artemonites, the Paulians, or the Photinians, you should know they are one and the same, just as we call the Donatists, the Montanists, and the Parmenianists by their leaders' names: Donatists from Donatus, Montanists from Montanus, and Parmenianists from Parmenian, who traveled throughout Africa writing books against us and composing new psalms.
Our own writer, Optatus, replied to him.
But let's return to the Paulians.
It is well known that we do not rebaptize heretics who come to us but extend a hand of reconciliation and then join them to the divine people.
However, the holy synod of Nicaea decreed that Paulians must be fully baptized before they can join the Catholic people.
This shows they did not keep the true rule of baptism, and hence this decree was established by Christ's bishops.
Heresy 45, the forty-fifth heresy, is the Photinian heresy, named after Photinus, who was our bishop just as Judas Iscariot was our apostle.
He created his own community.
Christ taught that a man was indeed pure and believed, like Paul of Samosata, that he began from Mary, but he always remembered that the Holy Spirit was eternal.
This belief differed from the forty-fourth heresy because he named the people who were led astray after himself.
The forty-sixth heresy was started by Mani, who formed the community of the Manichaeans.
Mani, a Persian citizen teaching in Persia, claimed to be an apostle of God and even went to Greece.
His Greek disciples, avoiding the name of madness, decided to call him Manichaean, which means "pouring out manna."
He proposed two principles that were different and opposing, yet eternal and coeternal, meaning they always existed. He believed in two natures and substances, namely good and evil, following other ancient heretics. They tell stories about the struggle and mingling between these principles, the purification of good from evil, and the eternal damnation of the part of good that could not be purified from evil, according to their doctrines.
They say that good souls are of the same nature as God. Therefore, they confess that the world was made by the nature of good, that is, by the nature of God, but from the mingling of good and evil that happened when both natures fought each other. They believe that the purification and liberation of good from evil is performed not only through the whole world and all its elements by the power of God but also through their chosen ones by the food they consume.
They claim that the substance of God is mixed in these foods, just as it is in the whole world, and that it is purified in their chosen ones through the kind of life the elect Manichaeans lead, which they consider holier and more excellent than their followers. They wanted their church to consist of these two groups, the elect and the followers.
As for other people, even their own followers, they believe that this part of the good and divine substance, which is mixed and bound in food and drink, is thought to be more tightly and impurely bound, especially in those who have children.
Whatever light is purified from all sides through certain vessels, which they believe to be the moon and the sun, is returned to the kingdom of God as its proper seats.
They claim that these vessels are made from the pure substance of God and that this physical light, visible to mortal eyes, is considered to be the nature of God.
They attribute five elements, which have their own rulers, to the race of darkness: smoke, darkness, fire, water, and wind.
Animals born in smoke are bipedal, from which they believe humans originate; in darkness, crawling creatures; in fire, quadrupeds; in water, swimming creatures; in wind, flying creatures.
To combat these five evil elements, they say that five other elements were sent from the kingdom and substance of God; and in that battle, they were mixed together: air with smoke, light with darkness, good fire with bad fire, good water with bad water, and good wind with bad wind.
They distinguish those vessels, namely the two celestial lights, by saying that the moon is made of good water and the sun of good fire.
They believe that there are holy virtues in these vessels, which transform themselves into males to entice the females of the opposing race; and through this attraction, their stirred-up lust causes the light mixed with their bodies to flee, to be received and purified by angels of light, and placed in those vessels to be returned to its proper kingdoms.
On this occasion, their elect are compelled to consume something like the Eucharist mixed with human seed, so that even from this, as with other foods they take, that divine substance is purified.
But when they deny doing this, they are exposed.
For they were revealed in the church of Carthage in this way.
Finally, in a gathering of bishops before all the people, a girl not yet twelve years old confessed this vile crime; and she revealed many things, asserting that she had endured violence for this wicked sacrament of theirs.
At first, when no one believed a single girl alone, she named many accomplices in the crime.
With the support of Ursus the tribune, who then presided over the royal house, they were expelled from various houses where they were hiding and brought by clerics to the Church of Restituta.
Because of this, having suffered greatly, they were finally compelled to confess.
The entire vile crime was then revealed, involving flour spread to catch and mix the seed of those having sexual intercourse.
With immense shame, it is said and heard that in recent times, some of them were brought to the church, as the episcopal records testify.
There are three types: Catharists, Macarians, and Manichaeans.
It is known that all these three forms were written by one master, the wicked Mani himself.
All of them read Manichean works, and all his books are undoubtedly common to them.
In these books, it is taught that through lust, the prince of darkness of both sexes is dissolved, and the divine substance, which they believe to be held stained in human seed, is freed from them.
Hence, they are also called Catharists, meaning purifiers.
Although they do not eat meat, they are so defiled that they even consume human seed with all their food, even though they do not take eggs.
They say that even eggs expire when broken.
Nor do they use milk as nourishment; not because they think there is no divine substance mixed in it, but because their beliefs are inconsistent.
For they do not drink wine, saying it is the gall of the prince of darkness, yet they eat grapes, even though they do not take a drop of must.
They believe the souls of their listeners are reincarnated into the elect; however, they assert that other souls, those not of their listeners, return into animals and into all things fixed by roots and nourished in the earth.
They believe that herbs and trees have life in such a way that they feel pain and suffering when harmed.
Therefore, they also accuse farming, the most innocent of all arts, as if it were responsible for many murders, foolishly blaming it especially when they see a field being cleared of thorns.
They believe their listeners are excused because they provide food for their chosen ones.
By purifying the divine substance in their stomachs, it is said to grant forgiveness to those whose offerings need purification.
Thus, the chosen ones themselves do not work in the fields, do not pick fruit, nor pluck any leaves, but wait for these to be brought to them by their listeners, living off many and great murders according to their vanity.
They also instruct their listeners that if they eat meat, they should not kill animals, so as not to offend the rulers of darkness bound in the heavens, from whom they say all flesh originates.
And thus, they use their spouses to avoid conception and generation, so that the divine substance that enters them through food does not get bound in the flesh of offspring.
They believe that souls come into all flesh through food and drink.
Hence, they undoubtedly condemn and, as much as they can, prohibit marriage when they prevent generation, which is the purpose of marriage.
They claim that Adam and Eve were born from the rulers of smoke, whose father, they say, is named Saclas, who they claim devoured the offspring of all his companions, and whatever of the divine substance was mixed within, he bound in the flesh of offspring by lying with his wife.
They assert that Christ was the one whom our Scripture calls the serpent, from whom their eyes were enlightened to discern good and evil; and they claim that Christ came in the last days to free souls, not bodies.
They say he was not in true flesh, but only appeared to have flesh to deceive human senses, where he not only faked death but also resurrection.
They affirm that the God who gave the law through Moses and spoke in the Hebrew prophets is not the true God, but one of the rulers of darkness.
They read the New Testament Scriptures in a way that supports their views, accepting what they like and rejecting what they don't.
They even regard some apocryphal texts as completely true.
They believe that the promise of our Lord Jesus Christ about the Paraclete was fulfilled in their leader, Mani.
Mani, in his letters, refers to himself as an apostle of Jesus Christ, claiming that Jesus promised to send him, thus making him an apostle through whom the Holy Spirit was sent.
To imitate the apostolic number, Mani also had twelve disciples, a tradition the Manichaeans continue today with twelve teachers selected from their elect and a thirteenth leader overseeing them.
The bishops, ordained by these teachers, and the priests, ordained by the bishops, are of an indefinite number.
The bishops also have deacons.
The rest are simply known as the elect.
Those deemed suitable among them are sent to propagate their beliefs, either to expand their influence or to prevent its decline.
They believe that baptism in water does not bring salvation and thus do not consider it necessary for their followers.
They pray to the sun during the day and to the moon at night if it is visible; if not, they pray to the northern part of the sky, where the sun returns to the East after setting.
They always stand while praying.
They attribute the origin of sins not to individual free will but to the substance of an opposing race, which they believe is mixed with humans.
They teach that all flesh is not the work of Divinity but of an evil mind, co-eternal with the opposing God.
They believe carnal desire, which causes the flesh to lust against the spirit, is a contrary substance that clings to us.
Even when liberated and purified, it regenerates and lives immortally by nature.
They claim there are two souls and two minds in one person, naturally opposing each other-one good and one bad-in perpetual conflict.
When this age ends, after the world's fiery destruction, they say that the substance of evil will be confined in a certain sphere like a prison.
They claim that this sphere will also contain the souls that are naturally good but could not be cleansed from the contamination of evil nature, adhering to it like a covering or plaster.
XLVII.
The forty-seventh heretic was Hierac of the Hieracites.
They deny the resurrection of the flesh.
They only accept monks and nuns into their community, and those who do not have marriages.
They say that children do not belong to the kingdom of heaven because they have no merits from any struggle by which vices are overcome.
Saint Aphrodisius, bishop of Hellespont, opposed them, asserting that the resurrection of the flesh is affirmed by both the New and Old Testaments.
He argued that infants are already human beings: and just as if someone kills them, they are charged with murder, so those who consecrate them with baptism acquire a reward for saving a human being.
Communion should be denied to no one, except those who, neglecting their own spouses, seek others.
XLVIII.
The forty-eighth heresy is that of the Meletians, named after a certain Meletius.
They refused to pray with those who had fallen during persecution and created a schism.
Saint Basil, bishop of Cappadocia, resisted them, saying that greater love of hope and faith, which endures all things, should extend a hand to those who have fallen.
He also encouraged those in despair of recovery to return, for even the angels in heaven have greater joy over one repentant sinner than over ninety-nine who did not sin (Luke 15:10).
XLIX.
The forty-ninth heresiarch was Arius.
He founded the Arian peoples, who do not believe that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are of one and the same substance.
Instead, they believe the Son is a creation and the Holy Spirit is a creation of a creation, that is, created by the Son himself.
In that he considered Christ to have taken on flesh without a soul, Epiphanius reported, and therefore says the Father is greater than the Son as the creator, and the Son is greater than the Holy Spirit as his creator.
They rebaptize our people, that is, Catholics, who come to them.
Whether they do this to others, that is, non-Catholics, is not documented anywhere.
The first to oppose them was Saint Hesiod, bishop of the Corinthians, a man said to have raised the dead.
Consequently, people, focusing more on holiness than on debate, cursed Arius.
It is said that during his prayers, Arius, while sitting in the restroom, expelled all his intestines along with his excrement.
Both Eastern and Western bishops have written against his sect, asserting that he blasphemes in every single chapter of his doctrines.
Epiphanius recalls the Audian schismatics from the 50th heresy, not as heretics, but as schismatics, whom others call Anthropomorphites because they imagine God in a carnal way, in the likeness of a corruptible human being, saying: "The eyes of the Lord are on the righteous" (Psalm 33:16); "The heavens are the work of God's fingers" (Psalm 8:4); and: "God sits on his holy throne" (Psalm 46:9); and: "God stands in the congregation of the mighty" (Psalm 82:1), and other things that can be thought of in a visible way.
Therefore, because they err in nothing else, Epiphanius, dealing more gently with them, did not want to call them heretics, forgiving their rusticity.
However, because they do not communicate with us, they claim that our bishops have wealth, which Christ also commands even laypeople to despise.
They celebrate Passover with the Jews.
Bishop Zenon of the Syrians acted against them.
The 51st heresy is of the Eunomians, from Eunomius.
These, filled with the spirit of the ancient serpent, assert not only that the Son is lesser, but also that the Son is not of similar essence.
Presbyter Ammonius acted against them.
The 52nd heresy is of the Macedonians, from Macedonius.
Our people in the East call them Pneumatomachians because they dispute about the Holy Spirit.
They understand the Father and the Son correctly but refuse to believe that the Holy Spirit is God, claiming He is a creature.
Philaster notes that Macedonius refers to the Holy Spirit as the divinity of the Father and the Son.
This implies he denies the Holy Spirit His own distinct nature.
The fifty-third heresy is that of the Aerians, named after Aerius.
Aerius was a presbyter who became upset because he was not ordained as a bishop.
He taught that prayers should not be offered for the dead and that established fasts should not be observed.
Instead, he believed fasting should be done whenever one wishes to avoid appearing bound by the law.
He also believed there should be no distinction between a presbyter and a bishop and that only those who abstain from marriage should be admitted to their communion.
The fifty-fourth heresy is that of the Aetians, named after Aetius.
Along with Eunomius, they claim that the Son is completely dissimilar to the Father in all respects.
They assert that anyone who agrees with their faith should know that no sins can harm them, no matter what they have committed.
A synod of 20 bishops in Achaia opposed them.
The fifty-fifth heresy is that of the Apollinarians, founded by Apollinaris.
They deny that Christ was a perfect man, claiming that divinity took the place of a soul in the man.
They teach that the flesh and the Word are of the same substance.
They assert, quite contentiously, "The Word became flesh" John 1:14, suggesting that something of the Word was converted into flesh.
Furthermore, they claim that none of Mary's flesh was involved in the incarnation of our Lord Jesus Christ.
A synod in Antioch opposed them.
The fifty-sixth heresy is that of the Antidicomarites, who vehemently deny Mary's perpetual virginity, asserting she united with a man after Christ was born.
Theodotus, the bishop of Cyprus, opposed them.
The fifty-seventh heresy is that of the Messalians.
Their name comes from the Syrian language; in Greek, they are called Euchites, named for their constant praying.
They do not chant psalms but pray continuously.
But because they act alone, without love, kindness, or humanity, they are refuted by the holy council among the heretics.
They also condemn those monks who, apart from reading and praying, engage in any other work, whether it be craftsmanship or agriculture.
Epiphanius reached this point and then fell silent.
I believe he lived up to that time.
Human curiosity can indicate past and present things, but only God can predict the future.
Philaster, in his books recounting the histories of various people, also includes the heresies that arose at different times.
We now present only the heresies excerpted from his books.
Ephrem, the priest of the Syrians, opposed these.
The Metangismonites started the fifty-eighth heresy.
The Greek word angeion means "vessel," and metangismos means a vessel within a vessel.
From this concept, they took their name, saying: "The Son is in the Father as a smaller vessel is within a larger vessel."
The Church rejects them because they think carnally about the incorporeal, treat the incomprehensible in a limited way, and propose a hierarchy within the equality of the Divinity.
Diodorus, bishop of Nicomedia, opposed these.
The fifty-ninth heresy involves the Seleucians, originating from Seleucus, who claim that the material elements from which the world was made were not created by God but are co-eternal with God.
They do not attribute the soul to God the creator but claim that angels create souls from fire and spirit.
They assert that evil sometimes comes from God and sometimes from matter.
They deny that the Savior sits in the flesh at the right hand of the Father, claiming instead that He shed it and placed it in the sun, interpreting the psalm "He has set up a tabernacle in the sun" (Psalms 19:4) in this way.
They deny a visible paradise, do not accept baptism in water, do not believe in a future resurrection, but assert that it happens daily in the generation of children.
These people, according to our faith's teachings, are not allowed to engage in debate with us; instead, they are meant to be condemned for their definitions.
The sixtieth heresy was created by the Proclinianists, followers of Proclus.
They claim that the Son of God appeared on earth like the angel Raphael or Gabriel-not by taking on flesh, but simply by being seen.
They blend in with the people of God so seamlessly that they go unnoticed.
Unfortunately, since they have no other errors, they interact with us freely.
This is more problematic because they can easily influence simple people to think and believe as they do.
They assert a belief that is very hostile to our salvation.
They question whether God had to endure the impurities associated with natural conception, birth, and delivery.
Did the Son of God have to deal with bodily functions like a cleansing stomach, a runny nose, saliva, earwax, or excrement?
Did he have to experience foul odors?
These ideas are the result of a disturbed mind.
Tertullian strongly opposes these notions, arguing that the Son of God is incapable of suffering.
He insists that these experiences do not harm but rather honor Divinity.
He uses an analogy: Just as a king might put on a servant's tunic to retrieve a gem-encrusted golden ring from a sewer, allowing the tunic to get dirty while he rescues the ring and cleans it, then wears it on his royal finger.
Similarly, the Son of God took on the form of a servant.
He came down not just to earth, where we live, but even to the underworld, which is far below us, to rescue humanity.
He endured all our filth-none of it his own.
For the living, he lived like us, differing only in that he led a sinless life, having God within him.
For the dead, he died similarly, differing only in that he rose from the dead on the third day.
By descending in this way, he rescued the saints and bound the prince of death.
But as for the golden ring with the gem that he placed, he taught in the following reading that the ring represents the body and the gem inside it symbolizes the soul.
Therefore, Christ, lifting this ring from the ancient filth and sewer of this world, washed it with the water of baptism, cleansing it from all grime, and made it shine in His holy hands.
For it is written: "But the souls of the righteous are in the hand of God" (Wisdom 3:1).
And again: "Set me as a seal upon your hand" (Song of Solomon 8:6).
And: "Into your hands I commend my spirit" (Psalm 31:5).
There are countless similar passages in the holy scriptures, which we omit for brevity, so let us proceed to the sixty-first heresy.
The sixty-first heresy was created by the Patricians, originating from Patricius.
They believe that the substance of human flesh was not created by God, but by the devil, and they detest it so much that they say one who can consistently kill himself is perfect.
Some of them even ask strangers they encounter to kill them.
This madness began long ago in parts of Upper Numidia and Mauretania.
Later, the wretched Donatists followed them and began to throw themselves from the peak of a mountain as if they would become future martyrs.
So those who abandon eternal life through the Catholic faith find eternal death by violence.
It is read that Optatus acted against them.
The sixty-second heresy is that of the Ascitae.
The Ascitae are named from the word for wineskin.
For askos means wineskin in Greek.
Though they have no issues with the Trinity, they place a large wineskin next to the altar, inflate it, cover it with linens, and worship it, because they add the blood of the Lord there, saying that evangelical phrase: "They put new wine into new wineskins, and both are preserved" (Matthew 9:17).
The sixty-third heresy is that of the Passalorynchites.
Whenever they gather at their church, they strive for such silence that they place a finger on their nose and lips, so as not to disturb the silence even with their breath.
But why those who composed this name preferred to signify a finger by a stake, I do not know.
In Greek, passalos means stake, daktylos means finger, and rhynchos means nose.
However, it seems better to me if they are called Dactylorynchitae.
The devil has found some in the law of God to turn them into Pythagoreans, observing what the Apostles said:
"I will pray with the spirit, I will pray also with the mind; I will sing with the spirit, I will sing also with the mind" (First Corinthians 14:15).
Therefore, they teach people outside the church what to say in their hearts while inside the church.
As if the same Apostle did not say:
"With the heart one believes unto righteousness, and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation" (Romans 10:10).
I say it is a futile effort to engage with such people, who waste time responding to them, and I believe it is right to conquer them by remaining silent.
The sixty-fourth heresy of the Aquarians, who are called Aquarians because they offer water in the sacrament cup.
They say that wine causes drunkenness, through which murders, fornications, and other crimes are committed, although it is clear that anything in excess causes crime and creates vice.
Therefore, crimes are not committed by drinking wine, but by excessive drinking.
For what is there that, when taken in excess, does not incur blame?
Let water be drunk excessively; let's see if it does not cause harm.
Let bread be eaten excessively; let's see if it does not cause gluttony.
Therefore, holding to moderation in all things is best, and we also condemn those who, separating the blood of Christ from the source, boldly infringe the rule established by Christ under the pretext of fornication and murder.
The sixty-fifth heresy of the Coluthians arose from a certain Coluthus.
They say that God created both good and evil, interpreting literally what is said:
"I am the Lord, creating evil and doing good" (Isaiah 45:7).
When God promised through the prophet that He would make them live without the sword of enemies and make the land give its produce and abundance of all crops if they kept His commandments; but if they were transgressors, they would suffer the sword and famine.
And after saying this, He added:
"I am the Lord, creating evil and doing good."
Those who transfer this to the substance from the appearance assert that God is the creator of evils.
Since no creature is evil, they can, as I see it, blaspheme God perversely because He says to the people: If you walk uprightly, I will walk uprightly with you; but if you walk perversely, I will walk perversely with you.
Leviticus 26:23.
The sixty-sixth heresy is that of the Florians, named after Florian, who says that both good and bad souls are created by God.
Therefore, he claims, those who are malicious are evil and cannot change; and the good who live simply are not drawn into the audacity of wicked men.
This statement is briefly refuted by Theodore, who points out that Judas was good and became a traitor.
At the very moment when the worst prostitute was washing His feet with her tears, seeking mercy, if the woman had an evil soul, why did she not persist in the crime of prostitution at that time?
It is evident, therefore, that good souls are created by God: to whom the Creator has granted by nature that, while they are good, they are not only improved by their own actions, but can also turn to evil itself, as diligence finds one thing and negligence incurs the other.
The sixty-seventh heresy is that of the Satannians, followers of Satannius.
They say that after the resurrection of the dead, we will not remain in the same state as we are now; nor will we be changed in such a way that there will be a new heaven and a new earth, as the Holy Scripture promises.
Second Peter 3:13.
The writings of both Testaments oppose these views.
The sixty-eighth heresy is that of the Gymnopodae.
They always walk barefoot because the Lord said to Moses: Remove the sandals from your feet.
Exodus 3:5.
And because it is written that Saint Isaiah walked barefoot.
Isaiah 20:2.
Therefore, they create a schism by condemning those who wear shoes.
The sixty-ninth heresy is that of the Donatists, named after Donatus.
They created a schism due to the ordination of Caecilian as bishop of the Church of Carthage, against their will, accusing him of unproven crimes, and especially that he was ordained by those who had betrayed the divine Scriptures.
When they were exposed as liars, they turned their division into a heresy.
They acted as if, even if the accusations against Caecilian had been true, the Church worldwide could have lost its status because of one man's fault.
Whether true or, as seemed more apparent to the judges, false, they believed only Donatus could have preserved the Church's status in Africa, while the efforts of the holy apostles and the suffering of the martyrs would have been erased globally.
Even the blood of our Savior, they argued, failed to preserve the assembly of the Catholic faith, which only Donatus and a few insignificant followers from Byzacena could obtain.
So, they dared to rebaptize Catholics.
In doing this, they proved themselves presumptuous and damnable, knowing that the universal Church did not approve of violating the power of baptism, even in heretics.
We read that the leader of this heresy was Donatus.
He came from Numidia to Carthage and divided the people of Christ against Caecilian.
He joined bishops of the same faction and appointed a man named Majorinus as bishop in his part of Carthage.
Another Donatus succeeded Majorinus in this division, and his eloquence confirmed this heresy so much that many believe the Donatists took the beginning of their heresy more from him.
His writings still exist today, proving that he opposed the Catholic faith regarding the Trinity.
Though he claimed that in the Trinity, God the Father is of one substance, he tried to assert that the Father is greater than the Son and the Son greater than the Holy Spirit.
However, no one among his followers paid attention to this error because their focus was elsewhere.
These heretics are called Montenses in parts of Italy, Parmenianians in inner Africa, and Donatists in Carthage.
In both Numidias, they have monks of sorts, called Circumcellions, rustic and very bold servants of demons, who not only fiercely attack others but also, poor souls, do not spare themselves.
They have become accustomed to ending their lives through various means, especially by jumping from heights, drowning, and burning, and they lure as many people as they can from both genders to do the same.
Sometimes, they even ask those they meet to kill them, threatening them with death if they refuse.
It's true that many Donatists disapprove of such actions, but only in words, not in deeds.
If they truly disapproved, they would not associate with these individuals, who accuse the churches around the world of the crime of one Caecilian.
They have often had disputes among themselves.
Finally, in Carthage, during the time of Count Heraclian, when Maximian was ordained by nearly one hundred bishops of the same error against Primianus, he was condemned by the remaining three hundred and ten bishops, who accused his ordination of crimes.
He taught his followers that the baptism of Christ could be administered even outside the Church.
Therefore, whoever moved from Primianus to Maximian or from Maximian to Primianus was not baptized again by the one they previously opposed and is accepted by the one they surely condemned.
They do not reject, refuse, or change the sacrament of baptism.
Whether someone is baptized or ordained as a cleric by Primianus or Maximian, it is as if it was done by one, not two opposing parties.
In the dignity from which one came to the other, they remain: baptism is not changed, nor is the dignity taken away; because the division was made not over the dispute of baptism, but over the contention of ordination.
They began to dissent over the ordination of Caecilian, not over the transgression of baptism or faith, and separated themselves from the Church.
Priscillian is recorded to have started the seventieth heresy of the Priscillianists among the Spaniards.
They claim that souls are of divine nature.
They believe these souls descend through seven heavens and various stages to engage in some voluntary struggle on earth and encounter an evil prince, who they think created this world, and from this prince, they are sown into different bodies of flesh.
They also claim that people are bound by the stars of fate and that our bodies are composed according to the twelve signs of the zodiac.
Just like astrologers, they place Aries in the head, Taurus in the neck, Gemini in the shoulders, Cancer in the chest, and so on, naming the signs down to the feet.
They have shifted from the sign of Christ to the signs of astrologers.
They invent many other fabulous and vain things.
They separate wives from their husbands when they can.
They avoid meat like the Manicheans.
They accept apocryphal books along with the canonical Scriptures and interpret them allegorically according to their own understanding.
They confess the Trinity, like the Sabellians, as the Father being the same as the Son and the same as the Holy Spirit.
The seventy-first heresy began with the Adelophagi, who say that Christians should not eat in a way that others can see them while they are eating.
This is the only reason they are considered separate from the Church.
They confess the Trinity of the same substance.
Bishops from Ephesus have dealt with them.
The seventy-second heresy of the Rhetorians, started by Rhetorius, is noted by Philastrius.
They have fallen into such vanity that they say all heretics are rightly following God because this is given in their minds: they worship God as best they can.
Their error seems reprehensible to us, but before God, there is neither error nor blame.
Their teachers instruct them to enter any place where Christ, born of a Virgin, is invoked, whether it is a temple or synagogue, and to make themselves participants with the heretics.
The seventy-third heresy is that of the Theopaschites.
They say that in Christ, while He suffered, the Divinity felt pain just as the soul can feel pain when the body is subjected to torment.
Bishop Gregory says of them: "Unfortunate and miserable ones, they do not see that when trees are cut with an iron tool, although sunlight is indeed present on the trees, the brightness of the sun does not feel pain, even though the iron strikes it before reaching the wood.
God, therefore, is light, and how can light be struck down?"
Because it is the soul that feels pain in the body, we notice this: when the soul leaves the body, the body cannot feel anything, neither good nor bad.
Therefore, in the body of our Lord Jesus Christ, the human soul felt what it assumed with the body, not He who assumed it, just as the sun shines on a tree.
Remember: even if the sunlight on the tree can be cut off by a blow, the Divinity in Christ cannot be touched by the one crucifying; because the light of the sun is a creature, but here the Creator is recognized and proven.
For the human soul felt the suffering, the Lord Himself said to His disciples: "My soul is sorrowful even to death" (Matthew 26:38).
And let this suffice: let us move on to the next point.
The seventy-fourth heresy was committed by the Triscilidae: they assert that God is threefold, so that one part of Him is the Father, one part is the Son, and one part is the Holy Spirit, and thus the Trinity is in unity.
Gregory said about them: "Unhappy and miserable, they do not see that they are blaspheming the entire Trinity." For God is only He who is perfect in Himself. Therefore, the perfect Father begot the perfect Son from Himself, and the perfect Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father. Behold, three perfect beings do not make three gods, but one, because there is one Deity. For, unlike three persons, there are not three deities: but there are three-the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit; yet one Deity, one majesty, one power, one will, and one substance to be confessed.
The seventy-fifth heresy was committed by the Hydrotheitae, who say that water is God, having neither beginning nor end, cleansing filth, forgiving sins, and having the Holy Spirit. The Catholic faith justly condemns them as blind and not seeing what filth water serves, and how God can serve, even in such squalor; or what significance water has without consecration. The living word gives it life, the holy word sanctifies it, so that the Holy Spirit may deign to dwell in it, or that it may cleanse the sins of believers.
Just as this entity gains its power through a blessing to cleanse all sins, it cannot cleanse the sins of someone who has not fully believed and offered their faith to God first.
Therefore, it's not just the act of washing, but more importantly, the act of believing that allows the Holy Spirit to be poured into people, granting the forgiveness of sins.
The seventy-sixth heresy was introduced by the Homuncionites, who claim that the image of God resides in the body of a person, not in the soul.
Gregory states that since the image of God should be sought in the profound and primary aspects of a person-such as memory, intellect, knowledge, and the inclination towards piety-these attributes are established in the soul, not in bodily features.
The purer these mentioned attributes are, the more a person resembles God.
The seventy-seventh heresy was proposed by the Ametrites, who believe there are countless worlds.
Those unfamiliar with the philosophers might think this is a new idea, but some ancient philosophers among the pagans proposed this long ago.
However, we accept Moses as sent by God, and our understanding and beliefs about the world come from him.
The seventy-eighth heresy was adopted by the Psychopneumones, who claim that the good souls of people transform into the spirits of angels, while the bad souls transform into the spirits of demons.
The seventy-ninth heresy is upheld by the Adecerditae, who assert that when Christ descended to the underworld, all the multitude of souls met him, believed in him, and were set free.
The eightieth heresy claims that the Son of God was born later, only because the Father willed it; if the Father had not willed it, he would not have been born.
We must confess that the Son is equal to the Father; his equality is not a matter of nature, but of grace.
The Father willed this, and therefore everything is from the Father, not from the Son.
We, on the contrary, say: just as a spring gives rise to a river from itself, so the Father generates the Son from Himself.
Just as a spring does not generate a river by willing or not willing, but by its very nature; so the Father does not generate the Son by debating, willing, or not willing, but by the nature of His fullness, He pours out the Son.
And just as the river flows around the whole world and enters the sea, yet never departs from the spring's source: so the Son never departed from the Father's bosom, not even when He humbled Himself and became obedient unto death.
Thus, He appeared among us by assumption, but by His majesty, He never departed from the Father's bosom.
For in order for this to happen, neither the possibility nor the will was lacking in God.
If either of these were lacking in God, He could not be called God.
For one who does not will what is good is evil; one who cannot do what he wills is not omnipotent.
Condemning this blasphemy in the heretic we mentioned, let us proceed to the others.
We accuse not the eighty-first heresy of Lucifer, but we argue schism.
Catholics indeed in every way, but by making people Luciferian and dividing themselves from the Church, charity excluded them from their faith: as the Apostle says: If I have faith so that I can move mountains, but do not have charity, it profits me nothing.
First Corinthians 13:2.
They boast of not deviating from the faith, but we argue that they incur no small crime in not wishing to have charity with God's Church.
The Jovinianists, named after a certain Jovinian, are detected to have taken up the eighty-second heresy.
Like the Stoic philosophers, they claim that all sins are equal: that a man cannot sin once he has received the washing of regeneration, and that fasting or abstaining from certain foods is of no benefit.
They destroy the virginity of holy Mary, saying she was violated by giving birth.
The virginity of nuns, the chastity of the continent, and the celibacy of men who choose a celibate life are equated to the merits of chaste and faithful marriage.
Some sacred virgins, already advanced in age, in the city of Rome where these teachings were spread, are said to have married upon hearing this.
Interestingly, Jovinian himself neither had a wife nor wanted one.
He believed this was not beneficial for future life but applied it to present convenience.
In response, Saint Ambrose, the bishop of Milan, took action and published a book to counter all of Jovinian's arguments.
After it was read in mid-Rome, specifically in the Lateran Church, the Roman people and priests, with one voice, declared anathema on the Jovinianists and Jovinian himself, at the very beginning of Lent, with Saint Anastasius the bishop presiding.
Ultimately, during Easter week, they were found feasting and indulging in pork banquets.
The people hung a roasted pig, which they found on their table, by its neck and paraded it throughout the entire city.
Jerome the priest also wrote several books against these people.
Those who read them thoroughly learn the great benefits of virginity, continence, and abstinence, and recoil at the great evils of gluttony and luxury.
Eighty-three: Our historian Eusebius places the eighty-third heresy in the sixth book, which neither Epiphanius, Polycrates, Africanus, nor Hesiod, who wrote many volumes describing all heresies in Greek, mentioned.
In the sixth book, as I said, Eusebius narrates that there were heretics in Arabia, whose leader he does not name, so we can call them Arabians.
They say that souls die and dissolve with bodies, and at the end of the world, both will be restored.
However, he notes that many of them were recalled by the great disputation of Origen.
Eighty-four: We recall that the eighty-fourth heresy was occupied by the Helvidians, named after Helvidius.
Those who dispute the holy virginity of Mary by claiming that she had other children with Joseph after the birth of Christ emerged recently, during the time of Siricius, the bishop of Rome.
They sent their followers throughout Italy and Gaul.
Jerome, an eminent scholar, wrote two books against them, which, when read at the time, were condemned with deserved abhorrence.
However, Epiphanius, an investigator of heretics, wrote a tract against those who were at that time proclaiming this blasphemous assertion, and he decided to call them Antidicomarites.
The Paternian heresy is recorded to have begun as the eighty-fifth heresy.
These people believe that the lower parts of the human body were made not by God but by the devil and live very impure lives, granting themselves the freedom to commit all sorts of sins with those parts.
When Bishop Damasus condemned them after discovering their crimes, he wrote about them in his report to Emperor Valentinian the Elder, saying:
"We wish your piety to know that the Venustians, discovered in their most shameful crime, have been condemned by the apostolic see."
He also sent their confessions along with his report.
Subsequently, a special law was enacted against them, so that wherever they were found, they would be dealt with by the sword of justice.
The Tertullianists were long ago condemned by Pope Soter of Rome.
The reason we say they adopted the eighty-sixth heresy is this:
A certain Octaviana, coming from Africa, whose husband, named Hesperius, seemed to be very close to the general Arbogast, who also held considerable power with the tyrant Maximus, brought with her a deceitful and cunning demon, who could scarcely be countered by a hundred speaking humans.
This demon claimed to be a Tertullianist priest, and through a sacred writing, he earned the right to establish a congregation outside the city walls.
When he obtained this from the tyrant Maximus, he excluded the place of our saints, the two brothers Processus and Martinianus, claiming they were Phrygians and therefore followed this law, as Tertullian did.
In this way, through the occasion of the martyrs, he was deceiving the people of God.
But when God granted victory to the devout Augustus Theodosius, and the followers of Maximus, from whose power the Tertullianist boasted, were punished, he immediately fled with the matron who had come, without any news of the living or the dead being renewed.
God restored the watch over His martyrs to the celebration of the Catholic Church.
Tertullian, however, was a citizen and presbyter of Carthage.
He published very eloquent and fervent works in defense of the truth.
He had a basilica in Carthage where people would gather to him.
This basilica remained until the time of Bishop Aurelius.
When Augustine, the bishop of Hippo, reasonably debated with them, they were converted and brought their church to the holy Church.
However, the Catholic authority reproaches Tertullian for saying that the soul is born from the soul, and for defending Montanus, Prisca, and Maximilla against the Catholic faith, and against Apollonius, the bishop of the East, and against Soter, the pope of the city of Rome, as we mentioned earlier when we exposed the Cataphrygian heretics.
From whom he later separated, lest the people seem to exclude Tertullian's name from Montanus.
He discarded all the vanity of Phrygia and propagated the Tertullianist gatherings, but he did not change anything in faith.
For he also condemned second marriages, as we mentioned, asserted that the soul comes from the soul, and called us Catholics psychics.
Wherever you read Tertullian against the psychics, know that he is acting against the Catholics.
In the eighty-seventh heresy, we name the Abelites, who, although they are earlier than almost all heretics, have now come to an end in our times.
They took their name from the son of Adam, that is, they wanted to be called Abelites from Abel.
They did not mix with wives, and yet it was not allowed for the sect itself to live without wives.
Therefore, a man and a woman, living together under the vow of continence, would adopt a boy and a girl as their future successors in the same bond.
When each of them died, others were appointed in their place, ensuring that two of different sexes succeeded in that household.
If either parent died, the surviving one would take care of the children until their own death.
After that, the adopted children would similarly adopt a boy and a girl.
They never lacked children to adopt, as their neighbors willingly gave their own children, hoping for an inheritance from others.
This was the only difference between us and them: they criticized our marriages, saying that those who marry do so as if they were not married.
The apostolic seat under Pope Saint Innocent I declared that it had found the eighty-eighth heresy in Pelagius when Coelestius, a disciple of Pelagius, taught in Carthage that humans could be without sin by relying solely on their own nature.
A deacon named Paulinus, a defender and advocate of the Church of Milan, opposed him by presenting many charges against the Catholic faith, which Coelestius refused to condemn, saying: "It does not concern me to address those accusations where my name is involved, and the crime is someone else's."
They then offered him their books, where he claimed that human nature alone could achieve perfection: that a person could exercise such justice that they could be without sin if they wanted. Adam was made mortal, and whether he sinned or not, he would have died. The law led to the kingdom, just as the Gospels did.
We confess that infants are baptized for the remission of sins because of the rule of the universal Church. Adam's sin did not harm humanity. All these points were used to condemn Coelestius. But he said there were many things in his beliefs, and he could not condemn them because of the rest.
Then, based on reports from nearly all the African bishops, Pope Innocent issued a condemnation against Pelagius and Coelestius.
However, whether before or after their condemnation by the universal Church, they continued to write that a person could be without sin, that Adam's sin did not harm the human race, that the law was given for the kingdom just like the Gospels, and that infants should not be baptized because they might have original sin.
They also claimed that nature was made so well by God that it alone is enough to be without sin.
In response to these writings, a certain writer named Constantius contended without using scripture.
Following him, Augustine, the bishop of Hippo, and Jerome, the presbyter of Bethlehem, also wrote against them.
However, the Pelagians or Coelestians are mixed with the Catholic people because they do not have a separate church.
Therefore, wherever it happens, they do not refuse communion.
They say it is of one confession in this part, in which the Eucharist is celebrated.
They argue that it is not about communion that we are distinguished.
Due to this boldness, they face dangers from our people if they are caught, and they are considered cursed by their own followers.
They also have their own presbyters and bishops.
Pelagius himself wrote in his commentary on Romans; while discussing the place where the Apostle says: Therefore, just as sin entered the world through one man, and death through sin, and in this way death came to all people, because all sinned Romans 5:12
Addressing Coelestius, who was the first to write against the transmission of sin, he says with these words: Those who oppose the transmission try to argue this way: If Adam's sin harmed even those who did not sin, then Christ's grace should also benefit those who do not believe.
They also add this: If baptism removes that original sin, then those born from two baptized parents should be free from this sin; for how can they pass on to their descendants what they themselves do not have?
These things, written by Pelagius himself, we have included.
Regarding the idea of a person being able to live without sin, the objection is this: Either a person can do it and doesn't need help, or they can't and do need help.
Anyone who seeks help admits they can't do what they want to do on their own; otherwise, it's ridiculous to ask for help with something they can do by themselves.
For example, if I wanted to lift ten pounds and asked for help, it would seem silly.
But if I wanted to lift two hundred pounds or more, because I can't do it alone, I would ask for help with great urgency, especially if my life depended on lifting that weight.
Similarly, if a child is born to two baptized parents, this reasoning teaches us that the child has nothing from the faith of the parents.
Those who are baptized have two births: one from the flesh and the other from the Holy Spirit.
From these two births, they pass on two generations to us: one from the flesh through marriage, and the other from the Spirit through the consecration of baptism.
So, I ask you, this child born of baptized parents, from which birth is he born?
From the flesh, that is, the first birth, or from the Spirit, that is, the second birth?
If he is born of the Spirit, he should not be baptized.
Why?
Because the Holy Spirit made him born, not the desire of marriage.
But if he is born from a carnal union, that is from a man and a woman, then just as they were reborn in Christ and the Church, they must also rebirth their offspring.
For we are born from the first Adam: from the second Adam, we are reborn, as the holy Apostle said:
The first man Adam was made a living soul, the last Adam a life-giving spirit.
But it is not the spiritual that comes first, but the natural; then the spiritual.
The first man was from the earth, earthly; the second man is from heaven, heavenly.
Therefore, just as we have borne the image of the earthly, that is, just as we have created children in a carnal way, let us also bear the image of the heavenly.
First Corinthians 15:45-49.
Those whom we have created physically, let us recreate spiritually.
Or we, who have been created physically by the Creator's will, let us again be spiritually recreated by His grace.
The Apostle said this: "Flesh and blood," meaning people born only by natural means, cannot find the kingdom of God unless they have earned divine grace.
Nor will corruption inherit incorruption.
The eighty-ninth heresy is attributed to Nestorius, the bishop of Constantinople.
It was customary for the bishop of Alexandria to send one of his sermons to Constantinople to be read at Easter, and for the bishop of Constantinople to send one to Alexandria to be read there.
In his sermon, Nestorius of Constantinople wrote that Mary should not be called Theotokos (God-bearer) but Christotokos (Christ-bearer); that is, she did not give birth to God, but to a man.
Cyril of Alexandria criticized this statement by writing a letter, suggesting that if Nestorius had made a mistake, he should correct it.
Because of this criticism from Cyril, Nestorius began to call Cyril a heretic.
A synod was held at Ephesus; and even then, Nestorius did not want to correct his statement to say that Mary gave birth to both God and man, but insisted she gave birth only to a man.
He argued that if we say she gave birth to God, we make her the mother of God, like the pagans.
So, Mary, he said, gave birth to a temple for God, not God Himself who dwells in the temple.
He was given a chance to either condemn his statement and return to his position as bishop, or if he refused to condemn it, he would not be able to return.
He refused and remained in the same confession.
The synod at Ephesus condemned him.
In this condemnation, Pope Celestine of Rome wrote, and all the bishops, both Eastern and Western, signed with him.
The ninetieth heresy, which we mentioned in our preface as falsely attributed to the name of Bishop Augustine, is called the Predestinarians.
They define the election of the good and the rejection of the bad as being decided by God, not by a person either striving or neglecting.
They do not want God's laws to be either kept by those who strive or violated by those who neglect.
They say that someone destined to do evil cannot achieve goodness, even if they try.
On the other hand, someone destined to do good will be led to it involuntarily, even if they neglect it.
They claim that the water of baptism doesn't cleanse all sins.
They believe that grace comes before free will, so a person receives it before asking, finds it before seeking, and has the door opened to them before knocking.
They say no one comes to faith in Christ unless drawn by the Father, referencing the passage: "No one comes to me unless the Father who sent me draws them" (John 6:44).
They argue that everything happens not in reality but in hope, applying the Apostle's words: "Hope that is seen is not hope" (Romans 8:24) to mysteries, suggesting that things perceived seem to exist but do not.
They say Adam harmed the human race more than Christ helped it.
They claim that Adam's harm remains in such a way that neither Christ's passion nor the sanctification of baptism can remove it.
But why should we delay, holy and eager reader?
We present to you their book in its entirety, as it was published, so that by reading it, you will recognize its definitions as inventions of the Antichrist's plotters.
Whenever we opposed them, they accused us of using heretical arguments.
Feeling so defeated that they couldn't even sigh, they always cast this slander on our Catholic efforts, fearing to be branded as heretics and stifling the voice of truth.
Therefore, for their sake, we have exposed all heresies from Simon up to now, to prove that we alone are in agreement with the Catholic faith.
We pray to you, Lord, Father of heaven and earth, who with Your Son and the Holy Spirit hold the majesty of one truth, the majesty of one divinity, the trinity of one divinity, to help us against your enemies who wield weapons.
Let them have the camps of Goliath set up in the line of the Philistines.
We Hebrews, your children taking up David's sling, will fight from your cornerstone so that we may confidently say with your Apostle:
Thanks be to our God, who gave us victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
First Corinthians 13:17.
Let there be peace for all Catholics, and with the angels, let them cry out with one voice with us,
singing, Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace to people of good will.
Book Two, Forged Under the Name of Augustine, containing the ninetieth heresy, which asserts that sins are committed by God's predestination.
Spiritual brothers suggested that I share in your intention to defend the truth.
Therefore, I briefly joined your efforts, avoiding a lengthy discourse.
I condensed the thoughts that seek a broad field of contention into a narrow scope to spare you the tedium of reading and to provide an opportunity to defend the truth and refute those fighting against the will of their Lord.
Specifically, those who say that human wills are moved against the will and desire of God, and that the power of the immortal God is thwarted by the power of mortals.
They add that people become holy through their own will and reach friendship with God by their own choice.
You will see these individuals easily falling, from whom human concern has taken the better and primary parts, and who say that a person can save themselves not by God's ordinance, but by their own will.
But you, O children of love, retaining the zeal of faith marked in your hearts, be assured of the ordinance of God, which He established by predestination.
Let the sentence spoken by the apostolic voice be certain to our minds: "For He has mercy on whom He wills, and He hardens whom He wills." For it is not of him who wills, nor of him who runs, but of God who shows mercy. As it is written in the book of Romans chapter nine, verses nineteen and sixteen: "For He has mercy on whom He wills, and He hardens whom He wills."
Because the potter has power over the clay to make from the same lump one vessel for honor, and another for dishonor, as stated in Romans chapter nine, verse twenty-one. Hence, it is that the flesh opposes the spirit, and the spirit opposes the flesh. The Apostle says, "These are opposed to each other, so that you do not do what you want" (Galatians chapter five, verse seventeen).
For in His work, God foresaw all people beforehand, and by foreseeing what would be fitting for each, He determined it.
This is a unique indication of His majesty, in which He has no equal.
For God alone foreknows what should be thought, spoken, and done.
Since He foresaw the deeds of all generally before they were done, He arranged their merits as if they were already accomplished.
And so, God predestined and determined things as if they were visible and clear to Him when He foresaw them.
He decided who would become like the image of His Son so that the Son of God would be the firstborn among many brothers.
Those He predestined, He called; those He called, He justified; and those He justified, He glorified.
Therefore, the prophet says, "It is not in man to direct his steps."
What do you think, you fragile, mortal, and miserable humans? Do you think you should be praised if you do good, or completely condemned if you sin?
The law speaks to instill fear; otherwise, nothing happens except what God wills. Whoever God wills to be holy is holy; nothing else will be. Whoever He foresees to be wicked will be wicked; nothing else will be.
For God's predestination has already set the number of the righteous and the number of sinners, and the determined limit cannot be exceeded.
However, this is not established as a respecter of persons but as one who knows all future events.
God fixed and established His predestination not by favoritism but by foreknowledge. Those He foreknew would not turn back in any way, He predestined to death; those He foreknew would turn back in every way, He predestined to life.
I am amazed that testimonies from the Old Testament are presented against the authority of the New Testament.
They usually misuse the testimonies of the holy prophet Ezekiel, who says, "This is what the Lord says: When I say to the wicked, 'You will surely die,' and they turn from their wickedness, as I live, says the Lord, they shall live."
This, as I said, was written in the old law for the time of captivity, for the reason that captivity happened, and for the people to whom it was inflicted, so that those in captivity would learn that they were subjected to the yoke of the Assyrian king because of their sins.
Certainly, captivity happened because of sin. And why did the righteous suffer captivity along with sinners, if not because the mysteries of God cannot be fully known by our frailty?
This mystery is written in the old law.
But in the new law, the Apostle exclaims:
"Vessels of wrath prepared for destruction" (Romans 9:22).
It is written, recalling what God said in his foreknowledge:
"Jacob I loved, but Esau I hated" (Romans 9:13).
Before they were born or had done anything good or bad (Romans 9:11), it was said in foreknowledge that one would be hated and the other loved.
These things were not invented by us, nor do we say anything other than what the Apostle preached.
He himself recalls that predestination is done through God's foreknowledge.
He says of God:
"Those he called, he also predestined" (Romans 8:30).
If you read in the Apostle about foreknowing, predestining, and calling, why do you accuse us of a crime for saying that God predestined people either to righteousness or to sin, lest it appear that he makes people do what he does not want?
For God remains undefeated in his will, while man is constantly overcome.
So if you confess that God is undefeated, confess also this: whatever he wanted those he created to be, they cannot be anything else.
Hence, we conclude that those whom God once predestined to life, even if they neglect, even if they sin, even if they are unwilling, will be led to life against their will: but those he predestined to death, even if they run, even if they hurry, labor in vain.
And do not admit this without the teaching of a clear example.
Judas heard the word of life every day, adhered to the Lord every day, engaged in virtues every day, and heard the Son of God himself as a teacher every day.
But because he was predestined to death, he perished suddenly with one blow.
Saul was a persecutor every day, a stoner of Christians every day, a ravager of churches every day.
Yet because he was predestined to life, he was suddenly made a vessel of election with one blow.
So why do you, who remain in sins, fear?
If God has honored you, you will be holy.
Or why do you, who live in holiness, become anxious as if your anxiety preserves you?
If God does not want it, you will never fall.
Be secure in God.
You, who are holy and anxious not to fall, who attend to prayers day and night, engage in fasting, are diligently devoted to divine readings, occupied with exhortations, and daily immersed in all holy studies-do you think you will be saved by this dedication?
Will you be holier than Judas, who received the power to heal the sick, cast out demons, raise the dead, and tread on serpents and scorpions, a fellow apostle and disciple of Christ; and yet, because he was predestined to death, found eternal death?
Cease worrying about yourself, O man.
Cease, I say, to be anxious about your virtue, and trust securely only in the will of God.
You will obtain nothing good from God against His will; but if God deems you worthy to remain in good, you will be saved.
You too, who are shaken by vain despair in sin, learn from the Apostle Paul.
Who could ever be found equal to him in crimes?
Could you have committed worse sins than he did?
And yet, because he was predestined to the apostleship, he suddenly escaped all crimes and ascended from the lowest depths to the highest heights.
Therefore, all whom God knows to be worthy of the salvation of His redemption, He has predestined to salvation: and He saves only those whom He knows He has predestined to salvation.
For the salvation of God does not serve the will of man; for He knows to whom He will give what.
Nor does the freedom of human will precede the grace of God, but the grace of God precedes the will of human choice.
For the will of man is vain and fruitless, and the judgment of human will is vain.
He errs who thinks he can reach Christ by his own will for good, when Christ Himself says: No one comes to me unless the Father draws him (John 6:44).
You who understand better from Christ, tell me if Christ lied: and then assert that we have set this opinion against the rule of Christ.
For if Christ spoke the truth, it is not a lie that we say the predestined are drawn to life, because He Himself is life.
If the force of the Gospel testimony weighs on you, and you come against our judgment, and you cannot give us an answer, being burdened by the weight of our judgment, at least explain to us the Apostles' definition, which says:
"It is not of him who wills, nor of him who runs, but of God who shows mercy" (Romans 9:16).
Therefore, no matter how much human will exerts its strength to build, it strives in vain.
Or why does human frailty think its vigilance will be helpful to eternal desires when the prophet clearly exclaims with evidence, saying:
"Unless the Lord builds the house, those who build it labor in vain. Unless the Lord guards the city, the watchmen stay awake in vain" (Psalms 127:1-2).
What is the point of someone hoping to work towards building against divine teachings and their own conscience, when these sacred writings teach that human building is uncertain and in vain?
But if you come against us, you do not come against us but against Him who said:
"Unless the Lord builds the house, those who build it labor in vain. Unless the Lord guards the city, the watchmen stay awake in vain."
Do you not know that it was not useful to the people of God who had these things written and directed to future generations until the end of time?
Therefore, you who criticize these things, remove them from the book of Psalms, because, as you say, those reading and singing these verses cannot be built up.
But what do these people think they can achieve by their own will, when even the chosen vessel did not claim to have fulfilled his own will?
For the Apostle says about himself:
"For I do not do the good I want, but the evil I do not want is what I do" (Romans 7:19).
So if the Apostle cannot accomplish the good he wants, how do these people say they can reach the fruit of grace by their own will?
These are the words of the Apostle, we add nothing of our own.
He says about himself:
"For I do not do the good I want, but the evil I do not want is what I do."
And you blame us because we say,
"None are called except the predestined?"
For the grace of God precedes the will of man.
God is first in the goodness of man; however, even the best of men are rarely the last in all good things.
Give the first place to God to eliminate human pride.
But if you want to nurture pride in people, it appears you seek the ruin of the human race, because you teach that in doing good, it is not God who goes first, but human will.
This makes it seem as if people are the ones reminding God to do good, as if He would not do good unless they told Him to, even though it is clear that God grants good to everyone without anyone suggesting or asking.
For the Apostle does not say "when we asked"; instead, he says, "when we were enemies, we were reconciled to God through the death of His Son" Romans 5:10. So where is the will of man? It is excluded. Why? Because not everyone who wants is saved; if everyone who wanted to be saved was saved, no one could be excluded from salvation.
For every person wants to be saved, but not every person is saved; rather, the one whom God wills is saved. Indeed, I say, the one whom God wills, so that the will of man is excluded and His complete grace is fully revealed.
But if God wants someone to be good and they are not good, then man would be defeating God. For man would indeed defeat God if God wanted him to be good and he was not. Therefore, the will and effect of God is in the goodness of man. For it was not when we asked or when we requested, but "when we were enemies, we were reconciled to God through the death of His Son."
And when you read that His Son died for all, I wonder how you understand "all" to mean everyone, when you scarcely see a few attain salvation. Wherever you read "all," you want to understand it generally as everyone, although often "all" is taught to mean a part.
For when it says, "All have turned away" Psalms 14:3, not all have turned away, and "every man is a liar" Psalms 116:11, not every man is a liar, because we read of someone: "There was a truthful man." And also, "Lying men will not be remembered by Him; but truthful men will be found in it" Sirach 15:8.
Therefore, the largest part seems to signify everyone, even though it is clear that not everyone should be understood.
And I am surprised that with your eyes closed, you pass by the enemy's traps.
You say that a person's will can achieve something of virtue, not noticing how many falls from chastity are caused by the devil, and how many crimes of lust, greed, envy, and treachery are committed daily.
If you could see these things, we would not have to show you the damage to virtues and the victories of vices.
If the freedom of choice were intact, these things would not happen.
Through the transgression of the first man, the freedom of choice perished from humans.
But you renew the Pelagian heresy again when you say that people can put an end to sins through the freedom of choice.
For you exclude grace through the freedom of choice.
We are either freed by free will or rescued by the grace of God.
Choose what you say.
If you give everything to grace, we think alike; if to free will, know that we cannot agree with you.
From where comes that greater freedom of choice in one for good, and the lesser in another, except that it is determined by God's dispensation?
For in one person, grace shows itself as slight, in another as abundant and generous, as grace itself wills, not as we will, who have departed from the order of our creation.
We recognize to such an extent that human nature is corrupted through Adam's transgression, that its restoration through Christ has been achieved not in reality but in hope, as the Apostle says:
"For in hope we have been saved; but hope that is seen is not hope"
(Romans 8:24).
Therefore, if we are saved in hope, we have not yet received the reality in this present age.
Thus, even those who are baptized still desire carnally and suffer the movements of the body; because they have received the aid of restoration in hope, not in reality.
For if they had received it in reality, after the grace of baptism, there would be neither the possibility nor the will to sin.
But because the power of baptism is so great that it erases all sins, the tendency of sins is not washed away by the water of baptism; for it is taught that it naturally exists through Adam.
For those parts of the body that have no shame at the moment of baptism later receive shame, causing them to avoid being seen and seek modest concealment.
The parts that God created were turned into shameful parts by disobedience and are now called shameful parts.
These shameful parts become parts again at the moment of baptism but soon turn back into shameful parts; for they are renewed not in actuality but in hope.
The desire of the flesh, which rules the body like a law of sin through Adam's disobedience, reclaims the baptized person and tries to overthrow their entire soul.
This is the root of that wound which Christ healed.
He healed it in the way the Apostle says: For in this hope we were saved (Romans 8:24).
He commands us to shift our mind to contemplate the unseen and not to fall by presuming on the things that are seen.
Therefore, he says: Hope that is seen is not hope (Romans 8:24).
Lest it be thought that sins are so completely removed through baptism that even the roots of sins are equally uprooted.
That movement of pollution, which invaded nature through disobedience, remains in the baptized person like the root of a hair, even when the surface has been cleansed and shaved with a razor.
For it has been shaved so that the place may be cleansed: it has not been eradicated, so that it may no longer grow back.
If all the frailty of Adam's disobedience were completely removed through baptism, all the baptized would be drawn to no crimes by the heat of passion, no one would be polluted by human filth, and no one would be pricked by the sting of desire.
But because we are saved in hope, what we do not yet see, we wait for with patience.
The time will come when they neither marry nor are given in marriage but are like angels in heaven (Matthew 22:30).
For when this perishable body puts on the imperishable, and this mortal body puts on immortality, then the saying that is written will come true: Death is swallowed up in victory.
Where, O death, is your victory?
Where, O death, is your sting?
The sting of death is sin, and the power of sin is the law (First Corinthians 15:54-56).
Then we will say: Thank God who gave us victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
Prologue of the following book
The book, which stands against humanity and opposes the Catholic faith, is now complete.
It is a deceitful book, filled with lies, and distorts pure doctrine.
As Saint Cyprian says, it presents falsehoods to steal the truth.
Although it is published under the guise of piety, it acts against all the institutions of the saints.
Because of this book, as we mentioned in the preface, we have compiled the sects of all heretics into one volume so that its defenders know we oppose all heresies and do not support any of them.
Therefore, O holy mother Church, mother of pure faith, against your hidden enemies, against new barbarians who pretend to be peaceful, against those who take up arms against you in your name, lift up our strength and help those willing to enter the battle.
Especially against those whom no one has yet challenged in writing, while they have almost wounded the whole world with their writings under the name of the priest Augustine, producing corrupted books and various letters which they falsely claim to be from the mentioned bishop of Hippo.
And to all defenders of the Catholic faith, we earnestly pray that you set aside all distractions and attentively consider our battle.
Keeping the future judgment in mind, defend what should be defended and condemn what should be condemned.
The reason we have brought this book to the forefront, leaving other wrongdoings aside, is because they pass it down to those they deceive as if it were a creed.
Therefore, we believed it necessary to write this entire book in order, so it does not seem that the easily refutable parts were taken from their book, while the cleverly omitted parts, which could have defended the book from our accusation, were left out.
We have therefore omitted nothing: revealing all his body in these writings, we brandish the sword of God's word against him.
Cutting him into pieces, we expose each of his limbs to the eyes of Catholics: showing the poison in his head, the twists in his mouth, and the arrows from his chest.
By examining the function of each limb, we expose his cunning opposition.
Laying him captive at the feet of the Catholic Church, we make him manifest to all:
So that he himself becomes his own condemner.
By abandoning Catholic doctrine, he wished to defile his own consent with the contagion of this book.
Book Three
Containing the refutation of the previous book falsely attributed to Saint Augustine
So far, the forests of all heretics have been set ablaze, where deceitful treachery has plundered the riches of faith.
The Church has suffered plunder, and the blood of souls has been shed.
But since thorns often sprout again after a fire, let us hold the sickle of divine judgment, so we can cut off the heads of the thorns that rise again and go against heaven.
There will be no lack of workers for this field, with God's provision, so that the blessed and blameless on the path, blameless in faith, who walk in the law of the Lord (Psalm one hundred nineteen, verse one), can reach their destination without the hindrance of thorns.
The Predestinarians made the ninetieth heresy, showing false books that they falsely attribute to Augustine, whose statements in many places are read in these books as very contrary.
Therefore, Catholics are given a true suspicion that such wicked statements cannot be those of an orthodox man, who, submitting to the Mathematicians, say that the human race is so subject to divine predestination that all the evils that happen in the world are said to be committed by God's will.
Therefore, human fear or shame should not make us share in their errors; we have taken care of all heretics and found that no one could err worse than those who say that all evils and crimes are committed by God's predestination.
Let all heretics have one book, in which we condemn them not by power but by true reasoning, so that the Predestinarians know that we do not consent to any heretic.
Let the Predestinarians also have one book, in which God himself proves against them, who knows that he has predestined no one to evil but has predestined all to good, so that we may approve what is good, as his.
For all the good things that people do now, or have done from the beginning, or will do, we say are completed by God's grace, God's mercy, God's help, and even God's predestination.
But by predestination, we mean not that God forces good upon the unwilling, but that he never changes his intention of goodness and is always ready for those who willingly choose good, but unprepared for those who willingly choose evil.
If those approaching goodness receive immediate rewards for their faith, such as forgiveness of sins and becoming children of God, while those heading towards evil do not immediately face the punishment they deserve, instead receiving generous periods of grace from His patience.
.
We confess and affirm this predestined and fixed plan of God.
Therefore, when evil occurs, it is not because God has forsaken His plan, but because man has introduced his own contempt.
Sin is never committed by God's will, but through man's negligence.
Mankind sins against God's will to such an extent that He is always angered by those who practice sin and aids those who act justly.
Indeed, when the whole world had turned away from righteousness and deserved to perish in the flood, it is shown that God wished to save it through His rebuke.
What does the apostle Peter say?
God's patience waited in the days of Noah while the ark was being built.
First Peter 3:20.
Tell us, what was God's patience waiting for?
Was it for predestined destruction or for a provoked conversion?
The construction of the ark served as a preacher of the flood.
The axe cried out, the hammer resounded, the saw testified, and even the tools themselves preached the flood to the unbelievers.
Given a period of 100 years, the law preceded, stating that those destined to perish could escape by repenting: predestination did not hinder this, as it did not deny that correction could lead to salvation.
If predestination set a fixed limit, the law would be unjust, as it seeks to invade others' boundaries.
Therefore, to establish predestination, refute the commandments: reject the law to bring the reign of predestination.
The law has always wanted to command everyone and never serve anyone.
So if predestination nullifies the law's authority, and the law disrupts the rights of predestination, one of the two carries tyranny.
Choose now, Catholics, to whom we should submit our necks.
If we consider the law, we must acknowledge that predestination removes the authority of the law.
The law says: Keep my commandments, and you will live; but predestination says: The vessels of wrath are already prepared for destruction, and the vessels of mercy are called to life.
Both of these are written: What should we do now, choose.
If the vessels of wrath are already prepared by God to sin, and the vessels of mercy are prepared for life, then we should all submit to the rule of predestination and set aside the law and its preachers.
And don't think this is a new sin; this has happened from the beginning with every group of sinners.
Why were the prophets, apostles, and all the saints killed?
Because they brought God's law to human minds and accused sinners of their vices.
If they had wanted to introduce the kingdom of predestination with flattering words, excluding the law of justice, no one would have been killed.
For they said, as it is written: Do not prophesy to us hard things Isaiah 30:10.
What does it mean, do not prophesy to us hard things?
It undoubtedly means: do not preach punishments to us through the threatening law.
To this they responded: If the monitors of our time had listened to them, they would have served them with flattering words in these matters, and, as you do, deceived them by wrongly interpreting the testimonies of the law.
Rest assured in the order of God, established by predestination.
God has mercy on whom he wants and hardens whom he wants.
It is not of him who wills, nor of him who runs, but of God who shows mercy.
The potter has the power to make from the same lump one vessel for honor, another for dishonor.
The flesh opposes the spirit, and the spirit opposes the flesh.
These are contrary to each other, so you do not do what you want.
God has already predestined those he foreknew; and those he predestined, he called; those he called, he justified; and those he justified, he glorified.
A man's way is not his own.
Do you think you should be praised for the good you do, when the law speaks to instill fear?
Ultimately, nothing happens unless God wills it: whoever He wants to be holy is holy; there is no other outcome.
Whoever He foresees as wicked is wicked; there is no other outcome.
For God's predestination has already determined the number of the righteous and the number of sinners, and it is inevitable that the set boundary cannot be surpassed.
If they had said these things you mention, they would have escaped human anger for a time, but they would have found eternal punishment from God.
So they did not say this, but they said:
"This is what the Lord says: If you are willing and listen to me, you will eat the good things of the land; but if you refuse and do not listen to me, the sword will devour you. For the mouth of the Lord has spoken this" Isaiah 1:19-21.
And again: "This is what the Lord says: Because you have turned away from me, I will also turn away from you and deliver you to the Assyrians for plundering. Your children will be killed by the sword before your eyes, and your wives will be taken away, because you have despised my law and chosen what I did not want."
And again: "This is what the Lord says: Have I become a disgrace to the house of Israel because they have abandoned me and considered my commands and laws as nothing?"
And again: "Because I have called and you have refused, I too will laugh at your disaster and rejoice when sudden calamity comes upon you" Proverbs 1:26.
Saying these and similar things, they were killed with various punishments.
Therefore, the Lord also cries out to the people of the city where the prophets were killed, both in the prophets and in His Gospels, saying:
"Jerusalem, Jerusalem, you who kill the prophets and stone those sent to you, how often I have wanted to gather your children together, as a hen gathers her chicks under her wings, but you were not willing" Matthew 23:37.
You were not willing, He says, for what I wanted; you wanted what I did not. So if God did not want what they wanted, either He was forced by someone more powerful to set the predestination, or if He set it Himself, He acted unjustly. For why would He say to a person: "I wanted this, but you did not," if He knew He had predestined them not to want it?
According to your view, man's guilt is dismissed, and the blame is shifted to God: the sinner is innocent, and the punisher is unjust.
It's more appropriate to feel sorrow for the sinner rather than anger,
because he was driven by divine predestination when he fell into sin.
This is what the Creator willed; the one who created is the same one who predestined.
If this is true, it's clear that the fault doesn't lie entirely with the sinner.
So, if he doesn't fully own the fault when he sins, and if everything the just God condemns is foreign to Him, it is found to be His work, and thus His sin.
It doesn't make sense to say that one person predestines while another is called the transgressor; nor is it fair to suggest that God's predestination causes another's crime.
To punish the sinner, show the predestinator; reveal the author of predestination so you can identify the judge of sin, because you can't claim the same one is both the predestinator and the condemner.
If God is the author of predestination and the establisher of our actions, show another who punishes predestined sins; or if He, as a just being, condemns the unjust deeds of human actions, show another who predestined this injustice.
Someone who disapproves of a deed could never have established it to be done.
It's foolish to believe that the same predestinator is also the condemner of actions.
No one is so impious as to despise something preordained by themselves and then punish the very deed they preordained.
Unless perhaps, by changing his mind for the better, he decides that what he previously did is condemnable, driven by better judgment.
But if He stands firm in omnipotence, knowing no equal or superior, tell us why He would condemn His own predestination?
Because if the actions of the predestined are guilty, then the order of the predestinator must be even more so.
If someone is guilty because of predestination itself, how much more is the one whose predestination leads to guilt?
Be careful, I beg you, not to let these false teachings corrupt the pure doctrine of the Church: sin is not directed by the one who predestines but is committed by the one who transgresses.
So, let the empty arguments of words cease.
The transgression of the sinner and the predestination of the avenger have nothing in common: because sin is in the will of the transgressor, but predestination is ordered by the power of the redeemer.
The Creator did not predestine anything other than that man could live according to His will.
It is blasphemous and extremely wrong to believe that human presumption comes from God's predestination, and that the vice of the sinner is judged by the preordination of the future judge.
They say: "God established His predestination through foreknowledge. For those He knew would not convert, He predestined to death; and those He knew would convert, He predestined to life."
Let's see if you are not twisting God's judgment to the detriment of justice with these unjust arguments.
So, men are not yet created, and already they suffer from a just God's prejudice?
It seems you have invented another God for yourselves, one so unjust that He surrounds the human race with bias, determines the fate of an unborn man by marking him, binds him to sin through predestination, and prepares eternal punishments for one not yet conceived; He prepares perpetual darkness for one to whom He has not yet given the transient gifts of this fleeting life.
Seek another God for yourselves, as I said, if you believe these things.
For you will never provoke our merciful and compassionate God to act this way, even with your blasphemies.
For He who tolerates you patiently, I do not know whom He would not forgive for sinning.
Every day, He helps us even when we act unjustly, and He continually grants us new gifts of forgiveness for our new sins.
Yet you say: Before the world's creation, He was already angry with us for future sins and destined us to condemnation.
In the present, He grants pardon to those who blaspheme, but you say: At that time, He was already angry with those who would sin and predestined them to death when He first formed the foundations of humanity.
So, did He already judge the world back then, before He even created the world itself, so that after the end of the age, He would find no one left to punish?
Perhaps He wanted to avoid the effort of judging people after they were made, by predestining them to death before they were created to live.
And yet, if He created those He predestined to punishment, He anticipated the act of killing; and someone who has not even begun to live has already received the sentence of eternal death.
Our God never did this: if there is some other god of yours, then attribute these blasphemies to him.
About our God, the prophet says:
"As I live, declares the Lord, if I say to the sinner: 'You will die,' and the sinner turns from his evil way and from his wicked pursuits, as I live, declares the Lord, he will live and not die in the sin he committed. And if I say to the righteous: 'You will live,' and he then turns from his righteousness, as I live, declares the Lord, he will die: his righteousness will not save him on the day he turns from his righteousness and commits iniquity; he will die in his iniquity" (Ezekiel 33:13 and following).
You see, our God warns both the righteous, so they do not fall from security, and the sinner, so they do not remain in despair.
If anywhere you have read about God saying: "As I live, declares the Lord, those I have predestined to life will be nothing else, and those I have predestined to death will undoubtedly die," who would tolerate you teaching such things?
Behold, God speaks against your judgment, and you do not believe God Himself as He testifies about Himself.
The righteous should not feel secure, he says, if I tell him: You will live, because if he turns away from righteousness, he will die in iniquity.
And when I have told the sinner: You will die, and he has repented, I live, says the Lord, I will not remember his iniquities, he will live.
For I do not desire the death of the dying, but only that he may turn and live.
Again, those who cry out meet us: This is written in the old law, but in the new, the Apostle proclaims: Vessels of wrath prepared for destruction (Romans 9:22).
Therefore, if mercy was already abundant before the coming of mercy, how much more now, when mercy itself has taken upon the sentence for the ungodly, to absolve the ungodly from their guilt and call them back to the grace of forgiveness?
So let us see by what order the vessels of wrath are prepared for destruction.
Listen to the Apostle, applying this not to God's predestination, but to man's negligence or diligence.
In a great house, he says, there are not only vessels of gold and silver, but also of wood and clay; and some are for honor, and some for dishonor.
If anyone cleanses himself from these, he will be a vessel for honor, sanctified, useful to God, prepared for every good work (Second Timothy 2:20-22).
Therefore, the vessels prepared for wrath, if they cleanse themselves from the things for which they were prepared for destruction, will be vessels for honor, sanctified, and useful to God, prepared for every good work; as he said above to the prophet: When I tell the sinner: You will die (Ezekiel 33:34), that is, when I say: You will be a vessel prepared for destruction, and this sinner turns away from his iniquity, that is, when he, being a vessel prepared for destruction, cleanses himself from these things, he will be a vessel for honor, sanctified.
After you have overcome them on this point, they flee to the more obscure places of Scripture to shoot in the dark at the upright in heart.
They say, Do you not know that it is written: Jacob I loved, but Esau I hated?
For when they were not yet born, and had done neither good nor evil, it was said from foreknowledge that one would be hated, and the other loved.
We need to shed light on the sacred law interpretation here, so you don't focus on anything misleading.
The goal isn't to strip Catholics of their beliefs but to address certain misconceptions.
In the book of Genesis, it is said about Rebecca:
"Two nations and two peoples will come from your womb, and one people will be stronger than the other, and the older will serve the younger" (Genesis 25:23).
This prophecy isn't about those born naturally, but about the Jews and the Gentiles.
Here, the greater people, the Jews, will serve the lesser, the Gentiles.
The Apostle follows this idea:
"It was said from foreknowledge that the older will serve the younger" (Romans 9:12).
Why did you say this, O blessed Apostle Paul?
Did you mean to suggest that predestination would affect those not yet born?
The Apostle answers:
"I said, 'The older will serve the younger,' so that the choice would be made from the Gentiles."
If the Apostle interprets this prophecy for us, who are you to explain it differently? Remember, it was said that if an angel from heaven preaches a different gospel, let him be accursed (Galatians 1:8).
Some argue:
We do not say anything other than what the Apostle preached.
He mentions predestination made through God's foreknowledge.
He says about God: "Those He called, He also predestined" (Romans 8:30).
If you read about foreknowing, predestining, and calling in the Apostle, why accuse us of a crime?
We aren't accusing you of a crime, but proving a point.
Whether you consider yourselves skilled or not, you shouldn't distort apostolic meanings.
We criticize you for making assumptions without proper knowledge and for promising to teach something you never truly understood.
If you had wanted to learn first and then teach, avoiding these interpretations, you would never have strayed from God's fairness, nor would you have said that God does not want all people to be saved.
Our knowledgeable Apostle of the law says he became all things to all people so that he might save all sinners.
As it is written in First Corinthians chapter 9, verse 22: "For he had already learned that God has confined everyone in disobedience so that he may have mercy on all." From the book of Romans, chapter 11, verse 32: "He had learned that every mouth should be silenced and the whole world held accountable to God." From Romans, chapter 3, verse 19: "And so he said: I say through the grace given to me, to everyone among you." Romans, chapter 12, verse 3: "Admonishing every person and teaching." From Colossians, chapter 1, verse 28: "The same God is rich to all of you." Romans, chapter 10, verse 12: "The grace of God has appeared to all people, teaching us." From Titus, chapter 2, verse 11: "So that everyone may be perfect in Christ." Second Timothy, chapter 3, verse 17: "And because he knew that the Son of God was born for everyone, and suffered for everyone, he therefore exclaims, saying: This is good and acceptable in the sight of God our Savior, who wants all people to be saved and to come to the knowledge of the truth." First Timothy, chapter 2, verse 3: "Hence, every day in his Gospels, the Lord himself cries out to us, saying: Come to me, all you who labor and are burdened, and I will give you rest." From the book of Matthew, chapter 11, verse 28: "Therefore, to show that he does not reject anyone from his generosity, always ready, generous, abundant, never lacking, he speaks in his Gospels, saying: Everyone who asks receives, and the one who seeks finds, and to the one who knocks, it will be opened." Matthew, chapter 7, verse 8: "For even the Scripture of the Old Testament, inviting all nations to listen, said: Hear this, all you peoples; listen, all who live in this world, both low and high, rich and poor alike." Psalm 49, verse 2:
And so, the same Apostle, seeing that God wants all people to be saved, but not all people want God, remembers the future judgment and cries out, saying: We must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ, so that each one may receive what is due for what he has done in the body, whether good or evil.
Second Corinthians 5:10
Hence, the Apostle Peter says: The grace of God is over all, and in all of you.
All the prophets call, all the apostles call, Christ calls everyone, and priests of God all over the world call everyone to the grace and mercy of God and to forgiveness.
Only a few small-minded men, with blind hearts, go out with these apostate books, pretending that they are written by Catholic men, and they harm the whole world.
By introducing a new kind of blasphemy, they say that God does not want all people to be saved and come to the knowledge of the truth.
And by enduring the obscurity of one passage, they want to impose the darkness of their own ignorance on such great light and immense splendor.
But because the light shines in the darkness, and the darkness has not overcome it (John 1:5), with the Lord's help, taking from his treasures, we have explained the passage that they think supports their heresy.
Now, let us also speak about foreknowledge and predestination.
God foresaw and foretold that in the offspring of Abraham, that is, in Christ, all nations would be blessed.
While this was coming to pass, the Jews were quite upset.
For this reason, they apprehended the apostles and kept them in custody, saying to them: We warned you not to preach in this name; yet you have filled all Jerusalem with your teaching.
Acts 5:28
But the Apostle Paul, seeing that the Jews were failing because the Gentiles were entering into the faith and excluding the Jews from the privilege of the Synagogue by the privilege of the Church, addresses them so that they would not be saddened, saying: Why do you now forbid us to speak to the Gentiles so that they may be saved, when you know that God said to Abraham that in your offspring all nations will be blessed?
First Thessalonians 2:16, Genesis 22:8, Acts 3:25
God knew in advance that the Jews would reject His Son and that people from other nations would believe in Him.
And so He says:
"Those He foreknew, He also predestined to be conformed to the image of His Son, that He might be the firstborn among many brothers." (Romans 8:29).
While the Jews, through circumcision, are taught to be the children of Abraham, the nations become children of God through baptism, and the Son of God becomes their firstborn brother.
The only begotten Son of God specifically becomes the brother of those who are generally adopted as children of God.
Hence, He says to the Father:
"I will declare Your name to my brothers." (Psalm 22:22).
So, as we said, He foreknew these people of the nations, knowing that they would receive His Son, whom the Jews were going to crucify, with a sincere heart and would worship Him as the Son of God, as was fitting:
"Those He foreknew, He also predestined to be conformed to the image of His Son, that His Son might be the firstborn among many brothers; those He predestined, He also called."
If you ask the Apostle when He predestined, he tells you:
"When He said to Abraham: 'In your seed all the nations shall be blessed.'
And therefore, through the prophet, He says:
"Hear this, all you nations." (Psalm 49:1).
So He says to the Jews: Nothing should seem new to you in what God has done, who wished to fulfill the promise He made to our father Abraham, that in his seed all the nations would be blessed.
Therefore, because He predestined all the nations, He concluded all in unbelief so that He might have mercy on all.
(Romans 11:32).
Therefore, those He predestined, He also called; those He called, He also justified by removing all sins; and those He justified, He also glorified, that is, He made them children of God.
Why then do you murmur, O Jews, preventing us from speaking to the nations?
If God is for us, who can be against us?
(Romans 8:31-32).
Why do you lay hands on us and cause scandal to the apostles of God?
For if God did not spare His own Son, but delivered Him up for us all, know this, O Predestined one, what He says:
He delivered Him up for us all.
By saying He was given up for everyone, He removed the scandal from the Jews and excluded your intention.
However, I am amazed at your prudence in reading this passage:
Those whom He predestined, He also called," so you were afraid to approach the previous verse.
For when you came to this passage, thinking it satisfied your intention, you did not want to look ahead to the verse that convicted you, that is,
He gave Him up for everyone"; but you closed the book and began to shout:
God does not call everyone to His grace, He does not invite everyone."
And when our people asked,
So does He not call everyone?"
you responded,
He does not call everyone."
Our people, stunned and anxious, hearing something no heretic had ever said, asked your expertise:
How do you prove that God does not call everyone to His grace?
Does God Himself not want to call them? Or does He want to and cannot? Or do they not deserve it?
If He wants to and cannot, He is blasphemed as powerless; if He can and does not want to, He seems unjust; if they do not deserve it, then grace is no longer grace, and the call is a matter of human merit, not God's grace.
But if it is God's grace and not human merit, He calls everyone.
For all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God, as the Apostle says in the Book of Romans, chapter 3, verse 23; and he added: "They are justified freely by His grace through the redemption that is in Christ" (Romans 3:24).
Behold, freely, behold redemption.
I boldly say: Where there is presumption of human merit, there is no grace of divinity; for we cannot apply everything we believe to be God's grace to our merits.
Therefore, if it is grace and not merit, how do you say that some are not called because they are unworthy of His calling?
For if no one is called by their own merit, but by the gift of God's grace, and one is called and another rejected, God is blasphemed as a respecter of persons.
The apostles are also argued to be false witnesses of His judgment.
For the blessed Apostle Peter declares: "In truth, I perceive that God shows no partiality" (Acts, chapter 10, verse 34).
Blessed Paul says, "For there is no partiality with God" (Romans 2:11).
And again, the Lord speaks of servants: "Do the same for them, giving up threatening, knowing that both their Master and yours is in heaven, and there is no partiality with Him" (Ephesians 6:9).
If this is true, or rather because it is true, how can you claim that He does not call everyone to His grace?
Who does He not wish to save, who prays even for those who crucify Him?
In this heresy, the devil rages with the fury of his tyranny, aiming to wound nearly the entire world with a deadly plague.
The creature wages war against the Creator, claiming that He has predestined what He punishes and has ordained what He has forbidden.
How impious and sacrilegious this is, even the most unskilled person can recognize.
For any sin is rightly called sin when both the guilt of the offender and the justice of the judge are evident; because the punishment for sin always follows the merit of the deed:
But no one is made guilty except the one who could have avoided the sin.
So, distinguish between the one predestining and the one committing the sin, so that the former condemns or corrects the latter's evil deed as something alien to Himself.
All things that God condemns are foreign to a just God.
Hence, if predestination is shown in the sinner, the sinner owes nothing to the just judge; because if predestination is asserted, the action is also approved.
Do you see, I beg you, how gravely God is blasphemed by these assertions?
For if the force of His predestination is brought to the point where sin is said to be by His preordination, a bad fruit can only grow from an impious root.
According to the Manicheans, there would be one God for evil and another for good: so that good things are attributed to the good God, and evil things to the evil God.
Let us not seem to be shouting blasphemy worse than the Manicheans, when we consider the same God whom we confess to be good and just to have predestined all crimes.
Therefore, let the empty arguments of words depart.
There is nothing in common between the wrongdoing of the sinner and the predestination of the avenger.
Sin lies in the transgressor's contempt, while vengeance is rooted in the judge's fairness.
So, consider one of two options: either prove the predestination of the judge to be just, or show that there will be another judge.
For no judge can reasonably punish his own established order.
If you attribute evil to God's predestination, you cannot attribute it to the will of man.
Either blame man's guilt and absolve yourself from blasphemy against God, or if you claim that predestination is set by God for the sinner, you remove the sinner's guilt but accuse God of wrongdoing.
Certainly, sin is nothing other than man's transgression, and predestination is nothing but God's order.
How then could such different and opposing things come together in one framework, where what is good from God becomes the evil of man, and the vice of the sinner is called the predestination of the one forbidding it?
But why do you not consider this, you who think that people consent to sins by God's predestination?
Every sin is certainly willed and desired by the devil.
Do you believe that God set his predestination according to the devil's desire for the destruction of man, wanting his predestination to serve the devil's will, so that humans, before they even had their own merit, would already be condemned to the enemy's will?
Let it suffice to have exposed the blasphemies of this place so far.
For with a trembling heart, I am overcome by unbearable fear.
We have written about eighty-nine heresies in the first book; we have seen none that so loosen the reins for people to commit crimes, none that so assert blasphemies against God.
I confess, Catholic confessors, their blasphemies are growing in this defense.
Therefore, I ask for the purity of your faith, that you help me with your prayers as I struggle against those whose every word is blasphemy.
I admit, my dearest friends, all the parts of my body are numb.
My spirit is failing, my hearing is trembling, my face is drained of color, and the hair on my head stands on end.
My mind is shaken with fear, and its plans are distressed.
My tongue itself cannot move in its place because we are speaking against those who say that God serves the will of the devil.
Now indeed, they say, God has predestined people, whether to righteousness or to sin; therefore, they cannot be anything other than what He created them to be.
When you ask them why they utter such blasphemy, they say because the Apostle said: "Those whom He predestined, He also called" (Romans 8:30).
And so they argue, those whom God has once predestined to life, even if they are negligent, even if they sin, even if they are unwilling, will be brought to life against their will.
But those whom He has predestined to death, even if they strive and hurry, labor in vain.
Who does not see that this statement removes the concern from the righteous of fearing they might fall and cuts off the hope from sinners that they might rise?
We have escaped the blasphemies against God; we come to the ruin of humans.
For if it is so, that each one is what he is predestined to be, the law ceases, the priest ceases, the devotion of the people ceases, the refuge hall is closed, the embrace of the Church is emptied, no one bends the knee to God, and no one bows their head for blessings.
The heights of God are closed, and all efforts of virtues vanish together.
For no matter how much, they say, anyone strives, and does not leave the Church of God, and the priests of God, and divine studies, if God has once predestined him to death, he cannot be saved.
Judas heard the word of life every day, adhered to the Lord every day, was occupied with virtues every day, and heard the Son of God as his guide every day.
And because he was predestined to death, he perished suddenly with one blow.
Saul was a persecutor every day, a stoner of Christians every day, a ravager of churches every day.
And because he was predestined to life, he suddenly became a chosen vessel with one blow.
What, then, they ask, you who remain in sin, are you afraid?
If God deems you worthy, you will be holy.
And why, you who live in holiness, are you anxious?
If God does not want it, you will never fall.
Both of you, be secure in God.
Are you who are holy and worried about falling, attending prayers day and night, occupied with fasting, and diligently engaging in divine readings, devoting yourself to exhortations and all holy studies daily, will you be saved by your own will?
Will you be holier than Judas, who received the power to heal the sick, cast out demons, raise the dead, tread on serpents and scorpions, a fellow apostle, a disciple of Christ?
And yet, because he was predestined to death, he found eternal death.
Stop being anxious, and be secure in God's will; for if God deems you worthy to remain, you will be holy.
But you who are a sinner, learn from the Apostle Paul.
Will you ever be able to commit worse things than he did?
And yet, because he was predestined to apostleship, he suddenly escaped all sins and ascended from the lowest of the low to the highest of the high.
This is the whole sum of your counsel.
From here you deceive the world, from here you enter homes and captivate little women weighed down by sins, led by various desires, always learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of God.
Second Timothy, chapter 3, verses 6 and 7.
Therefore, with the Lord's help, the spirit that shattered the plans of the false elders against Susanna will now divide you who handle falsehoods against the immaculate Church of God.
And just as they were found full of deceit by their own accusation, so you will leave defeated by your own opposition.
Therefore, we say the same words at the beginning that you yourselves said, but we gather the end of those same words differently.
We say that Judas was indeed an apostle and did not stray from Christ's path.
He received guidance for salvation directly from Christ, performed powerful signs, and obtained all the distinctions of apostleship.
Yet, because he was negligent, he fell.
Be vigilant so you do not fall; be diligent, because your adversary, like a roaring lion, prowls around looking for someone to devour.
First Peter, chapter five, verse eight.
However, do not think that Judas's fall was due to God's impiety; God did not want him to be evil.
But because he was a thief and had the money bag, John, chapter twelve, verse six, and because greed, the root of all evil, was in his heart, First Timothy, chapter six, verse ten, he fell miserably and burst open in the middle, Acts, chapter one, verse eighteen.
He neglected such divine gifts and, with the healer present, not only did he fail to heal his wounds, but he also tried to make them worse.
In Judas's sin, we ask you to judge yourselves.
We conclude, with Christ's help, that you must surpass yourselves by your own judgment.
In Judas's sin, there is a great sacrilege, an incomparable crime, an immense offense.
Tell us, to whom do you want to attribute this crime?
To Judas the betrayer himself, or to God the predestinator?
If you prove that this sin, worse than any other, is the sin of God the predestinator, I admit you have won; but if it is the sin of Judas the betrayer himself, our defense has triumphed: for God neither predestined him to be so, nor wanted him to be so.
Let us therefore defend the holy and blameless Lord from any crime; lest we accuse Him, whom Judas betrayed out of greed, of injustice; and by removing Judas's crime, call the Lord into guilt.
For if Judas was such because God predestined him to be so, not because he himself was negligent, we indeed free him from all weight of crime, and removing ourselves from the reproach of the betrayer, we accuse the cunning of the predestinating God, who supposedly wanted to make him an apostle, only to turn him into a betrayer; who supposedly wanted to elevate him to the heavens, only to throw him down from on high; who supposedly wanted him to cast out demons, only to hand him over to the power of demons.
Why do we delay?
Before your eyes, you have both, oh scholars of our time: the servant and the Lord, the Master and the disciple, the good God and the evil man.
Accuse either one you wish.
If you accuse God of predestination, Judas is innocent; if you accuse Judas of betrayal, you cannot teach that God predestined his crime, because God's predestination is good, but Judas's betrayal is evil.
Therefore, the good one did a good deed, because it is believed that he never did evil.
And if God's predestination is good, and Judas's betrayal is very bad, the evil deed of Judas and the good deed of God could not agree.
For it is impossible for darkness and light, good and evil, life and death, truth and lies, to have fellowship together.
Therefore, giving Judas alone his entire sin, and showing to God the purest honor of his justice, also give us the kiss of charity.
For you are struggling in vain, who excuse and defend all sinners through Judas, but accuse God's justice.
Now let us come to the good and truly blessed teacher Paul, and, removing the madness of evasion, let us explain what cannot be denied as true and complete.
It is one thing to persecute an innocent person out of malicious zeal, as Cain did; it is another to persecute out of zeal for God, as Elijah did.
Not only did he persecute, but he also commanded many people to be killed by the sword in his presence.
Cain killed one person and is punished with eternal damnation; Elijah killed many and is taken up to eternal glory.
Therefore, as you think, Paul did not imitate Cain, but, driven by zeal for God, he followed Elijah.
Perhaps you might say: How do you prove this?
Read Galatians where he bears witness to himself, saying: "I was persecuting," he said, "the Church of God, and was trying to destroy it beyond many of my contemporaries in my nation; being, he said, exceedingly zealous for the traditions of my ancestors" (Galatians 1:13-14).
Is it not known to all Catholics that the God of the Hebrews is the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ?
Whom, then, was he defending?
The Father, without a doubt, because his priests had told him that this was not the Son of God whom they had crucified.
Believing in his own law and trusting the priests of the living God, he received letters from them to go to Damascus and bring back Christians in chains to the synagogues (Acts 9:2).
He was a very wise and discerning man, who thought he was acting out of zeal for God.
He undoubtedly believed he was persecuting God's enemies, running for the sake of God's faith and truth.
He had not learned that Jesus Christ was the Son of God and considered Him a deceiver and misleader of His people, as he had heard from his teachers and priests.
With the spirit of Elijah, not Cain, he fiercely pursued the new worshippers of God and unknowingly committed crimes, thinking they were virtues.
However, God, who examines the heart and observes faith, allowed him to find mercy because his ignorance was confirmed by his innocence.
How do we prove this?
He himself says to Timothy:
I was a persecutor and an arrogant man; but I received mercy because I acted in ignorance.
Do you see, therefore, that where there is ignorance, there is no malice?
For to the ignorant, the teachings of God's justice are given; but to the knowing and contemptuous, judgment is pronounced.
Thus, Paul, walking through the darkness of ignorance, thought he was persecuting the enemy of his Lord: he burned with persecution because he strove to please the Lord as a good servant.
He did not rest; he raged, being more zealous than anyone for the traditions of his ancestors.
Which ancestors' zeal was he carrying?
Without a doubt, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob; and who is their God?
Without a doubt, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.
Therefore, striving to please Him, he thought he was pursuing His enemy, suffering the darkness of his own priests, to whom he gave his faith in obedience to the divine law.
It is well known what darkness brings.
Can experience not teach us that the nature of darkness is such that it presents the known and the unknown, the parent and the stranger, the citizen and the barbarian, in the same way before our eyes?
Unless he speaks, it is impossible to know who he is.
Like a good guardian of the vineyard of the Lord of hosts, the house of Israel, he walked through the night of ignorance with staff in hand.
Whenever he found someone gathering the Lord's harvest, he would destroy them with the spirit of Elijah.
To the good servant watching over his Lord's vineyard, zealously pursuing the faith, imitating Elijah, and fighting for the truth in the darkness of ignorance: to the one who knew he was called to fight for the truth even unto death, the Lord came saying: Rest, I am your Lord.
Now, judge for yourself.
If you enter your vineyard at night, and your servant, in the dark of night, senses you and begins to seize you, tell me: would you remain silent and allow yourself to be held by him, knowing he is not persecuting you out of malice, but defending you, while he mistakenly thinks you are a thief and is pursuing you for your own sake?
Such a servant deserves both praise and reward.
When you finally tell him who is pursuing you to stop, saying: I am your lord, he will immediately drop his staff, throw himself at your feet, and beg for forgiveness for his ignorance.
At that moment, he will do whatever you command.
So then, the blessed Paul, sent by the priests of God and already full of apostolic merits, was a chosen vessel.
With the spirit of Elijah within him, he persecuted those he thought were enemies of God's law, believing them to be thieves in his Lord's vineyard, when in reality, they were his own God.
He endured the night of disbelief caused by the priests.
The just Lord, pleased with Paul's righteousness even in his persecution, had given the law which Paul observed.
Therefore, it is not as though He, who accepts no one's person, took an unwilling person and made him willing, took a faithless person and made him faithful, took an enemy and made him a friend, or took a bad person and made him good.
Rather, He speaks to His own faithful servant who is working for Him and says:
"Why do you persecute me?"
Acts 9:4.
But he says the very words usually said in the darkness:
"Who are you, Lord?"
And the Lord replies:
"I am Jesus of Nazareth, whom you are persecuting."
Acts 9:5.
Immediately he believes, and immediately he transfers himself from the Synagogue to the Church, not by changing his Lord, but by recognizing that He is the same one whom he has always worshiped. He does not come from one God to another God, but by proving that He is the same God whom he has always worshiped. He does not come from faithlessness to faith, but by holding onto the same faith which he rightfully had.
Therefore, the righteous Lord recognized His servant, just as the Apostle himself says to Timothy:
"The Lord knows those who are His"
Second Timothy 2:19.
But to those whom He sees claiming to be His servants out of a desire for vain glory and some greed, He shouts to them, saying:
"Depart from me, for I never knew you"
Matthew 7:23.
But why do we stand in this place, when you not only hurl these insults at the Apostle, saying that he was dragged unwillingly, when you read that he says of himself:
"If I do this unwillingly, I am entrusted with a stewardship; but if I do this willingly, I have a reward"
First Corinthians 9:17.
Exclude him from his reward and say:
"Because you do this unwillingly, being unwillingly held and dragged, you do not run; for if you do not progress in your course, be secure now. Know that, even if you want to sin, you cannot."
To this, he himself responds to you:
"I run thus, not with uncertainty"
First Corinthians 9:26;
"I hasten every day, and I extend myself toward the prize of the heavenly calling"
Philippians 3:14.
And although I am aware of nothing against myself, yet I am not justified by this
First Corinthians 4:4.
Do not be deceived: God is not mocked
Galatians 6:7.
For unless I persist in many fasts, and mortify my flesh, and subject it to servitude, I myself will become a castaway
First Corinthians 9:27.
Oh good teacher!
O wise architect and instructor of all good things!
He who wants to offer the example of salvation builds the Church in this way.
He does not discourage those striving on the good path, so that they think they can reach God by removing the desire to please God from their souls and say:
We will not please Him by our effort, so why strive?
We will not please Him by our running, so why run?
We will not please Him by our will, so why desire?
We will not please Him by our vigilance, so why stay awake?
We will not please Him by our prayer, so why pray?
If we are predestined to life, we will not be damned.
Excluding this, the apostle Peter shouts: Be alert, because your adversary, like a roaring lion, prowls around looking for someone to devour (First Peter 5:8).
And the apostle Paul: Do not participate in the unfruitful works of darkness, but rather expose them (Ephesians 5:11).
He says, Do not participate.
Do you see how carefully he guides our consent?
He knows that through our consent each person is either deceived or saved.
I mean the consent by which we agree with the doctor who, wanting to heal us freely, calls out to us daily: Come to me, all you who labor and are burdened, and I will give you rest (Matthew 11:28).
Therefore, you hear the call, so present yourself as responding.
He who shouts for everyone to come to him did not ignore your doctrine.
For he would not say: Come to me, all; but he would say: Let those who are predestined to salvation come to me to be saved, and let those who are predestined to death depart from me to be punished.
But it is not so, as you teach.
For if a man withdraws his consent from the call of God, he perishes.
This doctor of ours indeed heals freely, but he commands observance.
Whoever has not been saved, either despised the caller, refused the invitation, or neglected the commands to abstain from certain things.
This is what we say about the perfect doctor.
What do you say?
Say what you will: if you praise the doctor and blame the sick person, you show the diligence of the doctor and the negligence of the sick person.
You're not saying this directly, but rather implying it through your writings.
God has predestined those He knows are worthy of salvation; He saves only those He has chosen.
God's salvation does not cater to the will of man, for He knows exactly whom to save.
Free will does not come before God's grace; rather, God's grace comes before free will.
These are your words, a mix of truths and falsehoods.
We will address each point.
If He calls those He knows are worthy, then He must have predestined everyone for salvation because He continually calls everyone.
If He only saves those He has predestined, then everyone must be predestined because He is the Savior of all.
If God's salvation isn't subject to human will but rather God's grace, show us someone who received baptism unwillingly and then desired it through grace; or someone who performed penance unwillingly, but later repented after being forgiven.
These acts, the sacrifice and confession, are vital to human salvation, and we perform them voluntarily.
The sacrifice, through which we are redeemed by Christ's blood and cleansed by water from His side, and confession, by which we acknowledge our sins and receive forgiveness.
Therefore, these two things-sacrifice and confession-are crucial for salvation and are done voluntarily.
Let's see if they are demanded from an unwilling person or requested from a willing one.
If from an unwilling person, you win; if from a willing person, truth prevails through our Lord Jesus Christ.
We voluntarily sacrifice to God and confess His name because He is good.
Yet, some say: The will of man is futile and unproductive, and human choice is in vain.
When comparing this to divine grace, we maintain one key point: we do not place human will above divine grace.
All good things are attributed not to human pride, but to God's mercy.
However, we cannot agree with you when you say that the will of man is useless.
We believe the will of man is not useless; if it were, it would neither deserve reward nor punishment.
Don't misunderstand us by not paying attention.
Take your catechumens and penitents to the bishops of all the Churches.
If you see them unwilling to grant baptism or lay hands for penance, know that you are Catholics.
But if they require a thorough examination of true and complete will before granting baptism, or voluntary confession before laying hands for penance, then you must understand: does grace precede the will?
Indeed, God's grace is greater than human will, but in this context, the will comes before grace.
The former precedes in merit, the latter in order.
I know the confusion you often create among the uninformed, using deceitful cleverness in this argument.
They say the will comes before grace.
In two respects, we agree: the will comes before grace in the attainment of baptism and in the conversion of penance.
This ensures that people, not influenced by your advice, begin to seek excuses for their sins (Psalm 140:4).
As one might say: If God wills, forgiveness will come to me; if Christ wants me in His flock, it will happen.
To this, we respond: Unless you wholeheartedly believe, forgiveness and grace will not come to you, nor will you become part of the divine flock.
Similarly, to those still in sin, it is said: Do penance (Matthew).
The kingdom of God is near.
When they say, "If God deigns to forgive sins, it is in His power," we respond, "Unless you repent with all your heart, God's forgiveness will never reach you."
In these situations, we assert that human will precedes God's grace. We explain that this human will comes before God's grace because we wouldn't even have the will to repent unless the Only Begotten, coming down from heaven, had opened the workshop of His grace to everyone. He came and suffered for all people. Therefore, in this order, God's grace precedes human will.
We make this point to reject two extremes. For those of you who say, "Grace precedes will," you sound correct but miss the mark. You argue, "Grace precedes will, so a person neither begins to want good nor seeks to be drawn to it, but waits to be made good against their will." And when he is bad, he says, "God wills this, because His grace does not come to me."
In this matter, we respond to both you and the one who says this by stating, "Human will precedes God's grace." For the Lord did not say, "First you will receive, and then ask; first you will find, and then seek; first it will be opened to you, and then knock." But He said, "Ask and it will be given to you, seek and you will find, knock and it will be opened to you. For everyone who asks receives" (Matthew 7:7-8).
By saying "everyone," He established a general principle and excluded the specificity of His predestination. And by saying "who asks receives," He demonstrated human will prior to the gift of grace. And yet, human will comes before grace, and God's grace comes before will.
We did not go to the Holy One as sinners; instead, the Holy One came to us.
We did not ask Him to come; He came without being asked.
So that humanity might ascend to God, God descended to us.
He emptied Himself to fill us.
He humbled Himself to exalt us.
He became poor to make us rich.
The living bread hungered to feed us.
The eternal fountain thirsted so that the sweet and eternal waters might wash over our dryness.
He was held so that we might be freed.
He was bound so that we might be saved.
He was sold to redeem us.
He received a crown of thorns to remove the thorns and thistles of the first curse.
He was stripped to clothe us.
He was hung on the cross to free us from the torments of eternal death.
Condemning the wood of concupiscence from the wood of the cross, He spread out His immaculate hands for our uncontrollable ones.
For the taste of concupiscence, He took the food of gall, and brought the death of life for the life of death.
He conquered for us, not for Himself.
He has always been, is, and will be victorious.
Because we lost life and paradise in Adam, we gain through Christ both paradise, eternal life, adoption as children of God, and the eternal kingdom.
Here, we strongly denounce anyone who says that the will of man precedes the grace of God.
We affirm that since the passion, resurrection, and ascension into heaven, grace has spread throughout the world.
Those who do not seek these great gifts of God and wait for the Church to come to them, we call insane.
To these people, we say: The grace of God is available to all in the Church.
If anyone seeks it, they will find it.
If anyone knocks, it will be opened to them.
But to those unwilling or lukewarm, divine grace is not given.
As the apostle Philip said to the eunuch: If you believe with all your heart, you may be baptized (Acts 8:37).
Wanting is not excluded by grace; rather, it is incited by it, awakening the will that sleeps every day.
Grace is established, as it is written, in the midst of the earth it cries out: Come (Matthew 11:28).
This word of God anticipates the one who will come; it anticipates the one who will ask, seek, and knock.
If a person seeks and finds, it is thanks to God's grace.
God invited you to seek and made you find.
If you do not seek, you will not find; this is your free will.
You have so much free will that you can even choose to ignore your Lord who is calling you.
Therefore, whoever is saved, it is by God's grace, who made you want to do so.
He invites you daily through the prophets, through Himself, and through His apostles to desire.
If you want and listen, you will receive the eternal good things of that land.
Therefore, what you want, ask, and accomplish is by God, because in this part, grace anticipates the will.
For you would not know what to want unless He called you, both directly and through His people, and taught you to ask and how to ask.
So, what shall we say now about you who do not ask?
Did God not want you, or did you not want God?
Did God not want you to do good, or did you not want to do good?
Did God not want you to be just, or did you not want to be just?
Therefore I ask you, O most holy predestinator, to make one of two choices.
Either admit you are defeated, or be convicted of blaspheming God.
If you allow yourself to be defeated, say with us: Man did not want good, and therefore he is evil; because if he wants to ask, the grace of God will be given to him.
When you say this, you extend your hand to brotherhood and reconcile yourself to Divinity through reverence.
But if you say: Therefore he is evil, because God wanted it, not because man did not want it, you will be proven to have blasphemed God, whom you confirm to want evil.
It will be necessary for the Church to anathematize the one who blasphemes God.
Let's now address the false commentaries of your books.
He is mistaken who thinks that he can reach Christ by merely wanting to do good, since Christ himself says: "No one comes to me unless the Father who sent me draws him" (John 6:44).
Those of you who understand Christ better, tell me if Christ lied, and only then assert that we have set our opinion against Christ's rule.
For if Christ spoke the truth, we do not lie when we say that those predestined are drawn to life, because life itself is Christ.
It is not new that fools can be deceived by the sound of words.
So too the vain Arius, following the sound of words, says that the Father is greater than the Son.
And he says to us what you say: If you believe in the Son, listen to him.
For he says, "The Father is greater than I" (John 14:28).
Those who attend to the sound of words, like the heresy of the Arians, join in the vanity of the Predestinarians.
For who does not know that no one can come to the Son unless the Father draws him?
Yet, before the Lord reveals the hidden mystery of this passage through us, we uncover your understanding.
You say this testimony so that no one may attentively receive the admonitions of the priests, no one may hurry to the embrace of Mother Church and be nourished by the two testaments; all flee the house of God, and each occupies himself with whatever vice he wishes, waiting for the Father to reach down from heaven to draw him unwilling and resistant, and make him chosen and holy without his consent.
This is your assertion and your doctrine.
But we say that, although anyone may be holy, whether he is an apostle, a martyr, a prophet, or a just person, he does not have the strength on his own to ascend to Christ.
Only the Lord ascended to heaven by his own power due to his divinity, and sits at the right hand of the Father.
Therefore, although anyone may be holy, or a friend of God, he does not have the strength to ascend to heaven.
And because the Son says to the Father: "Father, I desire that they also, whom you have given me, may be with me where I am" (John 17:14), explaining the unity of the Deity, he says: "No one comes to me," that is, no one can come to me by his own strength.
It is not possible for human holiness to reach me, where I sit at the right hand of the Father, unless the Father draws them.
Therefore, in the person of one, the entire assembly of saints says to God:
You have held my right hand, guided me with your will, and taken me up in glory.
Psalm 73:24.
And it adds: For those who distance themselves from you will perish.
Psalm 73:27.
It does not say, those whom you distance from yourself; but those who distance themselves from you will perish, showing that it is not by God's rejection, but by the distancing of man, that destruction comes to man.
Now listen to what the book Predestined says.
And if the weight of the Gospel testimony burdens you, and you cannot give us an answer because of the weight of the statement, at least explain to us the Apostle's statement, who says:
It is not of him who wills, nor of him who runs, but of God who shows mercy.
Romans 9:16.
We have declared the Gospel testimony with true assertions, and we clearly demonstrate this statement of the blessed Paul with evident inspiration.
But first, we uncover your understanding, so that holy testimonies may not be wrongly used by you.
You want no one to desire good, no one to run towards good, but to say in their heart:
No matter how much I desire, no matter how much I run, nothing will benefit the one who desires, nothing will benefit the one who runs.
It is not of him who wills, nor of him who runs, but of God who shows mercy.
However, we assert that no one obtains the grace of God unless they run with faith: and when they have obtained it, they are warned by the Apostle not to be proud.
For they did not receive the grace of God according to their running and their will.
For their running and will, no matter how great, no matter how vast, have limits, but the grace of God has no limits.
And therefore, even when the righteous reach the crown, they are not allowed to be proud of their crown.
For the Holy Spirit says:
He crowns you not because of your merit, but because of his mercy and compassion.
Psalm 103:4.
And the Apostle says: What do you have that you did not receive?
And if you received it, why do you boast as if you did not receive it?
First Corinthians 4:7.
So, he directed his path and will towards receiving from the giver.
But the gift surpasses the merit of the one working because of the grace of the giver.
Our will is between us and God, just like a beggar is with a giver.
The one who gives alms wants to give to everyone, as indeed our giver of grace calls out daily: "Come to me, all of you." And again: "Ask and you will receive."
For example, a needy person ran and received from the giver, and having received riches, he started to be wealthy who had been needy and poor. What will he say now? "I became rich from my work because I wanted to, because I ran?" He does not say this, but he says: "I am certain that I have something not because of the merit of my will or my running, but because of the grace of the one who gave everything."
And with this said, he can truly say with the Apostle, because "it is not of the one who wills, nor of the one who runs, but of God who shows mercy" (Romans 9:16).
Here we have spoken about the one who wanted and ran, because the gifts of God are so great that they surpass both the running and the will of man.
For the running and effort of man, unless they are helped by the invisible supports of God, are in vain.
For even the Apostle, fighting the good fight, finishing the race, and keeping the faith, and now only awaiting the crown (Second Timothy 4:7), says: "By the grace of God, I am what I am" (First Corinthians 15:10).
And again he tells us: "By grace you have been saved" (Ephesians 2:5, 8).
He is greatly unfortunate who thinks he can obtain the gift of God by the merit of his own will.
Every good and perfect gift is from above, from the Father of lights (James 1:17).
We claim nothing for human power; we attribute all good things to the mercy of God.
So we say that all good things are gifts from God, such that we attribute all the evil we do to our own negligence.
For otherwise, we do not deserve pardon unless we truly show that we have sinned by our own fault, not by any prejudice of the Creator.
And as we have said about good, that all the good he has done is by the grace of God, so whatever evil he has done, he should consider it due to his own negligence.
Wherefore the Holy Spirit cries out:
If you are willing and listen to me, you will eat the good of the land;
but if you refuse and rebel, the sword will devour you.
For the mouth of the Lord has spoken" (Isaiah 1:19).
Through the occasion of good testimony but a bad interpreter, you say:
"Do not will, for it is not of the willing";
the Holy Spirit says:
"If you are willing."
You say:
"Do not run, for it is not of the running";
the Holy Spirit says:
"Run in such a way that you may obtain it" (First Corinthians 9:24).
The Lord Jesus Christ cries out:
"Run while you have the light, lest darkness overtake you" (John 12:35).
Therefore, rejecting your notion, we adhere to the Holy Spirit.
For it is better, as the apostle Peter says:
"We must obey God rather than men" (Acts 5:29).
But what are we doing?
Once again, your erroneous teachings grow, in which it is read:
"However much human will exerts its strength to build, it strives in vain;
or what does human frailty think its vigilance will benefit eternal desires, when the prophet cries out with evident documents, saying:
'Unless the Lord builds the house, those who build it labor in vain.
Unless the Lord guards the city, the watchman stays awake in vain' (Psalm 127:1)?
What is it that someone hopes to study for building against divine principles and against their own conscience, when these sacred words teach that human building is not certain, but vain?
First of all, I ask, what building do you mean?
If you are talking about bricks and mortar, discuss that with the Egyptians.
But we here understand the building of the Word of God.
The Word of God is presented throughout the whole world by God's priests for the building of God's churches.
Is the speech of the priest therefore useless?
The doctrine empty?
The effort vain?
And if the building of this work is in vain, why is it commanded by the Apostle?
For the apostle Paul says:
"Encourage one another and build each other up, just as in fact you are doing" (First Thessalonians 5:11).
And again:
"As a wise builder, I laid a foundation" (First Corinthians 3:10).
If anyone builds on this foundation with gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay, or straw, the quality of each person's work will be tested by fire.
First Corinthians 3:10-12.
And the Lord in the Gospel praises the wise man because he builds his house on the rock, which is not brought down by the winds or the floods.
Matthew 7:24.
So, do priests build the Church in vain?
Do they watch in vain to protect the simplicity of the sheep from the bites of wolves?
And how do they guard the flock of Christ by condemning all heretics with eternal anathema?
Everywhere, the sheep of the Catholics are nourished, and in the flourishing pastures of pure faith, the mountains leap like rams and the hills like lambs of sheep.
Psalm 113:4.
Everywhere from the rising of the sun to its setting, there is one flock and one shepherd, by whom the wolves are killed so they do not harm the flock of God.
And do you still not see that the building of good will is not in vain but certain?
Every day, the house of God is built through good words, holy examples, and excellent efforts.
Every day, the Lord cries through the prophet: Build houses for yourselves, not those of mud that are moved by the wind, but those that remain solid like a rock.
Jeremiah 29:5.
But to you, all these things we have said seem empty and vain.
Your books say: The building of man is not certain, but vain.
From the beginning, all the saints have contributed to building up the minds.
For example, Abel first built justice, Noah innocence, Abraham faith, Isaac sacrifice, Jacob ambition for holy things, Joseph chastity, Moses priesthood, Joshua son of Nun steadfastness of spirit, David defense of God's people, Solomon wisdom, John repentance.
We mentioned these few among many, so that through these, the reader might recall the others we have not mentioned and inquire whether they were humans.
If they were humans, how do their books say: The building of man is not certain, but vain?
Therefore, we now conclude with the Catholic assertions against the words of the heretics.
Either they were not humans because their building remains, or they were humans, and the assertion of these others has vanished.
But if you come against us, they say, it is not against us that you come, but against Him who said: "Unless the Lord builds the house, those who build it labor in vain. And: Unless the Lord guards the city, the watchmen stay awake in vain" (Psalm 127:1).
So, did he not know that it was not useful for the people of God who had this written and directed to future generations until the end of the world?
Therefore, you who criticize these things, remove them from the book of Psalms, because, as you say, those who read and sing these verses cannot be edified.
We praise, approve, confess, confirm, and sing the words of the prophet, and we explain them according to the Catholic rule.
From the beginning, as we said, from righteous Abel to Zechariah and John, all built the house, not with stones, but with holy examples.
However, unless the Lord Jesus Christ had come and built this house in which they labored, those who built it would have labored in vain.
For they watched over the flock diligently, but unless the Lord Jesus Christ had provided His guardianship, those who kept watch would have labored in vain.
Hence, it also follows: "It is in vain that you rise before the light" (Psalm 127:2).
For Christ is declared to be the light by the prophets, the evangelists, and the apostles.
All the prophets, therefore, rose before the light, that is, before the birth of Christ.
It was in vain for them to rise before the light; for they could not show the truth to those enduring the night.
But the light came and revealed the hidden things of darkness, and only then did praise begin to be for each one from God.
Therefore, if He had not come and built the house, those who built it would have labored in vain.
Now, because He has come and built the house, those who build it no longer labor in vain.
And because He came to guard the city, those who keep watch no longer watch in vain.
And because the light has come and shines in the darkness, we no longer rise before the light in vain.
And because the bread of joy has descended from heaven, we no longer eat the bread of sorrow.
Hence, the verse follows in the psalm.
"You," he said, "wake up early for no reason, you who eat the bread of sorrow. But we, who eat the bread of salvation, should build our house on the rock and stay watchful, waiting for the Lord, because we do not know the day or the hour"
(Matthew 25:13).
Blessed is that servant whom the Lord, when He comes
(Luke 12:37), will find watching.
If it seems right, let us proceed to the rest.
But what do these people think?
Do they believe they can achieve edification by their own will, when even the chosen vessel himself asserts that he could not fulfill his own will?
For the Apostle says about himself: "For I do not do the good I want to do, but the evil I do not want to do, this I keep on doing"
(Romans 7:19).
If the Apostle cannot achieve the good he wants to do, how can these people say they can reach the fruit of grace by their own will?
He who wants his sin to endure never hastens to repentance.
Grant pardon, teacher of the nations, we beseech you, and do not allow us to partake in your injuries.
So let us see what the Apostle wanted to do but could not, and what he was compelled to do that he did not want.
He wanted to speak the truth and did not want to lie at all; therefore, he lied.
He wanted chastity and abhorred impurity; therefore, he was defiled.
He wanted contempt for the world and detested all worldly glory; therefore, he was vain and desirous of empty glory.
Finally, he wanted all that is good and utterly loathed all that is evil; therefore, he did not perform any good that he wanted to do but committed all that is most wicked.
For you say: The Apostle says about himself: "For I do not do the good I want to do, but the evil I do not want to do, this I keep on doing"
(Romans 7:19).
Do you see, I implore you, into what pit of blasphemies your blind sense has thrown you headlong?
You want to show that the Apostle was involved in crimes so that no one laments being a sinner, no one sighs deeply for their sins, and no one strives to wash away with tears what they have stained with their desires when they hear that the chosen vessel, the teacher of all the Churches, did not do the good he wanted to do, but the evil he did not want to do.
You have opened the gates, not of justice, but of iniquity to all people.
From the words of the Apostle, you have taken up arms against the Apostle, wanting to be teachers, even though you have never shown yourselves to be disciples.
Attending to the sound of the letter, you have suddenly begun to be your own teachers.
What do we do now, who cannot endure your blasphemies?
If we remain silent, you seem to have spoken rightly, and not only spoken but also written.
We speak, with the Lord's help, fleeing the glory of men, teaching the ignorant, instructing the eager, delighting the knowledgeable, and exposing you.
The scripture of your book is such that, what is worse, it does not die with you who are dying, and it creeps like a cancer to overturn the unsuspecting.
Let us see what follows in the book written from your vanity.
These are the words of the Apostle; we add nothing of our own.
He says about himself: "For I do not do the good I want to do, but the evil I do not want to do, this I keep on doing" (Romans 7:19).
Arius placed an epigram of this sort in the third book of his, saying:
We have received the words of the Son of God, and we believe them to be true, we also confess them to be true.
He says: "The Father is greater than I" (John 14:28), and: "I and the Father are one" (John 10:30), because "I am in the Father, and the Father is in me" (John 14:11).
He did not want to read; for he could have joined these two, that is, "The Father is greater than I" and "I and the Father are one"; and by joining these two, he would have found the Son of Man and the Son of God. For all kinds of suffering, removed from the Deity, could only apply to the Son of Man. For God is neither lesser nor greater, but He is always the same, lacking neither increase nor decrease.
Never grows by adding, never lessens by subtracting; it remains the same before and after all things, and in everything past, present, and future, it stays unchanged.
Consider these words as if said in another work.
We have mentioned that the accursed Arius spoke this in the chapter of his third book, following the order of the Predestined:
The words are the Apostle's; we have added nothing of our own.
He himself says:
Not what I want to do, this good I do, but what I hate, this evil I do.
Romans 7:15.
Now we seek your wisdom.
We read that the Apostle said:
I live, but not I, Christ lives in me; and the life I live now in the flesh, I live by faith in God.
Galatians 2:20.
What do you say now?
Was this man carnal or spiritual?
If you say carnal, you will be refuted, for he exclaims:
I live, but not I, Christ lives in me.
If you agree that he was spiritual, you will explain this passage with us.
You will find the head of this passage in the speech which begins:
We know that the law is spiritual, but I am carnal.
Romans 7:14.
If you are carnal, blessed Apostle, how do you rebuke the carnal, saying:
And I, brothers, could not speak to you as spiritual, but as carnal.
First Corinthians 3:1.
And again:
When there is jealousy and strife among you, are you not carnal?
First Corinthians 3:3.
And again:
As many of us as are spiritual, we think this way.
But we are taught by your writings, man of God, that not only were you spiritual, and rightly said that your conversation was in heaven while placed on earth; but we are also taught that your disciples were spiritual.
For you say to them:
If anyone is caught in any wrongdoing, you who are spiritual should restore such a one in a spirit of gentleness.
Galatians 6:1.
What then do you now say to us:
We know that the law is spiritual, but I am carnal.
Romans 7:14?
To this, he himself will deign to give us an answer:
I became as one carnal to those who were carnal, so that I might gain those who were carnal.
The truth has revealed itself to us, and falsehood has been excluded by the truth.
The spiritual teacher took on the role of a worldly person.
To avoid seeming offensive and pushing his listener away, he rebukes himself to correct another.
He even mentions this elsewhere, saying: "Or did I commit a sin by humbling myself so that you might be exalted?" Second Corinthians 11:7.
So what then?
He says, "I am worldly: who are you? I am the one who was sold under sin" Romans 7:14.
Apostle, were you sold under sin, you who, once redeemed by the blood of Christ, redeemed countless people for God through Christ?
It is clear, therefore, that the Apostle did not want to declare his own role here, but that of another, a worldly man.
He is the one sold under sin, who has not yet been redeemed by the blood of Christ, who is still worldly; and so it is said: "What I do, I do not understand" Romans 7:15.
For he does not understand that his actions are against his salvation; although he is a Gentile, he wants good things to come to him, to achieve good, to possess good, to acquire the good of his salvation, the good of his life: but he does not do the good he wants, but the evil he hates, he does.
He hates death but performs the deeds of death; he hates danger, but his actions are full of danger; he hates all evil, but does what he hates.
Why?
Because, he says, "Good does not dwell in my flesh," that is, the true God does not dwell in me.
The desire is present in me; it is certain that I want the true God, but I do not find this good that I want Romans 7:18.
For all these things happen to me, a worldly man, a man sold under sin, a man who does not understand what I do, a man who does not do the good he wants but does the evil he does not want, a man in whose flesh good does not dwell; all these things happen to me, so I do not find the good to complete it.
However, I delight in the law of God according to my inner man Romans 7:22; that is, my inner man, in which my intellect resides, delights in the law of God, which says that one invisible God must be worshipped.
Although I am fleshly, I know that wood and stone cannot be gods.
But I see another law opposing my understanding, conflicting with the law of my mind, which proves that these cannot be gods.
However, this fleshly law conflicts with the law of my mind, taking me captive under the law of sin, which is not in my mind but in my body.
I am led by my body, even when my mind does not agree.
Wretched man that I am!
Paul does not say this about himself.
For he was not wretched, but blessed and holy.
Wretched man that I am!
Who will rescue me from this body of death?
The grace of God through our Lord Jesus Christ.
(Romans 7:24)
So the grace of holy baptism will come and make this fleshly man spiritual, and redeem him from sin.
He will no longer say, "I do not understand what I do," for he will not do what he hates but will do what he wants, which is good. He knows that now good dwells in his body, that is, the Holy Spirit, through whom he both wills and finds the power to act according to his good will. Now he is secure and delights in the law of God according to his inner self, because he does not see another law in his body. He has only the law of Christ in him, which does not conflict with the law of his mind and does not lead him captive under the law of sin but leads him free to eternal life.
And now he is not a wretched man but a happy man, because he has escaped all these evils and found all these good things. If you ask who granted this to me: The grace of God through our Lord Jesus Christ. To avoid any ambiguity in this explanation, lest it be thought that the Apostle said this about himself, he puts it in a reproachful way, saying: "Therefore, I myself serve the law of God with my mind, but with my flesh, the law of sin." (Romans 7:25)
So there is no condemnation for those who are in Christ Jesus, who walk not according to the flesh.
(Romans 8:1) This means, if I, who am an Apostle, am considered fleshly, will there be no condemnation for those who live according to the flesh?
And he added: "The law of the Spirit of life has set you free in Christ Jesus from the law of sin and death." (Romans 8:2)
Hence, in another place, it says: When you were slaves to sin, you were free from righteousness.
But now, having been freed from sin, you have become slaves of God.
(Romans 6:20).
However, God boasts in the servitude of all, because His servitude cannot be compared to any other.
For all other forms of servitude are known to be forced, but God's servitude, unless it is voluntary, cannot stand, according to what is written: The Father draws no one unwillingly.
Hence the prophet, filled with the Holy Spirit, cries out: I will confess to the Lord by my will.
(Psalm 27:7).
And again: I will freely sacrifice to you.
(Psalm 54:8).
But contrary to all these things, they present to us a book filled with blind ambiguities, repeating the same points and saying again:
Only the predestined are called; for the grace of God precedes the will of man; God is prior in man's goodness, but man is found last in all goodness.
Give the first place to God, so that you may eliminate human pride.
But if you wish to nourish pride in men, it appears you seek the ruin of the human race, teaching that in good works, God does not precede, but man's will, suggesting to God to do good, as if He would not do good unless they had told Him; when it is clear that God, without anyone suggesting or asking, grants all good things to men.
For the Apostle does not say: When we begged, and asked, and ran, and kept watch, but, When we were enemies, we were reconciled to God; not by our will, but by the death of His Son.
(Romans 5:10).
Where is man's will?
It is excluded.
Therefore, not everyone who wills is saved; because if everyone who willed were saved, no one could be excluded from salvation.
Thus, every man wants to be saved, but not every man is saved.
For he is saved whom God wills.
Certainly, I say, whom God wills; so that, with man's will excluded, He may fully manifest His complete grace.
Blessed are our ancestors, who knew not the use of such a crime.
Who would ever suspect that good things could be done against goodness and that the weapons of justice could be used against justice?
"Only those predestined are called," he says. And we say with you: Only those predestined are called. For He who commanded His disciples to call all nations, saying, "Go and baptize all the nations" Matthew 28:19, predestined everyone before His coming. Therefore, He predestined all nations to life because He called all nations to life. Whoever comes will credit divine mercy for both predestining and calling; but whoever does not come should blame their own neglect for both rejecting and refusing. For it is not divine predestination that results in human destruction, nor is it God's will when the devil's will is fulfilled. These wills are indeed hostile and contrary to each other, and one cannot be fulfilled without contempt for the other. If some are not called to life, in those who are not called, the devil's will is fulfilled. And I wonder with what face you enter the Church if you are not afraid to say that someone is subject to the devil's will; for it is shown that the devil's will is fulfilled in those who do not want all men to attain salvation. Just as it is believed that His will is fulfilled in those He wants to save, so in those He does not want, the devil's will is fulfilled. But the good God wants everyone to be good; and here you suffer from error because not all whom He wants to be good are good. You usually say: Those who are not good are bad because God repels them from Himself, so that those who sin appear to be sinning not by their own fault. If you suffer from this error because God's will is not fulfilled, why do you not rather pass judgment on the sinners, whereby God is praised for His patient mercy, and man is blamed for the impatience of his own will? You say: "So man defeats God." Man indeed defeats God if God wants him to be good, and he is not good. What do you observe here? Do you see God and man wrestling, so that you say such things? If you saw them wrestling, you would rightly assign victory to one party.
Now, since the Savior of humanity, acting like a doctor, offers advice not for his own benefit but for our salvation, he commands certain actions to grant us life and forbids others to prevent death.
If you listen, you will credit the Savior for your life; if you ignore him, you will blame your own laziness when you start to feel the torments of death.
But if you claim that a patient's death is due to the doctor's incompetence, we assert that the doctor is perfect in every way.
And if you say that death happens by his will, he himself says to you, quoting Ezekiel thirty-three eleven: "I do not desire the death of the sinner."
If you are worthy to ask him, and you say: "If you do not want this, show what you do want"; he will answer: "I want him to turn from his ways and live."
Hence, we also make a universal statement against your cunning arguments. If a man can sin against God's will, how much more can he end sin with God's will? If a man can desire what God does not want, how much more can he desire what God wants? If a man can perish against God's will, how much more can he be saved with God's will? If a man could fulfill the devil's will against God's will, how much more can he fulfill God's will with God's will? If a man could reject God's predestination, how much more can he fulfill God's predestination by his own conversion?
Therefore, God said: "This I do not want, that I do want"; meaning, "I do not want the death of the dying, I want him to turn from his ways and live." What he said he wants, he predestined, for he predestined nothing unwillingly; what he said he does not want, he abandoned.
If a man can desire and do what God does not want, how much more can he desire and do what God wants? This is about human destruction and salvation. God wants us to be saved, the devil wants us to perish. If human destruction, which the devil wants, can happen through our negligence, how much more can human liberation, which God wants, happen through the diligence of good and faithful will?
Seventeen. But your book says: "The grace of God precedes the will of man."
We say: Not only does God's grace come before, but it also follows the will of man.
Before we show how it precedes and follows, let's clarify what we mean.
You say: God's grace comes before man's will, so when someone hears such a worthy and true statement, they might not pay attention to what comes next.
Your explanation suggests that man's will should cease.
Before he even begins to want, God seems to arouse him to zeal.
He should wait for grace to come first, which drags the unwilling, compels the reluctant, and holds back the fleeing.
Man wallows in filth, becomes the dregs of sewers, is submerged in the whirlpools of crimes, and feels secure in his vice.
For if preceding grace comes, man will turn away from crime.
Man will not be ahead of God's grace, but God's grace will be ahead of man's will.
We have revealed this intention of yours.
Now, it is necessary to demonstrate with clear assertions what Catholics hold against this.
Remember that we agree: God's grace comes before man's will.
We have said: It both precedes and follows.
It precedes because the Son of God came to save the whole world from death, not waiting for us to ask, plead, or even want.
And as we have already said, for man to ascend to God, God descended to man.
He came to invite the hungry to a feast, the thirsty to a fountain, the wretched to strength, the poor to riches, the sad to joy, the sold to redemption, the slaves to freedom, and the captives to rest.
Here we teach that God's grace precedes man's will.
Now let us see how it follows what it preceded.
The grace that preceded shows what to ask for, whom to ask, and how to ask.
It shows what to seek, how to seek, and where to seek.
It shows what to knock on, where to knock, and how to knock.
It excludes no one from this inquiry.
Not only does it exclude no one, but it also universally invites everyone: For everyone who asks receives, and he who seeks finds, and to him who knocks it will be opened (Matthew 7:7).
And he said again:
If a son asks his father for bread, will he give him a stone?
Or if he asks for a fish, will he give him a serpent?
If you then, who are evil, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more will your Father who is in heaven give good things to those who ask him?
Matthew 7:9-11.
Indeed, to those who ask.
As I mentioned before, because the grace of God precedes the will of man, now let's say together that the will of man precedes the grace of God; not through pride, but by asking; not by exalting, but by seeking; not by struggling, but by knocking.
For unless someone wills from faith, no one receives the gift of divine grace through baptism; unless they will to believe from faith, they will not partake in mercy; unless they desire from faith, they cannot reach the gift of God.
For if a Gentile coming to Christ says: I do not want to be baptized, he cannot be baptized.
If a delinquent coming to repentance says: I do not want to be reconciled, he cannot be reconciled.
The priestly judgment examines both cases, and cannot grant grace unless it learns their complete will from their own mouth: or if he dared, you yourselves know.
Let us consider something greater.
If the force of illness takes away the ability to speak, the abundance of God's grace cannot be administered to the silent.
For unless the secret of the mind is declared by the tongue, it cannot attain grace.
For with the heart one believes unto righteousness, and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation Romans 10:10.
Therefore, as the Lord says: Everyone who asks receives Matthew 7:7, it seems that the will of the one asking must precede, so that the grace of the one giving may be granted to those asking.
And lest I seem to leave you wavering, you who attribute all good to grace, do not struggle with me: not only do I say that grace preceded when God, not disdaining to be joined to man, came to us who were not asking; but even to this day, the will of God precedes the will of man.
For He wishes us to be saved, and we do not wish it.
Woe to me and those like me, because every day, God's grace, invitation, will, compunction, promise of eternal joy, and fear of eternal punishment come before our own wills.
Every day, God's grace comes before our wills, full of countless supports, but our will does not follow all these gifts of God.
So what does your book say?
God's will precedes man's will.
And what do we say?
It both precedes and follows.
So why did we labor to speak, since you say it only precedes and deny that it follows?
But what you say, that it precedes, you say so that a man in sin may let his will rest and wait for grace to come to him first, lest he begin to put his own will before God's grace.
But we Catholics abhor this and say: Grace goes before the will of men by showing eternal life in which they may delight, showing the eternal fire in which they may be terrified, so that they may be called back from the pleasures of sins.
Grace, I say, comes before our wills every day, but our will, which is worse, does not follow.
This is why we weep praying, groan repenting, because we do not follow the one who goes before, we disdain the one inviting, and neither do we honor the father as sons nor fear the lord as servants.
Hence, he himself speaks to us through the prophet: "A son honors his father, and a servant fears his lord. If I am a Lord, where is my fear? If I am a father, where is my honor?" (Malachi 1:6).
We now ask, does the preceding grace require something from us, or not?
Without a doubt, it requires.
What does it require?
Certainly what you yourselves say, the will itself.
Therefore, grace precedes.
What is grace?
That what you ask for, you receive for free.
And so he did not say: "Buy and it will be given to you," but: "Ask and it will be given to you."
And so that the simplicity of the brothers may more clearly recognize this meaning, let us offer a comparison.
Wisdom was shown to Solomon: behold grace; now listen to what Solomon himself, to whom it was shown, says.
"I have fallen in love with her beauty," he said. "I sought to make her mine and ran after her, but the more I pursued, the more she moved away from me." Wisdom 8:2. Doesn't it seem like a beautiful girl enticing and provoking a lover in a race?
Why mention this now? Listen to the grace of God. Let's consider the daughter of a father. This daughter, know, O man, is shown to you by her father with clear signs, so you may see her and become a lover of her beauty. He shows you how great her riches are, how great her love is, how great her kindness is, and how great her faith is. She is beautiful, rich, faithful, wise, and the daughter of the highest king.
Her father has shown her to you, O man, so that, becoming her lover, you might ask for her in marriage, and from her, bear children to God. Just as he who said: "Even if you have ten thousand guardians in Christ, you do not have many fathers; for in Christ Jesus, I became your father through the gospel." First Corinthians 4:15. From this union, Paul gave us birth to God, certainly through the grace of Christ, whose lover he became, asserting that he found all sufferings sweet for the love of Christ.
Take, therefore, from the example of the flesh a comparison with the girl, so you may better reach the spiritual sense. The girl is shown to you by the father: behold, the grace of the father precedes your will. Now you begin to desire. The grace of him who shows her is indeed shown, so you may consider how much you ought to believe he loves you, because to make you his own, he showed you his daughter, beautiful, rich, wise, so you might take her in marriage.
Behold, the grace preceding the will, the grace stimulating the heart, the grace enticing the mind, the grace awakening the sleeper. What do you now order the father to do for someone who does not ask, seek, desire, or show the warmth of love? Will he take his daughter and join her to you, who are preoccupied with disgust or surrounded by other loves? He does not do this.
But unless you seek it like silver, and unless you search for it like treasure, and unless you want it with faith, and unless you run with faith, and unless you show your true affection, you will not truly perceive it.
It is enough for you that, though you are a beggar, and it is rich, it enriches you with its wealth; you are baseborn, it is the daughter of the highest empire, and it ennobles you with its nobility.
But listen carefully to what her father says to her lovers, anxiously:
Whoever loves, he says, father and mother more than me, is not worthy of me.
Matthew chapter ten, verse thirty-seven:
He did not say: Whoever is poor, or who is baseborn, or who is wretched; but whoever loves anything more than me, is not worthy of me.
Oh, grace that precedes the will, demanding only love!
Oh man, love and receive; but if you love, show it with deeds.
Everyone who loves, wants, desires, asks, watches, runs, hastens, strives through friends, through children, through family, through servants, through himself opportunely, inopportunely, with entreaties, promises, fixed agreement, and complete evidence of love.
And to open your eyes, you who think you can be united with divine grace unwillingly and reluctantly, what is it when the father gives it, through his household grace is expressed beforehand?
It is asked of him who receives it, how it comes, if he renounces all worldly loves, all the enemy's pomp;
who unless he expresses his will in words, does he receive the grace he asked for?
What then does the man want, what does he run for, what does he desire?
To obtain grace; and what does he promise?
I renounce all the devil's pomp and pleasures.
He shows that he does not want what he wanted, and begins to want what he did not want; and then he begins to take pleasure in the participation of grace, by which he is called both rich and the son of a king.
Behold, we show you the grace of God both preceding and following.
It precedes, because it calls, because it provokes, because it invites you to come; it follows, because when you come, and want, and ask, it grants.
Let us see now where your intention leads.
For the accursed book written from your vanity says: Eighteen.
We did not reconcile with God by asking or begging, but while we were still enemies, we were reconciled to God, not by our will, but by the death of His Son.
So, you command that people should not ask God to be reconciled to Him, but rather become His enemies, so that the words of the Apostle Paul may hold true.
You also say that people should not rely on their own efforts because reconciliation with God is not by our will, but by the death of His Son.
Therefore, according to you, those who were enemies of God must be reconciled and saved?
Those who crucified Christ must be saved, and those who said, "We do not want this man," must be freed? But those who were friends and willing to give their lives for His love will be cursed by the Most High?
You are proving yourselves to be blaspheming more sharply than all heretics, who, not wanting to follow the right path, have handed themselves over to winding errors. The Apostle does not invite our enmity towards God, but our love. He says: "But God demonstrates His own love toward us, in that while we were still sinners, Christ died for us. Much more then, having now been justified by His blood, we shall be saved from wrath through Him" (Romans 5:8-9).
Therefore, He demonstrates His love through this work within us, so that by offering our love to Him completely, we may seem to repay with the vow of love what we cannot do by our strength.
For God's love benefits us; if we love God, we cannot benefit Him.
God needs nothing, is exalted by no one honoring Him, and is diminished by no one despising Him.
So why does He demonstrate His love in us?
Certainly, so that we may say: If when we were enemies, He loved us so much that He allowed His only Son to be killed for our salvation, how much more now, having been reconciled, will He save us through His life?
Hence, excluding your special defense, He introduced general grace, saying: Considering this, that one died for all.
And he added: "Therefore, all have died because He died for all, so that those who live might no longer live for themselves, but for Him who died for all" Second Corinthians 5:14-15.
At this point, your perplexing book comes to mind and says:
"You say, whenever you read 'all,' you want it to be understood generally, even though 'all' often means a part. For instance, when it says: 'All have turned away' Psalm 14:3; not everyone had turned away. And: 'Every man is a liar' Psalm 116:11; not every man is a liar, because we read of someone: 'He was a truthful man.' So, a large part seems to signify all, although it is clear that not all are meant."
"We find no place in your book without blasphemies. What is this assertion paying attention to? It aims to make those who agree with you say that Christ did not suffer for all. If you do not want to understand it this way, then the Apostle did not name 'all' here for a part, but he mentioned 'all' generally."
"So correct your book, because Christ suffered for all. He hurries to help all people. He calls all, He invites all: whoever is saved will credit the grace of God who calls, invites, and helps; whoever is not saved will blame themselves for neglecting, despising, and abandoning. For all good things are given to us by the grace of the Lord when we ask; all bad things, however, are inflicted on us by the devil when we despise God."
"For the devil cannot exercise his power over those who live by divine protections. Can a captive subject the vessels of his conqueror? No one, says the Lord, can enter a strong man's house and plunder his goods unless he first binds the strong man, and then he will plunder his house" Matthew 12:29.
"You consider the enemy strong; but we believe he is bound and subject to the trophy of the cross. We show his deceit, but also his traps exposed. Can the defeated prevail to touch the one armed with the sign of victory? Can they invade with arrows the one shielded by the Lord, clothed with the armor of faith, and protected by the helmet of hope and salvation" Ephesians 6:16-17?
A person is not overcome by the devil unless they have strayed from their protector.
The Apostle says, "Submit yourselves therefore to God; resist the devil, and he will flee from you" (James 4:7).
The invisible enemy is defeated by the invisible protector.
But your misguided book contradicts this and dares to claim that the devil has the power to drag people against their will, even those whom Christ has redeemed with His blood and made children of God.
You say: With closed eyes, you overlook the snares of the enemy, insisting that human will has some power to acquire virtue.
You fail to consider how much harm God suffers daily, how many acts of chastity are ruined by the devil, and how many cravings for crimes there are.
If you saw these things, we wouldn't need to labor to show you the damages to virtues and the victories of vices.
Tell me, please, the damages that God suffers daily-do they occur because the devil wins, or because humans neglect Him?
If you say the devil wins, we reject your blasphemy; if you say humans neglect Him, our assertion stands strong.
The devil is neither a lord, nor a creator, nor a father.
However, God is our Lord, Creator, and Father.
He joined His victorious body to ours to overcome our frailty.
He mixed His blood with ours to calm the heat of our natural fervor with His divine blood.
He anointed us with the power of His chrism so we could defeat the devil fighting against us.
He promises to protect us with the shield of His goodwill: "Because he holds fast to me in love, I will deliver him; I will protect him, because he knows my name" (Psalm 91:14).
Hence, the prophet says of Him: "He who dwells in the shelter of the Most High" (Psalm 91:1), that neither the arrow that flies by day, nor the pestilence that stalks in darkness, nor the destruction, nor the demon at noonday can harm him, and so on.
Therefore, it is clear from these signs that the devil has power only when he finds us negligent, when he finds us sleeping in faith.
For everyone who calls on the name of the Lord will be saved. Romans 10:13.
But what good is it to show that humanity is freed from the devil by God's victory if people are still captured by their own faults?
We are faced with another point of opposition.
Their book says:
Through the transgression of the first man, freedom of choice was lost by mankind.
But we say: Through the transgression of the first man, freedom of choice was revealed, allowing man to want what God does not want.
If freedom of choice was lost, then how are we sinners?
We are not sinners for any other reason than because we want what God does not want and do not want what God wants.
We commit what He forbids and refuse to do what He commands.
How can we do such great evil if we do it unwillingly?
Someone else must be acting through us; therefore, the law should be given to them, not to us.
The law is not given to the sword so that it kills a man; instead, the law is given to the one who kills with the sword.
For the sword is the same whether it kills or does not kill; it neither earns praise by being still nor incurs blame by killing.
If we are being driven and not acting ourselves, then we are excluded from sins when we transgress and excluded from faith when we believe.
Thus, defeated, they turn to slander.
Their book says: You are reviving the Pelagian heresy by saying that through freedom of choice, humans can put an end to sins.
Matthew 7:7; John 16:24.
The Church did not condemn Pelagius for this reason.
It accused him of exaggerating freedom of choice so much that he rejected God's help.
But we say: Through freedom of choice, we commit every sin; but from every sin, we are freed by God's grace with the agreement of choice.
We have taught from this passage that God does not give His grace to those who do not ask for it, for He said: Ask and you shall receive.
It has been shown to us what to ask for without asking; it has been shown to us what to seek without seeking; it has been shown to us what to knock for without knocking.
If we don't ask, we won't receive; if we don't seek, we won't find; if we don't knock, it won't be opened for us.
For everyone who asks receives, and the one who seeks finds, and to the one who knocks, it will be opened.
This is from the book of Matthew, chapter 7, verse 8.
Therefore, free will is so strong in us that it can obey God; yet it is weakened in us so that it can even despise God, from whom this very freedom is given.
Indeed, this freedom was given so that only the devil would be despised through it.
For if free will had ceased because of the transgression of the first man, then the law would certainly have ceased, which can only speak to one who can both despise it and hear it.
But the law did not cease, whether it is natural law, through which Abel, Enoch, Noah, Shem and Japheth, Melchizedek, Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, Joseph, and others pleased God.
They pleased by the instinct of natural law.
On the other hand, those displeased, whether those whom the whirlpool of the flood swallowed or those whom the sulfurous flame consumed.
For neither would those have pleased, nor these displeased, if natural law had not existed, and if freedom of will had not been in them.
What then do we do?
We do not avoid criticism unless we say it is only by God's grace.
For their book shouts, saying: "You exclude grace through free will." Either we are freed by free will, or we are rescued by the grace of God. Choose what you will say. If you give everything to grace, we are one; if to free will, know that we cannot agree with you. Listen, you critics, and hear what you fear. We say free will exists where divine grace is present. For without the grace of God, there is no free will, but captive will. For where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is freedom. This is from the book of Second Corinthians, chapter 3, verse 17.
We do not hand over this freedom to human pride, but we define it by the grace of God and His glory: which grants so much that some do more good than is commanded, and others do more evil than is forbidden. For the hand that can rob the clothed, which God forbids, can also clothe the naked, which God commands. What do you say?
One hand clothes the naked and strips the clothed.
It's blamed when it undresses because it could have dressed.
It's praised when it dresses because it could have undressed.
Take away the free will of both acts, and it neither incurs blame from vice nor acquires praise from virtue.
To explain free will, the choice is in the soul, and freedom is in the body.
Freedom without choice does not sin, while choice without freedom does.
For example, if you lock up a thief, you take away his freedom to steal but not his choice; you bind his hands, not his mind.
If someone becomes blind after indulging in lustful looks, their freedom of sight is bound, but their choice remains intact; for desire is exercised by the decision of the soul.
Therefore, Christ calls someone who looks at a woman with lust an adulterer (Matthew 5:28); they have choice, even if they don't have freedom.
They are guilty through their choice without action; the perfect will is accounted as the deed by a just judge; someone is said to have done everything if they did what they could.
The body is prevented by the impossibility of the act because the soul's choice is not bound.
So, what does grace do?
It does not take away free will, but it heals, amplifies, adorns, instructs, and exalts.
However, it exalts not the unwilling, but the willing.
For unless you want it from faith and run from faith, you cannot be liberated by grace.
Let us therefore be certain that grace does not reject us when we sin, but we reject grace when we sin.
The judging authority considers one of two things: either rejecting grace or despising man.
If grace rejects, it frees the man from sin.
Is someone to be blamed for not dining with someone who has rejected him from their feast?
And is he not rather shown to be worthy of pity when others are invited and he is rejected?
It is extreme cruelty if someone is forbidden to dine with those who are dining; and why should he not dine, being ordered to be killed by the one who did not want him to dine together?
Eventually, your book, now seemingly worthless, appears to offer freedom of choice-but only when it concerns measures, not the essence.
Where, he asks, is there greater freedom of choice in good, and where is there less, except as judged by God's will?
In one person, grace appears sparingly, while in another, it's abundant and generous, as we desire.
I am not arguing with you here, because both Christ and Paul refute you.
Christ says: "He who loves more is forgiven more; he who loves less is forgiven less" (Luke 7:47).
Paul also says: "Whoever sows sparingly will also reap sparingly" (Second Corinthians 9:6).
Therefore, grace is not given by God through favoritism, but through the love in a person's heart, whether that love is great or small.
For who, loving God more, is loved less by God?
In fact, even someone not loving God is still loved by Him.
But how can God be loved?
The Lord himself teaches, saying: "He who hears my words and does them, he is the one who loves me" (John 14:21).
He also tells his disciples: "If you love me, keep my commandments" (John 14:15).
So, let's consider what freedom of choice does to fully receive God's grace.
It gives up its own freedom and becomes a servant of God.
The Apostle teaches this, saying: "Do you not know that when you present yourselves as obedient slaves, you are slaves of the one you obey, either of sin leading to death, or of obedience leading to righteousness" (Romans 6:16)?
Therefore, whoever submits to God's will, gives up their own freedom of choice, so they can be liberated by divine choice.
Does it not seem that someone who denies themselves bread when hungry, drink when thirsty, and sleep when drowsy, is giving up their own freedom of choice?
But in these sacrifices, one cannot be worthy unless they do so willingly.
The Apostle says: "Not reluctantly or under compulsion, for God loves a cheerful giver" (Second Corinthians 9:7).
The prophet also says to God: "I will sacrifice to you willingly" (Psalm 54:8).
And again: "My flesh has flourished," he says, "and I will praise Him of my own will."
Psalm twenty-seven:seven.
But we read about the unjust: "He refused to understand in order to do good."
Psalm thirty-six:four.
Hence, the blessed Jacob says: "Simeon and Levi, brothers, completed iniquity of their own will."
Genesis forty-nine:five to six.
So, if before our true and complete freedom came, the Lord Jesus Christ, the just one, voluntarily sacrificed to God and confessed of His own will, while the sinner sinned of his own will; how much more now, with our freedom restored through Christ, are all things given back to us by right, not by the dominance of nature as Pelagius and Coelestius defined it, but by the grace of Christ granting it?
Not claiming strength for ourselves, but relying on God's help; not taking anything for ourselves, but attributing everything to God's grace. Everything, I say, everything; I repeat, everything, but the good. The evil, however, we incur from our own fault, from our own negligence, and from our own will.
Why do you turn to accusations and throw Pelagius' teachings at us? We anathematize all who say that, without God's help, a person can be without sin if they want. We anathematize those who say neither death came through Adam nor life through Christ. We anathematize those who say of two baptized parents that their child cannot need baptism. We anathematize those who say infants should not be considered sanctified by baptism for the remission of sins. We anathematize everything condemned by the Church in all heretics. We anathematize your book with you, which says:
We acknowledge that human nature was so corrupted by Adam's transgression that it achieved its restoration through Christ not in reality but in hope, as the Apostle says: "For in hope we were saved; but hope that is seen is not hope."
Romans eight:twenty-four.
So, if we were saved in hope, we do not yet possess the reality in this present age. Therefore, even the baptized still desire carnally and suffer those bodily impulses, because they have received the help of restoration in hope, not in reality.
If they had achieved their goal, after receiving the grace of baptism, there would be neither the possibility nor the desire to sin.
However, because the power of baptism is so great that it wipes away all sins, the tendency to sin is not washed away by the waters of baptism; it remains naturally present due to Adam.
Those parts of the body that are free from shame at the moment of baptism later become subject to shame, avoiding sight and seeking privacy out of modesty.
The parts that God made were turned into sources of shame by transgression.
At the moment of baptism, these sources of shame become parts again, but soon they revert to being sources of shame.
They are renewed not in reality, but in hope.
The desire of the flesh, which opposes the body as the law of sin due to Adam's transgression, once again claims the baptized person and tries to completely overturn their mind.
This is the root of the wound that Christ healed.
As the Apostle says: "We were saved by hope." He commands us to turn our minds to contemplate the unseen things, not to fall because of the visible things.
Therefore, he says: "Hope that is seen is not hope," so it should not be thought that sins are so removed by baptism that the very roots of sins are also taken away. The movement of defilement that invaded nature through transgression remains in the baptized person, just like the root of hair remains when the surface is cleaned and shaved with a razor. It is shaved to clean the area, not uprooted so that it would not grow again.
If every weakness of Adam's transgression were completely removed by baptism, all the baptized would not be drawn to crimes by any heat of passion, no one would be defiled by human filth, and no one would be pricked by the sting of desire. But because we are saved by hope, what we do not yet see, we wait for with patience.
The time will come when neither women will marry nor men will take wives, but they will be like angels in heaven (Matthew 22:30).
When this perishable body puts on the imperishable, and this mortal body puts on immortality, then the saying that is written will come true: Death is swallowed up in victory.
Where, O death, is your victory?
Where, O death, is your sting?
The sting of death is sin, and the power of sin is the law.
Thanks be to God, who gives us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
This is your little book, which you do not give to anyone to read except under oath.
Be careful not to betray it; do not let the unskilled read it.
The kingdom of God is for the few.
This shows that God has predestined you for life if you guard this little book as you would your own soul.
Most women earn the right to receive this little book from you.
Finally, the one who betrayed it, a woman in body but a man in mind, when she received this little book from you under oath, shuddered as she read it and gave it to those she knew to be Catholics for examination.
We read it too, which you always feared.
With the Lord's help, clearly exposing its blasphemies, we warn all Catholics to avoid this little book, to curse it, and to condemn it with eternal anathema.
Its damnability is such that it nullifies all the mysteries of the Savior.
It says that Christ's baptism has no benefit at all when it is given.
Hope, it says, which is seen is not hope, that is, the forgiveness of sins: and whatever is promised in the present is not, because it is reserved for the future.
Yet, here in this world, it is not received.
For the Apostle says: Hope that is seen is not hope.
Did the Apostle say this according to your meaning?
Therefore, we will first explain the meaning of blessed Paul with due reverence, and then we will cut your book to pieces, especially where its conclusion seems to have found perfect completion against us.
The Apostle, bringing consolation to the children of God, says that they should seek nothing in this world.
Lest, perhaps, seeing the wicked and unbelievers rejoicing in their successes, but themselves afflicted, they would say, Look at these sinners, and those who prosper in the world have obtained riches.
But we, even up to this very moment, are hungry, and thirsty, and naked, and beaten.
First Corinthians 4:11.
Therefore, considering the present age, he promises future joys.
And although, he says, we are worn out by great sufferings, these sufferings of the present time are not worth comparing with the glory that will be revealed in us.
Romans 8:18.
And so, he says, we are saved by hope.
Romans 8:24.
Note that he says we are saved, not that we will be saved.
He made salvation a past event; when we believed, we were saved.
Why by hope?
Because we hope to rise again, for we have not yet risen.
So, because we hope to receive rewards for good deeds and possibly incur punishments in hell for evil deeds; hoping for good and fearing evil, we are saved.
We who were children of wrath have become children of God.
Ephesians 2:3.
Hence another Apostle cries out: Beloved, we are God's children now.
First John 3:2.
Therefore, the adoption of children is not promised in baptism, but it is conferred.
But you say about what we have already received: Hope that is seen is not hope.
For us, all hope seems to be established in the sanctification of baptism; therefore, what seems to us as hope is not hope.
We see the foundation of our hope in the anointing of Christ's chrism; therefore, hope that is seen is not hope.
We see our hope in the body of Christ; therefore, hope that is seen is not hope.
We look to the blood of Christ for our redemption; therefore, hope that is seen is not hope.
You have nullified all the sacraments, emptied the mysteries, and like trustworthy and capable surveyors of the Antichrist, you have prepared a place for him by expelling us from some places.
For what the Apostle says about the joys of this world: Hope that is seen is not hope, you have transferred to divine mysteries.
What he mentions about perishable and transient things, you have ascribed even to holy baptism.
May we have no part with you forever, nor let our minds be further tainted by these blasphemies.
Therefore, they say, those who are baptized are again defiled and carnally desire, because they have not received the help of renewal in reality, only in hope.
But we hope for future rewards in such a way that we do not deny what we have received in the present.
For we deserve to receive benefits, as long as we do not deny what we have already received.
If you deny what you have received, you are proven ungrateful.
Therefore, if you have not yet received grace but are going to receive it, why do you communicate secretly with us?
Wait for another body of Christ, another blood of Christ; for you say this one is in hope, not in reality.
For if we had received in reality, they say, after the grace of baptism there would be neither the possibility nor the will to sin.
Therefore, you wish to show that the grace of baptism has not bestowed reality, because after baptism we can still want evil and do evil.
To whom would the law of God be given, if the possibility of evil were taken away?
Who would ask for a reward for keeping God's commandments, if he could not transgress?
Just as neither a mute person is praised for silence, nor a eunuch for virginity.
For they lack praise in good, who are denied the transition to evil.
Therefore, we say that the possibility of evil is good for those who despise it.
I will give a brief response to each of these points.
Someone could strip the clothed: behold, he could do evil; but because he did not want to, the possibility of evil became good, as he despised it with wise counsel.
Someone could steal money entrusted to him, could commit adultery: behold, the possibility of evil; and he who despised it, this very possibility made him be praised for not stealing money, and crowned for maintaining chastity.
We have spoken of one point, that is, the possibility of evil, which is good for those who despise it.
Now let us see how, conversely, the possibility of good becomes bad for those who despise it.
Someone has deposited money: behold, the possibility of good, for he can help all those in need.
But if he despises this possibility of good, it becomes a bad possibility, and so bad that it is proven to be the root of all evils, as mentioned in First Timothy.
But what are we doing?
Our baptism is in danger, and we are discussing the poison of greed.
Everyone knows that the sin of greed is serious, but the grace of baptism being nullified by unfaithful people has only recently come to light for Catholics.
They say that through baptism, sin is removed like hair shaved by a razor.
It's shaved to clean the area, not uprooted so it never grows again.
If all the frailty of Adam's transgression were entirely removed, all baptized people would not be drawn to sin by any stirring of passion or pricked by any stimulus of desire.
Therefore, the holy mysteries of baptism are nullified because, as you say, desire is the law of sin, and it claims the baptized person again.
If you were excluded from this desire, there would be full remission of sins and true comfort of graces in baptism.
I used "graces" in the plural because, although grace is one, it becomes multiple like a vine that produces many branches. There are as many vines as there are branches growing from one vine. From the single source of baptism, remission of sins is given in the present, and the kingdom is promised in the future. A man becomes a son of God, a son by adoption, a co-heir of the kingdom. He becomes a citizen from a foreigner, free from being a servant of the enemy, wealthy from being poor, and illustrious and great from being ignoble. But your book nullifies all these things, and you say:
If what is promised in baptism were given, no one would be pricked by the stimulus of desire after the water of baptism. Let's see whether this desire, as you say, is the law of sin. We say that desire is a natural struggle, deeply rooted in humans by God the Creator for the propagation of mankind. Even the first humans had not yet tasted from the tree of transgression when God blessed them, saying: Be fruitful and multiply, and fill the earth (Genesis 1:28).
Therefore, He who commanded the human race to multiply by blessing it before sin, undoubtedly provided this nature with the means to propagate.
For the different sexes could not have multiplied at all if there were no natural sexual desire.
The Lord said, "It is not good for the man to be alone; I will make a helper suitable for him" (Genesis 2:18).
Do you think this helper of the opposite sex was made by the Lord for consolation or for procreation?
If sexual desire is bad, which is shown to be the material of generation, then according to you, it is clear that God did not make woman as a helper for good, but as an occasion for sin.
But if you say that the woman's help was given not for restoration but for some consolation, then the different sexes were created in vain by Him, of whom we read that He made everything in wisdom (Psalm 104:24).
However, if the authority of the Old Testament does not hold you, listen to what our Lord Jesus Christ Himself said about the first humans.
He who made them male and female blessed them and said, "For this reason, a man will leave his father and mother and be united to his wife, and the two will become one flesh" (Matthew 19:4-6).
And after saying this, He added: "Therefore, what God has joined together, let no one separate." We read that they were made by God, blessed by God, and joined by God.
And I wonder with what face you can say that this desire, through which marriages are celebrated, was inflicted upon the human race by the devil. For who would doubt that a bad thing, if it is bad, could not have been given to man by the good God? For if it was given by God, it is recognized as good; but if it is bad, it is clear that it was instilled by the devil. Your book says so:
"The parts that God made, they made shameful by transgressing." If this is not in the parts that God created, and the enemy appeared over God's creation and, against God's will, made His creature contain a different order than He instituted, then marriages are cursed, and the entire mass of the human race coming from this curse exists under the devil's influence. Choose one of the two.
Either the generation of humans is good, and desire is good; or marriages are bad, and desire is unjust.
So, correct the rule of the Church; condemn the priests worldwide who bless, consecrate, and join marriages in the mysteries of God.
I wonder with what face you enter the church, where you recognize that everything done is against your sects.
You deny that God gave this desire, from which we are born.
Therefore, we are not His creation if marital desire is not His creation.
Take away this, which you say is the law of sin, and let's see who can adhere to a wife.
But He who gave the power of the seed for blessing, He Himself, to multiply offspring, implanted love in desire and wanted what He established to be multiplied to be loved.
The increase of the species is natural desire.
If through this, as you say, everything is the cause of sin, then He created the crime in the species, who wanted posterity to be multiplied through love, and commanded that the wife be loved beyond the rights of paternal affection.
Finally, our Lord Jesus Himself, when He says: Matthew 19:6: "What God has joined together, let no man separate," it is as if He said: You are not allowed to hate your wife, whom you began to love with me as the author. For He was jealous that the union made by Him should be stained by marital hatred. What a strange perversion of things! While hatred of a wife is punished by God, marital desire is condemned by men. But the just judge does not condemn natural desire, who, to multiply offspring, therefore implanted love.
For when matters of marriage and divorce were discussed, the Lord then dictated this sentence, saying: "What God has joined together, let no man separate." He said this to show that the union of marriage is specifically from God. For there could not be union without coupling, nor coupling without union. If marital desire is not from the Creator's creature, but from sin, they say, then according to you, God joined in blessing what the devil inserted through transgression.
If that is the case, he was not an adversary but a helper of God.
If those whom God wished to be one in the flesh were made inseparable through desire, and what He commanded to increase and multiply, he found a way for it to be fulfilled.
How unfortunate it is for the Predestinarians to claim that a blessing from the Creator came from man's transgression!
You call this the law of sin, but we affirm it as the law of nature, which you accuse of being a crime.
We say this is the cause of virtues, which you want to show as the source of vices.
While it helps parents to be fruitful in offspring, it also provides for the chaste and the virgins to be glorious.
And lest you think it is detrimental anywhere, it provides greater rewards by opposing than by helping.
When it helps, it shows the fruit of nature; when it opposes, it awards the prize of chastity.
There, it works without fault; here, it fights with a reward.
Remove desire, and marriages cease; remove desire, and the rewards of chastity cease.
What kind of evil is this, I ask, that is shown to be the cause of a double good?
It brings some to the joy of generation, others to the triumph of virtue.
Some act upon it lawfully, others fight against it gloriously.
If this is said to be sin in everyone, then spouses, the chaste, and virgins alike are condemned by it; for it is known to be present in everyone by nature.
We do not feel this way.
Instead, we praise it for maintaining its order and showing reverence to God.
Therefore, even in the baptized, it is blessed, not avoided, and it is adorned rather than removed.
For He who blessed the fountain of eternal water so that we are spiritually reborn, also blessed spouses so that we are born physically.
Therefore, we received this movement of desire from the Creator, just like other body parts.
If desire is evil because through it adultery is sometimes committed, then the hand is also evil because through it murder is carried out.
Blame the tongue, because through it, God is blasphemed; condemn the foot, because it leads a person to a brothel.
In this way, not only desire but all your members are condemned.
I will respond to you with a Catholic perspective, because just as the hand was made not for killing, but for working;
and the tongue not for blaspheming, but for the glory and praise of the Creator;
and all members not to serve vices, but to follow divine commandments;
so too is desire naturally implanted, not for adultery, but for generating:
which we have proven not only as a help to the fertility of spouses but also as a means to bring the palm of virtue to the continent.
Do you want to know that this desire is good?
I will compare it to divine mysteries.
For not only bad desires but even good presumptions are condemned.
Imagine someone presuming to take the body of the Lord before the light of baptism;
would not this person be condemned for presuming upon good?
What is given to some according to order brings salvation, while to others it brings condemnation outside of order, outside the accepted time.
Similarly, if a layperson usurps the priesthood, or presumes to offer sacrifice, would not this person be condemned for assuming power not granted to them?
If presumption of such holy things makes one guilty, not the action itself, how much more in desire, not the action keeping its order but going outside of order, is it called a crime, and makes cursed what the Creator placed as blessed in its order?
If this is so, or rather because it is so, why do you suffer, unhappy ones, who wanting to nullify the restoration of baptism, say that this desire remained so that all sins would not seem entirely forgiven to a person?
Why should you not rather suspect from this that it is not a sin, since it is not erased in baptized people?
For if it were a sin, it would surely be removed like the others.
Therefore, those of you who strive to diminish the gifts of baptism through desire are showing that the creator of desire is the devil.
By doing this, you imply that the Creator failed in His work during creation and that He could not fully provide help through baptism.
Those who willingly welcome you will share your fate.
For it is written that not only those who commit iniquity are guilty, but also those who consent to it.
Romans 1:32.