Theodulf, Bishop of Orleans, speaks on the Holy Spirit.
He discusses the views of the ancient Fathers, who believed that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
Preface to Emperor Charles the Great
Following the command of your empire, illustrious king,
I, Theodulf, bring these teachings gladly.
The Holy Spirit is shown to proceed from both Father and Son,
As the echoing trumpet of law declares.
The Gospel proclaims this, the Apostle confirms it,
And the sacred, united voice of the Fathers sings the same.
Go, little book, swiftly to the lofty steps of Charles,
And say to the pious emperor, "Hail!"
Prostrate on the ground, offer your graceful kiss to his feet:
Then rise and seek a fitting place on bended knee.
And if he fixes his shining eyes upon you,
And his gracious hand kindly receives you,
And if he asks, "Where do you come from? What do you wish? Where do you go?
Who are you?" You shall humbly answer thus:
"I, under Theodulf's guidance, ran through many meadows,
Behold, I come, laden with flowers for your view.
I seek to prove, through the teachings of faith,
That the Holy Spirit proceeds from both Father and Son.
I come ready to join hands with those,
Who walk astray and flee this path.
If you cannot say it yourself, let the pious one intercede:
'I can, I can, O king, God will provide aid.'
The glorious judgment of the holy prophets is with me,
Stirred by the breath of this same Spirit.
And you will lay your hand on that which the Spirit gives life to,
Whose cause began in your time.
You, the glory of the world, the light of the realm, the protector of justice,
The wall and weapon of the Catholic faith.
You command what is just, forbid what is unjust,
Bestow honors, and rightly nourish noble arts.
You love them, command their love, and refresh and support them,
Drinking deeply from the rich waters of their cup.
What more can I say? You shine with virtue, overflow with piety,
In all goodness, no one, I know, surpasses you.
If one should tell you to lay your hand upon the sword,
"Now show if you have any strength of virtue left."
Then behold the arms of the fathers, drawn from the deep flood,
As taught by both the new law and the old.
While our ranks, fortified with these, will never falter,
And you will win, following Him whom you serve.
Brilliant victory will come to you in splendid robes,
And you, pious king, will achieve your holy desire.
Here is a list of authors who are cited:
Athanasius. Cyril. Hilary. Ambrose.
Didymus.
Augustine.
Vigilius the African.
Proclus.
Agnellus.
Gregory.
Isidore.
Prosper.
Fulgentius.
Hormisdas.
Leo.
Cassiodorus.
Prudentius.
Athanasius, in his book against the Arian heretics, discusses the Holy Spirit proceeding from both the Father and the Son:
"I believe the Son is in the Father, and the Father is in the Son, and also the Holy Spirit, who proceeds from the Father and is of both the Son and the Father because he also proceeds from the Son. As it is written in the Gospel, by his breath, he gave the Holy Spirit to his disciples, saying: 'Receive the Holy Spirit. If you forgive anyone's sins, they are forgiven; if you do not forgive them, they are not forgiven.'"
(John 20:22)
Therefore, I confess the inseparable Trinity, neither excluding the Son nor the Holy Spirit, contrary to what the heretics claim.
I say from God the Father, because the Son, who is the wisdom of the Father, is also the will of the Father, which has always been in Him, and He is the angel of great counsel.
In the same work (Book 8), it's clear that the Holy Spirit knows everything and is inseparable from the Father.
Suggesting that the Father was ever without the Holy Spirit is utterly foolish.
As the Apostle says, the Holy Spirit searches the deep and high things of God.
First Corinthians 2:10.
Many Scriptures have shown that this same Spirit is of the Son.
The Spirit remains fully in the Son, and just as He proceeds from God the Father, He also proceeds from the Son, making the whole Trinity one God.
Therefore, the Father does nothing and arranges nothing without His wisdom, and He knows and arranges everything with His Holy Spirit.
The Prophet says:
"The Spirit of the Lord, the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and might, the spirit of knowledge and fear of the Lord" Isaiah 11:2, all of which exist in God, who is the Trinity.
Also in the same book (Book 8), it is stated that the Son and Holy Spirit are in the Father, and that the Holy Spirit proceeds from God, where the name of the Son is not excluded.
Therefore, we must serve Christ the Son because He is both perfect God and true Son.
Whoever faithfully serves the Son serves the Father and the Holy Spirit who is in Him.
Whoever worships the Father worships the Son and the Holy Spirit in Him, because the Son and the Holy Spirit are in the Father.
The Lord Himself says, "I am in the Father and the Father is in me" (John 14:11).
About the Holy Spirit, He also says, "The Advocate, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name" (John 15:26).
And when someone worships the Son, they worship the Father and the Holy Spirit in Him, because the Father is in Him, as He says, "Whoever has seen me has seen the Father" (John 14:9), and again, "The Father who dwells in me does His works" (John 14:10).
About the Holy Spirit, He says, "He will glorify me because He will take from what is mine and declare it to you" (John 16:14); and, "All that the Father has is mine; therefore I said that He will take from what is mine" (John 16:15).
Thus, the Spirit of the Father is the Spirit of the Son, as the Apostle says, "Because you are sons, God has sent the Spirit of His Son into our hearts" (Galatians 4:6); and again, "If anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, they do not belong to Him" (Romans 8:9); and again, "For I know that through your prayers and the help of the Spirit of Jesus Christ this will turn out for my deliverance" (Philippians 1:19).
In the Gospel, the Lord Himself also says, "The Advocate, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name" (John 14:26).
And in the Acts of the Apostles, it is written: "Passing through Phrygia and Galatia, they were forbidden by the Holy Spirit to speak the word in Asia; when they came to Mysia, they attempted to go into Bithynia, but the Spirit of the Lord did not allow them" (Acts 16:6).
Therefore, it is proved by very clear testimonies that the Holy Spirit, the Advocate, the Spirit who proceeds from the Father, is the Spirit of the Son, the Spirit of Christ, the Spirit of Jesus.
The entire Trinity is to be worshipped, revered, proclaimed, and loved as one inseparable substance, divinity, and power.
Similarly, in the same book, it is stated that the Holy Spirit is neither the Father nor the Son, but God in nature, proceeding from the Father and receiving from the Son.
This Holy Spirit, who is neither the Father nor the Son, neither begot nor was begotten.
One is in the person who begot, another is in the person who is the only begotten from him, and another equally in person, as I said, according to the Scriptures.
This is the Holy Spirit, of a single nature.
Therefore, in divinity, they share a common name.
As in the clarity of the Gospel Scriptures, the Son testifies concerning the Spirit the Comforter, saying, "He proceeds from the Father" (John 15:26), and continues, "He will receive from what is mine" (John 16:14).
Therefore, where persons are required, their own names distinguish them.
But where divinity is required, a single name is indicated in them.
It is demonstrated that "we" are said in reference to the names of the persons in the plural. In divinity, they are one, and in the names of persons, they are three.
In the book he wrote addressing the objections of a certain Potentinius, he explains:
Just as the Son cries out to the Father, "Father, glorify your name," and a voice from heaven responds, "I have glorified it, and I will glorify it again" (John 12:28), he repeats this in another place, saying, "I came from the Father and have come" (John 16:28).
If the Father himself was the same person as the Son, would he have said, "I came from myself and have come"?
Clearly, one is the one who came, and another is the one from whom he came.
He also added about the Holy Spirit, "When the Advocate comes, whom I will send to you from my Father, the Spirit of truth who proceeds from the Father, he will testify about me" (John 15:26).
Isn't it clear that one is the one who sends, another is the one from whom he proceeds, and another is the one who comes?
If there were only one person, from whom would he be sent, or from whom would he proceed?
The Apostle confirmed this in his greeting to the Corinthians, saying: "The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God, that is, the Father, and the fellowship of the Holy Spirit be with you all, amen" (Second Corinthians 13:13).
Doesn't he clearly distinguish, through each name, that there are distinct persons?
Therefore, the Father is the one who begets, the Son is the only begotten from him, and the Holy Spirit is the Paraclete, who proceeds from one nature.
You may ask, heretic, how does the Spirit consist of one nature?
Behold, the Son testified that he proceeds from the Father, and he continued, "He will take from what is mine" (John 16:14).
Also, in the same book on the profession of the Catholic Rule, Book 7:
By the word of the Lord, the heavens were established, and by the breath of His mouth, all their host.
(Psalm 32:6)
He declared the Word as the Son, and the Lord as His Father, demonstrating that the Spirit of His mouth is the principal Spirit.
Notice how briefly He distinguished each person: the Word, the Lord, and the Spirit.
Yet, He also showed that there is one operation among them.
If you still have doubts, let me repeat: when it says "by the word of the Lord," do not think it means just a sound of a voice, which, when emitted by someone powerful, echoes and is only heard in imagination.
Clearly, regarding this word of our Lord and Father, who is our salvation, the divine Scripture testifies everywhere that the Son of God is substantial, through whom all things were made.
Therefore, when it says, "by the word of the Lord, the heavens were established, and by the breath of His mouth, all their host," recognize that this substantial Word was truly born from the Father. The Spirit of His mouth refers to the Spirit that proceeds from the same united substance, as carefully stated; not from another nature, but from the same. Thus, the united substance of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, which the Greeks call ομουσιον, and the united operation of this same Trinity in creation.
In the same book, where he wrote against heretics (Book Eleven), he stated that the Holy Spirit is the inspiration of the Father and the Son, and that the Son is the source of the Holy Spirit.
This indicates that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son as well.
The inspiration of the Lord is the light of men, which searches the depths of the heart (Proverbs twenty: twenty-seven).
It is clear that the Spirit searches all things, as Paul writes in First Corinthians chapter two, verse ten.
From the beginning, when Adam was formed, God breathed the Holy Spirit into him, as Moses says, "And God breathed into Adam's face the breath of life, and man became a living soul" (Genesis two: seven).
According to Jewish storytellers, what was inspired by God is not the soul.
Otherwise, how could God condemn what He inspired to eternal fire?
Rather, it is the life-giving Spirit, of which Paul says, "The Spirit gives life."
He also mentions, "God breathed into his face the breath of life, and man became a living soul" (Second Corinthians three: six).
Therefore, the Holy Spirit and the spirit of life, from which some who have fallen are living dead, as Paul wrote, "But she who lives in pleasure is dead while she lives" (First Timothy five: six).
Otherwise, how could we understand Solomon saying, "The inspiration of the Lord is the light of men, which searches the inner parts of the belly," if not that the souls of men are considered the light of God?
Unless you acknowledge that the Holy Spirit is the light of the Lord and believe that He is the inspiration of the Son, as Moses says, "God breathed into Adam's face the breath of life"; and the Son of God, "I am life" (John fourteen: six).
Additionally, the wisdom of Solomon introduces the Savior saying, "Behold, I will pour out to you my spirit" (Proverbs one: twenty-three).
In Proverbs, it says, "Wisdom sings in the streets, acts confidently in the squares, stands powerfully at the gates, and acts confidently in the walls of the city. As long as the simple ones hold on to righteousness, they will not be ashamed, but the foolish, being desirous of insult, became impious and hated understanding, and became subject to rebukes."
Behold, I will share with you the source of my inspiration.
I will teach you my words. Proverbs chapter 1, verse 20 and following.
And Isaiah, proclaiming the promise of the Holy Spirit, said:
This is what the Lord says, the one who made the heavens and established them, who formed the earth and everything in it, who gives breath to its people and spirit to those who walk on it.
Isaiah chapter 42, verse 5.
Tell me, who are the people who receive inspiration?
Do you say that inspiration is the soul?
Or will you claim that people exist on earth without a soul?
But it is not so, for the prophet, proclaiming the promise of the Holy Spirit, said these things.
Finally, Luke wrote about the fulfillment of the promise to the faithful:
And when the days of Pentecost, the fiftieth day, had come, they were all together in one place.
Suddenly, there came a sound from heaven like a mighty rushing wind, and it filled the entire house where they were sitting.
Divided tongues, as of fire, appeared to them and rested on each one of them.
They began to speak in other languages, as the Spirit enabled them.
Acts chapter 2, verse 1.
Similarly, the great Job, speaking against his friends who were deprived of the Holy Spirit and neither spoke truthfully nor realized they were speaking before God, said:
Do you not speak in the presence of God?
And again:
To whom have you declared words?
But whose inspiration proceeds from you?
Job chapter 26, verse 4.
From whom one speaking greatly said:
It is the Spirit that intercedes for mortals, and the Almighty inspiration that teaches me.
Job chapter 32, verse 8.
Immediately, the Almighty Son of God, about whom Zechariah said:
Therefore, thus says the Almighty, After glory, He has sent me against the nations that plundered you.
Zechariah chapter 2, verse 8.
Let us also hear Solomon saying:
The light of the Lord is the inspiration of humanity.
Proverbs chapter 20, verse 27.
And being instructed by Moses, because the Lord breathed into Adam's face the breath of life, and man became a living soul.
Genesis chapter 2, verse 7.
And hearing the Savior say:
I am the life.
John chapter 14, verse 6.
And Paul writing:
For the law of the Spirit of life.
Romans chapter 8, verse 2.
And again, God sent the Spirit of His Son into our hearts, crying out Galatians 4:6.
Also, seeing the Only Begotten breathe into the faces of the apostles and say, "Receive the Holy Spirit" John 20:22, we learn that the Holy Spirit, remaining in the very life and substance of the Son, is the inspiration of the Son.
We do not believe that He is begotten or created by the Son, nor that He is the Word of the Son.
The Word, begotten by God, remains in His own life and substance as the Son of God, for He Himself is life; therefore, the Spirit is not begotten by Him, because He is not His Word.
However, it is blasphemous to say that the Holy Spirit is created; nevertheless, the holy Scriptures teach us that He is the inspiration of the Son of God.
We say that the Son of God is the source of the Holy Spirit, with the Son Himself saying in Jeremiah, "For my people have committed two evils: they have forsaken me, the fountain of living waters, and hewed out cisterns for themselves, broken cisterns that can hold no water" Jeremiah 2:13.
The living water is the Holy Spirit, as John taught that the Savior said to the Samaritan woman, "If you knew the gift of God, and who it is that is saying to you, 'Give me a drink,' you would have asked him, and he would have given you living water" John 4:10; and again, "Whoever drinks of the water that I will give him will never be thirsty again" John 4:14.
For He also cries out in the midst of the temple, "If anyone thirsts, let him come to me and drink. Whoever believes in me, as the Scripture has said, 'Out of his heart will flow rivers of living water'" John 7:37-38; and this is interpreted as, "Now this he said about the Spirit, whom those who believed in him were to receive" John 7:39.
Isaiah also says that the Lord said, "For I will pour water on the thirsty land, and streams on the dry ground; I will pour my Spirit upon your offspring, and my blessing on your descendants. They shall spring up among the grass like willows by flowing streams" Isaiah 44:3-4.
Therefore, clearly, by the confession of the holy Scriptures, we recognize that the living water is the Holy Spirit.
The Lord said that He is the fountain of the Spirit, thus: "They have forsaken me, the fountain of living waters" Jeremiah 2:13.
So, David also sings in the thirty-fifth Psalm, verse 10, saying to the Lord,
"For with you is the fountain of life."
Therefore, besides the Lord, show another fountain of life that is with him.
He did not say, "You are the fountain of life," but "with you is the fountain of life."
It is with you, truly, with God; and the Son is the fountain of the spirit, about which Paul writes to the Romans,
"The Spirit is life because of righteousness" (Romans 8:10).
Thus, he is said to be the Father's own, not foreign.
For when he declared, "with you is the fountain of life," he added,
"In your light, we see light" (Psalm 36:9); that is, in your Son, we see the spirit.
Also, in the name of God's power, the spirit is called, and shown to be, life and wisdom.
For we heard the Savior in the Gospel promising his disciples to send the Holy Spirit, saying to them,
"Behold, I send the promise of my Father upon you; but stay in the city until you are clothed with power from on high" (Luke 24:49).
In the Acts of the Apostles, the same Lord says,
"You will receive power when the Holy Spirit comes upon you" (Acts 1:8).
We also find this fulfilled later on the day of Pentecost.
Therefore, either you profess that the Holy Spirit is the power of the Lord, or like Sabellius, you preach that the Paraclete Spirit, being the power of God, is the same as the Son of God; and hearing Paul say,
"The Spirit is life because of righteousness" (Romans 8:10),
we are again taught that the Son is the fountain of the spirit.
Similarly, in the Creed, it is stated that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son.
The Father is made by no one, neither created nor begotten.
The Son comes from the Father alone, not made, not created, but begotten.
The Holy Spirit is from the Father and the Son, not made, not created, nor begotten, but proceeding.
Therefore, there is one Father, not three fathers; one Son, not three sons; one Holy Spirit, not three holy spirits.
And in this Trinity, there is nothing before or after, nothing greater or lesser, but all three persons are co-eternal and co-equal with each other.
So, in all things, as mentioned before, the Trinity in unity and the unity in Trinity is to be worshipped.
Therefore, whoever wants to be saved must think this way about the Trinity.
The Letter to Nestorius (Letter 3 on Excommunication) states that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
Regarding the Spirit, it says, "He will glorify me" (John 16:14).
Understanding this correctly, we confess one Christ and Son, who does not need the glory of another and has received glory from the Holy Spirit because His Spirit is not superior to Him.
Since Christ used His own power to perform miraculous works as a demonstration of His divinity, it is said that He was glorified by it, just as one might say humans are glorified by their own power or discipline.
Although Christ is in His own substance and is understood in His person according to what the Spirit is, and not the Son, He is not alien to Him.
The Spirit is called the Spirit of truth, and Christ is the truth, from which He proceeds just as from God the Father.
Finally, this same Spirit, performing glorious miracles through the hands of the holy apostles, glorified Jesus Christ after He ascended into heaven.
For Christ was believed to be God by nature, performing powers through His Spirit.
Hence, He said, "He will take from what is mine and declare it to you" (John 16:14).
The same Spirit is not said to be wise or powerful by participation with another because He is perfect in all things and needs nothing at all.
For the same Spirit of the Son is believed to be of the Father's power and wisdom, and thus He is proven to be the substance of power and wisdom.
In a dialogue with Theodoret, the bishop of Cyrus, it is mentioned that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
We recall Christ openly speaking about the Holy Spirit, saying, "He will glorify me" (John 16:14).
We know that the Holy Spirit's power crushes wicked and impure forces.
However, we do not say that he, like each of the saints, uses a foreign power through the Holy Spirit.
It was and is his spirit, just as it is the Father's.
Paul clearly explains this to us: "Those who are in the flesh cannot please God. But you are not in the flesh, but in the spirit, if indeed the Spirit of God dwells in you. Now if anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to him" (Romans 8:8-9).
The Holy Spirit proceeds from God the Father according to the Savior's words but is not separate from the Son.
He shares everything with the Father, and this is taught by Jesus when he says about the Holy Spirit, "All things that the Father has are mine. Therefore I said that he will take of mine and declare it to you" (John 16:15).
Therefore, the Holy Spirit will indeed glorify Jesus by performing extraordinary works.
Yet it is his own spirit, not a foreign power, and in this way, he is understood to be God.
Hilary teaches that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and receives from the Son, meaning He is sent.
In the eighth book on the Trinity, he writes:
"When the Advocate comes, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth who proceeds from the Father, he will testify about me." (John chapter 15, verse 26)
The Advocate will come, and the Son will send him from the Father.
The Spirit of truth proceeds from the Father.
Let every heretical school sharpen their wit and attempt to teach falsely, but explain what it means that the Son sends from the Father.
The one who sends shows his authority in what he sends.
But what do we understand by saying that he sends from the Father?
Is it received, dismissed, or generated?
It must mean one of these if he is to be sent from the Father, and he is to send the Spirit of truth who proceeds from the Father.
It is not a matter of receiving where the procession is shown.
So we must confirm our understanding, whether we believe it is the going out of one who exists or the procession of one who is generated.
I do not object to the freedom of understanding in this world, whether they think the Advocate Spirit is from the Father or the Son.
The Lord did not leave it uncertain.
For under the same words, he spoke thus:
"I still have many things to say to you, but you cannot bear them now. However, when the Spirit of truth comes, he will guide you into all truth. For he will not speak on his own, but he will speak whatever he hears, and he will declare to you the things that are to come. He will glorify me, because he will take from what is mine and declare it to you. All that the Father has is mine; therefore I said that he will take from what is mine and declare it to you." (John chapter 16, verse 12)
Therefore, he receives from the Son because he is also sent by him and proceeds from the Father.
And I ask, is receiving from the Son the same as proceeding from the Father?
If it is believed that there is no difference between receiving from the Son and proceeding from the Father, it will certainly be understood that receiving from the Son is the same as receiving from the Father.
For the Lord himself says, "Because he will take from what is mine and declare it to you."
Everything that the Father has is mine.
That's why I said that he will take from what is mine and will announce it to you.
John sixteen fourteen.
Whether it is power, virtue, or teaching, the Son said it must be taken from himself, and he also means that it must be taken from the Father.
When he says that everything the Father has is his, and therefore it must be taken from what is his, he teaches that it must be taken from the Father, yet it is taken from himself because everything that belongs to the Father is his.
This unity does not have diversity, nor does it matter from whom it is received; what is given by the Father is referred to as given by the Son.
Is the unity of will affirmed here too?
Everything the Father has belongs to the Son, and everything the Son has belongs to the Father.
For he himself said, "All mine are yours, and yours are mine."
John sixteen fifteen.
It is not yet the place to explain why he said, "He will take from what is mine."
It shows the significance of the future tense where he will take; now certainly he says he will take from himself because everything of the Father is his.
If you can, separate the unity of this nature and impose some necessity of dissimilarity, by which the Son would not be in the unity of nature.
For the Spirit of truth proceeds from the Father, but it is sent by the Son and by the Father.
Everything that belongs to the Father belongs to the Son, and therefore whatever he receives, he receives from the Son who is to be sent, because everything of the Father belongs to the Son.
Thus, nature holds its law in all things, and because both are one, the same divinity is signified in both through generation and nativity, since what the Spirit of truth receives from the Father, the Son admits to giving from himself.
Similarly, in the book about synods that he wrote to Germany, Gaul, Belgica, Lyon, Narbonne, Novempopulana, Toulouse, and Britain, it discusses the sending of the Holy Spirit from the Son.
We believe in the Holy Spirit, the Advocate, whom Jesus promised to his apostles and sent after his return to heaven to teach them and remind them of everything.
Through him, the souls of those who sincerely believe are sanctified.
If anyone claims that the Holy Spirit, the Comforter, is an unbegotten God, let them be cursed.
Adding that the Comforter is unbegotten subjects this proclamation of God to a curse.
It is extremely impious to say that He, who was sent by the Son for our consolation, is an unbegotten God.
If anyone, as the Lord taught us, says that the Comforter is not different from the Son; for He said, "And the Father will send you another Comforter, whom I will ask Him" (John 14:16), let them be cursed.
We remember that the Comforter was sent by the Son, and this was originally explained by the faith itself.
Since the Son often said that His works are the works of the Father by the power of their undivided nature, saying, "I do the works of my Father" (John 10:37), and since He also frequently promised to send the Comforter, sometimes He said the Comforter would be sent by the Father, as He often piously referred all that He did to the Father.
From this, heretics often seize the opportunity to say that the Son Himself is the Comforter: when He said that another Comforter is to be sent by the Father, He signifies the difference between the one who sends and the one who is asked to send.
If anyone says that the Holy Spirit is a part of the Father or the Son, let them be cursed.
The foolishness of heretical madness compelled me to write this, not a question.
Since the name of the Holy Spirit has its own meaning, and the Holy Spirit, the Comforter, has His own substance, office, and order, and since the unchangeable Father and Son are proclaimed everywhere, how can the Holy Spirit be asserted to be a part of either the Father or the Son?
But since, among other forms of insanity, this is often brought forth by the impious, it had to be refuted by the saints.
If anyone says that the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit are three gods, let them be cursed.
Ambrose teaches in the first book he wrote to Emperor Gratian, Chapter 10, that the Holy Spirit does not move from place to place when proceeding from the Father and the Son:
Indeed, if the Spirit proceeds from a place and moves to a place, and the Father is found in a place, and the Son, if He leaves the place from which the Father or the Son sends Him, the Spirit moving from place to place would seem to leave the Father and the Son like a body, according to impious interpretations.
I speak according to those who think that the Spirit has a descending movement.
But neither is the Father confined to any place, being above all things, not only of a bodily nature but also of invisible creation.
Nor is the Son confined to places and times of His works, being above all creation, the creator of all.
Nor is the Spirit of truth, being God's Spirit, confined to any bodily limits, being incorporeal, surpassing all intelligible substance of creation with the ineffable fullness of divinity, having the power to breathe where He wills and inspire how He wills, having power over all things.
Therefore, the Spirit is not sent from a place, nor does He proceed from a place when He proceeds from the Son; just as the Son Himself, when He says, "I proceeded and came forth from the Father" (John 8:42), eliminates all opinions that He moves from place to place as in some bodily things.
Similarly, when we read that God is either within or outside, we do not confine God within any body or separate Him from any body, but considering this with deep and ineffable understanding, we understand the mystery of the divine nature.
Thus, Wisdom says that it proceeded from the mouth of the Most High, not being outside the Father, but with the Father, because the Word was with God (John 1:1).
And not only with the Father, but also from the Father; for He says, "I am in the Father, and the Father is in me" (John 10:38).
But neither when He proceeds from the Father does He leave a place, nor is He separated like a body from a body; nor when He is in the Father is He enclosed in a body like a body.
The Holy Spirit, when He proceeds from the Father and the Son, is not separated from either.
How can He be separated from the Father when He is the breath of His mouth?
This signifies eternity and the unity of divinity.
Therefore, He always is and remains the Spirit of the mouth.
Yet, He seems to descend when we receive Him to dwell in us, so we are not alienated from His grace.
It appears He descends, not because He does, but because our spirit ascends to Him.
We would elaborate more, but we remember what was already stated in previous books: the Father said, "Come, let us go down and confuse their language" (Genesis 11:7); and the Son said, "Anyone who loves me will obey my teaching. My Father will love them, and we will come to them and make our home with them" (John 14:23).
So, the Spirit comes just as the Father comes; because where the Father is, there is the Son, and where the Son is, there is the Spirit.
Therefore, the Holy Spirit should not be thought to come separately.
He comes not from one place to another, but from the order of establishment to the salvation of redemption, from the grace of giving life to the grace of sanctification, to transfer us from earth to heaven, from injury to glory, from servitude to the kingdom.
Thus, the Spirit comes just as the Father does.
For the Son said, "I and the Father will come and make our home with him." Does the Father come physically? Therefore, the Spirit also comes, in whom, when He comes, the full presence of the Father and the Son is.
Who can separate the Spirit from the Father and the Son when we cannot even call the Father and the Son without the Spirit? For no one can say, "Jesus is Lord," except by the Holy Spirit (First Corinthians 12:3).
Therefore, if we cannot call Jesus Lord without the Spirit, surely we cannot preach without the Spirit.
And if even the angels proclaim the Lord Jesus, whom no one can preach without the Spirit, then the gift of the Holy Spirit also works in them.
We have therefore proven that there is one presence, one grace of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, which is so heavenly and divine that for this reason the Son gives thanks to the Father, saying:
I thank you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because you have hidden these things from the wise and prudent, and revealed them to little children.
Luke 10:21.
In the third book, Chapter 1, it is stated that the Holy Spirit is sent by both the Father and the Son, where "sending" is understood as "proceeding." Both the Father and the Son sent the Spirit. The Father sent Him because it is written, "But the Advocate, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name" (John 14:26).
The Son sent Him because He said, "When the Advocate comes, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth" (John 15:26).
Therefore, if the Son and the Spirit send each other just as the Father sends, it is not a matter of subjection, but a sharing of power.
Not only did the Father send the Son, but He also gave Him, just as the Son gave Himself.
For it is read, "Grace and peace to you from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ, who gave Himself for our sins" (Galatians 1:3).
If they think He was subjected because He was sent, they cannot deny it was an act of grace because He was given.
He was given by the Father, as Isaiah said, "For to us a child is born, to us a son is given" (Isaiah 9:6).
I dare to say He was also given by the Spirit who was sent by the Spirit.
For when it was not specified who gave Him, it showed that He was given by the grace of the Trinity.
And when the Son gave Himself, He could not be subjected to Himself according to His divinity.
Therefore, it could not be subjection to divinity that He was given.
The Holy Spirit was also given, because it is read, "And I will ask the Father, and He will give you another Advocate" (John 14:16).
And the Apostle says, "Therefore, anyone who rejects this instruction does not reject a human being but God, the very God who gives you His Holy Spirit" (First Thessalonians 4:8).
Isaiah also shows that both the Spirit and the Son were given.
Thus says the Lord who made the heavens and set them in place, who established the earth and everything on it, and who gives breath to its people, and spirit to those who walk on it (Isaiah 42:5); and to the Son, "I, the Lord God, have called you in righteousness; I will take hold of your hand. I will keep you and will make you to be a covenant for the people and a light for the Gentiles, to open the eyes that are blind, to free captives from prison" (Isaiah 42:6).
Since the Son was sent and given, and the Spirit was also given and sent, they share the unity of divinity because they have the unity of work.
That's why the Spirit is also called the finger of God.
Also, in the same book, it is said that the river flowing from the throne of God and the Lamb is the Holy Spirit, indicating his procession from the Father and the Son.
Therefore, the Spirit has what Christ has, and thus, he has what God has, because everything that the Father has, the Son also has.
That is why it is said in John 16:15, "Everything that the Father has is mine."
It is also significant that we read about a river flowing from the throne of God. As the evangelist John says: "And he showed me a river of the water of life, bright as crystal, flowing from the throne of God and the Lamb, down the middle of the street of the city. On either side of the river is the tree of life with its twelve kinds of fruit, producing its fruit each month, and the leaves of the tree are for the healing of the nations" (Revelation 22:1-2).
This is indeed the river flowing from the throne of God, that is, the Holy Spirit, whom he who believes in Christ drinks.
As he himself said, "If anyone is thirsty, let him come to me and drink; he who believes in me, as the Scripture has said, out of his heart will flow rivers of living water." Now he said this about the Spirit (John 7:37-39).
Therefore, the river is the Spirit.
Jerome, in the book of Didymus (Book 2, at the beginning), which he translated from Greek to Latin, teaches that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and is sent by the Son.
This is not in the manner of the ministry of angels, prophets, and apostles, but in a way befitting the Spirit of God being sent by the wisdom of God.
From this, it is concluded that the Spirit also proceeds from the Son.
Since the Holy Spirit, like the Father and the Son, is said to dwell in the mind and inner person, it is not just inappropriate but impious to call Him a creature.
Disciplines, virtues, and arts, as well as their opposing disturbances, ignorances, and emotions, can inhabit souls, but not as substantial beings, rather as additional influences.
It is impossible for created nature to dwell in the mind.
If this is true, and the Holy Spirit, existing without any ambiguity, is the inhabitant of the soul and heart, it is beyond doubt that He must be believed to be uncreated along with the Father and the Son.
Thus, from all that the preceding discourse has discussed, the Holy Spirit is shown to be incorruptible and eternal according to the nature of the Father and the Son, removing all ambiguity about Himself and eliminating any suspicion that He is one of the created substances.
As the words of the Savior in the Gospel declare, He proceeds from the Father.
"When the Comforter comes," He says, "whom I will send to you, the Spirit of truth, who proceeds from the Father, He will testify about me" (John 15:26).
He calls the coming Comforter the Holy Spirit, naming Him after His function.
This is because He not only comforts those He finds worthy but also frees them from all sorrow and disturbance, granting them incredible joy and cheerfulness.
To the extent that one, giving thanks to God for being deemed worthy of such a guest, can say, "You have put gladness in my heart" (Psalm 4:7).
Indeed, eternal joy dwells in the hearts of those in whom the Holy Spirit resides.
This comforting Spirit is sent by the Son, not like the ministry of angels, prophets, and apostles, but in a way that befits the Spirit of God-sent by wisdom and truth, and sharing the same substance with that wisdom and truth.
Similarly, in the same book, a little later, although the Savior often says that He came from God, He takes on the property and, so to speak, the closeness of the Father through the term, as we often discussed.
He says, "I am in the Father, and the Father in me" (John 14:11),
and elsewhere, "I and the Father are one" (John 10:30),
and many similar things that a reader observing the Gospel will find.
Therefore, this Holy Spirit, who comes from the Father, will testify about me, says the Lord (John 15:26),
bearing similar testimony to that of the Father, about whom He says, "The Father who sent me bears witness about me" (John 8:18).
But when the Son sends the Spirit of truth, whom He called the Comforter, the Father also sends Him.
For the Father does not abstain from sending when the Son sends, since the Spirit comes by the same will of the Father and the Son.
The Savior also speaks through the prophet, as it will be clear to anyone who reads the whole passage: "And the Lord sent me, and His Spirit" (Isaiah 48:16).
Indeed, God sent not only the Son but also the Spirit.
The apostle also speaks of this, "These things have now been announced to you through those who preached the gospel to you by the Holy Spirit sent from heaven" (First Peter 1:12).
And in Wisdom, which is titled Panaretos by those who have received divine gifts, a voice giving thanks to God is sent forth:
"Who can search out the things in heaven? Who will know your will unless you give wisdom and send your Holy Spirit from on high? Thus, the paths of those on earth were corrected, and men were taught what is pleasing to you" (Wisdom 9:16).
And in the present reading, not only is God's wisdom, namely His only-begotten Son, given by the Father, but the Holy Spirit is also sent.
In the Gospel itself, it is proclaimed that the Holy Spirit is given and sent by the Father, with the Savior saying, "And I will ask the Father, and He will give you another Comforter to be with you forever, the Spirit of truth" (John 14:16).
But the Helper, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, will teach you all things.
In these words, the Father promises another Helper, not different from the one sent by the Son.
When the Helper comes, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth, he is called another Helper, not because of a difference in nature, but because of a difference in operation.
Also, in the same work, Book Two, it is mentioned: Because the Holy Spirit is sent in the name of the Son by the Father, having the property of the Son in that He is God, but not as if He were His son, it shows the unity He shares with the Son.
Hence, He is also called the Spirit of the Son, making those who receive Him sons through adoption.
As the scripture says, "Because you are sons of God, the Father sent the Spirit of His Son into your hearts, crying out, 'Abba, Father'" (Galatians chapter 4, verse 6).
However, this Holy Spirit, who came in the name of the Son sent by the Father, will teach everything to those perfected in faith in Christ.
He will teach all spiritual and intellectual matters, and to summarize, all the sacraments of truth and wisdom.
He will teach, not as a teacher who has acquired knowledge from elsewhere, for that is typical of those who have learned wisdom and arts through study and effort, but as the very art and doctrine, the spirit of wisdom and truth, invisibly instilling divine knowledge into the mind.
In the same work, Book Two, shortly after explaining the interpretation of how he said, "He will take from what is mine," he immediately added: "All that the Father has is mine; therefore I said that he will take from what is mine and announce it to you" (John 16:15).
In a certain way of speaking, though the Spirit of Truth proceeds from the Father, and God gives the Holy Spirit to those who ask, yet because all that the Father has is mine, and this very Spirit is my Father's, he will take from what is mine.
However, be careful when these things are said, so that you do not fall into error by misunderstanding and think it is something or possession that the Father has and the Son doesn't.
Truly, what the Father has by nature, that is, eternity, immutability, incorruptibility, immortality, and goodness that exists from and in himself, the Son has these same things.
And to go further, whatever the Son himself is and whatever belongs to the Son, the Father has these same things.
Also, in the same work, Book Two towards the end, he said, "You, however, undoubtedly have received the wisdom of the Spirit and life and peace as disciples of Christ. You are not in the flesh, as stated in Romans chapter eight, verse nine, meaning you do not perform the works of the flesh, since you have the Spirit of God within you. This Spirit of God is also the Spirit of Christ, bringing and joining those who have it to the Lord Jesus Christ. Hence it is written later, 'If anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, they do not belong to Christ,' as stated in Romans chapter eight, verse nine."
Again, in the present, we learn of the relationship the Holy Spirit has with Christ and with God. Also, in Peter's epistle, the Holy Spirit is proven to be the Spirit of Christ, saying, "Searching and inquiring, that is, the prophets about whom the previous speech was made, in what or what kind of time it was signified by the Spirit of Christ in them, testifying in Christ the sufferings and the decrees that were to follow, in which it was revealed that they were not serving themselves, but us, who now have announced these things to you through the Holy Spirit," as stated in First Peter chapter one, verse eleven.
This Holy Spirit is called the Spirit of God not only in the present context but also in many other places, such as, "No one knows the things of God except the Spirit of God," as stated in First Corinthians chapter two, verse eleven. Then it follows after this, which says, "If anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, they do not belong to Christ," as stated in Romans chapter eight, verse nine. It is inferred, "If Christ is in you," it is most clearly demonstrated that the Holy Spirit is inseparable from Christ because wherever the Holy Spirit is, there also is Christ. And wherever the Spirit of Christ departs, there too Christ departs. For, "if anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, they do not belong to Christ," to which, if joined, someone might take the opposite and say, "If anyone belongs to Christ, such that Christ is in them, the Spirit of God is in them." The same should be similarly applied to God the Father. If anyone does not have the Spirit of God, they do not belong to Him. To which, again, someone might take the opposite and say.
If anyone belongs to God, the Spirit of God is in them.
As it is written:
Do you not know that you are the temple of God, and the Spirit of God dwells in you?
First Corinthians 3:16.
And in the Epistle of John, God is known to dwell in some people when the Spirit He gave them remains in them.
From all of this, the inseparable and indistinguishable substance of the Trinity is shown.
Also, in the same work, Book Three at the end, shortly after, we see that since the Holy Scripture does not say more about the Trinity except that God the Father is the Savior and the Son is begotten by the Father, we should only believe what is written.
It has also been shown that the Holy Spirit is uncreated, so it follows that what is not created rightly belongs with the Father and the Son.
Let these words, in light of our humble expression, be sufficient for the present.
Augustine, discussing the Holy Spirit proceeding from the Father and the Son, in his book against the heretic Maximinus (Book 3, Chapter 17, at the end), says this:
You seem to be making a significant point when you say, "The Son was in the beginning before anything existed, but the Father was before the beginning." Where did you read this to believe it? How did you presume to say this when there is neither any authority nor reason for it? What does "before the beginning" mean? Because if anything existed before, that would be the beginning. So, if the Father is before the beginning, He is before Himself, because He is also the beginning. What then does "In the beginning was the Word" (John 1:1) mean, if not that the Son was in the Father?
And the Son Himself, when asked by the Jews who He was, responded, "The beginning, who also speaks to you" (John 8:25).
Therefore, the Father is the beginning, not from the beginning, and the Son is the beginning from the beginning.
But together, they are not two beginnings, but one beginning.
Just as the Father is God and the Son is God, and together they are not two gods, but one God.
Nor will I deny that the Holy Spirit proceeding from both is the beginning.
But these three together, just as they are one God, I say are one beginning.
Similarly, in the same book, Book Three, Chapter Nine, you ask me: if the Son is of the substance of the Father, and if the Holy Spirit is also of the substance of the Father, why is there one Son, and another is not a Son?
Here is my response, whether you understand it or not.
The Son is from the Father, and the Holy Spirit is from the Father; but the Son is begotten, and the Holy Spirit proceeds.
Therefore, the Son is the Son of the Father from whom He is begotten, but the Holy Spirit is the Spirit of both, because He proceeds from both.
When He spoke about the Holy Spirit, He said that He proceeds from the Father, as it is written in John Fifteen: Twenty-six, because the Father is the source of His procession, who begot such a Son, and by begetting gave Him that the Holy Spirit might also proceed from Him.
For if He did not proceed from Him as well, He would not have said to His disciples: Receive the Holy Spirit, as it is written in John Twenty: Twenty-two.
By breathing upon them, He gave it, signifying that He proceeds from Him as well, showing openly by breathing what He gave secretly by spirating.
Therefore, if He were born not only of the Father, nor only of the Son, but undoubtedly born of both, He would without a doubt be called the Son of both.
Since He is in no way the Son of both, He ought not to be born of both.
The Holy Spirit is therefore of both by proceeding from both.
But who can explain the difference between being born and proceeding when speaking of that most excellent nature?
Not everything that proceeds is born, although everything that is born proceeds.
Just as not everything that is two-legged is a human, although every human is two-legged.
This I know, but to distinguish between that generation and this procession, I do not know, I am not able, I am not sufficient.
Therefore, because both are ineffable, as the prophet speaking of the Son said: Who shall declare His generation?
as it is written in Isaiah Fifty-three: Eight.
So it is truly said of the Holy Spirit, who shall declare His procession?
The Son is not from himself, but from the one he was born from.
The Holy Spirit is not from himself, but from the one he proceeds from.
As we have already shown, because he proceeds from both, he is also called the Spirit of the Father, as it is written:
"But if the Spirit of him who raised Christ from the dead dwells in you"
(Romans 8:11).
And the Spirit of the Son, as it is written:
"Anyone who does not have the Spirit of Christ does not belong to him"
(Romans 8:9).
There are not two Holy Spirits, as if one belongs to the Father and another to the Son, but rather one Spirit of the Father and the Son, of which it is written:
"For in one Spirit we were all baptized into one body, whether Jews or Greeks, slaves or free, and all were made to drink of one Spirit"
(First Corinthians 12:13);
And in another place:
"One body and one Spirit"
(Ephesians 4:4).
What then is this Trinity, if not one and the same substance?
Since the Son is not from any material or from nothing, but from the one he was begotten from; likewise, the Holy Spirit is not from any material or from nothing but from the one he proceeds from.
Also, in the same book about the Incarnation of the Lord:
The Holy Spirit is neither unbegotten nor begotten, but proceeds from the Father and the Son, as He is the Spirit of both the Father and the Son.
He is consubstantial and coeternal with both.
The Holy Spirit given when He breathed is the same Spirit sent after His ascension.
There is one Spirit of God, the Spirit of the Father and the Son, the Holy Spirit.
The same God works all things in all people, making the Trinity perfect due to the distinctness of the persons, and one God because of the inseparable Trinity.
Likewise, in the book "The Exposition of Faith to Peter," chapter one:
Just as the Son is neither later nor lesser than the Father, the Holy Spirit is neither later nor lesser than the Son. The Son is eternal and without beginning, having been born from the nature of the Father. Similarly, the Holy Spirit is eternal and without beginning, proceeding from the nature of both the Father and the Son.
For this reason, we rightly believe and say that the three are one God. There is one eternity, one immensity, and one divinity among the three persons by nature.
Therefore, let us hold that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are one God by nature. Yet, the Father is not the same as the Son, nor is the Son the same as the Father, and the Holy Spirit is not the same as the Father or the Son. There is one essence of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, which the Greeks call ousia.
Also, in the same work, shortly after, at the end of chapter one.
In that holy Trinity, which we repeat so often to deeply impress it on your heart, there is one God the Father, who alone essentially begot one Son from Himself, and one Son, who alone is essentially begotten from one Father, and one Holy Spirit, who alone essentially proceeds from the Father and the Son.
However, a single person could not do all of this-beget Himself, be born from Himself, and proceed from Himself.
Since to beget is different from being born, and to proceed is different from begetting or being born, it is clear that the Father is one, the Son is another, and the Holy Spirit is another.
Similarly, in the same work, at the beginning of chapter two.
In that Trinity, it is not unique to the Father alone that He was not born, but rather that He begot the one Son.
Nor is it unique to the Son alone that He did not beget, but that He alone was born from the essence of the Father.
Nor is it unique to the Holy Spirit that He was neither born nor begot, but that He alone proceeds from the Father and the Son in unchangeable eternity.
Also, in the same work, chapter eleven:
Hold firmly and do not doubt at all that the same Holy Spirit, who is one Spirit of the Father and the Son, proceeds from the Father and the Son.
For the Son says: "When the Spirit of truth comes, who proceeds from the Father" (John fifteen twenty-six), where he taught that it is his own Spirit, because he is the truth.
The prophetic and apostolic doctrine also teaches us that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son.
For Isaiah says about the Son: "He will strike the earth with the rod of his mouth, and with the breath of his lips he will kill the wicked" (Isaiah eleven four), about whom the Apostle also says: "Whom the Lord Jesus will kill with the breath of his mouth" (Second Thessalonians two eight).
The only Son himself signifies that it is the Spirit of his mouth, after his resurrection, when he breathed on his disciples and said, "Receive the Holy Spirit" (John twenty twenty-two).
About the mouth of the Lord Jesus, John says in Revelation that a double-edged sword comes out (Revelation one sixteen).
The Spirit of his mouth is the same; it is the sword that proceeds from his mouth.
Similarly, in the dispute among the letters of Augustine, he had against Pascentius, count of the Arians, with Lawrence presiding as the judge chosen by both parties.
Behold what "homoousion" (of the same substance) is, which is unjustly reproached.
For it is not just a word, but the meaning within the word: not just a sound heard by the ears, but the belief in the one substance of God in our minds.
If God is believed to dwell entirely in those who believe in Him, how can it be that the Father does not also fully encompass the Son, or the Son the Father?
Therefore, the Son remains in the Father, and the Father in Him, and the Holy Spirit is believed to have proceeded not only from the Father or the Son but also to always proceed to accomplish the works of the Trinity.
The same thing, that the Holy Spirit is in the Father and the Son, is said in the book he wrote against Pagans, Jews, Manichaeans, Sabellians, and Arians.
We have spoken about the Father and the Son as much as we could and to the best of our ability,
if indeed we were able to do anything worthy.
We have been silent about the Holy Spirit, but not because we overlooked Him.
For whatever we have said about the Father and the Son, we have also said about the Holy Spirit.
For He is in them and with them, equal, one true God, not lesser or a third God.
Why should I continue to speak, tired to those who are already tired?
Whoever separates the Holy Spirit from the Father and the Son in eternity and substance or communion, and denies that He is the Spirit of the Father and the Son, is full of an unclean spirit and devoid of the Holy Spirit.
For this reason, God is called love
First John four eight
because He does not divide unity into parts, but ineffably unites the Trinity.
For the Trinity itself is one God, a tower of strength from the face of the enemy, who guards those who believe in Him forever and ever.
Also, the Holy Spirit is from the Father and the Son and is equal, of the same substance, and co-eternal with the Father and the Son, as taught in the first book Chapter 4, on the Trinity, which is God.
All those I have read, who wrote before me on the Trinity, which is God, the Catholic interpreters of the old and new divine books, intended to teach according to the Scriptures that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are of one and the same substance with inseparable equality.
This suggests the divine unity, and therefore they are not three gods, but one God.
Even though the Father begot the Son, and therefore the Son is not the Father, and the Son was begotten by the Father, and therefore the Father is not the Son, and the Holy Spirit is neither the Father nor the Son, but only the Spirit of the Father and the Son, also equal to the Father and the Son, and pertaining to the unity of the Trinity.
Likewise, in the same book, Chapter 8, it is stated that the Holy Spirit is inseparably of the Father and the Son.
Given this, it is foolish not to profess that He proceeds from the Father and the Son.
Finally, due to this inseparability, it is sometimes sufficient to mention only the Father or only the Son to fill us with joy through His presence.
Neither is separated from the Spirit of both, that is, the Spirit of the Father and the Son.
This Holy Spirit is properly called the Spirit of Truth, which this world cannot receive, as stated in the Gospel of John, Chapter 14, Verse 17.
This is indeed our full joy, beyond which there is nothing greater, to enjoy the Trinity of God, in whose image we were made.
Therefore, it is sometimes said that the Holy Spirit alone is sufficient for our happiness.
He alone is sufficient, as He cannot be separated from the Father and the Son.
Just as the Father alone is sufficient because He cannot be separated from the Son and the Holy Spirit.
And the Son is also sufficient alone because He cannot be separated from the Father and the Holy Spirit.
Similarly, in the third book in the preface, it is stated that the Holy Spirit was sent by the Father and the Son.
When it was time to show that the Son is not lesser than the Father because the Father sent Him and that the Holy Spirit is not lesser than either because He is sent by both as it is read in the Gospel, we undertook this inquiry: The Son was sent to where He was because He came into this world and He was in this world and likewise, the Holy Spirit was sent to where He was because the Spirit of the Lord filled the whole world.
And what contains all things has knowledge of the voice as stated in Wisdom Chapter 1, Verse 7.
Likewise, it clearly teaches in the fourth book, Chapter 20, that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son just as from the Father.
When the Father is known by anyone through time, He is not said to be sent, for He does not have one from whom He is or from whom He proceeds.
Wisdom says: "I came out of the mouth of the Most High" (Ecclesiasticus 24:5), and it is said of the Holy Spirit that He proceeds from the Father (John 15:26), but the Father proceeds from no one.
Just as the Father begot and the Son was begotten, so the Father sent and the Son was sent.
But as He who begot and He who was begotten are one, so He who sent and He who was sent are one, because the Father and the Son are one.
The Holy Spirit is also one with them, because these three are one.
Just as being born is to the Son as being from the Father, so being sent is to the Son as being known to be from Him.
And just as being the gift of God is to the Holy Spirit as proceeding from the Father, so being sent is to be known to proceed from Him.
We cannot say that the Holy Spirit does not proceed from the Son; it is not in vain that the same Spirit is called the Spirit of the Father and the Son.
Nor do I see what else He meant when, breathing on the disciples, He said: "Receive the Holy Spirit" (John 20:22).
That breath, proceeding physically from the body, was not the substance of the Holy Spirit, but a sign that the Holy Spirit proceeds not only from the Father but also from the Son.
Who in their right mind would say that the Holy Spirit given by breathing was one and another whom He sent after His ascension?
There is one Spirit, the Spirit of God, the Spirit of the Father and the Son, the Holy Spirit, who works all things in all.
Also, in the same book six (Chapter 10), it is said that the Holy Spirit is the sweetness of the Father and the Son.
Therefore, whoever denies that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both must also deny that sweetness proceeds from the Father and the Son.
So that love, delight, happiness, or blessedness-if it can indeed be expressed worthily in any human words-has been briefly called "use" by him.
In the Trinity, it is the Holy Spirit, not begotten, but the sweetness of the begetter and the begotten, abundantly and generously pouring over all creatures according to their capacity.
This allows them to maintain their order and rest in their places.
Therefore, all these things that are made by divine art show a certain unity within themselves, as well as beauty and order.
For whatever of these things exists, is also one thing.
Likewise, in the fifteenth book, Chapter Seventeen, it states that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son.
I don't know why, just as wisdom is called both the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, and altogether they are not three but one wisdom, love should also be called both the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, and altogether one love.
In this way, the Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Spirit is God, and altogether they are one God.
Yet, it is not in vain that in this Trinity, only the Son is called the Word of God, only the Holy Spirit is called the gift of God, and only the Father is spoken of as the one from whom the Word is begotten and from whom the Holy Spirit primarily proceeds.
I added "primarily" because it is also found that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son.
But the Father gave this to the Son, not when He already existed and did not yet have it, but whatever He gave to the only begotten Word, He gave by begetting.
Thus, He begot Him in such a way that the common gift would also proceed from Him, and the Holy Spirit would be the Spirit of both.
Therefore, this distinction of the inseparable Trinity should not be taken lightly, but carefully considered.
Likewise, in the same book, Chapter 26.
In the supreme Trinity, which is God, there are no intervals of time to question whether the Son was born from the Father first, and then the Holy Spirit proceeded from both.
The Holy Scripture says He is the Spirit of both.
The Apostle says: "Because you are sons, God sent the Spirit of His Son into our hearts" (Galatians 4:6).
The same Son says: "For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father speaking through you" (Matthew 10:20).
Many other divine testimonies prove that He is the Spirit of the Father and the Son, properly called the Holy Spirit in the Trinity.
The Son also says: "Whom I will send to you from the Father" (John 15:26), and in another place, "whom the Father will send in my name" (John 14:26).
That He proceeds from both is taught because the Son says: "He proceeds from the Father." When He rose from the dead and appeared to His disciples, He breathed on them and said: "Receive the Holy Spirit" (John 20:22), showing that He also proceeds from Himself.
He is the power that went out from Him and healed them all (Luke 6:19).
As to why, after His resurrection, He first gave the Holy Spirit on earth and later sent Him from heaven, I believe this gift of God spreads love in our hearts.
This love enables us to love God and our neighbor according to the two commandments on which the whole law and prophets depend.
Signifying this, the Lord Jesus gave the Holy Spirit twice: once on earth for the love of neighbor, and again from heaven for the love of God.
Likewise, in the same book and chapter, it says:
Can we then ask whether the Holy Spirit had already proceeded from the Father when the Son was born, or had not yet proceeded and only proceeded from both after the Son was born, where there are no times?
Just as we could ask, where we find times, whether the will first proceeds from the human mind so that what is discovered is called offspring: because that will, which is already brought forth or generated, is completed, resting in its purpose, so that what was the desire of the seeker becomes the love of the enjoyer: which now proceeds from both, that is, from the begetting mind and from the generated notion, as from parent and offspring.
These things cannot be questioned there, where nothing begins in time to be completed subsequently in time.
Therefore, whoever can understand the generation of the Son from the Father without time, let them understand the procession of the Holy Spirit from both without time.
And whoever can understand in what the Son says: "Just as the Father has life in Himself, so He has granted the Son to have life in Himself" (John 5:26), that the Father did not give life to the Son who already existed without life, but generated Him without time so that the life the Father gave to the Son by begetting Him is co-eternal with the life of the Father who gave it: let them understand that just as the Father has in Himself that the Holy Spirit proceeds from Him, so He has granted the Son that the same Holy Spirit proceeds from Him, and both without time.
And thus it is said that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father, so that it is understood that He also proceeds from the Son, being from the Father and the Son.
For if the Son has everything from the Father, the Son certainly has from the Father that the Holy Spirit proceeds from Him.
But no times are considered there, which have a before or after, because there are absolutely none there.
Therefore, how could it not be most absurd to say that the Son is of both, when just as the generation from the Father grants the Son essence without beginning of time, without any change of nature, so the procession from both grants the Holy Spirit essence without any beginning of time, without any change of nature.
Therefore, since we do not say that the Holy Spirit is begotten, we also do not dare to say He is unbegotten, lest anyone suspect that there are two Fathers in the Trinity or two who are not from another.
The Father alone is not from another, and hence, He alone is called unbegotten-not in the Scriptures, but in the custom of those who debate and speak as best they can on such a profound matter.
The Son, however, is born of the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds principally from the Father and, without any interval of time, jointly from both the Father and the Son.
The Son would be called the Son of both the Father and the Son if, which is against the sense of all sound minds, both had begotten Him.
Therefore, He is not begotten by both, but proceeds from both as the Spirit of both.
However, in that co-eternal, equal, incorporeal, ineffably immutable, and inseparable Trinity, it is extremely difficult to distinguish generation from procession.
For now, it is enough for those who cannot grasp more to accept what we have previously said before the ears of the Christian people on this matter and have written down.
Among other things, when I taught through the testimonies of the Holy Scriptures that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both: If, therefore, I said, the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son, why did the Son say He proceeds from the Father (John 15:26)?
Why do you think, except that as usual, He refers to Him even what is His own, from whom He Himself is.
Hence, it is said: My teaching is not mine, but His who sent me (John 7:16).
If, therefore, His doctrine is understood here, which He said is not His own but the Father's, how much more should it be understood there that the Holy Spirit proceeds from Him too, where He says He proceeds from the Father, without saying He does not proceed from me?
From whom does the Son have to be God, for He is God from God; surely He has it from Him that the Holy Spirit also proceeds from Him: and therefore the Holy Spirit, to proceed from the Son as He proceeds from the Father, has it from the Father Himself.
Here, it is understood, as much as we can comprehend, why it is not said to be born but rather to proceed.
The Holy Spirit, if He were also called the Son, would be considered the son of both, which is absurd.
No son is of two people unless it's from a father and a mother.
We shouldn't suspect such a thing between God the Father and God the Son.
A human son doesn't proceed simultaneously from both a father and a mother.
He proceeds from the father into the mother, and then into the world from the mother, not from the father again.
But the Holy Spirit does not proceed from the Father into the Son, and from the Son to sanctify the creature.
Instead, He proceeds from both at the same time.
The Father has given the Son the ability to proceed from Himself, just as He proceeds from the Father.
We cannot say the Holy Spirit is not life since the Father is life and the Son is life.
Just as the Father, having life in Himself, gave the Son to have life in Himself, He also gave Him to have life proceeding from Him, just as He proceeds from the Father.
I have transferred these words from that speech into this book, speaking to the faithful, not the unfaithful.
If they find it difficult to contemplate this image and understand its truth, they should know these three aspects are not three persons but are all part of one man, who is one person.
Why not believe what is in the sacred scriptures about the highest Trinity, which is God, rather than demand a clear reason that our slow and weak human minds cannot grasp?
And certainly, when they believe the Holy Scriptures as the most truthful witnesses, let them pray, seek, and live well, so they may understand, as much as their minds can, what is held by faith.
Likewise, in the homily on John (Tract 99 on John), someone might ask whether the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son as well.
The Son is the Son of the Father alone, and the Father is the Father of the Son alone.
But the Holy Spirit is not the Spirit of just one of them, but of both.
You have the Lord Himself saying: "For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father who speaks in you" (Matthew 10:20).
You also have the Apostle saying, "God sent the Spirit of His Son into our hearts, crying out" (Galatians 4:6).
Are there two Spirits, one of the Father and another of the Son?
By no means, for he says, "There is one body," referring to the Church, and immediately adds, "and one Spirit" (Ephesians 4:4).
See how he completes the Trinity: "Just as you were called to the one hope of your calling; one Lord," clearly referring to Christ, and then he also names the Father. Therefore, it continues: "One faith, one baptism, one God and Father of all, who is over all and through all and in all." So, just as there is one Father and one Lord, that is the Son, there is also one Spirit, certainly of both. Christ Jesus Himself says, "the Spirit of your Father who speaks in you," and the Apostle says, "God sent the Spirit of His Son into our hearts" (Matthew 10:20; Galatians 4:6).
The same Apostle says elsewhere: "If the Spirit of Him who raised Jesus from the dead dwells in you" (Romans 8:11).
Here he clearly meant the Spirit of the Father, about whom he says elsewhere: "Anyone who does not have the Spirit of Christ does not belong to Him" (Romans 8:9).
Many other testimonies clearly show that the Spirit, who is called the Holy Spirit in the Trinity, is of both the Father and the Son.
I do not think it is for any other reason that He is specifically called the Spirit, since if we are asked about each individually, we can only say that both the Father and the Son are spirit, because God is spirit, that is, God is not a body, but spirit (John 4:24).
So, what we often refer to as a single entity should actually be understood as the one in whom the community of both appears.
Why, then, should I not believe that the Holy Spirit also proceeds from the Son, since he is also the Spirit of the Son?
If the Holy Spirit did not proceed from him, he would not have breathed on his disciples after the resurrection, saying: "Receive the Holy Spirit" (John 20:22).
What else did that breath signify if not that the Holy Spirit also proceeds from him?
This relates to what he said about the woman suffering from a flow of blood: "Someone touched me, for I perceive that power has gone out from me" (Luke 8:46).
The term "power" also refers to the Holy Spirit, as is clear from the passage where the angel responded to Mary, saying, "How will this be, since I do not know a man?" He replied: "The Holy Spirit will come upon you, and the power of the Most High will overshadow you" (Luke 1:34).
The Lord himself, promising the Holy Spirit to his disciples, said: "But stay in the city until you are clothed with power from on high" (Luke 24:49), and again, "You will receive power when the Holy Spirit has come upon you, and you will be my witnesses" (Acts 1:8).
The same author, in the book The City of God, chapter 24 of book 13, states that the Holy Spirit belongs to both the Father and the Only Begotten, and is one of both.
Given this, there is no doubt that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both.
Therefore, when the Lord breathed on them saying, "Receive the Holy Spirit" (John 20:22), He clearly intended us to understand that the Holy Spirit is not only of the Father but also the spirit of the Only Begotten.
For it is the same Spirit of both the Father and the Son, with whom there is the Trinity: Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, not a creature, but the Creator.
The breath that came from the mouth of flesh was not the substance and nature of the Holy Spirit, but rather a sign to help us understand, as I said, that the Holy Spirit is common to both the Father and the Son, because they do not each have their own separate spirits, but one Spirit is common to both.
Fulgentius explains that only the Father begot the Son, only the Son was begotten by the Father, and only the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
He details this in the third book he wrote against Fabian.
Indeed, we truly profess that only the Father begot the Son, only the Son was born of the Father, and we also affirm that only the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
Likewise, in the fifth book against the same Fabian, I have, as succinctly as possible, explained why we refer to the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit as one God.
I have indicated a certain aspect of divine knowledge within the image of God, where memory, intelligence, and will are not separate and distinct persons.
This image is created, not born, made, not begotten.
Just as we see a certain distinction of terms in this one image, we can understand the distinction of persons in the one divinity.
The unity in nature shows that the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit are one God.
The distinct properties of each person demonstrate that the Father is one, the Son is another, and the Holy Spirit is another.
The Father is distinct not because He is God, but because He is the Father.
The Son is distinct not because He is God, but because He is the Son.
Similarly, the Holy Spirit is distinct not because He is God, but because He is the Spirit of both the Father and the Son.
Therefore, the Father is distinct because He begets, the Son is distinct because He is born of the Father, and the Holy Spirit is distinct because He proceeds from the Father and the Son.
Yet, we do not have three Gods, but one God: the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit.
Unity does not confuse the Trinity, nor does the Trinity separate unity.
What is distinguished in the property of persons is shown to be one in the natural communion of one essence.
Additionally, in the seventh book of the same work, it is stated:
"For he will not speak on his own, but he will speak whatever he hears, and he will announce to you what is to come."
John 16:13.
First, it shows that the Holy Spirit has nothing other than what belongs to the Son. Then, to show that everything that belongs to the Father is also his, it adds:
"Everything that the Father has is mine; therefore I said that he takes from what is mine and will announce it to you."
John 16:15.
Let us first consider what was said: "For he will not speak on his own, but he will speak whatever he hears."
But who can comprehend what the speech of that simple nature is like, or what the hearing is like, where hearing is the same as being?
Therefore, the Holy Spirit hears whatever the Father and the Son say, and he says these same things, just as the Son sees what the Father does and does the same things.
In that nature, where there is the highest and true simplicity, the Son sees what the Father does, and the Holy Spirit hears what the Son says with the Father.
Through the communion of natural essence, the Son was born from the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
Therefore, for the Holy Spirit to hear is to proceed from the nature of the Father and the Son, and for him to speak is to ineffably communicate this to our hearts through grace.
Similarly, in the same book:
"And no one will snatch them out of my hand. My Father, who has given them to me, is greater than all, and no one can snatch them out of the Father's hand. I and the Father are one." John 10:28.
This is the voice that his sheep hear; they understand that no one can snatch them from the hand of the Son or the Father. In hearing that he and the Father are one, they recognize the true unity of essence between the Father and the Son.
This is the voice of the Son, and this is the speech of the Holy Spirit, because the Son is born of the nature of the Father, and from there the Holy Spirit proceeds. The Holy Spirit also hears from the Father and the Son, because he proceeds from both with equal divinity.
Therefore, the Holy Spirit does not speak of himself, because he naturally speaks from the Father and the Son, from whom he proceeds and has the truth of origin.
This relates to what he said:
"He will glorify me because he will take from what is mine and declare it to you. All that the Father has is mine; therefore I said that he will take from what is mine." John 16:14.
How well did the truth itself uphold the truth of its teaching! If he had not said this, he would have shown that the Spirit is only his own. But by saying "All that the Father has is mine; therefore I said that he will take from what is mine," he showed that the Holy Spirit is one with both the Father and himself.
He maintained the same understanding in a previous passage, saying:
"The Helper, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, he will teach you all things and bring to your remembrance all that I have said to you." John 14:26.
The Father sends, but in the name of the Son; the Spirit sent by the Father teaches, but the Son speaks.
This is also demonstrated where the Lord says:
"But when the Helper comes, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth, who proceeds from the Father." John 15:26.
Behold, here is the Paraclete, whom the Father sends in the name of the Son.
The Son himself sends Him from the Father.
He sends the Spirit of truth from the Father because He is the truth.
The Father sends Him in the name of the Son because He is one Spirit of the Father and the Son.
The Son sends Him from the Father because He proceeds from both the Son and the Father.
Likewise, the Spirit of the Father, who is the Spirit of truth, is received from the Son.
All that the Father has is also the Son's, which the Holy Spirit received.
He proceeds not from the Father alone, nor from the Son alone, but from both together.
Moreover, the term "procession" from the Father is not granted to any creature, showing that this property belongs only to the divine essence. We read that the Son was begotten of the Father, and although He is called the only begotten, natural generation is shown. Nevertheless, because of the grace of adoption, God the Father has also begotten us voluntarily by the word of truth.
Therefore, the only begotten Son is the one and only Son born of the Father's essence. But we too are called sons of God by adoption, and born of God, as the blessed Evangelist says:
John
1:12:
"But as many as received Him, to them He gave the power to become the sons of God, even to those who believe in His name, who were born not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God."
Therefore, since divine words show that we are both sons of God and born of God, no one can teach that the term "procession" from God has been granted to any creature. Why so? Because natural birth shows the only begotten Son to be true God, not adopted, nor of a different nature, but consubstantial with the Father.
However, no creature is said to proceed from God, so that He who proceeds from the Father and the Son is believed to be God, just as the Father and the Son are. This property of procession from the Father and the Son belongs only to the Holy Spirit, whose nature is common with the Father and the Son.
He indeed proceeds from the Father and the Son, but he does not depart, nor is he in any way lesser or subordinate.
He proceeds inseparably and wholly from the infinite Father and the infinite Son.
Thus, he cannot be commanded regarding what he speaks, just as he cannot be commanded regarding the marvelous works he performs.
In the same work, Book Eight.
The Son is sent by the Father, not the Father by the Son, because the Son is born of the Father, not the Father of the Son.
Similarly, the Holy Spirit is also read to be sent by the Father and the Son, because He proceeds from the Father and the Son.
But since the term "sending" is not used in just one way in the Holy Scriptures, the Son is sent in the mystery of the Incarnation not only by the Father but also by the Holy Spirit, because the mediator between God and humans, the man Christ Jesus, is formed by the work of the entire Trinity. However, the Holy Spirit is sent in another way by the Father and the Son, as He naturally proceeds from the Father and the Son.
The Holy Spirit is sent by the Father and the Son when the effect of spiritual grace is given by the Trinity, the one God.
Also, in the ninth book of the same work, we recognize God the Father as the source, not of the entire Trinity, but specifically of the Son and the Holy Spirit.
The only-begotten Son originates from the Father through eternal birth, and the Holy Spirit originates from the Father through eternal procession.
However, natural unity implies that the Son, the creator, comes from the Father, the creator, by natural birth, and that the Holy Spirit, the creator, proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
Also, in the tenth book of the same work, after affirming the true divinity and humanity of the only Son of God, we declare our belief in the Holy Spirit.
The Holy Spirit is one spirit with the Father and the Son, proceeding from both, naturally remaining in both, and sharing the same divine truth as the Father and the Son.
Likewise, to show that the Holy Spirit is equal to the Father and the Son, the same Holy Spirit is sent by both the Father and the Son, and the Son is sent by the Father and the Holy Spirit, as testified in the second book, Book II to Monimus, Chapter 6, written to King Thrasamund.
Now we also need to consider why, if a sacrifice is offered to the entire Trinity, only the mission of the Holy Spirit is required to sanctify our offering.
It's as if, so to speak, God the Father Himself, from whom the Holy Spirit proceeds, could not sanctify the sacrifice offered to Him.
Or, as if the Son Himself could not sanctify the sacrifice of His own body, which we offer, since He sanctified His own body to redeem us.
It seems as though the Holy Spirit must be sent to consecrate the Church's sacrifice, as if the Father or the Son were absent from those offering the sacrifice.
First, we should remember that in the term "mission," the Holy Spirit should neither be considered inferior nor lesser. If He were lesser, He would certainly be inferior, and if He were inferior, He would certainly be lesser. We mention this because heretics frequently object to our faith, claiming that the Holy Spirit should be believed to be lesser than the Father and the Son because He is sent by them. However, if the sender is considered greater than the one sent, they will recognize their own deception. Just as the Holy Spirit is sent by the Father and the Son, the Son is also found to be sent by the Father and the Spirit. The Son Himself said this much earlier through the prophet and confirmed it with His own testimony after He was sent.
When He came to Nazareth and entered the synagogue, the book of the prophet Isaiah was given to Him to read. He unrolled the scroll to the place where it is written: The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, because He has anointed me to preach the gospel to the poor. He has sent me (Luke 4:18; Isaiah 61:1).
After returning the scroll, He testified to the truth of that prophecy with the present effect, saying, Today this scripture has been fulfilled in your hearing (Luke 4:21).
In another passage by the same prophet, he shows that he has been sent by the Lord and by His Spirit with these words:
"And now the Lord has sent me, and His Spirit," Isaiah 48:16.
He also announces that he will send the Holy Spirit to his disciples before his passion in this way:
"But when the Helper comes, whom I will send to you, the Spirit of truth who proceeds from the Father, he will bear witness about me," John 15:26.
Earlier, he also taught that the same Spirit is sent by the Father:
"But the Helper, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, he will teach you all things," John 14:26.
Therefore, the Son is sent by the Father and by the Spirit, and the Spirit is sent by the Father and the Son.
However, no Christian should understand the sending of the Son or the Holy Spirit as a physical movement from one place to another:
Rather, we should understand the mission as the work of the granted revelation.
For the Son was not sent physically, nor is the Holy Spirit sent physically, just as the Father's coming is not a physical movement to any place.
Bishop Hormisdas of Rome, regarding the Holy Spirit proceeding from the Father and the Son, writes this in a letter to Emperor Justin, against the blasphemies of Nestorius and Eutyches:
Let us worship the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit-the indistinct distinctly, the incomprehensible and inexpressible substance of the Trinity.
Although reason acknowledges the number of persons, the unity does not lose the distinction of essence.
We preserve the properties of the divine nature and the properties of each person, so that neither the individuality of the persons is denied in divinity, nor is this proper name transferred to the essence.
Great is the holy and incomprehensible mystery of the Trinity:
God the Father, God the Son, God the Holy Spirit-an undivided Trinity.
And yet, it is known that it is proper for the Father to generate the Son, proper for the Son of God to be born from the Father equally, and proper for the Holy Spirit to proceed from the Father and the Son under one substance of divinity.
Leo, the Roman bishop, says in his letter to Turibius, the bishop of Astorga, that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son.
In the first chapter, it is shown how wrongly those who assert that the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit are one and the same person view the divine Trinity.
As if the same one is sometimes called Father, sometimes Son, and sometimes Holy Spirit.
They do not believe that one is the Father who begets, another is the Son who is begotten, and another is the Spirit who proceeds from both.
Instead, they claim a singular unity in three names, but not in three persons, which is a type of blasphemy taken from the opinion of Sabellius.
Gregory, the Roman bishop, says in Homily 26 that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
He explains this clearly:
"As the Father has sent me, I also send you"
John 20:21,
meaning that I love you with the same love with which the Father loves me, even as I send you among persecutors. This can also be understood in terms of divine nature: the Son is said to be sent by the Father because He is begotten by the Father.
Likewise, the Holy Spirit, who is equal to the Father and the Son but was not incarnated, is also said to be sent by the Son, as He says:
"When the Advocate comes, whom I will send to you from the Father"
John 15:26.
If "to be sent" only meant to be incarnated, then the Holy Spirit could not be said to be sent, as He was never incarnated. Instead, His mission is His very procession from the Father and the Son. Therefore, just as the Spirit is said to be sent because He proceeds, the Son is also fittingly said to be sent because He is begotten.
After saying this, He breathed on them and said,
"Receive the Holy Spirit"
John 20:22.
We must ask why our Lord gave the Holy Spirit once while on earth and once while in heaven. The Holy Spirit is not shown to be given anywhere else except now through breathing and later when He came from heaven in various tongues. Why then is the Spirit given first on earth to the disciples and later sent from heaven? It is because there are two commandments of love: love of God and love of neighbor. The Spirit is given on earth to love our neighbor and from heaven to love God. Just as there is one love and two commandments, there is one Spirit and two givings: first by the Lord on earth, then from heaven. This teaches us that by loving our neighbor, we learn how to love God.
Also, in the same book of Moralia, chapter 28: If the spirit of prophecy were always present to the prophets, Nathan the prophet would not have given permission for something he would later deny to King David when asked about building the temple.
Hence, it is well written in the Gospel: "Upon whom you see the Spirit descending and remaining on him, this is he who baptizes" (John 1:33).
For the spirit comes to all the faithful, but it remains singularly and always in the mediator alone, because it never left his humanity, from whose divinity it proceeds.
Therefore, it remains in him, who alone can do all things always.
Likewise, in the same book, chapter twenty-nine, shortly after.
Among these gifts, without which one cannot reach life, the Holy Spirit always remains, whether in His preachers or in all the elect.
However, in those through whom our life is not preserved but the lives of others are sought, He does not always remain in the preachers.
Although He always guides their hearts to live well, He does not always display the signs of virtues through them.
Sometimes He withdraws these manifestations so that virtues can be held more humbly, as they cannot be truly possessed when on display.
However, the mediator between God and humans, the man Christ Jesus, always continuously has Him present in all things, because the same Spirit comes from Him by substance.
Therefore, it is rightly said that although He remains in the holy preachers, He uniquely remains in the mediator.
In the preachers, He remains by grace for a purpose, but in Him, He remains by substance for all things.
Likewise, in the same book, chapter twenty-six, it is stated that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and takes from what is of the Son, indicating that He also proceeds from Him.
I heard a voice like a gentle breeze Job 4:16.
What is meant by the voice of a gentle breeze, if not the knowledge of the Holy Spirit, who, proceeding from the Father and taking from what is of the Son, is softly infused into our weak understanding?
However, when He comes upon the apostles, He is shown through an external sound like a mighty wind, as it is said: Suddenly there came from heaven a sound like the rush of a violent wind Acts 2:2.
The Holy Spirit, when He reveals Himself to the weakness of human understanding, is expressed both by the sound of a mighty wind and the voice of a gentle breeze: because, indeed, He is both mighty and gentle.
Gentle, because He moderates His knowledge to our senses to the extent that we can comprehend it; mighty, because no matter how much He moderates this, by His coming He illuminates and disturbs the blindness of our weakness.
Isidore, in the seventh book of Etymologies, chapter three, says that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son as follows: The Holy Spirit is called God because He proceeds from the Father and the Son.
He is not called begotten, so there are not two sons in the Trinity.
He is not called unbegotten, so there are not two fathers in the Trinity.
Instead, He is said to proceed based on the Lord's testimony, saying, "I still have many things to say to you, but you cannot bear them now. But when the Spirit of truth comes, who proceeds from the Father, and will take from what is mine, He will teach you all things." This is from the book of John, chapter sixteen, verses twelve to thirteen. Here, He not only proceeds by nature but continually proceeds to accomplish the works of divinity. The difference between the Son being born and the Holy Spirit proceeding is that the Son is born from one, while the Holy Spirit proceeds from both. And so the Apostle says, "But if anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to Him." This is from the book of Romans, chapter eight, verse nine.
Also, in the same work, shortly after, therefore, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are the Trinity and unity.
The same is one, and the same are three: one in nature, three in persons: one because of the communion of majesty, three because of the property of persons.
The Father is one, the Son is another, the Holy Spirit is another: distinct, but not different in substance, because they are equally simple, equally unchangeable good, and co-eternal.
The Father alone is not from another, therefore He alone is called unbegotten: the Son alone is born of the Father, therefore He alone is called begotten: the Holy Spirit alone proceeds from the Father and the Son, therefore He alone is called the Spirit of both.
Likewise, in the book "Differences" (Book 2, Chapter 3), the distinction between the persons of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit is made in this way: the Father is neither made nor born, the Son is born but not made, and the Holy Spirit is neither born nor made, but proceeds from the Father and the Son.
Therefore, the Father has eternity without birth, the Son has birth with eternity, and the Holy Spirit has procession without birth.
The Father originates from no one, the Son originates from the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son.
However, what we say about the Trinity is as much as human understanding can grasp.
Who can fully comprehend the inner mysteries of the Trinity?
How the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are three persons with one nature; how the Father is unbegotten, the Son is begotten, and the Holy Spirit is neither begotten nor unbegotten, nor can be seen as a creature, but is uncreated; how the Son is born from the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son.
How the Son proceeds by being born, and the Holy Spirit proceeds without being born.
How the Father is never without the Son, and yet the Father begot the Son without the Son.
How the Son is never without the Spirit, and yet says:
"If I do not go away, the Advocate will not come to you" John 16:7.
How the Son is not from Himself, but from the Father, yet is not later than the one from whom He is. How the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son, yet is not preceded by those from whom He proceeds. How the three are one, and the one is three. How they are relatively three to each other but essentially one.
Who can consider these things, who can comprehend them? If we do not grasp the secrets of Christ's human birth, how will we grasp the mysteries of divine nature?
Also, in the book of Sentences (Book 1, Chapter 17): The Holy Spirit is the creator, just like the Father and the Word.
This is testified by the prophet, "The Spirit of the Lord made me, and the breath of the Almighty gave me life" (Job 33:4).
The Holy Spirit belongs to both the Father and the Son.
Therefore, the Father and the Son are one, because the Father has nothing that the Son does not have.
Something cannot proceed from and exist in two consubstantial beings at the same time unless they are one from whom it proceeds.
Prosper, in the book "On the Contemplative Life" (Book 1, Chapter 18), teaches that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son in this way.
According to the Apostle, it's not only necessary for us to set an example for the faithful, but also to instruct those who have been divinely entrusted to us about the Father- how He alone is to be understood as unbegotten; about the Son-how He alone is called begotten; and about the Holy Spirit-how He proceeds from the Father and the Son, and thus cannot be called unbegotten or begotten.
These three are one, and this one is not divided but distinguished into three.
The Son alone, born ineffably from the Father alone, took on a whole human being without any change in His own substance, proving Himself to be true God and true man through His virtues and sufferings.
He allowed Himself to be captured, willed to be killed, rose on the third day, and by His own power lifted the human being taken up from us into heaven.
By the example of His resurrection, He provided us, reborn into Him, with the hope of happily rising again.
He made us His members, threatened punishment to those who do not believe in Him or who withdraw from Him, and promised the heavenly kingdom to those who adhere to Him.
These and other things the priest must know to teach, and the people must believe to understand what is taught.
As the Apostle says: "Unless you believe, you will not understand" (Isaiah 7:9).
Hence, it is understood that understanding does not come from belief, but belief from understanding.
It is not the one who understands who believes, but the one who believes who understands, and the one who understands acts rightly.
Bishop Vigilius of Africa demonstrates that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son in these words found in the book he wrote in Constantinople in defense of Pope Leo against the Eutychians.
Similarly, some might question the Trinity, arguing that since certain things are proper to the Father, which do not pertain to the Holy Spirit, and certain things are proper to the Son, which do not pertain to the Father or the Holy Spirit, and also certain things are proper to the Holy Spirit, which do not pertain to the Father or the Son, they accuse Catholics of worshipping three separate gods.
But so that you are not disturbed by this unexpected question, hear this: the dispensation of the assumed man pertains not to the Father, nor to the Spirit, but to the Son alone.
For it is proper to the Son, not the Father, to be born of a virgin.
Again, the voice often heard, "This is my beloved Son" Matthew 3:17, pertains not to the Son nor to the Holy Spirit, but to the Father alone. Similarly, the appearance of the dove at the Jordan, and the distribution of the tongues of fire, are shown to pertain properly to the person of the Holy Spirit.
But so you do not still doubt about these properties, listen more clearly. It is proper to the Father to have begotten, proper to the Son to have been born, and proper to the Holy Spirit to proceed from the Father and the Son. And what is proper to each person is not at all transferred to another person.
So, if these three persons, each having their own properties by which they are more clearly distinguished, not separated, make one God; how is the Son, with the properties of both natures preserved, not one Christ?
Proclus, the bishop of Constantinople, in a letter to the Armenians against heretics, teaches that the Holy Spirit proceeds inseparably from the essence of divinity with these words:
Let us flee the deceitful plans, the dangerous streams of heretics, and the harmful contagion against God.
The madness of Arius, who divides the inseparable Trinity into substances.
The audacity of Eunomius, who confines the incomprehensible nature within human knowledge.
The rage of Mani and Macedonius, who separate the Holy Spirit from the essence of divinity, though it proceeds inseparably.
Agnellius, in a letter to Nennius, teaches that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son in this way:
"Therefore, the Son is from the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son.
And, as some say, God does not have two sons, Christ and the Holy Spirit, but rather has an invisible Son, just as He is invisible.
The Son took on the body of our frailty to become visible, not to cease being invisible, but so that in Christ, He would remain invisible to the unbelieving."
For when it is said, "Blessed are the eyes that see what you see" Luke 10:23, then all the Jews, including those who crucified Him, were blessed, about whom it is said through David: "They have seen and observed me" Psalm 22:17.
You see, therefore, that He remains invisible and is seen with a pure and believing mind: therefore, if the Father is invisible, the Son is invisible, and the Holy Spirit is invisible.
And to bring you back to this point, from where it is made that we teach this from a frail human, these three invisible, indivisible, and united things, overflowing with the efficacy of virtue, that is, the generative voice of the word, with the word proceeding together with the voice, the efficacy that makes one consul and another killed, tell me, Arian, are these three one or not?
If they are not one, separate the voice from the word, and the efficacy from the voice and word.
But if in a frail human these three are indeed one, the voice, the word, and the efficacy; they are three persons, but one power of subsistence.
Even in the most fragile human, as we've mentioned, there is great power.
Imagine how much more power there is in God, the Almighty Father, the begetter of the Son, from whom the Holy Spirit also proceeds.
Cassiodorus, in his exposition of Psalm 50, explains that the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
He says, "Restore to me the joy of your salvation, and uphold me with a willing spirit" (Psalm 50:14).
It's not by chance that the holy man, enlightened in heart, mentioned the Spirit three times.
He devotedly asked the indivisible Trinity for forgiveness.
The Spirit, in terms of divine essence, is rightly called one God along with the Father and the Son.
However, to distinguish the persons, it is proper for the Father to have eternally begotten the Son.
It is proper for the Son to have been begotten by the Father, and for the Holy Spirit to proceed from both the Father and the Son.
Their ineffable love and cooperation, being of the same substance, eternal, and powerful, accomplish everything they will in heaven and on earth.
Although these concepts are incomprehensible and inexplicable to us now, some fathers propose an analogy using physical and coexisting things.
In the sun, we find three properties: its physical substance, which is the sun itself; its brightness, which remains in it; and the heat that reaches us from its brightness.
If any likeness of such a great mystery can be found, consider this: the physical substance of the sun is like the person of the Father in the Trinity.
The brightness of the sun is like the person of the Son in the Trinity, as the Apostle says, "The brightness of his glory" (Hebrews 1:3).
And the heat of the sun is like the person of the Holy Spirit in the Trinity, as it is written, "Who can hide from its heat?" (Psalm 19).
Another example comes from incorporeal things, such as the soul, which is known to be made in the image and likeness of God.
The soul is its own incorporeal rational substance, in which intellect and life reside.
To understand the substance of the soul, think of it like the person of the Father in the Trinity.
Think of the soul's power and knowledge as the Son in the Trinity, who is the power and wisdom of God.
And consider the soul's life-giving property as the Holy Spirit in the Trinity, through whom the act of giving life is proclaimed in many places.
As the Apostle Peter says in his letter: "Put to death in the flesh, but made alive in the spirit" First Peter 3:18.
Likewise, the Apostle says: "The letter kills, but the Spirit gives life" Second Corinthians 3:6.
And in the Gospel, the Lord says: "It is the Spirit who gives life; the flesh profits nothing" John 6:64.
These things we have mentioned are never found separately, even though we can understand them as distinct. They are so naturally united that when one is present, all three appear together.
Through these similarities, we get a glimpse of the truth of such a profound matter.
These and other similar arguments are discussed by the Fathers.
What our current limitations prevent us from fully understanding will be clearer when the blessed see the divinity in its full majesty.
Anyone who wants to know more should keep reading the works of Saint Hilary, Saint Ambrose, and Saint Augustine.
This topic is as significant to discuss as it is vast.
Blessed Jerome also explained the Trinity clearly and concisely against heretics in this psalm.
Also, in Psalm 61: "For from Him comes my salvation" (Psalm 61:4).
This refers to the only-begotten Son, who is salvation for those who believe.
When it says "from Him," it signifies the Son. The holy Trinity is unique in that the Father is unbegotten, the Son is begotten, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son. This is what complete faith and the Catholic Church professes.
You rightly profess to be subject to God, from whom you testify to have received an inestimable benefit. To honor the holy word with equal veneration, pay attention to what follows: "For He is my God and my salvation: my helper, I will not be moved anymore" (Psalm 61:3).
Previously, it was said that the author of salvation was begotten by the Father.
Now, this salvation is embraced by a triple confession.
First, so that you do not believe Him to be lesser, it says: "He is my God," just as it says above about God the Father. The equality of the highest name shows the substance and power of unity.
Hence, Father Augustine in the fifteenth book, chapter 3, on the Trinity says: Given the reason to the understanding, it is clear that in the substance of truth, not only is the Father not greater than the Son, but neither are both together anything greater than the Holy Spirit alone. Nor are any two in the same Trinity greater than one, nor are all three together anything greater than each individual. Thus, he demonstrated the perfect and singular nature of the holy Trinity with miraculous truth.
Prudentius, in his book against the Marcionists, Harmartigenia, verse 931, written in heroic meter.
O God, creator of all, giver of the soul,
O God Christ, from whose mouth proceeds the one Spirit of God.
Similarly, in the Book of Hymns, Cathemerinon, hymn 6, verse 5, written in iambic meter:
O power of this Trinity, one light, eternal God from God, God sent from both.
Similarly, in the book of Hymns hymn 5, verse 5, in the choriambic meter, which is called Asclepiadean:
O kind leader, inventor of the radiant light,
Who divides time into certain intervals,
When the sun is submerged, horrid chaos looms,
Christ, return light to your faithful.
In the same book, verse 157:
Through Christ, your Son, Highest Father,
In whom visible glory stands before you,
Who is our Lord, your Only Son,
Breathes the Paraclete from the Father's heart.
Through whom splendor, honor, praise, and wisdom,
Majesty, goodness, and your piety
Continue the kingdom in the triple name,
Weaving ages through eternal ages.