Sermon One: On the Passing of Saint Isidore
Isidore, an exceptional man, was born in Carthage to his father, Severian.
He served as the bishop of the Church of Seville, following in the footsteps of his brother, the holy Bishop Leander.
This blessed man dedicated himself to the study of literature from a young age.
He was educated in Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, proficient in all forms of speech, eloquent, exceptionally talented, and renowned both in life and teaching.
Advancing from virtue to virtue, he shone as a distinguished teacher.
His eloquence made him suitable for educating everyone, whether they spoke Latin, Greek, or Hebrew, regardless of their level of wisdom or intelligence.
This remarkable man was so wise, learned, and holy that it is rightly said of him: Behold a great priest who in his days pleased God and was found just.
(Ecclesiasticus Chapter Forty-Four and Chapter Fifty)
The title of priest comes from Greek and Latin, referring to one who gives sacred things.
Just as a king is named for ruling, a priest is named for sanctifying and dispensing sacred things.
Someone becomes a great priest for two main reasons: first, by living well, and second, by teaching well.
Even if an ecclesiastical teacher lives well, he is not great unless he also teaches well.
Likewise, if he teaches well but does not live well, he is not truly great.
Therefore, it is essential to teach while leading a good life, as teaching without a good life makes a teacher arrogant, and a life without teaching renders a teacher ineffective.
This is why the Lord says in the Gospel: Whoever breaks one of the least of these commandments and teaches others to do the same will be called least in the kingdom of heaven.
But whoever practices and teaches these commands will be called great in the kingdom of heaven.
(Matthew Chapter Five)
In this context, the kingdom of heaven refers to the congregation of the elect.
Scripture often refers to the Church of the faithful as the kingdom of heaven because, as it yearns for heavenly things, the Lord already reigns within it as if in heaven.
So, whoever breaks one of the commandments of our Lord Jesus Christ, meaning those who don't fulfill them in action and teach others to do the same, will be considered the least in the kingdom of heaven, which is among the faithful.
It's like saying: Anyone who neglects my commandments and instructs others to neglect them will be deemed the least, meaning they will be imperfect in the holy Church.
The Lord mentions this elsewhere: "They say and do not do" Matthew twenty-three.
It goes on: But whoever acts on my commandments and teaches others to do so will be great, meaning worthy in the holy Church.
Therefore, a priest's preaching must be backed by actions, so what he teaches with words, he also demonstrates through example.
This is supported by what's written in the Song of Solomon: "Look, Solomon's bed is surrounded by sixty strong men, the mightiest of Israel, all holding swords and well-trained in battle; each keeping his sword by his side because of the night terrors" Song of Solomon three.
Solomon means peaceful. So, who is Solomon if not Christ, about whom it is written: "He is our peace, who has made both one" Ephesians two.
Solomon's bed, representing the holy Church of Christ, is a place that withdraws from worldly worries, continuously purifying the heart from earthly contamination through repentance, and striving towards the heavenly homeland, creating a resting place where Christ finds delight.
Thus, he kindly tells his disciples: "Behold, I am with you all days, even to the end of the world" Matthew twenty-eight.
And again, through the prophet, he says: "I will walk among you and be your God, and you will be my people" Leviticus twenty-six.
The sixty strong men surrounding Solomon's bed symbolize the leaders of the Church, who safeguard it with words and examples, defending against visible and invisible enemies through prayers and preaching.
He says, "All are holding swords and are well-trained in battle."
What does the sword symbolize, if not the word of God?
And what do the hands holding the sword signify, if not action?
Clearly, when people fulfill the word of God through actions they know in their hearts, they become more learned, defeating the Church's enemies with wisdom and strength.
They are the most skilled in spiritual battles because they know how to cut away vices, first in themselves and then in those they guide.
They excel in battles because they practice God's commands, which they preach through their words.
They are wise and skilled because they use the sword of discretion to remove excesses in themselves and those under their care, as well as the pleasures of this world.
It is fittingly said: Each one's sword is on their thigh because of night terrors.
What does the sword represent, if not the rigor of conduct?
And what does the thigh represent, if not the desire of the flesh?
Therefore, the leaders of the Church who have reached the perfection of virtues always carry the sword on their thigh.
They constantly break the desire of the flesh with rigorous conduct.
This ensures that the enemy they fear in the night of this world does not come suddenly and find them weak and negligent in God's work.
Otherwise, they and those under their care could be easily deceived by the softness of pleasure and delight of the flesh, leading them to more serious sins.
Therefore, he who is called great in the kingdom of heaven, that is, in the Church, is the one who fulfills with good works what he preaches with words.
Thus, let it be said of blessed Isidore: Behold the great priest who, in his days, was pleasing to God and was found righteous.
Truly great, because he fulfilled the works of God that he preached with words through deeds.
Rightly, indeed, he is called a great priest whom God raised up in Spain in recent times after so many deficiencies.
I believe, to restore the wisdom of ancient men, which had nearly disappeared from human minds due to great antiquity.
Lest the Christian people grow old in ignorance and rusticity any longer.
Thus, full of love and wisdom, he did not hide in the ground the talents entrusted to him.
But he distributed them to all in common, and as a good merchant, returned them doubled to the Lord.
As it is written in the book of Matthew.
Just as Gregory was the successor of the apostle Peter, the blessed Isidore followed the apostle James, inspiring many to seek heavenly things through his preaching.
He nurtured the seed of eternal life sown by the blessed James with his teachings.
Like one of the four rivers of paradise, he lit up all of Spain with his good works and holiness, shining like a brilliant lamp.
In the vision of the four creatures, the prophet Ezekiel says:
"And the appearance of the creatures was like burning coals of fire, and like lamps" (Ezekiel 1).
These four creatures symbolize the multitude of saints.
Their likeness to burning coals and shining lamps signifies that those connected with holy people are inspired by their example and teaching, igniting a love for the Creator.
There is, however, a difference between coals and lamps: coals burn but do not dispel darkness.
Lamps, with their bright flames, illuminate the surrounding darkness.
Many saints live simple, hidden lives, so quietly that their lives are barely known to others.
These saints are like coals, warm in spirit but not visible enough to light up the darkness of sins in others' hearts, as they keep their lives private.
They are kindled inwardly but do not serve as a guiding light for others.
Though they burn with divine love, they do not inspire others through their example or preaching.
Lamps, however, cast their light far, shining from one place to another.
Those who shine through their good works and preaching spread their reputation like a lamp.
When neighbors hear of their goodness, they are inspired to love heavenly things.
When they reveal themselves through good works, they shine like the light from lamps.
Thus, when holy men inspire those around them to love the heavenly homeland, they are like coals; and when they illuminate those far away to keep them from falling into the darkness of their sins, they become lamps for their journey.
Appropriately, they are called lamps, as they set examples of virtues and demonstrate the light of good work to others through their life and words.
Truly, they shine like lamps, as they repel the darkness of error from sinners' hearts through the love of the Creator and the flame of good preaching.
Someone who lives well in secret but does not benefit others is like a coal; however, one who, placed in the Church, provides the light of righteousness to many through the example of holiness is a lamp, as they burn for themselves and shine for others.
Thus, this most blessed man is rightly compared to a shining lamp, as he illuminated both those present and absent through the word of preaching and the reputation of holiness, and kindled them to the love of the heavenly homeland.
He is fittingly compared to a burning lamp, as he burned with love for God and neighbors, and dispelled the darkness of sins from others' hearts.
Whoever approached him received the light of truth through constant vision and conversation and the example of good works, and burned with the desire for eternal light.
This most blessed man, among other works of holiness wisely conducted in the Church of Christ, confounded and destroyed the malignant heresy of the Acephalites, who denied two substances in Christ and proclaimed one nature in his person, asserting he was not truly God and the Son of God, but merely a pure man.
After overcoming Gregory, the leader of the aforementioned heresy, and convicting him with the authority of the holy Scriptures' testimonies, he taught that there were two natures in Christ, divine and human.
The divine nature, in which he is always co-eternal and co-equal with God the Father; the human nature, in which he, for our salvation, became the Son of Man, that is, of the Virgin, temporarily.
What can I say about his holiness and wisdom?
Words alone can't fully capture all the good that God bestowed upon His Church through him, nor how beneficial he was to those who were ignorant and to the aging world.
He unveiled the ages of the world and the timeline of events in his Chronicles.
"Chronicles" in Greek refers to what we call the timeline of events in Latin.
In Greek, "chronos" translates to "time" in Latin.
He revealed the timeline of events and the ages of the world to those who were unaware, explained the sacred laws, clarified ecclesiastical duties and ranks for priests, established rules for kings and princes, discouraged greed among judges, and instilled Christian discipline among citizens and all the faithful.
He wrote about the names, types, duties, and causes of things that were obscure and almost forgotten by people, covering matters both divine and human.
He thrived in wisdom and holiness during the reigns of Emperors Maurice and Phocas, and under King Reccared of the Goths.
He was generous in giving, exceptional in hospitality, firm in heart, truthful in judgment, just in decisions, persistent in preaching, cheerful in encouragement, diligent in winning souls for God, careful in interpreting Scriptures, wise in counsel, humble in appearance, moderate at the table, devout in prayer, distinguished in honesty, and notable in every virtue.
He was a father to the clergy, a comforter to the sorrowful, a protector of orphans and widows, a relief for the oppressed, a defender of citizens, a persecutor of heretics, and a hammer of the proud.
What more can I say?
He became a mirror of all good things to the world, and we believe he now reigns with Christ, without end.
He passed away during the time of Emperor Heraclius and King Suintila of Spain. This was the same Heraclius who restored and exalted the Lord's Cross, which the impious King Khosrow had taken away, back to its place in Jerusalem.
Blessed Isidore departed this life in the year 655.
Sound in doctrine and wise in counsel, he excelled beyond everyone else and was full of charitable works.
He was laid to rest at a ripe old age.
Meanwhile, dear brothers, it is fitting that we earnestly ask this most holy confessor to be our constant intercessor before God for us, as we are miserable sinners still in danger of losing our souls.
Through his sacred merits and prayers, may we join the company of God's chosen ones after this life.
By his grace, who lives and reigns as God in perfect Trinity, forever and ever.
Amen.
Second Sermon: On Saint John the Baptist
Isaiah the prophet was a noble man filled with God's grace, whose holiness and remarkable life were so profound that he wore just a single garment made of haircloth.
Later, he put this aside to cover himself with sackcloth for the people's sins, as mentioned in Isaiah Chapter Twenty-One.
He spoke more openly than others about the mysteries of Christ and the Church, to the point where he could be considered more of an evangelist than a prophet.
In today's reading, inspired by the Holy Spirit, he said among other things:
"The Lord called me from the womb, from my mother's belly he remembered my name," as found in Isaiah Chapter Forty-Nine.
Although, dear brothers, these words from the prophet Isaiah specifically refer to Christ alone, because Christ is the head of the Church, and the Church, meaning all the faithful, is the body of Christ, what is said about the head, that is, Christ, can also appropriately apply to the members.
So, let's repeat what we've proposed:
"The Lord called me from the womb, from my mother's belly he remembered my name."
It's clear that this was said about Christ when the archangel Gabriel spoke to Joseph about the virgin birth:
"And you shall call his name Jesus, for he will save his people from their sins," as written in the Book of Matthew Chapter One.
This also suitably applies to the blessed John, as one chosen from among Christ's members.
This is evident through holy Elizabeth, who testified that her son leapt for joy within her womb at the Savior's arrival, saying to the most blessed Mary:
"For behold, as soon as the voice of your greeting reached my ears, the babe leaped in my womb for joy," as recorded in the Book of Luke Chapter One.
The same archangel Gabriel also indicated this when, before John was born, he announced his name and life, mentioning his great virtue:
"And he will be filled with the Holy Spirit, even from his mother's womb."
Truly, he was the most blessed of all children who, while still in his mother's womb, was filled with the Holy Spirit and joyfully showed that the Savior of the world was present, even though he could not yet speak.
This aligns well with what Jeremiah prophesied about John:
"Before I formed you in the womb, I knew you, and before you came out from the womb, I sanctified you, and I appointed you a prophet to the nations" (Jeremiah 1).
It continues with:
"And He made my mouth like a sharp sword" (Isaiah 49).
The mouth of God the Father is primarily Christ, through whom God was revealed to the world.
Our Lord Jesus Christ speaks to the Father in the Gospel, saying:
"I have made your name known to the people you gave me" (John 17).
John also served as the mouth of Christ, announcing Him to the earth.
The holy apostles were the mouth of Christ as well, preaching Him to the nations:
"And He made my mouth like a sharp sword."
This sharp sword symbolizes Christ, as with the breath of His mouth, He will slay the wicked (Isaiah 11).
The Gospel speaks of this sword:
"I did not come to bring peace, but a sword" (Matthew 10).
It's as if to say: I came to separate the wicked from the good and to divide children from their parents.
He says,
"I came to set a man against his father, a daughter against her mother, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law, and a man's enemies will be the members of his own household" (Matthew 10).
The Apostle clarifies what this sword is:
"Take the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God" (Ephesians 6).
The sword of the Holy Spirit is what the Holy Spirit gives.
The word of God is a double-edged sword, teaching about the temporal and the eternal: offering consolation in the Old Testament and promising perfection in the New, striking and dividing whatever it touches in this world.
John also wrote about this sword in Revelation, saying:
"From the mouth of the Son of Man, that is, Christ, came a double-edged sword" (Revelation 1),
meaning from the mouth of those who preach.
The holy teachers are the mouth of Christ, like John, the apostles, and other preachers.
From them, as they reveal the mysteries of Christ, the double-edged sword emerges, that is, the divine word; just as a sword separates the soul from the body, so the divine word separates a person from worldly and carnal love.
A double-edged sword came out of Christ's mouth, cutting through both physical and spiritual faults, whether according to the New and Old Testament, or according to the letter and the spirit, or according to divinity and humanity.
Similarly, a sword sharp on both sides cuts through the faults of both the preacher and the listener, as it's written in the Psalm: "Gird your sword upon your thigh, O mighty one." Psalm Forty-Five.
It's fitting that the church preacher is instructed to gird a sword on the thigh, so that when addressing faults in others, he first seeks to control his own impulses.
Therefore, anyone who wishes to correct others' faults must first address their own excesses, as we read that the apostle Paul said: "I discipline my body and keep it under control, lest after preaching to others I myself should be disqualified." First Corinthians Nine.
Hence the Lord says in the Gospel: "Hypocrite, first take the plank out of your own eye, and then you will see clearly to remove the speck from your brother's eye." Matthew Seven.
The apostle Paul also says: "You who teach others, do you not teach yourself? You who preach against stealing, do you steal? You who say that people should not commit adultery, do you commit adultery?" Romans Two.
And the Lord in the Psalm says: "You who hate discipline and cast my words behind you, why do you recite my statutes and take my covenant on your lips?" Psalm Fifty.
Alas for me, miserable one, who does not remove the heaviest planks from my eyes, yet notices the small specks in my brothers' eyes! I do not correct my gravest sins, yet I rebuke my brothers for minor faults.
Still, I urge you, dearest brothers, not to hesitate to hear the words of the Holy Spirit because of my wrongdoings and numerous negligences, for the Lord tells preachers: "It is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father speaking through you." Matthew Ten.
Therefore, do not disregard the words of God that you have heard from me, but strive to fulfill them with good deeds.
Now, let's return to the matters we have proposed.
Blessed John, wanting to set an example for church preachers, first practiced what he would later preach.
This way, his listeners couldn't accuse him of any faults.
He disciplined his body by living in solitude, rejecting luxury, wearing rough clothing, and abstaining from wine or anything intoxicating.
He was content with simple food and completely disregarded worldly riches.
By living a life of strict virtue, he ensured that his rebuke of the wicked nation came without personal blame for indulgence.
Strengthened by God's grace, he boldly reproached the people for their misdeeds.
"Brood of vipers," he says, "who warned you to flee from the coming wrath? Produce fruit in keeping with repentance. Why? Because the axe is already at the root of the trees. Every tree that does not produce good fruit will be cut down and thrown into the fire" (Matthew chapter three).
True repentance is shown by those who, having sinned greatly, work tirelessly to produce the fruit of good deeds.
The greater the sin, the more one must strive for good works through repentance.
He also says: "In the shadow of his hand he hid me" (Isaiah chapter forty-nine).
Christ was especially protected by God's power, as the angel told the Virgin Mary: "The Holy Spirit will come upon you, and the power of the Most High will overshadow you" (Luke chapter one).
This divine power shielded the blessed Virgin from the heat of vice, strengthening her with virtues so completely that she never sinned in thought, word, or deed.
Thus, blessed Augustine says: When I discuss sinners, I affirm that this most blessed Virgin and the one born from her are without sin.
Similarly, blessed John the Baptist is undoubtedly protected by God's grace, because he could not be overcome in either favorable or adverse conditions, as if he were fortified by the invincible shield of that same grace.
Prosperity did not lift him up, nor did adversity break him, as confirmed by the testimony of Truth, which praised him by asserting that he was not a reed shaken by the wind as stated in the Gospel according to Matthew, chapter eleven.
Hence, John is rightly interpreted as the grace of God.
It follows: "He made me like a chosen arrow" as written in the book of Isaiah, chapter forty. In saying "chosen arrow," it is shown that God has many arrows. However, among many arrows, Christ is specifically chosen as one arrow; just as among many sons, He is the unique and only begotten son. With this arrow, in the Song of Songs, the bride recalls being wounded, saying: "I am wounded by love" as found in the Song of Songs, chapter two.
The other arrows of the Lord are the prophets and apostles, who spread throughout the world, about whom the Psalm sings: "Your arrows are sharp, peoples will fall under you, in the heart of the king's enemies" from Psalm forty-five. And again: "The arrows of the mighty are sharp with burning coals" as mentioned in Psalm one hundred and twenty. In sacred Scriptures, arrows signify the same as a sword; arrows are called the preachings or words of God. However, arrows and swords seem to differ in that a sword strikes nearby, while arrows are shot further.
Thus, the incomprehensible power of God is demonstrated, which no one can avoid, whether they are far or near. These arrows are sharp because they penetrate to the division of body and soul. Thus, the Apostle says: "The word of God is living and effective and more penetrating than any two-edged sword, and reaching to the division of soul and spirit, joints and marrow, and discerning the thoughts and intentions of the heart" as written in the book of Hebrews, chapter four.
Indeed, the word of God is both effective and alive.
The Son of God, who many unbelievers think is dead, accomplishes everything He declares.
It's sharper than any double-edged sword because, unlike a physical sword that cuts the body, it penetrates deeply, even dividing soul and spirit with its own power.
In the Holy Scriptures, the soul often represents life, as it is said: "He who loves his soul will lose it" (John, Chapter Twelve).
This suggests that anyone who loves this present life will lose eternal life.
Here, the soul refers to carnal vices, actions of the body like lust, theft, robbery, and similar behaviors.
In contrast, the spirit refers to spiritual vices, such as pride, greed, envy, and other mental inclinations.
The word of God also reaches the division of joints and marrow, acting as a discerner of thoughts and intentions of the heart.
Joints represent interconnected thoughts, while marrow signifies the most secret and intimate intentions of the heart.
Thus, the divine word separates them, discerning the nature of each thought and intention.
Often, our thoughts might be good, but our intentions could be bad.
We might think of both good and bad things.
In these matters, the divine word never mistakes good for evil or vice versa.
Therefore, it discerns thoughts and intentions, understanding what each person does and the mindset behind it.
As the Psalmist says: "God examines the hearts and minds" (Psalm, Chapter Seven).
Thoughts reside in the heart, while pleasures are in the mind.
Therefore, God examines the hearts because He knows what each person thinks; He also examines the minds because He understands where each person's greatest delight lies, whether in purity or in lust.
John is often called a chosen arrow for good reason.
He was not only chosen alongside other saints through Christ before the world was formed, but he was also announced by an angel at his conception, greeted and sanctified by Christ in his mother's womb, and undoubtedly chosen.
As blessed Maximus states, his special election was so remarkable that he was worthy to announce the Lord even before he was born or could speak.
Regarding this most blessed man, the Lord says in the Gospel: "He was a burning and shining lamp" (John, Chapter 5); burning with love and shining through his words.
Filled with love for God and his neighbors, he burned with passion; filled with the Holy Spirit, he shone through his preaching.
Through his love for God, he yearned for heavenly things; through his love for his neighbors, he enlightened their minds with good teachings.
Through his devotion to God, he disregarded earthly things and longed for heavenly ones; through his love for others, he illuminated people's minds with words of encouragement.
In his love for God, he disciplined his own body; in his love for others, by condemning evil and announcing the coming of the Son of God, he lifted people's hearts to heaven.
However, dear brothers, John the Baptist did not display the brilliance of his virtues at home with his parents, but publicly, in the sight of everyone.
He didn't shine at home, but out in the open.
Let us compare him, if you will, to the Chalcedony stone.
This stone is the third of the twelve precious stones on which the heavenly city of the great King, Jerusalem, is founded and adorned (Revelation, Chapter 21).
It's said that this stone doesn't shine indoors, but outside under the open sky, in the brightness of the day.
It emits a glow like a pale, burning lamp.
Therefore, because it doesn't shine indoors, it represents those who do their good deeds in secret, as the Lord says in the Gospel: "Let not your left hand know what your right hand is doing" (Matthew, Chapter 6).
This Chalcedony stone may not shine indoors, but outside in the open, it symbolizes those who, driven by unavoidable circumstances, step into the public eye.
There, either willingly or unwillingly, they feel compelled to display their good works to others.
This is why it is written: "Let your light shine before others, so that they may see your good deeds and glorify your Father who is in heaven." (Matthew 5:16).
This blessed man was among those individuals.
While he lived in his parents' home, he hid his good deeds out of humility.
But once he began preaching, he illuminated the entire province, indeed the whole Church, paving the way for the Lord and lifting people's minds from earth to heaven.
Dear brothers, as we reflect on the virtues of blessed John the Baptist, we must examine ourselves both internally and externally, and cleanse our sins with daily tears.
God has set before us the examples of the holy Fathers, so that by following in their footsteps, with the help of the Holy Spirit, we may earn eternal joy.
Therefore, ignorance can no longer be an excuse for sin, because God's law reaches our ears daily, and the example of the holy Fathers constantly encourages us to do good.
Now, the voice of the turtle dove has been heard in our land (Song of Solomon 2), meaning the voice of the apostles and holy Fathers, urging us to live well through their words and examples.
So, dear brothers, we must pray to God that the virtues He has prepared as a crown for His saints may benefit us and not be a source of punishment.
They will benefit us if we desire to imitate these numerous and great examples of virtue.
Therefore, beloved, let us pray to God with full devotion, that through the intercession of blessed John the Baptist, He may inspire us to fear and love Him, keep all His commandments, and after our death, enter the heavenly kingdom, where He lives and reigns as God in perfect Trinity through all ages of ages.
Amen.
Sermon Three: On the Assumption of Saint Mary
The Virgin Mary was taken to the heavenly chamber where the King of kings sits on a starry throne.
Mary is called the illuminator because she is the gateway to eternal light, through which light has risen for those sitting in darkness and the shadow of death.
She gave birth to the Son of the eternal Father, who enlightens everyone coming into this world.
Mary is also known as the star of the sea because through her, this vast sea, representing the present age, is illuminated.
For those of us navigating it, she points the way to the harbor of eternal rest.
Like a bright star, she enlightened the human race, showing us the right path amidst the darkness and storms of this turbulent sea, guiding us to the shore of perpetual stability.
Mary is also called Lady in the Syrian language.
It's quite fitting to call her lady because, through the Lord whom she bore, she is the lady in both heaven and on earth.
Indeed, she is called lady in heaven and on earth because all things serving Christ are devoted and reverent to her.
Truly, she is the lady in heaven and on earth because from the beginning, she was foreshadowed in figures and enigmas by the patriarchs and prophets, as revealed by the Holy Spirit and foretold.
From her birth, she was guarded and accompanied by holy angels who greeted her with reverence.
Moreover, she was gloriously overshadowed by God the Father as a bride, endowed with heavenly gifts, illuminated and filled by the Holy Spirit, and consecrated by Jesus Christ her Son with the integrity of perpetual virginity, as shown by the evangelists.
Even John the evangelist, to whom Christ entrusted her from the cross, cared for her until the end of her life, faithfully and devotedly attending to her needs.
It is believed that after her passing, he laid her to rest in a mausoleum in the middle of the valley of Josaphat.
Mausoleums are tombs or monuments of kings, named after Mausolus, king of the Egyptians.
After the death of Mausolus, his wife, the queen, constructed a tomb over his body that was immense in size and remarkable in beauty.
It was so extraordinary that all significant monuments of kings and princes in the Eastern regions are now called mausoleums, after King Mausolus.
This brings to mind what the archangel Gabriel foretold to the most holy Virgin Mary:
"Hail," he said, "Mary, full of grace, the Lord is with you" (Gospel of Luke, Chapter 1).
Indeed, grace was abundant in Mary, who was so devoutly served by heavenly and earthly beings.
As mentioned earlier, Mary was full of grace, enabling her to bear the Son of the eternal Father and to overcome all the wickedness of heretics, magicians, and philosophers.
It was fitting that such magnificent gifts be bestowed upon this most august Virgin.
She was enriched with gifts and full of grace, receiving respectful angelic service.
She brought glory to the heavens, God to the earth, restored peace, spread faith to the nations, put an end to vices, brought order to life, and discipline to customs.
She gave glory to the heavens when the angel announced Christ to the shepherds, and immediately the angelic choir sang glory to God in the highest, declaring that peace was granted to men of good will on earth.
God blessed the earth by giving us His Son, the Almighty, who redeemed us from the enemy's grasp with His precious blood and freed us from the threat of eternal damnation.
He brought peace by reconciling humanity with God and calling the angels to share in this peace.
He brought faith to the nations, as those who had long served idols in ignorance of the true God were converted to faith and knowledge of their Creator through His birth.
He ended sins because through baptism and the mystery of Christ's sacred body, the faithful are freed from both original and actual sin, as long as they renounce the works of the devil and faithfully follow the gentle guidance of servitude to Christ.
He brought order to life by organizing His Church and establishing leaders, commanding the lesser to obey the greater.
As the Apostle Paul says: "Whatever is ordained is ordained by God, and whoever resists authority resists God's ordinance" (Romans, Chapter 13).
He instilled discipline in morals because Christ, born of her, imposed penance on sinners.
Thus, those who fall into sins and vices after baptism and stain the garment of innocence can find forgiveness through pure prayers, tears, fasting, and other good works.
As the Lord Himself says through the prophet: "I do not want the death of the sinner, but rather that he should turn and live" (Ezekiel, Chapter 18).
Truly, in this most noble Virgin was full grace, through whom the holy Church received such great and countless blessings.
How can we adequately praise her, through whom we have merited the pledge of eternal salvation?
What thanks can we offer her, through whose birth we found the entrance to the heavenly kingdom?
What can we say in her praise that surpasses the divine and angelic proclamations already extolled and glorified?
Human words fall short when it comes to praising this most holy and glorious Virgin.
Our lives don't match hers, our eloquence is lacking, and our knowledge is insufficient.
Heaven is in awe, the earth is astonished, reason is ignorant, and the human mind cannot comprehend.
Yet every creature marvels at what is announced to her through the archangel Gabriel and what is fulfilled in her through Christ.
In the Song of Songs, the Holy Spirit, speaking on behalf of the heavenly citizens and marveling at her ascension, says: "Who is this that rises from the desert like a column of smoke, perfumed with myrrh and incense?"
(Song of Solomon 3:6).
She ascended through the desert of this world like a column of smoke, for she was slender and delicate, refined by heavenly disciplines, such as abstinence, fasting, vigils, and prayers.
Her conversation was no longer on earth but in heaven.
The Holy Spirit admired her as this most blessed Virgin was exalted above the choirs of angels.
The desert is referred to as desolate.
She ascended through the desert because she had already abandoned the present world with her whole mind.
She yearned for the heavenly homeland with all her devotion, despising earthly things and directing all her desires toward heaven.
Since she saw nothing sweet in the lower realms, she turned her whole heart to love the things above, despising worldly wealth along with all harmful greed, and aimed for the invisible.
Thus, she ascended through the desert because she abandoned the world with her entire intention.
Hence, she is said to have ascended like a column of smoke because she left behind the fragrance of a good reputation and the example of perfection for the holy Church.
She encouraged everyone she could to live by her example, to despise earthly things, and to love heavenly ones.
She especially urged virgins to preserve the integrity of mind and body, to avoid the temptations of mortal nature, and to faithfully await Christ with the lamps of good works lit until the day of their death.
The sweet fragrance of her perfect life was so compelling that countless people, both men and women, were inspired to follow her example.
They chose to set aside marriage and having children, dedicating themselves to Jesus Christ, her heavenly bridegroom, through her most sacred teachings.
It continues: "Like a column of smoke," she says, "from the scents of myrrh and incense" (Song of Solomon, Chapter Three).
It's important to note that this smoke is said to come from the scents of myrrh and incense.
Myrrh is used to anoint the bodies of the dead to prevent decay, while incense is burned in a censer to release a fragrance.
This most glorious Virgin, by mortifying her flesh to avoid the decay of sin and by denying all worldly pleasures through self-restraint, applied myrrh to her dying body.
She ensured, as much as possible, that after death, it would remain free from eternal corruption.
As she cast aside all unnecessary thoughts from her heart's chamber, she made her heart like a censer before God.
By gathering virtues through the love of God and neighbor, she equipped herself with the coals of fire in the censer, setting herself ablaze with the fire of charity before God.
As she sent fervent and pure prayers to God, she drew out the smoke of aromas from the censer, which smelled sweet before God, and she never stopped inspiring others to love God through her good examples.
Again, the Holy Spirit, marveling about her in the same Song, says: "Who is this that rises like the dawn, beautiful as the moon, chosen as the sun, terrible as an army with banners?" (Song of Solomon, Chapter Six).
The souls of the saints wondered with joy who this could be, surpassing even the dignity of the angels.
"Who is this," he says, "that rises like the dawn?" because the ever-Virgin Mary, leaving behind the darkness of corruption, shone brightly in her ascent with a newness of incorruption and eternal immortality.
"Beautiful as the moon, indeed more beautiful than the moon; for the moon sometimes waxes and sometimes wanes."
This passage highlights how the holy Church shines without any flaw of corruption, and within it, the eternal happiness continues to glow.
It's fittingly compared to the sun because the sun of righteousness chose her to be born from it.
As the prophet David says:
"He has set a tent for the sun" Psalm 19.
In this most blessed Virgin, symbolized by the sun, he prepared his dwelling. She is described as formidable as an army in battle formation because, during her ascension, she was surrounded by angelic choirs and accompanied by the spirits of the chosen.
We believe that on this day, all the heavenly hosts, along with the angelic ranks, joyfully greeted the blessed Mother of God, Mary, surrounding her with immense light. They led her with praises and spiritual songs to the throne that God had predestined for her before the world's foundation.
Therefore, let no one doubt that at the assumption of this glorious Virgin, all of heavenly Jerusalem rejoiced with indescribable joy. It was filled with immeasurable love and celebrated her presence with deep gratitude. As far as we can understand, Jesus Christ himself joyfully welcomed her and placed her with him in the glory of the Father.
Meanwhile, dear brothers, it is appropriate, as divine grace allows, to adorn ourselves with good morals and cleanse our hearts of sins and vices. This is so we may always properly praise God during this feast of the ever-Virgin Mary, for the path of our salvation lies in the praises of God.
Thus, the divine word says in the Psalms:
"A sacrifice of praise shall honor me" Psalm 50.
Specifically, the sacrifice of a contrite heart and a chaste body; the sacrifice of a pure mind and pure praise honors God. And there is the path, where I will show him the salvation of God.
On this journey, we don't walk with our feet, but with good morals.
It's not about physical steps, but about good deeds.
We complete it by engaging our bodies in holy actions and devoting our minds to praising God.
It's a glorious journey that leads those who praise to the Creator of heaven and earth.
A magnificent path that brings a person to eternal joys.
However, dear friends, we can't find this journey unless God deems us worthy to see it.
Therefore, we must urgently pray to God to show us the path of His praise, through which we seek to reach Him.
Since we are unworthy by our own merits to obtain what we seek, let's ask for help from the most glorious Queen of heaven and earth.
With her sacred prayers assisting us, we may be deemed worthy to reach the heavenly kingdom through the path of praises and see the Savior of God, reigning in the glory of the Father; who grants this, living and reigning with the same Father and the Holy Spirit in perfect Trinity, God forever and ever.
Amen.
Sermon Four. Two On the Nativity of Saint Mary.
The Israelites had forty-two stations, marking their journey from Egypt to the promised land.
In a similar way, Christians should strive to leave behind their worldly lives and reach their heavenly homeland.
It's fitting that we enter the kingdom of heaven through this number, as it symbolizes how our Lord reached Mary the Virgin from Abraham, akin to reaching the overflowing Jordan, rich with the Holy Spirit's grace.
Matthew the evangelist illustrates this in his Gospel, noting that there were forty-two generations from Abraham to Christ.
Matthew 1.
Through these generations, Christ descended from Abraham through David to Mary, choosing to incarnate for our salvation.
Mary, emerging from this royal lineage, is believed to support us with her prayers.
Thus, the Virgin Mary is always associated with royal lineage, descending from King David's line.
By nature, she came from royal ancestry, and by grace, God adopted her as His daughter.
Born of royal heritage in the flesh, she is also a daughter through God's adoption.
She gave birth to Christ, both God and man, yet Christ also created her.
So, she is both mother and daughter; mother, because she gave birth to God and man; daughter, because God created her to be born from her.
She is noble by her earthly lineage, but even more so through God's grace.
While she was glorious as King David's descendant, she is even more glorious as God's chosen one.
She is noble by her parents, but even nobler by her character; noble by her family, but even nobler by her holiness.
Why?
Because from childhood, with God's grace guiding her, she began to turn away from earthly things and embrace heavenly ones.
From the very start of her life, illuminated by divine grace, she focused on ignoring the visible and seeking the invisible.
She feared God with love and loved Him with reverence; she kept her words in check, turned away from indulgent foods, avoided the gaze of others, and aimed to please God more than people in her appearance and actions.
Moreover, she avoided anger and hatred like a deadly plague; she turned away from all worldly temptations.
She held firmly to her faith; no foolish teachings misled her, no false beliefs corrupted her, no depravity deterred her from righteousness, and no injustice separated her from God's love.
She refrained from everything forbidden by the law; she carefully avoided all that Scripture prohibits.
Every day, she dedicated herself to prayer, earnestly seeking God day and night, staying vigilant in praising God during the night watches.
She was grounded in humility, considered herself the least, called herself a servant of God, and worked diligently to be worthy in God's eyes.
She showed simplicity in her walk, purity in her movements, dignity in her gestures, and honesty in her demeanor.
But who can truly describe the perfection of her holiness?
Her entire life was filled with virtues; truly free from sins and vices.
The Holy Spirit illuminated her, strengthened her with virtues, filled her with the abundance of God's blessings, and purified her from all worldly desires, so that she loved God above all and clung to Him with complete devotion.
So much so that, driven by the desire for divine love, hardly anyone could match her in good deeds.
She grew so much in virtues among all the people of the Jews, setting an example of good works, that it can rightly be said of her: As a thorn produces a rose, so Judea produced Mary.
Judea is aptly compared to thorns because it consistently provoked God through its actions.
Scripture fittingly likens the Jewish people to thorns, as they inflicted painful wounds, cruelly shedding the blood of prophets and those close to them.
This is why the Lord says to them in the Gospel:
"Jerusalem, Jerusalem, you who kill the prophets and stone those sent to you."
Matthew Chapter Twenty-Three.
Elijah also expressed this complaint to God, saying:
"Lord, they have torn down your altars and killed your prophets, and I am the only one left, and now they are trying to take my life."
First Kings Chapter Nineteen.
This was also symbolized when the Lord appeared to Moses in the burning bush. The flame was in the bush, among the thorns, yet the bush was not consumed.
Exodus Chapter Three.
The bush represents the sins of the Jews, while the flame represents the law of divine commandments; just as the flame did not burn the bush, so too did the law not consume the sins of the Jews.
It is fitting, therefore, that the Virgin Mary is said to have arisen as a rose among thorns; although she came from Jewish ancestry, she remained free from sins and vices by God's grace. She provided perfect examples of conduct to both men and women. Just as a rose beautifies thorny bushes, she adorned Judea and indeed the entire Church. While she maintained herself through love of God and neighbor with all gentleness and patience, keeping innocence and purity in word and deed, and considering all earthly things as nothing, she was like a fragrant rose to those around her, offering them the sweet scent of a good reputation.
Thus, it is fitting that the Holy Spirit says in the Song of Songs:
"Like a lily among thorns, so is my beloved among the daughters."
Song of Solomon Chapter Two.
In sacred discourse, the daughters refer to those who are negligent and lukewarm in their love for God; as they nurture effeminate behaviors, having lost their masculine dignity, they are called by a feminine name for how they are inwardly perceived.
They recognize Christ only with their words, but their actions are driven by worldly concerns, which is why they are rightly called daughters, not sons.
Thus, it's fitting to say that the most blessed Virgin Mary is like a lily among thorns.
Even though she came from human frailty, descended from a mortal lineage, and emerged from a flawed nature, she elevated herself to heavenly beauty by rejecting the corruption of human life.
By turning away from the darkness of Jewish customs, she kept her heart and body pure.
By letting go of pride, she settled in the valley of humility, refreshing those around her, and indeed all the faithful, with the fragrance of her good reputation.
Therefore, she is rightly esteemed as a lily because from her youth she cherished the purity of virginity and maintained a cleanliness of mind, which allowed her to please Almighty God above all virgins, as Scripture says:
"God chose her and preferred her" (Psalm 132).
He selected her above other virgins and favored her with a unique dignity and love.
For there has been no one before or after who could be compared to her.
As the blessed Jerome also notes, she is found first among the foremost ranks of the great King.
She is called the first among all virgins of the great King, not only in time but also in dignity and holiness.
She is preeminent in the court of the great King because she is blessed above all virgins and indeed above all women.
Truly, she is blessed above all women because she was the first to offer the glorious gift of virginity to God.
She is deemed first in the court of the great King because she aspired to live an angelic life on earth.
Thus, the Prophet says: "Virgins will be brought to the King after her; her companions will be brought to you" (Psalm 45).
Other virgins will be presented to the Lord King, not in the first place, but in the second, as none will match her in holiness or reward.
The virgins dedicated to God will be brought to the King of Heaven, not at the same time but after her, because no one, no matter how holy or worthy, can be equal to her in reward.
Other virgins consecrated to God can follow her, but they cannot be her equals, because this most noble Virgin is a lady among servants, a queen among sisters, a teacher among virgins.
Without a doubt, she is the teacher of holy virgins because she provided them with examples of how to live well.
She is also their mother because she gave birth to them through the example of holy virtues.
Thus, Scripture says: Each person is called their child if they follow their teaching.
Surely, she is not only the mother and teacher of virgins but also of all holy women, because she was chosen and blessed by God above all women.
To her, the Holy Spirit says in the Song of Songs:
"You are completely beautiful, my friend, and there is no flaw in you" (Song of Solomon, Chapter 4).
But since it is written: "No one is without sin, not even an infant whose life is one day old on earth" (Job, Chapter 14); what does it mean that this most holy Virgin is called completely beautiful, in whom there is no flaw?
Elsewhere it is read: "The stars are not pure in the sight of God" (Job, Chapter 25).
And elsewhere: "In many things, we all offend" (James, Chapter 3).
And the apostle John says: "If we claim that we have not sinned, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us" (First John, Chapter 1).
Yet the most blessed Virgin Mary is proclaimed by the Holy Spirit as completely beautiful and without flaw, just as she is praised by the holy Fathers, which is not believed of any other saint.
Appropriately, the Holy Spirit proclaims her without flaw, because He completely purified her from sin in advance, liberated her from the root of sin, and entirely cleansed her from all unlawful thoughts; to such an extent that she later had no opportunity to sin at all.
Hence, the blessed Augustine says: With the exception of the most sacred Virgin, if all the saints and holy women were gathered together and asked whether they had sin, what would they answer except what John says?
If we claim to be without sin, we're only fooling ourselves, and the truth isn't in us.
However, this most glorious Virgin was uniquely blessed and filled by the Holy Spirit,
so she could bear the fruit of her womb, whom all creation has recognized as Lord from the beginning.
Therefore, it's fitting to call her, without any doubt, completely beautiful and without blemish.
Into her womb, the Word of the Father, through whom all things were made, chose to descend.
There, for the salvation of the whole world, He mercifully joined our humanity to Himself.
Still, she was completely beautiful and without blemish, in whose womb the Son of God
took on our flesh, in which He suffered for our redemption as He intended.
With this,
He powerfully defeated the ancient enemy and plundered hell, even though He descended there in spirit alone.
He carried its spoils to the heavens on the fortieth day after His resurrection, placing her, as we believe,
in eternal happiness.
Undoubtedly, she was completely beautiful and without blemish, who attained the dignity of motherhood
without losing her virginal purity.
The Virgin gave birth because she conceived as a virgin.
Blessed is that fruitfulness, which by giving birth illuminated the world, inherited the heavens,
restored what was lost by angels and humans, and yet preserved the veil of virginity.
Happy is that womb,
which knew how to produce without human seed and remained untouched by corruption.
Indeed, this ever-Virgin is happy and most worthy of all praise, having brought forth the heavenly bread,
that is, Christ, to the world, from whom the holy angels are nourished in heaven.
She herself brought forth the living bread to the world, from which the souls of the faithful are fed;
and yet she did not lose the seal of virginity.
Hence, it is said in the same Songs: A garden enclosed, a fountain sealed.
Your shoots are a paradise.
Song of Solomon chapter 4.
Indeed, it is a garden of delights, where all kinds of flowers and the fragrance of holy virtues
are planted: so perfectly enclosed that it cannot be violated in any way,
nor can it be corrupted by any thoughts or schemes of deceit.
A garden is aptly called enclosed because, while it inspires many through good examples, it also produces beautiful flowers like a blooming garden.
The fountain is sealed with the seal of the entire Trinity, from which flows the fountain of life, nourishing angels in heaven by itself and refreshing the faithful so they do not grow weary on the journey of this world.
Regarding this fountain, the Lord himself says in the Gospel:
"Whoever drinks the water I give them will never thirst."
John Chapter 4.
Additionally, the offspring of that womb, namely Christ, is the paradise of all heavenly citizens.
In Greek, paradise is called a garden in Latin. Eden in Hebrew translates to delights in Latin; together, they form a garden of delights.
Jesus Christ is fittingly compared to a garden in this context because, although in his divinity he is uncircumscribed with the Father and the Holy Spirit, he is so circumscribed that no hypocrite, heretic, Jew, or pagan can ever reach him.
It is rightly called a garden of delights because it contains all the delights and riches of heavenly citizens.
It is beautifully called paradise because it is nourishment and sweetness to those who run to it, and to all who dwell in heaven.
Therefore, it is called a garden of delights because it is the food and joy of all the blessed heavenly orders of spirits and the souls of all the saints.
Therefore, dearest brothers, if we desire to reach these delights, which is Christ, it is necessary to strive to serve him with all devotion, to please him in all our actions, and to cling to him with all our mind, so that we can rightly say with the Prophet:
"But it is good for me to be near God; I have made the Lord God my refuge."
Psalm 73.
As if to say: It seems delightful and beneficial to me to disdain the world, to cling to God, and to place my hope in him, rather than in temporal goods which quickly fade away.
It's fitting that we adhere to Him with pure morals and follow Him with holy actions, having first cleansed our hearts of impure, wicked, vain, and harmful thoughts.
No one can truly contemplate Him or perfectly follow Him without these virtues, for in His essence, He is most holy and refined, and an impure eye cannot see Him.
So, let's approach Him with a clean heart and pure mind, loving Him above all and beyond everything, loving Him in all things and through all things, and serving Him diligently.
He provides Himself as nourishment for us, so we don't falter on the path of this world, and He keeps the reward for us, that we may rejoice in the heavenly homeland.
But because our countless sins make us unworthy of heavenly gifts, let's implore the help of the most blessed Mary, ever virgin, that through her sacred prayers and merits, cleansed from all sins and vices, we may be worthy to share in eternal delights and reach the joys of eternal happiness.
And there see the same Jesus Christ, her Son, reigning at the right hand of God the Father: granting this, He who lives and reigns with the same Father and the Holy Spirit in perfect Trinity, God, forever and ever.
Amen.
Sermon Five: On the Holy Cross
Dear brothers, our Lord Jesus Christ graciously descended from heaven for our salvation.
He did this to lead us from earth back to heaven with Him.
For this reason, He chose to humble Himself to the point of death and endure the shame of the cross.
He did this to free us from the enemy's power and guide us to eternal happiness, which is the vision of His Father, through Himself, who is the way, the truth, and the life.
So let us listen to Him on how we should follow Him and reach Him, so that we may be where He is, through Him.
He says: Whoever wants to come after me must deny himself, take up his cross, and follow me.
Matthew chapter 16.
Therefore, whoever wants to follow Christ must first deny himself.
But what does it mean to deny oneself?
It means giving up one's own habits.
For example, someone who was proud and caused harm to others should, after turning to the Lord, do good not only to friends but even to enemies as much as possible.
One who was previously angry should present himself as gentle and kind in everything, bearing everything calmly and patiently.
Someone who was once indulgent should strive to be chaste in mind and body, so that the body is not defiled by touch nor the mind by impure thoughts.
Someone who was given to greed should not covet what belongs to others and, for the love of Christ, should give his possessions to those in need, love poverty, and despise riches.
Whoever renounces such personal desires undoubtedly denies himself; however, this is not enough for perfection unless he takes up his cross and follows Christ.
But what does it mean to carry the cross?
It means to mortify oneself.
Carrying the cross without dying is the pretense of hypocrites; carrying the cross and dying is the pursuit of God's servants.
Therefore, whoever approaches the service of God, if he has not yet died to sins and vices, seems to carry the cross, but does not truly follow Christ.
He truly carries the cross and follows Christ who, by renouncing the world, turns away from sins and vices.
He commits himself wholeheartedly to serving God, goes against his own desires in all things, and humbly submits to the authority of his master, the abbot.
This person can rightly say with the Apostle:
"But far be it from me to boast except in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom the world has been crucified to me, and I to the world!"
(Galatians, Chapter 6).
Without a doubt, the world is crucified to him who rejects its pleasures.
Conversely, he is crucified to the world, and the world despises him because of his love for Christ.
Sometimes, a person may not cling to the world mentally, yet the world, with its distractions, holds onto him.
He is dead to the world, but the world, as if alive, notices him and tries to entangle him in its activities.
But Paul does not desire the world, nor does the world desire him; like two dead people, neither sees the other.
It's as if he said:
"Neither do I desire anything of the world, nor does it recognize anything of its own in me."
Therefore, as already mentioned, carrying the cross means mortifying oneself, despising visible things, loving invisible things, and bearing the sweet yoke of Christ's discipline and the light burden of his commandments with complete devotion.
Let us also, beloved, glory in the life-giving cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, which was worthy to carry the price of this world. Through its mystery, the devil is defeated, and the world is redeemed.
We must greatly glory in it because its benefits are neither recent nor newly discovered; they have been shown and revealed from ancient times in symbols and enigmas. This was illustrated when the Lord showed Moses a piece of wood at the fifth encampment of the children of Israel, namely Mara. Moses immediately threw it into the very bitter waters, turning them into sweetness by divine power
(Exodus, Chapter 15).
The bitter waters are seen as representing the law and its letter, which bring death.
However, when the confession of the cross is introduced and the sacrament of the Lord's passion is added, the waters become wonderfully sweet, transforming the bitterness of the letter into the sweetness of spiritual understanding.
This is why it is written: "The Lord established a law and judgments for the people and tested them" Exodus twenty-one.
In another sense, the transformation of the bitter waters into sweet ones with a piece of wood symbolizes how the bitterness of the nations will one day be changed into sweetness through the wood of the cross.
In this higher meaning, Israel was first led to salty and bitter waters, and when the Lord showed them a piece of wood, the waters became sweet.
Then they came to the springs.
Indeed, the people are first led to the letter of the law, where, as long as they remain, they cannot escape bitterness or taste the sweetness of the Gospel.
But when the waters are sweetened by the wood of life and the law begins to be understood spiritually, one moves from the Old Testament to the New and reaches the twelve apostles, whom the Scriptures refer to as springs.
From these, the faithful draw sufficiently sweet water, which is spiritual teaching.
Seventy palm trees are also needed there, because not only did the twelve apostles preach the faith of Christ, but seventy others were also sent to spread the word of God, through whom the world would recognize the palms of Christ's victory.
Indeed, these twelve springs watering the seventy palm trees prefigured apostolic grace, with the watering multiplied tenfold, so that through the sevenfold Spirit, the Decalogue of the law is ultimately fulfilled.
Through the mystery of this holy cross, the doctrines of philosophers are typically destroyed.
What was once physically afflicted by various plagues in Egypt is now spiritually enacted in us.
Egypt, indeed, symbolizes the world, where the waters are turned into blood by the command of the Lord.
The unpredictable waters of Egypt and the elusive doctrines of philosophers are understood, and they are rightly turned into blood because they perceive the causes of things in a worldly way.
But when the cross of Christ brought the light of truth to the world, it corrected these ways so that from the nature of the punishments, people might recognize what they had done wrong.
By this cross, at the Lord's command, the rock provided water through Moses' service.
In the thirty-third stop, known as Kadesh, Moses offended the Lord because of the waters of contradiction, and he was forbidden to cross the Jordan and enter the promised land.
Upset by the people's complaints, he struck the rock hesitantly, as if God could not make water flow from it.
This is found in the Book of Numbers, Chapter 20.
But what does Moses' doubtful faith suggest here, as he hesitated to bring forth water from the rock?
In this, without a doubt, we see a prophecy about Christ.
For while Moses in the holy Scriptures assumes various roles for different reasons, here he signified the role of the Jewish people under the law and represented them prophetically.
Just as Moses, with the rod, symbolizing the wood of the holy cross, struck the rock and doubted God's power, the people, under the law given through Moses, did not believe Christ to be the power of God when they nailed him to the wood.
But just as the struck rock gave water to the thirsty, so the wound of the Lord's passion brought life to the believers.
The same rock that spewed water was a figure of Christ, and when it was opened, everything flowed forth.
To ensure grace flowed to the believers, the wood of the cross approached like a rod.
When the rock was struck, a fountain flowed; when Christ was struck on the cross, he poured out grace and the gift of the Holy Spirit for the thirsty and believing.
The Apostle confirms that this rock was a figure of Christ when he says: "They drank from the spiritual rock that followed them, and the rock was Christ."
This is found in First Corinthians, Chapter 10.
The people were thirsty for water and complained against Moses, so God instructed him to show them the rock from which they could drink.
What does this signify, except that the law of Moses, which kills according to the letter, complains against him?
Moses showed them the rock, which is Christ, and led them to it so they could drink and satisfy their thirst.
This represents the worldly despair concerning the divinity of Christ, which God commands to die in the height of Christ himself, as He ordered the death of Moses' flesh on the mountain.
Just as the rock signifies Christ, so does the mountain indicate Christ.
The rock symbolizes humble strength, while the mountain represents eminent height.
As the Lord Himself said: "A city set on a hill cannot be hidden" Matthew 5, asserting Himself as the mountain, and His faithful, founded in the glory of His name, as the city.
The wisdom of the flesh lives when the humility of Christ, struck like a rock on the cross, is scorned by unbelievers.
Christ crucified is indeed a stumbling block to the Jews and foolishness to the Gentiles, as written in First Corinthians chapter one.
The wisdom of the flesh dies again when Christ, like the height of a mountain, is acknowledged as exalted.
To those who are called, both Jews and Gentiles, Christ is the wisdom of God and the power of God.
The two sticks that the widow of Zarephath was gathering, mentioned in First Kings chapter seventeen, represented the cross of Christ, which is made not from one piece of wood, but consists of two.
The sign of the cross is expressed in the name of the wood and the number of the woods.
The heavens were closed when there was famine, as there was no abundance of knowing the divine; but in those times when famine pressed all of humanity, Elijah was sent to the widow.
See, brothers, how grace is kept for each: an angel is sent to the Virgin, as mentioned in Luke chapter one; a prophet is sent to the widow.
There were many widows, but one was preferred above all.
This widow is not only defined by bodily abstinence but is marked by virtue.
This holy widow was of great merit, because although there was a great famine throughout the land, her care was not lacking for God, as He sent the prophet to sustain her.
This widow represents the Holy Church, which became widowed by the death of her husband, Christ.
This widow is not favored among many without reason, but is justifiably placed above all.
What kind of widow can be compared to her, or where can one be found to whom such a great prophet, taken up to heaven, is sent?
This was especially significant when the heavens were closed for 3 years and 6 months.
What do these 3 years represent if not the time when the Lord came to earth and found no fruit?
As it is written: "Look, for 3 years I have come seeking fruit on this fig tree, and I find none" (Luke 13).
Solomon spoke of this woman: "Who can find a virtuous woman? Her worth is far beyond rubies" (Proverbs 31).
The value and reward of the holy Church is Christ, who came to her from the farthest reaches, that is, from heaven, and redeemed her with the price of his own blood.
This is indeed the widow of whom it is said: "Rejoice, barren one who does not give birth; break forth and shout, you who are not in labor, because the children of the desolate are more than those of the married woman" (Isaiah 54).
It is also rightly said to her through the prophet: "You will not remember the shame of your youth and the reproach of your widowhood anymore, for I, the Lord, am your Savior" (Isaiah 54).
This is the widow for whom, during the drought on the earth, prophets of the heavenly word were sent.
Thus, we do not consider the person of that widow to be insignificant, for she watered the dry earth with the dew of the heavenly word.
The closed heaven was not opened by human means, but by divine power.
Who can open heaven except Christ, to whom the members of the Church are gathered daily from sinners?
It is beyond human power to declare: "The jar of flour will not be used up, and the jug, that is, the vessel, of oil will not run dry until the day the Lord sends rain on the earth" (First Kings 17).
What does it mean, "until the day the Lord sends rain on the earth," except until the day when the Son of God descends like rain upon the fleece? (Psalm 72).
In the Scriptures, these truths are hidden under symbols; but now, the powers and benefits of the cross are revealed.
What are these benefits?
Clearly, kings believe in Christ and revere this most holy cross, laying down their crowns and kneeling, despite having once inflicted severe torments on Christians out of hatred for the name of our Lord Jesus Christ.
Through the power of this same holy cross, the strong and proud one, who seemed to guard his domain peacefully and possess his goods
as mentioned in the Gospel of Luke, chapter 11, is justly and reasonably defeated.
His goods, namely the hearts of the faithful in which he dwelt, are plundered; his weapons, such as pride and deceit in which he trusted, are broken.
Humanity is reconciled to God, the temples of idols are destroyed, the holy Church is strengthened, and Christians are solidified in faith.
Pagans, because they worshiped idols, are put to shame.
Jews are scandalized, the gates of hell are destroyed, and captives who were held there for a long time are transferred to the rest of eternal light and peace.
The gate of paradise is opened, the losses of the heavenly orders are repaired, demons are restrained, and enemies are overcome.
To put it briefly, without it, no sacrament is completed in the holy Church.
By its sign, indeed, the most sacred body of Christ is consecrated, the Church is dedicated to God, priests and all ranks of the Church are ordained, infants are baptized, and children and youths are confirmed in faith with sacred chrism by bishops.
The food of the faithful is sanctified, all Christian people are blessed, and the foreheads of both sexes and all ages are protected.
Hence the saying: There is no safety in the house unless a person marks a cross above the thresholds.
Truly, there is no safety in the house, that is, in the body, which is the dwelling of the soul, unless it bears the sign of the holy cross on the forehead.
By its power, the sick are healed, the dead are raised, the blind are given sight, lepers are cleansed, the paralyzed are cured, demons are driven out from possessed bodies, wild beasts are tamed, serpents are driven away, and fire is extinguished.
Finally, prosperity is granted, and all adversity is repelled.
Therefore, dear friends, let's give thanks to almighty God.
Through the suffering and cross of His Son, Jesus Christ, He has blessed the entire world with countless gifts.
Proud Adam took many good things from us with the tree of transgression, but humble Christ brought us even greater blessings through the tree of the holy cross.
Christ, the Son of God and the Virgin, showed such great humility that it suffices for the salvation of all, just as the pride of the first man harmed him and his descendants.
However, no human could achieve this reconciliation with God by their own merits, except for the lion of the tribe of Judah.
He opened the book and broke its seals, fulfilling all righteousness in himself.
This represents the most complete and perfect humility, greater than any other.
Other humans were debtors, guilty, and their virtue or humility was barely enough for themselves.
Therefore, none of them could offer a sufficient sacrifice for our reconciliation.
But Christ, both God and man, was the perfect and sufficient sacrifice.
He was humbled much more by tasting the bitterness of death than Adam was proud by enjoying the wrongful pleasure of the forbidden tree.
Through the death of the Only Begotten, we received great blessings, allowing us to return to our homeland.
Just as in the past, at the death of the high priest, those who had fled to the city of refuge were allowed to return safely to their own.
But among these things, dear brothers, it's worth wondering why the Son of God, who never sinned and from whose mouth no lie came, would so lovingly and mercifully choose to ascend the cross for us sinners and die on it.
Was it due to our deserving merits that He came to us and chose to redeem us from the hand of the ancient enemy, showing us the right path to heaven?
Did any good deeds precede this, making us deserving of such great and incomparable gifts, that the Son of God would bear our sins on the cross?
Without a doubt, it wasn't our holiness that made Him come down to us from the Father's embrace, but rather His supreme and incomparable love.
God the Father sent His only Son, co-eternal with Himself, to us.
He redeemed us from the power of the enemy, poured His love into our hearts, granted us the knowledge of Himself, opened the entrance to the heavenly kingdom, and allows us to see His face not through our own merits, but through His immense goodness.
Just as we were not born into this world by our own providence, we were neither redeemed from the enemy by our own decision nor spiritually reborn by our own counsel.
We were created by Him from nothing, instructed to serve Him spiritually, and mercifully helped to ascend to heaven.
He gave us the ability to move from exile to homeland, from the lowest to the highest, from misery to happiness, from darkness to light, and from tribulation to paradise.
Our Lord Jesus Christ, the Bridegroom, illustrates this when He figuratively says to the bride, the holy Church: "I awakened you under the apple tree" (Song of Solomon chapter eight).
What is meant by the apple tree, if not the holy cross, which endured that evil?
The same bride says earlier: "Like an apple tree among the trees of the forest, so is my beloved among the sons" (Song of Solomon chapter two).
Without a doubt, Christ awakened His bride under the apple tree; for, being on the cross, He called the Church, subject to Him, to life and encouraged her to good works, so she would rise from the sleep of death and, crucifying herself with Him, hasten to a new resurrection.
Hence, the Apostle says to anyone dead in soul: "Awake, sleeper, and rise from the dead, and Christ will shine on you" (Ephesians chapter five), meaning He will enlighten you.
So, dearest brothers, what thanks can we give to Almighty God, who has deemed us sinners, deserving of no good, worthy to receive such great gifts?
How can we truly honor the King of all ages, without whom we can't do any good or even think?
How can our human frailty adequately glorify Him, who not only provides us with temporary blessings but also calls us to heavenly realms?
What thanks can we offer Him that are truly worthy, except to always remember His commandments and, out of love for Him, willingly endure hardships just as He suffered for us?
So, my beloved, take up your cross sincerely.
Crucify your flesh with its vices and desires.
Let go of worldly prosperity.
Endure adversities with patience.
Approach divine duties with a willing heart.
Treat injuries from others as insignificant.
Thank God for the loss of worldly goods.
Reject temporary things, and desire eternal ones.
Follow Christ truthfully, so that, being dead in the flesh, you may live in the spirit and, through Jesus Christ, the shepherd of all the faithful, reach the heavenly homeland, who lives and reigns with the Father and the Holy Spirit in perfect Trinity, God, forever and ever.
Amen.
Sermon Six: On the Feast of Saint Michael the Archangel
Dear brothers, I urge you to listen closely to the words of blessed John the Apostle and Evangelist, as they offer guidance not just for you, but for the entire Church, in the Book of Revelation:
"A battle occurred in heaven," he says, "Michael and his angels fought against the dragon, and the dragon and his angels fought, but they did not prevail, nor was a place found for them any longer in heaven" Revelation 12.
The word "Church" comes from Greek and translates into Latin as "convocation," because it calls everyone to serve God.
The holy Church is also known as "catholic," because it is spread universally across the entire world.
Unlike the assemblies of heretics, it is not confined to specific regions but is widespread around the globe, as the Apostle affirms to the Romans:
"I thank my God for all of you, because your faith is proclaimed throughout the whole world" Romans 1.
Scripture often refers to the holy Church as "heaven," because it yearns for heavenly things, and the Lord reigns in it as He does in heaven.
Hence the phrase: "I saw a door opened in heaven" Revelation 5.
This open door symbolizes Christ, born and suffering in the Church.
As He says of Himself: "I am the door" John 10.
Similarly, here, the Church is called "heaven," where the battle is described to have taken place.
"A battle occurred in heaven," meaning within the Church, where the dragon fights against God's saints, tempting them through many adversities.
Michael is seen as Christ, and his angels are the holy people, with whom, in heaven-that is, in the Church-He continually battles the ancient dragon.
In Hebrew, angels are called "Malaoth," and in Latin, "nuntii," meaning messengers, because they convey the Lord's will to the people.
In Greek, archangels are understood as the highest messengers.
Those who announce smaller or lesser things are called angels, whereas those who announce greater things are called archangels.
They are called archangels because they hold the highest rank among angels.
The word Archos in Greek translates to "prince" in Latin.
In this context, the name Michael is understood to mean Christ, who is truly the Prince of the angelic army, before whom every knee bows in heaven, on earth, and under the earth.
Philippians chapter two states: "The government will be on his shoulder, and he will be called Wonderful Counselor, Mighty God, Everlasting Father, Prince of Peace."
Isaiah chapter nine mentions his rule, saying: "The government will be on his shoulder, and he will be called Wonderful Counselor, Mighty God, Everlasting Father, Prince of Peace."
Without a doubt, our Lord Jesus Christ is the Prince of Peace, who, through his own blood, reconciled humanity to God and restored true peace between angels and humans, as the choir of angels sang at his birth: "Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace to people of good will."
Luke chapter two shares this message: "Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace to people of good will."
Jesus Christ is also called the Prince of kings, as John testifies about him at the beginning of the book of Revelation to the seven churches, meaning the whole Church: "Grace and peace to you from him who is, and who was, and who is to come, and from the seven spirits before his throne, and from Jesus Christ, who is the faithful witness, the firstborn from the dead, and the Prince of the kings of the earth."
Revelation chapter one declares: "Grace and peace to you from him who is, and who was, and who is to come, and from the seven spirits before his throne, and from Jesus Christ, who is the faithful witness, the firstborn from the dead, and the Prince of the kings of the earth."
Why does John write to seven churches when there is only one Church?
It is so that the one Catholic Church is represented as being full of the sevenfold Spirit.
Thus, we know that Solomon said about Christ: "Wisdom has built her house; she has set up its seven pillars."
Proverbs chapter nine says: "Wisdom has built her house; she has set up its seven pillars."
These seven, however, are understood to be one, as the Apostle testifies: "The Church of the living God, which is the pillar of truth."
First Timothy chapter three confirms: "The Church of the living God, which is the pillar of truth."
Do not be troubled, whoever you are, if Christ is called an angel by his work, since in the prophet he is called the Angel of great counsel.
Isaiah chapter nine refers to him as the Angel of great counsel.
Although he is God and Lord of the angels, he is called an angel in the divine Scriptures because he announced the will of the Father and his own to the faithful people.
Hence, he says in the Gospel: "Father, I have made your name known to them."
John chapter seventeen speaks: "Father, I have made your name known to them."
Again, the Psalmist speaks to God the Father on his behalf, saying: "I have declared your righteousness."
The Psalms affirm: "I have declared your righteousness."
Thirty-nine, meaning faith that justifies, because the righteous live by faith, as stated in
Habakkuk
chapter two.
In the Church, he refers to the great, meaning not only in Judea but in the Church of all nations.
Michael means "who is like God," implying virtues. When something of extraordinary power occurs in this world, this archangel is sent by God. His name reflects his work because no one can do what God can do. In this context, Michael is rightly understood to mean Christ, as he truly leads all angelic spirits and all the heights of heaven. On earth, he is the Angel of great counsel, through whom God the Father redeemed the human race.
No one in heaven has angels except the Son of God. Although archangels lead angels, this one leads all according to what has been subjected to him by God the Father, everything under his feet. While higher powers govern the lower in the roles of angels, they do not have this authority from themselves but have received it from him to lead.
So, it is said: A battle happened in heaven, meaning in the Church. Michael and his angels, namely Christ and his saints, fought with the dragon, that is, with the devil. The devil, in Hebrew, is interpreted as "flowing downward" in Latin, because he refused to remain calmly at the height of heaven, but, weighed down by pride, fell downward. In Greek, the devil is called "slanderer" because he either reports the sins he entices people to God with or accuses the innocence of the chosen ones with false charges.
Hence it is said: The accuser of our brothers has been cast out, who accused them before our God day and night, as mentioned in
Revelation
chapter twelve.
About this battle long before, the Prophet joyfully said to Christ in the Psalm: "You will tread upon the asp and the basilisk; you will trample the lion and the dragon," as found in
Psalm
ninety-one.
He referred to death as the asp, sin as the basilisk, the devil as the lion, and hell as the dragon. Indeed, these names are fittingly applied to the devil, all of which were laid low under the feet of our Lord Jesus Christ in his glorious coming.
He walked over the cobra because by rising from the dead, he destroyed death; he walked over the basilisk because he committed absolutely no sin.
He crushed the lion because he defeated the devil, who had the power of death, and handed him over to the flames, binding him with the chains of hell.
Therefore, he said in the Gospel: "Now the ruler of this world will be cast out" from the Gospel of John, chapter twelve, meaning he will be expelled from the Church. This fierce lion had almost claimed dominion in this world, dragging everyone, both the good and the bad, the righteous and the sinners, to destruction with him through tyranny.
He trampled the dragon, meaning hell, when he was placed on the cross, entrusted his spirit to God the Father, descended into hell, broke its gates, and powerfully and mercifully rescued his captives held there from the Gospel of Luke, chapter twenty-three.
For although the devil, the perpetrator of all evil, did not know the order of our liberation, he knew that Christ had come for the salvation of mankind; yet he did not realize that he would redeem us by his death, and so he killed him. For if he had known that Christ's death would redeem the human race, he certainly would not have killed him.
The Gospel testifies that the devil knew Christ had come for the salvation of mankind, and when he saw him, he was afraid, saying: "What have you to do with us, Son of God? Have you come to destroy us before our time?" from the Gospel of Mark, chapter one.
Before the coming of Christ, the devil, like a strong man armed, guarded and possessed his courtyard in peace; but the true strength, the Son of God, came and attacked him, broke the weapons he trusted, distributed the spoils he unjustly held, and took them with him to heaven.
With what weapons did the Son of God attack him? Namely, with humility and wisdom. Listen, I ask you, brothers, to the fitting analogy of how the Son of God and the Virgin defeated the enemy of the human race.
There's a story about a bird from the eastern region with a large, armored beak.
This bird deliberately seeks out mud to prepare for a fight against a dragon, provoking it with daring hisses.
By covering itself with mud from its filthy wallow, the bird soils its beautiful, gem-like colors that nature has adorned it with.
Why does it do this?
So that, by appearing humbled and despised, it can both frighten the enemy with its strangeness and deceive it into underestimating its worth.
Additionally, it skillfully uses its tail as a shield in front of its face.
With a bold charge, it attacks the head of its raging opponent, piercing the brain of the stunned beast with its beak and defeating its enormous enemy with remarkable cleverness.
Similarly, our Lord and Redeemer, preparing to battle the spirit of the ancient serpent-the deceiver of the human race-took on human form and girded himself with human weakness for the battle of salvation.
He wrapped himself in the mud of our flesh to outsmart the wicked deceiver with righteous trickery.
He concealed his divinity with humanity, as if placing the tail of humanity before the face of divinity.
Like a very strong beak, he extinguished the venomous malice of the old murderer with the word of his mouth.
As the Apostle says: "He will kill the wicked with the word of his mouth"
Second Thessalonians 2.
It's important to note that against this dragon, it wasn't only the Son of God and the Virgin who fought, but also his angels, meaning his saints.
The evangelist says there was a battle in heaven, meaning in the Church: Michael and his angels, that is, Christ and his saints, fought with the dragon.
Therefore, Christ fought and his saints, and every day he battles against the ancient enemy who accused the human race.
He undoubtedly encouraged his disciples for this battle when he said in the Gospel: "When you hear of wars and rebellions, do not be terrified"
Luke 21;
"for they will hand you over to councils, and in their synagogues, they will flog you"
Matthew 10.
And elsewhere: "If they persecuted me, they will also persecute you"
John 15.
To reassure them once more, he says: Not a hair on your head will perish.
Luke chapter twenty-one.
The leader of the apostles, Peter, encouraged the disciples for this challenge, saying: Christ suffered for us, leaving you an example, so that you might follow in his steps.
First Peter chapter two.
And again: Since Christ has suffered, arm yourselves with the same mindset.
First Peter chapter four.
Paul, another strong soldier of Christ, urged the faithful to this fight when he spoke to the Ephesians, saying: Put on the armor of God so that you can stand against the devil's schemes, for our struggle is not against flesh and blood, but against the rulers, against the authorities, against the powers of this dark world, and against the spiritual forces of evil in the heavenly realms.
Ephesians chapter six.
And a little later: Stand firm, with the belt of truth buckled around your waist, the breastplate of righteousness in place, and your feet fitted with the readiness that comes from the gospel of peace.
In addition to all this, take up the shield of faith, with which you can extinguish all the flaming arrows of the evil one: take the helmet of salvation and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God.
Ephesians chapter six.
Therefore, for this battle with Michael, that is with Christ, who has no equal in virtues, the angels, meaning all the saints, gather and engage in war with the dragon in heaven, that is in the Church.
But who is this evil dragon against whom Christ battles with his angels in heaven, or in the Church?
He is the enemy of the human race, who out of envy expelled humanity from the delights of paradise and miserably dragged them to destruction with him.
And because he despised being a glorious prince in the palace, God made him a laborious craftsman in this world; so that he might be forced to serve with all his might, having previously refused to serve God happily, about whom Scripture speaks to God: I will make him your eternal servant.
Job chapter forty.
Although the devil did not want to be subject to God in heaven, yet, having been cast out, he unwillingly serves his plan.
Therefore, the devil is called Behemoth, meaning an animal, in sacred writings because he fell from heaven to the earth.
Therefore, Leviathan, meaning serpent from the waters, is named so because it moves cunningly in the sea of this world.
It's also called a bird because it rises high with pride.
In this way, the devil serves God's plan, as his wickedness aids the saints.
Everything in heaven and on earth is under divine power, so even those opposing His will unknowingly fulfill His plans.
The devil, full of envy and deceit, unknowingly serves the good of the saints in this world, like a dark craftsman, by cleansing them from sin through many trials, making them worthy of heaven.
The furnace of this craftsman is affliction and tribulation, the bellows are temptations and suggestions, the hammers are torturers, the tongs are persecutors, and the files or saws are the tongues of those who curse and slander.
Through such a furnace and these tools, the malicious enemy purifies the golden vessels of the heavenly king, that is, the chosen ones, renewing the image of the Creator in them.
However, he punishes the reprobates who act against God as a torturer in hell.
It follows: "And the dragon," he says, "fought, and his angels."
It's unthinkable to believe the devil and his angels dared to fight in heaven when, on earth, he asked the Lord for permission to harm just one man, Job.
It's not believable that this evil dragon would dare to wage war against the Word of God, the creator of all, or the hosts of holy angels, when he didn't even presume to enter a herd of pigs without permission
(as seen in the Gospel of Matthew, Chapter 8).
How could he fight in heaven when, as soon as he was created, he burst into pride against God and immediately fell?
According to the voice of truth, he was a liar from the beginning and did not stand in the truth
(as stated in the Gospel of John, Chapter 8),
because as soon as he was made, he fell.
He was indeed created in truth but did not remain, and immediately fell from the truth.
Hence, in the Gospel, the Lord says: "I saw Satan fall like lightning from heaven"
(as found in the Gospel of Luke, Chapter 10).
The devil once held a high position among the angels, from which he fell due to pride, in such a way that he can never be restored.
The prophet highlights this great excellence with these words:
"The cedars were not taller than him in the paradise of God, and the fir trees did not match his height; no tree in paradise was like him, because God made him more beautiful" (Ezekiel 31).
Here, the cedars and fir trees represent the powers of the heavenly orders, which seemed inferior in comparison to him.
It is written about him: "He is the beginning of God's ways" (Job 40).
Thus, in comparison with the angels, he was called an archangel.
He was the first created in the preeminence of order, not in terms of time.
Therefore, this evil dragon does not battle in heaven with God and his angels, but in the Church with the Word of God made flesh and his saints.
But what does Scripture say?
"And the dragon," it says, "fought, and his angels; and they did not prevail, nor was their place found anymore in heaven."
This means, in heaven, in all the saints, who, by believing in Christ, do not welcome the devil once expelled, but repel him entirely with their hearts:
Thus, the evil dragon was expelled from heaven, meaning from the Church, the ancient serpent, known as the devil and Satan, who deceives the world; he was cast down to the earth, and his angels were thrown down with him.
The word "serpent" refers to all kinds of snakes, which can coil and twist.
It is called a serpent because it is angular and never straight.
Hence, the ancient enemy is rightly called a serpent because he operates in this world with tortuous and versatile cunning.
About whom it is said: "O twisted serpent, you who through a thousand meanders and deceptive twists disturb peaceful hearts."
Satan in Latin means adversary or transgressor.
He is indeed the adversary, the enemy of truth, always trying to oppose the virtues of the saints.
He is the transgressor, who, having become a betrayer, did not remain in the truth in which he was created.
Demons are referred to by the Greeks as almost "demna," meaning skilled and knowledgeable of things.
They foresee many future events, and thus are often known to give certain responses.
They have knowledge beyond human limitations, partly due to sharp insight, partly from the experience of a very long life, and partly through divine command and angelic revelation.
These beings thrive by nature of aerial bodies.
Before the fall, they indeed had heavenly bodies, but after falling, they've changed into a different form.
They're not allowed to occupy large spaces of that air but are confined to gloomy places, serving as a prison for them until the time of judgment when they will be condemned.
This evil dragon, who was cast out, is the leader of all evils, and his angels are evil beings and unclean spirits expelled from heaven, or from the Church, with him.
All who agree with him in evil are cast out of the Church with their leader, compelled by divine justice and power.
By "heaven," we mean holy people, and by "earth," we understand sinners.
Hence the saying: In the beginning, God created heaven and earth.
Genesis 1.
Heaven signifies spiritual people who meditate on heavenly things; earth signifies those who are carnal and have not yet set aside earthly vices, that is, the earthly man.
So too, the Lord said to the devil: You will eat dust.
Genesis 3.
Meaning, those whom you overthrow with earthly desire will belong to you.
Again, he said to sinful man: You are dust, and to dust, you shall return.
Genesis 3.
Therefore, they are excluded from the just who desire heavenly things and are cast down to earth to be trampled under the feet of the saints.
Hence, the Lord speaks to his disciples: Behold, I have given you the power to tread on serpents and scorpions of the earth, and over all the power of Satan.
Luke 10.
This doesn't mean that the saints physically trample on evil people or demons, as they should not return evil for evil; but when the wicked desire earthly things, the saints yearn for heavenly things and desire nothing earthly.
They endure tribulation and poverty with equanimity, walking over them not physically but mentally.
He adds again, saying: Now salvation, and strength, and the kingdom of our God, and the power of His Christ have come.
Revelation 12.
A powerful voice in heaven declares that victory belongs to Christ and the salvation He brought to His Church when He came in the flesh.
All the kingdoms of the world serve Him, referring to the holy ones He redeemed with His own blood from the enemy's grasp.
Indeed, salvation and power have been achieved because the Son of God has driven the ancient enemy from the Church, specifically from the hearts of the holy ones.
Now, salvation, power, and the kingdom of our God have come because the world, once under the devil's influence due to idol worship, is now under God through faith in Christ.
"For the accuser of our brothers, who accused them before our God day and night, has been cast down," and they overcame him by the blood of the Lamb and through their testimony, as mentioned in the same passage. They did not love their lives so much as to shrink from death.
This voice is not from angels, as some might think. If it were from a higher heaven, it wouldn't say "the accuser of our brothers," but "our accuser." If angels called the righteous on earth their brothers, there would be no joy in the devil being sent to earth and humans living here. If that were the case, the joy would be in humans living on earth with demons.
But as we've mentioned before, we believe this voice to be that of the apostles. They recognized that the devil was bound and the Son of God was reigning in His holy ones incarnate, as they proclaimed: Now, salvation, power, and the other blessings, which are now evident in the Church, have come. Sacred Scripture often uses "day" for prosperous times and "night" for challenging times.
Therefore, he does not stop accusing day and night, as he tempts us with both prosperity and adversity and accuses us of our shortcomings. He accuses during the day by suggesting we have sinned in thought, word, or deed during good times; he accuses during the night by showing we lack patience during difficult times.
So, my dear ones, it is right that we give thanks to Almighty God the Father, who, through Michael the archangel, unmatched in virtues-that is, His beloved Son-cast out the evil dragon, the accuser of our brothers and sisters, from heaven, namely from the Church.
Stand firm, then, my dear ones, strong in spiritual battle, and fight against the ancient serpent.
After victory, you may reach the delights of paradise, from which you and your ancestors were deprived by the envy of that same ancient enemy.
Act courageously, and take up spiritual weapons against the evil and invisible enemy.
Soldiers fighting for an earthly emperor strive to obey all his commands; how much more should those who fight for the heavenly emperor strive to fulfill heavenly commands?
Earthly soldiers, wherever they are sent, are ready and prompt, and cannot excuse themselves for the sake of their wives or children.
Much more should the soldiers of Christ, without the hindrance of this world, obey the same emperor, our Lord Jesus Christ, and fight with spiritual weapons for love of Him against the powers of the air.
Worldly soldiers go to war against visible enemies; but you, instructed by the example of your emperor Jesus Christ, fight without ceasing against the devil, the master of all evil.
Earthly soldiers strive to fight their enemies using iron weapons; but your struggle is not against flesh and blood, but against the rulers and powers of these dark forces, against the spiritual forces of wickedness in the heavenly realms with spiritual weapons, as mentioned in Ephesians chapter six.
Worldly soldiers wear iron helmets on their heads in battle; but against the evil dragon, Christ is your helmet and defense.
To avoid being wounded by enemies, they wear iron armor; but you are clothed with the love of Christ as your armor.
Soldiers of a mortal emperor do not cease to throw spears and arrows at their enemies; but you, soldiers of the eternal Emperor, send pure prayers against the invisible enemy.
They don't discard their weapons until the fight is over, ensuring they won't be harmed by their enemies.
You should always have your weapons ready because your enemy is more cunning than theirs.
Earthly soldiers might fight their enemies for a time, but your enemies won't stop as long as you live.
Their weapons are burdensome and heavy, but yours are light and pleasant.
While they receive a worldly reward for their efforts, you will earn a heavenly reward for your spiritual labor.
So don't be afraid, dear ones, to engage in battle with the dragon, because the Lord Jesus Christ will come to your aid.
To worldly people, the devil seems terrifying, but to the spiritual, his terror is insignificant.
Unbelievers might fear him like a lion, but those strong in faith see him as a worm, easily trampled and quickly driven away.
As the Lord says: He wasn't driven away by a skilled archer, as mentioned in the Book of Job, Chapter 41, but he will be driven away by the faithful sending pure prayers against him.
Stones from a sling become like straw to him, yet he fears the servants of God who are strong in faith.
This wicked enemy sees iron as chaff and bronze as rotten wood, yet he fears those who are dedicated to the law of the Lord and humble in their holy conduct.
He might regard the hammer as straw and laugh at the brandished spear; however, he fears the faithful who uphold perfect love for God and neighbor.
Therefore, let the love of God and neighbor remain in you, and frequently send the arrows of prayer against the wicked dragon.
Keep the love of God and neighbor in your heart, and may constant prayer to defeat the enemy never cease from your lips.
Let the fire of love remain strong in your heart, and may the darts of prayers be launched continually against the invisible enemy.
Frequent prayer overcomes the weapons of the devil.
The frequency of prayers expels unclean spirits.
This is the primary virtue against the assaults of demons.
Demons are conquered by prayer.
Therefore, dearest ones, love God above all things and call upon Him without ceasing.
In doing so, He may grant you the strength to fight against the cunning of the dragon.
With His grace, you may ascend to the place from which that wicked enemy is known to have fallen.
With His help, through His beloved Son, He has deemed it worthy to cast him out from His Church.
Amen.
Sermon Seven: On the Feast of All Saints
John the Apostle and Evangelist, the son of Zebedee, was chosen by the Lord and was especially loved among the others.
Christ called him away from earthly ties when he was about to marry.
During the Last Supper, John rested on Jesus' chest, and from that closeness, he was deeply inspired by the Lord's heart.
He nourished the holy Church with God's word, much like one of the rivers of paradise.
Later, filled with divine grace, John was taken up to heaven in spirit on the Lord's Day.
There, guided by an angel, he witnessed divine mysteries, which he recorded in the Book of Revelation, Chapter One.
From these visions, he shared with us for our learning: Behold, I, John, saw another angel ascending from the rising of the sun, having the seal of the living God.
This is found in the Book of Revelation, Chapter Seven.
The angel ascending from the rising of the sun, carrying the seal of the living God, symbolizes the Church.
It rises from the passion of Christ, the true Sun of Justice, beginning from His side as He hung on the cross and receiving the sign of the entire Trinity in baptism.
In Greek, "angel" means messenger in Latin. Thus, the holy Church is rightly called an angel because it spreads God's commandments to all nations, promising the joys of paradise at times and warning of the punishments of hell at others. It encourages some to seek good, advises others to avoid evil, supports those who remain in goodness, and urges others to quickly turn away from wrongdoing.
Therefore, let it be said: Behold, I, John, saw another angel ascending from the rising of the sun, having the seal of the living God: namely, the holy Church having the seal of the living God on its forehead.
He cried out with a loud voice to the four angels, who were given the power to harm the earth and the sea, saying: Do not harm the earth or the sea or the trees until we have sealed the servants of our God on their foreheads. This is from the Book of Revelation, Chapter Seven.
These four angels represent the devil, who resides in all parts of the world among evil people. However, from the time of Christ's passion until the coming of the Antichrist, he is restrained and placed under the Church's authority, preventing him from causing as much harm to humanity as he wishes.
Here's what we read in the Gospel:
The Lord gave His disciples power over all demons and to heal the sick.
Luke chapter nine.
And again:
Who can enter a strong man's house and steal his possessions without first tying up the strong man?
Matthew chapter twelve.
Therefore, the devil is bound in his own body, that is, in evil people, so that he may not deceive the nations of believers across the world, namely, the holy Church, which is the body of Christ.
Thus, the angel, representing the Church through the four angels, warns him not to harm the earth and sea, which symbolize the congregation of the faithful, until the chosen ones are sealed, those predestined for the kingdom of heaven.
Indeed, the devil is allowed to harm the earth and sea, meaning he has the power to tempt the Church of God.
However, he tempts the good for testing and the wicked for condemnation.
The devil's temptation benefits the good by increasing their reward, but for the wicked, it adds to their condemnation.
The devil does not tempt the chosen ones more than God allows, because although he always wishes to bring temptations to them through his evil will, if he does not receive power from God, he cannot achieve what he desires.
Therefore, even though his will is unjust, his power is just when God permits it.
The strength of God's chosen ones could never endure the temptations of demons if God did not restrain their malice with loving moderation.
Therefore, it is now said:
Do not harm the earth, or the sea, or the trees.
As if to say:
Do not harm the earth, which refers to those devoted to earthly actions, or the Jews already cultivated by the law, and the sea, representing the Gentiles troubled by various vices.
In this present Church, good and evil are mixed together.
So it is said:
Do not harm the Church of God beyond what is allowed to you, nor before the time appointed by God, so that the righteous may still be justified, and those in filth may still be filthy.
Revelation chapter twenty-two.
Until Christ comes to judgment, where your wickedness will be condemned more severely, and the patience of the saints will be crowned more gloriously.
Here it is:
I heard the number of those who were sealed-144,000 sealed from every tribe of the children of Israel.
Revelation seven
The 144,000 symbolize the entire Church, sealed in the image and likeness of its Creator.
Thus, in the person of the Church, the Prophet sings: "The light of Your face, Lord, is marked upon us."
Psalm four
This indeed represents the whole Church, believed to be established with this number of members by Christ, the strongest rock.
The number of saints is said to be countless, as mentioned in the Psalm: "Your friends are greatly honored by me, O God: their authority is greatly strengthened.
I will count them, and they will be multiplied beyond the sand."
Psalm one hundred thirty-nine
The number of all saints is unknown to us, as it is said to be multiplied beyond the sand, but it is fully known to Almighty God, in whose image and likeness they are preordained.
Without a doubt, every faithful soul that follows the footsteps of its Creator and keeps His commandments with devotion bears the mark of the living God on its forehead.
Even if one is baptized in the name of the Lord and anointed with holy chrism, if they engage more in evil deeds than in holy actions, they are not counted among the sealed.
Therefore, whoever desires to have the mark of the living God on their forehead should demonstrate the faith received in baptism through good works.
It continues, saying: After this, I saw a great multitude that no one could count, from every nation, tribe, people, and language, standing before the throne.
Revelation seven
He did not say, after this, I saw another people or another multitude, but I saw the same people; that is, the same ones he saw in the mystery of the 144,000, he now saw as innumerable. Those he saw from every tribe of the children of Israel are the same great multitude from every tribe, people, nation, and language.
The Lord reveals in the Gospel that the entire Church, whether from the Jews or the Gentiles, is the twelve tribes of Israel.
"You," he said, "who have followed me will sit on twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel" (Matthew 19).
The holy apostles are destined to judge the entire Church, which includes not only those from the circumcision but people from every tribe and nation.
The 144,000 are not the infants killed by Herod, as some believe, because those were mostly from the tribe of Judah, with nearly 2,000, and a few from the tribe of Benjamin.
These 144,000 come from every tribe, nation, and language.
This represents the entire Church, founded on the solid rock of Christ, established in nine steps.
In the first step, the Church is founded on the Lord's passion and is specially guided by His example of poverty and love.
It is reborn through the saving bath and perfected by the doctrine of humility.
Ultimately, it is strengthened by the victory of the cross and redeemed from captivity by His precious blood.
In the second step, the twelve apostles shine like twelve gates, or like twelve hours of daylight, bringing light to the whole world under the guidance of one Master.
By practicing and teaching through words, they multiplied the number of believers abundantly.
Triumphing in patience, love, and humility, by following the Savior's example, they entered the heavenly kingdom.
In the third step, countless armies of martyrs followed in the footsteps of the holy apostles.
Armed with the holy faith and clothed in the breastplate of righteousness, they turned away from worldly greed, seeing it as refuse for the sake of Christ's name (Philippians 3).
To avoid serving idols unto death, they sacrificed their bodies.
Crowned with glorious martyrdom, they too are counted with the apostles in the kingdom.
In the fourth step, the blessed confessors bravely and faithfully stood against the fierce rage of pagans defending their idols.
By confessing the Lord and Savior of all, they also brought a significant number of people to the Lord through their example of good conduct.
They endured insults with patience for the love of Christ, and with love, they prayed to God for their enemies.
In the fifth rank, we find the dignity of bishops and other orders of Catholic priests, who take on the role of the holy apostles for governing the Churches and bringing believers to rebirth through baptism.
In the sixth rank is the sacred religion of monks and nuns, who separate themselves from the chaos of the world to serve the holy and almighty God.
Living very religiously, in great abstinence, and persevering in a life of good conduct until the end, they leave worthy examples for future generations.
In the seventh rank, we see the way of life of the holy Fathers, the hermits, who withdraw from public life to embrace the solitude of the desert, enjoying divine conversation and completing their lives, desiring to be with Christ, as mentioned in Philippians chapter one.
In the eighth rank is the order of penitents, who mourn their serious sins, strive not to sin further, and continue to lament their past.
As their intention was perverse in sinning, their devotion is now full of humility and love, persevering until the end.
The ninth and final rank compares to the innocence of young children, who, before they incur the guilt of harmful sin, complete their journey in this life.
About them, the Lord says in the Gospel of Matthew, chapter nineteen: "Let the little children come to me; for the kingdom of heaven belongs to such as these."
Ascending through these nine ranks of holy institutions, the Catholic Church, universal and gathered from the whole world, has penetrated and continues to penetrate the kingdoms of heaven since the passion of Christ, reigning with its head, Jesus Christ, forever.
It continues: "Clothed in white robes, and palm branches in their hands," as stated in Revelation chapter seven.
The white robe signifies an immaculate life.
And the mention of palm branches in their hands is intentional, as the life of the just is compared to palm branches.
The palm tree feels rough at the bottom, wrapped in what seems like dry bark.
But at the top, it stands out with its beautiful appearance and fruit.
While the base is constricted by the bark, the top spreads out with lush greenery.
This mirrors the life of the chosen ones: undervalued on earth but magnificent in heaven.
The life of the righteous here on earth is like being wrapped in layers of bark, constricted by countless challenges.
Yet, in the ultimate eternity, it opens up like the leaves of beautiful greenery, receiving the reward of eternal happiness from God.
The palm tree differs from other trees.
Most trees are stronger near the ground but taper off as they grow taller.
Conversely, the palm tree is narrow and tight at the base but broad at the top.
What starts slender at the base grows wider as it ascends.
What other shrubs are like this except among those focused on worldly gains?
Indeed, lovers of this world are strong in earthly deeds but weak in heavenly ones.
They aim for temporary glory, even unto death, but neglect efforts for eternal life.
They endure hardships for earthly rewards but won't bear even minor insults for heavenly ones.
They tirelessly engage in worldly matters all day, yet grow weary in just an hour of prayer before God.
In contrast, the life of the righteous is like the palm tree: narrow on earth but expansive in heaven.
They may appear weak in earthly pursuits but are strong in heavenly ones.
Often, their conversations accomplish more in conclusion than they intended at the start.
If they begin timidly, they finish tasks with fervor, always seeing themselves as starting anew, thus persevering tirelessly in good works.
Witnessing the perseverance of the righteous, the prophet proclaimed:
"Those who trust in the Lord will renew their strength and will soar like eagles. They will run and not grow weary; they will walk and not faint" Isaiah 40.
So, dear brothers, if you wish to attain the rewards of eternal life, let your life mirror that of a palm tree.
If you truly seek eternal happiness, let your actions reflect the qualities of a palm tree.
Let your life be narrow at the base, yet broad at the top; let your actions be disciplined at the start, but expansive at the end.
For narrow is the way that leads to life; broad is the way that leads to destruction Matthew 7.
It is through the broad path that the wicked descend into hell, but through the narrow path, the righteous ascend to heaven.
Indeed, it is through the wide road that the lovers of this world head towards ruin, while through the narrow road, the friends of God reach the kingdom.
Therefore, beloved ones, let your hands be ready for good deeds, and let them be weighed down with chains of love for God and neighbor against evil.
Let your feet swiftly move to serve the almighty God, and let them be bound with the shackles of faith while wandering through the streets of the city Song of Solomon 3.
Keep your eyes from seeing the vanity of this world; instead, open the eyes of your mind to contemplate God in spirit.
Let your ears be attentively open to hear the word of God, and protect them with the thorns of fear of God so that no harmful or deceitful words enter through them.
Place a guard over your mouth, as the Psalmist advises Psalm 140, so that no murmuring, backbiting, or insult escapes from it.
Let your tongue be free in the praises of God, yet bound with the chain of silence when necessary, so that it does not lash out against anyone.
Guard your mind with all diligence, cleansing it from sins and vices through true confession, for it is the source of good or bad thoughts.
Let your heart be open to Christ through the meditations of the Scriptures, but closed to the devil by rejecting harmful and vain things.
Also, let us keep the stomach in check, ensuring it isn't overfilled with food but instead nourished moderately and sensibly.
In this way, my brothers and lords, live your earthly life with restraint, like a palm tree, while expanding your spiritual pursuits if you wish to receive the rewards of your efforts with all the saints on the day of judgment.
Cleanse the blemishes of your life with daily tears, so that after your death, you may reach the heavenly kingdom and see the King of the saints reigning in His splendor, by His grace, who lives and reigns as God in perfect Trinity through all ages.
Amen.
Sermon Eight: On the Translation of Saint Isidore
"She is not afraid for her household when it snows; for all her household are clothed in scarlet" (Proverbs 31).
In the year of our Lord, around 1147, a messenger from the Highest King, an angel sent by the Lord to those who fear Him (Psalm 34), one of those who always see the face of the Father in heaven (Matthew 18), joyfully announced in the court of the Highest Emperor, who commands the winds and the sea (Matthew 8), that the home of the blessed Isidore of Seville, the former metropolitan bishop, was to be prepared-or rather restored-within the city walls of Leon for the order and residence of religious clerics.
Upon receiving this news, the venerable Father Augustine, a distinguished doctor of the Catholic Church, filled with joy and exultation, looked at Lord Isidore, among the foremost confessors, and, as if deep in thought, addressed him:
"What is it, reverend brother, that you are pondering? Are you perhaps thinking of explaining some Scriptures? But here in this spiritual homeland, heaven, Scriptures are not spread out like a skin (Psalm 104), but folded like a book (Isaiah 34); nor do you find people in need of teaching, because here is fulfilled what is written: 'No one will teach their neighbor, for all will know me, from the least to the greatest' (Jeremiah 31).
However, since you seem concerned about the governance and arrangement of churches, it is fitting that you focus on the one affecting you more spiritually and personally.
I am speaking of the one within the walls of Leon that holds the treasure of your body, prepared for habitation by religious clerics.
"
To this, Lord Isidore replied:
"I am concerned about these matters, but especially about the clothing for those who serve God in that house of clerics; for I have already prepared most of the necessities for their sustenance and will prepare the rest sufficiently; however, that land does not abound in clothing. I want them, having food and clothing, to be content with these" (First Timothy 6).
Father Augustine said:
"I will provide clothing for your children.
In Proverbs, it's written about a woman who isn't afraid for her household when it snows, among other virtues.
It also mentions: 'She works with wool and flax.'
In this spirit, I will provide your children and household with a garment made from woven linen and wool-a surplice and a cloak.
In one, I want you to see cleanliness, and in the other, humility; these qualities can be recognized by the color and appearance of these garments.
The cleanliness of the body is represented by the color white, while the blackness of the garment symbolizes humility.
You know that the most blessed Virgin Mother of the Lord was adorned with both.
This is why it is written about her: 'The glory of Lebanon was given to her: the beauty of Carmel and Sharon.'
And she herself said: 'For the Lord has regarded the humility of His servant.'
The same principle applies to the making of these garments; the linen garment requires much labor and difficulty, unlike the woolen garment.
Thus, the cleanliness of the body is achieved and maintained through significant effort, as it is opposed by the law of the members, the fuel of sin, the weakness of nature, and the sting of the flesh, which even the Apostle admits he suffers from.
The Apostle mentions in Second Corinthians that he suffers from a thorn in the flesh.
There is also the corruption of fleeting habits, the tempting allure of another's skin externally, and the inciting suggestions of the inner enemy.
As for linen, it is first pulled from the ground, gathered into bundles, submerged in a pool, dried in the sun, cleaned of debris and tow, spun into threads with a distaff, wound into balls, stretched and woven into fabric, and finally cut and sewn to fit as a surplice.
Linen comes from the earth, symbolizing the shining beauty of cleanliness, and bodily and spiritual chastity."
First, the flax is pulled from the ground.
Anyone who desires the purity of chastity, motivated by fear and love for God, must first leave behind earthly and worldly ways and join a community of religious individuals.
It's also fitting for them to physically leave places where they recall engaging in vices.
Often, a change in location can lead to a change in mindset.
Next, the flax is gathered into bundles.
This is like someone who has lived sinfully through illicit acts; they must, bound by the bond of divine love, gather themselves within the sanctuary of their heart.
After this, the flax is placed in water.
The water symbolizes the compunction of the heart because, just as flax is cleaned and washed in water, so too is the sinner cleansed and washed from sins and vices through tears of compunction, which arise with deep sighs from the heart.
Then, the flax is dried in the sun.
God is the true Sun of righteousness, from whose awareness no one can hide.
The heat of the eternal Sun dries up sinful desires in a person because, inflamed with His awareness and the fervor of love, they immediately turn away from the intention of wrongdoing.
The flax is also cleaned of straw and refuse, just as anyone who has converted is cleansed of illicit and unnecessary actions through penance.
The flax is turned into threads through a distaff.
The distaff is held in the left hand, and the spindle in the right.
Just as the threads come down from the distaff, all the actions of a servant of God depend on the judgment of their superior, ensuring they do nothing without their advice.
Then, the flax is wound into balls because it is restrained under the authority of its superior.
After this, it is spread out and woven into cloth, as, by the command of the superior, it works externally and internally on the good it can do.
The fabric is finally cut and sewn while the servant of God perfectly despises the world, shunning visible things, and gathers inwardly in the contemplation of his Creator.
It's as if he is already detached from the turmoil of the present age and, with his mind and desire, is woven into, or connected with, the citizens of the eternal homeland.
This allows him to savor the sweetness of the heavenly kingdom, which he cannot fully experience yet, except through longing.
Thus, he is adorned with the robe of all purity and honesty because he is already made suitable for the company of the perfect.
By the grace of God, brothers, you already have the robe, but you still need the woolen cloak.
The woolen and black garment signifies the humility of religious life.
Wool is first sheared, then cleaned and washed, hung on the distaff, spun into threads, woven, and sewn, and thus the cloak is completed.
In the wool, the gifts of God are revealed, which are granted to us by God in this present life.
Wool is sheared when earthly possessions are discarded for God's sake.
Wool is cleaned and washed when a person is cleansed from sins by giving alms.
Hence the saying: "Give alms, and behold, everything is clean for you" (Luke, Chapter Eleven).
Wool is hung on the distaff when great vigilance is observed so that nothing is given out of pride or the love of vain glory.
It is spun into threads when alms are distributed with discretion.
Wool is woven when one diligently engages in works of mercy.
The fabric is cut when the desire for possessions is perfectly excluded from the mind.
Finally, it is sewn when each convert, ascending from an active life and leaving all things behind, is joined with the contemplative life.
Thus, the regular cloak is completed when one earns for themselves the garment of eternal glory from God through good works.
Again, the most blessed Augustine speaks to Saint Isidore, saying: "Reverend brother, behold, I have clothed all your household, as I promised, with double garments. Therefore, do not fear for your household from the chill of the snow, as all your servants are clothed in double garments."
First, I gave them a surplice, symbolizing purity of mind and body.
Then, a cape made of sheep's wool, representing innocence of life and humility of conduct.
So, dear brother Isidore, ensure they have enough provisions so that, with ample clothing, they can serve God without want.
It is also your duty to advise them, while you are present in spirit and body, to strive with all devotion to follow the rule I have set for them.
Also, encourage them to diligently adhere to spiritual duties, lest, God forbid, they become so delighted by earthly goods that they miss out on the eternal ones.
To this, our patron Saint Isidore replied:
O most revered Father Augustine, it is fitting for you to encourage them to live well.
We give thanks to Almighty God, who made you a Teacher of the holy Churches.
See, dearest brothers, by God's grace, you have been sufficiently instructed by blessed Augustine, and doubly clothed in the regular garments, namely, the surplice and the cape.
The surplice, as mentioned, represents purity of mind and body.
So, brothers, be cautious that no damnable fornication is hidden under the surplice.
Believe me; whoever is tainted by fornication is not truly clothed in a surplice.
What good is it to show a surplice washed with water to people, while inside, before God, you carry a body polluted by fornication?
Or what good is it to display the cleanliness of a garment to people and hide the impurity of fornication within?
Nothing is hidden from God: He sees the secrets, who made the hidden things.
All things are naked and open to His eyes, as stated in the book of Hebrews, Chapter Four.
Therefore, I advise you, beloved, not to be like whitewashed tombs, which appear beautiful to people on the outside, but inside are full of dead bones, worms, and all kinds of filth, as written in the Gospel of Matthew, Chapter Twenty-three.
The cape is woven from sheep's wool and thus signifies the humility of religious conduct.
So, dearest ones, be careful that a wolf does not hide under the sheep's clothing.
In the Gospel, the Lord says:
"Beware of false prophets, who come to you in sheep's clothing, but inwardly they are ravenous wolves" (Matthew chapter seven).
A wolf hides under sheep's clothing when deceit, discord, and envy are disguised as a normal life.
A wolf also hides under sheep's clothing when someone causes harm under the appearance of religion.
Inwardly, they are ravenous wolves who, while pretending to be innocent outwardly, secretly devour their neighbors by slandering, murmuring, and whispering.
Therefore, brothers, fulfill the religious habit you show externally with good deeds.
Do not be one thing in private and another in public.
Let your inner spirit align with your religious garments.
Let your life reflect your words.
The habit is holy; let your spirit be holy.
The garments are holy; let your deeds be holy.
So, dear brothers, having food and clothing, be content with these (First Timothy chapter six), and do not keep anything for yourselves.
Without a doubt, one who shares everything with others but keeps something hidden for themselves is stealing.
To possess everything in common with your brothers yet hide something away is essentially handing yourself over to punishment after death.
Sharing food and clothing with your brothers while keeping something hidden is clear theft.
Therefore, dearest brothers, despise riches, love poverty, disdain earthly things, and desire heavenly ones.
Seek nothing superfluous, keep nothing for yourselves, hide nothing, if you wish to reach the common society of God's chosen ones, to which may He, who lives and reigns as God in perfect Trinity through all ages, bring you.
Amen.
Chapter Nine: On the Translation of Saint Isidore, Part Two
She is not afraid of snow for her household, for all her household are clothed in scarlet.
(Proverbs 31)
The messenger of the highest King, the angel whom the Lord sends around those who fear Him,
(Psalm 34)
is one of those who always see the face of the Father who is in heaven,
(Matthew 18)
and happily announced in the court of the supreme Emperor, who commands the winds and the sea,
(Matthew 8)
that the house of the blessed Isidore of Seville, once the metropolitan bishop, should be prepared or rather repaired within the walls of the city of Leon for the order and habitation of religious clerics.
Upon hearing this news, the venerable Father Augustine, an outstanding Doctor of the Catholic Church, joyful and exulting, looked at Lord Isidore, the Doctor of the Spaniards, as he pondered something to himself, and spoke to him:
"What is it, reverend brother, that you are considering? Are you perhaps meditating on explaining some Scriptures?
But in this homeland of spirits, heaven, Scripture is not spread out like a curtain,
(Psalm 104)
but folded, like a scroll.
(Isaiah 34)
Nor do you recognize that the people need teaching, because here it is fulfilled what is written: No one will teach their neighbor, for all will know me from the least to the greatest.
(Jeremiah 31)
However, since you seem concerned about the governance and arrangement of the Churches, it is fitting that you should be especially concerned about the one that affects you more personally and closely.
I am speaking of the one within the walls of the city of Leon, which contains the treasure of your body, being prepared for religious clerics to inhabit.
"
To this, Lord Isidore replied, "I am concerned about these things, but especially about the garments for those serving God in that house of clerics; for their sustenance, I have already prepared the necessary things in large part, and I will prepare the rest sufficiently; but that land does not abound in clothing.
I want them to be content with having food and clothing."
(First Timothy 6)
To this, Father Augustine said, "And I will provide clothing for your children."
In the writings of Solomon, there's mention of a certain woman who doesn't fear for her household when it snows.
It's also noted that she works with linen and wool.
So, I offer these children and your household a double garment made of wool and linen: a surplice and a cloak.
In these garments, I wish for cleanliness to be represented by one, and humility by the other.
This is evident in their color and design.
The whiteness of the garment symbolizes cleanliness, while its blackness signifies humility.
You also know that the most blessed Virgin Mother of the Lord was especially adorned in these garments.
Thus, it is written about her: "The glory of Lebanon was given to her, the beauty of Carmel and Sharon."
And she herself says: "Because the Lord has looked upon the humility of his servant."
In creating these garments, a pattern emerges: a linen garment is completed with much labor and difficulty, unlike a woolen one.
In this manner, maintaining and preserving the body's cleanliness requires significant effort and striving, as it faces resistance from the law of the members, nature's weaknesses, the sting of the flesh, which the Apostle also acknowledges suffering from.
Challenges include bad and loose habits, the tempting allure of another's skin, and the inner enemy's suggestive incitements.
The process of making linen is straightforward: it's first pulled from the ground, gathered into bundles, soaked in a pool, dried in the sun, cleaned of impurities and tow, spun into threads, wound into balls, woven into cloth, and finally cut and sewn to fit as a surplice.
In this way, much effort is exerted to remove the rust from the flesh and overcome its stubborn adhesiveness, which man experienced after sin, before the movements of other sins.
This was when streams of desires began spreading through the members without law, previously restrained by nature, to prevent disorderly outbursts.
Thus, he was ashamed of his nakedness and sought cover to hide his shame.
The Apostle highlights the challenge of overcoming this temptation by saying:
"Flee from sexual immorality"
First Corinthians 6:18,
which is a natural inclination that pursues you fiercely and closely.
For all the strength of the enemy is in its loins, and its power in the navel of its belly
Job 40:16.
This is like Delilah, who rests in our lap
Judges 16:19,
from whom the prophet instructs us to guard the doors of our mouths
Micah 7:5,
because no plague is more harmful than a familiar enemy.
Augustine: Therefore, to prepare the wedding garment for the bridegroom, so that at all times the garments of your children, O brother Isidore, may be white, let them not walk naked.
First, let them pull up the flax from the earth of filthy pleasure, and gather the abomination of carnal pollution into bundles by the discipline of regular order.
Let the fear of punishment cast it into the pit, let the heat of heavenly desire dry it in the sun.
Let the cleansing of the flesh purify it from debris and stubble through grinding.
Let contemplation of heavenly things draw it into threads through a sieve.
Let frequent meditation twist it into balls.
Let sure expectation of future things stretch it onto the loom.
Let the bond of love weave it.
Let regular exercise cut it.
Let the strength of perseverance sew it.
In the first step, a person is displeased with themselves. In the second, they deny themselves.
In the third, they let go of themselves within themselves. In the fourth, they suspend themselves above themselves.
In the fifth, they restrain themselves within themselves. In the sixth, they transcend their mind above themselves.
In the seventh, they recollect themselves. In the eighth, they are strengthened by themselves.
In the ninth, they are united above and around themselves. In the tenth, they are fortified.
And in the last, they are perfected and completed.
For when a person begins to think within themselves how brief the pleasure is, enduring its own hunger,
they find it is rejected with disgust or regretted.
For this is what all pleasure has: it drives those who are raging with its stings,
and like a swarm of bees, where it has poured out pleasant honey, it leaves its sting in the conscience.
When someone focuses on these things, they become like an animal, driven by their appetites and desires.
Yet, God gave them an upright face and encouraged them to look up to the sky and lift their eyes to the stars.
They turn away from the filth of base pleasures and reject the mire of indulgence, thus distancing themselves from earthly concerns.
For every sin a person commits is external to the body, but those who commit fornication sin against their own body.
As the Apostle said, "What benefit did you gain from the things you are now ashamed of?"
Those who hear this are drawn away from earthly matters.
Therefore, when they prepare themselves to enter the strength of the Lord, they choose to be humble in God's house rather than live among sinners.
They commit to a vow of chastity and the discipline of a regular order.
This commitment is evident, as they are so devoted that they become like a bundle of myrrh, akin to Isaac bound on the altar, placed on a stack of wood.
For they have a mouth but will not speak; they have eyes but will not see, and so on, allowing them to truly say: "I am crucified with Christ."
Yet, they are still caught between two grinding stones, which Moses forbids as a pledge; through the lower one, like flax lowered into a pit, aware of past actions and anxious about future ones, they fear punishment for past sins and the potential for future sins.
For blessed is the one, says Solomon, who is always watchful.
And the Psalmist says: "The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom."
For the fear of punishment is the gateway to the kingdom.
However, amidst all this, the person of desires yearns for the heavenly, eager to partake in the new Passover in the kingdom of God, like a burnt offering on the altar: all earthly desires in them are dried up as in the sun, so they might be praised like God on the timbrel, and only what is roasted by the fire of the Paschal lamb will be consumed.
Jeremiah was consumed with this fire, saying:
It became like a blazing fire, shut up in my bones
Jeremiah 20.
And the disciples said:
Wasn't our heart burning within us?
Luke 24.
And David:
My heart grew hot within me
Psalm 39.
Between the hammer and the anvil, he is crushed through the mortification of the flesh, but not broken.
He is cleansed of excess, not deprived of necessities, so that if he pursues the enemy, the citizen is not extinguished according to the Apostle's saying:
Romans 13: Make no provision for the flesh, to gratify its desires.
When the belly and the genitals, like in place, are joined together in vice, and the belly, boiling with wine, easily foams over into lust, no more effective medicine can be applied to maintain bodily purity than to serve moderation, restrain gluttony, restrict the belly, and mortify the flesh so that it does not overflow and dissolve into shameful lust; just like Lot, whom Sodom did not conquer, but wine did
Genesis 19.
Hence the prophet said:
The sin of Sodom was arrogance, and abundant bread
Ezekiel 16.
The first parent also took up arms against himself through eating from the forbidden tree, experienced this, and made loincloths to cover the shame he understood
Genesis 3.
The chief cook destroyed the walls of Jerusalem
Jeremiah 52.
Hence the Apostle:
Do not get drunk on wine, which leads to debauchery
Ephesians 5.
And Solomon:
Wine is a mocker, strong drink is raging
Proverbs 20: which even exposed Noah's thighs, making them a laughingstock to his son
Genesis 9.
Thus, wine did not spare even its own author.
Anyone can read these things better in the book of experience:
Wines prepare the spirit and make it fit for passions.
The contemplation of divine things produces the most subtle threads, from which the garment of philosophy is woven according to Boethius:
that like a column of smoke from aromatic spices, caught up to the third heaven
Song of Solomon 3, he may hear words that are not lawful for a man to speak
Second Corinthians 12.
These things are also folded and gathered like threads into a ball by frequent meditation, as it is read about the most glorious Virgin:
But Mary treasured up all these things, pondering them in her heart
Luke 2.
The Apostle says: Reflect on these things from First Timothy chapter four, keeping your mind alert.
Otherwise, Isboseth could be struck down while the doorkeeper sleeps, as mentioned in Second Samuel chapter four.
Meditating on the words of the Lord provides understanding to the simple, as noted in Psalm one hundred nineteen.
The upper millstone, symbolizing the expectation of future things, lifts the loom high.
As it is said: Our citizenship is in heaven, where we await Jesus Christ, who will transform our humble bodies to be like his glorious body, as described in Philippians chapter three.
Truly, love begins and completes the weaving of the garment, making it a seamless robe, woven from top to bottom.
This garment remains whole and is given by divine predestination, as stated in John chapter nineteen, to those predestined and chosen to conform to the image of his Son, as described in Romans chapter eight.
This is the wedding garment.
Blessed is he who keeps it, lest he walk naked, as mentioned in Revelation chapter sixteen.
Regarding the practice of regular order in reading, prayer, and other aspects associated with Mary, praised as the better part; or in the instruction of the young and works of mercy, where Martha is troubled and anxious about many things, as seen in Luke chapter ten.
You, more experienced, can teach me better than I can learn from the unlearned.
It is necessary to sew this many-colored garment with perseverance, like Joseph's long robe, as mentioned in Genesis chapter thirty-seven.
And so the tail of the sacrifice may be offered to the Lord, or rather in the burnt offering, as seen in Leviticus chapter seven.
For whoever perseveres to the end will be saved, as stated in Matthew chapter ten.
With this surplice, this white garment, let your children be clothed from the inside: for all the glory of the king's daughter is within, as noted in Psalm forty-five.
So that they may be whiter than snow, like his purified Nazarites, as mentioned in Lamentations chapter four.
But to be perfectly protected from the cold of snow and to be clothed doubly, I will also prepare for them a cloak of humility.
For the cloak to be suitable, the wool is first sheared from the animal, then spun into threads, woven into cloth, dyed, cut, and sewn.
The removal of wool symbolizes preparing the cloak of humility, achieved by letting go of personal desires.
The wool is spun into threads by adhering to rules, woven into cloth through a commitment to obedience, dyed with an awareness of one's weaknesses, cut with the remembrance of mortality, and sewn with the assurance of reward.
Each of these actions has its purpose: the first frees, the second educates, the third binds, the fourth humbles, the fifth disturbs, and the sixth uplifts.
Wealth often breeds and nurtures pride, as seen with the angel and the first man, whose wickedness stemmed from excess, as mentioned in Psalms 73, just as the earth's richness overflows upon the land, as stated in Psalms 140.
It's like wool being shorn to create a garment of humility when someone renounces their own will, possessions, freedom, and thoughts, saying to their father and mother, "I do not know you." Just as an animal feels relieved after being shorn, with parasites dying and wool removed, so does a camel feel relieved by shedding its burdens, allowing it to pass through the eye of a needle, as described in Matthew 19.
Human happiness is mixed with many sorrows, acquired with labor, held with fear, and lost with pain, as noted in Matthew 13. That's why it's compared to thorns in the Gospel.
Hence, the Apostle says: Those who desire to be rich fall into many pains, as found in First Timothy 6. The parasites of worldly concerns and the torment of hell are also destroyed.
As Solomon says: Just as a worm consumes wood, so does sadness consume the mind of a man, as written in Proverbs 25. And Isaiah says to Nebuchadnezzar: "Below you, the worm will be spread out, and worms will be your covering," from Isaiah 14. And again: "Their worm will not die, and their fire will not be quenched," as mentioned in Isaiah 66.
In regular instruction, wool is spun into threads to prepare the cloak of humility in silence, which is the cultivation of righteousness according to Isaiah 32, through prayer, reading, and other acts of humility, such as tonsure, frequent bowing of the head, asking for forgiveness, confessing to one another, sharing everything in common, wearing simple clothing, and eating plain food.
The Apostle wanted this wool to be spun into threads, saying: Let everything be done decently and in order among you.
First Corinthians Chapter 14.
To this end, there are countless examples from the Fathers in both the Old and New Testaments.
The fabric of humility is woven by the vow of obedience.
For what is as effective and preservative of humility as placing a person in the place of God over oneself and thus relying entirely on another's judgment?
So that without a superior's nod, one has a mouth but does not speak, eyes but does not see, feet but does not walk, hands but does not extend them even to receive gifts: and therefore obedience is rightly preferred over sacrifices.
First Samuel Chapter 15.
In sacrifice, another's flesh is offered, but in obedience, one's own self is sacrificed, sometimes even to the point of shedding blood, as it is said: Christ became obedient to the Father for us unto death.
Philippians Chapter 2.
Conversely, it is better understood what is thought of this praise.
The disobedience of one person condemns his descendants to death and outlaws everyone.
As Samuel says: To refuse to obey is a sin of divination, and to refuse to acquiesce is a crime of idolatry.
First Samuel Chapter 15.
Therefore, obedience is the only thing that possesses the merit of faith.
To this, the Apostle urges, saying: Obey your leaders.
Hebrews Chapter 13.
The fabric is dyed black by the consideration of one's own weakness.
For if a person considers what they were, what they are, and what they will be, they realize they are vile seed, a vessel of excrement, food for worms: Why then does earth and ash boast?
Sirach Chapter 10.
Why is the skin of a corpse stretched?
Why does a person, whose conception is fault, birth is punishment, life is pain, and death is inevitable, boast?
Know yourself, a decaying corpse; from heaven descends "know yourself." In all your ways, remember your end, and you will never sin. Sirach Chapter 7.
And this is what cuts the fabric for the cloak of humility to be sewn.
Pride is humbled when we reflect on the inevitability of death, as stated: "You are dust, and to dust you shall return" Genesis Chapter 3.
There's also the threat of damnation for the wicked, as it is said: "Your pride is brought down to hell" Isaiah Chapter 14. And: "Like sheep they are laid in the grave" Psalm 48.
However, this is balanced with the promise of reward. When one considers their nature, God's gifts, and the rewards to come, their own righteousness seems like filthy rags Isaiah 64.
This is similar to winged creatures lowering their wings when a voice speaks over the firmament above their heads, as described in Ezekiel Chapter 1.
The pastor of the Church advises us to wear this cloak of humility, saying: "Humble yourselves under the mighty hand of God, so that He may exalt you in the time of visitation" First Peter Chapter 5.
Therefore, dear friends, clothe yourselves with these virtues so you need not fear for your household against the cold of sin and the attacks of the ancient enemy, aptly called snow.
Just as snow descends from heaven and doesn't return, so too the devil, having fallen from high due to pride, won't return to the hand from which he was cast out. And like snow, which hardens in the air, the devil is hardened like a stone, as stated in Job Chapter 41.
He is also referred to as the cold north wind, both cold and hard. As mentioned in the Song of Songs: "Awake, north wind, and come, south wind" Song of Solomon Chapter 4.
This coldness diminishes the love of many, as the Lord says in Matthew 24. And Solomon notes: "Because of the cold, the lazy man does not plow" Proverbs 20.
Therefore, to protect your household from these threats, dear friends, clothe yourselves with these virtues, so you may overcome the two prominent horns of that ancient viper. As Job says: "He lies under the lotus plants, in the covert of the reeds and marsh" Chapter 40. And again: "The mountains bring him food." "He is king over all the children of pride" Job Chapter 41.
This queen, this most serious offense, this little creature, which killed more from Absalom's army than David's sword; this is what you must be especially fearful of and avoid even in the good things you do.
For arrogance, when added, taints even the most excellent character.
It is something of heavenly origin, dwelling in the minds of the lofty, lurking under ashes and sackcloth.
The first to leave those departing from God, and the last to return with those coming back.
For when you have fought well, when you think all is subdued, pride remains to be conquered.
Sometimes pride is long even in a short sleeve.
Therefore, clothe yourselves in these double garments, not with a cloak of confusion, but with the robe of twin glorification.
Walking with the Lamb in white, as mentioned in the Book of Revelation, Chapter Three.
Becoming like the angels of God, who neither marry nor are given in marriage, as stated in the Book of Matthew, Chapter Twenty-Two.
Through the humility which you now preserve, sitting upon twelve thrones judging the twelve tribes of Israel with Him who lives and reigns with God the Father in the unity of the Holy Spirit, God forever and ever.
Amen.