Mystical Exposition on Ecclesiastes
by Salonius
How many names was Solomon known by?
According to the Holy Scriptures, the three names associated with Solomon are Solomon, Jedidiah, and Ecclesiastes.
Why was he called by these names?
Solomon, whose name means "peaceful," was called that because there was peace during his reign.
He was also known as Jedidiah, meaning "beloved of the Lord," because the Lord loved him.
What is Ecclesiastes called in this language?
Greek; in Hebrew, it is called Qoheleth.
How do Coheleth or Ecclesiastes sound in Latin?
He is properly called Ecclesiastes, the one who gathers the assembly, meaning the Church.
In Latin, Ecclesiastes is rightly called the Preacher because he addresses the people.
His message isn't directed at one person but to everyone.
So, in the holy Church, the Preacher can indeed be called a preacher.
How many books did Solomon write?
There are only three, according to the number of their names: Proverbs, Ecclesiastes, and Song of Songs.
What does Solomon say in the Proverbs?
What does he teach in Ecclesiastes or the Song of Songs?
In Proverbs, he guides a young child, instructing him like a son through various sayings.
In Ecclesiastes, he teaches a mature man to understand that nothing in this world's affairs is permanent, glorious, or significant; rather, everything we see is brief, fleeting, and vain.
In the Song of Songs, he unites a fully mature and perfected man, adorned with various virtues, with the embraces of the bridegroom, who is our Lord Jesus Christ.
But spiritually, what do Solomon, Jedidiah, and Ecclesiastes represent?
The Lord Jesus Christ, who is our Solomon—that is, the one who makes peace by His blood—made both one.
From two peoples, He built one Church for Himself.
Thus, the Apostle says: Christ, our peace, who made both one.
He is Yedidiah, that is, the beloved son of the Father, about whom the Father Himself said to the disciples:
This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleased
(Matthew Chapter 3; Mark Chapter 1; Luke Chapter 3).
He is certainly the Ecclesiastes, our preacher who gathers the assembly—namely, the holy Church from the whole world—to whom He speaks, saying:
Learn from me, because I am gentle and humble in heart, and you will find rest for your souls
(Matthew Chapter 11).
He is the son of David, to whom the blind men in the Gospel cried out, saying:
Have mercy on us, son of David
(Matthew Chapter 9, Chapter 15, and Chapter 20).
He is also the King of Jerusalem, not earthly, but that heavenly one, which is the mother of us all.
What does Ecclesiastes mean when it says, "Vanity of vanities, all is vanity"?
In the book of Genesis, it says, "God saw everything that he had made, and it was very good."
If everything that God made is very good, then how can everything be vanity?
And not just vanity, but "vanity of vanities"?
Heaven and earth, the seas, and everything within this world are indeed good because they were created by a good God.
However, when compared to God, they should be considered as nothing because God will always remain as He is, while all these things will pass away.
What is seen is temporary because it is transitory, but what is unseen is eternal.
Why did he repeat his statement twice, saying: Vanity of vanities, said the Teacher; vanity of vanities, all is vanity?
To emphasize the greatness of vanities, he repeated his statement.
This shows that all the glory of the world will wither like the flower of grass, and will pass away like smoke.
Regarding these generations, it says:
One generation passes away, and another generation comes
(Ecclesiastes 1:4).
On the generations of the Jews and the generations of the Gentiles.
The first generation of Jews passed away due to their lack of faith, and the generation of Gentiles took their place.
This new generation is the holy Church of the faithful, saved through faith in Christ.
It can also be understood this way: One generation passes, and another comes.
As some die, others are born.
Those you saw before are no longer here, and you begin to see those who were not there before.
Why does Solomon say, "The earth stands forever" (Ecclesiastes 1:4), while the Lord in the Gospel says, "Heaven and earth will pass away" (Matthew 5:18 and 24:35; Mark 13:31; Luke 21:33)?
Truly, according to the Lord's judgment, Heaven and Earth will pass away through improvement, but not through destruction.
They will be purified by the fire of judgment, improved, and renewed, but not completely destroyed.
Indeed, Heaven above and Earth below will burn only to the extent they have been defiled by the wickedness of humans and demons together.
Therefore, according to Solomon's judgment, the Earth will stand forever.
As stated in the book of Ecclesiastes chapter one, it will never be destroyed; however, it will be renewed and improved.
What did Solomon mean when he said: The sun rises and sets, and returns to its place, and there it rises again, circles to the south, and turns to the north (Ecclesiastes 1:5-6)?
Who doesn't know that the sun rises and sets, and through paths unknown to us, returns to its place where it rose, so it may rise again?
This is why Solomon says this: to show that the sun itself, which is given to people for the light of day, by its changing nature—its rising and setting—daily signifies the end of this world.
Through these changes of time, and through the rising and setting of stars, Solomon teaches that human life also rises and sets daily.
What does the sun spiritually signify here?
The true sun, the Lord Jesus Christ, is the sun of justice.
The prophet says:
"For you who fear God, the sun of justice will rise"
Malachi 4:2.
This sun of justice rises every day for those who fear Him, meaning His faithful, the holy and pious people.
However, it sets at noon for false prophets, meaning heretics and bad Catholics, because their sins cause them to lose the light of His grace.
It also sets for unbelievers, as they do not deserve to be enlightened by the light of faith.
What does it mean when it says:
All rivers run into the sea, yet the sea is not full;
To the place where the rivers come from, there they return again to flow once more
Ecclesiastes 1.
Who knows that the rivers return to their place to flow again?
Ecclesiastes, that is, Solomon, knew through the grace of the Holy Spirit.
But our Ecclesiastes, namely Jesus Christ, who is the creator of those waters, through the power of divinity by which he is equal to God the Father, fully knows that rivers, because they flow into the sea, descend into the abyss and return to the sources of springs through hidden channels, bubbling up again from the mother abyss.
Spiritually, though, what do these rivers signify?
These rivers symbolize holy preachers.
When they shine with virtues and their teachings sparkle, they truly become rivers.
They nourish the dry land of carnal hearts with their holy preaching and actions, producing the fruits of good works.
How do these rivers flow back to the place from which they come?
Holy preachers, in all their teachings and actions, always return to the praise of their Creator.
They give thanks and praise to the Lord, their author, through whom they received the ability to do such things and all their good.
They constantly go back to the true source of light to prevent themselves from withering and drying up.
They receive from it the water of knowledge and the grace of virtues, so they can be replenished with good works and pour the streams of spiritual doctrine into the hearts of others.
All the faithful are like rivers, returning to the place from where they came.
Through holy desires, they return to the love of their Creator and give thanks and praise for all the good they have received from Him.
So, why did Solomon dedicate his heart—meaning he diligently applied himself with a concerned heart—to understand wisdom and knowledge, as well as mistakes and foolishness?
Ecclesiastes, Chapter One
It's certainly good to understand wisdom and knowledge, but what benefit is there in understanding mistakes and foolishness?
Just as it's important to know wisdom and teachings, it's equally valuable to understand errors and foolishness.
True wisdom begins with freeing oneself from foolishness, and no one can achieve this without first understanding it.
Similarly, no one can avoid mistakes unless they recognize them.
In earthly matters, many harmful things exist, teaching us wisdom as we learn to avoid them.
Why was Solomon equally eager to understand wisdom and knowledge, as well as errors and foolishness?
So, while he seeks some things and avoids others—meaning he goes after good things and avoids bad things—his true wisdom is proven.
What does Solomon mean when he says: "For in much wisdom there is much vexation, and he who increases knowledge increases sorrow" Ecclesiastes 1:18?
How is there much vexation in having a lot of wisdom?
Therefore, with much wisdom comes much indignation.
The more wisdom a person gains, the more they become frustrated with themselves, grieving over their vices and sins and their lack of virtues.
As a person grows in wisdom, they become more upset with themselves for their past wrongdoings, feeling sorrow and grief over their sins.
Consequently, they also add to their toil.
The more they understand heavenly and eternal matters, the more they labor with sorrow and tears to escape the traps of errors and free themselves from the misery of this world.
Why does it say:
aɪ said laughter is foolish, and to joy I said, 'Why are you deceived in vain?
'"
(Ecclesiastes 2),
when it is natural for humans to laugh, and the Lord in the Gospel says:
"Rejoice and be glad, for your reward is great in heaven"
(Matthew 5; Luke 6)?
Solomon does not criticize natural laughter, which is modest and honest.
Hence, elsewhere he says: A wise man will laugh quietly (Ecclesiasticus 21).
But he calls uncontrolled and excessive laughter a mistake; such laughter is called "cachinnus."
Similarly, he refers to not spiritual but temporal joy as a deception.
Those who do not mourn their past mistakes, nor understand the downfall caused by their sins, laugh loudly and rejoice in temporary things.
They think new and brief pleasures are eternal, and thus, deceived by the sweetness of the present life, they are troubled daily by the errors of this world.
What does it mean when it says: I saw vanity and affliction of spirit in everything, and nothing lasts under the sun
Ecclesiastes
2:4, 6, 8, and 12?
How can it say that nothing lasts under the sun when earlier it said: But the earth stands forever
Ecclesiastes
1:4?
Nothing under the sun will last forever, for everything is vanity.
In the Gospel, the Lord says: "Heaven and earth will pass away" (Matthew 24).
However, the earth will stand forever, not because it won't be destroyed, but because it will be renewed, as mentioned earlier.
Why does it say,
"A wise person's eyes are in their head, but a fool walks in darkness"
(Ecclesiastes 2)?
Aren't the fool's eyes also in their head?
The eyes here are not physical but spiritual: specifically, the eyes of the mind, meaning the senses and intentions of the soul.
By the head, Christ is signified, as the Apostle says: The head of the man is Christ First Corinthians 11.
The eyes of a wise man are on his head because a wise man directs all his intentions toward Christ, places them in Christ, and always lifts the eyes of his mind to meditate on heavenly things.
But a fool walks in darkness, obscured by his foolishness, the darkness of his sins, and the love of this world.
He hates heavenly things and, unlike a wise man, cannot lift his eyes to heaven because he focuses on worldly things rather than the things of God.
So, what exactly distinguishes a wise man from a foolish one?
This is different because one is illuminated and adorned with wisdom and clarity, while the other is darkened and disturbed by the errors of their foolishness.
Indeed, the difference between a wise person and a fool is as great as the difference between day and night, light and darkness.
How much difference is there between the wise and the foolish when the same fate awaits both?
The learned die just as the unlearned, the wise just as the foolish.
Ecclesiastes chapter 2
Even though everyone faces the same end, and the wise person's death is similar to the foolish person's, and often the wise suffer more in this life; nevertheless, their memory won't be the same in the future, nor will they receive equal rewards.
Because on the day of judgment, the wise will be elevated to the glory of the heavenly kingdom, while the foolish will be plunged into the eternal torments of damnation.
Who is this wise person who stands out from the fool as light differs from darkness?
Is it the one who excels in philosophical learning or shines with the eloquence of liberal arts?
Sometimes worldly wisdom goes against God's teachings, and even though carnal wisdom may be adorned with eloquence, it lacks spiritual fruit and the promise of eternal happiness.
True wisdom lies in loving the Lord, keeping His commandments, and striving to fulfill His will in all things, as much as human frailty allows.
This is reflected in the scripture: "To the person who pleases Him, God gives wisdom, knowledge, and happiness" (Ecclesiastes 2:26).
So, he immediately adds:
But to the sinner, he gave affliction and unnecessary worry.
If God gave the sinner unnecessary worry and concern, then why does he continue to sin despite being troubled by these worries and concerns of temporal things?
The cause of excessive worry and anxiety isn't in God, but in the one who sinned by their own choice.
Because of their sins, they deserved to experience excessive worry and anxiety.
So, when it is said, "But to the sinner, He gave excessive worry," it means that God allowed it to be given because they were a sinner.
What does he mean when he says:
Everything has its time
(Ecclesiastes 3)?
If everything has its time, does the essence of the eternal Divinity experience time?
Absolutely not; the ineffable, eternal essence of divine majesty, which created everything out of nothing, is not confined by place, constrained by time, or limited by any space.
Therefore, Solomon, to clarify his point, immediately adds, saying,
And all things under heaven pass away in their own times.
He wants to show that everything in the world is contradictory and nothing is permanent among all things under heaven; these things are bound by time.
What planting is he talking about, or what uprooting does he mean when he says:
"There is a time to plant, and a time to uproot what is planted"
(Ecclesiastes 3:2)?
Is he referring to planting or uprooting trees or herbs?
No, but concerning the birth and death of people:
For what was said earlier, "A time to be born," is the same as what follows, "and a time to plant"; because planting is the same as being born.
What was said previously, "a time to die," is the same as what follows here, "a time to uproot what is planted"; because uprooting is the same as dying.
Only God knows the beginning and end of people, that is, the time to be born, the time to die, the time to plant, and the time to uproot.
He established both the time when each person would be born and planted in life, and the time when they would die and be uprooted from this life.
This is determined by the decree of death.
What does it mean when it says again:
A time to kill and a time to heal
(Ecclesiastes Chapter 3, Verse 3)?
There is no doubt that the time to heal is granted by God.
However, God never established a time to kill another.
Once a man has killed, he can never heal the one he has killed.
Certainly not; only He who speaks through Moses has the time for killing and the time for healing, saying:
"I will kill and I will make alive; I will wound and I will heal" (Deuteronomy 32).
He sets the time when sinners are killed and the sick are healed, meaning those weakened by sins.
He kills when He afflicts sinners with bodily weakness or worldly adversity so that they may be corrected, die to their sins, and live for God.
Often, God chastises the wicked to kill and heal them, so they may cease to be what they are and begin to be what they are not.
Therefore, there is a time for healing when Almighty God, through hidden inspiration, touches the hearts of those He has killed—mercifully afflicted with adversities—and calls them to repentance.
What destruction or building is he referring to when he says:
"A time to tear down and a time to build up" (Ecclesiastes 3:3)?
Is he perhaps talking about the construction and demolition of houses?
What benefit would it be for us to know this?
After all, who doesn't know that some people destroy houses while others build them?
Solomon here is not talking about houses, but about the destruction of evil and the building up of good.
It's necessary to first destroy evil and then build up good, as the Psalmist says:
"Turn away from evil and do good" (Psalm 37).
Therefore, he says there is a time to destroy evil and a time to build up good.
In this present life, we are given time by God to destroy evil and build up good.
First, through repentance, we erase sins in ourselves; and then, through holy desires, we construct the buildings of virtues.
Why does it say: A time to weep, and a time to laugh; a time to mourn, and a time to dance (Ecclesiastes 3)?
Who doesn't know that we weep at one time and laugh at another?
And what was the purpose of saying, a time to dance?
Did he mean we should indulge in the frivolities of dancing?
God forbid; we should not behave foolishly.
This present life is for weeping, and the future life is for laughing.
So, whoever cleanses themselves daily with tears and weeping now will laugh in the future life—they will rejoice.
Similarly, this present life is for mourning, while the blessed life is for dancing.
When we dance, we show the joy in our minds and the affection in our spirits.
Therefore, whoever strives to wipe away sins through mourning in this life will dance in the future—they will be happy and rejoice in the glory of eternal happiness.
What does it mean when it says: Ecclesiastes 3:5?
A time to scatter stones, and a time to gather them.
What good is it to scatter stones, or what good is it to gather them, unless perhaps someone wants to build a house?
Solomon doesn't mention this reason, but rather talks about the dispersion and gathering of the nations.
By stones, he means nations.
That's why John says, "God is able to raise up children for Abraham from these stones" (Matthew 3).
Before the coming of the Lord, there was a time of scattering stones because the Gentiles did not stay united in faith.
Turning away from God, they worshiped various gods and served different idols, causing their dispersion.
However, after the coming of the Lord, there was a time for gathering stones.
As the Apostle says, "When the fullness of time had come, God sent His Son, born of a woman, born under the law, to redeem those who were under the law, so that we might receive adoption as children" (Galatians 4).
That's when He began to gather stones.
After completing the mystery of His passion and resurrection, He sent His apostles into the world, saying, "Go, teach all nations, baptize them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit" (Matthew 28).
Then, after celebrating His ascension into heaven on the fortieth day, the fame of His name spread far and wide through the apostles.
Stones, meaning the Gentiles who were scattered by various idolatries, were gathered.
Repenting and turning away from idols, they came together in the unity of faith.
Why does it say again:
There is a time for love and a time for hate;
yet the apostle John says:
Whoever hates his brother is a murderer First John three;
and in the Gospel, it is said:
Whoever hates his life in this world will keep it for eternal life John twelve;
likewise:
Whoever does not hate his father and mother, brothers and sisters, wife and children, and even his own life, cannot be my disciple Luke fourteen.
So tell me, when is the time for love, and when is the time for hate?
Now is the time for love because, after the Lord, we must love our father, mother, wife, children, and other relatives.
But there is also a time for hate because, for the sake of confessing Christ, we must scorn and even hate our father, mother, and all relatives if they are against us in the way of the Lord, as the holy martyrs are often read to have done.
What does it mean when it says: "A time for war and a time for peace" (Ecclesiastes 3)?
How can there be a time for war when the Lord says in the Gospel: "Agree with your adversary quickly, while you are on the way with him;"
and also: "If anyone slaps you on your right cheek, turn to him the other also, and if anyone wants to take your tunic, let him have your cloak as well" (Luke 6)?
Truly, as long as we are in this life, it is always a time of war and struggle.
We constantly need to fight against the traps of the ancient enemy and defeat the powers of the air—that is, evil spirits.
However, the time of peace will come when we leave this world.
If we have fought well here, we will be crowned in the future and rest in eternal peace in the heavenly Jerusalem.
Why does it say that God made everything good in its time, when earlier it said that everything is vanity?
If everything is vanity, how can they be good?
Everything is fleeting because it is temporary.
However, all things are good because they are created by God and indeed are good, but only in their proper time.
It is good to stay awake, and it is also good to sleep.
But always staying awake or always sleeping is certainly not good.
Why does Solomon speak hesitantly, saying:
"Who knows if the spirit of the children of Adam ascends upward, and the spirit of the animals descends downward?"
Ecclesiastes 3.
For who does not know that the spirit of the animals
(that is, livestock and all other brute animals)
perishes together with the body?
But the spirit of the children of Adam
(that is, humans)
does not perish with the body; rather, as soon as it leaves the body, it is either taken to glory or plunged into punishment.
Earlier, Solomon demonstrated that, in terms of physical usefulness, there is no difference between an animal and a human.
Just as an animal dies, a human dies too.
However, to highlight the difference in the value of their souls, he said:
"Who knows if the spirit of the children of Adam goes upward, and the spirit of the animals goes downward?"
(Ecclesiastes 3:21).
This indicates that the only difference between humans and animals is that the human spirit ascends to heaven, while the spirit of an animal or livestock descends to the earth, as it dies and dissolves along with its flesh.
So why does Solomon say:
"Who knows?"
as if no one can understand this!
Therefore, he says: Who knows? to show the difficulty of the matter.
For who in the sacred Scriptures usually signifies not impossibility but difficulty or rarity.
Just as in this:
But who shall declare his generation
(Isaiah 53)?
This means, either no one, or very rarely.
For what is impossible cannot be done at all, even with great effort.
Therefore, he says: Who knows?
because a spiritual person who can perfectly understand at the moment when the spirit leaves the body, whether it ascends or is led to punishment, is very rare or certainly difficult to find.
What do these sons of Adam, or those beasts, mean spiritually?
The sons of Adam represent holy and chosen men, who are rightly called humans because they live rationally, holy, and spiritually.
On the other hand, animals represent the carnal ones, who are called animals because they live in a bestial and carnal way, like beasts and livestock.
Hence, the holy prophet David says: "You save humans and animals, Lord" (Psalm 36).
It often happens that those who seem to be righteous humans sin, turn away from their righteousness, and commit iniquity; conversely, those who are wicked and impious turn away from their iniquity and do justice and equity.
Therefore, Solomon says: "Who knows if the spirit of the sons of Adam rises upward and the spirit of animals goes downward?"
Because the state of this life is so uncertain, the sinner who is called an animal may rise and ascend to heaven through repentance, and the righteous one may fall into sin from his righteousness and be submerged into hell.
What does it mean when it says: A fool folds his hands and eats his own flesh (Ecclesiastes 4)?
Who would be so foolish as to eat their own flesh?
This fool, this lazy person, is described in Proverbs:
"The lazy person buries their hand in the dish, and won't even bring it back to their mouth"
(Proverbs 19).
This lazy and foolish person folds their hands and consumes their own flesh, preferring to live in idleness and laziness
with a handful of grain, rather than working to earn their food.
However, "consumes their own flesh" is an exaggeration.
What is hyperbole?
Hyperbole is an exaggerated statement or claim not meant to be taken literally.
It's often used for emphasis or to make a point.
For example, when someone says, "I'm so hungry I could eat a horse," they don't actually mean they could consume an entire horse.
They're just expressing that they're very hungry.
Hyperbole can be found in many forms of communication, from everyday conversations to literature and even the Bible.
In the Bible, hyperbolic language is used to convey strong emotions or emphasize the significance of an event or teaching.
For example, in the Book of Psalms, it says, "My tears have been my food day and night" (Psalms 42:3).
This doesn't mean that the person is literally eating tears.
It means they are deeply sorrowful.
Another example can be found in First Corinthians, where Paul says, "I have become all things to all people so that by all possible means I might save some" (First Corinthians 9:22).
Paul isn't claiming to have actually transformed into different people.
Rather, he's emphasizing his efforts to relate to others in various ways to share the gospel.
Understanding hyperbole helps us appreciate the depth and emotion behind these statements.
It's a powerful tool for communication that, when used appropriately, can leave a lasting impact.
Hyperbole is when you say something unbelievable.
So, how is it said in exaggeration, ɪɡˌzædʒəˈreɪʃən? "He eats his own flesh?"
It's hard to believe anyone would eat their own flesh.
But to highlight just how lazy this fool is, it says, "He eats his own flesh." This shows the fool would prefer to let his body waste away in starvation and misery rather than support himself through hard work.
Who is the one that Solomon talks about?
There is one, and he has no second, no son, no brother, yet he never stops working, and his eyes are never satisfied with riches.
He is the one who, being alone and without a second—that is, without a son, brother, or any relative—never stops working.
He is constantly gathering wealth, yet never gathers enough to satisfy himself.
Therefore, it is the greatest vanity to amass wealth and not know to whom you will leave it.
Who does the one with no spiritual equal signify?
The Lord Jesus Christ, by nature, is the only Son of God the Father and the only one who descended from heaven to redeem the human race.
How can someone not have a son or brother when, through holy baptism, all Christians become children of God and brothers of our Lord Jesus Christ?
He is the only true and natural Son; all others are adopted, making them his brothers not by nature, but by grace.
So, why doesn't this one stop working?
Because He patiently endures our sins and mercifully waits for us to repent, He intercedes for us every day with God the Father.
Why aren't his eyes satisfied with riches?
Because he always wants what's best for us.
Who is this threefold cord that Solomon speaks about?
A threefold cord is not easily broken. Ecclesiastes 4:12.
The unity of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit; there are three persons in divinity, but only one nature.
Why then does he say, "It is difficult to break"? For something difficult can still be done, though with great effort. So, can this cord be broken?
Truly never, because the nature of the Holy Trinity is indivisible.
In this case, "difficult" should be understood as "impossible," because the nature of the Divinity cannot be divided.
Who is that poor and wise boy that Solomon talks about:
"A poor and wise boy is better than an old and foolish king"
(Ecclesiastes chapter 4)?
The Lord Jesus Christ is called a child because of His innocence and simplicity.
He did not sin, nor was deceit found in His mouth First Peter two.
Although He was rich, He became poor for our salvation.
He is truly wise, because in Him dwells all the fullness of divinity in bodily form.
Who is that old, foolish king?
The devil, who has ruled over humanity since nearly the beginning of time, is often called an old man.
He's truly a foolish king because the more he deceives, the greater the punishment he brings upon himself.
In the realm of this old and foolish king, the devil, a remarkable child was born—our Lord Jesus Christ, who became the King of kings and the Lord of lords.
What does it mean when it says, "Watch your step when you enter the house of God"?
Is it warning us to be careful not to trip over stones when we enter the house of God, meaning the church?
Even though we should always enter the house of God with honesty, fear, and silence, it teaches us to guard not just the foot of the body, but the foot of the soul.
This means the step of the mind, so that we may offer pure prayers in the sight of God.
The idea is that when you enter the house of God that is, the church guard your foot, meaning the step of your mind, so you do not stumble with evil thoughts.
This ensures that your prayer may be directed purely to God.
What does it mean when it says, "Do not let your mouth lead you into sinning" (Ecclesiastes 5)?
How can a person let their mouth cause their body to sin?
When someone speaks empty words and lustful talk that incite the flesh to sin.
But the true meaning of this passage is:
Do not let your mouth lead your flesh to sin; in other words, do not make empty excuses that give your flesh a chance to sin.
Do not say: It is not I who sin, but the sin that dwells in me, referring to the weakness of my flesh.
Because if you say this, you provoke the Lord to anger, as if He were the author of wickedness and sin.
What does it mean when it says, "All of a person's labor is for their mouth, yet their soul is not satisfied" in
Ecclesiastes 6:7?
How can everything a person works for be just for their mouth?
The wise and learned churchman dedicates himself to his words.
Everything he learns from the Holy Scriptures, he meditates on daily, preaches, and teaches.
His soul will never be completely satisfied because what he has learned is never enough for him.
He always desires and strives to learn more and more.
What does it mean when it says: "It is better to see what you desire than to long for what you don't know" (Ecclesiastes 6:9)?
How can a person see what they desire, or how can they long for what they don't know?
The person who uses their mind to distinguish between good and evil sees that they desire good and reject evil.
However, the one who follows their heart and desires often wishes for what they don't understand, because they want to grasp what they cannot.
About this, Solomon says:
"Who is to come has already been named, and it is known that he is a man."
The Lord Jesus Christ, whose name was foretold in the Holy Scriptures, took on flesh from the Virgin.
The prophets and saints of God knew that a true man was going to come.
If this is said about the Lord Jesus Christ, what does it mean when it follows with: And he cannot argue against someone stronger than himself in judgment?
Who is this stronger one that the Lord Jesus cannot argue against in judgment?
God the Father is stronger because the Son, in His humanity, is lesser than the Father.
What does it mean when it says, "Anger is better than laughter" in Ecclesiastes chapter 7, when laughter is natural, but anger is a vice?
Anger isn't always a vice; sometimes, it's a virtue.
When we get angry at ourselves or at others who are sinning, this kind of anger is better than laughter.
Laughter can weaken the mind, and joy can corrupt a person's spirit.
However, this type of anger can correct and amend sin.
What does it mean when it says: "Slander troubles the wise person and destroys their strength of heart" (Ecclesiastes 7:7)?
For someone who is truly wise is not troubled by any slander, nor brought down by any adversity.
The wise person in this passage should not be seen as someone who is perfect and complete in wisdom, but rather as someone who has just begun to acquire wisdom and is still imperfect.
Such a wise person can be easily disturbed and lose the strength and courage of their soul due to human slander or some adversity.
They become troubled with impatience when they do not endure adversities patiently.
What does it mean when people say that the earlier days were better than the times we live in now?
Therefore, it's not appropriate to say this, because he himself said: Such a question is foolish.
It's a silly question to ask:
Why were the old days better than now?
Ecclesiastes 7:10
Therefore, it's a foolish question because there's one God who is the creator of all time and all days.
Even though there is one God, the creator of all times and all days, aren't there good times and bad times?
Indeed, they existed, but virtues bring us good times.
Vices and sins bring bad times.
So, we should always live well to make the present days better than the past ones.
What does Solomon mean when he says, "Do not be overly righteous, and do not make yourself too wise" Ecclesiastes 7?
What harm is there if a person is very righteous, or who can be wiser than necessary?
He is excessively just when his justice is harsh and cruel, causing others to complain and murmur.
For example, someone who sees his brother sinning and prefers to condemn and punish him rather than guide him to repentance is certainly excessively just.
How does a person know more than they need to?
When someone thinks arrogantly, the Apostle advises:
Do not be proud.
Romans
11,
meaning do not think arrogantly, but be afraid.
A person thinks more than necessary when they try to understand things that are beyond their grasp.
Why does Solomon say, "Whoever fears the Lord neglects nothing,"
Ecclesiastes
7:18,
while the apostle James says, "We all stumble in many ways,"
James
3:2?
Did James or the other apostles not fear God, since they confessed that they stumble in many ways?
They were genuinely afraid and made many mistakes, because no one on earth does good without sinning.
So, how can it be true then when it says: "Whoever fears the Lord, neglects nothing."
Ecclesiastes 7:18.
Those who possess a holy and pure fear of God neglect nothing.
They are neither uplifted by prosperity nor cast down by adversity.
Whatever happens to them does not sadden them.
So, who is the one who truly has the holy and pure fear of God?
Who does not want to offend the Lord in any way,
and as far as he is able,
strives to fulfill His will and commandments in everything.
What does it mean when it says:
"Wisdom strengthens the wise more than ten rulers of the city"
Ecclesiastes 7:19?
What is this wisdom, or who are these rulers?
Wisdom in this context signifies the Lord Jesus Christ, who is the power and wisdom of God.
The princes of the city are understood to be holy angels, the princes of the heavenly Jerusalem.
They are also the princes of the Church, as they govern and protect it every day.
So, why are they called the ten?
There were ten orders of angels, but one fell due to pride.
As a result, the good angels work towards fulfilling this number with humans, aiming to reach the perfect number, which is ten.
How does wisdom strengthen the wise more than ten rulers of a city?
Because the wisdom of the Lord Jesus Christ is greater than that of the angels.
What does Solomon mean when he says,
"I
found one man among a thousand, but
I
did not find a woman among them all"?
Were there not many holy women, both virgins and widows, who pleased God with their chastity and good works, many of whom were crowned with martyrdom?
Indeed, there have been, and still are, many virgins and widows acceptable to God.
But Solomon says this because, in his time, he could scarcely find one good man among many.
Among women, he found none, as they all led him not to virtue, but to indulgence.
Can we interpret this sentence on a spiritual level?
It can truly be, for by man is meant a good thought of the mind, while by woman is meant a carnal and dissolute thought.
Therefore, among one thousand men, one is found, that is, one pure and clean thought which is not disturbed by perverse thought, that is, not polluted externally; but among women, none is found that pleases God, because a carnal and perverse thought is not acceptable to God.
What does it mean when it says, "Whoever keeps God's command will experience nothing bad" (Ecclesiastes 8)?
How can those who keep God's commands experience nothing bad, when holy men who followed God's commandments have endured many hardships in this world?
It's true that anyone who follows God's commandments—everything He has commanded and instructed—will not face any evil in the future.
This means they won't suffer harm or endure any evil on the day of judgment.
While they might face some challenges in this life, these are light and temporary.
However, in the afterlife, those who attain the glory of eternal happiness will experience no evil.
What does it mean when it says, "A living dog is better than a dead lion" in Ecclesiastes 9?
What is Solomon referring to with a living dog or a dead lion?
A living dog represents the Gentile people, while a dead lion symbolizes the Jewish people abandoned by God.
This living dog is better before God than the dead lion, because we who believe from the Gentiles, alive through faith, recognize God the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
A living dog can also be seen as a sinner who acknowledges being dead in sins; and through repentance, begins to live righteously.
A dead lion, on the other hand, represents a righteous person who relies on their own righteousness and boasts of their merits; and thus, lifted by pride, is dead before God.
Therefore, a humble sinner corrected by repentance is better than a proud righteous person.
The former is acceptable to God, while the latter is abominable.
What does it mean: "Let your clothes always be white, and do not let oil be lacking on your head" (Ecclesiastes 9)?
Can anyone always have white clothes?
And if someone is wealthy enough to always have white clothes, which is very difficult, how can it be that oil never runs dry on their head?
Who could bear to always have anointed oil on their head?
This statement should be understood not historically, but spiritually.
Clothing represents virtues with which the soul is dressed and adorned, while oil symbolizes the work of mercy, such as charity or spiritual joy.
The meaning is: Let your clothes always be white; that is, whatever good you do, be clean and pure, so it may be acceptable to God.
Never fail in works of mercy, and always strive to have spiritual joy.
What are the flies that Solomon refers to when he says, "Dead flies ruin the sweetness of it?"
(Ecclesiastes 10)
Surely, Solomon truly understands spiritual flies.
What are these spiritual flies?
Demons, vices, and sins: all these ruin the sweetness of the ointment here, which is the grace of the Holy Spirit.
What does it mean when it says:
"The heart of the wise is on their right, and the heart of the fool is on their left"
(Ecclesiastes 10:2)?
After all, who has their physical heart in their right or left hand?
Truly, no one should take this statement literally; it should be understood spiritually.
How can we understand it spiritually?
The heart represents intention or thought; the right hand represents good deeds; and the left hand represents evil deeds.
Therefore, the heart of a wise person is on their right hand, because their intentions and thoughts aim towards always doing good deeds.
So that on the day of judgment, they may be found at the right hand of the Lord, among the righteous, and may glory with them in eternal happiness.
However, the heart of a fool is on their left hand, because they accumulate evil thoughts and deeds.
For which, on the day of judgment, they will be placed on the left, among the wicked, and will be punished with them eternally.
Who is that spirit of whom it is said, "If the spirit of the ruler rises against you, do not leave your place?"
Who is this powerful being, whose spirit, if it rises against us, we should not abandon our position?
The devil, the ruler of this world, embodies an evil suggestion.
How does the spirit of the devil come upon us?
When the devil suggests bad thoughts, we shouldn't let them take root in our hearts.
Instead, we need to fight against them strongly to prevent these thoughts from turning into actions.
Think of it this way: if you possess humility, purity, chastity, patience, and love, and the devil tempts you with pride, lust, impurity, anger, and hatred, don't abandon your virtues.
For example, don't let go of humility and become proud.
This principle applies to all other virtues as well.
Why does Solomon say:
"Woe to you, land whose king is a youth, and whose princes feast in the morning?"
Wasn't the land of Israel blessed with a young king, namely David, who was thirty years old when he took the throne?
And wasn't Josiah a good king, who began to reign in his youth?
Truly, King David was good, and so was Josiah.
But woe to the land whose king is young, where wisdom is scarce and fragile, and worldly prudence follows youthful desires, hating justice, truth, and judgment.
How do princes eat breakfast?
The leaders eat in the morning when they lead a luxurious life.
Therefore, woe to the land whose leaders eat in the morning, for they cherish worldly pleasures and fleshly delights more than the well-being of the people.
By living in luxury, they distort judgment.
How blessed is the land whose king is noble and whose leaders eat at the proper time?
If the king is noble—distinguished by wisdom, shining with justice, and adorned with good morals and actions—truly blessed is the land he rules.
He governs it with judgment and fairness, and elevates justice.
Who are the princes that eat at the right time?
Certainly, those who avoid excess, who don't love worldly pleasures, and who live without gluttony and drunkenness, but seek food only for the body's sustenance: blessed is the land that has such leaders.
Because while they love justice and fairness, they surely do not pervert judgment.
What does it mean when it says:
"Give portions to seven, and also to eight"
(Ecclesiastes 11)?
What are those seven or eight portions we are commanded to give?
The number seven represents the Old Testament because of the Sabbath, the seventh day made holy by the law.
In contrast, the number eight signifies the New Testament due to the Lord's Day, the eighth day made holy by the resurrection of Jesus Christ.
How should we understand what he said: "Give portions to seven, and also to eight"
Ecclesiastes 11:2?
This means: hold both Testaments namely the Old and New in equal reverence by believing in them and diligently striving to fulfill their commandments.
What does it mean when it says:
"If a tree falls to the south or to the north, in whatever place it falls, there it will lie" (Ecclesiastes 11:3)?
Doesn't a tree that falls to the north or the south often get moved to other parts of the world?
No one doubts this, but this statement should be understood spiritually.
A man is represented by a tree because each person is like a tree in the forest of humanity.
The south wind, which is warm, symbolizes the peace of paradise.
The north wind, which is cold, symbolizes the torment of hell.
The meaning is: Wherever a person prepares their future home—if to the south, when they die, they will remain in the peace of paradise and the glory of the heavenly kingdom forever.
But if by living badly they prepare a place to the north, they will suffer the punishments of hell for all eternity.
What does it mean when it says, "Those who watch the wind will not sow, and those who look at the clouds will never reap" (Ecclesiastes 11)?
Who is so foolish to always watch the wind and not sow, or to always look at the clouds and never reap?
This sentence should be understood spiritually: just as wind and clouds often bring about storms, the devil is represented by the wind, and the adversities of this present world by the clouds.
Therefore, whoever fears the persecution of the devil or the adversities of this world does not sow, meaning they do not preach the word of God, nor do they perform the good works they are capable of, and they will never reap.
Because even if they start some good deeds, they do not bring them to completion.
What should be done then?
Without worrying about the clouds or fearing the winds, we must sow even in the midst of storms.
In other words, despite all adversities, we must preach the word of God and always do the good works that we are able to do.
What does it mean when it says, "In the morning, sow your seed, and in the evening, do not let your hands be idle" (Ecclesiastes 11:6)?
How can anyone always sow both in the morning and in the evening, especially when no one dares to sow during the freezing season?
In this context, "seed" shouldn't be thought of as grain or any other kind of seed. Instead, it represents the seed of good works, from which the fruit of justice grows, leading to the reward of eternal recompense.
So, what does it mean when it says: "In the morning sow your seed, and in the evening do not let your hands be idle"?
So that at no time, in no age, should we stop doing good works.
Let the evening find us with our morning righteousness, and let the rising sun add to our evening mercy.
In both youth and old age, the abundance of virtues always commends us to God.
Therefore, in the morning, sow your seed, and in the evening, do not let your hand be idle.
This means, always engage yourself in good works.
Ecclesiastes Eleven, Verse Six
What does it mean when it says, "And the almond tree will blossom, the locust will grow fat, and the caperberry will be scattered" (Ecclesiastes 12)?
Why mention this, when everyone knows that the almond tree blossoms, the locust grows fat, and the caperberry scatters?
This saying should be understood spiritually, and it holds a profound mystery.
The almond represents the Lord Jesus Christ.
Just as the almond consists of a shell, a stone, and a kernel, Christ consists of flesh, soul, and divinity.
The almond stone symbolizes divinity.
What do the locust and the caper bush represent?
Through the locust, the Gentile people; through the caper bush, the Jewish people.
How, then, should we understand this sentence?
The almond tree will bloom, signifying the birth of Christ and the miracles he will bring.
The locust will become fat, symbolizing that the Gentile people will believe and be filled with spiritual gifts.
The caper will be scattered, representing the Jewish people's downfall due to their unbelief.
Why are the words of the wise compared to goads and nails?
Solomon says,
"The words of the wise are like goads and like nails driven deep"
Ecclesiastes 12:11.
The words of the wise are best compared to nails and goads because they don't just gently touch the faults of sinners—they pierce them.
Truly wise individuals use their words as nails and goads.
They don't flatter sinners; instead, they rebuke them with stern reprimands.
These words prick the hidden parts of their conscience, causing pain and lamentation, leading to correction.
What does it mean when it says,
"What was given by one shepherd through the advice of teachers"
Ecclesiastes 12:11?
Who are these teachers through whose advice the wise words were given, or who is that one shepherd from whom they were given?
The teachers are the prophets and apostles.
There is one shepherd, God, from whom all the words of the wise were given.
He taught the teachers, that is, the prophets and apostles, and rebuilt their understanding, for He placed words in their hearts and mouths.
What does Ecclesiastes say at the end of his book?
Fear God and keep His commandments, for this is the whole duty of man.
How can it be that this is all there is to being human?
To fear God and observe His commandments?
Surely, a much larger portion of people neither fear God nor keep His commandments.
Truly, there are more bad people than good, because as the Lord says, "Many are called, but few are chosen." Matthew chapter twenty. The number of unbelievers far exceeds the number of believers.
What is Solomon trying to show us here?
This is evident in these words: there is no one who does not fear God and keep His commandments.
Why isn't he considered a man?
Because he doesn't adhere to the measure and reason of his nature.
What is the nature and condition of human nature?
To live reasonably, because among all living creatures, only humans were created as rational beings.
Humans received reason and understanding from God so they could recognize their Creator, love Him, fear Him, and praise Him with both heart and mouth.
What does it mean to fear God?
To carry out His will and accomplish the good things that need to be done.
So, if someone doesn't fear God and doesn't follow His commandments, what does that make them?
The beast is.
How can it be a beast when it has human substance and personality?
Although it seems to have human qualities and personhood,
since it lives not rationally but like an animal,
it should be called not a human but a beast.
What is the beast called?
If someone is cruel to their family, subjects, or neighbors, they are a lion, not a human.
If they are a thief, they are a tiger or a wolf.
If they are an adulterer, fornicator, or impure, they are a dog or a pig.
If they are foolish, they are compared to a donkey.
Therefore, if they are deceitful or a hypocrite, they are fittingly compared to a fox.
This pattern can be understood for other characteristics as well.
Who then is truly human?
The one who fears God and keeps His commandments.