Sermon on Predestination
by Florus Deacon of Lyon
Almighty God, being the one and only true God, knew everything in His eternal and unchanging knowledge before it happened.
As Scripture testifies, saying:
Eternal God, who knows hidden things, who knows everything before it happens (Daniel thirteen forty-two).
Therefore, without a doubt, He knew both the good actions of good people and the bad actions of bad people.
In the good, He made them good by His grace; in the bad, He did not make them bad—far from it; He only knew they would become bad by their own fault.
God's foreknowledge did not impose on them the necessity to be otherwise, but He, as God, foresaw from His almighty majesty that they would be so by their own will.
Hence, Scripture, indicating His unblemished justice to us, says of Him: He commanded no one to act wickedly, and gave no one space to sin.
Therefore, the wicked and unjust actions they commit, and the time of life in this world, which God gave them to do good, they turn to doing evil instead.
This is their fault, not God's, and thus they are rightly condemned by His justice.
This same almighty God also knew of their eternal damnation, but due to their own merit, as He foresaw they would persist in their own wickedness, not because of His, far from it, injustice.
He who establishes nothing unjustly, will render to each according to their works (Romans two six), that is, to those who do good, eternal rewards, and to those who do evil, perpetual punishment.
Therefore, He completely foresaw the good, and by His grace they would be good in the future, and by the same grace would receive eternal rewards, that is, living well in the present age and being happily rewarded in the future, both by the gift of God's mercy.
Hence, the Apostle calls them vessels of His mercy, saying: to show the riches of His grace in the vessels of mercy, which He prepared for glory (Romans nine twenty-three).
Conversely, He foresaw the bad, by their own wickedness, would be bad in the future, and by His justice would be condemned to eternal punishment.
As he foresaw about Judas the betrayer, that he would betray him, as the Gospel says, when he was one of the twelve.
He also foresaw his eternal damnation when he said: "Woe to that man by whom the Son of Man is betrayed. It would have been better for him if that man had not been born." Mark 14:21. Likewise, he undoubtedly foresaw the wickedness of the impious Jews, about which he predicted in the psalm: "They gave me gall for my food, and for my thirst, they gave me vinegar to drink." Psalm 69:22. He also foresaw their subsequent damnation, about which he added in the same psalm: "Let them be blotted out of the book of the living, and not be written with the righteous." Psalm 69:28. But in these and in all the wicked, the first thing comes from their own depravity, and the second follows from divine justice. In this way, we must understand God's predestination entirely: that in the good, he predestined both their future goodness from the gift of his grace and their eternal reward for that goodness, so that by his gift they would become good and by his gift be rewarded. Hence the Apostle says: "He predestined us for adoption as sons through Jesus Christ." Ephesians 1:5. And in another place: "Those whom he foreknew he also predestined to be conformed to the image of his Son." Romans 8:29. Thus, he predestined his chosen ones, that they would now be taken up in adoption as sons of God through the grace of baptism and in the future become conformed to the image of the Son of God, renewed and glorified by the same grace of God according to his image. He predestined entirely that they would be good here, not from themselves, but from him; and blessed there, not through themselves, but through him. Therefore, in both cases, he foresaw and predestined his good in them and from them. But in the wicked and impious, almighty God did not predestine wickedness and impiety, that is, that they would be wicked and impious and could be nothing else. But those he foreknew and predestined to be wicked and impious by their own fault, he predestined to eternal damnation by his just judgment: not because they could not be anything else, but because they did not want to be anything else.
They, therefore, became the cause of their own destruction.
But God is a just judge and a fair ruler of that condemnation.
He did not predestine unjust things, but just ones.
He predestined both rewards for the righteous and punishments for the unjust because both are just.
The Apostle, commending His justice to us, says: "Is God unjust who inflicts wrath? By no means" (Romans 3:5).
And because He now grants patience to all, so they may turn to repentance, those who perish, perish by their own contempt and stubbornness.
They despised the great goodness of God.
He says again in another place: "Do you despise the riches of His goodness, forbearance, and patience, not knowing that the goodness of God leads you to repentance? But according to your hardness and your impenitent heart, you are storing up wrath for yourself in the day of wrath and revelation of the righteous judgment of God, who will render to each one according to his deeds" (Romans 2:4-6).
Hence, another Scripture also testifies, saying: "God did not make death, nor does He delight in the destruction of the living. But the ungodly, by their hands and words, have called it to themselves. Considering it a friend, they have fallen away and made a covenant with it because they are worthy to be of its party" (Wisdom 1:13, 16).
Therefore, the almighty God is not the cause of death or destruction for any human.
The ungodly bring upon themselves death and destruction by their own hands and words, while acting wickedly and persuading others to do the same, bringing damnation both to themselves and to others.
Loving the path of iniquity and destruction, they turn away from the right path and hasten towards eternal damnation.
Almost as if by mutual agreement, bound by wickedness, they rush forward, allied with death and enemies of eternal life.
According to their hardness and impenitent heart, they store up wrath for themselves on the day of wrath.
On that day of the righteous judgment of God, since each one receives according to his deeds, no one is condemned by God's prejudice but by the merit of their own iniquity.
He did not predestine anyone to be evil.
Instead, He truly predestined that every evil deed would not go unpunished.
Just as every just law does not create crime to remain just, it punishes the criminal to maintain justice.
Therefore, claiming that those who perish are predestined to perdition and that it cannot be otherwise, or that the righteous are saved because they are predestined to salvation, as if it could not be otherwise, is a confused and foolish notion.
It removes the merit of damnation from some and the merit of salvation from others.
By this reasoning, it implies that those who perish are forced to perdition and those who are saved are forced to salvation.
Thus, the former could not be justly condemned because they could never have been righteous, and the latter could not be justly rewarded because they could never have been anything but righteous.
In both cases, perdition and salvation would not result from their own actions but from the prejudice of divine predestination.
And where would that leave: "Who will repay each person according to what they have done?" Romans 2:6. And again: "Is God unjust in bringing His wrath on us? Certainly not!" Romans 3:5.
Indeed, if God predestined some to destruction so that they could not be otherwise, the cause of their perdition would be attributed to Him, which is a horrible blasphemy to think or say. But the faith of the Catholic Church, whose children and followers we must be, teaches us firmly, as indicated above according to the authority of Holy Scripture, that God, in His omnipotence, foreknew their wickedness because it comes from them. He did not predestine it because it does not come from Him. However, He foreknew their punishment because He is God and predestined it because He is just, so that in them there is the merit of their damnation, and in Him, the power and judgment of just condemnation.
For God does not predestine anything except what He Himself will do. He foreknew many things that He Himself will not do, such as all evils, which are certainly done by the wicked, not by Him.
The wicked do not perish because they couldn't be good, but because they didn't want to be good.
By their own fault, they became vessels of wrath fit for destruction Romans 9:22.
They persisted and remained in a state of condemnation, either original or actual.
But for the good, as has been shown above, Almighty God foreknew and predestined both aspects: that they would be good in the present life through His grace and also blessed in the future.
For He is the author and giver of both their present and future goodness.
Therefore, without a doubt, He is the foreknower and predestinator of both.
Because they, by themselves, not only could have been different but indeed were different before they were made righteous by Him who justifies the ungodly.
Whether in those who are saved or in those who perish, personal will is rewarded or condemned.
But for the saved, because their will was healed by the grace of the Lord Savior to become good and upright from being evil and crooked, it is most worthily crowned.
For the damned, because they did not accept healing through the Savior, they will justly experience eternal condemnation by the same judge.
This, in short, is the whole truth about free will according to the Catholic faith: that God created every human being with free will.
But because sin entered the world through one man, and through sin, death, and so death spread to all men because all sinned Romans.
So, the free will of the entire human race, which was damaged and corrupted by that transgression, is now so blinded and weakened that it is only sufficient for man to do evil, to fall into iniquity, and can only be free for that purpose.
But for doing good, that is, exercising virtue and bearing the fruit of good works, it cannot rise and be strengthened unless it is renewed, enlightened, and healed by faith in the one Mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus, and the gift of the Holy Spirit.
As the Savior Himself promises in the Gospel, saying: "If the Son sets you free, then you will be truly free" (John 8:36).
And the Apostle says: "Where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is freedom" (Second Corinthians 3:17).
So, through this grace of Christ and the Spirit of Christ, human free will is liberated, enlightened, and healed.
It may joyfully proclaim with the Psalmist: "The Lord is my light and my salvation: whom shall I fear?" (Psalm 27:1).
Therefore, whoever desires to receive this grace of freedom, so that they may truly be free to live well and piously, should not rely on their own strength, but should faithfully entrust themselves to be healed and strengthened by Him, of whom the same Psalmist says: "The steps of a man are directed by the Lord, and He delights in his way" (Psalm 37:23).
Let them pray and plead with Him, saying: "Direct my steps according to your word, and let no iniquity have dominion over me" (Psalm 119:133).
And again: "Lord, lead me in your way, and I will walk in your truth" (Psalm 5:9).
I have briefly written these words to you in response to what you commanded.
Now I faithfully beseech and exhort you to be grounded in the simplicity and sincerity of true faith, and to close your ears against the wicked tongue of that most vain and miserable man, who, ready for contention and stubborn against the truth, preferred, in his wretchedness and inflated by a diabolical spirit, to separate himself from the Church of Christ and its priests, rather than abandon his profane and idle talk.