Against Greed Book Twoby Salvianus of Marseilles
We have discussed remedies for sins, or rather, the hopes for remedies and comforts.
The first step in seeking salvation is for the sinner to regret their mistake.
Then, according to the sacred word, to immediately redeem their sins with acts of mercy.
Finally, if they have not done this, at least not to leave anything untried when dying and to assist themselves with the final offering of their possessions.
But perhaps it might be said that if sinful people are bound by the necessity to redeem their crimes, then undoubtedly the saints, who are free from crimes, are not bound by this and thus do not need to give away their possessions because they do not need to redeem anything with generosity.
I hear this.
But we will see what this means soon.
Meanwhile, even if past wrongs do not need to be redeemed by everything a holy person owns, there are still eternal goods that they ought to obtain at a great cost.
We will discuss this more fully later.
For now, I say this freely and firmly assert that there is no one among the saints who is not indebted to God in many ways.
Thus, whatever they give to their Lord, they are not so much donating as repaying.
First, to speak of general blessings, whoever you may be, whether saint or rich person, you were born, raised, and educated by the goodwill and gift of God.
Provided with necessities for life, enriched with even non-necessities, given more by your Lord than what your needs required, extended His gifts beyond your hopes, and, which is the greatest and rarest, His gifts even surpassed your desires.
I add, however, after all these things, that the same Lord who first gave you birth by His gift, later also saved you by His suffering.
Indeed, for your sake, O man, the Lord of all things came to the earth and its dust—a small part of earth and dust.
He came to earth, advanced from flesh and in flesh, humbling Himself to the shame of human origin, the filth of swaddling clothes, and the lowliness of a manger.
He endured the unworthy sufferings of this life: the frail cycles of eating, drinking, sleeping, and waking, and the disgraceful necessities of this fleeting existence.
He even endured the foul company of those who interacted with Him—people stained with the mud of their sins, always guilty of a bad conscience, exuding the stench of their shameful deeds, and thus unable to grasp heavenly teachings.
They could not bear the light of sacred radiance because their eyes, darkened by sins, were overwhelmed by the brilliance of divine light.
And not only this.
But after all these things, add the stubborn contradictions of a proud people, add insults, add curses, impious persecution, false testimony, bloody judgment, mockery of the people, spitting, blows, extremely bitter punishments, and indignities even more bitter than the punishments—a crown of thorns, a cup of vinegar, food of gall, the Lord of all condemned by men, hanging on the cross for the salvation of the human race, God dying by the law of earthly condition.
Seeing that these things are so, whoever you are, whether you are holy or believe yourself to be holy, tell me, please: can these alone be repaid, even if nothing else is owed?
For no matter what a man endures for God, he can never repay what God endured for man.
Because even if the suffering itself does not differ in the kind of punishments, it must differ greatly in the diversity of those who suffer.
But perhaps you say that what we have mentioned is a general debt of all humanity, and in this, the entire human race is indiscriminately liable.
That is true.
But does anyone owe less just because another owes the same?
Or if one hundred promissory notes for one hundred sesterces each are written by one hundred people, does that relieve the debt of one person if all are debtors for the same amount?
The Apostle says, each person will carry their own load Galatians 6:5, and each will give an account of themselves.
Therefore, one person's burden is not lightened by another's burden, nor is a guilty person absolved by the company of many.
Similarly, the severity of a person's condemnation is not lessened even if they share their punishment with many accomplices.
As I mentioned before, although a debt may be general, it is undoubtedly specific for each individual; although it is common to all, it is particularly singular for each person.
Thus, what applies to everyone equally does not reduce the amount owed by each person.
For just as Christ suffered for all, so too did He suffer for each individual.
He gave Himself entirely to everyone and entirely to each individual.
Therefore, whatever the Savior granted through His passion, the entire amount is owed by all and by each person individually; and in some sense, each individual owes more than the totality since each received as much as everyone together.
Where one person receives the same as everyone, even if the measure is equal, the envy is greater.
Thus, even though one receives the same, they seem to owe more because they are compared to everyone.
These things should be said up to this point because some of the saints do not consider themselves debtors to God, as they cannot estimate the debt.
But perhaps someone will say: The saints are not debtors, but the debts of secular people are much greater because they have more sins.
This is like someone saying: I am innocent because someone else is more guilty; I am just because another is unjust; I am exceptionally good because another is singularly bad.
Firstly, it is improper for a holy mind to think that their goodness increases because of the evil of others, or to consider themselves better by comparison to the worse.
It is a most unfortunate form of consolation to take solace in the miseries of sinful people, while the Apostle commands us to rejoice with those who rejoice and weep with those who weep Romans 12:15.
And do not think only about what is best for yourselves, but also about what is best for others.
Philippians 2:4
Now, let's say this kind of comparison seems fair and honest: can it also be considered trustworthy?
Who can be truly certain about that great and terrifying future judgment of God?
Or who can say: I owe less, he owes more?
Finally, who can presume about themselves or despair about others?
For we all, says the Apostle, will stand before the judgment seat of Christ.
Romans 14:10
And each one will carry their own burden.
Galatians 6:5
So, someone might ask, is there no difference between the saints and sinners?
There is a great difference, indeed almost immeasurable.
But because Scripture says: Blessed is the one who is always fearful.
Proverbs 28:14
And the wise person's mind is never secure about their own salvation;
Although there is a great difference between saints and sinners, I still ask everyone who professes religion:
Who among you is sufficiently holy according to your own conscience?
Who is not fearful of the terrible severity of the future judgment?
Who is secure about their eternal safety?
And if that is not the case, as it should not be, tell me, I beg you, why does not anyone strive with all their might to redeem with the devotion of death whatever they have incurred through the offense of life?
Although I want all who read this to know that I am not speaking about all saints, but only those who, although they have not professed religion, still do not abandon their wealth.
For those who, free from all burdens, follow the way of the Savior, and imitate the Lord Jesus Christ not only in holiness but also in poverty, there is nothing more to say except what the prophet also said:
To me, your friends are highly honored, O God.
Psalm 138:17
For I honor all these people as imitators of Christ, I revere them as images of Christ, and I respect them as members of Christ, and only remember them so that I may be worthy of their memory.
But those things we mentioned above may seem to be injurious to the religious profession.
What then, someone might ask, if a wealthy widow does not leave her widowhood despite her great riches?
What if a virgin has vowed purity and is dedicated to maintaining an unblemished body?
What if a marriage is without marital relations, with the couple living as if they were not married?
What if a monk has been serving God since childhood?
What if a cleric completes the service of sacred ministry with diligent faithfulness?
Are these individuals also at risk of losing eternal salvation if they keep their wealth while living or die without giving anything to the needy?
I do not have the authority or words to pronounce judgment on such a matter.
Let us therefore see what the sacred scriptures and heavenly commandments say about this, and align our opinions according to God's standards.
First of all, no one should seek refuge in the comforts of old examples, suggesting that some saints were rich either under the law or before the law.
That time has passed, and the situation has changed.
Before the Law, everyone had the freedom to possess or pursue wealth because, at that time, heavenly prohibitions had not yet been established.
As the Apostle says, where there is no law, there is no transgression.
Romans 4:15
The Law has since made certain things forbidden, as stated: For I would not have known lust, says the Apostle, unless the Law had said: You shall not covet.
Romans 7:7
Therefore, the wealth that God did not condemn before the Law could be freely possessed by man.
Under the Law, a similar right was available to everyone: the Law did not entirely forbid a person from having what they desired, as long as it was obtained justly.
Thus, at that time, all the saints used their resources within the limits prescribed by the Law, walking, as we read, in all the commandments and ordinances of God without blame.
Luke 1:6
Just as those people themselves walked,
about whom these things are remembered, like the prophetess Anna, living in fasting and prayers; like Nathanael, praised as a true Israelite, and amazed with the Lord and God himself as a witness; like Tobias, who exceeded the commandments of the law with his great devotion, serving in the burial of dead men even at the risk of death, and helping the needy up to his own need.
He reached such a level of generosity that he allocated a portion of all his goods to his servant; and this, which is more remarkable, even though he was already wealthy; and, more miraculously, wealthy from being poor, because wealth after need almost always excites a greater desire to have more.
Such were the saints then, having everything according to the law, leaving everything according to the law.
And thus, everyone who adhered to the law was perfect, and as devoted as those under the law who did less, compared to now in the Gospel, who do more.
For then, the law was almost the Gospel.
Therefore, those who showed themselves obedient to the law back then, almost fulfilled the Gospel.
So now, no one should think they can take refuge in the law.
For as the Apostle says, the old things have passed away: behold, all things have become new.
Second Corinthians 5:17.
More indulgence and license existed back then.
Then, the eating of meat was proclaimed, now abstinence.
Then, in all life, there were very few days of fasting, now life is almost one continuous fast.
Then vengeance was available to the wronged, now patience.
Then the law was an ally to the angry, now it is an adversary.
Then it handed a sword to the accuser, now it offers charity.
Then even carnal temptation was indulged by the law, now the Gospel forbids even the gaze.
Then bodily pleasures had a certain license, now even the eyes are commanded to keep restraint.
Then the law allowed a husband to take many wives, now devotion to chastity binds him to exclude even one.
For the Apostle says, "The time is short. From now on, those who have wives should live as if they do not; those who weep, as if they do not weep; those who rejoice, as if they do not rejoice; those who buy, as if they do not possess; and those who use the things of the world, as if not engrossed in them. For this world, in its present form, is passing away" First Corinthians 7:29-31.
See how briefly the teacher sent by God has moderated everything and concluded everything within such perfection. He has not only cut off what is forbidden but also restricted what is permitted, trimming, as it were, the use of marriages, the unfaithfulness of tears, the intemperance of joys, the desire to possess, the greed of buying, and even the short and shadowy pleasure of this world.
And why all this? Why indeed, if not because, as he said, "this world in its present form is passing away"?
How far, then, are they from God's command, who, when God has ordered them to renounce their wealth while alive, instead desire to possess it even for their dead relatives? Or how far are they from the devotion that would disinherit themselves for God, who do not wish to disinherit even strangers for their own sake!
To such people, I would gladly and freely say: What madness is this, O most miserable ones! That you should make anyone else your heirs, but disinherit yourselves; that you should leave others wealthy, even for a short time, but condemn yourselves to eternal poverty.
But perhaps someone asks, what is it that God now demands more from Christians through the Gospel than from Jews before through the law? There is a clear reason for this. For we pay more to our Lord now because we owe more.
The Jews once had the shadow of things; we have the truth.
The Jews were slaves; we are adopted.
The Jews received the yoke; we have freedom.
The Jews received curses; we have grace.
The Jews had the letter that kills; we have the spirit that gives life.
A servant was sent to the Jews as a teacher; a son was sent to us.
The Jews crossed the sea to the desert; we enter the kingdom through baptism.
The Jews ate manna; we eat Christ.
The Jews had the flesh of birds; we have the body of God.
The Jews had the frost of heaven; we have the God of heaven.
Who, as the Apostle says, being in the form of God, humbled Himself to death, even death on a cross Philippians 2:6, 8.
He was not content with merely undergoing death for us, but He also endured the extreme suffering of voluntary execution.
Therefore, what can man offer in return for this, since Christ gave Himself for us through the utmost bitterness of punishment?
Or what worthy thing can man repay to the Lord, to whom he owes his redemption?
This is why the Lord wants us to be more devoted to Him, because He purchased our devotion at such a great price.
And so, the most blessed Paul says: Who shall separate us from the love of Christ?
Shall tribulation, or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or danger, or sword Romans 8:35?
The Apostle does not say that only money or riches are owed to God, but also tribulation, distress, famine, sword, suffering, the shedding of blood, the exhalation of the soul, and finally, death in every form of punishment.
Therefore, let all religious people understand that they do not give enough to God, even if they give all their possessions, because they owe themselves as well.
And so, as we began to say earlier, if there is a widow, let her not think that the name of widowhood alone is sufficient for eternal salvation, but let her see what kind of widow God commands in the Apostle, saying: The real widow, left all alone, puts her hope in the Lord and continues in prayers night and day.
But the widow who lives for pleasure is dead even while she lives First Timothy 5:5-6.
Under one and the same commandment, the Apostle expressed two forms of widowhood: one of life and the other of death, when he placed death in pleasures.
Therefore, without a doubt, he does not want someone to be rich where he cannot allow someone to be indulgent, because all the fruits of wealth are placed in the use of pleasures.
Otherwise, if the use of pleasures is removed, there is no reason to have wealth.
Since the Apostle mentioned that death lies in the pleasures of the widow, it is clear that he wants everything to be distributed for the benefit of eternal life, and does not want anything to be reserved for the use of death.
And so he says: "She who is truly a widow, left alone, has set her hope on the Lord" (First Timothy 5:5), teaching that it is not enough for a widow to not be indulgent or rich, unless she clings to God, is devoted to prayer, is desolate from all the allurements of the world, and through all these things is truly a widow.
If this is the case, any woman who wishes to be of life, not of death, should not think it sufficient to renounce both pleasures and riches for God's sake, unless she also earns through prayer and labor to be seen as truly a widow of God.
Because there is no doubt that as one clings to Christ in this world, so will they remain in the body of Christ, according to the saying: "My soul clings to you; your right hand upholds me" (Psalm 63:8).
This shows that only the soul that clings to God in this world will be upheld by the right hand of God in the future.
This, therefore, is the rule of widowhood.
For regarding those who have professed continence and are full of the Spirit of God, should anyone doubt that they would not want to serve their worldly heirs who have removed themselves from the world?
How could those who deny themselves to themselves dedicate anything belonging to them to others?
Endowed with such new virtue, and trampling underfoot the permitted and, what is more, experienced bodily pleasures with admirable austerity of continence, how could they not vow some of their possessions to God, who have made God dwell within themselves?
In my opinion, it could very well be said about such a marriage:
Rejoice, barren one who does not bear children; burst into song and shout, you who have not been in labor; because the children of the desolate woman are more than those of her who has a husband
Isaiah 54:1.
For barren is the one who does not give birth, and desolate is the one who has separated herself from all the lures of the world, and without a husband is the one who, while having a husband, is seen as not having one.
Who then would doubt that such married couples, while they live, live for God both in themselves and in their possessions, and when they depart from this life, they go to God with their wealth, to whom they have lived?
Otherwise, if any of them gives their possessions to the world and leaves them to the world, they have inscribed the name of religion in vain and seem to have always lived for the world to which they die.
So, these things are sufficient about married couples.
Let's move on to the sacred virgins, to whom the Savior himself prescribed the law of devotion
Matthew 25:1 and following, by the example of the ten virgins, of whom he says that the foolish ones are to be given to eternal punishment only because he knows they will lack the work of mercy.
By saying this, he very clearly taught how much he valued abundant mercy, without which he said even the virgin's purity would not benefit her.
But perhaps some deceive themselves and think it is enough for them if, having many great possessions, they at least give a little.
Nor do I deny that if this is the reasoning, it should be believed to be so.
Let little be given if giving little is sufficient.
But I do not know that giving little is sufficient: rather, I am certain that little is not sufficient.
If they know otherwise, let them know it for themselves.
I know one thing, that God says the lamps of the foolish virgins were extinguished for not having the oil of good works.
But you, whoever you are, do you think you have enough oil?
Those foolish virgins I spoke of surely thought so too.
For if they had not believed they had enough, they would have provided to have it.
For as the Lord said, when later they wished to borrow and sought it with all effort and ambition, without a doubt they would have sought it before if their confidence in having it had not deceived them.
And so, young woman, be careful not to think you have something you don't.
You share the same name and profession as others.
You are a virgin, and they were virgins too; you presume to be wise, and they did not think they were foolish.
You judge that you have light in your lamp, but they lost their light through the presumption of future light.
It is written that they prepared their lamps because they believed they would be illuminated.
And what more can be said?
I believe some light did shine in them.
When they feared their lamps would go out, they certainly had something to fear.
Their fear was not unfounded; their lamps were indeed extinguished, and they were blinded.
Integrity showed the light of virginity in them, but the substance of oil did not support it and failed.
From this, we understand that a little is almost nothing: it does no good to light a lamp that will immediately go out, nor does it help for something to shine if it is destined to set as soon as it rises, and to begin living only to start dying.
Clearly, therefore, a lamp needs to be worked on so that the light can last.
If the light in the lamps we use for a short time fades and fails unless oil is generously poured in, how much oil do you need for your lamp to shine eternally?
No one can reach eternal life if they think they have what they do not.
Foolish assumptions lead to perdition, not salvation.
As the Apostle says, "If anyone thinks they are something when they are nothing, they deceive themselves" (Galatians 6:3).
Unless, perhaps, you have had the measure of generosity revealed to you by God, and have the limits set by the Holy Spirit for giving, which you believe it would be a sin to exceed, and you judge it to be a kind of transgression if you are more religious than God commands you to be.
If this is the case, I do not forbid you to use the knowledge granted by Divinity.
But if this is as false as it is frivolous, what madness it is not to do everything you can with cautious and careful foresight, since you are completely unaware of what is necessary for your salvation?
It remains to say something about ministers and priests, although some things might be said unnecessarily.
For whatever is said about others undoubtedly pertains more to those who should be examples to everyone and who should surpass others in devotion as much as they surpass all in dignity.
Nothing is more disgraceful than for someone to excel in rank but be despicable in behavior.
What is authority without merit, if not a title of honor without substance?
Or what is dignity in an unworthy person, if not an ornament in the mud?
Therefore, all those who stand at the sacred altar must excel in merit as much as in rank.
If God has given such a perfect rule of life to ordinary men and weaker women, how much more does He command those to be perfect who must teach everyone to be perfect?
He wanted them to be such great examples that He bound them to a singular rule of life with the strictness of both the new law and the old law.
Although the old decree gave everyone ample opportunity to increase their wealth, it confined all Levites and priests within a certain limit of possession, permitting them to have neither fields, nor vineyards, nor any land at all.
From this, we can understand whether our God now wants His clerics living under the Gospel to leave worldly inheritances to their heirs when He did not even want those under the law to possess them.
Hence, the Savior Himself in the Gospel imposes the duty of perfection on them, not as a voluntary act but as a command.
For what do we read that He said to the young man, a layman?
"If you want to be perfect, go, sell what you have, and give to the poor" (Matthew 19:21).
But what about His ministers?
"Do not," he says, "possess gold, nor silver, nor money in your belts. Do not carry a bag for the journey, or two tunics, or sandals, or a staff."
Matthew 10:9-10.
Notice the significant difference in these words of God.
To the layperson, he said: "If you want to be perfect, sell what you possess."
But to the minister: "I do not want you to possess anything."
Yet, he thought it was not enough to take away the possession of greater wealth from him, unless he also took away the very bag from the apostle who was to undertake a long journey, and deprived him of having more than one tunic.
And what then?
This was still not enough.
He also commanded his servants to traverse the world with bare feet and took away their shoes even in the freezing cold.
What more can be said?
He snatched the bag from the apostle's hand and did not leave his ministers, who were to travel throughout the world, even the use of a single staff.
And after this, it is not enough for their successors, that is, for the deacons and priests, who are engaged in such great administration of divine matters, if they themselves are only rich, unless they also leave rich heirs.
Let us be ashamed of this unbelief, I ask.
Let it be enough for us that we seem to reject God up to the end of our lives.
Why do we act in such a way that we extend our contempt for him even after death?
We have spoken about the roles and duties of each.
And all this because, as we said above, some who have professed religion either think they do not owe their substance to the Lord as much as other worldly people do, or certainly think they owe less; whereas they ought to owe more.
Because the servant who knows his master's will and does not do it will be beaten with many blows; but the one who does not know and does things deserving punishment will be beaten with few blows.
Luke 12:47-48.
Religion, however, is the knowledge of God; and therefore every religious person, by following religion, testifies that he knows the will of God.
Thus, the profession of religion does not remove the debt but increases it: because assuming the religious name is a pledge of devotion; and therefore, the more one promises by profession, the more one owes by action, according to that: "It is better not to vow than to make a vow and not fulfill it."
Ecclesiastes 5:4.
But perhaps someone says, "If these things are so, then irreligion is safer than religion."
Not at all.
The religious person is indebted because they profess to be religious; the irreligious person is indebted because they neglect religion.
Thus, both have their own debt according to their condition.
The religious person owes whatever they have professed to acknowledge; the irreligious person owes even what they do not deign to acknowledge, according to what the divine word specifically says about them: "They did not want to understand to do good" (Psalm 36:4).
Even though we seem to have burdened the religious with this matter, because we said that the profession of the name is a pledge of religion, let us remove this burden and assume that what I have said is not so.
Let us consider, then, not what we should do by profession, but by reason; not by vow, but by the very healthiness.
Tell me, please, all religious people, is there anyone who does not do everything they do for the sake of their own salvation or at least their own benefit?
I think not.
For all are led to the desire and pursuit of their own benefit by the teaching and impulse of nature itself.
Those who serve in the military think it is honorable; those who trade think it is useful; those who farm think it is fruitful.
Even thieves, robbers, poisoners, assassins, and every kind of person of poor conduct think that what they do is appropriate for them, not because wrongful acts are appropriate for anyone, but because the person who engages in wrongful acts believes that what is wrongful is appropriate for them.
We pursued philosophy not for its own sake, but because we saw it as suitable for us through the lens of religion.
When we reflect on the brevity of the present and the eternity of the future, we realize how insignificant the former is compared to the latter.
Thinking about the future judgment and its severe consequences—the burning valley of eternal tears amidst the masses—we see that it is an immense and supreme evil not just to enter and endure it, but even to witness and fear it.
Amidst these dreadful punishments, we also consider the glorious and blessed things: new heavens and a new earth, a more beautiful appearance of all creation, the eternal dwelling of justice, and the newly built world.
The golden homes of all the saints above the rustic heavens, halls polished with sparkling gems and adorned with the brilliance of immortal metals.
A light seven times more illustrious, always shining with a crimson radiance, happiness filled with unspeakable goods, perpetual joy with its inhabitants, the fellowship of patriarchs, the companionship of prophets, the brotherhood of apostles, the dignity of martyrs, and in all the saints, the likeness of angels.
The abundance of heavenly riches, the affluence of immortal delights, and a shared life with God.
Reflecting and contemplating these things, we sought refuge in the worship of sacred religion and its duties.
We adopted it as an advocate and intercessor, believing it to be the most effective means to obtain these goods for us.
We entrusted ourselves to its protection and patronage with ambitious humility.
Since we have reflected on and sought these great things, let us now see and carefully consider if there is anything in our actions or possessions that can buy such great things from God.
If there is not, why does each of us not offer everything he has, since he cannot offer everything he owes?
Especially since the Savior Himself
and our God said that nothing is safer and more beneficial for every person than to use their resources and wealth for acts of mercy.
He commanded this particularly in both the Old and New Law, saying that those who share their possessions will become richer, and that mercy saves from death.
In the book of Tobit, it is written: "Mercy saves from death" (Tobit 12:9).
Elsewhere, about the holy man: "He scattered, he gave to the poor, his righteousness endures forever" (Psalm 111:9).
Also in the Gospel: "Do not," He says, "store up for yourselves treasures on earth" (Matthew 6:19).
And again: "You cannot serve God and wealth" (Matthew 6:24).
And again: "Woe to you, rich people, who have received your consolation" (Luke 6:24).
To those guilty of greed and inhumanity: "Go," He says, "into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels" (Matthew 25:41).
It is easy to understand what their eternal punishment will be, for those whose fate is assigned with the devil.
Through these greatest torments, not even the most atrocious crimes of fornication, murder, or sacrilege are punished, but only greed and the inhumanity that denies mercy.
From this, we should understand what those will suffer who, besides other sins, are also guilty of greed.
Those who are to be punished with the greatest penalty, whom, being free from all other sins, only the crime of greed condemns to death.
If we truly believe that all these things will happen, we must undoubtedly avoid them.
If we do not avoid them, we certainly do not believe.
If we do not believe, we are in no way Christians.
For we cannot call anyone a Christian who does not think that Christ should be believed.
But suppose we do not fear the punishments mentioned above; can we hope for a reward we do not deserve?
If we don't give wealth to redeem our sins, let's at least give to gain happiness.
If we don't give to avoid condemnation, let's give to be rewarded.
Even if the saints don't need redemption from past evils, there are everlasting goods to be acquired at great cost.
Even if there's no punishment to fear, there's still a kingdom to strive for.
So, even if the saints have nothing to redeem, they still have things to buy.
Perhaps someone fears a loss in the purchase, thinking they might give more than they receive, or that small returns might come from great investments, that repayment might not match generosity, and that giving money at great cost might endanger their wealth.
As if, having entrusted something great to the Lord on earth, Christ might not have the means to repay it in heaven.
If this doubt exists, I advise against doing anything at all, because nothing benefits a doubter.
The effort is in vain without certain faith, and it's pointless to invest if you despair of receiving.
We believe that Christ rewards all deeds.
So, if you think He is either too poor to repay or unwilling to repay, how can you hope for repayment from Him, whom you have condemned for both inability and unfaithfulness?
But if you don't doubt that He will do what He has said, what foolishness or error is it not to give Him as much as you can, when you surely don't doubt that you will receive much more than you gave?
What misery, indeed, to want to receive nothing from what you give up when you can completely possess everything you believe in?
But (woe is me!) I think that God is not believed.
And when I say "I think," I wish I were uncertain and didn't clearly recognize it.
Perhaps I would struggle within myself to overcome my opinions and force my mind not to believe doubtful things, so I could direct it to better things.
But what are we to do? We are not overcome by doubtful matters but are constrained by clear ones.
For who believes the Lord in mind and does not believe Him with their means?
Who entrusts their soul to God and denies Him their money?
Who believes in heavenly promises and does not act to be a part of those promises?
Therefore, when we see people not acting this way, we must recognize them as non-believers.
We cannot consider them to have faith in God when their actions clearly deny it.
This situation calls for mourning and lamenting the disbelief of almost everyone.
Oh, misery!
Oh, perversity!
People believe in each other but not in God.
They put hope in human promises but deny it to God.
In all human matters, hope for the future drives actions.
Even this temporary life is sustained and nourished by hope.
For this reason, we plant seeds in the earth, believing they will yield a harvest.
For this reason, people work hard in vineyards, comforted by the hope of the grape harvest.
For this reason, merchants spend their treasures on purchases, hoping to accumulate wealth through sales.
For this reason, sailors entrust their lives to the winds and storms, hoping for a safe return.
And what more can I say?
Peace among even the wildest and most barbaric peoples is based on hope and is strengthened by mutual trust.
Even robbers and murderers do not deny faith to each other; they trust that promises will be kept.
As I said, everything among people is driven by hope.
Only God is despaired of.
Although our Lord has made the very elements and nature of the world faithful, He alone is almost universally not believed in, He who made it possible for everything else to be trusted.
However, it might be said that using one's resources is not always due to disbelief but sometimes due to necessity, and that religious people do not disbelieve in God but reserve necessities for life and use.
Indeed, many holy people are sometimes prevented from the utmost perfection in dispensing wealth by gender, age, or the fragility of their weaker bodies.
Fine, let this be accepted; but even if it is accepted, it must be managed so that only what is necessary for the quality of needs and causes is retained, and excess is cut away.
For the Apostle says, "Having food and clothing, with these we shall be content."
For those who seek to become rich fall into temptation and the devil's trap.
First Timothy, chapter 6, verses 8 to 9.
Therefore, as we observe, safety lies only in necessary things, while in excess there is a trap; in moderation, there is God's grace, and in wealth, the devil's chains.
Finally, what does the Apostle immediately add?
"Which drown men in destruction and perdition," he says. Therefore, if riches carry destruction within them, let us avoid wealth, so we do not fall into destruction.
It is said that ample and wealthy means bring about perdition. A large estate must be avoided, so it does not lead to deep ruin. Thus, whether gender, age, or infirmity requires necessary sustenance, they must be content with what is sufficient; anything exceeding temporary use should be spent on religious duty.
But if you, regardless of your holy profession, are eager to preserve wealth or accumulate resources, you are making an excuse in vain about infirmity. Can a weaker gender not live otherwise, unless their mind is burdened by the management of a large inheritance? Can a sacred girl or a widow devoted to chastity not maintain the unblemished perseverance of their holy profession, unless they burden themselves with weights of silver and gold, knowing they possess such great wealth that the needs of the owners are not required?
Or because tranquility is especially necessary for both this gender and modesty, does someone perhaps consider it impossible to maintain inviolate tranquility with only a few servants, unless the noise of a large family's activities and the tumultuous clamor of surrounding crowds batter their ears? This indeed is not only too much unrest for a soul desiring true peace, but even seeing it is in some way a part of unrest. Even if someone wants to subject them to discipline and silence, they still cannot suppress their unrest along with their own peace: even the correction of another's unrest is thus a disturbance to our own peace.
Everything we've discussed about this matter applies to everyone, regardless of age, gender, or weakness.
So, no one should think that wealth is beneficial to religion: it's actually a hindrance, not a help; a burden, not a support.
Possessing and using wealth doesn't uphold religion but rather undermines it, as the Lord Himself says:
"The worries of this world and the deceitfulness of wealth choke the word of God, and it becomes unfruitful" (Matthew 13:22).
He rightly called wealth deceitful.
People think of it as good and call it so, but it deceives them by appearing as a present good while actually being the cause of eternal evils.
But even though this is as God predicted, let us still consider the struggles and weaknesses of those who believe they cannot live without great wealth.
For you, holy and devout, suppose you hold on to your wealth and riches until the end of this life, as long as you eventually dedicate them to yourself.
Use your resources in this life, but remember yourself when dying, and dedicate your wealth to His worship and honor, acknowledging it as His gift.
It's a kind and joyful request to all of you, the wealthy of this world.
If you can't bring yourself to be poor in this world, at least ensure you won't be in want in eternity.
If you avoid present poverty so much, why not fear it forever?
Fear the brief matters and avoid the long-lasting ones.
Why do you dread poverty in this life?
Why are you so scared?
It's much less than what you fear here.
If you find temporary poverty heavy, what will it be like if it never ends?
We're addressing your souls and desires.
If you don't want to completely lack the use of your possessions, act in a way that you may never lack them.
We're asking something delightful and pleasant from you.
For those of you who cannot be content without riches, take action to ensure you can always be wealthy, as it is written: "If you delight in thrones and scepters, kings of the people, love wisdom so that you may reign forever" (Wisdom of Solomon 6:22).
Otherwise, what error or insanity is it for any person who has led a life of great wealth—which alone is enough for guilt—to reach the end of their life and not remember themselves generously and healthily?
In their own dire extremity, they do not help themselves, even though their wealth, which by itself accuses the Lord, is according to this: "Woe to you who are rich" (Luke 6:24).
There are also other kinds of sins that arise from wealth, as if it were a natural breeding ground.
They do not take action, strive, or earnestly use their resources to avoid guilt, to avoid leaving behind a body and soul to be tormented.
Who, then, is so faithless or insane that they do not consider or fear these things?
They care for others more than themselves with their wealth, losing the only hope they could cling to like a shipwrecked person in the middle of the sea.
Not only do they lose it, but they throw it away and cast it out from themselves, striving in every way not to leave anything for themselves to escape perishing.
Since these things are so, tell me, I beg you, all lovers of Christ, can there be any humans so cruel and ruthless against their enemies as these people are against themselves?
There are none so fierce, so inhuman, who do not at least stop pursuing their desperate and dying enemies.
Yet, these people pursue themselves even in death.
Is this not persecution, or can there be any greater persecution, for a person to disinherit themselves, to be made an exile from all their goods, and driven into exile by themselves?
And this not in a common or usual way, but in a new and most cruel one.
All exiles, even if their bodies are banished, are not removed in spirit.
Even if they are captives in the flesh, they can, if they choose, remain free in their hearts.
However, what we're discussing now is a new kind of exile and torment, where the soul itself is sent into exile, where the spirit is stripped of its faculties.
Oh, how much lighter are external and physical enemies!
They are only enemies of the body, but you are enemies of the soul.
Thus, in comparison to your deeds, their hatred is insignificant.
Anything that harms in this present world is easy to bear.
What is truly grave and destructive is what will strangle in eternity.
And so, the Savior Himself said, "Do not be afraid of those who can kill the body but cannot kill the soul" Matthew 10:28.
Therefore, the hatred that harms the body is easy to bear because it does not harm the soul. For when the body is harmed, the soul remains unharmed, and the happiness of the spirit is not disturbed by the sufferings of the flesh. That indeed, that inexpiable evil, that which cannot be valued at all, is what will utterly damn the whole man without end.
And for this reason, your enemies are lighter than you yourselves. Indeed, all enmity is dissolved by death. But you act against yourselves in such a way that you do not escape your enmities even after death.