On the Heresy and History of the Manichaeans: Two Books
Book One
Introduction
After wrapping up the work of previous years, we felt inspired to take on something more significant.
We thought of many notable events related to sacred matters where our efforts could be worthwhile.
Friends advised and encouraged us to focus on the history of the Manicheans.
Many distinguished scholars have written about various heretics for the benefit of the church and Christian community.
These works highlight the authority of sacred leaders, their strong spirit, and their duty in challenging and refuting heresies.
I believed it would be beneficial for readers and those dedicated to critical studies if I focused my efforts on this task.
I knew that many writings about this heresy were scattered in the works of others and needed examination.
If these could be refined to uncover the truth and compiled into a single work, readers would be relieved from the burdens they currently face.
These include sifting through numerous volumes and dealing with unorganized and complex issues often found in such discussions and writings, which can easily lead to misunderstandings.
I also knew that the Catholic writer, J.
Beausobre, had written a history of the Manicheans in French, more in line with his own views than with the truth.
He published this work, filled with many notes, through Frederick Bernard's press in Amsterdam in 1734.
The extent to which he dared to invent in his hatred and destruction of the Catholic faith is almost beyond explanation.
His critical pen was aimed solely at the ancient holy Fathers, the pontiffs of the Roman See, and the sacred synods convened because of this heresy.
He criticized their writing, speaking, and methods with false annotations, intending to undermine or twist them into a wrong meaning.
At the start of this work, I realized I would have to engage in difficult debates if I decided to refute Beausobre's books, which I only came across after writing seventeen chapters of this history, and address their errors.
Finding countless contradictions in his books against both the truth and my observations, I tried to adjust what I had already written to a different method of discussion, ensuring I didn't appear to discuss Manichaean matters superficially.
Whenever my daily studies and other duties allowed, whether within or outside the cloisters, I didn't plan to waste leisure time idly.
Instead, I considered what could be contributed for the common good of literary matters and the writing of ecclesiastical history.
I resolved to discuss the entire history of the Manichaeans as truthfully as possible.
In composing these books, I commit to no partisan interests, as a writer's mind should be entirely free from them.
I have resolved to pursue and defend only the truth to the best of my ability in these and future debates.
Chapter One
On the Principal Founders of the Manichaean Sect.
The Manichaean heresy, named after its founder, had three primary originators.
The first to establish the foundations of this sect and confirm its main errors was a Saracen named Scythianus, who was raised among the Arab people near Palestine.
He was well-versed in Greek literature, having studied it thoroughly.
Initially, he engaged in trade, traveling to India, and quickly amassed enough wealth to focus entirely on studying philosophy and Egyptian disciplines upon reaching Alexandria.
Leaving his trade behind, he aspired to live like Aristotle.
With both wealth and leisure at his disposal and a keen intellect, he contemplated introducing new, albeit paradoxical, doctrines to the world.
Inspired by Empedocles, he proposed two co-eternal principles of existence: one good and the other evil.
He referred to the good one as God and light, and the evil one as matter and darkness.
This error was a principal doctrine of the Valentinians and Marcionites, who challenged the Christian religion of the Catholic Church in the second century.
He also explored other ideas from Pythagorean principles, not only pondering them but also documenting them in writing.
He produced four volumes filled with fables and lies, which became the seeds of wickedness and impiety, from which, under Mani's influence, many diabolical teachings later emerged.
He titled these volumes "Gospel," "Chapters," "Mysteries," and "Treasures."
Armed with these works, he traveled to Judea to debate with the elders of Mosaic law.
However, when he was defeated by them with the aid of the divine Scriptures, he attempted to erase his shame and disgrace through magical incantations, trying to deceive the Jews of Jerusalem with tricks.
Using the magical arts he learned in Egypt and India, he climbed onto the roof of a certain house.
From there, either struck by God or out of his mind, as Saint Cyril of Jerusalem writes, he threw himself down, leaving his possessions and prized books to his servant Terebinthus, whom he had made his heir.
Both old and recent writers have shared these stories about Scythian's homeland, character, life, customs, and books.
However, none have precisely defined when he lived.
Although Epiphanius, in Heresy 66, seems to suggest that he went to Jerusalem around the time of the apostles, William Cave argues that his words should be taken more broadly.
He believes they refer to the period closely following the apostolic age, suggesting that Scythian died towards the end of the second century.
However, Beausobre disagreed with both Epiphanius and Cave.
Discussing the origin of Scythian and Manichaean doctrines, he claims that Scythian was actually born among the Arabs, not the Scythians.
Based on various uncertain conjectures, he extends the birth date to the third century, creating the idea that Scythian was a contemporary of Mani.
The only admitted difference being that Scythian was older and Mani younger, with the suggestion of correspondence between them.
Whether this reasoning accurately defines when the leader of this heresy flourished or whether that correspondence is real or imagined, is for the reader to decide.
Meanwhile, we argue that Beausobre's conjectures are completely flawed, noting that ancient writers, when describing Christian men of the second century, used similar ways of speaking.
Therefore, Epiphanius cannot be accused of error for claiming that Scythian went to Jerusalem around the time of the apostles.
In that declining century, many people in Jerusalem who had listened to the apostles were still alive, including the renowned Hegesippus.
In Asia, there were also figures like Quadratus and Polycarp, known as apostles or apostolic men because they adhered closely to the teachings of the apostles.
Eusebius confirmed this in numerous instances and also mentions Saint Irenaeus, who is believed to have memorized the teachings of a certain apostolic man.
Therefore, it's not surprising that Epiphanius thought Scythianus traveled to Jerusalem around the time of the apostles, since we see that, by divine arrangement, some apostolic men, who were listeners of Christ's apostles, remained alive until the early third century.
Indeed, Photius, a man of keen insight, often praised by Beausobre, reviewed Epiphanius's writings multiple times and was careful in his critique.
In fact, while writing against the Manichaeans, he refers to the works of Cyril of Jerusalem and Epiphanius written against this heresy, without a hint of suspicion regarding their authenticity, and he calls Epiphanius great in miracles.
Therefore, after clarifying Epiphanius's way of speaking, another comment from Beausobre needs to be addressed, which is that Scythianus was a contemporary of Manes.
To gradually convince readers of this, he first refers to the biased opinions of the Greeks and Romans, who typically condemned the customs, culture, and philosophy of the Arabs, often labeling them as barbarians due to their desert lifestyle.
However, he argues that the Arabs were actually devoted to the study and cultivation of sciences and the fine arts, as evidenced by the Queen of Sheba's journey to Jerusalem to meet Solomon, and by Pythagoras's educational journey, who, after learning in Egypt, moved to the Arab lands to be further educated by their king.
What more is there to say?
Beausobre, in the same source on page 20, includes various praises about the people of Arabia in the Life of Muhammad in his own history.
He suggests that their vernacular language is smooth and pleasant in every way, adorned with great eloquence and poetic skill.
He claims that the people themselves excel in intelligence and ease of thought compared to others, with their way of life being passed down with much simplicity from family heads to their young sons, a fact he claims to be well-known.
The writer of the Manichaean history doesn't only focus on things unrelated to our subject.
When discussing the religion of the Arabs, he believed that a purer form of it flourished among them longer than among the Jews.
Especially since the Israelites, due to various Egyptian superstitions, frequently strayed from the true worship of God, undermining the Mosaic law with false rituals.
Going further, he begins with a comparison between a certain Scythian and Muhammad, both seen as architects of heresies and depraved doctrines, who also came from Arabia.
To prevent readers from thinking that evil demons and spirits of lies dominate the inhabitants of that land, he points out Moses.
Moses was chosen for the ministry of the highest God when he retreated to the wilderness of the Midianites in Arabia, during the time he was sent to Egypt to carry out a divine mission to destroy idolatry.
With these and other similar points made by Beausobre to show trivialities rather than true learning, he immediately refers to the maps of geographers and divides Arabia into its parts.
He adds that he could easily believe the Scythian originated from mountainous Arabia.
This opinion seems to be supported by the testimonies of Archelaus and Epiphanius, who at least vaguely indicate that the Scythian had an Egyptian wife, and that this origin was in the part of Arabia known as Desert.
Guided by these conjectures, Beausobre believed that a Manichean had been recognized by the priesthood and performed his duties in the province of Ahuaz, where he spread his false teachings.
Based on this and other factors, Beausobre, dismissing the testimonies of others, thinks he can conclude that some correspondence of letters happened between Scythianus and the Manichean.
This could suggest that Scythianus lived later and was a contemporary of Manes.
He bases this conjecture on two fragments of letters: one from a letter that Scythianus gave to Condatus the Saracen, and the other from a letter that Manes addressed to Scythianus, which Photius preserved for us, as noted in Fabricius's Greek Library, Book 5, page 284.
These are the serious considerations that might have led Beausobre to dismiss the testimonies of Cyril, the bishop of Jerusalem, Epiphanius, Titus, the bishop of Bostra, Heraclian, and others, to construct this kind of correspondence.
But who ever claimed that the Scythianus to whom Manes gave the letter (if it is genuine) was the Saracen we are currently discussing?
Indeed, Photius did not mention this.
Following the histories of previous Fathers, he did not suggest that there was any falsehood.
He would have mentioned it, however, if he had found something untrue in them.
And indeed, there was another man commonly called Scythianus, to whom Manes wrote the praised letter, according to Tillemont.
Tillemont could not convince himself that the first founder of the Manichean sect, Scythianus, could still be alive in the third century of the Church, to whom Manes would give such a letter.
Especially since the person we are discussing, before he died a bad death, had already left the borders of Arabia and moved to Judea.
There, he engaged in various disputes with the elders of the Mosaic law, trying to mock the Jews of Jerusalem with magical spells and tricks.
Tillemont, who is rightly praised, should have distinguished between two men with the same name to prevent discrediting the Holy Fathers who wrote about the deeds of Scythianus.
So, Beausobre wrongly criticized Tillemont for envy due to this distinction, as noted in Book One, page twenty-six.
John Christopher Wolf not only noted those two fragments of letters but, when discussing the age of Scythianus, he didn't accuse Archelaus or Saint Epiphanius of error.
He directly questioned whether that Scythianus could have received letters from Manes, since Terebinthus should be placed between them.
Therefore, he rightly suspects that Manes' letter was addressed to a different Scythianus; furthermore, he asserts that Manes himself was sometimes called Scythianus, as Beausobre admits, as we will discuss in Chapter Four of this work.
Thus, Wolf, who enriched and published two books on Manichaean history written by Photius, did not confuse the Scythianus we are discussing with another, possibly more recent, one.
Since this cannot be gathered from Photius, and Photius himself supports Epiphanius, he remained in suspense, so as not to discredit the Fathers or lead himself into error.
At least he left the matter undefined by any reasoning, or he thought it better to support our opinion.
Now, let's move on to Terebinthus, the successor of Scythianus, about whom we will say much against Beausobre in Chapter Three of this work.
When Scythianus died, his heresy did not die with him.
Instead, it became even more intense, thanks to the work of Terebinthus, whom some called a disciple and others referred to as his servant.
It is commonly agreed among the ancient Fathers that he was a constant companion of Scythianus and privy to all his secrets.
After the death of his teacher, having stayed in Palestine for a while, he fled to Persia with the wealth and writings that Scythianus had left him in his will.
He was received as a guest by a certain widow and called himself Buddha to remain hidden more safely.
He first engaged in debates with the priests of Mithras.
After being shamefully defeated by the same people, he turned to tricks and magical arts, following his teacher's example.
He wanted to ensure that no one would dare contradict him again.
So, when he went to the upper part of the house, a demon struck him, throwing him into the air, and he died miserably.
He left behind the widow with whom he had stayed as the heir to his books and riches.
Regarding the inheritance of the books, Socrates claims they were written by Terebinthus in Persia, whom Tollius later followed.
However, since the ancients attribute those books to Scythianus, I won't dwell on this matter, as it's of little importance now.
As we've learned, Terebinthus's widow, or the heir of Budda, kept these books until her death.
Since she was childless a few years before she passed away, she purchased a seven-year-old Persian boy named Cubricus to be her servant.
She later granted him freedom and ensured he was educated in Persian disciplines.
Then, as she neared death, she left all her possessions, including the books deposited with her by Terebinthus, to Cubricus in her will.
Established in such a prosperous state, he shuddered at his previous condition of servitude.
Fearing it might disgrace him, he rejected the name Cubricus and adopted a new one, Manes.
Regarding the meaning of this name, especially among the Greeks, Eusebius of Caesarea explained, "At that time, a certain Manes, driven insane by his name and agitated by a demon, taught a hated and detestable heresy to all."
Therefore, for insanity, the Greeks took the opportunity to mock the name Manes, as Cyril of Jerusalem later testified in Catechesis 6, supported by Saint Augustine.
To avoid this mark of infamy, Manes' disciples, by changing the word, called it Manichaeism, with the letter N doubled.
Manichaeism, says Augustine in the Book of Heresies, chapter...
His disciples preferred to call him by a different name to avoid the association with madness.
Some of them, thinking themselves wiser and thus even more deceitful, called him Manichaeum with a doubled 'N', as if he were pouring out manna.
However, Caveus, drawing from Cyril and Epiphanius, shows that among the Persians, Chaldeans, and Syrians, this term indicated something of honor, not insult.
The Persians used it in speech because that impostor flaunted his notable dialectics, and the Chaldeans and Syrians interpreted it as a vessel;
as if, like Saint Paul, the sacrilegious and insane man wanted to signify that he was chosen by God as a vessel.
From these three sacrilegious impostors, namely Scythianus, Terebinthus, and Manes, I believe it has been sufficiently explained that this diabolical sect originated.
We will need to revisit what Beausobre extensively wrote in chapters three and four of this work about the various names of Manes, their etymologies, his homeland, institutions, and duties, to refute many of this writer's frivolous arguments and conjectures;
and to defend, as much as possible, the tradition of the ancient Latin and Greek Fathers, the ancient discipline of the Church, and the conviction of Catholic writers.
Then, we will more clearly reveal how much Beausobre indulged in his own studies and the aspects of non-Catholic religion.
Chapter Two
The time when Manes began spreading his teachings around the world.
We highlight the testimony of Saint Leo the Great and prove Paschasius Quesnellus wrong due to excessive negligence.
From a man with a barbaric lifestyle and customs, who had a sharp mind and a deep familiarity with demons, and who also misled his listeners through the misuse of dialectics, nothing but harmful seeds of wickedness could emerge.
These seeds burst into the Christian world when Saint Felix was at the helm of the Roman See.
Among others, Eusebius wrote about this in the previously mentioned text, Ecclesiastical History, Book Seven, Chapter Twenty-Seven.
We believe William Cave's chronology is not accurate enough, as he claims the beginnings of this heresy should be traced back to the year two hundred seventy-seven.
Indeed, Felix was elected pope in two hundred seventy, reigned for only five years, and died during the reign of Aurelian, as accurately proven by the records and catalogs of Roman pontiffs, along with Dionysius Petavius and the distinguished Francis Blanchinus.
But a famous testimony of Saint Leo the Great, in which he asserted during a sermon that Manes became notorious for being condemned at the time two hundred sixty years had passed since the Lord's Resurrection, during the consulship of Probus and Paulinus, when the eighth persecution against Christians was raging, cannot indicate that this heresy erupted much later.
To this testimony, Paschasius Quesnellus, noticing in Volume One, in the notes on sermon two on Pentecost, notes one, two, and three, made three main annotations to create a great deal of work.
Firstly, he suspected, as did Dionysius Petavius in his annotations to Epiphanius, page two hundred twenty-seven, that there was an error, and proposed that instead of reading two hundred sixty, by transferring one number, it should read as two hundred forty.
The reason is that the consulship of Probus and Paulinus fell around the year two hundred seventy-seven in the Dionysian era, from which, he says, subtracting thirty-one years, two hundred forty-six years remain from the Lord's Ascension.
Thus, Quesnellus calculates based on Petavius, relying on the authority of the Oxford manuscript, which shows the subsequent Roman numeral two hundred fifty.
This error can be blamed on the printers or scribes, as most Vatican manuscripts, which we will note in the margins, clearly indicate.
The seven manuscripts we used to correct the works of Saint Leo don't describe the mentioned sum of years with letters, but with numerical symbols that the Romans always used in their calculations.
If the number of years, as expressed in the popular editions of Saint Leo's sermons, were correct, the entire chronology of Christian and civil affairs would be disrupted.
For instance, Manes would not have been known until the end of the third century of the Church, specifically in the year 291 AD, when not Probus and Paulinus, but C.
Junius Tiberianus and Cassius Dio held the consulship.
However, by that time, it was well-known that Manes had already been executed by the decree of the Persian king.
The second point noted by Quesnellus is obvious even to barbers and the shortsighted.
Among scholars, it's well-known that Probus and Paulinus only achieved the consulship after Emperor Aurelian's death.
This should be dated to the year 277 AD, as Petavius' tables declare, and Beausobre also acknowledges in the first part of his history of the Manichaeans, which we will explore in the fourth chapter to come.
However, I am unsure why Quesnellus suggested that the Consular Records of Cassiodorus or the Ecclesiastical Annals should be corrected, which place the consulship of Probus in the year 277 AD along with the seventh year of Emperor Aurelian.
Sacred and secular records show that Aurelian was killed in the year 275 AD, having reigned only five years, due to the betrayal of Mnestheus, a secretary notary at Coenophrusium, between Byzantium and Heraclea.
After Aurelian's removal, following an interregnum of about seven months, Tacitus Caesar was proclaimed by the senate, who died of fever on the two-hundredth day, in Tarsus.
When Florianus was appointed as a successor, Probus was declared emperor by the majority of the army.
Florianus took this very badly, and driven by despair, he voluntarily cut his veins and died after 60 days in the year 276 AD.
As a result, the Ecclesiastical Annals could not align the consulship of Probus with the seventh year of Emperor Aurelian, since Aurelian had only ruled the Roman Empire for five years.
I believe the cause of this error was that Probus was also known as Aurelius.
Thus, when in the Roman consular records for the year 277, the names Aurelius Probus appeared, some people perhaps suspected that Aurelian's reign needed to be extended by two years, so that Probus could have held the consulship while Aurelian was still alive.
But let no one be misled into thinking that Cavei's view on the origins of the Manichaeans is more valid.
For Saint Leo the Great, in the cited testimony, did not discuss the origins of this sect but rather the time it was condemned.
It suggests that the errors of the Manichaeans had already been around for a long time, and through the ministry and preaching of the disciples of Manes, they had spread across various parts of the East, making these devilish falsehoods and obscene superstitions known to many bishops of the Churches.
Who would believe that this could have happened instantly?
Especially given the great distance between Persia and Rome, making it unlikely that this heresy, barely arisen, could have been reported immediately to the Roman see.
Additionally, by the year 277, when Aurelius Probus and Paulinus held the consulship, Archelaus, the bishop of Caschara in Mesopotamia, renowned for his sanctity and learning, had vigorously and steadfastly opposed the madness of Manes, as recounted by Epiphanius in heresy 66 and Cyril of Jerusalem in catechetical lecture 6.
3.
Finally, the third point that Quesnellus brings up is related to those words of Leo: when the eighth persecution against Christians was raging.
So, the annotator noticed that if Leo is indeed referring to persecution under Aurelian, as it seems, this wasn't the eighth but the ninth, as Augustine lists in The City of God, Book 18, Chapter 61.
But where does Quesnellus get the idea that Leo followed Augustine in counting eight tyrannies and persecutions of the Church?
Does he truly believe that both ancient and modern writers completely agree on listing the Church's persecutions and that Aurelian must be included among the tyrants against Christians?
This is a mistaken conclusion.
Different writers had various approaches and goals when describing the same persecutions.
For example, Eusebius, when discussing Aurelian, mentions that in the early years of his reign, he was never hostile to Christians.
In fact, regarding the case of Paul of Samosata, Aurelian acted as a defender of ecclesiastical rights, even ordering Paul to be expelled from the Church by public decree.
If later on, over time, he deviated from his original mild intentions due to bad advice and even planned to persecute the Church of God, to the point where it is said that letters were already dictated and written, only awaiting his signature, yet this evil intention never came to fruition.
God prevented the signing by Aurelian's infamous hand.
The one who was judging the death of the faithful was himself condemned by sudden death.
Therefore, it is difficult for me to accept, with Eusebius as the authority, that Aurelian is counted among the tyrants of the Church, since he died before signing those impious edicts.
Lactantius also concurs with Eusebius, writing in On the Deaths of the Persecutors that Aurelian was not allowed to fulfill his plans, but was immediately stopped at the onset of his fury.
Who would deny that the holy pope followed this same perspective in writing?
He aimed to highlight only those persecutions by tyrants where countless martyrs, through their triumphs, demonstrated that the Holy Spirit was bestowed upon them.
But during Aurelian's reign, where are the martyrs?
Which authors have recorded them?
How many thousands are documented?
Let the opponents present the official records detailing both the types of punishments or deaths and the confessions of the martyrs.
Let Quesnell himself name the consuls and prefects who, following Aurelian's decrees, sought out Christians for punishment by death.
Clearly, no such records were presented by Eusebius, Lactantius, or anyone else, so we cannot truly claim that countless thousands of martyrs proved with their victories that the Lord's promise was fulfilled, as He said:
"But when they hand you over, do not worry about how or what you are to say.
For it will be given to you in that hour what you are to say.
For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father who speaks in you" (Matthew 10:19-20).
To clearly understand the intent of the holy pope, which Quesnell failed to grasp, let's carefully consider what he aimed to prove with this argument and what he wanted to persuade the people of during his preaching.
Saint Leo the Great sought to overturn the main doctrine of Manes, who blasphemously and sacrilegiously claimed to be the Paraclete promised by the Lord, asserting that the Holy Spirit had not come until he, the deceiver of the unfortunate, arose.
Manes claimed that the Holy Spirit dwelled in him in such a way that he was nothing other than the divine Spirit.
To counter this great impiety, upon which the entire structure of the Manichaean sect was built, he first called upon the testimonies of the New Testament, which show that the Holy Spirit was promised and given to the apostles, while they were still alive, as well as to other disciples and believers.
Here are the reasons for this mission and arrival, along with some of the outcomes of its remarkable power.
Starting with the novelty of the doctrine and preaching of secular matters, which are claimed to be completely foreign to the Holy Spirit.
The truth to be introduced and the doctrine to be preached was none other than what Christ, the Son of God, had taught.
However, it was necessary, he said, for the capacity of those being taught to grow and for the constancy of that love, which drives out all fear, to strengthen and not fear the fury of persecutors.
These remarkable effects of the Holy Spirit were always seen in the apostles and disciples of Christ.
Fearless of any storm, they overcame the challenges of the world with faith, despised death, and spread the Gospel of truth to all nations.
Saint Leo draws evidence from the Church's records.
To achieve this more effectively, he refers to the persecutions by tyrants.
These persecutions, like fire or touchstones, tested the steadfastness of the martyrs and the truth of the evangelical preaching.
Therefore, in recounting these persecutions, it was necessary to list only those that occurred from the Resurrection of Christ up to the consulship of Probus and Paullinus.
In particular, those in which countless thousands of martyrs, with their very own crowns, showed that the prophecies of Christ had been fulfilled, as stated in the Gospel of Matthew, chapter ten, verse nineteen.
Since the persecution that Aurelian had considered was never carried out, it was not included.
Therefore, Quesnellus was completely mistaken in writing that the holy pontiff had spoken of the persecution by Aurelian.
He couldn't have mentioned this, as no Christian suffered martyrdom by decree of Aurelian.
As a result, it was rightly recorded:
During the eighth persecution against Christians, Aurelian's letters and decrees targeting Christians for execution were ignored because divine intervention rendered these malicious plans against the emperors ineffective.
Therefore, I am amazed that a certain Quesnellus, who only superficially examined the writings of Leo, attempted to cast doubt on this holy pope's courage.
It is indeed quite bold for the commentator to accuse someone of error whose virtue and wisdom were always evident to everyone, and whose involvement in Church matters could not be concealed.
If Leo did not fully align with Augustine and other writers in listing the Church's persecutions, this should be seen as wisdom, not a fault.
Otherwise, if he had mentioned the ninth persecution, referred to as Aurelian's, he would not have effectively countered the Manichaean, and his arguments would have lost their impact.
Please, let no one be upset with me as if I intended to contradict Augustine and others.
My aim is not to discredit them or accuse them of error, but to clarify the true and genuine views of Leo.
Moreover, Augustine and others were correct to include Aurelian among the persecutors of the Church.
He had a fierce and brutal attitude toward Christians, whom he would have tormented with various punishments, as he had decreed, if he had not been killed early in his campaign by the will of Almighty God.
Whether what we have written so far clearly shows Quesnellus's negligence is for the reader to decide.
Our sole intention was to clear Saint Leo's testimony of any error, and to demonstrate that it remains true that, during the consulship of Probus and Paulinus, the errors of Manes became known, while the eighth persecution against Christians was ongoing.
But what if it were finally raised against me that the eighth persecution, attributed to Valerian, had ceased many years before the consulship of Probus and Paulinus?
What if this persecution was extended beyond its intended period, with no regard for Gallienus, Valerian's son, who remained in power; or for Claudius, who defeated the usurper Aureolus; Quintillus, Aurelian, and Tacitus, who all governed the Roman Empire after Valerian's death?
Could those words of Leo, "When the eighth persecution against the Christians was raging," refer to Valerian's time, even though he passed away in the year two hundred fifty-nine?
Indeed, from his death until the consulship of Probus and Paulinus, eighteen years had passed.
As I pondered these things, driven by my pursuit of truth, which guides all my writings, I set myself the challenge of solving this puzzle: what did the term "was raging" mean, or how did Saint Leo intend it?
It was necessary to investigate more thoroughly.
In this matter, since ancient Latin writers do not agree and used the word "desaevio" in various ways, I chose the meaning most fitting to Leo's context to present here.
The ancients did not always use "desaevio" to signify the intensity of cruelty someone exerts over others; rather, and more suitably, they used it to indicate someone who, gradually abandoning cruelty and setting aside anger, makes peace with their enemies.
Indeed, the records of the Church show that Leo spoke in this latter sense.
For Gallienus, who ruled alongside his father Valerian, while the eighth persecution against Christians was instigated by their joint decrees; nevertheless, after Valerian died, Gallienus, remaining in power, acted with kindness towards Christians, halted all acts of cruelty, and, reversing previous decrees, began to treat our people more gently and moderately.
As Eusebius recounts in
Church
History, Book 7, Chapter 16, discussing the peace restored to the
Churches
under Gallienus, who doesn't see that this difficult issue has been completely resolved?
The entire problematic period that was criticized has almost been removed from consideration.
Furthermore, Gallienus's reign is shown to extend up to the year 269, according to both the
Church
and Roman imperial records.
Therefore, if during the sole reign of Gallienus, Christians were treated more leniently and moderately throughout the entire Roman Empire;
if, moreover, Aurelian's decrees to seek out Christians for execution were not enforced;
and if, finally, no martyrs existed under Aurelian himself, who could ever suspect that either Leo spoke less appropriately there, or that those words, when the eighth persecution against Christians was raging, contained any error?
But now, it is time to move past Quesnell's quibbles and address those issues which expose the nonsense and arguments of Beausobre, opposed in previous chapters.
Chapter Three
We refute the false arguments of Isaaci Beausobre, which contradict the previous two chapters.
We defend the rites and doctrines of the Catholic Church against his criticisms.
It seems I've achieved very little, or at least not much, in describing the actions of the leaders of the Manichaean sect or in determining, from the writings of Saint Leo the Great, the exact time when this heresy was condemned and became known worldwide.
This is true for those who have either studied Beausobre's history of the Manichaeans themselves or discussed it with reliable sources.
In this work, as we've mentioned, the author not only attempts to overturn the tradition of the ancient Church Fathers but also, by accusing the most holy men of error or ignorance, he attacks them whenever he finds something in their writings that contradicts his views and his non-Catholic beliefs.
This approach is evident in chapters four, five, and six of the first part of his History, or in what he planned for the second part, where he criticizes and agitates against our most holy pontiff, the divine M.
Leo.
He examines how Leo dealt with the Manichaeans and almost blindly flares up with envious anger against him.
In the highlighted chapters of the first part, he discusses the main three authors of the Manichaean sect and, intending to rely on the testimonies of the Greek and Latin Church Fathers, following Saint Epiphanius, he agrees with us that Scythianus originated from the Saracen people.
Scythianus later sought to acquire Greek institutions and sciences and wanted to live near the borders of Palestine.
But eventually, he moved to the East Indies with the help of ships, engaging in trade.
In this venture, he always prospered, quickly amassing great wealth thanks to the favorable seas, the fertile lands, and his exceptional talent, which seemed to always favor him.
These two qualities-an abundance of wealth and a sharp mind-says Beausobre, along with a comprehensive and varied knowledge of sciences like medicine, philosophy, mathematics, and astronomy, are rarely found in one person.
He claims that this man, due to the heresies he invented or stirred up, made his name eternal.
But what if, the author suggests, Scythianus had simply fallen into heresy?
We wouldn't need to hate him; we should pity him, since heresy should be seen as a weakness of the mind, involving involuntary and distorted thoughts.
It's through these thoughts that a person's intellect, straying from the source of truth, can be led into error.
Therefore, always wanting to deal more gently with Scythianus, Beausobre questions another testimony from Epiphanius that we previously praised.
We saw that this man was said to be involved in tricks and magical incantations of demons, practices common among Egyptians.
Epiphanius alone vouched for this opinion.
Beausobre describes him as a very gullible writer, too forceful in his assertions, especially since neither Archelaus, Bishop of Caschara, nor Cyril of Jerusalem mentioned any magical arts or tricks associated with Scythianus.
But what kind of and how many fabrications does Beausobre's style of argument present?
I think it's clear to all Catholics.
If heresy is mainly due to depraved and entirely involuntary movements of the mind, and if it's limited to these, why is it considered a crime?
Why is it widely agreed that stubbornness of will is involved in the error of heresy, without which no one can be called a heretic?
Indeed, if the mind were involuntarily trapped in errors contrary to the doctrines of faith, it would hardly constitute a crime, since no act of serious offense is regarded as such if it is not done voluntarily.
Furthermore, what purpose do these claims about Scythianus's magical arts serve?
Does Beausobre think that Epiphanius's testimony can be weakened by the silence of those two fathers?
It's indeed nonsensical.
Archelaus, whom Epiphanius cites as an earlier authority, mainly focuses on describing and condemning the matters related to Manes.
He barely has time to detail the life and deeds of Scythianus.
Similarly, Cyril of Jerusalem didn't aim to describe all the deeds of the three founders of the Manichaean sect in his teachings.
Instead, he briefly considered how these three wicked men combined all evil to create a heresy filled with blasphemies and crimes.
So, when speaking quickly about Scythianus, he briefly mentions his origin, homeland, the Aristotelian life he imitated, the four books he composed, and his end in Judea, before quickly moving on to Terebinthus, who inherited his wealth, books, and heresy, to describe his crimes.
But even if such an argument based on the silence of Archelaus and Cyril were assumed to conclude something, wouldn't the previous method of reasoning by Beausobre immediately falter and fail?
Where do writers earlier than Epiphanius, specifically Archelaus and Cyril, mention Scythianus's trade, philosophy, and studies in mathematics, medicine, and astronomy?
They truly maintained a deep silence on all these matters, so it would be permissible to infer that Beausobre invented all these things, using excessive and violent exaggeration in writing his histories, never keeping the truth in view, despite claiming in numerous places that he proposed it to himself alone.
What if Cyril hadn't maintained such deep silence about the magical art of Scythianus at all?
For he attributes it to Terebinthus, Scythianus's successor and heir, as if derived from Scythianus's books, writing:
"When he was finally to be captured, he fled to a certain widow.
Then, going up to the house and summoning aerial demons, whom the Manichaeans still invoke in their abominable rites to this day, he was struck down divinely and died, being thrown from the house."
Cyril makes two claims: first, that Terebinthus was involved in magical arts and relied on demons, using tricks that, as Beausobre notes, were commonly practiced by Egyptians and Indians.
Second, that the Manichaeans were known for invoking demons in their abominable rituals.
So, can you tell me where they got this art and these practices, if not from the books of Scythianus?
Did the followers of this sect travel to Eastern India to pursue these wicked activities?
We have no record of Terebinthus visiting the Indians, unless we assume he accompanied Scythianus when he traveled there.
Therefore, it's more plausible to say that both were trained in the same disciplines, or that Terebinthus and the other Manichaeans, already known for practicing magical arts according to Cyril, gained such knowledge from reading Scythianus's books.
Consequently, if we can reason freely, Epiphanius's testimony, which claims that Scythianus used tricks and demon incantations, seems more credible.
Let's put these topics aside and introduce another idea, which Beausobre tries to attribute to Epiphanius, regarding the marriage initiated by Scythianus with a woman from Upper Thebaid.
Archelaus tells us that she was a captive, supported by Socrates.
Beausobre, supported by some testimonies, asserts that Easterners do not object to having captive wives.
But he uses this to criticize Epiphanius for allegedly trying to portray a beautiful young captive as a ruined and infamous prostitute, as if it should be shameful for Scythianus, supposedly ruined in morals and religion, to marry a harlot.
But where could such a damaging story about Scythianus's reputation come from, since Epiphanius remains silent on it?
Beausobre, unaware of this, does not hesitate to call Epiphanius a slanderer in his anger.
It's believed that he was driven by intense enthusiasm and a fiery spirit to describe the actions and behaviors of the heretics.
However, we can easily dismiss this kind of reasoning and writing, which is filled with Pyrrhonian arguments, by reflecting on the corrupted behaviors of the Manichaeans among us.
Indeed, no sect, not even among the pagans, was more criminal in their impurities.
No other group was more depraved in the incestuous acts of unchecked lust than the Manichaeans.
They considered it a sin to restrain their bodily desires, having cast aside any sense of human decency and shame.
They avoided marriage to prevent the procreation of children and instead engaged in mutual and unspeakable relations continually.
So, what decency, what sense of public and private honor could exist in someone who taught his followers to detest marriages and indulge in the incestuous and most disgraceful acts of lust?
Moreover, it is clearly documented by the Acts of the Roman Inquisition, under Pope Leo the Great, that the Manichaeans were not only accused of these crimes but were also repeatedly convicted through public and credible evidence and testimonies.
Or those held in the Churches of Africa, about which we will speak more appropriately in their own place, keeping the timing in mind.
But let's return to Beausobre.
He concedes that Scythianus's wife was a captive.
But from what source does he gather that, just as he did not hesitate to take her captive, it was against his religion to take her from a life of prostitution into marriage?
Beausobre indeed claims her to be beautiful and young without an author; he believes this can be proven because Scythianus loved her more than others.
Therefore, for the sake of this great love, he could have had her as his marriage partner, even though she had long been publicly known in Thebaid.
It's worth noting that Epiphanius and earlier sources are silent about the origins of the event, as no ancient writers questioned or reported otherwise.
Those who studied Epiphanius's works likely believed that the holy bishop recorded the events involving Scythianus and his character based on traditions passed down from their ancestors.
If anyone from that era or later centuries, influenced by the Manichaean heresy, had known differently, they would have challenged Epiphanius and labeled his words as lies to protect their founder from disgrace.
The silence of these people, along with Epiphanius's strong assertions, highlights the weight that should be given to Beausobre's poorly constructed criticism.
This is particularly evident because, without new evidence after so many centuries, only Beausobre, far removed from the times of Scythianus and Epiphanius-considering he passed away in 1739-attempted to overturn and erase the traditions of the ancient Church Fathers with mere fictional tales.
However, our critic seems to have treated Saint Cyril, the bishop of Jerusalem, more gently, suggesting that Cyril, though not mistaken, tended to exaggerate.
Thus, in describing the deeds of Scythianus, he took on the role of orators who prefer to embellish their arguments with declamations and superlatives rather than reveal the truth.
Cyril, when discussing Scythianus's religion, stated that it had nothing in common with either Judaism or Christianity.
He claims to have read this in the Greek text of Cyril, even though an ancient Cologne version omits the earlier words, "with Judaism."
But even if we assume that the Greek manuscripts...
We have both accounts as we read in Fourteen from Photius.
What does Cyril have that contradicts the truth?
What, if not an obvious mistake, at least shows excessive exaggeration and overstatement?
Christopher Wolf, while preparing the Photian books, which he ensured were printed in Hamburg with new types, wrote about Scythian:
"He was the first among Christians to spread the foolish idea of two principles."
But everyone knows that this foolish idea is just one of many blasphemies invented by the Manicheans regarding the birth, death, and resurrection of Christ's flesh,
which completely undermine the foundational and solid principles of the Christian faith,
and we'll explain this further below.
So, what could that religion have in common with the Christian faith, which attacks and abolishes fundamental mysteries?
If Beausobre's conjectures were correct, even a pagan who denies the existence of one God and the distinction of three persons,
who honors created and sensible things like the sun, light, and stars as divine,
and who blasphemes that the Mother of God and the divine Word of the Father became man,
and professes countless other similar errors, could have something in common with us, solely because he boldly claims the name of Christ for himself.
But who would ever affirm this as the truth?
For the pagan in question, besides the Christian name, which he sacrilegiously usurps,
would have nothing at all of the faith, morals, rites, and institutions of Christians.
In fact, he would strive to corrupt or abolish all these things.
I believe Cyril reasoned this way when he wrote that Scythian had nothing at all in common with Christianity.
And if later Beausobre imagines opposing Cyril, prompted by the testimony of Archelaus, who called Scythian a heretic and an apostate,
who failed in his intense ambition to obtain a bishopric, just as it is known about other heresy authors,
our explanation would remain steadfast.
What stops a pagan man from pretending to be a Christian?
Especially since, according to Beausobre, Scythianus never wanted a permanent home anywhere.
Instead, he moved from place to place, living in regions like the Saracens, Palestine, Thebaid, Judea, Egypt, and India.
It's possible that while staying among Christians, he pretended to follow Christianity outwardly with great deception, hoping to gain the honor and dignity of a bishopric.
Without a doubt, he would have introduced his corrupt beliefs, which he had internalized and cherished, making them easier for others to believe and profess.
When examining the beliefs and doctrines of the Manichaeans, I couldn't find even one fundamental article of the Christian faith that they preserved intact and pure.
I find it hard to believe that their principal author had anything in common with Christianity in his teachings.
As I move on to other topics, I conclude this discussion with this reasoning.
Just as this man's wickedness wasn't restrained by any law from attempting to undermine or destroy all Christian doctrines, he also flattered himself with the hope of attaining the honor of a bishopric through evil means.
These two points show that the statements of Cyril and Archelaus can be reconciled without any forced interpretation.
Now, if we were to follow Beausobre's writing style gradually, as we've decided, we would need to discuss the four books of Scythianus.
However, since we'll talk about these writings later in another part of this history, we'll skip this discussion for now, preferring to return to Epiphanius in our language again.
Beausobre brought him back on stage, criticized with insults and abuse, on the occasion of Scythianus's bad death.
Epiphanius's account of Scythianus's death is compared with the writings of other ancient authors.
Noticing that they don't completely align in wording, it suggests that the heretic in question died of natural causes.
Archelaus himself claims he wrote nothing about Scythianus's death that would imply he died unnaturally.
Cyril of Jerusalem, who lived before Epiphanius and was acquainted with the events in that city, briefly describes the heretic's arrival in Judea, suggesting it was like a plague on the region.
He then immediately adds, without any transition indicating debates with teachers of Mosaic law:
When he died of illness, the Lord ended the plague.
Finally, Photius, with a shorter statement, said that Scythianus suffered a harsh death.
From this diversity in accounts, Beausobre finds satisfaction and, as if seeking a flaw in a simple thing, translated Epiphanius's Greek text into French, adding numerous notes and comments.
He argues that this narrative collapses because no one supports it, and it is clearly contradicted by Jewish histories.
These accounts detail the destruction of the Jewish people and the fall of the Jerusalem temple by the forces of Titus and Vespasian, making it impossible for Scythianus to have debated with Jewish priests or used magic to enter the city's temple.
With the city already in ruins and the temple demolished, Scythianus could not have performed all the deeds that Epiphanius narrates, especially since he didn't visit during the apostles' time.
As we've already pointed out against Epiphanius's account in the first chapter of this work, his words should be interpreted more loosely.
Who would consider all these things truthful without reviewing the histories of the Jewish people after the reign of Titus?
However, experts in Jewish history will view it differently, recognizing that Jerusalem, not yet fully destroyed by Titus and Vespasian, still had various buildings and towers standing.
It was later rebuilt by Emperor Hadrian and inhabited not only by foreigners but also by thousands of Jews.
During that time, the city was renamed Aelia, and Rufus, the governor of Judea, used the military force given to him by Emperor Hadrian to suppress the uprising led by Bar Kokhba, a brave yet ruthless leader who had incited the rebellion, resulting in the deaths of many thousands of men, women, and children.
We noted this second destruction of the Jewish nation under the Roman emperors in our annotations on the Ecclesiastical History of Eusebius of Caesarea.
Therefore, Beausobre mistakenly praised him to support his conjectures.
Later, if the city was inhabited by foreigners from various regions of the world, as it had fallen under Roman control and its customs and name were changed, the Jews who remained there did not abandon their legal ceremonies.
They maintained the succession of priests, Levites, and other ministers.
Just as during the captivities by the Assyrians and Babylonians, they were even more determined to strictly observe the Mosaic law in synagogues, prayer houses, and other congregations.
The Pharisees, doctors of the law, and tribal leaders made every effort to ensure that the masses did not pledge allegiance to Christ or follow idols in the Roman fashion.
How then could it be possible that, as the second century came to a close, Scythianus, arriving in Jerusalem or Aelia, challenged the Jewish priests, trying to argue through debates that the Old Testament and Mosaic law came from an evil god?
And when he was defeated by his opponents, wouldn't he have tried to erase his disgrace by resorting to trickery, perhaps climbing the roof of a house near the temple ruins, or one of the ancient towers that survived the destruction by Titus and Vespasian, with the help of demons?
I don't see how these things contradict each other.
Everyone knows that the third book written by Scythianus, which he called "On Mysteries," contains refutations of the law and the prophets and is full of slanders against the sacred writers of the Old Testament.
To spread such fabrications and refutations to the public and persuade people by claiming that the Mosaic law was delivered by an evil spirit, he first needed to go to Judea to infect that region with his harmful influence.
He couldn't spread his wicked poison unless he held meetings, sermons, and debates in front of the Jews themselves.
It's revealed that this man, known for blasphemies and sacrileges, was struck down by God and removed from life by a sudden death, not only by Cyril's words:
"The Lord calmed the plague when he died of disease,"
but also by other accounts, which tell that Terebinthus, the disciple of Scythianus's wickedness and heir to his heresies, was known in Judea and Palestine but was excluded from those regions, forced to move to Persia because of this.
The disciple stirred such hatred and horror among the people due to the master's death and crimes that he was not allowed to remain there any longer.
Even Photius affirms that Scythianus's death was bitter.
A death is not usually called bitter when it results from a natural illness of the body, which separates the mind from the corruptible flesh due to the dissolution of the limbs.
We tend to call it bitter when guilty people suffer it violently with God as the avenger of crimes, or when judges and executioners, exhausted by the severity of punishments, inflict or order it to be inflicted on criminals.
That God was the author of Scythianus's death is suggested by Cyril's words;
it's likely that Photius indicated a cruel and violent death by saying "bitter death."
Finally, the hatred the Jews felt towards Terebinthus grew so intense that the uproar and anger of the people forced him to leave the territories of Palestine and Judea as an exile.
This is evident from his flight to Persia.
It is believed that he sought to hide and erase the mark of disgrace and shame by fleeing, taking on the role of a servant, and abandoning his old name.
However, Beausobre is not convinced by this claim.
Terebinthus supposedly changed his ancient name to Buddha to erase the mark of disgrace.
To persuade readers of his opinion, he crafted a rich array of scholarly knowledge and a magnificent display of words, intending to gradually lead the early Church Fathers into bad faith, causing those who read his work in French to stray from the path of truth.
In the fifth chapter of his praised book, he discusses various etymologies and explanations of the name Terebinthus, hoping to find satisfaction in interpretations that either completely refute or at least greatly diminish the deceit and tricks of the clever man.
He praises the Acts of Archelaus, Bishop of Caschara, arguing that the name Buddha was not adopted by Terebinthus to avoid the hatred and vengeance of the people.
Instead, it derives from the Chaldean language and means the same among the Persians as Terebinthus does among the Greeks.
He adds that these two names correspond perfectly to each other, just like those found in the sacred scriptures: Christ and Messiah; Peter and Cephas; Dorcas and Tabitha.
Beausobre offers this as a mystery explained to his readers.
But after reviewing Fabricius's work, he realized he had long been anticipated in understanding such a profound mystery.
Therefore, after considering these observations, he confidently affirmed that Terebinthus and Buddha have exactly the same meaning.
To support his point, he cites reliable experts like Simon Assemani, a specialist in Oriental languages and curator of the Vatican Library, along with Bochart, a dedicated writer on Sacred Geography.
They explain the Syrian words: Bethma, Boutema, and Butema.
Despite minor differences, these terms were historically used interchangeably to refer to the same Terebinth, or Budda.
Whether Beausobre's detailed exploration of these topics is accurate or fictional is for scholars of Oriental languages to determine.
Meanwhile, we are cautious about fully accepting his views, as the details he presents contain contradictions that warrant careful consideration.
We might believe that Terebinth was the original name of a Scythian servant or disciple, another figure in the Manichaean school, and that it should have been consistently used by all, including the Chaldeans, albeit pronounced differently due to language variations.
Alternatively, it could be argued that Terebinth had a compelling reason to change the name.
If Beausobre accepts the former idea, why was Terebinth replaced with Buta or Buda, without keeping the Chaldean ending in "a" or "m"?
It's clear that these names bear no resemblance to the original and do not maintain the essential elements of the original letters.
Thus, I find it difficult to accept Beausobre's claims that the Assyrians customarily altered even personal birth names.
The argument made by Bochart falls apart because, in his "Sacred Geography," the author does not claim that the words Terebinthus and Butam, or Budam, are connected in meaning for the Assyrians and Greeks. Instead, these words correspond to the Persian word Buddas and are used to refer to Terebinthus, the impious teacher of Manes.
Even if Bochart supported Beausobre's ideas, it wouldn't be difficult for us to dismiss the old Church Fathers' opinions as false. Cyril clearly wrote: "So that he would not be known in Persia by his real name, he called himself Budda," exposing Terebinthus's deceitful efforts to hide his and his teacher's actions. Photius confirmed this from the words of both Cyril and Epiphanius, stating that Terebinthus went to Persia and took the name Budda. His reputation had already spread, and hatred for the impious man had grown before he joined any group.
What more? Peter Siculus, who carefully studied the actions of the Manicheans through various writings and consistent accounts, supported what has been said so far. It's puzzling that Beausobre, in exploring ancient texts, didn't find anyone who claimed that the word Terebinthus was used by the Greeks to mean a tree and then interpreted by the Assyrians as Budda or Butha. He wondered why the Persians would give this name to Terebinthus, as if they preferred to call him by the local name rather than the Greek. It's strange that no one testified to this.
Therefore, the three examples taken from sacred scriptures, which refer to the same person, do not apply to the current question, considering the diversity of languages where it was necessary to duplicate those two words. The sacred writers themselves explained the reason for the duplication to avoid any confusion.
So, to ensure no one thinks we're straying from the examples given, let's refer to the New Testament Scriptures where Christ and the Messiah, Peter and Cephas, Tabitha and Dorcas are mentioned.
In all these cases, the sacred writers and interpreters used different approaches to highlight the diversity of languages and interpretations, so no one would mistakenly think these were different people.
John talked about Christ and the Messiah, writing: "I know that the Messiah is coming, who is called Christ"; and more clearly in another passage, he quotes Andrew, Simon Peter's brother, saying: "We have found the Messiah, which is translated Christ."
Again, John, when speaking about Peter and Cephas, says: "You are Simon, son of Jonah, you will be called Cephas, which is translated Peter."
Finally, Saint Luke, in the Acts of the Apostles, to clear up any confusion, when discussing Tabitha, states: "In Joppa, there was a disciple named Tabitha, which is translated as Dorcas."
Indeed, we find countless other examples like this in the Scriptures and among the holy Church Fathers, which we don't need to focus on now, as we don't want to delve too deeply into countering Beausobre's attempts to mislead.
Therefore, as we wrap up this argument, we conclude this way.
Among so many ancient writers, none have said that Terebinth, a Greek word, is translated as Buddas in Syriac, so we don't understand why Beausobre wanted to use previous examples from the Scriptures to involve the ancient holy Church Fathers.
Writers who delve into Manichaean topics often face criticism, with accusations of deceit and falsehoods.
Yet, what Beausobre wrote about Terebinthus in this chapter might have been acceptable if he hadn't later paved the way to challenge more significant accounts from earlier writers about the Manichaeans.
Furthermore, he made every effort to dismiss those doctrines of the Christian faith clearly stated in the sacred scriptures.
The first area involves his writings on the discussions of Buddas, or Terebinthus, with the priests of the Sun in Babylon, as mentioned by Cyril, Epiphanius, Photius, and others.
Apparently, this most wicked man, seeking fame and honor, shamelessly claimed to be born of a virgin, as also noted in the Acts of Archelaus.
The second area concerns his writings about the tricks and demonic arts of Terebinthus, which ancient testimonies indicate he was well-versed in.
Indeed, Beausobre argues that it's unreasonable to believe that evil angels or demons could have any influence or power over elements, humans, or other creations.
Adhering to this view, he ridicules the Roman Church's rituals, where divine aid is sought through exorcisms and exsufflations over living beings, elements, and other inanimate objects to expel demons.
Regarding the first matter, the esteemed critic firmly denies that Terebinthus, or Buddha the Manichaean, could have fabricated and declared himself to be born from the womb or side of a virgin.
First, he mentions that one of the main doctrines of the Manichaeans was their denial of the mystery of the Incarnation of the Divine Word and the union of two natures in one person.
They believed that a virgin woman could not conceive and give birth to a human son without physical intercourse and a man's seed.
He attributes this belief to another man with the same name, who was the founder of the Gymnosophists' sect, according to ancient writers.
Some even attributed it to Simon Magus.
Saint Jerome, in his book against Jovinian, explicitly names the author of this deception as Buddha the Indian, writing:
Among the Gymnosophists of India, it is believed that a virgin gave birth to their leader, Buddha, from her side.
I acknowledge that this claim about the Manichaean Buddha is not supported by Cyril, Epiphanius, Photius, and others who documented the activities of the Manichaeans.
However, this tale of a virgin birth is mentioned in the Acts of Archelaus.
But what does it mean?
Was such a narrative part of the original acts and older copies of that discussion?
Did anyone ever affirm it?
Those acts, despite the backing of learned individuals, were often significantly altered and damaged by the biases of interpreters and the carelessness and laziness of scribes, making it difficult, if not impossible, to judge their integrity today.
Therefore, I am inclined to believe that if we must acknowledge another Indian besides the Manichaean Buddha as the founder of the Gymnosophists' sect, unskilled scribes, confused by the similarity of names, might have inserted that mythical birth into the Acts of Archelaus as if it were announced by the Manichaean Buddha.
Our theory is indeed supported by the silence of other writers and the testimony of Beausobre himself.
Cyril, Epiphanius, Photius, Peter the Sicilian, and other writers often argue in numerous instances that when discussing Manichaean topics, they relied on the Acts of Archelaus.
They refer to these acts as apocryphal and either summarized or expanded on their content in their own writings.
Therefore, according to Beausobre, since no writer after Archelaus has mentioned this mythical generation as being taught by the Manichaean Buddha, we must conclude that it was neither in the original writings of Archelaus nor in their early copies.
Or, if it was, it was dismissed as a false addition.
Although the Buddha we are discussing may not have created or spread the story about his own generation, we can't deny without some boldness that this other Manichaean leader wanted to engage in discussions with the priests of the Sun and the learned men of Persia.
For Cyril, after describing his flight from the borders of Palestine, his name change, and his move to Persia, immediately added:
"But there he had opponents, the priests of the Sun, and, after many speeches and debates, he was refuted."
Finally, when he was about to be captured, he fled to a certain widow.
Photius also noted that this trickster did not benefit from his changed name. When he became known through his works and teachings to those previously unaware of him, he was refuted and expelled by the learned men among the Persians, who, despite not having a pious opinion, still held a better view on all matters concerning him.
As for what topics Buddha might have discussed and debated with the Persian priests, I don't feel it's my place to judge, lest I be accused of recklessness.
However, Beausobre tried to investigate the matter more thoroughly.
He noticed differences between the writing style of Archelaus and the speaking style of Epiphanius but overlooked that he could have reconciled their testimonies without any contradiction.
Using his usual method of criticism, he argued that the Church Fathers misunderstood Zoroaster and the Persians' theories-whether they involved two principles or just one, and the transmigration of souls.
He claimed to prove this in another part of his History, which he kept for himself.
He concludes from Archelaus's testimony that Archelaus did not say the debate between Buddha and the Persian priests or sages was about the existence of two principles.
Instead, it referred to the war waged by opposing powers against God.
Yet, if we consider these things carefully, shouldn't we conclude that Beausobre was merely indulging in nonsense?
For if, according to Archelaus, the debate was about the war that opposing rulers or powers waged against God before the creation of things, then indeed Buddha was boldly defending the concept of two eternal, conflicting principles, as Epiphanius asserted.
Therefore, what difference can we say exists in the speaking style of each author when both speeches aim for the same goal, differing only in wording?
Archelaus described the debate more elaborately, while Epiphanius was more succinct.
Photius ultimately claims that only Buddha and the priests of the Sun debated, arguing more accurately than that Manichaean would have thought.
Indeed, he gained no disciples from his debates at all, except for that widow friend, deceived by tricks and wicked arts, who provided him lodging, as we now know from Archelaus's account.
He then added: Early in the morning, he ascended a high terrace where he began to invoke certain names, which Turbo told us only the seven chosen ones had learned.
Archelaus immediately explains what Buddha did after ascending to the rooftop and the consequences he faced as a result of divine retribution.
When he ascended
he says
it was for some unknown ritual or purpose, and he did it alone to ensure no one could witness him.
While contemplating these things, the most righteous God commanded that a spirit cast him down beneath the earth.
Beausobre points out that this account has many flaws.
When Archelaus mentioned that Buddha invoked certain names, Cyril diverged from him, replacing them with aerial demons-those the Manichaeans commonly invoked in their sacrifices or gatherings, as interpreted by Christophorus Wolfius.
Beausobre also noted that Greek writers do not agree on the rituals used by Buddha.
Archelaus only mentioned his ascent to the rooftop to invoke certain names, while Epiphanius claimed these were magical rituals intended to perform some supernatural sign to silence his opponents.
Archelaus ultimately concludes that a spirit was ordered by God to cast Buddha down from the rooftop, which Epiphanius referred to as an angel.
Cedrenus, as if witnessing the scene himself, describes the angel attacking the wicked Terebinthus, suddenly throwing him down headlong.
Beausobre is convinced that all these accounts are unreliable since no one could have known them without revelation.
To dispel these ancient prejudiced opinions against heretics, Beausobre focused on using more intelligent observations to seek the truth by adhering only to the narrative of Archelaus, which he describes as simple, natural, and innocent.
His first observation is as follows: Buddha, it seems, went up to the rooftop of his house early in the morning to pray to God, and he ascended alone
he says
to obey divine commands, which state that we should avoid the eyes and presence of people when praying.
The next point is about the Manichaean practice of prayer, which comes from the teachings of Zoroaster.
Followers are instructed to pray facing East, envisioning the fire seen in the sun as both the throne and the divine presence.
It's also noted that people in the East traditionally climbed onto the roofs of their houses to pray.
We can see this from Peter praying in Joppa and Esther going to the upper parts of the house when she wanted to do something in secret.
Quite amusing, Beausobre!
However, I'm puzzled by how he tries to claim that these practices align with Scripture and the prayer rites of ancient Catholics and holy men.
Indeed, prayer should be done in secret to avoid vanity and to focus the mind, which is essential for keeping the heart's thoughts centered on God.
But who would think that Buddha had this goal in mind during prayer?
Or who would imagine he intended to follow divine commands for this purpose?
There were also priests of the Sun present, whom he had called as adversaries-since he had lost in their debates-to witness his tricks.
Moreover, an essential doctrine of the Manichaeans was to see the light and sun not as the seat and throne of the highest God, but to worship it as the true God.
This was noted by the highest pope, Leo the First, who discussed the Manichaeans in Rome worshipping the rising sun, turning and bowing their heads in honor of the shining orb.
However, this occurs partly due to ignorance and partly because of the spirit of paganism.
Saint Peter, grieving, considered and added:
Even if some intend to worship the Creator of the beautiful light rather than the light itself, which is merely a creation, the ritual of such services differs little from the superstitious worship of the pagans.
He adds: Therefore, the perversity that must be condemned should be removed from the customs of the faithful, and the honor due to the one God should not be mixed with the rites of those who serve created things.
This is what Leo said and wrote to guide certain Christians of the Roman Church, who were misled by the corrupt practices of the Manichaeans, away from such a manner of praying, as the entire text of his speech clarifies.
It will be shown through countless arguments that the Manichaeans, like the pagans, although guided by a different principle, offered worship to the sun and stars.
We read that Saint Peter, in Joppa, around the sixth hour, went up to the upper parts, not at sunrise.
But it is not confirmed that he went up to the roof of the house.
Scripture, discussing the prayer of Queen Esther, only states that she stood in ashes and dirt, humbled her body with fasting, filled all the places where she used to rejoice with torn hair, and always turned to the Lord, saying: Help me, alone, for besides you, there is no other helper.
So where did Pricaeus, praised by Beausobre, find that Queen Esther retreated to the flat surface of her palace to engage in more secret exercises of Jewish religion?
We gather this somewhat obscurely from the history of Daniel, which perhaps Beausobre overlooked, lest he be caught in his own trap.
The sacred text narrates how the prophet of the Lord, at three set hours of the day, entered his house, and with the windows open in his upper room towards Jerusalem, knelt and prayed.
This manner of acting clearly signifies that Daniel intended to look towards the temple built in Jerusalem, rather than the East, while praying.
So, Beausobre cannot stop us from believing that Saint Peter, while staying with Simon in Joppa, went up to the rooftop at six o'clock to pray facing the temple in Jerusalem.
But let's move on from that.
Although these things might have a certain harmful influence-used by heretics to gradually undermine the devotion of Catholics-they trouble us in matters related to the most sacred rites and ceremonies of Christ.
These heterodox individuals try to overturn, or at least claim, that these rites aren't based on apostolic institutions and divine commands, but rather on human choice and the customs of various regions and peoples.
However, they aren't significant enough to overthrow or openly disrespect the true doctrines of religion, especially if they don't challenge the authority of sacred pastors in prescribing ecclesiastical rites and ceremonies.
Therefore, it troubled us more that Beausobre's complex and twisted mind is also influenced by things explicitly stated in sacred writings.
He tries to introduce his blatant infidelity, surrounded by many slanders, into the minds of others.
This follows the usual display of vain and deceitful learning meant to captivate the unsuspecting reader, who enjoys novelty over piety, and traps them with lures and snares.
Indeed, everything else he adds at the end of that chapter, intending to conclude the history of Terebinth, or Buddha Manichaeus, from Greek and Latin Fathers, should be viewed in this light.
Looking more closely at the actions of this heretic, it's likely that he was influenced by the superstitions of magicians.
This is because he came from the Babylonian people, whose philosophers were used to honoring angels not as gods but as ministers of Divinity.
They believed that these angels presided over the days, months, and years in a specific order, much like they presided over the elements and everything that usually happens to people in this life.
He boldly claims that the Catholic Church might have drawn its sacred rites and the order of feast days and divine services from this Babylonian and Persian superstition.
He suggests that those peoples were accustomed to invoking their angels as intermediaries and mediators, similar to how recent Catholics mention a saint each day in daily services and liturgies.
He asserts that such prayers are called spells and magical chants by the Muslims.
Despite this collection of nonsense and falsehoods, Beausobre says he is unsure whether the names of angels, or the intelligences of the heavens, were revealed only to the chosen Manichaeans, who far exceeded the number seven, as Turbo confessed when he presented himself before Archelaus, the bishop of Caschara.
Indeed, Augustine, who was once a mere listener of this sect, mentions a certain love song in which the aeons are written.
It seems to me that Beausobre is inconsistent with himself, as he now dismisses or overlooks what he previously wrote about Terebinthus, Buddha, that is, the superstitious institutions of the Babylonians and Persians.
He argues that the Manichaeans did not invoke angels, even though they gave them honor and praise.
He criticizes Cyril for confusing angels with demons, claiming that the Manichaeans invoked aerial demons trapped between the earth and the space of the moon.
However, he insists that these practices should not be invoked but completely rejected.
This is prompted by Turbon's confession, where he mentioned that Manes instructed his followers to anoint their heads with exorcised oil after meals, while invoking or uttering certain names that represented the mysteries of that false religion.
The knowledge of these names was reserved for only a select group of seven, or rather seventy, chosen followers.
This exorcised oil was referred to as "fascinated" according to the Greek and Latin versions, as Tillemont indicated.
Therefore, Beausobre, focusing on these two terms, adds: "If 'exorcised' should be understood as 'fascinated,' what can be said about the many rituals and ceremonies of the Roman Church?"
He concludes: "If the Manicheans performed exorcisms over oil before using it, it clearly shows that they were influenced by the absurd belief that demons could afflict elements and bodies, a belief that has significantly persisted in the Church, using prayers and exorcisms to drive them away."
We must carefully address all these matters to dispel the deceptions, false accusations, and mockeries with which the sycophant Beausobre dared to attack the Catholic Church.
Firstly, he confuses the aeons of heretics with angels and demons. The creators of these aeons were Simon Magus, the leader of heretics; Montanus; the Menandrians; Saturnilians; Cerinthians; Carpocratians; Valentinians; and others derived from Mark the Egyptian.
They, inspired by the tales of ancient poets and pagans, invented the existence and army of aeons, which they named differently at will for the various roles they imagined them to perform in their dreams.
But the doctrine of the ancient pagans was quite different.
Although they lacked the illumination of faith, Hesiod was the first to acknowledge the existence of certain immortal spirits endowed with reason and intelligence, positioned between God, who held the highest place, and humans, who were at the lowest. He called them demons or genii; we call them angels.
Plato clearly mentioned demons, especially in Timaeus, where he considered them to be bound to the orbits, or rather, that the orbits and stars themselves are like lesser gods.
According to this, he described demons as being generated, lowly creatures.
Although they are naturally dissolvable and mortal, by the supreme will of God, which is stronger than nature, they are made immortal and eternal.
He asserts that animals are created by them; indeed, even the bodies into which he infused human souls.
Plato is supported by his interpreter Alcinous, the magician Hostanes, Orpheus, Thales, Pythagoras, and others, who all affirmed the existence of demons or angels without any doubt, even though they reasoned differently about their nature and properties.
The other system regarding the existence of aeons has appeared to all writers as an inextricable fable.
It has not yet been thoroughly explored whether these aeons have anything in common with the substances we call angels or demons.
Therefore, Augustine, when mentioning the amorous song of the Manichaeans in which aeons were described, did not believe angels or demons were indicated.
Instead, he was well aware of the frauds of these heretics, who falsely invented those intelligences fixed in the stars and orbits.
Led by superstitious persuasion, they falsely claimed that the entire human life depends on the influences of stars, elements, or aeons, or at least that these influences could sometimes be changed if they were supplicated; when, indeed, from their erratic movement, or stable permanence, they might harm by certain malignant aspects.
Our Leo the Great, in various places, attacked both the Manichaeans and the Priscillianists, defenders of these lies, reproaching them thus: What is the sun, or what is the moon, but visible creatures and corporeal elements of light?
One of which is of greater brightness, and the other of lesser light.
Then, distinguishing daylight from nighttime, he suggests that different qualities, not levels of life, exist in them.
Before the sun, moon, and stars were created, three days passed without the sun's path and nights without the moon and stars.
On the fourth day, the Creator explained why he made them, saying they were for the benefit of humans, so the rational being would not be confused about the distinction of months, the cycle of years, or the counting of time.
Through the unequal length of hours and the visible signs of different risings, the sun concludes the years, and the moon renews the months.
If I could spend more time examining the superstitions of ancient Babylonian and Persian philosophers, who claimed that various conjunctions of ages were tied to each hour, day, and month, falsely saying human destinies depended on them, and whom they sought to appease- I could easily show that they have no connection with our beliefs.
Who would believe that Belial aligns with God or that an idol has any connection with truth?
An idol is merely a fabrication, created by lies to deceive rational beings.
Therefore, if, as Leo, the wisest interpreter of divine Scriptures, said, it was through divine omnipotence that the stars and heavenly signs, lacking sense and life, were made to distinguish the succession of days, months, and years, as stated in the sacred writings of the Old Testament, it is fitting to praise only divine power and providence, which created such signs for our knowledge, instruction, and benefit.
However, since the movements of the heavens, changes in the air, and the ascensions and descensions of stars or ages, with their courses, degrees, retrogradations, rises, and falls, are all entirely derived from inanimate nature, what praise, honor, or reasonable worship can be attributed to them?
Therefore, nothing is more superstitious or contrary to the truth than the deceptive philosophies of both pagans and ancient heretics, who, when they observed wondrous events in the world, attributed them to the influences of ages.
Augustine wrote about Montanus and the Cataphrygians, among other heretical figures; they used an impure washing for their followers instead of the sacred cleansing and regeneration of baptism, reciting as many names of ages as they imagined were contained in the entire circle of the year.
We learn from a synodical book that Montanus invented eight hundred seventy ages, each with its own name.
What similarity or resemblance can the institution of Catholic rites and festivals have with these fictional tales?
Doesn't the Catholic Church, in organizing festivals, reciting offices, and liturgies, considering the diversity of times and the dignity of mysteries that should be celebrated with solemn worship as divinely instituted, offer praises to the most good and greatest God?
Indeed, Catholics dedicate worship exclusively to God in offices, liturgies, and both public and private prayers, directing their voices and hearts to Him.
So how does Beausobre conclude that the daily rites of the Catholic religion can in any way be compared to the superstitious ceremonies of the Babylonians, Persians, and magicians?
One might wonder if the connection lies in the Roman Church dedicating certain anniversary festivals to specific days of the year and instructing that these be observed with sacred rituals and ceremonies.
Or perhaps it's because, on each day of the year, as the birthday of a person known for holiness, teaching, martyrdom, or virginity is celebrated, the Church recalls the most notable acts of virtue of these individuals.
This is done to praise God and inspire others to pursue similar virtues.
It is clear that these practices do not correspond to the superstitious celebrations and mythical rites used by the Persians, Babylonians, and magi in the worship of eternal beings and stars.
If I were discussing this with someone other than Beausobre, perhaps a Gentile, atheist, or Epicurean who does not adhere to the Holy Scriptures or divine mandates, I would rely solely on reasons derived from the natural light of reason to explain the sanctity and excellence of the Roman Church's rituals.
However, since this discussion concerns a Christian, yet non-Catholic, who accepts the authority of the Old Testament Scriptures, where various annual solemnities are mentioned, and also the evangelical mandates of the New Testament, while professing the mysteries related to Jesus Christ's life and mission:
I understand that Beausobre foolishly attempted to critique these traditions.
He seemed excessively captivated by Persian and Babylonian fables, aiming to mock and mislead readers who might not think wisely about the Roman Church.
And, returning to other matters, does Beausobre not recall that in sacred evangelical writings, demons are also referred to as angels?
In the Gospel of Matthew, Christ refers to those spirits who, out of pride, fell from divine grace with the devil and were condemned to eternal fire, as angels.
The Scriptures also refer to them elsewhere as evil angels, under the name of demons.
It's not surprising, then, that Cyril claims Terebinthus, or Buddha, called upon aerial demons for protection.
This aligns with Turbo's confession, where he mentioned that the Manichaeans would anoint their heads with exorcised oil after eating and drinking.
By "exorcised," we mean magically enchanted oil, typically used by necromancers to summon evil spirits for protection, seeking their help when attempting to perform unnatural acts through tricks.
Thus, it shouldn't be seen as a fault for Tillemont to interpret "exorcised" as "enchanted."
The writer of Ecclesiastical History notes that ancient magicians used enchanted candles, lamps, water, oil, and other items, not to expel but to summon spirits for protection, assistance, and to foresee future events.
Pliny, in his writings, mentions Osthanes, who described various methods, saying that through water, spheres, air, stars, lanterns, basins, axes, and others, they promised divination.
It's quite likely that the Manichaeans, skilled in this art, wanted to use oil desecrated by incantations to summon evil spirits.
Finally, we find no contradiction with Tillemont's interpretation of the word "exorcised" as used in Turbo's confession.
Turbo likely used the language of Manes, whose actions he describes, who might have referred to sacred and natural things corrupted by wicked rites as exorcisms, which we will explore more clearly in its proper context.
In this situation, once everything is revealed and explained, most people would see it as unnecessary to continue further, as there are more pressing matters to address.
Some argue that exorcisms should be mocked and that evil spirits, or demons, do not actually have the power to disturb the elements or bodies.
But why is that?
Beausobre, a Christian by profession, though not Catholic, is knowledgeable about the Gospel Scriptures and aware of the deeds of Christ and those described by the apostles.
Yet, he dares to deny both the power and effectiveness of exorcisms in expelling demons and the influence and fury these demons have on living beings and objects.
What does this mean, other than implying that Matthew, Mark, and Luke fabricated stories?
Either when they said that Jesus cast out demons with a word or when they described the two men from the region of the Gerasenes who came out of the tombs, possessed by demons, and were so fierce that no one could pass that way.
How can it be that people cannot be tormented by unclean spirits if the Evangelists clearly narrate that a blind and mute man was brought to Christ, and when the demon was cast out, the mute man spoke?
And if, after considering these and other similar deeds of Christ, Beausobre still remains doubtful and does not believe, I would point to what Saint Luke recounted about the father who brought his son to Christ.
The son had a mute spirit which, whenever it seized him, would throw him down, making him foam at the mouth, grind his teeth, and become rigid.
Did not that evil spirit, at the command of Christ, fall to the ground convulsing and foaming?
With these terrible and violent movements, the son, from his earliest childhood, was often thrown into fire and water to destroy him.
If someone doesn't accept these arguments and others we can present to Beausobre, and refuses to believe that Terebinthus, or Buddha, was cast down to the earth and tormented by a demon until he died, then what can we do with someone in a frenzy, lacking reason, who argues about religion based on their own impulses?
But if they think that these effects, which we sometimes observe, are caused by diseases like madness or mania, what could be more absurd?
The words of the evangelists would make no sense, where Christ, by the command of His voice, said: Deaf and dumb spirit, I command you, come out of him, and do not enter him again.
It would be no different from the cry of the impure spirits tormenting the men of the synagogue: What do we have to do with you, Son of God?
Have you come here to torment us before the time?
Or the plea made by the same spirits to Christ: If you cast us out, send us into the herd of pigs.
Then, having heard the Lord's voice: Go, they went into the pigs, and the whole herd rushed down the steep bank into the sea and died in the waters.
Experience shows us that such expressions cannot relate to madness, mania, or any illnesses.
Diseases are healed, not cast out to migrate from one body to another.
We've never heard them exclaiming or pleading; only the afflicted, seized by illnesses, feel the pain, bursting into cries and wails, asking for treatment and relief.
The Jewish people marveled at Christ's power and authority in expelling evil spirits from human bodies.
Although there were wicked slanderers who claimed he used sorcery to expel demons, they couldn't deny that sometimes elements and bodies were tormented by evil spirits.
He addressed the accusation, "He casts out demons by Beelzebub, the prince of demons," by confronting his accusers directly.
He questioned, "If I cast out demons by Beelzebub, by whom do your sons cast them out? Therefore, they will be your judges."
This manner of speaking suggested that the power to exorcise the possessed had been granted to other sons of the synagogue, who could openly testify that they expelled demons not by tricks, but through the name of Christ and the power of the Almighty God.
Indeed, they seem to support our cause, as Mark narrates John's words to Christ:
"Teacher, we saw someone casting out demons in your name, who does not follow us, and we prohibited him."
But to prevent John and the other apostles and disciples from believing that the power of exorcism depended on human strength, he immediately commanded them not to stop him and added:
"For no one who performs a miracle in my name can soon speak evil of me."
So let Beausobre, the mocker, come now and consider the source of the power of exorcisms, what exorcisms involve, to whom the power of exorcising has been given, and then mock, if he can, that sacred rite which the Catholic Roman Church has always preserved as received from the Son of God.
Indeed, the power and effectiveness of exorcisms deriving from the name of Jesus is more than sufficiently confirmed by the Holy Scriptures.
For there is no other name given under heaven by which we must be saved than that one.
Especially when, at its invocation, every knee shall bow, in heaven, on earth, and under the earth.
Therefore, it is no wonder that when that name is invoked in exorcisms, such support and authority are granted to the sacred ministers of the Church, that, having driven away the evil spirits from the bodies of the possessed, people who were previously severely tormented, like Mary Magdalene from whom Jesus cast out seven demons, are no longer troubled by any distress or demonic madness.
When we focus on the nature or purpose of exorcisms, it's clear what they are and what they involve.
They are not to be confused with the spells of sorcerers; instead, they were established by God Himself to counter enchantments.
Therefore, Beausobre is misleading and malicious when he compares these sacred and divine rites to superstitious incantations.
Christ Himself acknowledged that prayer combined with fasting can expel particularly stubborn spirits.
When questioned about why His disciples couldn't free a demon-possessed person, He responded: "This kind of demon is not driven out except by prayer and fasting."
Let Beausobre recognize and understand the power given to the ministers of the Church. The priests and evangelists of Jesus Christ, as sacred ministers of the law, have been granted authority over demons, as clearly stated by the evangelists Luke, Matthew, and Mark. They noted that when Christ was about to send the apostles to preach the Gospel, He gave them power and authority over all demons.
Also, regarding the seventy-two disciples He sent in pairs ahead of Him to every city and place He planned to visit, it is recorded that upon returning from their mission, they said without hesitation: "Lord, even demons are subject to us in Your name."
If Beausobre, motivated solely by a desire to argue and criticize, distorts the ecclesiastical and divine laws by claiming that this power and authority were only for the apostles and disciples of Christ to destroy pagan religion and overcome Jewish disbelief, we cannot agree with him. It has been thoroughly shown that this power to drive out demons will persist in the Church and can be exercised by both good and bad ministers alike.
This topic finds a remarkable testimony in the Gospel of Luke.
When Christ judges the wicked ministers of the Church, he will not reward them with the crown of merit and glory, even though they may say:
"Lord, did we not cast out demons in your name, and perform many miracles in your name?" Those who cannot truly serve Jesus, the Savior of mankind, are those who, despite using the power of virtue and ministry, do not seek to align themselves with the good morals of Christ Jesus.
Since enough has been said about the power of exorcisms in driving out demons, a well-meaning Catholic reader will find it easy to believe that Buddha, or Terebinthus, the most wicked magician, was driven and struck by demons, suffered a cruel death, and was suddenly taken away from the joys of this life.
Finally, Beausobre openly denies such a bad death and, using the words of a charlatan, boldly tried to confuse this Buddha with another man of the same name, the false apostle and disciple of Mani.
Therefore, being more generous with him, he grants him a longer life, extending his days to the time when Mani sent twelve announcers of his false doctrines far and wide, aiming to overturn the evangelical doctrine of Christ the Lord.
If we consider that this elaborate story merely appears to be true, then our current efforts would already be pointless; not only would they falter, but they would completely collapse.
Supporters of Beausobre, who have so far praised the Manichaean history written by a non-Catholic, would have more reason to laugh now than to lament, as we would have attempted in vain to dismantle and remove so many and such great heretical and nonsensical tales with which the praised history is filled.
Meanwhile, let no one be upset with me if I strive to remove the preceding foolishness of Beausobre with the wisdom of the ancient holy fathers.
I haven't included testimonies to make the sacred Scriptures more familiar to readers, nor to imply that they could be interpreted differently or twisted to imply certain diseases.
Ancient medical experts only metaphorically called these "demonic" due to the conflicts among bodily fluids, spirits, and nerves.
If we wanted to explore this argument further, it would take a lot of effort and seem like we were deviating from our usual discussion.
Beausobre didn't, and couldn't, present a single old Catholic Church writer against our views or efforts. He understood very well that both Greek and Latin Church Fathers agreed on the interpretations of the praised Scripture texts, which also affirmed and praised the power and authority of the exorcist order to expel demons.
Thus, there was no need to appeal to tradition as an interpreter of the sacred Scriptures. However, to acknowledge the authority of the Holy Fathers, I will provide one or two testimonies from Saint Leo the Great, especially since our focus is on illuminating the writings of this holy pope and teacher of the Catholic and Apostolic See.
He explained the preceding words of Saints Matthew, Luke, and Mark about the spirits of demons without ambiguity, interpreting the cruelty with which the bodies of the possessed are usually tormented and the command by which they are expelled, particularly when exorcists' prayers are combined with fasting.
Therefore, he recommends fasting in the seventh month to be more devoutly observed by the faithful.
In every Christian struggle, self-control is incredibly valuable.
It's so powerful that some of the most stubborn demonic spirits, which cannot be expelled by exorcists' commands, are driven out solely through fasting and prayer.
As the Lord says, this kind of demon is not driven out except by fasting and prayer.
The prayer of someone who fasts is pleasing to God and terrifying to the devil.
Besides the power given to Church ministers to cast out spirits from possessed bodies, another type of exorcism is mentioned.
Priests and other sacred ministers often apply this for the sanctification of catechumens before they are cleansed by baptism, so that their souls may be delivered from diabolic power.
Therefore, the letter to the bishops of Sicily states, Given these facts, dear brothers, with so many clear documents available, you can see that for the baptism of the elect, who must be examined with exorcisms, sanctified by fasting, and instructed by frequent teachings, only two times are to be observed: Easter and Pentecost.
Let Beausobre note, I ask, that the rite of exorcisms comes from no other source than the Scriptures and the rule of the apostles, as our most holy pontiff implied here, and as Saint Siricius affirmed in a letter to Himerius of Tarragona.
Then let him criticize and attack, if he can, the custom of the Roman Church and the authority of sacred ministers in performing exorcisms, and in freeing bodies and souls from demonic power.
Let us begin a new discussion with Beausobre in the next chapter.
Meanwhile, we will set aside many other trivial matters and his futile conjectures, which do not pertain to the ecclesiastical history we aim to compose.
Chapter Four
On Manes and His Main Teachings.
New Beausobrean Ideas Are Discovered and Overturned.
Beausobre wanted to address the affairs and morals of Scythianus and Terebinthus lightly, and he boldly criticized both the Greek and Latin Church Fathers, sometimes distorting the Holy Scriptures for incorrect or extreme interpretations.
I believe I've explained enough in the previous chapter.
In that chapter, I also aimed to discuss matters concerning the person of Manes, his homeland, parents, teachings, and errors.
However, I realized that the chapter had become quite lengthy due to various Beausobrean arguments, many of which were barely relevant to the author's intention and the purpose of writing history.
This could have complicated things for our readers in exploring these issues.
So, to avoid confusion with our current method of debate, we decided it would be more appropriate and prudent to discuss Manes separately here.
We were indeed confirmed in this decision when, upon reviewing two Beausobrean chapters, namely the sixth and seventh, we encountered so many topics that if we wanted to address each one individually, it would almost indefinitely prolong this method of writing and debating.
Therefore, staying true to our intention, we proposed to discuss and refute only those things that either undermine the tradition of the Holy Fathers or damage and overturn the sacred rites and doctrines of the Catholic Church, causing great harm to souls.
Now, let us begin our discussion from the sixth chapter, to which Beausobre gives the title: Examination of the History of Manes Before His Heresy.
In this, he presented both Greek and Latin testimonies, not to follow them, but as he did in previous chapters with Scythianus and Terebinthus, to criticize and challenge the authors, arguing that their testimonies should be refuted with his inept commentaries.
Regarding the birth year and original name of the heretic Manes, the Persian, our learned friend Simon Assemani, in Volume One, page 393, follows the Chronicle of the Edessenes and writes in his Eastern Library: Manes was born in the year 551, which corresponds to the year 240 AD according to the Greek era.
Beausobre believed that this testimony from the Edessene Chronicle could be confirmed by another account from Eutychius, which states: Manes appeared in the world during the reign of Gordian.
Furthermore, Gordian was declared emperor in the year 238 AD and remained in power until 244 AD.
However, a diligent writer like Beausobre should have distinguished between the Gordians.
The elder Gordians usurped power in Africa while Maximinus was at war with the Germans.
They were killed shortly after, and Balbinus and Pupienus, along with Gordian the Younger, held the empire for one year.
They were murdered by soldiers in the year 238 AD.
In that same year, Gordian, either the son or grandson of the thirty-first Gordian killed in Africa, took control of the empire, won several victories against the Persians, and was defeated by order of Philip six years later.
Upon closer examination of Eutychius of Alexandria's history, Beausobre discovered that it did not speak of Manes' birth year but of his already spread heresy, for which he was punished.
Beausobre noted that Eutychius had made a serious chronological error by claiming that the reign of Varanes the First, son of the Persian King Hormisdas, began in the third year of Gordian's empire, an account that is evidently false.
For the Syrian writer Abulpharagius states that Varanes the First began to reign when Probus was declared emperor, specifically in the year 276 AD.
But Beausobre should have noticed that Abulpharagius made a mistake, as the most accurate chronicles show.
.
According to Dionysius Petavius, Varanes the First began his reign after the death of Hormisdas, specifically in the year 273.
The ruler who took over the Persians when Probus was declared emperor was Varanes the Second.
He held the kingdom from the year 273 to 293.
However, since these details are minor, we consider it unnecessary to focus on them.
It is worth noting, though, that the Syrian writers, often cited by Beausobre, should not be blindly trusted.
According to Asseman, all ancient writers stated that Manes was originally Persian.
However, whether he was born in the province of the Babylonians or the Chaldeans is not as certain.
Saint Ephraem described him as Babylonian, while Archelaus, a bishop in Mesopotamia, in a debate with him, indicated rather clearly that he was of Chaldean origin.
Beausobre noted that Suidas and Cedrenus opposed these views.
They, not following the common belief, wanted to attribute a different origin to him, namely that of the Brahmins, referring to that region extending towards the ocean, inhabited by people dedicated to religious and philosophical studies, as Cellarius mentioned in his commentaries on Ptolemy.
Some more recent proponents of innovation, eager for argument, have tried to suggest through fanciful stories that the Brahmins descended from Abraham.
They further explained the etymology of the name, interpreting the term Brachma as someone highly skilled in the knowledge of all things.
Those who focus on discussing the truth of matters based on solid reasons now realize that these types of arguments are frivolous.
But who would think that a person always ready to invent wouldn't fit this description?
Mainly because Beausobre himself is so dedicated and diligent in his study, he always refers to authors who contradict each other.
This approach allows him to gradually reach his goal, which is to convince, with all his effort, that no trust should be placed in the historical accounts handed down and written by the ancients.
But since these points can be known to everyone, let us proceed to the topic at hand, specifically to those things that seem like myths when Beausobre proposes to discuss the native and birth name of the heretic.
He says the Latin writers called him Corbicium, the Greeks called him Cubricum, but Augustine, in his book on Heresies, either through the carelessness of his scribe or himself, called him Urbicum.
However, Beausobre argues, without citing an author, that these three names, seemingly corrupted from the name Carcubium, possibly refer to the homeland of Manes located in the region of the Babylonians or Chaldeans.
He particularly insists it can be argued because we understand that the earlier names, Corbicus and Cubricus, do not have the ending or sound of Eastern words.
He offers various conjectures for this opinion.
One of which he thinks is derived from the city of Carcoub, or Carcub, which Assemanus mentions in his writings about Eastern matters.
From this native place, he suggests those names Corbicius and Cubricus are derived, as all the fundamental elements are preserved in them.
Another theory he derives from the mythical rank of presbyter, in which he believes Manes was distinguished among Christians.
Performing this role, he says, in Ahvaz, or Ehvaz, a chief place of a small province that the Chaldeans once ruled.
Since at that time presbyters and bishops were not appointed unless from cities or at least territories where they had to perform sacred duties, so that the families from which they originated and the customs and institutions of those they had to govern would become known to them, he concludes that Manes had his birthplace in the praised province.
From this, he infers the following consequence.
Since the province of Ahvaz has a city named Carcoub, or Carcub, within its district, we can conclude that the heretic was called Carcubium after this local name.
The theories that attempt to overturn old traditions and introduce a new form of church discipline, which Beausobre invented, not only falter but completely fall apart if we examine his reasoning.
First, the name Carcubii was unknown to the ancients, since it is derived from the place or city where Manes was born, and could now be common to all the residents of that place.
So, why then would it have been unique to Manes?
Why would the ancients have used it to specifically identify this particular heretic?
It might have been because the ancestors of Manes built that city, Carcubium, or gained such renown for their notable deeds that they received a surname from their homeland, just as we understand happened with Antenor, Romulus, Constantine, Hadrian Aelius, Antinous, and others.
However, reasoning in this way is contradicted by the heretic's efforts, who, after the death of the widow who adopted him as her son and heir, took care to reject his birth name and adopt a more honorable one.
Indeed, all writers agree, supported by Christophorus Wolfius, Gataker, Menagius, and others among the recent scholars, that the name Cubrici meant something disgraceful or implied a servile condition.
They claim he changed it to Manes to avoid a mark of disgrace on his personal fortune.
Therefore, if Cubrici was a name of servitude and not tied to his homeland, he would never have changed it, as Wolfius seems to argue in his notes on the History of Photius written against the Manichaeans.
"I remain silent," he says, "because a servile name can indeed disgrace a free man, but it cannot impose servitude." Meanwhile, he wonders why the man exchanged a servile name for another that was no less so.
Among the Greeks, the name Manes was associated with servitude, as Gataker and Menage clearly explain in their commentary on Diogenes Laertius, page two hundred fifteen, using ancient texts to support their claims beyond doubt.
For the Greeks, the name Manes carried the same connotation of disgrace and servitude as Cubrici.
Although in Persian, Manes meant an eloquent and vigorous debater, ancient writers note that the Greeks used it to imply madness, as explained by Cyril of Jerusalem, Epiphanius, Titus of Bostra, and others who have discussed the name.
However, Beausobre criticizes and mocks these interpretations, calling them foolish and trivial.
He specifically targets Epiphanius for suggesting that divine Providence arranged for a heretic to have a name implying madness, so that the Greeks, repulsed by this name, would be shielded from the errors taught by Manes.
But Manichaeus might argue that Epiphanius misunderstood the workings of Providence.
The plan that Epiphanius boasted about was ineffective, as many Greeks were still drawn in by this heresy.
How can one remain undisturbed when faced with Beausobre's wicked and impious criticism?
Do divine Providence's plans impose a necessity on human minds so strong that their wickedness cannot escape them and often thwarts them?
The forbidden tree was given to the first parents as a safeguard of original innocence and a protection against death.
They should have feared death as the most terrible of all things.
But what happened?
Deceived by gluttony's allure and the serpent's suggestions, they recklessly took the forbidden fruit and ate it, casting aside their fear of death.
Furthermore, aside from other examples from divine writings, isn't it true that divine Providence arranged for prisons, chains, crosses, torturers, and terrifying names to be used for upholding justice, protecting the state, and preserving peace?
So that people, afraid of punishment, would avoid committing crimes and not have to endure those evils?
If no one, except a blasphemer, could say that God, with less wisdom, arranged through His providence that death, greatly feared by the first parents, was threatened to them to deter them from eating and desiring forbidden food;
if only the foolish would claim that so many kinds of punishments were wrongly invented for criminals and established by the most holy laws, then I do not see how Beausobre could criticize and mock Epiphanius for writing that it was arranged by divine Providence for Manes to take on a name full of horror, so that Greeks would abhor his heresy.
Indeed, that name could have stirred a certain horror in the minds of the Greeks, just like death, prisons, chains, whips, crosses, killings, and torturers.
But the Greeks themselves, influenced by the corrupt principles of the Manichaean philosophy and greatly indulging in sensual pleasures and shamelessness, easily shook off all horror, which could have protected them from such corruption, and chose to embrace the teachings of that wicked sect.
We consider it unnecessary to mention the other etymologies of this name described by Beausobre there;
however, the reader may consult section 5 of this chapter.
Regarding the priesthood of Manes, we do not deny that Gregory Abulpharagius asserts it without any author.
But I don't see how much trust we can place in it, especially when it describes Manes as if he were one of the first Doctors of the Catholic Church, who taught and interpreted the sacred books of Scripture.
He was known for debating with Jews and pagans, and eventually, after departing from the faith, he called himself the Messiah.
Furthermore, if we consider this testimony of Abulpharagius and evaluate it according to the rules of true criticism, several things seem to indicate signs of falsehood.
I omit, firstly, that none of the Fathers and writers from the third and fourth centuries spoke of such Manichaean deeds and his priesthood, lest I be accused of using negative arguments to undermine the positive assertion of the Syrian writer; although Beausobre almost always uses similar reasoning.
However, I cannot overlook Cyril of Jerusalem's actions; who, in his catechesis, describing the more serious crimes of Manes, did not even mention this lightly.
He would not have omitted it if a heretic had first been enlisted in the clerical militia and priesthood and then fallen into that horrible and immense sacrilege.
Indeed, he would have presented this to enlighten people as something utterly detestable.
Unless we suspect that Cyril was unaware of the man's priesthood, or at least wanted to hide it, lest he bring the other sacred priests and their order into disrepute and contempt among certain pagans and Jews then residing in Jerusalem.
But let's suppose Cyril wanted to use this strategy to protect the honor of the priesthood.
Shall we then say the same for other writers who described Manichaean matters?
Away with such a notion.
It's interesting to note that everyone who mentioned Xenaia, Severus of Sozopolis, Peter of Apamea, Zoara, and Isaac the Persian highlighted their priesthood and clerical status.
They believed that no harm or disgrace could come to the Priesthood of Christ if they stated that those tainted with serious crimes and heresy, shamefully abandoning the sanctity of the priesthood and sacred duties, and corrupting themselves and the divine mysteries with heinous acts, should be held in utmost contempt.
We all know that in the sixth century of the Church, the Manichaean sect, known as the Acephali, sought the support of the Caesars and Eastern emperors.
Their goal was to gradually lead churchmen away from marriage and corrupt women with vile and sacrilegious acts.
Furthermore, the records of the Constantinopolitan synod under Pope Agapetus and Patriarch Menas of Constantinople, along with the letters of Pope Hormisdas and many other documents, clearly show that the Manichaeans, under the guise of the Acephali, held prominent positions in the East during the sixth century and spread the false teachings and practices of their sect.
We will illustrate this more clearly by considering the historical context.
If the council fathers and ancient writers neither concealed nor ignored the priesthood or other clerical orders within the Manichaean sect; and if those at the Council of Gangra acknowledged the priestly role and monastic life of Eustathius of Sebaste, a bishop in Armenia.
He, in the fourth century of the Church, just before the Nicene Council, worked hard to advance the Manichaean sect and its practices.
I really don't understand why, among so many writers who discussed Manes, only Gregory Abulpharagius claims he was initiated into the priesthood.
It seems more likely that Manes pretended to be a priest, recklessly and sacrilegiously imitating priestly duties.
We believe this is reasonable because he boldly claimed to be an apostle and advocate of Jesus Christ without the proper mission from the Spirit of the Lord.
By assuming these false titles and roles, he gained authority among simpler men and women, making it easier to deceive them into giving him their complete trust and obedience.
They wouldn't have trusted him if they hadn't seen him perform religious duties and ministries.
It's clear how weak and unfounded the argument is that Beausobre follows to suggest Manes' homeland and priesthood.
Those well-versed in the history of the sacred church know that in the early centuries, when the Catholic religion was spreading, priests and bishops were rarely chosen from their birthplaces.
Instead, they were ordained by the apostles and their successors and sent to foreign nations with well-known customs and disciplines, as we have demonstrated extensively with Eusebius of Caesarea in another work.
Moving on to the other meanings Beausobre argues are associated with the name of Manes, considering the Persian and Syrian languages and the different expressions of the Church Fathers, we will try to summarize what he reported from others' opinions.
He claims it means vessel, instrument, and clothing, according to Epiphanius, Archelaus, and Ephraem the Syrian.
But who doesn't understand that the esteemed Church Fathers were referring more to the characteristics of the Manicheans' behavior than the genuine meaning of the word?
More reasonably, Archelaus refers to him as the vessel of wickedness and the tool of the Antichrist, echoing the language of the Scriptures, particularly the style of Saint Paul, who describes those who undermine the Gospel and the Catholic law as both vessels and tools of wickedness, as well as Antichrists.
These labels clearly fit their behavior.
Similarly, Saint Ephraem, praised by Assemanus, explains that Manes was dressed in the guise and attire of the devil, writing:
"The devil clothed Manes like his own garment so that he might use him as his tool and reveal his own oracles through him."
Since these traits are common to all heretics who undermine the Gospel of Christ, I truly don't understand why they claim these traits stem solely from the name of Manes. Otherwise, we would need to call the founders of every false sect Manes, because they are vessels and tools of the devil, and the devil clothes them in his own garment to reveal his oracles through them.
He criticizes Cyril of Jerusalem, who believed that the word Manes was used by the Persians to mean speech. However, Manes himself claims in a letter to Marcellus that the eloquence of that speech does not suit him. He then dismisses as foolish and joking Pearson's observation, who, following the interpretation of the rabbis, believes that Manes is derived from min, which indicates a heretic.
But who can invent a name associated with infamy and disgrace, common to all founders of false sects, especially when it's clear that this name was chosen by no one other than himself?
It seems unlikely that he would deliberately abandon the name "Curbicius," meaning servitude, to adopt another name that, if not more disgraceful, at least carried equal infamy, as would be the case with Manes according to Pearson's opinion. Although he argues that "To Manes" was originally a title rather than a name derived from the Hebrew min, meaning heretic.
Thomas Hyde is the author who claims that the name "Mani" is interpreted differently by the Persians, suggesting it means a painter.
Beausobre noted that Wolfius shared this view, writing about the etymology provided by Thomas Hyde in chapter 21, page 280, regarding the religion of the ancient Persians, based on the Persian language.
Hyde rejected Epiphanius's etymology and confirmed that Manes was correctly called "Mani," which in Persian signifies a painter.
However, the etymologies and meanings we've discussed might seem like an attempt to discredit this man if we don't immediately compare it with other aspects related to the term Manes.
Therefore, Usher of Armagh presents an opinion, relying on a testimony from Severus Sulpicius, claiming that an Israelite king was named Mane, known as Manahem in the book of Second Kings and referred to as Manaem by the Seventy interpreters.
He suggests these words correspond to the terms Paraclete and Comforter.
Beausobre asserts this is the straightforward and natural origin of the name Manes, and since he considers it more honorable than the others, he believes it should be preferred above all.
Furthermore, he is ready to resolve any complexities found in it to persuade his readers gradually.
As he addresses these complexities, he first considers it likely that Mane could be derived from Manaem, especially given the speaking style and usage of the Orientals.
It was customary for the Greeks to drop the final "m" of such words, turning them into Manes, just as they did with Budda into Buddas.
He imagines Augustine supporting this earlier conjecture, as in the book on Heresies, Augustine refers to the heretic we're discussing as Manin, not Mane, following the Latin practice of changing the Greek "e" into "i."
Augustine was known for maintaining this rule, as shown by the example of Adimantus.
He believed it should be written not as
Adamantum, but in Latin as
Adimantum.
Similarly, Theodoretus preferred
Manens over
Manes.
Suidas appeared to agree, noting that in the genitive case, it is
Manentis.
This serves as evidence that in the nominative, it should be read as
Manens.
However, Beausobre seems confident that he has discovered the true origin of the word
Manes and its explanation.
He applies this understanding to the term
Manichaeus, a name commonly used by the followers of this heretic for their teacher and adopted by many writers.
He argues that this word should also derive from the Chaldean word
Manahem.
He suggests that the only differences between the two names arise from various pronunciations and linguistic evolution, as supported by Pagninus, Junius, and Tremellius.
These scholars used different letter combinations, writing and pronouncing
Menaehem and
Manachem in various ways, while the Greeks, wanting to add new letters, formed
Manichaeum.
Whether these theories are valid can be better judged by experts in Greek and Oriental languages.
Meanwhile, we cannot agree with Beausobre's narrative style.
Names, which serve as identifiers of things, expressing their origins and properties, can be completely altered by the addition or subtraction of letters according to personal preferences.
It seems to me that Cicero sought to challenge or criticize this overindulgence in speculative philosophy when he wrote:
"Since you think Neptune is named from swimming, there will be no name that you cannot explain, with one letter changed, where it came from."
So, what should we conclude about the numerous and significant changes and additions in the writings that Beausobre collected regarding the origin and properties of the word "Manes"?
Even if we agree that his method of discussion isn't trivial or fictional, what does that really mean?
Is "Manes" a title of honor because a certain king of the Israelites was called by that name in the Old Testament Scriptures?
Wasn't the name Judah also considered honorable and highly praised in the same Testament?
Yet, if we look at the New Testament, we find that Judas, a disciple of Christ, was a traitor, sacrilegious, and the source of many evils.
Does this imply he had a royal origin and was owed the scepter of the Israelites?
That's nonsense.
But since dwelling on this could be seen as a fault, we'll skip over countless examples that could strongly criticize Beausobre and overturn his misguided conjectures.
Now, concerning the name "Paraclete," which Manes presumptuously took for himself, we'll soon explain with insights from Leo the Great and others to more thoroughly refute Beausobre's false conjectures.
As we begin discussing the teachings of Manes, we should focus on what forms the foundation for all his other ideas, which this entire construct of sacrilege and fables was built upon by that most impious architect.
First and foremost, we encounter the monstrous blasphemy that Manes erupted into as he began spreading his wicked heresy among the people.
He boasted sacrilegiously about a divine power given to him, aiming to display the power and authority of the divine to gain the faith and reverence of the people.
He tried to demonstrate that he now bore the form of Christ and proclaimed himself to be the Paraclete.
Beausobre questions this final point.
Though he is convinced by others' testimonies and doesn't deny that Mani was called the Paraclete and Comforter, he argues that this title likely came from the widow who adopted Mani as her son and heir.
She, having first granted him freedom, wanted him to be the Comforter of her widowhood and old age.
He finds it hard to believe that people could be so foolish as to trust in such a blatant deception.
Therefore, it's more reasonable to think that once his status as a servant changed, thanks to his benefactress, Mani might have added a syllable to his name, becoming Manahem, as if he had transformed into a new man through his freedom.
He claims this name was very honorable, citing Assemani, who noted that the name Maanus was well-known among both Syrian and Arab kings.
However, Eusebius of Caesarea challenges these speculative tales, which Beausobre either ignored or chose not to acknowledge.
Eusebius, who couldn't have borrowed Mani's deeds from Cyril of Jerusalem or Epiphanius because he preceded them, drew from older records preserved in church archives, as he mentions in his preface.
He writes in his ecclesiastical history that during Pope Felix's time, a certain Manes, living up to his name and driven by a demonic impulse, taught a universally despised and cursed heresy.
Thus, Eusebius presents the true name of the heretic, explains its etymology and meaning, and highlights the demonic assistance he used to spread his errors.
He reiterates that Mani's madness, or fury, was acquired through demonic art, and points to the consequences of his actions to persuade readers of this.
To demonstrate his point, he immediately added what we mentioned earlier: he tried to assume the role of Christ, declaring himself to be the Paraclete.
Eusebius aimed to convey three things:
First, that the heretic Manes, not Manahem, was named by the Persians.
Second, that madness, audacity, and insanity were present in him through the influence of a demon.
Third, that he falsely claimed to imitate Christ and declared himself as the Paraclete sent for the comfort and instruction of the world and the Church.
Who doesn't see that these three points clearly contradict Beausobre's tales?
If he initially crafted everything to convince his followers of his sacrilegious remarks, pretending to be an apostle and a comforter sent by Christ?
To avoid unjustly criticizing Beausobre as a storyteller, I turn to Leo the Great, the pope in Rome, who, during a general inquiry against the Manichaeans hiding in Rome, was eager to uncover what they believed and what Manes' disciples dared to teach.
He clearly stated that the Manichaean disciples believed, or at least preached, this blasphemy:
That his disciples believed the Holy Spirit appeared in their teacher Manes, making it seem as if they followed a great leader, and that the Paraclete promised by the Lord had not come until this deceiver of the unfortunate emerged, in whom the Spirit of God resided, so that Manes himself was none other than the Spirit, guiding his disciples into all truth through his voice and tongue?
Therefore, the truth of the events must prevail and dispel every contrary conjecture by Beausobre.
We must be convinced, without any doubt, that Manes paved the way for many sacrilegious doctrines with his egregious and blasphemous lie, which either corrupt or utterly overthrow the sacred mysteries of the Catholic faith.
But let's return to the sequence of the story.
For this reason, the heretic attempted to obtain books of Sacred Scripture with money and attract Christian men to his side with tricks.
He mixed some truths with lies and fables.
By doing this, as he tried to make his sect more credible, he gradually instilled his errors into the minds of others.
Moreover, he reinforced all this with magical arts and tricks, which he certainly used to deceive people.
He was unafraid to attempt things sometimes completely impossible with human and diabolical powers.
For instance, when he tried in vain to cure the son of the King of Persia, who was abandoned by doctors and suffering from a severe illness.
After laying these sacrilegious and superstitious foundations, he spread other foolish and impious doctrines.
Eusebius says he borrowed from various heretics who had already died, undermining and completely corrupting the Catholic religion with Persian poisons.
Among other fabrications, borrowed from Marcion, Valentinus, Carpocrates, and other authors of the Gnostic sect, the following are usually included:
namely, that there are two principles of all things, God and the devil.
He taught that all good things come from God and all evil things come from the devil.
That God is the source of all virtue and perfection, from which the New Testament is derived, while the devil is the author of sin and the Old Testament.
That the substance of humans was produced by both Gods, but in such a way that the good God only created souls, while material bodies, being imperfect and always subject to corruption and change, originated only from another evil God.
He completely took away free will from humans, introducing fate and necessity into our human affairs.
Christ also denied the true incarnation and claimed that he took on only a phantom body.
He taught people various ideas like these, which, as we mentioned, were partly drawn from the most corrupt sources of ancient heretics, partly from the absurd beliefs of pagan philosophers, and partly from the misinterpretation of the very teachings of the Christian religion.
All these nonsensical tales and fabricated dreams were more clearly outlined by Saint Epiphanius.
With these and other sacrilegious doctrines, Manes, above all other authors of heresies, sought to make himself great and famous.
Meanwhile, that cunning impostor, aiming to display great authority over people, especially those who only look at the surface of things, tried to win them over to his views.
He pretended to imitate Christ the Lord, the Savior of the human race, both in selecting disciples and in other aspects related to the apostolic mission.
This will be explained more fully in the next chapter, as we discuss the number of these disciples.
Chapter Five
The number of false apostles of Mani, as defined by the Holy Fathers, remains unchanged.
The opinion of Father Natalis Alexander is noted but dismissed.
Eusebius of Caesarea briefly described Mani's method of spreading his heretical ideas in Book 7 of Ecclesiastical History, Chapter 27.
He wrote, "In his madness, he chose twelve disciples to preach, imitating Christ."
All ancient writers agree with Eusebius, except for one.
Recent scholars also support this view, including Beausobre, as we will mention later.
Therefore, I believe Father Natalis Alexander, though a very learned man, should not be heeded on this point.
He, while discussing the number of Mani's disciples, somehow mistakenly concludes from Augustine that the number exceeds twenty-two.
Meanwhile, he writes in Ecclesiastical History, 3rd century, Article 9, that Mani, leading many disciples into error, selected twenty-two to preach his wicked doctrines and impious tales, with three being particularly notable: Thomas, Hermas, and Addas.
I believe this view should not be accepted.
How could Mani have sought to imitate the Lord Christ in establishing his disciples if he had chosen more than twelve false apostles?
Furthermore, it is incorrect that Father Natalis has Augustine as a supporter of his opinion.
Augustine, who closely aligns with Eusebius, defined the number of Mani's disciples as only twelve.
Indeed, other ancient writers have followed this opinion, except for Epiphanius.
Augustine could not have been clearer on this topic, writing in Book on Heresies, Chapter 46,
"From where he calls himself an apostle of Jesus Christ in his writings, because Jesus Christ had promised to send, and sent the Holy Spirit through him.
For this reason, Mani also had twelve disciples, in the manner of the apostolic mission, a number that the Manichaeans still maintain today."
Theotoretus used similar phrases when discussing the stories of heretics.
He described how Manes chose his disciples and imitated a false Christ with these words:
Having appointed twelve disciples in the manner of the Lord, he set out for Mesopotamia.
What more?
A consistent tradition over the following 600 years confirmed the truth we speak of.
Photius briefly noted the number of Manes' disciples and their mission, saying,
From then on, he gathered together twelve disciples, whom he sent out as heralds of error.
Peter Siculus, who lived shortly after, was well-informed about Manichaean matters and institutions.
Known for his learning and nobility, he served on various missions for Emperor Basil, especially to the Armenians.
He documented the history of the rise, progress, and fall of the Manichaeans, listing not only the names of those twelve disciples but also detailing their deeds, roles, missions, writings, interpretations, and commentaries in a brief Greek-Latin work addressed to the Archbishop of Bulgaria.
This writer reports the following about Manes' disciples:
Furthermore, the disciples of Manes were twelve in number.
In listing them, he first mentions the one who succeeded Manes after he was executed by order of the Persian king, saying, 'Siginus succeeded Manes.
'
He is followed by another named Thomas, who wrote the Gospel of the Manichaeans.
Saint Cyril of Jerusalem warned Catholics not to read this, writing,
Let no one read the Gospel according to Thomas.
For he is not one of the twelve apostles, but one of the three disciples of Manes.
This fraudulent work was forbidden for all Catholics to read or keep under the penalty of excommunication, as will be seen in due course.
These two, Buddha and Herva, along with Adan and Adamantus, were added.
The latter, being more wicked and daring than the others, was sent by Manes as his messenger to various parts of the world, serving as a faithful precursor.
Then he appointed three others: Hierax, Heraclides, and Apphthonius, to interpret and explain his teachings and preachings.
To them, he added three more: Agapinos, who conceived the Heptalogus, Zarva, and Gabriarius.
Peter the Sicilian reviewed these matters related to the equally nefarious and superstitious first Manichaean Hierarchy.
Although he lived long after the time of Manes, he elaborated this work using both the ancient and consistent traditions of the Greeks and Armenians, as well as the most certain documents, as we will see in due course.
Since these things are supported by so many significant testimonies, I do not believe Epiphanius was gravely mistaken, as I am unsure of the foundation or testimony on which he explicitly affirmed about Manichaeus Heresies sixty-six, number three.
He had already, in a manner of speaking, gathered his troupe, naming them twenty-two disciples.
But I think the error should be attributed more to the scribes or translators than to Epiphanius himself.
Or perhaps he intended to allude not to the first hierarchy of the Manichaean sect and its form and number, but to a later one, which was larger and about which Augustine spoke elsewhere.
The more shameful error should be attributed to P.
Natalis Alexander, who, in discussing the errors of the Manichaeans, after examining Augustine's works, failed to notice that the opinion about the more than twenty-two disciples of Manes was very shaky and entirely in peril.
Or at least, to clear himself of this oversight, he needed to present both opinions openly, allowing the reader to choose the more firm and plausible one.
Perhaps a well-educated man, distinguished by a wide range of topics and questions, held firm to the first opinion that came to him.
He believed that Epiphanius, the most prolific writer of the Manichaean sect, was not misled by any error.
We felt it necessary to mention this to avoid being seen as negligent.
It's quite surprising that Beausobre, who often seeks complexity in simple matters, works diligently to undermine the tradition of the ancient fathers by pointing out and expanding on their apparent contradictions.
He failed to notice that Epiphanius disagreed with other writers on this significant issue, or that P.
Natalis Alexander mistakenly cited Augustine when attributing eighteen disciples to Manes.
Therefore, by aligning with the more common belief, he assumes and asserts that this heretic had twelve disciples.
Among them, as he described in chapter seven of the previous book, there were three more notable preachers who first carried out the Manichaean mission and were more malevolent than the others.
In detailing the events following the widow's death, whose inheritance Manes had acquired, he suggests that Manes left the city of Seleucia or Ctesiphon, known to the Arabs as Modain, or as Assemanus notes, the city of Citez, where he was initially raised and educated in various sciences.
Eventually, Manes retreated to Huzistan, one of the provinces in the Babylonian region of Iraq.
He supports this theory by referencing the Acts of Archelaus, stating that the heretic was educated in the royal city of the Persians, where a school of sciences and magic thrived.
Furthermore, he mentions that the Greeks rarely referenced anything about the life of Manes from ages twelve to sixty.
He also notes that this last detail is presented differently in the copies of the debate held with Archelaus, about which he plans to discuss when addressing the time the holy bishop convened at Cascharam.
As we mentioned earlier, to stay within our intended scope, three of the twelve disciples stand out as more distinguished: Thomas, Addaeus, and Hermas.
Cyril of Jerusalem noted a variation, listing Buddha instead of Addaeus, which some authors also mention when naming the twelve disciples.
In their accounts, Buddha is placed in the second position instead of Addaeus.
However, I won't linger on this to avoid criticism.
Although a non-Catholic writer offers different views on the mission of these three disciples, we will discuss their missions and roles in detail elsewhere to adhere to our guidelines.
For now, let's focus on the killing of the Persian king's son by Manes.
Chapter Six
The Killing of the Persian King's Son by Manes.
Beausobrian's comments and conjectures are completely rejected.
After being imprisoned, Manes bribed the guards and escaped, making his way to the borders of Persia and Mesopotamia.
He chose twelve disciples and sent them to various provinces in the East to spread his foolish and sacrilegious sect.
Manes, eager for greater fame and to showcase a unique and divine power above other humans, was contemplating achieving something beyond natural means.
He thought this would work out favorably when he heard that the Persian king's son was severely ill and bedridden in the royal city.
As we know, Persian kings typically lived in either Seleucia or Ctesiphon.
Tillemont notes that both cities are located near the Tigris River (Volume 4, on the Heresy of the Manichaeans, article 7).
According to Epiphanius, Manes, although far from the royal court, rushed there without delay.
He relied on the books he had received from Terebinthus of Scythianus, who got them from the widow of Terebinthus or Budda, believing he could find a remedy to cure the royal boy's illness, to the amazement and applause of the entire Persian kingdom.
But what happened next, as Epiphanius tells us, was that when Manes revealed his intention, he promised certain help to the king's son.
However, his hopes were shattered.
When he applied certain medicines to the sick boy, his expectations were so disappointed that the young man eventually died in his hands, proving his promises to be empty and deceitful.
Thus far Epiphanius.
Socrates described this matter somewhat differently (History, Book 1, Chapter).
This story is about a Manichaean who reluctantly went to the royal court to heal a sick person.
The king of the Persians, worried about his son's health and influenced by Manichaeus' reputation, called him as an apostle, hoping his son would be cured through his actions.
It's unclear whether, before this incident, Manes tried anything beyond human abilities with trickery, which might have spread his reputation to the king.
It's also uncertain whether the cunning trickster applied a real remedy to the sick boy, just pretended to, or used magical arts.
We lean towards the last option, based on the testimony of Saint Cyril of Jerusalem, who wrote in his sixth catechetical lecture that Manes promised to heal the boy through prayer to boast of his integrity and power, as if he were pious.
Photius narrated this event in a similar way.
Relying on ancient writings he had collected and reviewed, he not only agreed with Epiphanius, Socrates, and Cyril of Jerusalem but also briefly explained the mission of the twelve disciples Manes had chosen as heralds of his impious doctrine and accomplices in his crimes.
He immediately adds: "But the mad Manes, notorious for his misdeeds, became known to the Persian king.
When the king's son fell ill and he heard that Manes promised to cure him through prayers, he called the arrogant man for his son's treatment and dismissed the current doctors, even though they promised an easy treatment.
As soon as Manes finished his prayer, he took the life of the boy, who might not have died if his safety had not been assured."
Beausobre, following some absurd and fabricated rules of his criticism, critiques Archelaus, Cyril, and Epiphanius.
He does this because they weren't afraid to tell falsehoods, and because Cyril, in his Commentaries, seems to attribute a deceitful or mad character to this heretic.
Additionally, he complains about Photius describing this type of event with excessive embellishment.
He particularly objects to the statement:
"But that mad Manes became infamous for his crimes."
Understanding these words were aimed at him, he burst out with:
"When do leaders flatter themselves," he says,
"thinking they will achieve miracles of healing with the help of criminals?"
Finally, he criticizes recent writers, especially targeting P. Natalis Alexander, for wrongly suggesting that the heretic relied on magic arts and tricks to take on the task of curing the king's son. He claims they fell into a shameful contradiction, as they relied on the Acts of Archelaus, who, to prove that the heretic was not the Paraclete promised in the scriptures, said:
"He did not show any sign or wonder."
Therefore, the holy bishop criticizes Manes mainly on this point, reasoning:
"The Paraclete promised by Christ Jesus was supposed to glorify the Lord with an infinite multitude of miracles, and the Manichean throughout his entire life and appearance did not perform even the smallest miracle."
But who doesn't see that Beausobre wanted to play on the stage and weave a story instead of providing historical criticism? On this matter, since I ought not to have a lengthy discussion now, I would remove these fabricated falsehoods with the major distinction assigned, which great men have taught and natural reason itself ought to persuade, that there is a difference between tricks and miracles. Archelaus rightly denies that Manes performed any signs that derive solely from divine power and might.
He doesn't deny that the man was known for engaging in evil deeds and tricks, which involved the arts of magicians.
Especially since, as Beausobre notes, he was initially taught magic in Seleucia or Ctesiphon.
Therefore, Archelaus argued that Manes couldn't perform true miracles because God wasn't with him.
Those miracles, which belong to the Paraclete or the Holy Spirit, show that those practicing sorcery are far removed from divine power.
So how could Beausobre, Natalis, Tillemont, and more recent writers infer that they departed from Archelaus' testimony, to which they should have given credence?
They should have concluded that they either wanted to ignore or misuse the rules of dialectics to deceive unsuspecting readers, who, without reflecting on the variations in his trivial arguments, confuse true divine miracles with the tricks of magicians.
From this, our Catholic reader understands that more recent writers haven't contradicted the sayings of the ancients but have wished to adhere more solidly to them.
Indeed, Manes truly couldn't perform any miracles; though he tried to deceive others' minds, eyes, and opinions with the fallacies he was known for.
In this sense, unless one is foolish, Photius' testimony should be understood, which stated: "Manes became famous for his crime, etc."
Indeed, someone should be called infamous in crime and wickedness if they pretend that the apostleship to overthrow the truth of the Catholic religion was given to them by Jesus Christ;
who calls himself the Paraclete; who has already sent false preachers to spread a false religion in various parts of the world;
whose reputation must have been well-publicized not only among the uneducated and common people but also among magistrates, nobles, and princes.
Who could believe that his name, deeds, authority, and power, which he falsely claimed, were unknown to the king of the Persians?
Drawn by these magnificent gifts and hoping to restore his son's health, the king either wanted to summon Mani to the royal court, or Mani himself decided to go there, hoping to use a demon's help to heal the sick prince.
Therefore, Beausobre's outcry shouldn't be taken too seriously when he asks, "When did wicked princes ever hope to help themselves?"
While it's true that the most wicked people, without any pretense of piety and religion, reveal their evil lives openly, or when these become evident from clear signs, if their depraved ways remain hidden and are carefully masked by a false cloak of religion and piety, they can easily be deceived, and often are.
Thus, Photius's words shouldn't be twisted to suggest that Mani was notorious for wickedness at the king's court; rather, he was known before God and the Church, which was being undermined by his heresies, blasphemies, and errors, especially as he spread his wicked doctrines and continued to gain more followers each day.
After troubling both the oldest Fathers of the Greek and Latin Churches and more recent writers, Beausobre admits he's tired of finding Gregory Abulpharagius, the Assyrian patriarch and Eastern writer, leaning towards the opinions of his predecessors, which he reported as borrowed from others' opinions and rumors; specifically, when, using a certain formula of economic writing, he said:
It is said that Sapor, the king of the Persians, stuffed the skin of the slain Mani with straw and hung it on the city walls on a cross because, although Mani boasted greatly, he couldn't cure the king's son of his illness.
According to Beausobre, Gregory seemed hesitant to fully believe the previous story.
This hesitation is suggested by the phrase "is said," which appears at the beginning of the passage.
Furthermore, he expresses surprise that such a public and memorable event was supposedly recorded with less care by only one Easterner, as only Bar-Hebraeus, also known as Abulpharagius, mentioned it.
Yet, despite speaking of it with uncertainty, he might have ignored it altogether if he hadn't encountered it in Greek writings.
Nonetheless, he states he is willing to accept the truth of this event.
In considering this, he acknowledges that the matter requires various explanations.
Specifically, that Mani did not decide to ensure the leader's health for any reason other than being persuaded by royal pleas, given the man's renowned reputation for his scientific knowledge and virtuous excellence.
He claims this explanation is supported by Socrates' testimony, which we noted earlier.
Additionally, he mentions the backing of all the Easterners, who stated that Mani quickly gained Shapur's trust, believing it would benefit himself and his ill son due to Mani's knowledge.
Indeed, he tries to show through many arguments that a heretical man like Mani had nothing that would typically earn royal esteem.
First, because the common belief was that Mani possessed great and exceptional holiness.
Traits such as self-restraint, abstinence, fasting, and an outward devotion or piety, which give the appearance of a deeply spiritual person and which hypocrites often use to gain public admiration, were especially noted in him;
not to mention the austerity, sadness, and paleness, with which, according to Ephraim, the devil had marked Mani to deceive the unsuspecting.
Considering his poverty, it's evident he followed the Manichaean way, wanting his chosen ones to be subject to the law, so they wouldn't own anything at all.
Experience shows that nothing gains people's goodwill and esteem more effectively than the disdain and renunciation of worldly things, a practice that holds significant power among Eastern peoples.
From the Treasury of the Persian Language, we learn that Indians take great pride in apparent holiness when they strive for voluntary poverty.
Another clue comes from Archelaus, who noted that Manes could be called the foremost of the wise men of his time, especially in Persian sciences, with medicine being highly valued, as they believed nothing was more essential to life's needs, as Xenophon observed.
These two songs suggest that medicine was another aspect of the magi's philosophy:
"He is a Persian mage who knows the stars, who knows the powers of herbs and the worship of the gods."
Thus, immersed in his studies and pursuits, Beausobre reasoned, gathering many other points that oppose tradition, aiming to reduce the uncertain testimony of Gregory of Albupharagius, the Monophysite metropolitan, into a fictional system that would erase the truth of this history.
What he added was intended to persuade the reader that Manes was highly versed in medical disciplines, using examples like Zoroaster, the Persian prophet, who in the city of Divavar ordered a sick person to be healed with fluid extracted from a plant, or Alexander of Lycopolis, who accompanied Sapor the Persian during war, concluding that he was present with the king as a physician.
This passage highlights the high esteem in which doctors were held among the Persians, a fact supported by Saint Ephraem.
Before departing from this life, Ephraem wished to bless a man named Simeon, saying, "Just as a doctor in the camp, may your name spread across the world."
According to Beausobre, this saying became a proverb among Eastern peoples, reflecting the belief, noted by Strabo, that the art of medicine was intended for preserving human life. Strabo also mentions that Scythianus, who was rumored to have taught Mani, was involved in the study of medicine, and Hierax, one of the twelve Manichaean disciples, also pursued this discipline.
As Beausobre concludes his narrative, he notes that many individuals from monastic communities, solitary professions, and even the episcopal order were eagerly sought after by the Eastern peoples. They easily became part of the Persian kings' clientele and customs, as mentioned in the "Miscellaneous History" Book 15, concerning a certain Bozan whom King Cavades of the Persians greatly admired as an excellent doctor. The learned Assemanus provides various examples of this in his "Bibliotheca Orientalis."
These observations lead Beausobre to conclude that any Persian or anyone at the Persian royal court might be regarded in a similar way. This suggests that Mani could have been summoned by Shapur to the court as a most excellent and noble doctor, known for his great experience in healing illnesses.
However, where do we read, or which writer has ever claimed, that Mani held such a reputation for himself? All we have is the unfortunate experiment on a royal child, as recorded by Abulpharagius, whom Beausobre relies on, and this alone could not justify him being declared a most wise doctor.
What can we conclude from this situation, except that the court of the Persian kings was filled with doctors, much like armies and fleets are used to fortify camps?
But could anything be more unlikely?
It seems plausible that Shapur had some men skilled in medicine among his household and close friends.
We know he expelled them from the royal palace when informed that the charlatan Mani claimed to possess divine power in healing.
This wasn't because Mani had actual medical knowledge, but because Shapur hoped Mani could help his sick son due to the remarkable holiness Mani claimed to have.
Mani professed to be a follower of Jesus Christ, a claim he fabricated, and he displayed great piety and devotion, which he pursued diligently.
It is reasonable to affirm this, especially since all Greek and Latin writers agree on the story, even if they differ slightly in their wording.
Moreover, Beausobre stated that Mani was a follower of extreme poverty, which he used to claim exceptional holiness.
But what evidence did he provide for this poverty?
None is available.
In fact, it is unknown how he could be called a practitioner of such great virtue, since we are unaware of how he might have used the wealth he acquired from a widow's inheritance.
For this reason, it should have been explained how, when, or for what purposes Mani spent the inherited wealth: whether he used it to support the poor and sick, to enrich friends and relatives, or if he completed some notable work of piety to reduce himself to extreme poverty.
Beausobre did not deny in previous chapters that Mani acquired great wealth from the Scythians and from the widow whose property he inherited.
Therefore, it was most appropriate for someone claiming to be a more accurate and diligent writer to reconcile these two contradictory accounts using the best critical methods.
This would prevent the introduction of absurd stories into the new history of the Manichaeans.
Since this was not achieved, we can infer that Mani either did not care or only outwardly pretended to embrace poverty.
With these notes in mind, let's return to the story.
Sapor, the king of the Persians, was deeply grieving the loss of his royal son and was determined to punish the perpetrator of this crime, considering him a murderer and a bold, wicked impostor.
Mani was captured and confined in a small prison, but his disciples, who accompanied him, visited him.
Some of them had previously been sent to Jerusalem or other Christian areas to obtain copies of the Old and New Testaments.
Their intention was to misuse these texts to deceive and mock the followers of Christianity.
The disciples, as Epiphanius notes, promptly acquired these books and returned to their master, now imprisoned, to present them.
During his leisure time in prison, Mani eagerly read the divine Scriptures he received.
Although he pretended to embrace the New Testament, he audaciously corrupted and distorted it in numerous places, sometimes omitting sections that condemned his deceitful and wicked lifestyle, and at other times adding content to support the errors, fables, and delusions of his impious sect.
Cyril of Jerusalem, speaking to the catechumens, highlights many of this impostor's crimes, blasphemies, vile acts, false promises, and disgraces.
However, he does not mention that Mani corrupted the Scriptures while imprisoned.
Instead, he ridicules Mani for escaping from prison.
So, it's important to note: The one who claimed to be the Comforter and defender of truth ended up fleeing.
Unlike Christ, who willingly went to the cross, this person ran away, acting in opposition to him.
Escaping from prison or slipping away would have been impossible for Mani if the guards hadn't given in to greed and laziness, allowing his escape.
This cunning individual knew exactly how to manipulate the head of the public guard using two things: prayers and money.
By cleverly using both without delay, he managed to break free from his chains easily.
Epiphanius describes the event like this: Mani persuaded the jailer with a large sum of money and constant prayers, allowing him to escape and move from Persia into Roman territories.
The Persian king's wrath, which Mani avoided, was harshly felt by the prison guards, as Cyril noted.
When the king discovered their betrayal, or perhaps their greed, he sentenced them to death, the same fate he had planned for Mani.
Thus, the man responsible for the royal child's death due to his arrogance also caused the guards' deaths through his escape.
With all these life-threatening situations that he brought upon himself through his wickedness and the king's intense anger, it seemed necessary for Mani to become more cautious.
He needed to avoid rash or wicked actions in the future.
However, the opposite happened, as credible authors and undeniable records confirm.
After deceitfully regaining his freedom and retreating to Roman territory near Persia and Mesopotamia, Mani appeared to devote himself to solitude.
However, instead of finding peace and tranquility in his seclusion, he was plotting new crimes, driven by the spirit of pride and arrogance that guided him.
However, Photius describes this escape from the prisons of Manetis a bit differently, without detailing the methods and tricks used to outsmart and deceive the guards.
He simply states:
"But when he was a servant skilled in servile craft, and knew that he would soon face punishment for the murder he had committed, having killed the king's son through his wickedness, he fled from the house and caused the death of the prison guards; for since they did not carefully guard that wicked man, they were all executed."
Photius does not clearly mention what servile skills Manes might have used while chained to escape from prison and avoid execution.
But as we noted earlier from Epiphanius, it is very likely that he bribed the prison prefect and the guards with a large sum of money and persistent pleas. After all, it was common for people in lowly positions to be swayed by gold and riches, and servants could often be persuaded to sell their services.
So, could this be evidence of the great poverty to which Manes had fallen, as Beausobre suggests, even before Shapur summoned him to court to help a sick boy with remedies and prayers? The reader must judge for themselves.
Before we conclude this discussion, we should consider something that could completely challenge some previous conclusions if Beausobre's theories hold weight and truth.
Based on the writings of the Orientals, Beausobre is convinced that the Persian king's hatred towards Manichaeism wasn't because of the murder of the royal boy, but because of the Christian religion that Manes claimed to have founded.
The king, a follower of idols and superstitious magic, knew that Manes had sent Thomas, Adda, Hermas, and other false apostles to various parts of the world, who, spreading far and wide, proclaimed the name of Christ, asserting that Manes was a true apostle.
Convinced with certainty, he decided that by capturing Mani, imprisoning him, and sentencing him to death, the spread, extension, and growth of this new sect could gradually lead to the destruction of idolatry and the superstitious fabrications of the magicians.
The reason for this royal decree is clearly reported in the Acts of Archelaus, which states: "He sends his disciples to boldly preach false and feigned errors, etc."
When the King of Persia learned of this, he prepared to subject Mani to appropriate punishments.
It is worth asking Beausobre, to which mission the praised words of the Acts of Archelaus should refer: Is it to the earlier mission of the false apostles of Mani, which they carried out before their teacher was summoned by Shapur and detained in prison; or to the subsequent mission, undertaken even after they knew their teacher was to face a death sentence by royal decree?
Beausobre must admit that these words cannot and should not refer to the first mission. When Thomas, Addas, and Hermas returned from it to report on their past preaching, they found Mani detained in prison. Upon visiting him, they not only recounted their deeds but also brought some New Testament Scriptures to be corrupted.
Beausobre rightly suggests that this preceding narrative of Archelaus does not reek of falsehood or fabrication, guided by the testimony of Saint Epiphanius, who affirms that Mani had possessed Christian books long before the Persian king imprisoned him.
If indeed he could have had some poorly acquired books of the New Testament, and perhaps those which the Valentinians and other heretics had corrupted, it is already known to scholars that Catholic Christians took great pains to preserve the canonical books intact.
Eusebius recounts efforts to prevent pagans from destroying these texts by fire and the leaders of heretics from corrupting and perverting them, as we learn from the book of Constitutions attributed to the apostles, which we will discuss at a more opportune time.
How then could it not have happened that Manes brought with him into prison some books of the New Testament, either whole and genuine, which he corrupted at will, or already corrupted and perverted according to the interpretations of Valentinus, Carpocrates, and Marcion?
And also sent his disciples into parts of the East and Asia to seek out others?
Or perhaps at that time, those fabulous books had not yet appeared under the name of the New Testament, which were titled the Gospels of Peter, Thomas, and Matthias?
Was not the Gospel of Philip, devised by the Gnostics, circulated?
Or finally, another which the Gaianites published under the name of Judas the traitor?
It is certain that Scythianus and Manes drew their heresy from these and other similar poisonous sources, about which Eusebius and the Fathers spoke.
Therefore, these two things can very well coexist without any trace of contradiction.
Namely, that Manes, confined in prison, had some books of the New Testament, which he corrupted and perverted more and more with fabulous comments, to support his sect.
And finally received others from Thomas, Adda, and Herma, returning from a previous mission, which those swindlers had bought from the Orientals with financial support.
Who cannot see that the preceding explanation does not at all contradict the Beausobre system, but rather coheres with it?
Indeed, he himself says in the said chapter.
When it comes to discussing the religion of the Manichaeans, it's often assumed that from a young age, he absorbed a version of Christianity that was corrupted by various errors, primarily from the writings of Scythianus.
He might have later altered it further to fit his own and the magi's philosophies.
Now, let's consider whether Shapur was deeply angered with Mani because of that false apostle mission, which Beausobre, guided by Archelaus's testimony, claims was the main reason for such animosity.
To keep the timeline of past events clear, we can infer that Mani's disciples embarked on two missions.
The first was before Mani tried to heal the royal boy.
Upon their return, they brought some New Testament texts to their teacher, who was imprisoned.
It's likely this was followed by the second mission.
Indeed, if we rely on the testimonies of the Acts of Archelaus, as we have previously done, when Mani was visited in prison by the same disciples, he encouraged them not to fear and began to pray.
According to Beausobre, this could demonstrate both remarkable holiness and the great spirit that a dedicated disciple of Christ should possess.
Thus, he concludes that it wouldn't have been easy for Mani to establish himself as the leader of this sect unless he had significant qualities or mental capabilities.
Therefore, to further show this confidence of spirit, Mani initially pretended to fear neither the threatened punishments nor death itself.
For this reason, to gain authority for himself and elevate his doctrine, he sent his disciples once more to boldly preach the fabricated errors.
No one will doubt that these last words relate to the earlier ones.
So, when Shapur became aware of such audacity, especially considering the death of the royal son, he decided not to keep the murderer alive in prison any longer, ordering him to face the death that had been postponed, preparing to subject him to appropriate punishments.
Before the orders Shapur had given for the execution of this wicked man could be carried out, he managed to escape with the help of a bribed prison guard and other soldiers, as we mentioned earlier.
We felt it was necessary to discuss these matters to refute Beausobre's arguments and to align with the testimonies of ancient writers.
Beausobre, inconsistent and twisting everything, insists these should be disregarded and considered untrustworthy.
Now, let's return to the story.
Chapter Seven
How and by what means Manes attempted to undermine the Catholic religion in Mesopotamia.
Bishop Archelaus of Caschar's efforts to counter these attempts.
Beausobre's conjectures on this subject are noted.
As we delve into the final attempts by Manes to destabilize the Catholic faith, let's pick up from where the last chapter left off.
After escaping prison and living in solitude, Manes learned about an exceptional man, known for his deep piety, named Marcellus or Marcellinus, residing in Caschar, a town in Mesopotamia.
He was known to be a devout Christian and exemplary in all acts of justice.
Manes hoped this man might one day become an ally in his misdeeds, a defender of his crimes, and a champion of his corrupt sect, if he could ensnare him with his deceitful teachings.
He believed that gaining the support of such an individual could help him take control of the entire province.
So, after considering various strategies, Manes decided on one of two approaches that he carefully pondered.
He could either visit Marcellus under the guise of piety or concern for his eternal salvation, gradually introducing harmful doctrines during their conversations.
In this way, once these doctrines were accepted, the purity of the Catholic faith that Marcellus professed would be subtly corrupted.
However, Manes feared this method might be too risky, as a sudden attempt to undermine the Catholic religion could backfire on him.
Thus, he considered the second option, which he believed would be more advantageous for him.
The plan was to first reach out to Marcellus with letters.
If Marcellus responded kindly, or at least wasn't stubbornly opposed, the next step was to exert more effort so that fear or curiosity would drive Marcellus to ask to see all the doctrines of the Manichean sect and its empty fictions.
Finally, as a safer and more effective strategy, Manes settled on this approach.
So, he called upon Turbo, one of the disciples corrupted by Addas with those wicked teachings, and entrusted him with a letter for Marcellus, instructing him to set out immediately and head to Cascharam.
Turbo wasted no time in following the order.
After enduring much effort and discomfort on his swift journey, he arrived at Marcellus's welcoming home as a traveler after five days.
However, he wasn't immediately received by Marcellus.
The hospitality staff at Marcellus's place questioned Turbo about his identity, origin, and purpose.
He explained that he was from Mesopotamia, had come from Persia, and was on a mission for Manichean, the Christian teacher at the Castle of Arabion.
But since they didn't recognize the sender's name, they refused to admit Turbo, even denying him water.
Bishop Archelaus of Caschara described the situation, adding that Turbo endured these and even worse hardships over several days.
Exhausted by labor, hunger, and distress, he might not have survived if he hadn't finally told the hospitality staff that he had letters for Marcellus.
Eventually, he handed the letters to Marcellus, in whose house Bishop Archelaus of Caschara was present at the time.
Upon hearing the blasphemies contained in those letters, Archelaus became enraged at their author, driven by religious zeal, and like a caged lion, he ground his teeth, wishing for Manes to be brought to him.
However, Marcellus remained more composed.
He promised his bishop that he would ensure letters were sent so that Manes would indeed come to Cascharam, as promised, if Marcellus himself requested it.
From the copies of these letters, detailed by both Epiphanius and Archelaus, anyone could easily see the numerous blasphemies against God, the Mother of God, and the saints they contained.
However, we don't see the need to transcribe all of them right now.
Instead, to spare our readers the effort of going through these writings in their entirety, we'll briefly summarize their main points here.
Firstly, the title or heading of these letters, number fifty-one, is sure to provoke great indignation in any devout and religious person.
Or, if someone less informed about matters of faith or not well-versed in Catholic philosophy reads it, they might feel both bewildered and anxious.
The heading reads: Manichaeus, apostle of Jesus Christ, and all the saints and virgins with me, to my dearest son Marcellus, grace, mercy, peace from God the Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ, and may the right hand of light preserve you from this present evil age, and from its ruins, and from the snares of the evil one, amen.
But what could be more audacious, more wicked, or more insulting to God and the saints than what this barbarian Persian devised?
Did he think that the name and duties of an apostle of Jesus Christ, which the most holy Paul took great pride in, could be self-assigned?
After expressing his disdain for these impious acts, he conveyed even more wicked sentiments in the letter.
To win Marcellus's favor, he briefly confessed, praised Marcellus's piety, and admitted his annoyance because Marcellus did not believe according to right reason.
Very arrogantly, he claims he was sent to improve humanity, helping those misled by deceptions and errors.
He found it necessary to write this, he says, first for the salvation of your soul, and then for those who are with you.
The doctrines of salvation he suggested are not hard to predict, as we've already discussed them mainly in chapters three and four.
He argued that two gods must be accepted; each creating things corresponding to its nature, so that good and light were made by a good god, and evil and darkness by a bad god.
Surely, no one could mix good and evil without offending divine goodness or risking the ultimate curse from the omnipotent God.
On this occasion of promoting such wicked doctrine, he boldly misused the Savior's words:
"A bad tree cannot produce good fruit, nor can a good tree produce bad fruit."
When he twisted this testimony to fit his interpretation, he added:
"I am very surprised how they dare to call the Lord the creator and maker of Satan and his evil deeds."
Bailius elaborated on these fanciful ideas about two causes of things, following the corrupt opinion of Manes, not only extensively in his Historical Dictionary, but also, driven by a peculiar spirit, he painstakingly sourced from the testimonies of Ovid, Zoroaster, and other pagan philosophers and poets.
Whether he did this to flaunt his knowledge or to lend weight to the corrupt opinion of Manes, I dare not judge.
However, it's clear that those arguments, based solely on natural principles, seem utterly weak and trivial without divine revelation.
Did not the older Fathers and theologians, relying only on natural principles, against the Marcionites, Manichaeans, and other heretics of this doctrine, prove in every age that there has always been only one cause of all things?
We'll soon explain this ourselves by examining the writings of those who opposed the Manichaeans.
But for now, let's set aside Bailio, the interpreter of his own writing purpose, and delve into other errors of Manes described in the letter to Marcellus.
He then discusses the nature of man, philosophizing as a secondary point, and by distinguishing the inner man from the outer, he argues that these parts are in conflict.
He claims that the good God is the creator of the inner man, but he wrongly asserts that the condition of bodily and fleshly matter originated from the devil.
Following this, he challenges the Catholic mystery of the incarnation of Christ the Lord.
As if the apostles and their fifty-two successors had mistaken this crucial article of our faith, he reasons: If only their vanity had reached the point where they wouldn't claim that the Only Begotten, who descended from the Father's realms, was the son of a woman named Mary, born from blood, flesh, and other impurities of women.
Thus, Manes did not believe that the Only Begotten Son of God the Father could have been clothed in true, bodily flesh, or carried in a woman's womb, or that Mary was truly the Mother of God.
How offensive these ideas were to good men like Marcellus and Archelaus, who were learned in sacred letters and distinguished by their utmost piety towards religion, is left for the reader to judge.
It brought us great sorrow that we couldn't help but notice these and similar blasphemies.
After reading such a letter, Marcellus decided to respond to Manes without delay.
Through these letters, he planned to arrange for that impostor to be summoned to Cascharam, so he could engage in a debate with Bishop Archelaus, making the truths of the Catholic religion more apparent.
Marcellus concluded his letter succinctly, and to maintain the seriousness of the discourse, he used a title of majesty, stating, Marcellus, a well-known man, sends greetings to the Manichaean indicated to him through the letter.
In the body of the letter, he pretends not to understand the meaning of the messages he received through Turbo.
He suggests that perhaps you could explain everything, word by word, as you promised in your letter.
When Marcellus's letter was given to Turbo for delivery, no amount of persuasion could convince him to return to Manes.
Archelaus mentioned remembering the hardships of the journey.
Turbo had asked for someone else to be sent in his place, refusing to return to Manes or have any association with him.
Despite Turbo's insistence on returning to Manes, Marcellus remained firm in his decision.
He called one of his servants, named Calistus, and instructed him to go instead.
After three days, Calistus arrived at the Castle of Arabion, where Manes had sought refuge.
When Manes received the letter, he was partly glad that Marcellus had invited him without delay; however, he also sensed something amiss about Turbo's absence, his disciple.
Nevertheless, Manes boldly set out on the journey.
Accompanied by twelve young men who aspired to cultivate virginity and attend to him dutifully, he headed to Cascharam and reached Marcellus's house.
There, when he inquired about Turbo in vain- for Turbo had renounced his master's superstitious sect and disclosed its secret and mythical errors to the holy bishop.
Marcellus had rewarded him with many gifts and arranged for him to stay at Bishop Archelaus's house-Manes finally greeted Marcellus.
When Marcellus saw him, it was as if a charming actor stood before him, more suited for entertaining than discussing religion and doctrines.
Wouldn't his gait, clothing, appearance, gestures, and the instruments he carried compel any serious person to burst into laughter repeatedly?
Archelaus describes Manes's appearance to Marcellus with these words: He wore footwear with thick soles, commonly known as such, and a cloak of various colors, resembling the sky.
In his hand, he held a strong staff made of ebony wood.
He carried a Babylonian book under his left arm; his legs were covered in different colors, one red and the other a sort of green.
His face resembled that of an old Persian artist and a leader of wars.
When Marcellus first saw this man, he immediately recognized the tricks of a true deceiver.
So, he ignored him and avoided any conversation, quickly sending a message to Archelaus.
When Archelaus saw Manes present, driven by great zeal for religion, he felt compelled to confront him, barely able to contain his deep-seated hatred for the imposter.
He was further incited by the man's appearance, his demeanor, and especially by the secret confession of all impieties made to him by Turbon, and by the curse of these matters, which had deeply wounded the heart of the most holy Shepherd.
But the wise Marcellus, shifting focus away from conflicts, decided both sides should be heard, summoning the leading men of the city to his house.
Among them, he chose four judges of the same religion: Manippus, a grammarian skilled in rhetoric, Aegialeus, a noble chief physician learned in literature, and the brothers Claudius and Cleobulus, both experienced in rhetoric, deciding to hold a frequent assembly.
Whether this assembly should be seen as a synod is not easily defined, especially since Archelaus asserts that such a meeting wasn't held in the Church but in Marcellus's house, and because he explicitly mentioned that four judges of the same religion were chosen in the case of Manes.
But these two points do not trouble those advocating the affirmative side.
For other synods, or councils, were sometimes held in the palaces of emperors and princes, as we read about the one convened in Trullo, Constantinople.
Non-Christian philosophers were also allowed to attend other councils, even general ones, as clearly shown by the acts or history of the First Council of Nicaea.
A supporter of this affirmative opinion in synodical writings agreed.
He mentioned that the errors of Manes were condemned at a certain synod in Mesopotamia by the great Archelaus, bishop of the Cascharans.
This way of speaking might suggest that the author of the praised writings interpreted "assembly" as "council."
But none of the ancients, as noted by Father Natalis Alexander, mentions such a synod.
This suggests it might have been fabricated.
However, how can the silence of ancient writers, like Cyril of Jerusalem and Epiphanius, to which the learned Father Natalis appeals, be an argument for fabrication?
Does Father Natalis give more weight to the silence of two writers than to the testimony of Archelaus, who was both the author of the dispute and the one who organized the assembly?
I acknowledge that no other bishop besides Archelaus attended this assembly.
But what about the presbyters and the rest of the clergy residing in the city of Caschara?
Should we assume they were absent from that gathering?
I cannot agree with that.
Bishop Archelaus, when discussing such an assembly, called it a grand gathering, so much so that the house of Marcellus, which was immense, was filled with those summoned to listen.
Moreover, besides those called to listen, Archelaus testified that selected judges were present, seated in a higher place.
Furthermore, the previous conjectures and the testimony of the synodical writings seem weak when we consider the history of Photius.
He not only described the events led by Archelaus, bishop of Caschara, against Manes differently but also indicated that the assembly and gathering of people could not rightly be called a synod.
It describes how Manes, after fleeing to Mesopotamia, began to lay the groundwork for his rebellion.
"But Bishop Cascharae," it states, "whose name is Archelaus, a holy man well-versed in divine and human matters, gathered a group of Greeks, or Gentile listeners, to ensure that the truth did not appear to have prevailed through favoritism in the judgment of Christians."
After arranging a devout debate against Manes, he so thoroughly shamed and refuted the impious man that Manes fled immediately afterward.
Therefore, according to Photius, if the Greeks and Gentiles were allowed to participate in the debate to avoid the appearance of favoritism in the Christian judgment, how could such a gathering of Greeks or Gentiles be considered a council?
It has always been ensured that laypeople, particularly those not of the Christian faith, should not judge matters of faith and doctrine.
This is how Catholics, from the early days of the Church to today, have vigorously defended against heterodox believers.
Observing this, I clearly understood that Photius's account supports previous assumptions rather than undermining them, along with the testimony of the synodical document.
Those Gentiles must have been present as listeners and witnesses at the assembly to dispel any suspicion that favoritism, instead of truth, was sought in the judgment of Christians, which would greatly harm justice and fairness.
But what prevents this from occurring?
Does not the entire multitude of believers gather for the councils in Jerusalem?
Yet Catholics provide solid evidence, against Blondel and other heretical groups, that only the apostles made judgments.
We should refrain from delving into this discussion now to avoid seeming off-topic or wandering aimlessly, as Beausobre often does.
After considering all of this, I couldn't be convinced to fully believe that the diocesan synod, where the errors of Manes were at least condemned after the debate with Archelaus, was entirely fabricated.
It's more likely that this would be clear from the Acts of that debate, if not for the passage of time and the negligence of translators, which have either corrupted or distorted them.
However, Cyril of Jerusalem, among others, asserts that each of this impostor's false teachings was refuted and condemned by Archelaus, primarily using Scriptures.
He writes, highlighting various Scriptural evidences:
"With these and many other similar arguments, the dragon was cast down, and through such debates, Archelaus overcame Manes, so that he fled again just as he had before from the prisons."
Therefore, having defeated and convicted Manes, he decided to flee, just as he did from the prisons, to avoid not only shame and embarrassment but also the intense anger of the people seeking his death.
He would not have escaped death if Marcellus and Archelaus hadn't used all their strength to restrain the people's violent rage.
Since all elements usually present in councils against those accused of crimes against the Christian faith are present in this case, nothing could prevent us from understanding that the assembly held at Caschara was a council.
Now, let's finally consider Beausobre's critiques.
Beausobre put a lot of effort into subtly dismantling and overturning what has been said so far, and then he devalues the credibility of the Acts so much that he decides they should be completely dismissed as fictional and fanciful.
His sermon begins primarily with a story, which we believe was added to those Acts along with Tillemont.
It describes 12,000 Christians, including men, women, and children, who left the city and gathered in a certain field, fasting and praying day and night, pleading with God, the only invisible being, to send rain upon the earth and seeds at the right times.
It is affirmed that ancient Christians observed this rite there annually.
However, while these people were engaged in such pious and religious activities, Roman soldiers, not far from that field, were seized by a grave suspicion.
They believed the crowd had gathered there to oppose the imperial army and intended to use force against them if the opportunity arose.
Therefore, the Roman soldiers did not hesitate to attack the Christians while they were sleeping.
Without sparing any women or children, they forced some to perish by the sword.
Finally, they took 7,700 of them captive after three days of travel to Cascharam, to sell them into slavery for a sum of money.
Becoming aware of such a great crime, Bishop Archelaus quickly hurried to approach Marcellus, or Marcellinus.
He immediately opened all the treasures of his wealth and offered the pagan soldiers such a portion of gold as would be sufficient to grant that multitude of captives their former freedom.
When the military cohorts could not marvel enough at the greatness and immense charity of his spirit, they immediately changed their plan.
Some of them, leaving behind their military belts and the worship of idols, immediately gave their names to Christ.
Others, having taken only a fourth part of the money necessary for their journey, returned to their former stations.
At first, Beausobre thought this story seemed like pure fiction.
So, by relying on many assumptions and examining everything in detail, he used a critical style to highlight various arguments of improbability.
This approach allowed the reader to judge that the Acts, circulated under the name of Archelaus, along with the entire debate, should be dismissed as completely fictitious.
Secondly, he convinced himself that the aforementioned Tillemont did not contradict these annotated assumptions, as Tillemont mentioned that the previous account had the features of a tale.
Especially since it seemed highly unlikely that twelve thousand Christians could be found in the same city while idolatry was still prevalent.
He also noted Tillemont's amazement at how the Christian population could have persisted for so long, gathered in a large field, fasting and praying, unless perhaps the Easter fasts were recurring at that time.
He concluded the discussion on Tillemont, who faced many difficulties, particularly the idea that such a large number of people, caught unarmed by soldiers while they were asleep, would allow themselves to be distracted without deciding to return to the city from which they departed just as the sun was setting.
He said that Tillemont, amidst so many significant dilemmas, preferred to hesitate rather than assert that the Acts of Archelaus were entirely fabricated.
Instead, Tillemont considered the history in question as an appendix by the interpreter, an attempt to add a patchwork addition to those Acts of Archelaus, but he couldn't detract from their credibility and authority.
Despite all this, Beausobre, rejecting Tillemont's opinion, believes he can argue effectively and intends to engage the reader's mind with the following precautions.
All stories, he says, tend to have some foundation drawn from true histories.
Wanting to examine this more closely in this case, he believed it could be more plausibly drawn from a certain ancient testimony described by Mr.
Hyde in his work on the Religion of the Persians.
After considering and examining the matter himself, he realized it was unstable, like something weak.
He didn't hesitate to add this detail to avoid any suspicion of deceit among readers in the future.
Thus, he reasons as follows.
Let's assume, then, that the praised story has some basis in true history.
First, he suggests that Marcellus, mentioned in the Acts, was indeed a famous and distinguished man from the Roman nation, blessed with great wealth.
He held significant authority in Mesopotamia, managing all affairs in the emperor's name.
Secondly, we should also suppose that the group of people praying and fasting in the field was discovered by soldiers.
They were engaged in religious practices, following the customs and rites of the Persians, without considering Christian devotion and evangelical traditions.
According to church tradition, these are observed during Lenten or Ember Days' fasts.
The author, discussing the religion of the ancient Persians, claims that the Persians would gather in the fields on specific days of the year.
They would ask for blessings from an invisible God for the fertility of their land and crops, as we will see shortly.
Considering the former supposition, Beausobre presents this proposition as entirely certain:
that Marcellus, mistakenly named due to scribes' carelessness, truly managed all the affairs of the province of Mesopotamia.
He governed the people as a true ruler under Aurelian's reign, around the year 273 AD, after defeating Zenobia and bringing the Palmyrenes under Roman rule.
Zosimus recounts that the administration of those provinces was given to a certain Marcellinus.
Therefore, it could easily have been read as Marcellus instead of Marcellinus.
It's well known that the ancients frequently made similar errors.
As a result of the tests and dangers faced, it is now evident that Marcellinus, a leader of the Roman people, was a man of the utmost integrity and steadfastness, qualities that were barely matched by others.
Many believed they were gaining glory and honor, driven by the ambition for higher status, authority, and power.
In doing so, they shamelessly ignored the principles of justice and equity, taking advantage of others and appropriating their possessions.
The people of Palmyra, suffering the devastation of their cities and the disgrace and captivity of Queen Zenobia, struggled greatly to free themselves from Emperor Aurelian's rule.
Marcellinus was offered the opportunity to break away from his loyalty to the emperor and join them in an alliance to claim the entire kingdoms of Mesopotamia and the East for himself.
However, Marcellinus firmly resisted their temptations and flattery, refusing the supreme rule for himself.
Instead, he worked diligently to ensure that, with all thoughts of rebellion set aside, they would remain loyal to the Roman Empire that had conquered them.
He reported the situation to Aurelian, concerned that the growing unrest could lead to an uprising breaking the bonds of servitude.
Therefore, as Beausobre concludes, it might have been that Marcellinus favored Christians and their faith.
He then discusses another assumption mentioned by Beausobre, noting that it is too uncertain.
Who could imagine that Roman soldiers, under disciplined command, would be so ruthless as to want to destroy a defenseless group of women and children who were loyal to the state?
It is equally unlikely that they would capture free and innocent people.
If they had been Persian, soldiers might have presumed them to be enemies, gathering to invade Roman-controlled lands.
So, when the innocence of those captives was later proven, the highest official of that province was supposed to order their return to freedom without any payment.
Regarding the third supposition, which involves the fifty-seven Persian supplications celebrated with superstitious worship, Mr.
Hyde was believed by Beausobre to have intended to indicate this.
When he described certain ceremonies of the magi that had some similarities to our rites of baptism and Eucharist, he was led by a testimony wrongly attributed to Mr.
Chrysostom.
He included this testimony in his notes as follows:
"In their sacred rites, the Mithraics also had washings, as if of regeneration, where the priest baptizes certain believers and promises the expiation of sins through the washing, thus initiating them into Mithras.
This is mentioned by Justin Martyr and Chrysostom. Every year, after the threshing harvest, they would ascend a mountain, called the Mountain of Victory in their language, which had a cave in the rock, delightful with springs and chosen trees. They would enter it, wash, and pray in silence to God for three days."
Beausobre asserts that while this account is not poorly constructed, the foundation on which it stands is shaky and crumbling, as neither Justin Martyr nor Chrysostom affirmed this.
On the contrary, he says, the praised testimony is actually from the author of the "Imperfect Work on Matthew," which is filled with fanciful tales. It doesn't mention the magi's supplications but rather discusses a tradition generally accepted by Christians of the Eastern communion, which he plans to explain more clearly when he talks about the apocryphal writings of the Manicheans.
Gradually, he also shifted his focus to Mr.
Hyde, advising readers to question the testimonies of the ancients, even those celebrated by scholars, and to examine them carefully.
Even though these men didn't intend to deceive or mislead in their writings, they still made errors in praising and annotating similar passages.
I needed to detail these issues a bit more thoroughly, to determine whether Beausobre was speaking nonsense or, as he claimed, was seeking the truth without bias.
Firstly, concerning Justin, I have to say that Beausobre either skimmed through his works carelessly or at least read them with tired eyes.
The holy martyr talked mainly in three places about the rites, mysteries, and ceremonies of the Persians, recounting what Mr.
Hyde noted from Chrysostom about their ancient religion.
His first testimony appears in the apology for Christians, commonly referred to as the second, where, while discussing the sacrament of the Eucharist, he supports its truth with the Gospel words of Christ, adding that the same thing is done in the mysteries and initiations of Mithras as an imitation by evil demons.
The Persians, thus, guided by demons, attempted to mimic the sacred Christian table in their rituals and solemn initiations.
However, Justin notes a distinction: bread and a cup of water are used in the sacrifices or divine rites of the one being initiated, and with certain words added, you either know or can recognize them.
This was also a practice of the Manichaeans, which we will more suitably examine in its proper context from Leo the Great, specifically in Chapter 9 of the second book of this history.
The Persians celebrated their mysterious and abominable rituals in caves and caverns, particularly during the rites of Mithras.
Justin, in his dialogue with Trypho, explains: When those who pass on the rites of Mithras say he was born from a rock, they refer to a cave or cavern as the place where believers are initiated.
When discussing the birth of Christ in Bethlehem, he describes how Joseph, having nowhere else to stay, went to a cave near the village.
It was there that Mary gave birth to Christ, placing him in a manger, where the wise men from Arabia found him.
After some intervening words, he adds: In such words, those who established the mysteries of Mithras in a place called a cave or cavern, initiate their own, performing their secrets under the devil's influence.
Thus, the Persians and magi carried out these rites and ceremonies in caves and caverns, aiming to serve the devil and misusing the Scriptures of the New and Old Testaments, pretending to align with the divine institutions and mysteries of Christians.
Therefore, the foundation of the previous narrative is solid.
It should stand even firmer, as writers after Justin, perhaps drawing from his authority, adopted the rites, ceremonies, and supplications of the Persians.
But can anyone argue that Chrysostom made no mention of these Persian rites?
So, what then?
Could Chrysostom's silence undermine the testimonies of Justin Martyr?
After all, Justin flourished when the religion of the Persians and magi dominated Mesopotamia and other provinces, and the name of Christ had barely been announced there.
During Chrysostom's time, even though Christianity had spread in various regions and the dismantling of magic and idolatry had begun, these practices hadn't been completely eradicated everywhere.
This was because of the fierce nature of those nations who, following their ancestral customs, continued to honor idols.
Chrysostom himself confirms this in his eleventh Homily to the people of Antioch.
Beausobre shouldn't have criticized Dr.
Hyde for praising the "Opus Imperfectum in Matthew" as if it were Chrysostom's work. Most of the ancients attributed it to Chrysostom, and the old editors included it in the second volume of his works, as such homilies were commonly credited to him in manuscript form. Later scholars, after more diligent study, found traces of Arian doctrine, along with various interpolations, corruptions, and additions. They concluded with better insight that these homilies were actually composed by a Latin writer and filled with errors and additions by someone with compromised faith.
None of them, however, dared to claim that these works contained pure and simple fables, as Beausobre admitted. Now, Beausobre turns to the letter of Manes, which he arranged to have sent to Marcellus through Turbo, translating it entirely into French. He shamelessly praised this work as if it had been written in the style of the apostles, filled with phrases and expressions of Apostle Paul. These two aspects do not fit a new convert who had been reading the sacred Scriptures for just a few months, or someone with the fierce, barbarous, and impious character that ancient writers attributed to Manes.
Saint Paul was then revered by the Manichaeans, who were misled into believing they could use his writings to support the existence of two principles and the inherent corruption of humanity.
This was especially important because Paul, among his fellow apostles, had worked the hardest to liberate the Christian Church from the constraints of Mosaic law.
Consequently, Beausobre gathered these and many other related issues in his exposition of the Manichaean letter and the account of the debate with the heretic and Archelaus, the bishop of Caschar.
Some of these matters are too embarrassing to discuss, so we have chosen to remain silent about them.
However, since the others are more related to Manichaean philosophy, morals, worship, and discipline, we have decided to keep them in order, trying to explain or dismiss each one as appropriate.
Chapter Eight
After leaving Caschara, Manes sought refuge in Diodorid, a district within the same city.
There, he engaged in new debates about religious doctrines with Diodorus, a priest.
Archelaus was informed and initially sent letters to Diodorus, which Beausobre, in his discussions, tries to undermine the discipline of the church.
When Archelaus arrived, Manes attempted to flee, but it was in vain.
When Manes thought he had evaded the hatred of the Persians and overcome the judgment at Caschara, which we mentioned earlier, and had used much deceit and trickery each time, he was still forced to seek refuge for his safety and protection.
He withdrew to a hidden part or insignificant village in the Caschara diocese.
There, with all witnesses to his previous wickedness and crimes removed, he decided to engage in a debate about religious doctrines with a certain priest, the leader of that parish.
We cannot be certain whether he was alone or with those virginal disciples who outwardly pretended to be chaste, whom he had brought with him from the Castle of Arabion to Caschara.
From the praised Acts, we know he immediately went to a certain Diodorus, called Tryphon by Epiphanius, who was in charge of a Christian parish, to start disputes with him.
Cyril calls this parish a very lowly place.
Photius supports this, writing: From there, he fled to a certain insignificant village, and there again sought to nurture and reveal his impiety.
However, he makes no mention at all of Diodorus or Tryphon, the priest whom Manes attempted to challenge and provoke with new disputes.
Although this priest stood out among others there for his piety, pure religion, and other virtues, he was not well-versed in sacred writings and could have easily been deceived by Manes, who flattered himself that he would bring him over to his own views.
However, this opinion deceived the author of heresies.
When the priest barely heard the blasphemies from the creator of the new teachings, he sought the advice and help of Bishop Archelaus.
Archelaus quickly sent a lengthy letter to his priest.
Beausobre deemed this letter unworthy of his history or not suitable for his studies, so he neither translated it into French nor included it in his work.
In the title of this letter, Beausobre points out a flaw in a seemingly simple matter.
He identified two things that seemed suspect, which clearly indicate, unless it's a misunderstanding, that the letter was not written during Archelaus' time.
One issue was that a single church was established there without a bishop, and was led only by a priest.
Therefore, he argues, it's hard to believe that in the third century of the Church, any churches were founded in cities, suburbs, or villages without bishops.
At that time, the Church had not grown enough in the number of believers, and bishops only had deacons serving under them.
There were no bishops in name only, performing all sacred duties themselves.
It was only after a long period that rural bishops or chorepiscopi lost all superior authority and were demoted to the rank of priests.
Therefore, Diodorides, a village or suburb, would have had a bishop at that time, as D.
Assemanus suggests in the Bibliotheca Orientali.
After discussing this first significant issue, Beausobre quickly addresses the second, which further casts doubt on Archelaus' letter.
He argues that even if bishops in villages and towns had only simple priests leading the congregations, it's clear that these priests would not be referred to as 'sons' by their bishops, but rather as 'brothers,' especially in their writings.
He insists that the term 'sons' is appropriate only for deacons, as they are the true ministers of bishops in carrying out sacred duties.
Why does he convince himself that there are no examples from the first three centuries where bishops, in their letters to elders, refer to them as "sons"?
This is the position of Beausobre.
Is he trying to make readers believe in stories that, despite being skillfully composed and well-written, hold no credibility or authority?
Such beliefs are only among those who are foolish and ignorant, completely unaware of the church hierarchy and its ancient order and management.
It doesn't help him to reference the church history of the first three centuries without citing any authors.
He should have first highlighted the difference between a specific assembly of believers under one legitimate pastor, specifically a bishop, and the actual place where the faithful gathered for their meetings.
Especially on Sundays, the Lord's days, when divine mysteries were celebrated under one leader and matters of the Christian faith were discussed.
Who doesn't know that the term "Church" was used for both the assembly and the place?
Therefore, when it is stated that the Church, in the former sense, couldn't exist without a bishop, and each had its own presiding bishop, whom the ancients, like Justin and Tertullian, called the high priest, it should be understood according to the old and new hierarchy of the Church, which should be clear to everyone.
In the early days of the Church, it often spanned vast areas, covering many cities, suburbs, villages, castles, and rural regions.
Because of this, a single location for religious ceremonies and one priest couldn't meet the needs of all the faithful.
Thus, within the same diocese, which they referred to as the Church, multiple sacred gatherings were necessary, especially on Sundays.
Priests were responsible for leading these gatherings, teaching the people, and conducting the holy assembly.
To assure those who doubt the faith, it's well-documented by Tertullian and Justin Martyr that this was the ecclesiastical practice in the second century.
In his apology for Christians presented to the Roman Emperor Antoninus Pius, Tertullian openly mentioned these sacred gatherings celebrated in towns and rural areas by Christians on Sundays.
He detailed everything, from the leaders' actions to the enthusiastic responses of the people, and what the church readers recited from the writings of the apostles and prophets.
After the president's prayer, which instructed and inspired the people to emulate such virtues, the entire assembly joined in prayer.
Consecrated bread and wine mixed with water were then distributed to everyone present.
They also made sure to send these to those who were absent through deacons.
Those unable to attend the sacred gathering on Sunday due to illness, captivity, imprisonment, or any other reason were not excluded from participating in these sacred offerings.
Additionally, travelers who arrived were offered hospitality.
Indeed, it was the leaders' duty to assist them, as the leader also cared for all those in need.
So, taking into account Justin's words, which we'll discuss at the end, it's important to counter Beausobre's claims by reasoning as follows:
By the second century, despite ongoing persecutions from both Jews and pagans, the Christian community had grown significantly.
As Eusebius notes, not only in major cities but also in towns and rural areas, believers would gather together on the Lord's Day.
During these gatherings, church leaders or presidents would lead the religious services.
Therefore, if each church had only one bishop in charge, as we know from the canonical Epistle of John and the succession of bishops described by Hegesippus and Tertullian, it would have been impossible for him to travel from place to place within the diocese on the same day.
He couldn't visit the entire diocese and conduct all the gatherings, given the expected attendance and the number of people involved, which is the issue at hand.
Moreover, it's unreasonable to think that the entire Christian population of each diocese could gather at the bishop's seat from every corner of the diocese on the recurring Lord's Day, putting aside all other concerns.
First of all, Justin mentions that sacred gatherings were held in towns and rural areas.
Then, the distance between places would have made it difficult for women, children, and the elderly to undertake long journeys.
Lastly, they could have easily been captured by imperial officials if they had to gather in large groups at set times in a specific place before their sole bishop.
Bishops were always targets for capture and execution by the emperor's officials, as evidenced by the martyrdoms of Ignatius, Polycarp, Peter, and Dionysius, as well as the noble end of the Roman bishops who held the seat of Peter up to the time of Justin.
In gatherings held in towns and the countryside on Sundays, someone would preside and conduct the sacred rites.
This challenges Beausobre's first claim:
that in the first three centuries, the terms bishops and presbyters referred to the same person, authority, and power.
After Aerius, Blondel, Salmasius, and others from the Puritan school repeated this idea,
they twisted the meaning of the Acts and Paul's words to argue incorrectly that the dignity and power of presbyters and bishops were the same not only during the apostles' times but also in later centuries.
This is not something we can refute at this moment.
Among the distinguished men who debated this distinction, the very learned Petavius has addressed it thoroughly.
To further challenge Beausobre, we consider it better to refer to John the presbyter, mentioned by Irenaeus in Eusebius, or to Irenaeus himself, who served only as a presbyter while Pothinus was the bishop of Lyon;
or to Achillas, the Alexandrian presbyter during the time Theonas and Peter governed that Church.
And Origen, who was ordained a presbyter by the bishops of Palestine at Caesarea against Demetrius's will.
Tertullian also supports the view that by the end of the second century and the beginning of the third, presbyters had less authority and jurisdiction in divine matters than their bishops.
He compared and opposed the ministries of presbyters to the rights of bishops, saying:
The high priest, who is the bishop, has the right to administer baptism;
then the presbyters and deacons, but only with the bishop's authority, for the honor of the Church, which, when preserved, keeps peace intact.
Therefore, Tertullian distinguished three ecclesiastical orders, assigning each their own rights.
He wouldn't have stated that presbyters and deacons couldn't baptize without a bishop's authority if bishops and presbyters shared the same honor and power.
This aligns with the Carthaginian laws and the ancient laws of the Catholic Church, as recorded in the Constitutions attributed to the apostles.
Particularly, it ensures that presbyters and deacons cannot act without the bishop's decision, just as they shouldn't leave their assigned parishes without their bishop's knowledge.
So, when considering the ancient Church's discipline and order, bishops had supreme rights that differed from those of presbyters, who relied entirely on bishops to carry out their duties.
I can't understand how Beausobre could claim that Diodorus or Tryphon, who managed a rural or suburban parish in the third century, wouldn't or couldn't withdraw from the challenge Manes boldly presented with Bishop Archelaus present.
Would it have been allowed for him to dispute with a heretical and cunning person in front of his bishop, whose delegate he was acting as a leader or president?
Who could have done this without causing offense?
Even with the bishop present, he shouldn't have baptized or performed other sacred duties.
Tertullian, whom we recently praised, warns presbyters, deacons, and others in the clerical order not to assume the episcopal office to avoid rivalry, the mother of schisms.
Furthermore, the role of teaching, debating, and defining matters of faith, whether in councils or other gatherings, clearly belongs to bishops by virtue of their ordination.
Why did certain rural suburban priests in the fourth and fifth centuries of the Church attempt to extend the rights of their ordination and unlawfully assume episcopal duties with reckless boldness?
They were deprived and prohibited from sacred ministry by the apostolic see and all the bishops of the world, as Pope Damasus declared in his letter.
He further affirmed that the establishment of these individuals was extremely improper and impious.
Since they, striving for the highest priesthood in episcopal seats, lacked all authority, their arrogant and unnecessary elevation was aimed at abolishing sacred canons and disrupting the entire ecclesiastical hierarchy.
Saint Leo the Great, following the rules of his predecessors and councils, declared everything they did in the ministry of the aforementioned highest priesthood to be empty and vain.
Beausobre, from his perspective, argues that in the first three centuries, priests and bishops had the same authority and power, and that bishops were not superior to priests.
He claims those priests, in managing the parishes entrusted to them and in carrying out other ministries among the faithful, should not have depended on the approval and authority of bishops.
When the reader considers what has been said so far, I do not fear that they might judge and wish to consider weaker the objections Beausobre raised last, intending to prove that the letter of Archelaus to Diodorus, which is currently being discussed, is spurious.
Since, if in the first three centuries bishops did not customarily call their fellow priests, whether suburban, by the name of sons, but instead, dealing more honorably with them, called them brothers in letters, then the divine authority of the letters of Peter and Paul would already be undermined and would fall away, since we find these terms and characters in them.
Indeed, the Apostle Peter calls Mark the bishop his son, writing in his first letter: "The church that is in Babylon, chosen together with you, greets you, and so does Mark, my son."
The way Saint Paul consistently spoke is evident in his letters to Timothy:
"To Timothy, my beloved child in faith."
He addressed him further, saying:
"I entrust this command to you, Timothy, my child."
And he starts another letter with:
"Paul, an apostle, etc., to Timothy, my dearest child."
Finally, without listing many other examples, when he directed Titus to appoint elders in every city of Crete, as he had done himself,
he referred to Titus as a son, as seen in these words:
"To Titus, my true child according to the common faith."
What does this imply?
According to Beausobre's theory, we could conclude one of two things:
either the esteemed letters of apostles Peter and Paul show signs of being inauthentic, which is unprecedented, or those divine authors exercised some freedom in their personal correspondence, different from the formalities expected between bishops and priests.
The latter cannot be claimed without boldness.
Those apostles, guided by the divine Spirit, chose expressions suitable for their audience and the topics they addressed.
Thus, those they called sons in one context, they called brothers in another, as when Paul, while imprisoned, wrote to Philemon and referred to Timothy as a brother, a title he used for those reborn in Christ through baptism.
However, when considering the instruction of those he brought to Christ through preaching or initiated through the sacrament of order, he rightly referred to them as sons. This is clear in his letters concerning Timothy, Titus, Onesimus, and others.
Since Beausobre's arguments are rather fanciful and fictional, there's no reason to dismiss the letter from Archelaus to his presbyter Diodorus or Tryphon as fabricated.
Now, setting aside Beausobre's trivialities for a moment, let's return to the order of our history.
Based on Epiphanius's testimony, we believe, or rather we're certain, that Archelaus didn't immediately set out for the village of Diodorus in his diocese, nor did he immediately inquire about the wolf fleeing from Caschara.
The situation is clearer than what Cyril describes, saying: Archelaus was unaware that Manes had taken refuge in that village.
He met with the presbyter in charge of the parish once and again, initiating a debate on religious doctrines.
Although the presbyter, whom Epiphanius calls Tryphon, lacked eloquence and rhetorical skill, he nonetheless overcame Manes.
In this, the divine promise made to the apostles was fulfilled: "Do not worry about how or what you should speak. For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father speaking through you."
Manes, deeply troubled by this, wanted to challenge Tryphon or Diodorus again with new debates, arguing that the two Testaments of the sacred Scriptures do not agree with each other and trying to prove their greatest contradiction from the gospel witnesses.
This cunning and sacrilegious man's pure fiction aimed primarily at discrediting the authority of the Old Testament, suggesting that it originated from some evil and eternal principle.
But the presbyter Diodorus, wishing to curb the audacity of this fraudster, decided to inform his bishop Archelaus of the whole matter in writing.
We learn what those letters contained from both Epiphanius and Archelaus.
Epiphanius claims that Diodorus used these precise words, which he copied:
A certain man came here, trying to destroy the sheepfold like a vicious wolf.
But I ask you to write to me about how I should deal with him and what methods to use to counter his harmful teachings.
If you could come yourself, you would relieve the flock of Christ from all worry.
However, Archelaus, responding to Diodorus's requests and letters, reveals in his letter that these were not the only things pointed out by his presbyter.
Among other things, he mainly focuses on demonstrating the wonderful harmony and agreement of both the Old and New Testaments.
He supports this with various analogies taken from the use, condition, and nature of things.
One example includes a piece of clothing, which appears woven under both covering and texture.
He adds that just as we see the color purple in the garment, the glory of Jesus in the New Testament is woven into the fabric of the Old.
Another example comes from a mirror.
We do not usually discard it when it shows us the true image of things.
He also mentions children led to teachers by a tutor, who should not disrespect the tutor once they mature, even if they no longer need his help.
Finally, he proves that both Testaments should be kept and respected by the example of a child who, after being nourished by milk and moving on to stronger food, cannot reject and despise the nurse's breast without great injustice; instead, he respects and honors it, acknowledging his debt of gratitude.
These and other similar things, in a very lengthy letter which Epiphanius calls a book, Archelaus suggested to his presbyter Diodorus, always showing, as we have said, the wonderful and sincere harmony and supreme concord of both Testaments.
We don't believe that Archelaus's sole purpose was to emphasize the harmony between the Testaments.
Instead, the holy bishop aimed to reveal something deeper with the reasons he presented.
Specifically, he wanted to show that human nature, already threatened by significant vices and shrouded in ignorance, wasn't immediately ready to grasp the truth clearly.
It shouldn't have been instantly freed from the bonds of eternal death.
Humans, who were wandering like wild beasts and never contemplating divine matters, needed to be guided through various stages of heavenly and eternal wisdom.
Initially, this guidance came through the figures and shadows of natural things, which they would draw from the Mosaic law, like milk.
Ultimately, it came through grace and the clear contemplation of divine matters, which the New Testament offered as solid food, provided by the Son of the eternal Father.
With these strong reasons, had Diodorus chosen to follow Archelaus's advice, he could have easily confounded and defeated Manes.
The core teachings of the Catholic faith and the authority of the divine Old Testament, which were primarily questioned, would have been affirmed.
Therefore, Diodorus, the presbyter, relying on Archelaus's writings, even while waiting for his bishop's arrival, was compelled to engage again in debate with the boldness of Manes.
Manes, appearing early in the morning in the village center, initiated his debate with Diodorus once more.
He was the first to challenge Diodorus with his doctrines.
But Diodorus responded to all the questions and, with wisdom granted by God, gently challenged his impostor.
As Epiphanius notes, when Archelaus began to hesitate slightly, he unexpectedly appeared, like a fierce head of the household devoted to his own, boldly confronting the plunderer.
So, what did Manes do then?
Like a cunning trickster with feigned charm, he turned to Archelaus, asking to debate only with the presbyter.
He claimed it was especially unbecoming for a bishop to argue with someone beneath him about religious matters.
However, the people present, having uncovered the wickedness of Manes, attacked him so vigorously that they even sought to stone him.
He wouldn't have escaped this danger if he hadn't fled back to the Fortress of Arabion for the third time, where he had first taken refuge.
Beausobre presented this new debate between Archelaus and Manes differently in his History.
Determined to reach his intended conclusion, he gathered arguments from all sides, not only to reject those Acts as forgeries but also to denounce them as sources of many heresies.
We have discovered that this cunning and malicious man dared to launch various accusations and pretenses, completely injurious to Bishop Archelaus and the entire assembly of Catholics.
Our love for the truth does not allow us to ignore these matters, so the supporters of false criticism may not seem wise.
Our task will be to defend against all slander and deceitful accusations and to uphold the true tradition of the Catholic and Apostolic Church concerning the chief doctrines of our faith, which have been corrupted, undermined, and debased in the current third century.
We shall vigorously correct this man of great audacity, who continually engages in nonsense and fabrications.
Chapter Nine
Archelaus' Debate with Manes at Diodorides is Defended Against Critical Notes and Beausobrean Slanders.
The Bad Faith of the Non-Catholic Writer in Reviewing Archelaus' Testimonies is Explained.
Finally, it is Rightly Demonstrated that Archelaus Should be Considered Both Catholic and Holy in the Church, Based on Both the Writings Circulating and His Zeal for the True Religion of Christ.
I believed I had fulfilled my duties when I briefly reviewed in the previous chapter the matters related to the debates between Manes and Archelaus.
My intention was not to create theological discussions but to compile a concise history of the Manichaeans from authentic documents and authors, similar to how others have written about the Pelagians, Donatists, Arians, Eutychians, and other heretics who sought to undermine the Catholic faith.
However, while reading Beausobre's work, I found numerous lies and slanders shrouded in obscurity, prompting me to shed light on these stories and arguments, like a rising sun dispelling darkness.
If I had merely pointed out the bad faith of this heretical writer, contemporary scholars, who often only scratch the surface, might wrongly believe Beausobre's arguments are too strong for us to refute if we only summarized or ignored them.
To begin, we may overlook some criticisms from this Dutch writer, particularly those where he tries to depict Bishop Archelaus as arrogantly boasting about his past victory and, before a defeated opponent, wishing to stand again at the village of Diodorides, forcing Diodorus, or Tryphon, a priest, to halt the initiated contest, allowing him to start a new debate with Manes on matters of faith.
I won't hide the fact that the bishop described the interest in Christian religious matters as pride, arrogance, and madness, expressing his displeasure with Manes' way of acting and speaking.
When the heretic asked Archelaus to allow him to conclude the debate he had started with the priest, he was cautious about discussing religious doctrines with the bishop, who had more authority and dignity than him.
"It was a serious absurdity," he said, "to fabricate such words in the mouth of a heretic." This was someone who had not only previously debated new doctrines publicly with Archelaus but also arrogantly and wickedly dared to call himself a disciple of Christ, an apostle of Jesus, and the Paraclete promised by the Son of God.
When Gothofredus Arnoldi recognized this significant difficulty and convinced himself that the Acts of Archelaus were authentic, he believed that those courteous words were slyly and ironically spoken by Manes, to avoid the embarrassment he had experienced in Cascharam, especially since he hoped it would be easier to overcome a priest than a bishop.
So, I don't see what absurdity would arise from such a natural explanation, considering that the efforts of heretical people are mainly focused on gaining favor, authority, and reputation among the uneducated and ignorant masses.
Manes hoped to achieve all these if he could overcome the parish priest in debates. Wouldn't he have drawn all the faithful who came there from Diodoride and nearby places to his view, if they hadn't suddenly been supported by divine help and enlightened by the light of truth?
Therefore, it shouldn't seem absurd to Beausobre that Manes, to avoid a new risk of shame and disgrace, which he certainly foresaw was imminent due to his previous experience in Cascharam, again refrained from contending with Archelaus over matters of faith.
It's often a wise move for those who've been defeated by their rivals to avoid fighting the same opponents again, especially when those opponents have grown stronger in both knowledge and fortune.
They steer clear of conflicts they know will end badly for them.
So, when Manes found himself at the village of Diodorides, he should have realized that without better knowledge, he shouldn't enter a new debate with Archelaus.
This was particularly true since Archelaus was well-versed in the sacred texts of both the Old and New Testaments.
Therefore, we shouldn't assume that the Acts of Archelaus are false just because Manes, having lost the debate publicly, refused to engage in another, more challenging encounter.
I also can't ignore the harsh criticism Beausobre directs at both Archelaus and the Church's traditions and the teachings of the ancient Church Fathers when he reviews this last debate between Manes and Archelaus.
He unfairly accuses the wise bishop of many heresies, which he tries to extract from his words and opinions.
To avoid seeming futile, our aim was to remove this stigma as much as possible and defend the ecclesiastical tradition by addressing each of Beausobre's wrongful objections.
Thus, he presents three main arguments of the Manichaean debate, each met with responses from Archelaus.
The first argument concerns the mystery of the incarnation, which Manes sought to challenge by claiming that Christ, the Son of God, was not truly a man born of a woman.
Instead, he argued that Christ merely appeared as such by divine arrangement, without possessing a genuine human nature.
He misinterpreted the words of the Apostle Paul to the Philippians, which state that Christ was made in the likeness of men.
To strengthen his misguided teachings, he referred to the words of Luke, which mention that the Holy Spirit descended on Christ at the Jordan in a bodily form like a dove.
Thus, as Manes reasoned according to Beausobre, the Holy Spirit wasn't actually a real dove but only appeared as one.
Similarly, the Son of God didn't truly take on human nature but merely appeared in human form.
This is the first simplistic argument of Manes, says Beausobre, which Bishop Archelaus refuted with strong reasoning.
However, he also presented ideas that were equally heretical.
He felt readers should be warned that faith shouldn't be based on antiquity or be subject to the authority of tradition and the early Church Fathers, whom non-Catholics claim were undermined when Constantine took control of the empire.
But it must be noted that true faith ended even earlier if we assume that the virtues and privileges of that age belonged to the bishops.
So far, Beausobre.
But I wonder why, leaving aside the usual stories, he becomes so vehement, attacking the ancient Church as if he wanted to lash out at its holy bishops like a rabid dog.
He argues against accepting tradition and placing faith in the early Church Fathers.
But before we seem to overstep, let Beausobre explain how the Catholic doctrine of the incarnation, which was central to the debate with both Manes and Archelaus, has been proven if Archelaus didn't follow the authority of his predecessor bishops, but chose to interpret the testimonies of Paul and Luke, which Manes distorted, according to his own understanding?
If Archelaus had turned away from the teachings and traditions of his predecessors and chosen to interpret the mentioned passages of Scripture differently, ignoring the consensus of other churches, he would have introduced even more misguided ideas with new commentaries.
Both, while discussing the same mystery, would have ended up in different heresies.
But Beausobre claims that Archelaus rightly, solidly, and wisely debated and understood the true nature of Christ's flesh, His baptism, death, burial, and resurrection.
Therefore, he did not indulge in new and strange doctrines but followed the teachings of the sacred leaders of the churches who preceded him.
So, what is tradition?
What is that divine rule of the Church from which the doctrines of true faith are drawn?
What is the consensus and doctrine of the Holy Fathers?
It is everything that Beausobre currently criticizes and seeks to overturn with fanciful commentaries to favor his own interests rather than the truth.
Yet, Beausobre boldly argues that Archelaus adhered to novelties while defending those Catholic doctrines about the true flesh of Christ, His true suffering, and death.
According to him, the bishop affirmed that Jesus was truly nailed to the cross and that after He rose from the dead, He was taken up to the place where Christ, the Son of God, reigns.
He insists that Archelaus excellently explained the Lord's descent to the underworld, suggesting that this place is the same as the tomb, from which Jesus, having come back to life, ascended to heaven.
He adds that this interpretation is reasonable and just, although he argues it is accompanied by various terrible heresies.
He calls this praised interpretation reasonable and just only because he believes it aligns with Theodore Beza, Calvin, and himself, who deny that Christ's soul descended to the underworld.
The Fathers of both Churches have spoken extensively on this well-known and common question, criticizing those who, following the Hebrew readings, believed the underworld should be understood more strictly as the tomb.
We don't think it's appropriate to prolong this discussion any further at this time.
Learned and meticulous individuals have already published various writings that refute the false opinions of Theodore Beza, Calvin, and Erasmus, proving that the phrase "descended to the underworld" should not be removed from the Creed.
Even before these scholars accomplished this, Leo the Great condemned the errors of the Manicheans and Priscillianists, defending the truth we are discussing using many passages of Scripture. He was surprised that Bishop Turribius of the Asturian Church consulted the apostolic seat on this article of the Christian religion:
"I am surprised that any Catholic would struggle with the idea that, when Christ descended to the underworld, His flesh rested in the tomb; just as it truly died and was buried, so it was truly raised on the third day."
He then refers to the testimonies of Scripture, which we have noted, and immediately adds:
"With these words, it is clear that the flesh of the Lord was truly buried and rested and did not undergo corruption, because it was quickly brought back to life by the return of the soul and resurrected. Not believing this is quite impious and undoubtedly relates to the doctrine of Manichaeism and Priscillianism. Those who, with sacrilegious intent, pretend to confess Christ, thus undermine the truth of incarnation, death, and resurrection."
But Beausobre, adhering to Manichaean and Priscillian doctrine on this issue we are discussing, must be criticized for his objections against the faith of Bishop Archelaus. First of all, he makes him suspect of faithlessness because he refers to the divine nature of Jesus by the name of Christ, a term that can only designate a person who has attained grace, gifts, perfections, and dignity. He adds that such a way of speaking was already familiar to heretics.
Although Petavius argued that it was used by Catholics like Justin Martyr, Dionysius of Alexandria, Novatian, or the author of the book on the Trinity, and Ambrose, all of whom, except for Ambrose, are increasingly regarded as suspect of Arian doctrine.
Because of this way of speaking, he thought Archelaus should be excused.
However, because his arguments both precede and follow the Nestorian doctrine, stating that Jesus was transferred after the resurrection to the place where Christ, the Son of God, reigns, Petavius finds him inexcusable.
The praised words clearly suggest that Jesus and the Son of God are two separate persons, one ascending to the other, as the following words more clearly show.
It is indeed the son born of Mary, who wished to endure this entire struggle, Jesus.
This is the Christ of God, who descended upon him who is from Mary.
To reinforce the preceding words and to bolster his own bad faith in writing, Beausobre reasons this way.
He argues that the one who descended on the baptized Jesus could not be the person of Jesus himself.
And because the one who descended on Jesus is Christ, the Son of God, Jesus could not have been the Son of God until after He descended on him; that is, after Jesus was endowed with baptism.
He claims that these were the heresies of Cerinthus and Carpocrates, who troubled the Church from the beginning, and proves this by referring to Dionysius Petavius.
Furthermore, he asserts that the Ebionites preached similar things about Jesus, and that the Elcesaites, Orphites, and Serpentinians, according to Theodoret, falsely claimed that Jesus was one person and Christ, who descended upon him, was another.
He ends this first objection against the faith of Archelaus with vile insults.
Like someone filled with intense rage, he attacked the holy bishop with slander and curses, denying his reputation for holiness.
He believed that, being cut off and struck down by the same censures and anathemas, the bishop was cast out of the Catholic community, just like that unfortunate crowd of heretics, who had indeed been condemned by a more sacred judgment than that of the Church of Archelaus.
As I considered these and similar matters, my spirit did not flare up against Beausobre.
I only observed his eagerness to twist and corrupt the previous testimonies and opinions, aiming to completely undermine the authority of the Acts and utterly diminish the piety of that most holy bishop.
But I understood very well that Beausobre always tried to express his own opinion, attempting to deceive and sell nonsense to the reader by confusing the two descents of the Holy Spirit upon Jesus; one of which, as the sacred Scriptures clearly testify, refers to His conception from the Virgin Mary and the hypostatic union of the Son of God with human nature, and the other to the baptism of Christ.
Therefore, it could not occur to Archelaus, who was debating the mystery of the incarnation, that Jesus Christ became the Son of God when the Holy Spirit descended upon Him after baptism.
For he would have strayed from the central question of whether Christ, the Son of God, truly had a human nature united to Him when He emerged from the virginal womb, which Manes denied; asserting only a phantom humanity for Him and wisely and in a Catholic manner contradicting Archelaus.
Since the inquiry focused solely on whether it was contradictory and improper for the Son of God to truly be born of a woman and to unite a true human nature with Himself in the womb, Archelaus could in no way accept that Jesus was born as one person and brought forth from the virginal womb, and that another person of Christ and the Son of God emerged with the descent of the Holy Spirit after baptism.
Otherwise, the objections of Manes would have prevailed; and Archelaus would have impiously tried to align with the Jews and Photinus beyond the question.
Therefore, it was appropriate that he was rebuked by Manes.
Clearly overwhelmed by the strength and weight of the arguments, he would have to admit that from Mary, a man-not God-was born and came into being.
So, who can conclude or imagine that Archelaus fell into such a terrible mistake from the words that Beausobre presented?
Jesus is indeed the name of a true and unique man.
The angel, announcing the mystery of the incarnation, said this name was to be given to His Son by the command and authority of the Father, as the Evangelists testify.
The name of Christ's person is not a proper name but a designation of power and kingdom.
These two names, perfectly fitting without any distinction or difference of persons, belong to the only Son of God, born in the flesh from the Virgin Mary.
Archelaus demonstrated this from the sacred writings and the common agreement of his elders, both in his community and in the letter he gave to the priest Diodorus, refuting the claims of those heretics who said that Jesus was different from Christ the Son of God.
Therefore, Beausobre's reasoning is false when he argues that the name Jesus itself signifies a person separate from Christ the Son of God.
Even Lactantius, when discussing these names against the heathens, writes: "But even though His name (meaning the Son of God), which the highest Father bestowed on Him from the beginning, is known by no one else besides Him, He still has another name among angels and another among humans.
Indeed, He is called Jesus among humans.
For Christ is not a proper name but a designation of power and kingdom.
"
Therefore, Beausobre unjustly criticizes those words of Archelaus. When he noticed that the holy bishop wrote: "For the Son born of Mary is the one who chose to endure this entire struggle, Jesus," he alludes to the struggle Jesus underwent to reign, enduring true death and burial, and appearing revived on the third day, about to return to the Father from whom He had descended.
This Jesus, Archelaus adds, is the Christ of God, who descended upon the one who is from Mary.
No one, unless they intentionally misinterpret the words, would ever claim that Archelaus intended to imply a distinction of persons from the diversity of names, duties, and natures.
Indeed, the holy bishop is entirely focused on the issue of how Christ, the Son of God, took on true human nature from Mary, arguing against Mani in this way.
If you acknowledge that He was born of Mary, then suffering must follow; and after suffering, resurrection; and after resurrection, judgment; thus fulfilling the commandments of Scripture.
Therefore, as if wanting to challenge his opponent further, he demonstrates through the following Scriptures that the same and only Son of God came into the world from Mary with true humanity.
Namely:
"When the will of God was fulfilled, He sent His Son, born of a woman."
And again: "Christ, our Passover, was sacrificed."
And because God raised the Lord and will also raise us by His power.
Therefore, Beausobre should have compared the words objected to us with the rest of the context of the discussion, and with those written to Diodorus, or to the presbyter Tryphon.
There, by comparing the Old Testament and the New, he proves that both are from God due to the utmost harmony of the prophecies, providing many examples. Speaking especially of Moses and Jesus, he explicitly calls Jesus the true Lord of Moses without any embellishment, affirming that Jesus is the author of the Sabbath and the giver of blessings.
By His own power, He led the people out of the bonds of sin and captivity, delivering them to eternal salvation.
Indeed, all other expressions like these clearly indicate that Jesus was the true Son of God, and they reveal the sound and catholic faith of the holy bishop concerning the mystery of the incarnation, without any mark of heresy.
All these points, which may not seem like our own ideas, are well-supported by the statements in the letter to Diodorus the priest, as we mentioned earlier.
Enthusiastic learners can easily look into this themselves, so we found it unnecessary to replicate and compare it in this work.
Now, let's briefly address another claim made by Beausobre regarding the descent of the Holy Spirit on Jesus after His baptism.
Beausobre, from previously weak arguments that greatly misrepresent truth and holiness, wrongly associates Archelaus with vile heretics.
He claims that the bishop didn't discuss the mystery of the incarnation more holily or wisely than Mani himself.
Beausobre then moves on to another argument, which he begins with these terms.
Archelaus challenges the Manichaean opponent, urging him to respond.
He denies the real and true birth of Christ the Lord from Mary, suggesting that this same Christ only appeared to be a man, lacking the true essence of body and soul, over whom the Holy Spirit descended in the form of a dove.
He further presses him to explain who was baptized by John at that time.
Then he states: If He was perfect, if He was the Son, then the Spirit could not enter, just as a kingdom cannot enter within a kingdom.
After describing this testimony, Beausobre argues that this Latin interpretation of the Greek and Arabic text seems barbaric.
He claims that the Greek word translated into Latin as "kingdom" actually signifies throne, dominion, power, or principality-terms more commonly used in Scriptures to denote heavenly intelligences. Therefore, our master of ancient theologians points out Archelaus and his words, adding a false criticism that Archelaus referred to Christ as Jesus and affirmed that He was born of Mary, as if Jesus, even Christ according to the flesh, could not be called. But this accusation by Beausobre should rather be aimed at the evangelists.
Matthew, when discussing the birth of the Son of God in the flesh, used both names, writing: "The book of the genealogy of Jesus Christ, the son of David," and later adds: "Jesus who is called Christ."
The Scriptures frequently contain testimonies like this, almost countless, indicating that the Son of God was born from Mary with both names, showing no distinction between Jesus and Christ.
I don't understand why or on what basis our critic would assume that using these two words together was meant to assert or imply Archelaus.
Beausobre, in his eagerness to detract and slander, fabricated this claim, as his next accusation clearly shows.
He examines the rest of the praised sentence's words and twists them to mean the opposite; assuming he is speaking to only dull and uninformed people who have never studied theology or explored the holy Fathers and Scriptures, he again attacks the holy bishop, accusing him of heresy by claiming that Jesus Christ became the Son of God only after being baptized by John.
Otherwise, one would have to suggest that divine power entered one, and the one Spirit entered another.
Therefore, it was necessary for Jesus Christ to truly have human nature so that the Holy Spirit could descend upon him.
However, the pious and Catholic mind of Archelaus was far removed from such a way of thinking, as the previously mentioned points clearly reveal.
Once, since Manes and Archelaus agreed on this point-namely, the beginnings of the appearance of Jesus Christ, acknowledging that he was truly God and the Son of God, and born from Mary with true human nature assumed in her womb and united with the divine Word-controversy arose.
Archelaus could no longer exceed the established bounds of this debate or deviate from, or deny, the true divinity of Christ.
He had to affirm and prove that the descent of the Holy Spirit upon Jesus at his baptism occurred for the grace of human nature.
This was so it would be clearly known to the world, angels, and humans that he is the helper of the human race, the mediator, and the true atoner predetermined from eternity.
He was sent in time from the seat of the Father to humans to preach forgiveness to captives, sight to the blind, release the broken into forgiveness, and proclaim the acceptable year of the Lord and the day of vengeance.
Thus, with that descent, the abundance and fullness of grace were manifested, which we all received through the mediator, the high priest, anointed by God.
Therefore, the Holy Spirit wanted to indicate this ministry, power, and authority to be exercised, which is why he was called anointed, as Isaiah had already prophesied.
Therefore, even if the Popes, in the Catholic sense, have explained the descent of the Holy Spirit upon the baptized Jesus in various ways, they all agree it happened so we would be taught that the first fruits of human nature were restored when he wished to appear as a true man, capable of sanctification, as Cyril says.
At the same time, it was made known that his anointing was completed then because he took on all the ministries, functions, and exercises prophesied by Isaiah, pertaining to the priesthood.
From all this, it follows that it was a great injustice for Archelaus to be suspected of heresy because he attributed both the names Jesus and Christ to Mary's only son.
This way of speaking was essential for him to maintain to signify the union of the two natures, as Theodoret points out.
According to Augustine, truly knowing Jesus Christ means recognizing him as more than just a man.
For if he is merely a man and nothing more, then he is not truly Jesus Christ.
To thoroughly counter any clever and deceitful interpretations of Archelaus's words, why do we need the manner of speaking and opinions of other Catholic Fathers?
The arguments, sequence, and meaning of words in the discussion clearly show that Archelaus explained himself fully, revealing the blasphemies of Mani and the objections he tried to counter with the testimonies of the Scriptures.
Archelaus approached Mani with this argument.
If, as you claim, he was not born, then without a doubt, he did not suffer, for it is impossible for someone who was not born to suffer.
And if he did not suffer, then the significance of the cross is lost.
After inserting similar remarks, addressing Mani, he adds:
You connect all these points, denying that he was born of Mary; for if you admit he was born of Mary, then suffering must follow, then resurrection, and then judgment, and the commandments of the Scriptures will be upheld for us.
Shortly after, he addresses him further:
So, answer me each question: how will we reject the profound and noble words of the Apostle, which say: "But when it was God's will, He sent His Son, born of a woman."
And again: "Christ, our Passover, has been sacrificed."
And because God raised the Lord, He will raise us by His power.
Archelaus firmly relied on these and other testimonies from the Apostle to defend the true birth of Jesus Christ from the Virgin Mary.
After this, Archelaus discussed the descent of the Holy Spirit on Jesus at his baptism, which Beausobre argues is marked by heresy.
He challenges the Manichaean with these words:
Tell me this, O Manichaean.
If you claim that Christ was not born of Mary but appeared as a man without truly being one, because of the power within him, then tell me, upon whom did the Holy Spirit descend like a dove?
Who was baptized by John?
If he was perfect and powerful, the Spirit could not enter, just as a kingdom cannot enter within another kingdom.
Whose voice from heaven declared: This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased?
Tell me, don't delay.
Who is the one who prepares all these things, who does everything?
In response to Archelaus's question, Manes boldly asserted that it seems pious to him to say the Son of God needed nothing, as his coming was arranged for the earth.
He needed neither a dove, nor baptism, nor a mother, nor brothers, and perhaps not even a father, who according to you-meaning Archelaus-was Joseph.
But the one who descended entirely, transforming himself into whatever he wished as a man, just as Paul says he was found in appearance as a man.
What then would he need who transforms himself into everything?
Show me.
Then, seeking to mock what Archelaus had advocated as orthodox, he presents this other argument, which he thought would challenge the bishop:
For if you say he was only a man from Mary and received the Spirit at baptism, then he would be seen as the Son through development and not by nature.
Finally, when comparing the Holy Spirit with Christ, the Son of God, the argument goes like this:
If I allow you to say that the Son is in accordance with growth, as if He became a man, then you think He is truly a man, meaning flesh and blood.
In that case, you must also consider the Spirit, who appeared like a dove, to be nothing other than a literal dove.
For it was said LIKE A MAN and LIKE A DOVE.
Whatever thoughts you have about the phrase LIKE A MAN, apply the same to what is said LIKE A DOVE.
These must be accepted equally because that is how they are written in the Scriptures about Him.
Meanwhile, Archelaus was pondering many things, having heard so many blasphemies spoken by Manes.
He was particularly worried that this debate, if discussed too thoroughly, might pose more risk than benefit to the ignorant and unwise who were present.
Knowing that the understanding of the Scriptures is not granted to everyone, he realized he couldn't clearly explain and resolve the complex question, except for the sake of those listening to us.
However, compelled by the necessity of the crowd, he tried to address only the points that Manes had clearly preached, which were wrapped in obvious and serious errors, while omitting some objections.
Therefore, continuing his argument, he reasoned directly to the person, as they say in school:
Tell me, if we understand that Jesus naturally became a man from Mary, having flesh and blood, then do we also need to believe that the Holy Spirit is a real dove and not a Spirit?
To refute this false conclusion, he immediately points out that a real dove cannot enter and remain within a real man, just as flesh cannot naturally enter flesh.
On the contrary, we truly understand the Scriptures when we acknowledge that Jesus Christ is a genuine human being with real flesh and blood, born of Mary, and that the Holy Spirit only appeared in the form of a dove.
The Spirit, for a specific reason, dwells in a person, descends, and remains; this has fittingly happened and continues to happen always.
Therefore, it's essential to naturally affirm the true human attributes of Jesus Christ, as Archelaus demonstrates.
However, it's incorrect to attribute the true characteristics of a dove to the Holy Spirit.
This is clearly prohibited by the operations, perfections, attributes, and actions of the Holy Spirit.
When he revealed this distinct reasoning, neither Manes nor any other supporter of falsehood could contradict it; thus, he addresses the adversary, mockingly engaging with playful words.
Since Manes claimed to be the Paraclete of God, he asserted that the Spirit had come upon him, whom Jesus had promised to send; and as Archelaus points out, from where else, unless it descends from heaven?
Therefore, he confirms with admirable words that the Holy Spirit resides in heaven, descends into a person, and remains there; suggesting that it can only descend upon a person worthy of it, that is, full of grace and virtue.
But it would be more fitting to think that real doves descended upon Manes himself, not upon Christ:
So that we might consider you (he says) rather a thief of doves, setting traps for them; for you deserve to be mocked with absurd words.
Returning to the discussion from which he had slightly deviated, regarding Manes' false claim that God transformed himself into a man or the sun, to show that our Jesus appeared as a man only in appearance, a statement any faithful person should reject as heretical, he refers to all the promises and figures in the Scriptures about this birth.
Even the name of the Advent would need to be erased, as, if positioned in heaven, he could do what he wanted if we affirm he was only Spirit and not a man.
He disproves this with the Apostle's words to the Philippians: He emptied himself, taking the form of a servant.
He then adds: I speak of him who was made man from Mary.
This way of speaking clearly reveals the nature and person of the divine Word before being born of the Virgin.
Just as in the world after baptism, the Father's voice announced, speaking of him who was born of Mary as the Son: This is the Christ of God who descended upon him who is from Mary.
I am aware that this last phrase is not sufficiently approved by Beausobre and is suspected as a source of the Nestorian heresy.
But it is far from true that even in the heat of this argument, Archelaus distinguished two persons in Christ, one of man and one of God.
He only discussed the two natures united with each other, which the only Son of God, truly born of Mary, had joined in himself, as he consistently professed throughout the argument in a Catholic manner.
And indeed, those words of Archelaus, which Beausobre maliciously tried to interpret, clearly show this: This is the Christ of God, that is, the Son, who descended upon him who is from Mary.
Shortly after, he unequivocally asserts that this Son of God was born of Mary.
Speaking of Jesus baptized, who had already come up out of the waters of the Jordan, he said: For immediately Jesus was led by the Spirit into the desert to be tempted by the devil, whom the devil, not knowing, said to him, If you are the Son of God.
However, he didn't understand why he had begotten the Son of God, who preached the kingdom of heaven.
Archelaus declared that the Son of God was truly born in human form from Mary.
Furthermore, he received the Holy Spirit at baptism, through whom the Father's voice testified, saying: This is my beloved Son.
No one else could bear this, except he who was born of Mary, Jesus, above all saints.
Manes had presented various arguments to Archelaus, which seemed yet to be refuted and overturned.
He attempted to challenge his opponent wisely and more strongly, never straying from the boundaries of the set debate.
Therefore, he was not going to prove that Jesus, the son of Mary, was a man by appearance alone.
The bishop then said: If you say he is a man by appearance and form, how could he have been captured by the Pharisees, who were born of man and woman, and brought to judgment, since a spiritual body cannot be grasped by denser bodies?
Rebuking and provoking the same Manes, who claimed that the Son of God could transform himself into any form and appearance at will, even into the sun, he added: Go ahead, I ask, and bring me a handful of sun, or a bushel full!
The sun itself, because it is of a more refined body, can cover and surround you, but you, even if you trample on it, do not harm it at all.
On the contrary, he concludes, my Lord Jesus, if he was captured, he was captured as a man by men.
If he is not a man, he was not captured.
If he was not captured, he did not suffer, nor was he baptized.
If he was not baptized, none of us were baptized either.
If there is no baptism, there will be no forgiveness of sins, but each one will die in their sins.
Realizing the disadvantage that Archelaus's words brought upon him, Manes skipped over this whole argument and focused only on those final words, bringing forth two conclusions.
First, he responded: So baptism is given for the forgiveness of sins?
When Archelaus said this and responded with "Amen," he quickly added another blasphemy: "Did Christ sin because he was baptized?"
Shocked by this remark, Archelaus immediately objected, saying, "God forbid," and using the words of the Apostle Paul, he concluded with:
"Rather, he became sin for us, taking on our sins. For this reason, he was born of a woman and came to baptism to sanctify this part; so that the Spirit, which descended in the form of a dove, could rest upon the body he had taken on."
Beausobre argues, without hesitation, that Archelaus deviated from the principles of Catholic truth in the last part of his response.
Although he knew and preached the utmost innocence of Jesus Christ, insisting that he did not receive baptism to be cleansed from his own sins-an idea that would be blasphemous-when he added that Jesus was baptized to receive sanctification as one born of a woman, and to become capable of bearing the Spirit that descended upon him, he significantly departed from the principles of Catholic faith.
But isn't it clear that this is slander and fabrication?
Throughout the entire discussion, Archelaus both implicitly and explicitly professed that Christ's soul was perfectly sanctified through the hypostatic union with the divine Word: there was no sin in his soul to be erased by baptism.
However, since he was to undergo the severe trials of the cross, passion, and death, the Holy Spirit descended upon him in that visible form to strengthen the weak, fleshly body he assumed from the Virgin, so it could endure all the torments of such a bloody trial.
So, how does Beausobre conclude that Archelaus, by that statement, departed from the Catholic faith?
The body and soul, which at the moment of its conception was united to the Word's person and was substantially sanctified, did not need a new purification through baptism to become the dwelling place of the Holy Spirit.
Didn't Archelaus acknowledge this when he denied that Christ had His own sin, but rather was made sin for us, taking on our sins?
Therefore, while He took on our sins to atone for them, He also needed to be outwardly purified with visible signs, so He could affix our sins to the cross and erase them through His death and passion.
Ultimately, Archelaus intended to suggest that He needed some external purification, appearing as a sinner in the world for us, having truly carried our weaknesses and borne our sorrows.
Didn't He experience mental anguish in the garden before ascending the cross, and was comforted by an angel?
Didn't He, while on the cross and experiencing mortal pains, pray to God the Father, saying: "My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?"
The unanimous consensus of Catholics affirms that He did not need support due to the hypostatic union of the divine Word.
But who, except for Beausobre, could ever deny that these things were necessary to demonstrate the true human nature?
Finally, Beausobre, to more eagerly support the parts of his non-Catholic sect, refers to Saint Methodius, a contemporary of Archelaus, whom he criticizes as a supporter of Arian and Nestorian doctrines.
Led by this reasoning, he tries to show that the bishops and martyrs of the Catholics, who thrived in the third century of the Church, were not sincere guardians of the evangelical and Catholic faith, but had undermined and corrupted it with distorted opinions.
However, since our current leisure study doesn't allow us to spend too much time on dispelling these and similar matters, we'll move on to examine other aspects related to the history of Mani, specifically his death.
We will more successfully arrive at the truth, which Beausobre admitted he only wished for in false words, to further deceive his followers and mislead unsuspecting and unlearned readers.
Chapter Ten
Manes, while fleeing from Diodorus, is captured by Persian officials and, after being flayed, faces the consequences of his actions.
Beausobre mistakenly blames Archelaus for this death, but his arguments are proven wrong.
Eventually, the Manichaeans commemorate Manes' birthday with solemn and religious ceremonies.
In previous chapters, we've worked hard to dismantle Beausobre's false accusations against Bishop Archelaus's faith and religion, which were unjustly fabricated.
Our motivation was to thoroughly re-evaluate the Manichaean's malicious arguments against Catholic truth, and to highlight Bishop Archelaus's efforts to counter and completely reject the heretical teachings aimed at him.
Whether Archelaus was more effective in debunking the Manichaean and defending Catholic truths than Beausobre claimed, who accused the revered and holy bishop of violating faith and defending many heresies, will soon be evident from what we have discussed.
We now aim to appeal to those readers who are familiar with the writings of the Holy Fathers and ancient theologians.
These readers, who have a thorough and orderly understanding of Christian matters, are not eager to refresh their minds with novelties, nor are they driven by a restless desire for diverse and unfamiliar knowledge.
They avoid eagerly diving into non-Catholic books, which can gradually fill the mind with false and biased opinions, and corrupt the piety of the Christian name.
However, if I were to seek the judgment of those who, driven by a love of novelties, merely promote ideas borrowed from heretical books among crowds and gatherings of the unlearned, to claim the opinion of the learned, I would already understand that my cause, and that of Archelaus, might falter, even though it uniquely relies on Catholic truth drawn from Scripture and tradition.
To stay focused on our topic and keep things brief, we state that Manes was disgracefully and confusingly expelled from the parish or village by Diodorus.
He would have undoubtedly faced a violent death due to the people's anger and uproar if not for Marcellinus, a wise administrator of civil affairs for the Roman Empire in that province, and Archelaus, who, guided by leniency, managed to calm the people's fury.
With the help of a swift escape, Manes sought refuge across the Stranga River and returned to the fortress of Arabion, where he had been before heading to Mesopotamia.
He might have found some comfort in thinking that the death sentence issued by the Persian king against him was either abolished or changed due to shifts in civil affairs during his time away from the court.
Archelaus lightly recounted the matter in his debate with these words, adding:
Retracing his steps, Manes crossed the river and returned to the fortress of Arabion.
Later, when captured there and brought before the king, who was extremely angry with him for various reasons, the king sought double vengeance for the deaths of his son and the jailer.
He ordered that Manes be flayed and hanged at the city gate, his skin filled with preservatives and inflated, while his flesh was left for the birds.
Cyril, the bishop of Jerusalem, recounted Manes's death similarly in the catechumen lessons, adding other details, such as Manes being brought before the Persian king and forced to present himself, facing many accusations for his lies and escape.
The king further mocked his servitude, accused him of murdering his son, and condemned the guards to death because of him.
Thus, Cyril concludes, supporting Archelaus's words, that the king ordered Manes be flayed according to Persian law, and the rest of his body was given to beasts.
However, his skin, which harbored such wickedness, was hung like a wineskin before the gates.
In a similar manner, Socrates described the death of Mani.
Wanting to document the history of church matters, he reviewed the debate between Archelaus and Mani, which was already recorded, and examined it himself.
He explained everything we've mentioned so far, maintaining a faithful account of the events.
He aimed to ensure that his report wouldn't be suspected of falsehood, and to clear any prejudices from the reader's mind.
When the king of Persia learned that Mani was in the region, he had him captured, ordered his skin to be removed, filled it with straw, and hung it at the city gates.
To prove the truth of these statements, he added, "We did not invent these things; we extracted them from a certain debate of Archelaus, bishop of the city of Caschar in Mesopotamia, which we have read."
This debate of Archelaus, having been written down and translated into Greek, was circulated.
No one from that time until the year seventeen forty dared to claim it was false or fictitious.
No one, I say, argued it contained made-up stories.
Therefore, should we think this judgment was reserved only for Beausobre and a few others who try to agree with the aforementioned writer?
We will discuss this type of criticism more clearly later.
Finally, when we consider the death of Mani, in addition to the authority of Epiphanius, who supports earlier writers, there is also the testimony of Photius.
Although he might be seen as a person of questionable faith due to the schism he introduced to the Catholic Church, no one has yet dared to deny his diligence in examining ancient writings and his great learning.
So, even though he didn't follow the usual methods of previous writers when reviewing the death of Mani and the deeds of Archelaus, it's found that he hardly deviated from their accounts.
Chapter 13 tells the story of how Manes had to wander around to escape the wrath of the Persian king.
It describes guards searching everywhere to capture him and bring him before the king, where he faced severe rebukes and suffered a death considered unworthy because of his terrible impieties.
The well-regarded chapter concludes with these words, believed to be borrowed from Socrates and Archelaus:
While the unfortunate man was still alive, his skin was removed, his body flayed and discarded like a bag; the rest of his body was thrown to the beasts as prey, and his skin was filled with air like a bag and hung in front of the doors.
Such was the end of a traitorous and most wicked man.
Again, the praised Photius, in chapter 15, recalls this bitter death but first mentions the famous debate that Archelaus had against Manes.
He refers to Archelaus as a divine and holy man, the bishop of the Caschar people in Mesopotamia.
He then recounts how Manes, unexpectedly shamed, fled from a public meeting, defeated by Diodorides.
Once more, when Archelaus debated with him again, Manes was forced to flee and appeared as a wicked man, deserving ridicule and detestation for all his teachings.
Eventually, he was captured by the king's ministers who were searching and investigating, and he suffered harsh punishments.
Although Beausobre dared not deny this truth, supported by so many significant points, he nevertheless gradually attempted to weaken it with much effort.
In chapter 11 of the previous book, about to describe the death of Manes, he claims that its author and almost executor was Bishop Archelaus, citing these words spoken in French after the debate:
When I found this out, I also found it necessary to inform you, because he is still sought by the king of Persia to this day.
I think no one is unaware that these praised words refer to the crimes committed by Manes in Persia.
Archelaus was compelled to reveal the truth when, after his final debate with Manichaeus, he announced silence to the astonished crowds gathered from various parts of the province to hear their religious discussion.
He unveiled the entire sequence of events and the crimes committed by Manes.
Beausobre criticized Archelaus's approach, arguing that the bishop should not have made Manes' crimes public, especially those for which he was being pursued by the royal Persian officials, like the murder of a royal prince.
As a good pastor, Beausobre believed Archelaus should have only addressed the Manichaean errors in faith, so people could be wary of them.
Beausobre presumed he could easily understand and interpret the mind, intentions, and actions of the holy bishop, suggesting that Archelaus aimed to incite the crowd to fury and rebellion, so Manes would be captured and handed over to the Persians.
These Persians lived on the borders of Mesopotamia, only separated from Roman control by the Stranga River.
Beausobre claimed that Archelaus's intentions were therefore improper and irregular.
The people clearly understood this before the bishop even finished his speech, rising against Manes and attempting to capture him and bring him in chains to the neighboring barbarians.
However, Manes fled diligently to the fortress of Arabion.
Is this really surprising?
Beausobre imagined that Epiphanius wanted to support this malicious interpretation as well, according to his opinion.
It is said that this holy bishop realized that Archelaus's extreme zeal greatly dishonored the nature of being a bishop.
As a result, he set aside the previous account and created an entirely new one on his own.
He wrote that the people, driven by their passion for the Catholic faith, aimed to stone Mani, but he intervened to prevent this, allowing Mani to escape and find refuge.
According to Beausobre, Tillemont was convinced that this brief account was falsely attributed to Epiphanius, as it does not appear in the Acts of Archelaus.
However, even if we accept what Epiphanius later recounted without naming an author, it still shows that the bishop of Caschara wanted Mani's downfall without being directly blamed for his death.
Indeed, although he opposed those who wanted to stone this criminal, he took steps to ensure that Mani, who was sought everywhere for numerous crimes, would be apprehended once captured.
He informed the royal ministers of Persia so that Mani would be brought before the king and face the death penalty.
Thus far, Beausobre criticizes and challenges both bishops, Archelaus and Epiphanius.
However, all the objections he raised cannot suppress the truth of the events if we carefully examine the purpose of the narrative praised in the Acts of Archelaus.
Moreover, the two Fathers do not contradict each other in describing Mani's death, as will be explored in the following observations.
Firstly, regarding Archelaus's actions and discussions with the people of Diodoris, he not only revealed the Manichaean errors in faith but also exposed the serious crimes committed by this wicked man, for which he was sought for execution by the Persian king's public authority.
I believe nothing in his actions dishonors the episcopal character.
We wouldn't consider Archelaus's words as driven by zeal unless there was a very serious reason, which Beausobre could have easily understood had he examined the Acts of Archelaus more diligently.
We, who have meticulously studied these Acts and engaged in lengthy discussions, have come to understand that a significant uproar erupted among the people present at the conclusion of the most recent meeting.
Some supporters of Archelaus were eager to celebrate his great achievements with loud acclamations.
Meanwhile, others, filled with anger and hatred towards Manes, seemed driven by fury, possibly to the point of wanting to kill him.
The commotion among the people is clearly indicated by the text of the Acts, which we present here.
Thus, it seems likely that while Archelaus's praises were being sung amid the crowd's noise, Manes' heresy and infamous teachings were being condemned and denounced with insults and reproaches.
If Beausobre still wished to challenge me, I would ask what the term 'uproar' is intended to signify?
If, as Cicero suggests, it implies a disturbance causing significant fear, we understand that due to the discussions, the reputation and opinions about Manes were jeopardized.
It is very likely that the crowd, with equal fervor, wanted to detain Manes, bind him, or stone him, to prevent him from escaping the consequences he deserved.
Therefore, it was necessary for Archelaus to calm the crowd with words and prayers to prevent such a disturbance from leading to actions against the laws of nations and the church.
Didn't Marcellus indeed invite Manes, by letter, to come to Cascharam?
Thus, the laws of nations had to be respected, and it could never be allowed, without breaching the given trust, for anyone to be harmed by hostile actions; especially since Manes was under the jurisdiction of the Persians, not the Romans.
Therefore, it could not have occurred to Archelaus, with Marcellus present, to incite the people to rebellion and seek the death of the heretic.
Why did the same holy bishop, in an effort to maintain ecclesiastical gentleness, advise the people not to leave the gathering, promising to address them again soon?
Yet, crowds continued to gather, indicating that neither the tumult nor the disturbance had been quelled.
Later, when they were gathered, Archelaus urged them to listen to his words.
If the people were not causing an uproar against Manes, and if they were not seeking his death, why did Archelaus employ additional efforts and persuasion to get those gathered to listen?
As Epiphanius more clearly described the series of events, he did not fabricate anything but rather reviewed what might have been recorded in the same Acts long ago.
These records may have been omitted, perhaps due to the inexperience of the copyists or the bad faith of the translators.
The preceding words, which we have already transcribed, indicate that a gap had emerged.
After these words, so that the crowds, with all their effort, tried, the following words immediately appear, which provide no genuine meaning: beyond they would not allow him, etc.
Zacagnius, noticing this manuscript gap, suggested that at least the word "and" should be added, which anyone can easily judge still causes confusion and disorder in the text.
But I will not strongly oppose the idea that nothing is missing there.
However, what then?
Did Epiphanius invent from his own opinion that the people sought to stone Manes?
Away with such a fabrication.
The series of Acts narrates how a multitude of people from the entire province had gathered in that parish, with others from neighboring places present.
When silence was established, Archelaus began to speak about Manes in this manner.
After saying a few words, he urged the people to set aside all disturbances and noise, and to listen to what he had learned about Manes and what he intended to reveal, without hesitation.
"But now," he said, "I ask you to listen in silence as I speak briefly, so you may know who he is, where he comes from, and what kind of person he is."
Therefore, Archelaus had to call for silence once, twice, and finally a third time to calm the crowd's disturbances and commotion. This was necessary because the people were already beginning to attack Manes. The last words we transcribed clearly show that their minds were stirred against the heretic.
So Archelaus, using sound judgment, promised to speak to the people about this heretic's character, background, homeland, teachings, and crimes, hoping his narrative could secure the attention of the gathered audience and, in the meantime, open a wide path for Manes to escape, so he could secure his life and safety.
Eventually, it happened that he retraced his steps, crossed the river, and reached the stronghold of Arabionis.
But let's assume the people of Diodoridis were not yet stirred to anger and hatred against Manes. What then? Did Archelaus want to incite the people by revealing Manes' life and crimes, so that when the heretic was captured, he would be carefully led away as a victim to be sacrificed by the Persians?
Who could judge this without being reckless? It's more reasonable to think that Archelaus wanted to discuss Manes' origin, birth, status, deceit, and Manichaean crimes to ensure that the Persians, who sought him everywhere with public authority, would not allow the simpler and less knowledgeable in matters of faith to be misled by his false teachings.
Didn't the Arians, Nestorians, Eutychians, and in more recent centuries, the Calvinists, Lutherans, and Socinians, spread their heresies through preaching and debates?
This could have been more successful for them when they relied on the noise and power of arms, or when they became more renowned through the authority of dignities or the knowledge of sciences.
Or finally, when they gained the support of certain secular princes, disregarding all restraints of modesty and fear, which allowed them the freedom to corrupt and distort the minds, morals, and faith of others with the depravity of their opinions.
Therefore, it was necessary for Archelaus, with the people applauding him, to demonstrate not only that the adversary of his Catholic law lacked true and genuine knowledge and understanding of the Holy Scriptures, but also sought to overthrow the principal mysteries of our faith and abolish them with his tales.
Moreover, that he was deprived of all the goods and resources of nature and fortune; so that his name, wicked morals, and crimes, already known to many nations, were utterly abhorred everywhere.
Therefore, I do not see at all what crime could be found in such a narrative and manner of action.
Considering that the people who gathered to hear the debate at Diodorus' place were not disturbed by Mani, wasn't it fitting for the bishop to remind them of everything he had learned from the mouths of Turbo and the other disciple?
Wasn't it appropriate for the bishop to use all the precautions and means he deemed more effective and stronger for maintaining the peace of his diocese, the safety of his flock, and preserving and defending the purity of Christian doctrine?
Beausobre indeed fabricates, attempting to turn such a manner of action into a crime.
Especially since Archelaus did not falsely accuse Mani, nor did he become angry with him for an unreasonable cause by making things up; he only reported what he had learned from the mouths of the two disciples of Mani.
Now indeed the Holy Fathers.
.
The writers, all in agreement, have detailed the death of Manes, as the testimonies provided at the start of this chapter clearly show.
However, Beausobre, even after critiquing Bishops Archelaus and Epiphanius, continues to find faults, pointing out slight differences in the expressions and wording used by these esteemed writers.
He gently criticizes them in a disapproving manner, attempting to portray them as inconsistent, with the aim of undermining the credibility of the Acts of Archelaus.
Initially, he claims Epiphanius, in describing Manes' death, added embellishments, stating Manes was flayed with thorns and his skin filled with straw, a detail seemingly supported by the Syrian writer Albulpharagius.
However, he suggests it's likely that this information was learned from and copied from Epiphanius's writings, given his proficiency in Greek.
He notes that Photius, who reviewed the Greek account based on the Acts of Archelaus, reported that Manes' skin was filled with air or wind, like a bellows.
He finds this version more plausible.
This is because the skins of criminals flayed by the Persians were typically filled with air, not straw, to preserve them, as was the case with Emperor Valerian, flayed by Shapur's order after his death.
The Persians then displayed his preserved skin to the Roman emperors' emissaries as a symbol of a glorious victory.
However, if we trust the Greek accounts and stories, we might be led to believe that Saint Bartholomew and the monk Studius met a fate similar to Manes.
Lastly, Epiphanius erroneously claims that the Manichaeans would lie on straw or thorns to commemorate their patriarch, who was flayed with thorn pricks and whose skin was filled with straw or chaff.
But Beausobre, guided by Augustine's testimony, argues that Epiphanius fabricated this story.
Augustine recounts that a schism arose among the Manichaeans in Rome when Constantius.
.
Citizen, when several people of this sect gathered to strictly follow the Manichaean teachings, the group quickly split into two factions.
Some abandoned this way of life because it was too strict, while others remained committed to rigorously observing the praised commandments.
Regarding the schism described by Beausobre, we will let his words speak for themselves, especially when our discussion turns to the various ranks of the Manichaeans.
Meanwhile, I'd like you to notice that everything we've just described from Beausobre, regarding the different ways and phrases used by earlier writers and Church Fathers, doesn't undermine or overturn the truth of the events or the history of the Manichaean execution.
The aim of the praised writers wasn't to describe every minute and subtle detail of this execution.
Some provided more detail, while others were more succinct, stating that Mani was flayed by the Persians as punishment for his wickedness.
Even if some added details omitted by previous writers, these might have happened, either due to popular and possibly certain traditions received from the Persians or because their writings were increasingly adapted to Persian customs, rites, and institutions.
However, one thing was unanimously affirmed and recorded by all: namely, that Mani was officially sentenced to be flayed.
Whether he was still alive when flayed or if his skin was removed with spiky thorns or an iron stylus doesn't affect the truth of history.
Such details are of little or no importance and aren't so necessary that we should accuse the writers who added or omitted them of lying or telling fanciful stories.
We must assert the same about his body, which wasn't buried but left to decay and serve as food and nourishment for beasts and birds.
Beausobre confidently asserts that the Persians and other nations had a way of acting that wasn't considered disgraceful, based on strong testimonies.
However, the basis for this claim seems not only weak but completely falls apart.
Specifically, the idea that the Persians were horrified at the thought of digging graves due to their reverence for the elements.
But who doesn't know that the Persians had vaults, crypts, and caves?
If they were religiously opposed to digging into the ground out of respect for the elements, it's unclear why they couldn't place the dead in natural hollows, pits, and caves.
Therefore, we believe all those monuments collected from Porphyry, Assemanus, and Hyde, which were added at the end, are misplaced as they don't help us in proving that the dead Manes' flesh was left for animals and birds to devour.
I realize that such an infamous and cruel death, which should have caused fear and terror, greatly disturbed the followers of Manes.
Yet, they began to celebrate it annually with joy and superstitious religious practices.
Consequently, after the Easter celebration of our Lord Jesus Christ was abolished or observed with little enthusiasm, they only honored the day of Mani's death with great reverence.
Augustine once shed light on the reasons behind these profane and sacrilegious rituals.
He was almost in awe when he listened to the teachings of the Manichaean sect.
He would ask them why they didn't celebrate the Lord's Passover with vigils, extended fasting, or festive preparations.
In contrast, they honored their Bema, the day Manichaeus was killed, with a tribunal set up in five steps, adorned with precious linens, displayed openly, and celebrated with grandeur and devotion.
When Augustine inquired about this, he was told that they should celebrate the day of the passion of the one who truly suffered.
However, since Christ was not born and only appeared to have a human body, he did not suffer but only pretended to.
After his conversion, Saint Augustine reflected on this falsehood and lamented.
He spoke out against those who, while wanting to be called Christians, denied that Christ was born of a woman and had a human body.
They would not celebrate his passion, which is now the most festive time worldwide, replacing it with the sacrilegious celebration of Bema.
They sought to honor it as the most delightful and worthy of great respect.
Whether more recent Manichaeans still practice these solemn rituals is entirely unknown to me.
I might only ask Beausobre and Bailly, who passionately defended the Manichaean religion, if what we reviewed from Augustine is still practiced.
Their responses could further enrich our current reflections.
These are the thoughts that come to mind about the life, customs, deeds, and end of Manichaeus from ancient writings.
Now, to gain a fuller understanding, we must return to Archelaus, who, persuaded by Marcellus, documented the confession of Turbonis and the discussions held with Manichaeus.
Chapter Eleven
The Fanciful Creations of Manichaean Philosophy and Theology, Denounced by Turbo, a Disciple of Mani Converted to the Catholic Faith, and Documented by Archelaus, Bishop of Caschar, Through the Persuasion of Marcellus, Along with Mani's Debates.
I want to share the public confession and denunciation of crimes made by Turbo, a follower of Mani, before Archelaus and others in the city of Caschar in Mesopotamia.
We'll then focus on the writings of Archelaus, as he documented what he heard from the repentant Turbo and what the bold Manichaean himself presented in two Catholic debates.
By examining Archelaus's books, we can uncover the truth.
Any attempts by Beausobre to discredit these accounts won't harm us or the truth, as we'll clarify later on.
First, setting aside the main and fundamental errors of this sect, which Turbo was the first to denounce in his public confession, we move on to describe other impious, trivial, sacrilegious, and fanciful inventions.
Among these tales, those concerning the first creation of humans, their fall, and restoration hold a prominent place, as invented by the Manichaeans.
They claim there are two eternal, opposing gods of light and darkness, engaged in a great war, each creating parts of humanity.
During this creation, when the author of darkness advanced beyond his limits to reach the light, the good parent of light produced a soul from his power, called the mother of life.
With this soul, he first adorned a human and clothed him with the four elements, so that he might fight downward against the darkness.
However, when the rulers of darkness, seemingly provoked to battle, opposed the man, they caused him great harm and consumed his armor, which is the soul.
In such a perilous situation, it's said that the first man suffered his initial fall and ruin.
They claimed that the afflictions, diseases, and hardships of this man's mind and body did not stem from disobedience or gluttony, but from the darkness itself, which severely oppressed him.
They assert that all these events occurred before the creation of heaven, earth, luminaries, the firmament, and the spheres.
Thus, before the first man entered the world, the chaos of darkness already existed, and he prayed to the father of lights, who heard him kindly and mercifully.
Another power, which came from the divine substance, known as the living spirit, descended and extended a helping hand to the downtrodden and afflicted man to lead him out of the darkness that endangered him.
The Manichaeans openly professed this mystery of impiety not only in their beliefs but also through their external rituals and ceremonies.
When they met each other, they would give their right hands as a sign that they had escaped the bosom and prisons of darkness.
But what they theorized about the creation of the world was equally absurd and irrational.
They imagined that the living spirit, the creator of the world, descended with three other unnamed powers to lead the rulers of Jesus into the firmament, which they considered his body, the sphere.
They believed the firmament to be animated, similar to the luminaries we see circling it.
They claimed that these vital movements had such power that the wills of men were compelled to act against their free will, leading to injury and destruction.
They added absurdity upon absurdity.
When they discussed the creation, state, and movement of the earth, they argued that it was formed, not believing at all that it was held in the middle of the world by divine power, but rather carried on the shoulders of some imagined support, which, when strained from carrying it, would tremble.
They claimed this was the cause of earthquakes outside their usual times.
Indeed, what they proposed about these earthquakes was utterly ridiculous and blasphemous, suggesting it was the reason the blessed Father brought forth his Son from the depths into the heart of the earth and its inner parts.
Then they said the earth, or matter, produced plants and sprouts on its own.
When these were taken by certain rulers, the eternal Father summoned all the primary rulers, took individual powers from them, and created this man according to the form of that first man, bringing the soul into him.
What the Manichaeans meant by the names of these primary rulers is not clear from Turbo's confession.
Only one thing is clear from the previous words: they suggested two lineages of the human race, with the first preceding the Adamitic one, possibly paving the way for the harmful and erroneous belief in the Pre-Adamites that emerged later.
They also attempted to derive another reason why the blessed Father sent the Son into the world from the most recent lineage of this man.
Not in the way the mystery of the Incarnation is testified by the Scriptures as predetermined.
Instead, they claimed the Father was moved to send his beloved Son because of the hardships and afflictions this man's soul endured in the body.
For this reason and because of the support, the Father sent his Son, the Manichaeans taught.
They fabricated that the coming of the Son into the world did not occur in real and passible assumed flesh, but only in a simulated and apparent form of a man.
So he might appear as a man to others, even though he was not truly a man; although born of a woman, he was merely perceived to be.
If someone were to ask about the purpose of this mission and arrival, they would acknowledge that it wasn't primarily focused on human salvation.
They didn't believe humans had faced any downfall or failure except those tied to the bonds of flesh and body.
To counteract these evils, they claimed a certain device was created for the salvation of souls at that time.
This device had a single wheel with twelve buckets, used to draw up the souls of the living.
When brought into the presence of the sun, these souls would be purified by its rays.
Once purified, they would be transferred to the lower light, namely the moon.
In describing the journey and motion of these two celestial bodies, they imagined all sorts of fanciful stories.
They envisioned the sun and moon as two ships, or celestial boats, sailing across the heavens.
The moon, first loaded with the souls of humans, would transport them to the eastern region.
There, the souls, moved up and down through certain buckets, would load and unload these ships, until they could escape the bodily afflictions that oppressed them.
They asserted that every soul and every living creature drew part of its essence from the good Father.
They added that when the moon delivered the souls it carried to the eras of the Father, they would remain in the column of glory, known as the perfect man.
This man, they explained, is the column of light, filled with pure souls, and this is the reason for the salvation of souls.
Furthermore, they believed that some souls were subject to death, but spoke so foolishly and absurdly about the cause of their destruction!
They imagined a beautiful and adorned virgin, very elegant, who secretly enticed the princes in the firmament, led out and crucified by the living spirit.
In maintaining this delusion, they clearly followed the opinion of the ancient Greek pagans, as revealed by the words of Turbon.
As the anonymous virgin, known as Venus, appeared to men as a beautiful woman, she revealed herself to women as a handsome and desirable young man.
Her beauty and elegant adornment captivated the rulers of the heavens, igniting a passionate desire for her.
As they pursued her, she suddenly vanished from their sight.
In his anger, the great prince summoned clouds to obscure the world.
When deeply troubled, like a man sweating after hard work, this prince sweats from his tribulation.
From pagan writings, it can be inferred that they referred to Jupiter, the ruler of all planets.
However, they also claimed that sometimes the ruler of harvests faced similar misfortunes.
When deceived by that virgin, he becomes so enraged that he brings famine to the earth and afflicts humans with death.
They taught that two worlds existed, both inhabited by humans.
The lower world is visible and subject to the higher one, with all humans below tethered to roots above.
They explained that when the prince of harvests is deceived by the virgin, he begins to sever these roots, leading to pestilence and death.
If the upper parts of the roots are shaken more forcefully, it causes an earthquake, shaking everything.
They believed that death arose from these calamities, making no distinction between the destruction of bodies and souls.
Following these events, Turbo, who aimed to expose and denounce the mythical principles of Manichaean secret philosophy, openly explained to Bishop Archelaus, Marcellus, and others what the Manichaeans taught about the transmigration of souls according to the Epicureans.
Therefore, he presented this.
I'll explain how souls are transferred into different bodies.
In the initial body that the spirit inhabits, only a small portion of the soul is purified.
Then, it's transferred into a dog, a camel, or another animal's body.
If the soul, confined in its current body, has committed murder, it's transferred into elephants, or if it has harvested crops, into walls.
They elaborated on these changes or migrations extensively, covering all kinds of things.
By moving step by step from animals to plants, to vegetables, seeds, and even inanimate objects, they claimed that the human spirit could be infused into and transformed into anything.
As we considered all this, our amazement at the Manichaeans' principles, which were so contradictory, was so great that we could hardly believe that even someone ignorant but of sound mind wouldn't have detected the falsehood.
The most significant of these were their assertions about the names and properties of the soul.
They taught that these attributes and properties belong to the soul: Mind, sense, wisdom, intellect, and thought.
We know these are more contrary and alien to the nature of animals, the properties of plants, or the substances of inanimate things than we understand light to be distant from darkness, heaven from earth, and stars from the elements.
Therefore, since the Manichaeans themselves argued that among these lower-order things there could be no harmony or bond of society, what, I ask, were they reasoning so ineptly and foolishly by claiming that the substances of thinking beings could be transferred into hay, a bean, barley, ears of grain, or vegetables, so that even the reapers themselves would be cut down and harvested?
Similarly, they discussed those who eat bread or kill a chicken, saying: Whoever eats bread must also be eaten like bread.
And if he kills a chicken, he will also become a chicken.
However, they fabricated a belief for the souls of wealthy individuals, claiming that when they leave this physical life, their souls would be cast into the bodies of the poor.
They would have to endure all the hardships of poverty, and after that, they would face eternal punishments.
They didn't just focus on these myths when discussing the transmigration of souls.
They also asserted that the body and matter of all visible and tangible things were the beginning of everything.
Therefore, they claimed it was necessary for someone who plants a Persian tree to live through many ages until that tree perishes.
They said similar things about building houses or washing in water, claiming that whoever built a house would be scattered through all bodies, and if anyone washed in water, they harmed their soul.
This last notion shows that the Manichaeans not only rejected any civil or profane washing with natural water but also the one Christ instituted for human regeneration.
These and other similar beliefs reveal that the Manichaean sect despised and condemned all adornment and refinement in this mortal life.
They were excessively focused on and took pleasure in poverty and destitution, in filth and squalor, which they tried to imitate outwardly under the guise of false piety and religion.
What does this pursuit demonstrate, where they sought to be nourished by the resources of others and supported by others' labors?
It betrays the desires by which they were greatly inflamed, so that those called the elect in this sect were fed with the best foods, obtained through the generosity and offerings of others.
The Manicheans, seeking to advance their own interests and encourage others to fulfill their needs, would often threaten people with the torments of hell and other severe, secret sufferings.
They would say:
"And whoever does not provide food for the elect is subjected to the punishments of hell and is transformed into the bodies of catechumens until they show much mercy."
As a result, the hearers, intimidated by these threats, would offer the best food to the elect. However, the elect would not consume this food until they had performed a superstitious prayer. Bishop Archelaus described this from Turbo's confession in these words:
"And when they want to eat bread, they first pray, saying to the bread: 'I neither harvested you, nor ground you, nor threshed you, nor put you in the oven. Someone else did and brought you to me. I eat you innocently.'"
Then, secretly to himself and without anyone hearing, the Manichean would say this. He would then turn to the one who brought the food and pretend to thank them with the following response: "I prayed for you."
When he considered performing such an unlawful act, the one consuming the bread and food of others would, as a testimony of his superstitious sect, add:
"If anyone reaps, they will be reaped. So if someone puts grain in the mill, they too will be put in the mill. If anyone kneads, they will be kneaded. So if anyone bakes bread, they will be baked."
Thus, they would curse with these and similar other evils those who showed them mercy and from whom they received food or nourishment. This cruel behavior reveals their wickedness and excessive cruelty of nature.
Moreover, all the mythical stories about the essence of multiple worlds, which we briefly mentioned earlier, are further explained by Turbo before Archelaus. They also claim there are other worlds besides the one we see, where the lights of this world rise when they set here.
While coming up with new, almost delirious ideas, they neglected to learn about the structure of the universe and the properties of the earth and air, even though they pretended to be deeply devoted to the studies of mathematics and astrology.
They claimed that the earth was harmed by people walking on it.
Similarly, they believed the air was harmed by those who raised their hands high, thinking the air was the soul of humans, animals, birds, fish, and the paradise of reptiles, which they called the world.
They thought all the desires and other corrupting temptations of human thoughts were like trees in this paradise.
In defending this belief, they sometimes misused words from the First Epistle of John.
They explained these words with such twisted allegories.
Then they believed there was a special tree planted in this paradise from which the knowledge of good could be obtained.
Following previous allegories, they said that Jesus and his knowledge, which is in the world, were represented there, and whoever receives it can distinguish good from evil.
Therefore, Turbo added: Since the world is not God's, but from the Father of matter, it and everything in it must be destroyed.
But if the soul leaves the world without knowing the truth, it is handed over to demons to be tamed in the hellfire.
And after being corrected, it will be transferred into ninety other bodies to be tamed, thus being thrown into that great fire until the end.
After Turbo recounted these and other similar things from his teacher's doctrine with equal revulsion, he tried to explain what kind of judgment or opinion they had about the ancient prophets, or what the Manicheans thought of them.
For they did not believe the prophets ever spoke truthfully, thinking they were taught and deceived by a spirit of impiety and falsehood and by the most wicked prince of darkness.
Therefore, they said their minds were blinded by the father of lies, and they always predicted falsehoods to the ruin of those who believed in these prophecies.
Hence he added: And if anyone follows their words, they will die forever, bound within the mass, because they have not learned the knowledge of the Paraclete.
Manes instructed his chosen followers, no more than seven in number, that after eating, they should pray and pour consecrated oil over their heads, invoking many names to strengthen their faith.
However, what this consecrated oil was, and the names invoked during this ritual, Turbo himself did not explain because he simply did not know.
Manes and his so-called apostle leaders, who often claimed to understand profound mysteries, tried to hide their wickedness behind certain secretive practices.
This was so the shame of their many vile rituals would remain hidden and the disgrace of their demonic beliefs would not be exposed.
It's chilling to recount what they said about Moses, the prophets, and the ancient priests.
They claimed these prophets had spoken with the prince of darkness, arguing that there should be no distinction among Jews, Christians, and pagans, since all worshiped the same God, who they believed was susceptible to passions and desires.
This God, they said, tempts them with desires because he is not the God of truth.
As a result, those who put their hope in this God are bound in chains because they did not trust in the true God.
For he spoke to them according to their desires.
We are ashamed to repeat and record these blasphemies against the almighty and greatest God, as our holy faith is deeply troubled.
Especially since, from Turbo, we learn that they boldly attacked and showed contempt for the great and honorable Lord Sabaoth, whose name is revered by the angels of heaven, feared by the creatures of the earth, and trembled at by the tribes of the underworld.
They claimed that his nature was human and that he was the father of desire.
Thus, the simpler ones worship desire, mistakenly thinking it to be a god.
They claimed that this God, whom they argue is the author of evil and sin, should be subjected to bondage, as He is worshipped by Jews, Christians, and pagans, according to Scythian, the elder prince of this sect.
Such ideas could only be conceived by foolish and wicked people.
However, there are still two main fabrications of the Manichaeans that need to be discussed before we describe their spread.
One pertains to the downfall of Adam and Eve, and the other relates to the end and destruction of this visible world.
Regarding the first, the Manichaeans misused the words of Genesis: "Let us make man in our image and likeness," by adding these other words, "and according to the form we see."
Here, they introduced a prince addressing his fellow princes, as if he were saying:
"Come, give me of the light we have received, and let us make according to our form, by which we are princes, and according to the form we see, which is the first man."
Who cannot understand the kind of nonsense these words contain?
Indeed, these are injurious to the supreme God, who admits no colleague equal to Himself, and who cannot receive from any other outside Himself, neither light, nor attribute, nor anything else.
He has no external and visible form in Himself, according to which He has created creatures; who finally created Adam himself, not according to the form of another first man, but solely in His own image and likeness out of nothing.
Furthermore, contrary to the light of nature, they imagined multiple equal gods bearing a visible and bodily form, who created man, who also made Eve, giving her of their own desire to deceive Adam.
Nothing could be more disgraceful, nor anything more wicked than these accusations, which audaciously depict the creator of the first parents.
Could he be the author of evil and desire, whom the Manichaeans themselves affirmed to neither have a part in the world nor rejoice in the evils that happen in it?
Were they not speaking nonsense?
Scythianus, the founder and leader of this sect, wrote about the end and destruction of the visible world, saying:
When its image becomes clear, the one who bears all will leave the earth behind, and a great fire will be released, consuming everything, where all the souls of sinners will be eternally tormented.
Then, they claimed, all this will occur when Jesus appears in a small ship with the mother of life and twelve helmsmen; with them will be the virgin of light and a certain third elder, whose name Turbo he did not disclose.
But when that great living spirit appears in his ship, there will be walls of great fire, wind, air, and inner water.
Everyone will dwell on the moon until the entire world is consumed by fire.
After this, there will be a restoration of the two lights, and the leaders will dwell below.
With these tales, they wickedly distorted all the prophecies about the end of the world, the last judgment day, and the majesty of the judge, as taught and proclaimed by sacred writings.
Thus, with the religion of Christ shaken, people would completely turn away from the truth and embrace fabulous and insane fictions.
Therefore, Turbo ends his faithful confession and rejection of this devilish doctrine with these words:
This is all the teaching that Manes gave to his three disciples, instructing them to travel to the three regions of the world.
Thus, I believe it is clearly revealed from Turbo's confession, recorded by Archelaus, bishop of Caschar, or as commanded to be recorded, that the leaders and founders of the Manichaeans, in their studies of philosophy and theology, have raved impiously and foolishly.
But in reviewing these fabrications and impieties, we had to undertake a great deal of work.
Archelaus's discussion, even as published through the efforts of Zacagni, is filled with many complex expressions and unusual foreign words from Persian, Syriac, and Mesopotamian languages.
It's riddled with numerous serious errors due to the negligence of various interpreters or the carelessness of scribes.
Nonetheless, Turbon's denunciation contains nothing false or of doubtful credibility, except for some harsh phrases that don't quite fit scholarly use, although they were contemporary with Archelaus.
Back then, heresies that the Church later rejected in councils had not yet arisen, and they established a more perfect and proper way of speaking that the Fathers and theologians followed religiously.
Augustine supports this, as he occasionally references such trivialities and Manichean fabrications in his works.
He, as a holy doctor, not only reveals them as things to be avoided by all but also attacks and overturns them as excessively harmful to the truth of religion.
Therefore, it is not permissible to suspect that Archelaus's work and other disputes related to Diodorus or Tryphon are not genuine, as all the ancients have testified.
We reserve the proof of this, intending to describe a catalog of those who have spoken about Turbon's confession.
Chapter 12
On the Year of Mani's Death.
We'll explore various opinions about this topic and attempt to reconcile some of these viewpoints.
We'll also explain the Beausobrean perspective on the matter we're discussing.
Determining the exact year of Mani's death is challenging without relying on certain conjectures.
Some of these conjectures relate to when this heretic first sought to have two meetings, initially with Bishop Archelaus and then with Presbyter Diodorus, where he debated the principles and doctrines of his false sect.
Other conjectures arise from our discussion in the second chapter of this work, where we talked about the timing when the Manichaean heresy became widely recognized and condemned, particularly when Mani began spreading his corrupt doctrines globally.
In that discussion, we mainly relied on the testimony of the great Pope Leo, who stated that Mani became recognized as someone to be condemned when Probus and Paulinus were consuls, during the eighth persecution against Christians.
We have demonstrated, based on substantial evidence from both ancient and more recent records, chronicles, and catalogs, that they held the consulship after the death of Emperor Aurelian, which we determined to be in the year Two Hundred Seventy-Seven AD, supported by the writers we referenced at the end.
However, whether this year was indeed the year of Mani's death is not indicated anywhere in the Acts of Archelaus.
Additionally, Beausobre criticizes the author of these writings for being careless, as he seems to suggest that the entire Manichaean tragedy occurred under a single king of Persia, which is considered impossible.
Nevertheless, the distinguished Alexander Zacagni, who examined this topic thoroughly, reasoned differently.
He relied primarily on the previously mentioned testimony of Saint Leo the Great, proving that the Manichaean heresy became widely recognized and condemned during the consulship of Probus and Paulinus.
As the learned writer Zacagnius suggests, the debate between Archelaus and Manes, which exposed the errors of Manes, took place between July and December of the year 277 of the Christian era.
It is considered reasonable to interpret the words of Archelaus in chapter twenty-seven of the debate, where he, aiming to criticize Manes before the judges, insists that Manes is not the Paraclete promised by Christ.
Otherwise, Christ would have left his apostles and disciples as orphans without a leader, guide, and teacher, if the Spirit of truth, who was meant to teach everything, arrived nearly three hundred years later and claimed to be the heir of the Church.
Therefore, it is believed that Archelaus did not exaggerate the foolishness of Manes, as Zacagnius suggests, but rather spoke with precise words.
Even though he mentioned the round number of three hundred years, he showed some moderation by using the adverb "nearly" to indicate that the third century of the Church was nearing its end when this significant debate took place.
Archelaus himself did not need an interpreter or excuse in this matter.
In developing his argument, to further press Manes, he points to the signs that should have revealed the coming of the Holy Spirit to the whole world.
Although, either due to a scribe's error or an interpreter's oversight, when dealing with this number of years, he deviates from the original calculation method regarding Christ's promise, which stated that he would send the Paraclete soon after him to wipe away the apostles' and disciples' grief and tears. It is found more than three hundred years later that this one was sent, who bears witness to himself.
But who does not see that either an error has crept in, or Archelaus followed a different method of calculation?
He doesn't mention the Christian era, but rather the years from the rule of Tiberius Caesar to Probus, motivated by the desire to challenge Manes with the promises of Christ the Lord.
From Tiberius's death to Probus's rule, only 239 years passed, as clearly shown in the Petavian tables.
Therefore, I find it hard to believe that Archelaus, caught up in the argument, could have made such a serious mistake, especially since the affairs of the Roman Empire wouldn't have been unknown to him.
By then, the Romans had already dominated the eastern regions and Mesopotamia, as everyone knows.
However, Archelaus didn't discuss the start of the Christian era from the birth of the Savior, but from his death, which took place while Tiberius ruled over the Romans and Jews, clearly showing his intent.
What was he trying to prove in that whole praised chapter, except that Manes falsely claimed the name of the Holy Spirit for himself, and sacrilegiously assumed its power, authority, and gifts?
To strengthen his argument, he first referred to those specific promises of Christ the Lord, where he stated in John that he would soon return to the Father to prepare a place for his disciples and would ask the Father to send another Comforter, who would remain in the Church forever.
He then describes this Comforter as the Spirit of truth, whom the world cannot receive because it neither sees nor knows him; but you will know him, for he will remain with you and be in you.
Finally, to further confirm the truth of these statements, he added: I will not leave you orphans; I will come to you.
It can hardly be doubted that Christ made this promise to his apostles and disciples, whom he addressed.
Indeed, they would receive that Spirit not many days later, so they could be true and sincere witnesses across the earth of his preaching, suffering, death, and resurrection.
But who can ignore that Christ made such promises during the reign of Tiberius, right before his suffering, after celebrating Passover with his disciples, at which point the Jews had already decided to inflict a horrible and bloody death upon him?
For these promises to be fulfilled, not enough time could have passed from Tiberius's reign to that of Emperor Probus, as confirmed by the records of Roman consuls and emperors, showing that 340 years elapsed between their rules.
At this moment, Archelaus argues that Manichaeus should be rejected and expelled as a thief and a robber because he did not present signs and examples of divine promises showing him to be the Paraclete, as prefigured by Jesus.
This omission might unwittingly portray Jesus as a liar, for Jesus said he would send the Paraclete shortly.
Archelaus asserts that such a long delay would have rendered the divine promises utterly void.
He introduces those whom Christ the Lord will judge on the last day, as if they were speaking on stage, referring to all who have passed from this life from Tiberius's rule to that of Probus, and thus addresses Manes, reasoning.
What will those who have already died from that time until now say to Jesus on the day of judgment?
Will they not argue this: Do not torment us if we did not do your works; for why, when you promised under Tiberius Caesar to send the Paraclete who would convict us of sin and righteousness, did you only send him under Probus?
You left us as orphans when you yourself said, I will not leave you as orphans, when you said you would soon go and send the Paraclete.
Therefore, who would deny that the timing of this debate was defined by Archelaus?
If it's asserted that Probus was in power at that time, the encounter with Manichaeus should be placed in 277 A.
D.
according to Petavius' calculations, or in 282 if we follow the reasoning of the distinguished Pagius.
Now, I understand that everything written so far doesn't completely absolve Archelaus from error and negligence, even though he indicated that his discussions with Manes took place while Probus was ruling the Roman Empire.
Furthermore, Probus reigned for six years, beginning in 277 and continuing until 282, and Pagius assigns the discussions and the execution of the Manichaean to this time, although Beausobre places it earlier, thinking it happened in the first year of his reign.
However, settling this controversy isn't something we can do right now.
Nevertheless, we believe the phrase found in the Acts of Archelaus, "after three hundred and more years he sent this," slipped into Archelaus' discourse due to a translator's error or a copyist's mistake, and it should actually read: "after two hundred and more years."
Indeed, Tiberius died in the year 37, and from his death to the reign of Probus, 239 years passed.
We believe we've discussed this matter sufficiently.
Especially since the earlier words of Archelaus support our conjecture, clearly indicating that not yet three full centuries had passed.
Thus, we must either say that Archelaus was inconsistent in the same section of the discussion, which is unlikely, or attribute the anachronism error to the translator or copyists.
Now, we must move on to other matters to explore the rest that pertains to the destruction of Manes.
First, we must consult the list and chronology of the kings of Persia to determine whether all the events we have written about concerning the Manichean affair occurred under one and the same king.
Beausobre claims that Archelaus, or the author of the disputation attributed to Archelaus, indicated this, though he criticizes him in a harsh and judgmental tone as being careless.
As for the catalog of Persian kings during the medieval period, it is certain that after the extinction of the Parthian royal lineage and the abolition of their empire in the year 226 AD, the Persians came under the rule of Artaxares; or as Petavius calls him, Artaxerxes.
After reigning for fifteen years, he was succeeded by the first Sapores of that name, who enjoyed a longer rule and inflicted great losses on the Romans, as Agathias affirms.
Beausobre does not dispute these facts, as he follows the critical analysis of the distinguished Pagi and extends Sapores' reign until the year 271 or the beginning of the following year, 272.
However, Beausobre, in developing his own novel system for the history of Manichaeism, not only adheres to the Chronicle of Edessa but also convinces himself that Mani was born in the year 240.
Moreover, based on the silence of Eastern writers, he denies that Mani was ever subjected to servitude.
Instead, he imagines that Mani was of Magian descent and had a father who was a Magian priest, who at some point attained the rank of bishop and was called Manes.
In short, he fabricates a long period of activity for Mani, asserting that he was well-versed in Greek literature and dedicated himself to mathematics, music, astronomy, geography, astrology, medicine, and painting.
Beausobre also claims that Mani excelled in the art of painting as well as in understanding and interpreting the sacred scriptures.
Ultimately, he asserts that Mani fell into heresy.
The person was excommunicated from the Church, yet he found favor with King Sapor of Persia and stayed among the courtiers.
He was tasked with accompanying the king during battles against the Romans, as it was believed he could heal himself and the soldiers.
It's not recorded exactly when he was appointed as the chief physician by Sapor, but it's likely it happened when Sapor was leading his armies against the Romans.
This is particularly noted during the reign of Emperor Valerian, according to Roman historical records.
Valerian, betrayed by the commander Macrianus, faced severe consequences for the unjust killing of Christians, seen as divine retribution.
He was captured by King Sapor and taken to Persia, where he was mocked for a long time and eventually flayed by the king's order as punishment for his crimes.
Since these battles occurred after the year 254, and Valerian died in the seventh year of his reign, it's hard to believe that Manes had the knowledge or medical skill to be highly regarded by Sapor.
Only someone naive would believe such a thing.
According to Beausobre, Manes was born in 241.
Sapor began defeating the Romans in 245, according to Baronius; Valerian's capture and betrayal happened around 256, and his death in 260.
Therefore, when Valerian faced the consequences of his actions, Manes was barely nineteen years old.
When Sapor was leading his forces against the Romans, Manes could still have been very young, with Valerian's betrayal and capture likely occurring when Manes was about fifteen or sixteen.
This clearly shows that Manes couldn't have been the best and noblest physician at Sapor's court at that time.
The stories Beausobre shares about the order or priesthood of Manes, his interpretation of sacred Scriptures, and how he fell into heresy and was cut off from Catholic communion, seem quite fantastical.
He found refuge in the court of Shapur by securing support mentioned earlier by the same author.
Equally fantastical are the tales of his ministries and parish duties, as well as the debates he supposedly held against Jews, magicians, and pagans in defense of Catholicism before being expelled from the Church, which our critic invents without a credible source.
For what reason?
When Shapur the First, the first Persian king of this name, died, Manes was only about 19 or 20 years old, as we know.
So, how can we believe he was already initiated into the priesthood against sacred canons, then deprived of communion due to heresy, and expelled from the Church before Shapur's death, especially when the king was leading armies against the Romans with great fortune and forces?
No sensible person who doesn't believe in dreams could be convinced of this.
In fact, Beausobre himself suggests several years passed between Manes' fall into heresy and Shapur's death.
Therefore, he should have admitted that even Manes' ordination was premature.
But Beausobre, who prides himself on being a diligent critic, overlooked this inconsistency, thinking he could weaken and overthrow the testimonies of ancient Greek and Latin Church Fathers.
For this reason, indulging in novelties, he incorporated many paradoxes and fables into his work, praising the testimonies of Persian and Assyrian writers who flourished long after Manes' time.
He then describes the characteristics, minds, interests, and ways of acting of the Persian kings to showcase his abundance of learning.
In a particular digression, he recalls the ancient religion of that people and credits King Sapor of Persia for reviving this long-neglected faith.
He praises the king for his wisdom, courage, and justice.
He then explains the etymology of the word magi, a title used by the priests and philosophers of Persia.
He also elaborates on Zoroaster's philosophy, studies, theology, religion, and worship.
Ultimately, he includes so much nonsense, silliness, and frivolous interpretations that we think it would be inappropriate for a sensible and religious person discussing Christian matters to repeat them.
Therefore, we have decided to leave these and similar topics unmentioned.
Now, we need to explore under which Persian king Manes faced the consequences for his actions.
This task wouldn't require much effort if not for Beausobre, who is inconsistent in his statements.
First, let's recall what we previously mentioned about the year of King Sapor's death.
After his son Hormisdas succeeded him, as confirmed by Persian annals and conceded by Beausobre, it's established that he ruled for only two years.
His successor was Varanes the First, who passed away just after completing the third year of his reign, leaving Varanes the Second as the next king.
However, there's disagreement about which year of Christ marks the beginning of Varanes the Second's reign, with Petavius, Pagius, and others differing from Beausobre.
They argue it should start in the year 276.
In contrast, Beausobre, based on various conjectures, claims it should begin the following year, 277.
Thus, according to Beausobre, Manes's punishment occurred not under Varanes the Second, but under Varanes the First.
For the sake of his argument, we must pay close attention.
First, following Pagi, he assumes as a certainty that Sapores took control of the Persian kingdom in the year 241 and held power until 272.
As for his son and successor, Hormisdas, Beausobre assigns him not a full two years of rule but only one year and ten days; or possibly ten months.
He also believed that during the reign of this king, Mani, who had first been exiled from Persia by Sapores, returned to Persia and presented the new king with a book of revelations adorned with various highly detailed paintings.
Furthermore, Beausobre is convinced; based on a testimony from Photius; that this book was none other than the Gospel of Mani, which contained a false history of Jesus Christ.
He laments that copies of this work have completely perished due to the hostility of the times and the hatred of men, insisting that it contained the product of one of the wisest minds of that era, who dedicated himself to the study of Eastern philosophy.
Finally, he denounces as an intolerable abuse the religious policies of both church leaders and secular rulers, by which such harmful books; designed to corrupt the faith, piety, and morals of the people; were ordered to be burned and destroyed by flames.
However, he admits that he does not know whether any fragments of this work remain among the writings of ancient Eastern, Arabic, or Persian scholars.
But who cannot see that Beausobre, here and in many other places, seeks to attack and slander the Church's long-standing practice, which has been preserved even to this day?
We will reserve our response to such false accusations for when we discuss the decrees of Pope Leo and other pontiffs against Manichaean books.
Nor do we need to dwell on the additional matters he introduces, where he discusses Persian rituals and ceremonies related to the wearing of a belt, which he claim; based on the author Hyda; was included among the moral precepts of Zoroaster.
Therefore, it concludes that the Persians attribute the same power to their belt as the Roman Catholics claim for the sign of the cross and holy water, specifically for expelling demons and freeing people from their influence.
Thus, it suggests that both rituals of the Persians, Muslims, and Christians are steeped in superstition.
It mentions how King Hormizd of the Persians graciously accepted the praised Gospel of Mani and became a Manichaean.
Since many soon followed the king's example, he quickly established his name and authority among the Persians.
However, it notes that the king's protection did not help Mani much in living more safely and securely.
This is because the Christians and the magi, realizing he opposed their religions, immediately became hostile to him.
To escape their wrath, King Hormizd provided him with protection and refuge in an impregnable fortress, allowing him to avoid the death that the fury and assault of so many enemies would have undoubtedly brought him.
Hormizd eventually died, having ruled for barely two years, according to the common opinion of writers, which even Beausobre did not dare to contradict.
They refer to his death as occurring in the year 273 or 274, affirming he was succeeded by Varanes the First, his son.
Following his father's example, Varanes initially provided Mani with protection and refuge at the start of his reign.
But then, as the persecution by the pagans, magi, and Jews intensified against him, and he was defeated in a public debate, he was eventually executed as the author of heresies.
However, Beausobre does not specify the form of punishment the king's decree subjected him to.
He claims that Mani faced a capital punishment similar to that of a Sadducee, citing various opinions, such as Hyde's, who claims he was crucified at the city gate, or Abbot Renaudot's, who asserts that his skin was removed while he was alive, filled with straw, and hung up to terrify others.
In his testimony, he references a book by an unknown author detailing the history of the Persians, or by Abulpharagius, who claims that Mani's skin was removed after his death.
Valerian provided a more believable example by dying a natural death, and Shapur ordered his skin to be removed to show the Romans, intending to curb the arrogance of this proud nation.
He also mentioned a third viewpoint, suggesting that Mani was killed, hung up, and split into two parts, one placed at one city gate and the other at another.
This resulted in these areas being referred to as Upper Mani and Lower Mani.
But who would believe all this happened during the reign of Varanes the First?
According to the most reliable writers, it is known that he died in the year 276.
Thus, it was impossible for Aurelius Probus Augustus and Aruntius Paulinus, consuls, to learn of his heresy to condemn it, nor could he debate with Bishop Archelaus and Presbyter Diorides, or with magi, pagans, Jews, as Beausobre suggests, since he was no longer alive due to the execution he faced by the king's decree the previous year.
Therefore, to avoid such ambiguities and pitfalls, based on the testimonies of the Greek and Latin Fathers, we extend the death of Mani to the year 277, during the rule of Varanes the Second over the Persians.
We believe Beausobre's statements should be taken with caution, as he seemed intent on creating a misleading display of doubtful, humorous, and disorganized knowledge to deceive unsuspecting readers; leading the sincere and consistent tradition of the Catholic Church astray with certain fictional traditions from unknown and impure sources, as we will demonstrate more clearly in the next chapter.
Chapter Thirteen
Are the Acts of Archelaus, including the debates against Manes held under his name, truly authentic?
We examine Beausobre's viewpoint and refute his weak arguments.
It would seem remiss of me, after thoroughly exploring the origins, heresy, errors, crimes, and punishment of Manes, not to address the debate and Acts attributed to Archelaus, bishop of Caschar.
This work was published in a complete form by the Roman Sacred Congregation for the Propagation of the Faith in 1698, and it was meticulously curated by the esteemed Laurentius Alexander Zacagnius, the prefect of the Vatican Library, in his collection of ancient monuments from the Greek and Latin Church.
This work was widely accepted by scholars until Beausobre's "History of the Manicheans" was published, which many are aware of.
Since 1740, when Beausobre's work was printed in Amsterdam, doubts about the authenticity of the History of Archelaus and the Acts have emerged, even among knowledgeable Catholics.
On one hand, they consider ancient traditions, while on the other, they weigh Beausobre's arguments aimed at undermining their credibility and authority.
This has led many to believe that either the history is entirely fictional or it contains several inconsistencies with the actual events, the context of the times, civil moderation, and Church matters.
In my efforts to resolve or at least reconcile these issues, the first thing I noted was the silence of Eusebius of Caesarea and other writers of that era.
Beausobre heavily relies on this silence, using it as negative evidence to claim that the Acts of Archelaus and the associated debates are mere fabrications and myths.
I believe that the silence of Eusebius and other writers from that era should not and cannot unsettle any learned person.
Why?
The events, debates, and exile of the Manichaeans occurred toward the end of the third century of the Church.
The Acts of Archelaus and the two subsequent debates were written in Persian and Syrian.
It's not surprising, then, that such records didn't reach Eusebius, who composed his Church History after the first celebrated Council of Nicaea.
He only knew of the Manichaean heresy, which he mentioned in his Chronicle for the year 277.
If the silence of writers from that era could support Beausobre's argument, he should have introduced Syrian and Persian writers who, in describing the state of their Church and Manichaean matters, would deny or completely overlook this History of Archelaus and the debates.
But where are they?
Few writers from that age could achieve this.
If we look at the Greeks, who were unaware of Syrian and Persian affairs, we only find Anatolius of Laodicea, who thrived under Probus, or the presbyter Pierius of Alexandria under Carus and Diocletian, or Methodius, martyred under that same Diocletian, since he wrote against Porphyry and Origen, Arnobius the rhetorician, and his student Lactantius.
It's evident to anyone that all these figures, due to the great distance and lack of interaction with the Persians and Syrians, must have been unaware of the Manichaean issues.
It shouldn't be surprising, then, if we lack writers from that era who reviewed the Acts and debates of Archelaus.
Yet, it is well established that soon after the first Council of Nicaea, the Manichaean issues became known to the Greeks.
In the fourth century, specifically in the year 348, Cyril of Jerusalem, a bishop, in his sixth catechesis, took the opportunity not only to criticize the heresy of Scythianus, Terebinthus, and Mani, exposing their errors, but also to mention Archelaus, the bishop of Mesopotamia.
Archelaus confronted Mani as he was escaping from prison and, by setting up a Greek audience, even refuted him with philosophers as judges.
This was so that if Christians judged, they wouldn't seem biased.
Now, who would deny that these words indicate the disputes and Acts of Archelaus with Mani?
But please tell, from which sources could Cyril have drawn this, unless from the well-known tradition of Macarius and Maximus, bishops of that church, a tradition that had already gained credibility and authority; or from some Persian or Syrian writing he had at hand.
It should not be considered that Cyril dreamed this up or deliberately fabricated it for those who were to be enlightened by sacred baptism.
Otherwise, all the Fathers who flourished in his time and after him would have noted his error and criticized his writings, claiming that the disputation of Archelaus with Mani was entirely fictitious.
Meanwhile, one important point should not be overlooked, which can be very valuable in refuting various arguments by Beausobre.
Cyril, for instance, called Archelaus the bishop of Mesopotamia.
However, he did not specify which city he was the bishop of.
This caution was not followed by Epiphanius, who, in Heresy 66, called Archelaus the bishop of Caschar, and he agreed with Cyril in other respects, though he provided a more extensive account of these Manichaean matters.
Beausobre then argues that the original manuscript of this work was never written in the Syrian language, and that it first appeared through Greek deceit.
Therefore, he concludes that it is nothing but a pure fabrication.
He similarly criticizes Laurence Zacagni for writing that Epiphanius consulted Greek copies.
But he unjustly attacks this distinguished man.
He demonstrates this not only through Jerome's testimony but also by presenting compelling conjectures.
One such conjecture is from Archelaus, who, in discussing the sun's path, mentions in chapter thirty-two that it is referred to as a sphere by the Greeks.
Therefore, the original document likely did not first appear in Greek; instead, it was translated by someone who rendered the Acts from Syriac into Greek, allowing all the faithful worldwide to have complete knowledge of them in a more widely understood language.
It's evident that the Greek version we're discussing predates Epiphanius, who includes significant excerpts from it in Greek in the context of the Manichaean heresy.
It cannot be claimed, as Laurence Alexander Zacagni suggests, that Epiphanius translated these from a Syriac copy into Greek, since everything he quotes from the Acts of the debate between Archelaus and Manes is found verbatim in the Latin version we publish.
It is irrelevant that among Latin writers, the first to review such Acts was St.
Jerome, who was active around the year 392 AD.
Instead, Philastrius, Bishop of Brescia, should have mentioned them, as he had already written a catalog of heresies much earlier, around the year 370, as noted by Beausobre, but more precisely by Cave in 380.
The evaluation of Philastrius's study and writings by scholars like Beausobre and William Cave indicates a less precise judgment.
For nearly all 101 works of Greek writers were unknown to Philastrius, and his compilation clearly shows a lack of accuracy.
Beausobre frequently criticizes Philastrius for ignorance and negligence, as those familiar with his History of the Manichaeans are well aware.
Therefore, if even Beausobre believed Philastrius was not trustworthy and criticized him for it, why would he think Philastrius's silence supports his argument?
Such conjecture and reasoning are baseless, and should be dismissed.
As for the translator, both Beausobre and Zacagni discuss the topic, but they do not share the same opinion.
Zacagnius, in an effort to reconcile the testimonies of Saint Jerome, Epiphanius, and Heraclian of Chalcedon, references the authority of Photius.
In codex 87 of Heraclian, Photius cites certain excerpts and adds these words, which we find in chapter 39 of these Acts, suggesting that the same acts were recorded by Hegemonius.
Consequently, Zacagnius considers it likely that Archelaus himself later added some details to his earlier debate, believing that Epiphanius and Jerome could be reconciled with Heraclian.
This could be true if we assume that Archelaus first published everything he presented against Manes before selected judges in the Syrian language.
Additionally, Hegemonius not only organized what Archelaus had already published into a better order but also enhanced it with a preface, an epilogue, and some other additions, ensuring that the Acts of this renowned debate would be passed down to future generations in perfect form.
Beausobre finds Zacagnius's arguments and conjectures quite plausible, yet he argues they cannot be conclusively proven.
The expressions used by Archelaus to describe the person of Christ and the mystery of the incarnation suggest they were written by someone who lived and wrote after the Council of Nicaea, around the year 330.
However, it has already been noted that Beausobre is inconsistent in his own work.
In chapter 9, he objected to Archelaus by arguing that the debate we are discussing is filled with expressions that clearly favor the heresies of the Arians, Nestorians, and Eutychians.
Therefore, to avoid complications, we were unable to clear Archelaus himself of such negative notes in chapter 9 of this work.
Ultimately, the inexperienced critic concludes that, since none of the ancient Syrian authors he encountered mentioned either Archelaus or his debate, he is compelled to admit that either the history was fabricated by Hegemonius or that Hegemonius received it from someone in Mesopotamia, possibly Turbon, who had seen a Manichaean and adopted the name of this sect, embellishing it with many details he invented.
He concludes that his judgment is derived from a certain modern scholar, who believed that the work should not be attributed to Archelaus.
Instead, Hegemonius added or removed parts as he saw fit.
He admits that he cannot change his opinion until clearer evidence is presented to him.
But did Beausobre really lack the more common belief, when testimonies from praised writers, along with others from later centuries, agree?
When Photius, Peter the Sicilian, and other discerning critics approved of the praised Acts and debates of Archelaus, it doesn't take many words to explain; it's better to have addressed similar negative arguments in earlier discussions, and Beausobre himself, through his imagination, poses and resolves questions.
One such question he raised is whether the debate with Caschara truly existed or should be considered fictional.
He mentions the debate with Caschara because he cannot firmly assert or deny that Manes once debated with an orthodox bishop about his errors or had meetings.
He says he cannot inform readers more certainly about this matter since there are various examples from ancient writers who invented fictitious debates not only between heretics and orthodox bishops but also claimed they were held with apostles and heretics.
This text provides an example from the books of the Recognitions, circulated under the name of Clement.
It tells the story of Saint Peter debating with Simon the Magician.
William Cave believes this imaginative story was brought from Syria or Mesopotamia by Bardesanes, who was skilled in Greek eloquence.
But which of the learned has not read William Cave's Literary History themselves?
He certainly did not claim that the story was purely fanciful.
He acknowledged it as a very ancient work, also praised by Origen.
While he did not attribute it to Clement, he listed it among his supposed works.
This was not because the content was filled with fables, but because the name of Clement may have been attributed to other authors.
Therefore, Beausobre wrongly used these examples and Cave's testimonies to claim that the acts and debates of Archelaus were completely fabricated.
Nor did Beausobre find it better to gradually undermine the credibility of these Acts with similar trivialities.
Instead, he aimed to use more serious and obvious arguments of falsehood concerning the location described as the place of the debate.
Firstly, it is said the debate was held publicly in a city of Mesopotamia by Manes and Archelaus.
Secondly, that city was reported to have been under Roman control.
Thirdly, the city was known as Caschara or Carchara.
Therefore, the praised Acts suggest these three characteristics align with the debate of Archelaus.
If no city matches these characteristics, it must be admitted that the debate is entirely fictitious, as the author invented a setting that cannot be found.
It's noted that Zacagni conducted a more thorough investigation into this city of Mesopotamia.
He eventually convinced himself that the three characteristics might correspond to the famous city of Carrhae, which later became more renowned due to Crassus's defeat, as noted by Ammianus Marcellinus.
Indeed, various coins reveal this city was a Roman colony, as can be seen in the works of Spanheim, Celarius, and others.
Zacagnio laid the groundwork for this theory with a Latin version of certain writings known as Charra.
In his research on ancient histories, he found no Roman-controlled city in Mesopotamia named Caschar or Carcar.
Instead, similar names were linked to a city in Arabia Felix, as noted by the Anonymous of Ravenna, a geographical writer, and Ammianus Marcellinus, who mentioned another place called Carcha.
However, Zacagnius points out that Archelaus was not the bishop of either of these locations.
The debate he had with Manes occurred in a Roman-controlled Mesopotamian city, where Archelaus was the bishop, as clearly stated by Epiphanius and in the Acts of the debate.
The Charcha mentioned by Marcellinus was outside Mesopotamia, across the Tigris in Persian territory.
Similarly, the city of Charchae in Arabia, mentioned by the Anonymous of Ravenna, couldn't have had Archelaus as its bishop, since all ancient writers describe him as a bishop of Mesopotamia, not Arabia.
Zacagnius's view was already dismissed and refuted by Asseman, the esteemed chief librarian of the Vatican Library.
Beausobre quotes Asseman, saying: "It is likely a scribal error in that one part of the Acts, where it should read Carrha instead of Caschar or Carcar at the beginning of the Acts, and among noted writers like Epiphanius, Socrates, Photius, who certainly would never have called Carrha, or Haran, the renowned city of Mesopotamia, Carcar or Caschar."
Despite Asseman's otherwise credible opinion, it was challenged by the scholar Le Quien in his work "Christian East."
In the second volume, discussing the Churches of the Chaldeans, he describes the city of Caschar on the borders of Mesopotamia, which is very different from another city built near Cosdresna.
The former city, once dedicated to idol worship, was said to have embraced the name of Christ through the teachings of Saint Thaddeus.
Archelaus was appointed as bishop during the reign of Emperor Probus, aligning with the accounts of Epiphanius, Jerome, and Photius, supported by a wide array of ancient writers.
So, even if Zacagni's theory, which Beausobre aimed to dispute, fell apart due to scribal errors, it doesn't imply that the history in question was fictional, nor that the names of Archelaus or the bishopric mentioned were fictional.
However, other theories proposed by Beausobre completely fall apart.
He claims that this bishop sought to defend the Catholic faith in front of pagan judges, with the audience ready to stone Manes for blasphemy if Archelaus agreed.
But this is an unfounded theory.
Beausobre should have considered the words of Cyril of Jerusalem: that even some pagan judges were invited to avoid the appearance of biased Christian judgment.
Thus, those philosophers, called as witnesses, lacked power and authority, especially under Roman rule.
No one has denied that pagan philosophers were admitted to the Council of Nicaea to listen and even debate.
So why is it surprising if Bishop Archelaus held a meeting with a heretical figure, who followed the false principles of Zoroastrian philosophy and magic, even allowing pagan philosophers whom he convinced to reject the fanciful and deceptive arguments of Manes?
Beausobre further notes that the Acts describe Archelaus, driven by indignation against Manes, accusing him of being merely a priest of Mithras, the Sun, worshipping false gods.
Beausobre suggests that such a rebuke wouldn't have been accepted by the pagan populace, considering the city was filled with idols.
The applause would have been warmly welcomed by the Christian people, who were under the rule of a Christian emperor.
If this had occurred, the entire city might have erupted in outrage against the bishop, even threatening him with harm.
To demonstrate the lack of credibility, it points to the actions of Julian the Apostate, who, during his ill-fated Persian expedition, chose not to proceed to the city of Edessa because many Christians resided there.
Instead, he diverted his journey to Carrhae to offer sacrifices to the gods.
Thus, when the citizens of this city, who were deeply devoted to the worship of false gods, heard the news of Julian's death, they stoned the unfortunate messenger who brought the news.
Beausobre's method of discussion and his expertise could easily convince those not well-versed in ecclesiastical history.
However, those informed by Eusebius of Caesarea and other trustworthy writers about the Christian affairs in the Churches of Mesopotamia, Persia, Egypt, Phoenicia, and Phrygia, from 277 to 293, know that these affairs changed significantly; so much so that those which once thrived were utterly devastated during the intense persecution under Diocletian.
But who could be unaware that before such harsh and severe persecution was unleashed against Christians, our people were already held in high esteem by the pagan rulers?
So much so that they were entrusted with governing provinces and given the authority to administer justice.
The rulers allowed their wives, ministers, and entire households not only to believe in our Lord Jesus Christ but also to practice their faith with full confidence and freedom; they were seen as loyal and trustworthy, assured that they harbored no treachery for the sake of Christ.
Christians enjoyed such great tranquility and privileges under Marcus Aurelius Probus, who was elevated to the empire by military consensus in the year of Christ 276 or 277, as recounted by Vopiscus, Victor, Eutropius, Idatius in the Chronicles, Zosimus, and also by Petavius.
It's not surprising, then, if what Archelaus explained in the praised Acts could be verified.
Especially since, as we've already seen, Marcellus, or Marcellinus, who oversaw the province of Mesopotamia with imperial authority, was eager for the truth of the faith and its spread.
He could have used military force against those who rebelled against Bishop Archelaus.
The fact that Christians at that time were appointed by emperors as administrators of provinces, chamberlains, accountants, and other roles of honor and authority, is inferred from the decree of Diocletian issued in 303 in Nicomedia, which declared that Christians would be deprived of all honor and dignity.
This would have been absurd if Christians hadn't previously enjoyed these honors and dignities.
Therefore, Beausobre shouldn't have attempted to mislead people against a truth clearer than daylight by twisting timelines and persuading his readers to be deceived by his statements.
It's a myth that the Eastern Churches were always oppressed under pagan emperors and that Christians faced the same conditions under Marcus Aurelius Probus as they did later under Diocletian, Shapur, and Julian the Apostate.
We could refute this idea with many other serious arguments if it weren't already known that there's no basis for what is objected from Julian the Apostate, who, after renouncing the Catholic faith, reopened the temples of idols.
But how could he have reopened them if they hadn't already been closed to protect and propagate the Catholic religion?
After these matters, Beausobre diligently investigated whether Carchar, or Caschar, was a city located in Mesopotamia, Assyria, Chaldea, or within the borders of Persia, not far from Seleucia, and whether it could have been under Roman rule during the reign of Probus.
He gathered various conjectures and arguments from different writers in his typical way of discussing.
By sometimes referring to Assemani and at other times to both ancient and more recent geographers, he provided such a wealth of information that he seemed to have thoroughly explained this debate.
He demonstrated that it could not have been Cascar or Carchar, nor could it have been any city, fortress, or town under Roman control.
When he mentions the distinguished Assemani, it's worth noting what this praised author described in his Oriental Library: In the year 277 AD, Archelaus restrained the heresiarch Manes, who was emerging from the Persian borders, with a learned argument.
Therefore, if from the ancient monuments presented by Assemani, when Manes came to debate with Archelaus, he had indeed emerged from the Persian borders, then the episcopal Church was not in Persia but in another nearby province.
Assemani adds: Saint Jerome in Catalog Chapter seventy-two calls him the Bishop of Mesopotamia.
Saint Epiphanius in Heresy sixty-six, Socrates in Book one of Ecclesiastical History Chapter twenty-two, and Photius in the book against the Manichaeans, refer to it as Cascar or Carchar, without declension, or in plural or singular as Caschara and Carchara, which is a city located on the borders of Mesopotamia.
Older Syrians prefer Cascar, while more recent ones call it Gargar, or Carcar, or Carcha.
However, I must mention that this very learned man has also discussed this city elsewhere and, after describing a catalog of the bishops of that city following our Mare Archelaus, placed and affirmed that this city, built on the Persian borders, belongs to the province of the Chaldeans.
But what if the same division of provinces was not always maintained by ancient writers and geographers due to the changes of wars and the shifts of the Roman Empire?
At the time, the Romans were in control of Mesopotamia, and they could have easily placed Carchara, or Caschara, under the authority of the province's governor or proconsul.
Later writers, when discussing this, focused more on the rights of the monarchy than on the geographic location, claiming it was within Mesopotamia's borders.
The history of the Roman Empire itself provides the most substantial evidence, revealing that from the year 235 AD to 276 AD, the Persians and neighboring peoples suffered from major war devastations.
We learn that Gordian, in the fifth year of his reign, led a large force primarily against the Persians, recapturing Carrhae, Nisibis, and other towns, driving them back into their territory.
It's known that Gordian's successor made peace with Shapur the First, the king of the Persians, before returning to Rome.
However, the same eastern borders were invaded again, Antioch was plundered, and various Roman territories were ravaged, until Odeactus, a commander of the Palmyrenes and husband to Zenobia, forcefully suppressed them.
He preserved the Roman state while assuming the royal title himself.
After capturing Nisibis and Carrhae, reclaiming Mesopotamia, driving away the Persian king, and killing many, he sent the captured satraps and celebrated a triumph as if he had achieved the victory himself.
Trebellius recorded this victory during the consulship of Gallienus and Saturninus, in the year 264 AD.
From this year until the reign of Marcus Aurelius Probus in 276 AD, no notable changes were reported in the affairs of the Persians and Mesopotamia in the East.
Therefore, since we can reasonably conclude that the Romans maintained the same rationale and jurisdiction, it's not surprising that Archelaus, the author of the discussion, as suggested by Assemanus or Hegemonius, described the entire series of Acts, attributing that city in Mesopotamia and stating it was within its boundaries, which was later assigned to Chaldea in subsequent provincial divisions.
The term "province" was commonly used by the ancients to refer to regions conquered outside of Italy through war. Some were consular, governed by proconsuls, while others were praetorial, governed by praetors, as well established by ancient writers.
When this occurred, they were said to be organized as a province.
Nor should anyone object regarding Carrhae and Nisibis, as there is explicit mention of these cities being under Roman rule; I say this should not be objected to me.
Writers also mention other towns conquered under Roman rule due to Persian defeats, though their names weren't described at all.
Therefore, it's plausible that with that general expression, other towns received from the Persians by Gordian, like Cascharam or Carcaram, which were closer to the Persian borders, were also included.
However, I consider it unnecessary to dwell longer on these matters.
Especially since the arguments presented last by Beausobre are entirely negative; they rely on the silence of Syrian writers, whose purpose was not to mention Archelaus and his well-known discussion.
Indeed, these arguments can be thoroughly refuted with positive testimonies from all the Greek Church Fathers of any age who flourished after Manes and Archelaus.