Homily on the Prologue of the Gospel According to John
by John Scotus
Homily of John Scotus, Translator of the Hierarchy of Dionysius.
The voice of the spiritual eagle reaches the ears of the Church.
The outer sense hears the fleeting sound, while the inner mind grasps the enduring understanding.
The voice of this high-soaring bird does not travel through the physical air, ether, or the entire visible world.
Instead, it transcends all contemplation, beyond all things that exist and do not exist, with the swift wings of deep theology and the clear, exalted vision of supreme contemplation.
I speak of things that are, which do not completely escape human or angelic perception, as they are after God and do not exceed the number of things created by the one cause of all; and of things that are not, which indeed elude all powers of understanding.
Thus, the blessed theologian John soars not only above what can be understood and spoken, but is also carried beyond what surpasses all understanding and expression.
With an ineffable flight of mind, he is exalted into the secrets of the one principle of all, discerning purely the incomprehensible unity of that principle and the Word, that is, the Father and the Son, as well as their distinct and super-substantial essence.
He begins his Gospel, saying:
In the beginning was the Word.
O blessed John, you are rightly called John.
The Hebrew name John means in Greek "hoi echarisato." and in Latin, "to whom it is given." To which of the theologians has it been given, what has been given to you, namely, to penetrate the hidden mysteries of the supreme good and to communicate to human minds and senses what has been revealed and declared to you?
Tell me, I ask, to whom has such a great grace been given? Perhaps someone might say: to the highest of the apostles, Peter, who responded to the Lord's question about who he thought he was: You are the Christ, the Son of the living God. But it is not without reason, I think, that someone might say Peter spoke such things more in the manner of faith and action than of knowledge and contemplation, for Peter is placed in the form of action and faith, while John embodies the type of contemplation and knowledge.
One reclined on the Lord's chest, symbolizing contemplation, while the other often stumbled, representing anxious action.
Following divine commandments, before they become habitual, sometimes perceives the pure forms of virtues, but other times its judgment is clouded by carnal thoughts.
However, the clarity of inner contemplation, once it gazes upon the face of truth, is never turned back, mistaken, or hidden by darkness.
Yet both run to the tomb.
The tomb of Christ represents divine Scripture, where the mysteries of His divinity and humanity are securely guarded.
But John runs faster than Peter.
The power of purified contemplation penetrates the secrets of divine works more sharply and swiftly than the power of action that is still being purified.
Nonetheless, Peter enters the tomb first, followed by John, and just as both run, both enter.
Peter symbolizes faith, while John signifies understanding.
As it is written: Unless you believe, you will not understand, faith necessarily precedes in the tomb of holy Scripture, then understanding follows, gaining access through faith.
Therefore, Peter recognized Christ as God and man made in time, declaring: You are the Christ, the Son of the living God.
He reached a great height.
But higher still is he who understood Christ as God from God, born before all time, saying: In the beginning was the Word.
Let no one think we prefer John over Peter.
Who would do such a thing?
Who would place anyone higher among the apostles than he who is called their summit?
We do not prefer John over Peter but compare contemplation with action, perfectly purified to the still purifying soul, ascending in virtue to an unchangeable habit through virtue already attained.
For we are not considering the dignity of apostolic persons but investigating the beautiful differences of divine mysteries.
Peter, representing the action of virtues, sees the Son of God, miraculously and ineffably manifest in the flesh, through faith and action.
John, representing the highest contemplation of truth, marvels at the Word of God, absolute and infinite, in its beginning, that is, in its Father.
Through divine revelation, Peter sees the eternal and the temporal united in Christ.
John introduces only the eternal to the knowledge of faithful souls.
Therefore, the spiritual creature, John the theologian, surpasses all visible and invisible creation, transcends all understanding, and enters into God, who deifies.
O blessed Paul, you were caught up, as you assert, into the third heaven, but you were not taken beyond every heaven.
You were caught up into paradise, but you were not taken above all paradise.
John transcends every created heaven and paradise, that is, every human and angelic nature.
In the third heaven, O vessel of election and teacher of the Gentiles, you heard inexpressible words, which it is not lawful for a man to speak.
John, inspector of intimate truth, in the paradise of paradises, beyond every heaven, that is, in the cause of all, heard the one Word, through which all things were made, and desired to speak that Word, and to preach it to men as much as it can be preached to men, confidently proclaiming: In the beginning was the Word.
So John was not merely a man, but more than a man, when he transcended both himself and all things.
Lifted by the ineffable power of wisdom and the purest sharpness of mind, he entered into the secrets above all things, namely, the unity of essence in three substances, and the three substances in one essence.
He could only ascend into God by first becoming God.
Just as our eyes cannot perceive the forms and colors of physical things until they mix with sunlight, the minds of the saints cannot grasp the pure knowledge of spiritual matters and the incomprehensible truth until they are made worthy to do so.
Therefore, the holy theologian, transformed in God and sharing in the truth, declares that the Word of God exists in God from the beginning-that is, God the Son in God the Father.
"In the beginning," he says, "was the Word."
Behold the heavens opened, revealing the mystery of the supreme and holy Trinity and unity to the world. See the divine angel ascending over the Son of Man, announcing that He is the Word before all things in the beginning, and then descending upon the Son of Man, proclaiming, "And the Word was made flesh."
He preached that the Word of God was made man supernaturally by being born from the virgin, and He ascended proclaiming that the same Word was begotten from the Father before and beyond all things. "In the beginning," he says, "was the Word."
It should be noted that in this context, the blessed evangelist uses the word "was" to indicate a substantial meaning rather than a temporal one. The word "sum," from which it is derived, has a dual meaning: it can signify the existence of something without any temporal motion, acting as a substantive verb, or it can indicate temporal motions like other verbs.
Therefore, when he says, "In the beginning was the Word," it is as if he openly declares, "The Son exists in the Father." Who in their right mind would say that the Son ever existed temporally in the Father? Here, only eternity is considered, where unchangeable truth is understood.
To ensure that no one thinks the Word existed in the beginning without any distinction between substances, it immediately adds: "And the Word was with God," meaning that the Son exists with the Father in unity of essence and with a substantial distinction.
Furthermore, to prevent the misconception that the Word only existed in the Father and was with God, but did not substantially and coessentially exist as God with the Father-an error embraced by the faithless Arians-it immediately adds: "And the Word was God."
Anticipating that some would claim the evangelist wrote about different Words: "In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was God," implying different Words at different times, it counters this heretical opinion by adding: "This was in the beginning with God," as if to say: This Word, which is God, is with God himself, not something else that existed in the beginning.
This can be understood more clearly from the Greek examples. In them, ουτος is written, meaning "this," and it can refer to both the Word and to God; these two names, Θεος and λογος, are masculine in Greek. Thus, it can be understood: "and the Word was God; this was in the beginning with God," as if saying more clearly: This God the Word was with God, he is the one of whom I said: "In the beginning was the Word."
All things were made through him. Through him, God the Word, or through him, the Word God, all things were made. And what does it mean that all things were made through him, except: by him being born before all from the Father, all things were made with him and through him? For his generation from the Father itself is the condition of all causes, and the operation and effect of all things that proceed from causes into genera and species.
Through the generation of God from God in the beginning, all things were made. Hear the divine and ineffable paradox, the irrecoverable secret, the invisible, profound, incomprehensible mystery. Through the one not made, but begotten, all things were made, but not begotten.
The beginning, from which everything comes, is the Father; the beginning, through which everything exists, is the Son.
When the Father speaks His word, that is, when the Father generates His wisdom, everything is made.
The prophet says: "You made everything in wisdom"; and elsewhere, introducing the person of the Father: "My heart has uttered."
And what did His heart utter? He explains: "I speak a good word, I speak a good word, I generate a good Son." The heart of the Father is His own substance, from which the Son's own substance is born; the Father precedes the Word not by nature, but by cause. Listen to the Son Himself saying: "The Father is greater than I, His substance is the cause of my substance."
The Father precedes the Word causally, I say, and the Son precedes everything that was made through Him naturally. The Son's substance is co-eternal with the Father. The substance of those things that were made through Him began to exist in Him before secular times, not in time, but with time. For time itself, among other things that were made, was created; not procreated, but created together.
And what is the consequence of the word spoken by the mouth of the Most High? For the Father did not speak in vain, not without fruit, nor without great effect; for even people, when they speak, achieve something in the ears of those who hear. Therefore, we must believe and understand three things: the Father speaking, the Word pronounced, and the things that are made through the Word.
The Father speaks, the Word is generated, everything is made. Listen to the Prophet when he says, "He spoke, and it was done," that is, He generated His Word through which everything was made. And lest you think that some things that exist were made through the Word of God and some outside of it, or that they exist by themselves, so that not everything that exists and does not exist refers to one beginning, the conclusion of all theology was added: "And without Him, nothing was made"; that is, nothing was made outside of Him, because He encompasses everything, comprehending everything within Himself, and nothing is understood to be co-eternal or consubstantial or coessential to Him, except for His Father and His Spirit proceeding from the Father through Him.
This concept is easier to understand in Greek.
While the Latins say "without him," the Greeks say "choris autou," which translates to "outside of him." Similarly, the Lord himself tells his disciples: "Without me, you can do nothing." He means, "What you cannot achieve on your own, you cannot achieve outside of me." In this context, the Greeks use "choris" instead of "anen," meaning "outside" rather than just "without."
I mentioned it is easier because when someone hears "without him," they might think it simply means without his counsel or help, and therefore they do not attribute everything to him. However, hearing "outside" implies that nothing exists that wasn't made in him and through him.
What was made in him was life. After revealing the divine mysteries far beyond human reason and understanding, the blessed evangelist unveiled the Word of God speaking in God, leaving the understanding of the Holy Spirit in divine Scripture to the contemplators.
Just as someone speaking necessarily breathes out the spirit in their words, so too does God the Father simultaneously generate his Son and produce his Spirit through his begotten Son.
After declaring that everything was made through God the Son, and that nothing exists outside of him, the evangelist redirected the course of his theology from a new beginning, saying: "What was made in him was life."
Previously, he said, "All things were made through him," and as if asked by someone about the things made through the Word of God, how and what they were in him, he answered: "What was made in him was life."
This sentence can be understood in two ways. It can be broken down as: "What was made," and then add "in him was life." It can also be: "What was made in him," and then add "was life." Thus, in two pronunciations, we observe two meanings.
It's not the same theory that says: what was made, distinct in places and times, differentiated by kinds, forms, and numbers, compacted or separated into sensible and intelligible substances, all this was life in itself; and the one that declares: what was made in itself was nothing but life.
So the meaning is: all things that were made through it are life in itself and are one.
For they existed, that is, they subsist in it causally, before they exist in themselves effectively.
Things that were made through it exist under it in one way, and in it in another way, than it itself is.
Therefore, all things made through the Word live unchangeably in it and are life; in which all things neither were in temporal intervals or localities, nor will be, but only above all times and places are one in it and universally subsist: visible, invisible, corporeal, incorporeal, rational, irrational, and simply heaven and earth, the abyss, and whatever is in them, live in it and are life, and eternally subsist.
What seems to us to lack all vital movement lives in the Word.
But if you ask how or by what reason all things made through the Word subsist vitally, uniformly, and causally in it, take paradigms from the nature of creatures.
Learn the maker from those things made in it and through it.
For the invisible things of Him, as the Apostle says, are understood by the things that are made.
Observe how the causes of all things, which the sensible globe of this world comprehends, subsist simultaneously and uniformly in that sun, which is called the greatest luminary of the world.
From there proceed the forms of all bodies, the beauty of differing colors, and other things that can be declared about the sensible nature.
Consider the vast and infinite power of seeds.
Each seed contains a multitude of plants, fruits, and animals, giving rise to a beautiful variety of forms and an innumerable multiplicity.
Look with your inner eyes at how the many rules in the art of the craftsman are one, residing in the mind of the one arranging them.
Notice how the infinite number of lines exists within a single point, and observe such natural examples.
From these observations, as if lifted by the wings of a physical theory beyond all things, and assisted by divine grace, you will be able to perceive the mysteries of the Word with the sharpness of your mind.
To the extent that human reasoning allows, those who seek their God will see how everything made through the Word lives in Him and is life.
For in Him, as the divine voice says, we live and move and have our being.
As the great Dionysius the Areopagite says, the being of all things is the superessential divinity.
And the life was the light of men.
The Son of God, whom, O blessed theologian, you previously called the Word, you now name life and light.
You did not change the names without reason, but to suggest different meanings to us.
You indeed called the Son of God the Word because through Him the Father spoke everything into existence when He said and it was done; and light and life because the Son is the light and life of all that was made through Him.
And what does He illuminate?
None other than Himself and His Father.
Therefore, He is light, and He illuminates Himself, declares Himself to the world, and reveals Himself to those who do not know Him.
The light of divine knowledge departed from the world when man abandoned God.
Thus, the eternal light declares itself to the world in two ways: through Scripture and creation.
For divine knowledge is not renewed in us except through the signs of divine Scripture and the forms of creation.
Learn the divine words, and conceive their understanding in your mind, through which you will know the Word.
With your physical senses, perceive the shapes and beauties of the things around you, and in them, you will understand God the Word.
In all these things, the truth will reveal nothing to you except Himself, who made everything.
Beyond Him, you will contemplate nothing because He is everything.
For in all that exists, whatever there is, He is.
Just as there is no substantial good, there is no essence or substance apart from Him.
And the life was the light of men.
Why is the light specifically added for men?
As if the light is specifically and particularly for men, who is the light of angels, the light of the created universe, the light of all visible and invisible existence?
Or perhaps the Word, which gives life to everything, is called the light of men specifically and particularly because in man, not only men but also angels and all creatures capable of participating in divine knowledge, He revealed Himself?
For He did not appear through an angel to the angels, nor through an angel to men, but through a man to both men and angels, not in a fantasy, but in true humanity, which He fully assumed into the unity of His substance, and He provided His knowledge to all who know Him.
Therefore, the light of men is our Lord Jesus Christ, who in human nature manifested Himself to every rational and intellectual creature and revealed the hidden mysteries of His divinity, by which He is equal to the Father.
And the light shines in the darkness.
Listen to the Apostle: "You were once darkness, but now you are light in the Lord."
Listen to Isaiah: "The people who sat in the region of the shadow of death, a light has dawned."
The light shines in the darkness.
The whole human race, because of the original sin, was rightly in darkness, not of the external eyes, which perceive the shapes and colors of sensible things, but of the internal eyes, which discern the forms and beauties of intelligible things;
not in the darkness of this gloomy air, but in the darkness of ignorance of the truth;
not in the absence of the light that reveals the physical world, but in the absence of the light that illuminates the incorporeal world.
After His birth from the virgin, the light shines in the darkness, namely in the hearts of those who know Him.
Because the whole human race is divided into two parts-those whose hearts are illuminated by the knowledge of truth, and those who still remain in the darkest shadows of impiety and disbelief-the evangelist added: "and the darkness did not comprehend it."
In other words: The light shines in the darkness of the faithful souls and grows stronger, starting from faith and aiming towards vision; but the treachery and ignorance of the hearts of the impious did not comprehend the light of the Word of God shining in the flesh. For their foolish hearts were darkened, as the Apostle says, and claiming to be wise, they became fools.
But this is the moral sense. The physical interpretation of these words is as follows: Human nature, even if it did not sin, could not shine by its own strength, for it is not naturally light itself but a participant in the light. It is indeed capable of wisdom but not wisdom itself, which it can become wise by sharing. Just as this air does not shine by itself but is called by the name of darkness, yet it is capable of solar light; so our nature, when considered by itself, is a kind of dark substance, capable of and participating in the light of wisdom.
And just as the aforementioned air, while it participates in the solar ray, is not said to shine by itself, but the splendor of the sun is said to appear in it, so that it does not lose its natural darkness and yet receives the light that comes to it, so the rational part of our nature, while it possesses the presence of the Word of God, does not know things intelligible and its God by itself, but knows through the divine light implanted in it.
Hear the Word itself: "It is not you who speak," it says, "but the Spirit of your Father who speaks in you." By this single sentence, He wanted to teach us to understand the same in other aspects and always to hear in the ear of our heart in an ineffable way: it is not you who shine, but the Spirit of your Father who shines in you, that is, manifests to you that I shine in you, because I am the intelligible light of the world, that is, of rational and intellectual nature.
It is not you who understand me, but I myself understand myself in you through my Spirit.
You are not the substantial light, but a participation in the light that exists by itself.
So the light shines in the darkness.
The Word of God, the life and light of men, in our nature, when investigated and considered by itself, is found to be a certain formless darkness.
Yet, it does not cease to shine.
Nor did it ever want to abandon it, even when it sins.
It has never abandoned it, forming it by nature by sustaining it, and reforming it by grace through deification.
And because the light itself is incomprehensible to every creature, the darkness did not comprehend it.
For God surpasses all sense and intellect and alone has immortality.
His light is called darkness by excellence because no creature comprehends what or how it is.
There was a man sent from God whose name was John.
Behold the eagle, descending with gentle flight from the highest peak of the mountain of theology into the deepest valley of history.
From the sky of the spiritual world, it spreads the wings of the highest contemplation.
Indeed, Divine Scripture is a certain intelligible world, constituted by its four parts, like the four elements.
Its earth is in the middle and the lowest, like the center: history.
Around which the abyss of moral intelligence, which the Greeks call Ethics, surrounds it like waters.
Around these, history and ethics, like the two lower parts of the aforementioned world, the air of natural science revolves.
This natural science, which the Greeks call Physics.
Beyond all these and beyond, the fiery ardor of the empyrean heaven, that is, the highest contemplation of the divine nature, which the Greeks call Theology, surrounds it; beyond which no intellect goes.
Therefore, the great theologian, John, at the beginning of the Gospel, touches upon the highest peaks of theology and penetrates the secrets of the heavens.
Ascending beyond all history, ethics, and physics, he delves into the events just before the incarnation of the Word.
He then descends into the narrative of history and says:
"There was a man sent from God, whose name was John."
John is then introduced into his theology. Deep calls to deep in the voice of divine mysteries. The Evangelist recounts the history of the forerunner; he who knew the Word in the beginning recalls him who preceded the incarnate Word.
"There was a man," he says; not simply "sent from God," but "there was a man," to distinguish the man who participated only in humanity, from the man who was united with divinity and humanity, who came after him. This separates the temporary voice from the eternal Word, suggesting the morning star at the dawn of the kingdom of heaven, and declaring the coming of the sun of righteousness.
He distinguishes the witness from the one he bears witness to, the one sent by him who sends, the flickering lamp from the brightest light that fills the world, dispelling the darkness of death and sin for all humanity. The forerunner of the Lord was a man, not God; but the Lord, whom he preceded, was both man and God. The forerunner was a man destined to become like God through grace; he whom he preceded was God by nature, destined to take on humanity through humility, for our salvation and redemption.
A man was sent. By whom? By God the Word, whom he preceded; his mission was his forerunning; the voice crying out sends forth the message. The voice of one crying in the wilderness prepares the way for the Lord's coming. His name was John, and he was granted to become the forerunner of the King of kings, the manifestor of the incarnate Word, and the baptizer into spiritual sonship, the witness by voice and martyrdom of the eternal light.
He came as a witness, to bear witness about the light.
About Christ, indeed.
Hear his testimony:
Behold the Lamb of God, behold him who takes away the sins of the world;
and again:
He who comes after me has been made before me.
This is more clearly read in Greek as emprosthen mou, which means "before me, in my presence."
As if he were openly saying:
He who was born in the flesh after my birth, I saw prophetically before my eyes, even when I was still in my barren mother's womb.
He was not the light, but came to bear witness to the light; from above, understand and interpret it this way:
He was not the light, but was sent to bear witness to the light.
The forerunner of the light was not the light.
Why then is he called a burning lamp and the morning star?
He was a burning lamp, but not lit by his own fire; he did not shine by his own light.
He was the morning star, but did not receive his own light from himself.
The grace of the one he preceded burned and shone in him.
He was not the light, but a participant in the light; it was not his own light that shone in him and after him.
As we said above, no rational or intellectual creature is substantially light by itself, but by participation in the one true substantial light, which shines everywhere in all things that shine intelligibly.
Therefore, it is added:
He was the true light, which enlightens every man coming into the world.
He calls the Son of God the true light, existing by himself, begotten by God the Father, who exists by himself before all ages; he calls the same Son the true light, made man among men for the sake of men.
He is the true light, who says of himself:
I am the light of the world; whoever follows me will not walk in darkness, but will have the light of eternal life.
He was the true light that enlightens every man coming into the world.
And what does coming into the world mean?
And who is every man coming into the world?
And where does he come into the world from?
And into what world does he come?
When you think about those who come into this world through birth, in specific places and times, what kind of light is there for those destined to die, grow old, and eventually dissolve, moving from the peaceful silence of nature into the chaos of existence?
What kind of spiritual and true light is there for those born into a temporary and often misleading life?
Is this world truly a suitable place for those disconnected from the true light?
Isn't it rightly called the shadow of death, the valley of tears, a depth of ignorance, and an earthly dwelling that burdens the soul and blinds the inner eyes from seeing the true light?
So, we should understand this illumination not as referring to those who come from hidden seeds into physical forms, but rather to those who enter the invisible world spiritually through the grace given in baptism.
These individuals reject the birth of the corruptible body and choose the birth of the spirit, leaving the world below and rising to the world above.
They abandon the shadows of ignorance and death, seeking the light of wisdom and life.
They stop being children of men and start becoming children of God, forsaking the world of vices and overcoming it within themselves.
They establish the world of virtues before their minds and strive with all their strength to ascend into it.
Therefore, the true light illuminates those who enter the world of virtues, not those who plunge into the world of vices.
He was in the world.
Here, "the world" refers not only to the visible creation but also specifically to the rational nature within humans. In all these things, and simply put, in the entire created universe, the Word was the true light. It exists and always has, because it never ceases to exist in all things.
As someone speaks, their voice eventually fades away.
Similarly, if the Heavenly Father were to stop speaking His Word, the universe, created by His Word, would cease to exist.
The continuation and permanence of the created universe depend on the speech of God the Father, that is, the eternal and unchangeable generation of His Word.
This statement can also apply specifically to this sensible world, as it says: In the world was He, and the world was made through Him.
To prevent anyone from thinking, like the followers of the Manichaean heresy, that the world, which we perceive with our senses, was created by the devil and not by the Creator of all things visible and invisible, the theologian adds: In the world was He, meaning that in this world was He who contains all things, and the world was made through Him.
For the Creator of the universe does not dwell in the works of others, but in those He made.
We must note that the blessed evangelist generally referred to the world.
However, we should understand that there are three worlds.
The first is filled solely with invisible and spiritual substances of virtues; whoever enters this world possesses full participation in true light.
The second world, which is opposed to the first, consists solely of invisible and bodily natures.
Though it holds the lowest proportion of the universe, the Word was in it, it was made through the Word, and it is the first step to ascending to the knowledge of truth for those willing to use their senses.
The forms of visible things attract the reasoning mind to the knowledge of invisible things.
The third world has the nature of mediation, connecting the higher spiritual and the lower bodily within itself, making one out of two, and is understood in humans alone, in whom all creation is united.
It consists of both body and soul.
Gathering the body from this world and the soul from the other world, it makes one being.
The body possesses all bodily nature, while the soul possesses all incorporeal nature.
When these elements come together in one structure, they create all the worldly adornments of man.
Therefore, man is called "all" because every creature is, so to speak, molded in him like in a certain workshop. Hence, the Lord himself commanded the disciples who were to preach: Preach the Gospel to every creature.
This world, meaning man, did not recognize its Creator, neither through the symbols of the written law nor through the paradigms of visible creation. They did not want to know their God, being held back by the chains of carnal thoughts. And the world did not recognize him. Man did not recognize the Word of God, neither before his incarnation as purely divine, nor after his incarnation as clothed in flesh. The invisible, he was ignorant of; the visible, he denied. He did not want to seek the one seeking him; he did not want to hear the one calling him; he did not want to worship the one deifying him; he did not want to receive the one receiving him.
He came to his own, meaning those things made by him, and thus they are rightly his own. And his own received him. His own are all humans, whom he wanted to redeem and did redeem. But to all who did receive him, he gave the power to become children of God, to those who believe in his name. Now, it is not the rational humanity of the world that is divided, but the will; the receivers of the incarnate Word are separated from those who reject him. The faithful believe in the coming of the Word and gladly receive their Lord. The impious deny and stubbornly refuse, the Jews out of envy, the pagans out of ignorance.
To those who received, he gave the power to become children of God; to those who did not receive, he still gives the opportunity to receive. For the possibility of believing in the Son of God, and the possibility of becoming a child of God, is taken away from no one; for this is established in the free will of man and the cooperation of grace. To whom did he give the power to become children of God? To those who received him, that is, to those who believe in his name.
Many receive Christ. The Arians receive him, but they do not believe in his name; they do not believe he is the only-begotten Son of God, consubstantial with the Father. They deny him as homoousion, that is, coessential with the Father; they affirm him as heteroousion, that is, of a different essence than the Father.
And so, it does not benefit them to accept Christ while denying His truth.
But those who accept Christ as true God and true man, and firmly believe this, are given the possibility to become children of God.
They are born not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God.
In the ancient Greek manuscripts, it is written simply: They are born not of blood, but of God.
Not of blood, meaning not by physical procreation, those who obtain the adoption of God's children by the merit of faith; but by God the Father through the Holy Spirit into the co-heirship of Christ, sharing the sonship of the only-begotten Son of God, neither by the will of the flesh nor by the will of man.
A double gender is introduced, from which the multitude of those born in the flesh is propagated carnally; by the name of flesh, the evangelist signified the female, and by the name of man, the male.
And lest you say: It seems impossible for mortals to become immortal, for the corruptible to be free from corruption, for ordinary humans to be children of God, for the temporal to possess eternity, consider this argument from greater things, by which you can lend faith to the thing you doubt:
And the Word was made flesh.
If, therefore, what is greater undoubtedly happened, why does it seem incredible that what is lesser can follow?
If the Son of God became man, which none who receive Him doubt, what is so surprising if a man believing in the Son of God becomes a son of God?
Indeed, the Word descended into flesh for this reason, so that flesh, that is, man believing through flesh in the Word, may ascend to it, so that through the natural only-begotten Son, many may become adopted sons.
The Word was made flesh not for itself, but for us, who could not be transformed into God's children except through the flesh of the Word; He descended alone, but ascended with many; He makes gods of men, who made man of God.
And He dwelt among us, that is, He possessed our nature, so that He might make us partakers of His nature.
And we saw His glory, the glory as of the only-begotten from the Father.
Where did you see, O blessed theologian, the glory of the incarnate Word, the glory of the humanized Son of God?
When did you see it?
With what eyes did you perceive it?
Was it with your physical eyes on the mountain during the Transfiguration?
For at that moment, you were the third witness of the divine glorification.
You were there in Jerusalem, and you heard the voice of the Father glorifying the Son, saying: I have glorified it, and I will glorify it again.
You heard the crowds of children proclaiming: Hosanna to the Son of David.
What can I say about the glory of the resurrection?
You saw Him rising from the dead when He entered to you and your fellow disciples through closed doors.
You witnessed His glory ascending to the Father when He was taken up into heaven by angels.
And above all these things, with the highest gaze of your mind, you contemplated the Word, in its beginning with the Father, where you saw His glory as of the only begotten from the Father, full of grace and truth.
The understanding of this is twofold.
It can be seen regarding the humanity and divinity of the incarnate Word, where the fullness of grace refers to His humanity, and the fullness of truth to His divinity.
For the incarnate Word, our Lord Jesus Christ, received the fullness of grace according to His humanity because He is the head of the Church and the firstborn of all creation, that is, of all humanity universally, which in Him and through Him is healed and restored.
In Him, because He is the greatest and principal example of grace, by which, without any preceding merits, man is made God, and in Him, it was originally manifested.
Through Him, we have all received the grace of deification from His fullness, through the grace of faith by which we believe in Him, and the grace of action by which we keep His commandments.
The fullness of Christ's grace can also be understood as coming from the Holy Spirit.
For the Holy Spirit, who is the distributor and operator of the gifts of grace, is often called grace.
The sevenfold operation of the Spirit filled the humanity of Christ and rested upon Him, as the prophet says:
"And the Spirit of the Lord will rest upon Him, the Spirit of wisdom and understanding, the Spirit of counsel and might, the Spirit of knowledge and of the fear of the Lord, and He will be filled with the Spirit of the fear of the Lord."
So, if you want to understand what is meant by Christ being full of grace, recognize it as referring to the fullness of His deification and sanctification according to His humanity.
By deification, I mean the unity of human and divine nature in one substance; by sanctification, I mean that not only was He conceived by the Holy Spirit, but He was also filled with the fullness of His gifts.
Just as the lamps of grace shone at the summit of the mystical church's candelabrum, so they shone in Him and from Him.
If you prefer to understand the fullness of grace and truth of the incarnate Word according to the New Testament, the same evangelist seems to have sensed this a little later.
For he says:
"The Law was given through Moses; grace and truth came through Jesus Christ."
You would not be wrong to declare that the fullness of grace of the New Testament was given through Christ, and the truth of the legal symbols is embodied in Him.
As the Apostle says:
"In whom the fullness of the Godhead dwells bodily," referring to the fullness of the divine mysteries of the legal shadows, which Christ, by coming in the flesh, truly embodied and taught and revealed in Himself.
For He is the source and fullness of grace, the truth of the legal symbols, and the fulfillment of the prophetic visions.
To Him be glory with the Father and the Holy Spirit, forever and ever.
Amen.