Chapter One
The followers of Valentinus, a significant group among the heretics, have many who have strayed from the truth.
They are easily drawn to tales and are not deterred by discipline.
They focus on concealing their teachings, if they teach at all, because they prefer to hide.
Guarding their doctrine is a matter of conscience.
They preach confusion while claiming it as religion.
Even those Eleusinian mysteries, a type of Athenian superstition, are embarrassed by what they keep secret.
They first test those who seek them out.
Initiation is a lengthy process, taking five years at the gates, to build a reputation by withholding knowledge.
This builds up a sense of majesty through the anticipation they create.
Then comes the obligation of silence; what is discovered slowly is carefully guarded.
All the divinity is hidden in inner sanctuaries, behind many veils, with the entire secret sealed by silence.
The image of the male organ is revealed, but the venerable name of nature, cloaked in allegory, obscures the sacrilege with a guise of truth.
Therefore, those we now call heretics use sacred names, titles, and arguments of true religion to craft vain and disgraceful tales, taking advantage of many divine opportunities.
The Valentinian Eleusinian mysteries have become enticing, sacred in their great silence, and celestial only in their secrecy.
If you ask sincerely, with a serious expression and a raised eyebrow, they respond, "It is profound." If you subtly inquire, they affirm common beliefs with ambiguous language. If you show understanding, they deny what they acknowledge. If you argue closely, they confuse your straightforwardness with their cunning. They do not even share these teachings with their own disciples until they have fully indoctrinated them. They have the skill to persuade before they teach, whereas truth persuades by teaching, not the other way around.
Chapter Two
We are often criticized for being simple, as if that’s all we are, and not wise as well—as if wisdom must vanish when simplicity is present.
However, the Lord combines both:
"Be as wise as serpents and as innocent as doves" Matthew 10:16.
If we are thought foolish because we are simple, then are they not simple because they are wise?
Those who lack simplicity can be harmful, just as those who lack wisdom can be foolish.
I would prefer to be seen as having a lesser fault, believing it is better to know less than to know incorrectly, to err rather than to deceive.
Moreover, God looks favorably upon those who seek Him with simplicity, as Wisdom itself teaches—this is not the Wisdom of Valentinus, but of Solomon.
Furthermore, children bore witness to Christ by being anointed with blood.
Do you call those who cry out for the cross children?
They were neither children nor infants, meaning they were not simple.
The Apostle also urges us to become like children in following God First Corinthians 14:20, to be innocent in evil through simplicity, and thus wise in understanding; at the same time, entering the realm of wisdom that stems from simplicity.
In summary, a dove is known to represent Christ, while a serpent is known to tempt.
The dove has always been a symbol of divine peace; the serpent, from the beginning, a thief of the divine image.
Thus, simplicity alone can more easily recognize and reveal God, while prudence alone tends to unsettle and betray.
Chapter Three
So, let the serpent hide itself as much as it can, twisting and turning through its concealed paths.
It lives deep, buried in darkness, weaving through winding routes, never fully revealing itself, as it is a creature that shuns the light.
Our dove's home is simple too, always in high, open places, basking in the light.
It embodies the spirit of the Holy Spirit, the essence of Christ.
The truth is only embarrassed by being hidden:
for it is never ashamed to listen to Him, to recognize Him as God, whom nature has already entrusted to it, whom it feels in all works each day.
It remains less known only because it did not see Him as unique, naming Him among others, worshipping Him among others.
Otherwise, persuading one from the crowd and moving to another assembly, shifting from a familiar rule to an unknown, twisting from the obvious to the hidden, is to challenge faith at its core.
Now, if it were part of a complete fable, wouldn’t it remind you of stories from childhood, like those about the towers of Lamia and the combs of the sun?
But if someone comes to faith from another understanding, encountering so many names of Aeons, marriages, offspring, outcomes, events, fortunes, and misfortunes of a fragmented divinity, won't they hesitate, seeing them as fables and endless genealogies, which the spirit of the Apostles foresaw to condemn when heretical seeds were already sprouting?
Rightly, then, they are not simple, rightly only shrewd, who neither easily produce such things nor defend them openly, but do not fully teach everyone they instruct; cunningly so, if they are shameful: otherwise inhumanely, if they are honorable.
And yet we, the simple, understand everything.
In short, we have armed ourselves with this first wedge of conflict, the revealer and marker of their entire conscience, and we begin this first victory:
because to simply reveal what is hidden with such effort is to destroy it.
Chapter Four
We know where they came from and why they're called Valentinians, even if they don't always seem to be.
They have strayed from their founder, but their origin can't be erased; any change they make only highlights it.
Valentinus had hoped to become a bishop, as he was both talented and eloquent.
However, he was disappointed when someone else was chosen for the position due to the honor of martyrdom.
Driven by ambition, he left the established church and aimed to challenge the truth.
He adopted an old belief and paved the way for Colarbasus.
Ptolemaeus later expanded on this, defining Aeons with names and numbers as personal entities, but set apart from God, unlike Valentinus, who integrated them into the divine nature as thoughts, feelings, and movements.
Heracleon, Secundus, and the magician Marcus also developed paths from this foundation.
Theotimus worked extensively on interpretations of the Law.
Even though Valentinus is no longer around, there are still Valentinians who trace their roots back to him.
Only in Antioch does Axionicus single-handedly uphold Valentinus' memory by strictly following his teachings.
Otherwise, this heresy is as changeable as a she-wolf that alters her appearance daily.
Why not?
They believe their spiritual essence is unique to each person.
When they introduce something new, they quickly call it a revelation, viewing their assumptions as gifts, celebrating diversity over unity.
This leads to noticeable divisions among them, even among those who speak sincerely, saying, "This isn't right;" "I see it differently;" or "I don't accept this."
Their beliefs constantly shift, adding layers of ignorance as well.
Chapter Five
For me, the distinction lies with the original teachings of the main instructors, not with the imitation leaders followed by passive students.
We can't claim to have invented these subjects ourselves, as so many people, distinguished by holiness and excellence—not only our predecessors but also contemporaries of these heresiarchs—have both revealed and refuted them in the most informed writings.
Think of figures like Justin, the philosopher and martyr, or Miltiades, the sophist of the Churches, or Irenaeus, the most thorough investigator of all doctrines, or our Proculus, known for the dignity of virgin old age and Christian eloquence.
I aspire to follow them in every work of faith, including this one.
If heresies did not exist, as some claim those who oppose them have invented them, then the Apostle who spoke of them would be lying—First Corinthians 2:19.
Furthermore, if heresies do exist, they are precisely those being reconsidered.
No one would be idle enough with a pen to invent subjects when there are already so many to address.
Chapter Six
In this little book, where we aim to demonstrate that secret, don't be confused by names that are foreign, forced, or ambiguous.
Let me first explain how we'll be using them.
Some Greek interpretations don't easily translate into recognizable names, and some don't match in gender, while others are more commonly known in Greek.
So, we'll often use Greek; meanings will be provided in the margins.
Even for the Latin, Greek references will appear above the lines, especially for personal names, due to overlapping meanings.
Although I've held back from fully diving in, focusing on the narrative for now, if any unworthiness deserves criticism, it won't be a brief attack.
Think of it as a prelude to the real battle, dear Reader.
I'll show wounds but not inflict them.
If there's laughter to be found, it will come from the material itself; many things are too unworthy to be taken seriously.
Vanity naturally gives way to amusement.
Truth finds joy in laughter and mocks its rivals with confidence.
We must ensure that its laughter doesn't become laughable if it's unworthy.
However, when laughter is justified, it is fitting.
And with that, I will begin.
Chapter Seven
The first Roman poet, Ennius, described the vast halls of heaven, likely inspired by Jupiter feasting there as depicted in Homer.
It's fascinating how some heretics have imagined and exaggerated the grandeur of their god's abode.
Even for our creator, Ennius' halls resemble small houses, stacked with different levels, assigning each god as many steps as there are heresies.
The world has turned into a marketplace.
Imagine an island of Felicula with countless layers of heaven; who knows where.
For the God of the Valentinians resides at the highest point.
They call him ΑΙΩΝΑ ΤΕΛΕΙΟΝ in essence, and personally ΠΡΟΑΡΧΗΝ and ΤΗΝ ΑΡΧΗΝ, also Bythus, which seems unfitting for someone dwelling in such heights.
They describe him as unborn, vast, infinite, invisible, and eternal, as if defining him this way proves his existence, because we assume he must be like that to be said to exist before everything.
But I ask for proof of his existence: and notice nothing more than those found after everything are claimed to be before everything, and not by their own doing.
So let this Bythus exist in infinite past ages, in great and high calm, in much leisure, embodying a peaceful and, so to speak, stunned divinity, as Epicurus suggested.
Yet, despite their desire for him to be alone, they assign him a second presence within himself, Ennoea, also known as Charis and Silence.
They might even, in this highly praised calm, counsel him to finally bring forth the beginning of things from himself.
He places this as a seed in his Silence, akin to the generative parts of a womb.
She immediately receives it, becomes pregnant, and gives birth silently to Nous, who is very similar to and equal to the father in every way.
Ultimately, only he can comprehend the immense and incomprehensible greatness of the father.
Thus, he is also called Father, the beginning of everything, and uniquely Monogenes.
However, it's not entirely accurate, since he isn't recognized alone.
Along with him came the female, Truth, the Only Begotten.
Being born first, how much more fitting it is to call him the Firstborn!
Therefore, Depth and Silence, along with Mind and Truth, form the first chariot defended by the Valentinian faction, the source and origin of all things.
There, Mind, as soon as it began its role of expression, also emitted from itself the Word and Life.
Which, if they weren't present before, certainly were not in Depth.
And how could it be that there was no life in God!
This offspring, sent forth at the beginning of the universe and the formation of the entire Fullness, produces fruit by creating Man and the Church.
You have an Ogdoad, a double Tetrad, from the unions of males and females; the dwelling places, so to speak, of the primordial Aeons.
The fraternal marriages of the Valentinian gods; the census of all heretical sanctity and majesty; an unknown crowd of either crimes or divinities, certainly the source of remaining fertility.
Chapter Eight
Behold, the second Tetrad: Word and Life, Human and Church, flourishing in the glory of the Father.
Eager to offer something of their own to the Father, they bring forth additional offspring through the union of both natures.
Here, Word and Life together produce a group of Aeons.
Meanwhile, Human and Church add two more, matching their parents, as they too, along with the ten, create as many as they themselves made.
Now, let me give you the names of this group: Bythos and Mixis; Ageratos and Henosis; Autophyes and Hedone; Acinetos and Syncrasis; Nonogenes and Macaria.
In contrast, the number twelve includes: Paracletus and Pistis; Patricos and Elpis; Metricos and Agape; Ainus and Synesis; Ecclesiasticus and Macariotes; Theletus and Sophia.
Here, I'm compelled to share an example of what these names signify.
In the Carthaginian schools, there was a rather uninspired Latin rhetorician named Phosphorus.
When he praised a brave man, he said, "I come to you, excellent citizens, from the battle, with my victory, with your happiness, expanded, glorious, fortunate, greatest, triumphant." The students immediately shouted, "The Family of Phosphorus: Alas! You heard Fortunata, and Hedone, and Acinetos, and Theletus, shout: The Family of Ptolemy, Alas."
This is that mysterious Pleroma, the fullness of the divine trinity. Let's explore the significance of these numbers: four, eight, and twelve. Meanwhile, in the thirty, all fertility ceases; the strength, power, and generative desire of the Aeons are halted. As if there were not enough remaining ideas and no other names from the school. Why aren't fifty and one hundred also created? Why aren't they called Dung and Foster-children?
Chapter Nine
This is also favoritism, where only Nus, among everyone, has the privilege of knowing the immense Father, rejoicing and exulting while others remain sorrowful.
Indeed, Nus, as much as it was within his power, both wanted and attempted to share with others his knowledge of how great and incomprehensible the Father was.
However, the Mother, Silence, intervened—she even commands her own heretics to be silent.
Although they claim it was by the Father's will, desiring everyone to be stirred with longing for Him.
Therefore, while they are tormented within themselves, consumed by a silent desire to know the Father, a near-crime occurred.
Among the twelve Aeons that Man and Church produced, the youngest Aeon, forgive the solecism, named Sophia, in her lack of self-control, without her partner Philetus, impulsively sought to inquire about the Father.
She contracted a kind of fault, which had indeed begun in those around Nus, but spread to her, that is, to Sophia, much like how faults originating in one part of the body often spread their harm to another part.
But under the guise of love for the Father, jealousy overcame Nus, who alone rejoiced in the Father.
As Sophia, striving for the impossible, was frustrated and overwhelmed by difficulty, she was nearly consumed by her affection and effort.
She was about to dissolve into the remaining substance and would not have stopped except by perishing, if not for the good fortune of encountering Horon—a certain force, the foundation, the external guardian of that universe—also known as the Cross, the Redeemer, and the Harvester.
So Sophia, rescued from danger and gradually convinced, ceased her investigation of the Father and laid out all her Enthymesis, that is, her animation with the Passion that had additionally occurred.
Chapter Ten
Some envisioned Sophia's restoration differently.
After several unsuccessful attempts and the loss of hope, I believe she was marked by paleness, thinness, and neglect of her appearance, as she mourned a father not only lost but denied.
In her sorrow, she conceived alone, without any help, and gave birth to a female.
Are you surprised by this?
Even a hen can lay eggs without a mate.
It's also said that vultures only produce females, becoming mothers without males.
Initially, she grieved over the unfulfillment of her creation, then feared an end would come, puzzled over the situation, and worried about keeping it hidden.
There were no remedies.
For where were the tragedies and comedies from which she could borrow a way to reveal what was born without shame?
In her distress, she looked up and turned to the Father, but her efforts were in vain, and her strength left her, so she resorted to prayers.
Her entire family also prayed for her, especially Nus.
Why not?
He was the cause of such a great misfortune.
However, Sophia had no way out and her struggles continued.
Indeed, at that time, the conflict reached the origin of Matter; ignorance, fear, and sorrow became her substance.
Finally, the Father was moved and, through Monogenes Nus, whom we previously mentioned as Horon, revealed in his image a female to a male, as they differ in the Father's gender.
They add that Horon is also called Metagogea, meaning the guide, and Horotheten.
They proclaim the works of this one, who restrained from illicit things, purified from evils, strengthened Sophia thereafter, and restored her to her rightful place, while she remained in the Pleroma.
Her thought and that appendage of Passion were banished and crucified by Horon, and made external, as they say, Evil was cast out.
Yet that spiritual substance, like a natural impulse of the Aeon, was formless and unshaped, as it had grasped nothing; therefore, it was pronounced a weak fruit and a female.
Chapter Eleven
After Enthymesis was banished and his mother Sophia was reunited with her husband, the Only-Begotten, also known as Nus, was once again free from his father’s duties and oversight.
He concentrated on strengthening and stabilizing the Pleroma to prevent further disruptions.
He created a new pairing, Christ and the Holy Spirit—an unusual duo of two males, unless the Holy Spirit is female, which would imply a male is affected by a female.
Their mission was to maintain harmony among the Aeons.
From this shared responsibility, two schools of thought quickly emerged, marking the beginning of Valentinus's divided doctrine.
Christ's role was to teach the Aeons about the nature of couplings.
He enabled them to recognize the Father within themselves, which they couldn’t perceive or understand otherwise, not through sight or hearing, except through the Only-Begotten.
Yet, I will allow them to learn about the Father so that they may not truly know him.
I will highlight the distortion of this doctrine, which claims that the Father’s incomprehensibility is the reason for their eternity, while his comprehensibility is seen as the cause of their creation and existence.
This setup, I believe, implies that it is preferable for God not to be understood: because his incomprehensibility leads to eternity, while his comprehensibility pertains to birth and formation, for those lacking eternity.
However, they regard the Son as the comprehensible aspect of the Father.
How he is to be understood was taught by Christ when he was revealed.
The Holy Spirit’s proper role is that, through dedicated teaching, everyone might equally learn how to give thanks and be guided to true peace.
Chapter Twelve
In this chapter, everyone is equal in form and wisdom, each becoming their true self; no one is different because they are all alike.
They merge back into Nus, into Sermones, into Men, and into Philetos.
Women also merge into Sigas, into Zoas, into Churches, and into Fortunatas, such that if Ovid had known of a greater transformation today, he would have rewritten his Metamorphoses.
From there, they find refreshment, are established, and enter a state of rest from truth, singing joyous hymns to the Father.
The Father is filled with joy, naturally, as his children and grandchildren sing beautifully.
Why wouldn't he be happy, with the Pleroma set free?
What captain doesn't rejoice, even amidst challenges?
We see sailors celebrating joyfully every day.
In the same way sailors celebrate with a feast, the Aeons do something similar.
All have become one, not just in thought but also in form, welcoming new brothers and teachers like Christ and the Holy Spirit, each offering something of the best and most beautiful.
However, I think this is pointless.
If everyone was already one due to the equality mentioned earlier, then the reason for the feast is lost, as it usually thrives on the pleasure of variety.
They all contributed one good thing, which they all essentially were.
Perhaps the focus was on the manner or form of the equality itself.
So, from their collective offering, in honor and glory of the Father, they created the most beautiful star and perfect fruit of the Pleroma: Jesus.
They named him Savior, Christ, and Word, drawing from the paternal lineage.
Now, everything, crafted from the essence of all, became like the Daw of Aesop, Pandora of Hesiod, the Dish of Accius, the Drink of Nestor, and the Miscellany of Ptolemy.
How close it was to being called the All-Fruit from some Attic works, by such imaginative name-givers!
To further embellish this small statue, they bring forth angels as his attendants, similar in kind.
If this happens among themselves, it makes sense, but if they are of the same substance as the Savior (which I found ambiguously stated), what will be his distinction among these equal attendants?
Chapter Thirteen
This order, therefore, includes the initial procession of both the emerging and the marrying, as well as the generating Aeons.
Sophia's perilous fall, driven by her longing for the Father, Horus's timely help, the purification of Enthymesis and the related Passion, the guidance of Christ and the Holy Spirit, the reformation under the Aeons' protection, Soter's peacock-like adornment, and the angelic authority comparison.
You might wonder what's left for you to do—be well and applaud, perhaps?
Instead, I suggest you listen and let go of the rest.
These events are said to have taken place within the assembly of the Pleroma, marking the first scene of the tragedy.
But if someone else is to step forward, it happens outside the Pleroma, I say:
And yet, if such things occur under the Father's protection within Horus's domain, what might happen outside in freedom, where God was not present?
Chapter Fourteen
Enthymesis, or Achamoth as it's sometimes called, was expelled along with the flaw of her deep-seated Passion into regions beyond the light of the Pleroma, into the empty void described by Epicurus.
She was miserable even in her location.
She had neither form nor appearance, being a flawed and incomplete creation.
In this state, Christ, moved by higher powers, was guided by Horos to shape this unformed being with the power of his own substance, though without fully knowing its form.
She was given some hope, momentarily infused with the essence of incorruptibility, to prepare her for the desire for greater things.
Having shown this mercy, accompanied by the Holy Spirit, Christ returned to the Pleroma.
He took the opportunity to add names from acts of kindness.
Enthymesis arose from action, and the origin of Achamoth remains a matter of debate; Sophia flows from the Father; the Holy Spirit is from the angel with Christ, from whom she immediately felt desire when left alone.
She rushed to seek his light; if she had not known it invisibly, how could she have sought his unknown light with him?
Despite her efforts, she might have succeeded if not for Horos, who had once favored her mother but now met her unfavorably, even shouting "JAO," like "Forward, citizens," or "Trust in Caesar," as found in the Scriptures.
Thus, she was driven away and could not cross the threshold, which is Horos, as she had not been prepared in any of Catullus' Laureolus.
Left to her Passion in a complex and intricate snare, she was afflicted by all kinds of emotions: sorrow for not completing her endeavor, fear of being deprived of life as she was of light, overwhelmed and ignorant.
Unlike her mother, who was an Aeon, Enthymesis was in a worse condition, which led her to turn to Christ, who had given her life, and in this turning, she was tempered.
Chapter Fifteen
Let the Pythagoreans learn, the Stoics acknowledge, and even Plato understand where the matter they claim is innate actually originates.
This is something that even Mercury Trismegistus, the master of all physicists, hadn't considered.
You've heard of Conversion, another kind of Passion; from this, it's said that every soul in this world was constituted, even that of the Demiurge, our God.
You've heard of sorrow and fear; from these, other things began.
From his tears, the entire nature of waters flowed.
Consider what outcome this led to, and how many kinds of tears it produced.
There were false ones, bitter ones, sweet ones, warm ones, cold ones, bituminous ones, rusty ones, sulfurous ones, and even poisonous ones.
Nonacris sweated from it, which killed Alexander, Lyncestus flowed from it, making people drunk, and Salmacis dissolved from it, weakening men.
Achamoth wept celestial rains; and we even preserve foreign sorrows and tears in cisterns.
Thus, from distress and fear, physical elements were drawn.
Yet, in such solitude, in such abandonment, she laughed, remembering seeing Christ, and from that joy, the light of laughter shone.
What benefit of providence made her laugh?
Perhaps so we wouldn't always dwell in darkness.
Don't be amazed, since her joy radiated such a splendid element to the world, just as her sorrow provided a necessary tool for the age.
O illuminating laughter!
O nourishing tears!
She could already act as a remedy against the horror of that place.
For she could dispel all its darkness whenever she wanted to laugh, or so she wouldn't need to apply her deserters.
Chapter Sixteen
She indeed turns to prayers in a motherly manner.
But Christ, who was already hesitant to leave the Pleroma again, appointed the Paraclete as a representative.
The Savior, granted by the Father of all Aeons the supreme power to subject them all, sends him with the duty and company of coeval angels; you might even believe with twelve groups.
There, at last, with his grand arrival, Achamoth was shaken and immediately covered herself with a veil as her first act of reverence and modesty.
Then she looks at him, a fruitful suggestion.
With the strength she gained from this, she approaches him, saying, "Lord, Hail."
Presumably, he acknowledges and confirms her, cleansing her from all injuries of the Passion, not with the same negligence that had occurred in the mother's downfall.
However, he confounded the vices that had been practiced and perfected through use; and thus, solidly united, he fixed them separately in the material preparation of the body.
He transformed the innate incorporeal passion into the ability and nature by which he could soon reach rival equivalencies of bodies, arranging a dual condition of substances: from vices, the worst; from conversion, passionate.
This will be the matter that brought us into contention with Hermogenes and others who assume that God created all things from matter, not from nothing.
Chapter Seventeen
From this point, Achamoth, finally free from all troubles, begins to grow and thrive in greater works.
Overjoyed by such success arising from misfortune, and inspired by the contemplation of the angelic lights, she, in a way, absorbed them within herself.
She immediately became spiritually pregnant with the image she had seen and the joyful, eager intention she had embraced and internalized.
Eventually, she gave birth, resulting in a trinity of kinds, emerging from a trinity of causes:
one material, from passion; another animal, from conversion; and the third spiritual, from imagination.
Chapter Eighteen
Having three children gave her the authority and experience to manage things, leading her to create different types of beings.
However, she struggled to understand the spiritual realm because she herself wasn't spiritual.
Their nature, being nearly equal and of the same essence, didn't allow for such a union.
With this in mind, she turned to the animal kingdom, following the teachings of the Savior.
First, though it must be spoken, read, and heard with great horror for its blasphemy, she envisions God, our God and the Father of all, except the heretics, as the Creator and King of everything that came after Him.
For everything originates from Him, if indeed it does, and not rather from Achamoth herself, who, without His knowledge, set everything in motion as if guided externally by a seal.
Finally, due to this ambiguity among the people and their works, they mixed the name of Metropator, using different names for others based on their roles and positions in the works.
They refer to the father of the animal substances on the right side, and the Creator for the material substances on the left side, while commonly calling Him the King of the universe.
Chapter Nineteen
The specific meanings of names don't align with the meanings of the works from which all these names originate.
Ideally, they should be named after the one who carries out the actions, but that's not the case here.
When they say Achamoth created images in honor of the Aeons, they actually credit this to the author Soter, who worked through her.
This means she was intended to represent the image of the invisible and unknown Father—naturally unknown and invisible to the Demiurge.
The Demiurge would then depict the son Nun, while the Archangels would illustrate the work of the Demiurge and the remaining Aeons.
When I hear about these grand images of the three, how can I not laugh at the images created by such a twisted artist?
A woman, Achamoth, as an image of the Father?
And the Demiurge, unaware of his mother, let alone his father?
An image of Nus that's unaware of the Father?
And angels, as servants, merely copies of their masters?
It's like painting a mule from a donkey and describing Ptolemy from Valentinus.
Chapter Twenty
So, the Demiurge, being outside the boundaries of the Pleroma, created a new realm in the endless void of eternal exile, which is this world.
He organized the chaos and differentiated the dual nature of animals and materials, forming bodies from incorporeal elements: heavy, light, ascending, and descending, celestial and terrestrial.
He completed the sevenfold structure of the heavens with his throne above.
That's why the Sabbath is named, from the week of his seat; and Ogdoad, the mother Achamoth, from the concept of the primordial Ogdoad.
They consider the heavens to be intelligent and sometimes equate them to angels, much like the Demiurge himself.
Paradise is also seen as the fourth archangel, as it is placed above the third heaven, from whose power Adam took, residing there among clouds and trees.
Ptolemy recalled enough of the fanciful notions, like apples growing in the sea and fish on trees.
Thus, he assumed there were nuts in the heavens.
The Demiurge works in ignorance, which might explain why he doesn't realize trees should only grow on earth.
Of course, the mother knew.
Why didn't she suggest it?
She who also exerted her influence.
By elevating her son with works that portray him as father, god, and king, even before the Valentinians' ideas, why she didn't want these things to be known to her, I will question later.
Chapter Twenty-One
Interestingly, they referred to Sophia as Earth and Mother, almost like she was Mother Earth, and amusingly, even the Holy Spirit.
They seemed to give every honor to a woman, and perhaps even imagined her with a beard, among other things.
On the other hand, the Demiurge wasn't really in control, as spiritual matters were becoming involved with the census of animals regarding health.
He proclaimed, "I am God, and there is no one besides me" Isaiah Forty-five verse six.
Yet, he clearly understood that he wasn't alone in the past.
Therefore, he realized that something had been created, and there was indeed a creator of the creation.
So, how could he see himself as the only one?
Even if he wasn't completely sure, he at least suspected there was some creator.
Chapter Twenty-Two
The infamy surrounding the devil is somewhat more acceptable to them, perhaps because it originates from a more degrading source.
They believe it arises from the evil of that sorrow, which they associate with the origins of angels, demons, and all spiritual evils.
Yet, they also claim that the devil is the work of the creator, referring to him as the ruler of the world.
They argue that he possesses greater knowledge of the higher realms, being a spiritual entity by nature, more so than the creator, whom they view as possessing an animal nature.
He is favored by them, to whom all heresies are attributed.
Chapter Twenty-Three
They place the strongholds of unique powers within these boundaries.
At the highest peaks resides the group of thirty, with Horos marking the outer boundary.
Below, Achamoth marks the middle, trampling on the son.
Beneath lies the creator in his realm, and even more so, the devil in this common world we share.
They are mingled and embodied, as previously mentioned, originating from the significant fall of Sophia.
Without Sophia's sorrow refining it, she wouldn't even have the space to breathe.
The delicate garment of all bodies, the indicator of all colors, the instrument of times, all depend on this refinement—like the fear of creatures and even her transformation, including the creator himself.
Among all these elements and bodies, fire is ignited.
The original passion of Sophia, which they have not yet revealed, I will argue, is shaken by her minor disturbances.
You might even believe she created amidst such great troubles.
Chapter Twenty-Four
What kinds of stories about God or gods are similar to those about humans!
The creator, after making the world, focuses on humans but doesn't fully understand their essence.
It's said that humans didn't originate from the dry earth we know, even though it became dry later, once the waters receded, leaving mud to dry.
Instead, humans came from an invisible form of that material, specifically philosophical, in its liquid and molten state.
I can't determine where this material originated because it exists nowhere.
If the molten and liquid state is characteristic of a liquid, and all liquid flowed from the tears of Sophia, then we might believe that the mud was formed from the mucus and phlegm of Sophia, which are the sediment of tears, much like mud is the residue of water.
The creator shapes man and brings him to life with his breath.
This makes man both earthly and living, created in the image and likeness: a fourfold being.
The image is considered earthly, meaning material, although the creator is not made of material.
The likeness, however, is living, and the creator is living too.
So you have two aspects.
Meanwhile, they say a fleshly surface was added to the earthly being later, which is the leather tunic subject to sensation.
Chapter Twenty-Five
Within Achamoth, there was a unique spiritual seed from her mother Sophia's essence.
Achamoth kept this hidden from her son, the creator, without his awareness.
Think about the cleverness of this secret plan.
She placed and concealed it so that when the creator gave a soul from his own breath to Adam, that spiritual seed would also be transferred into the earthly being.
It would then grow within the material body, like in a womb, becoming ready to receive the perfect Word in the future.
So, when the creator passed his soul into Adam, the spiritual human remained hidden, inserted through the breath, and was introduced into the body as well, since the creator knew neither the seed nor the mother.
This seed is known as the Church, reflecting the heavenly Church and the essence of humanity.
Therefore, they relate it to Achamoth, just as they connect the animate being to the creator and the earthly being to the beginning's substance: the flesh to matter.
Here you have the new concept, the quadruple Geryon.
Chapter Twenty-Six
They also divide the outcome for each one.
For the material, which they refer to as the carnal, is called left, and they predict certain destruction for it.
But for the animal, which they call right, the outcome is uncertain, as it wavers between the material and the spiritual, going where it is most inclined.
However, they say the spiritual can join with the animal and can be educated and trained through interactions.
They claim the animal needed instruction even in the sensible disciplines.
In this, the preparation of the world was foreseen, and in this, the Savior was represented in the world as an animal, for the salvation of the animal.
In another complex composition, they wish that he would take on the properties of the substances he would bring to salvation.
That he received the spiritual from Achamoth, and the animal, which he soon took from the demiurge, Christ.
However, the bodily aspect, from the animal substance, was crafted with a marvelous and indescribable skill.
For the purpose of administration, he brought power, to be subject to engagement, and sight, and touch, and even death, though it was unwelcome.
Yet, there was nothing material in him, as he was foreign to salvation, except for those needing salvation.
And all of this was to separate the nature of our flesh from Christ and to remove even the hope of salvation.
Chapter Twenty-Seven
Now, let's talk about Christ: some people freely insert Jesus into this discussion, much like they infuse spiritual seed into the soul with their breath, creating a sort of blend of both men and their deities.
They claim that their Christ is the natural son of the Demiurge.
He was eventually revealed as a living being by the Demiurge and announced by the prophets.
Christ was involved in the concept of the Prepositions, meaning he was brought forth through a virgin but not born from her, as he passed through the virgin in a manner of transmission, not generation; through her, not from her; seeing her not as a mother, but as a pathway.
They say that during the sacrament of baptism, the Savior descended upon this Christ in the form of a dove.
Moreover, Christ had a spiritual enhancement from Achamoth, to keep the rest of the mixture from deteriorating.
In the likeness of the principal Tetrad, he was surrounded by four substances: the spiritual from Achamoth, the living from the Demiurge, the indescribable bodily one, and the one from the Savior, represented by the dove.
The Savior remained within Christ, incapable of suffering, unharmed, and beyond grasp.
Ultimately, when it was time for his capture, he departed during Pilate's questioning.
Therefore, he did not allow the seed of the mother to suffer harm, equally resistant, and not even known to the Demiurge.
However, the living and fleshly Christ did suffer, serving as a representation of the higher Christ, who had been affixed to the Cross, that is, Horus, in a substantial form for the creation of Achamoth, not in a form of recognition.
Thus, they interpret everything into images, clearly making themselves imaginary Christians.
Chapter Twenty-Eight
Meanwhile, the Creator of all things remained unaware of what was happening, even though he preached through the Prophets without fully understanding his own work.
They also divided prophetic support among Achamoth, the seed, and the Creator.
Upon hearing about the arrival of the Savior, he eagerly and joyfully hurried over with all his forces, much like the Centurion from the Gospel.
Enlightened about everything, he even learns from the Savior about his hope of succeeding his mother.
Reassured from that moment on, he continues to manage this world, especially under the guise of protecting the Church, for as long as it is necessary.
Chapter Twenty-Nine
Let's now bring together what we've discussed to conclude our exploration of the nature of humanity as a whole.
Initially, we talked about a threefold nature, but this unity in Adam is broken down through the unique traits of his descendants, with distinctions also drawn from their moral differences.
Cain, Abel, and Seth, in a sense, represent the origins of the human race, offering insights into nature and essence.
The chaotic and lost are linked to Cain; the hopeful and intermediate to Abel; and the spiritually destined for certain salvation to Seth.
They differentiate souls further by two properties, good and bad: chaos from Cain, animal from Abel, and spiritual from Seth.
They don't attribute these outcomes to nature, but rather to indulgence, suggesting those given good souls by Achamoth fall into the animal category.
For those with chaotic, or bad souls, they can never perceive what's beneficial.
This nature is considered unchangeable and beyond reform.
Therefore, the small grain of spiritual seed grows through faith, as we mentioned previously:
and through this, these souls excel, such that the Demiurge, once unaware, elevated them.
From this group, he would choose kings and priests:
who, by fully understanding these concepts, naturally become spiritual and are granted certain salvation, rightfully deserved in every sense.
Chapter Thirty
They don't consider necessary tasks important for themselves, nor do they follow any duties of discipline.
They also avoid the need for martyrdom with whatever interpretation they prefer.
They believe this rule is meant for the natural order, that we must work for salvation, which we don't have by privilege of status, but through the support of action.
For us, who are the imperfect essence, this seed is inscribed because we are seen, due to the loves of Philetus, and indeed destined for incomplete development, as their mother.
But woe to us if we have in any way exceeded the yoke of discipline.
If we have become inactive in works of holiness and justice.
If we wish to confess elsewhere, I don't know where, and not under the authorities of this age, in the courts of governors.
They claim their nobility both from accepting life's passivity and from the diligence of sins, with Achamoth flattering them, for she herself also progressed by sinning.
For in honor of the unions of the higher realms, it is said among them that it is always a mystery to be meditated upon and celebrated by attaching to a companion, that is, a woman.
Otherwise, he is considered degenerate and not legitimate in truth, who has not loved a woman, nor joined with her while wandering in the world.
And what will the eunuchs, whom we see among them, do?
Chapter Thirty-One
Now, we reach the conclusion and the distribution of rewards.
When Achamoth has fully harvested her crop and begins gathering it into the barn, or when it's taken to the mills, ground into flour, and hidden in the kneading troughs until it's all leavened, then the completion will be near.
First, Achamoth herself is transferred from the middle region, from the second floor to the highest, restored to the Pleroma.
She is immediately received by the more compact Soter, the bridegroom, and together they form a new union.
This is what the scriptures refer to as the bridegroom and the bride, and the bridal Pleroma.
You might think that, when moving from place to place, the Julian laws also apply, as well as the supper.
Then, the Demiurge will move from the realm under heaven to higher places, into the now empty upper room of the mother, knowing and no longer seeing her.
If this were the case, he would have always preferred to remain unaware.
Chapter Thirty-Two
The human race will face this outcome: those who are marked by earthly and material things will meet total destruction, because all flesh is like grass, and the soul is mortal among them, except for those who find salvation through faith.
The souls of the righteous, which means our souls, will be sent to the receptacles of the Demiurge in the middle realm.
We give thanks, content to be counted with our God, to whom we ascend.
No animal nature is allowed into the palace of the Pleroma, except through the spiritual examination of Valentinus.
There, people are first stripped away, meaning the inner ones.
To be stripped is to lay down the souls with which they were clothed and return them to their Demiurge, from whom they were diverted.
The spirits themselves will become entirely intellectual, subject neither to detention nor observation, and thus, they will be received invisibly into the Pleroma.
In secret, if it is so, then what happens next?
They will be distributed to the angels, companions of the Savior.
Will they become sons?
No.
Will they become attendants?
Not even that.
Will they become images?
If only that.
Into what, then, if it is not shameful to say?
Into brides.
Then they will applaud among themselves like the Sabines seized for marriages.
This will be the reward for the spiritual, the reward for believing.
Such stories are useful, like Marcus or Caius in this flesh with a beard, and all this; a stern husband, father, grandfather, great-grandfather, certainly masculine, in the bridal chamber of the Pleroma by an angel, I have already said by keeping silent, and perhaps you may bear some Onesimus Aeon.
For these weddings to be rightly conducted, instead of a torch and bridal veil, then I believe that a secret fire will burst forth, consuming the entire substance; it will also end with everything turning to ashes into nothingness; and no more tale.
But indeed, I am reckless, having betrayed such a sacrament even in jest.
I must fear lest Achamoth, who did not want to be recognized even by her son, goes mad; lest Philetus becomes angry, lest Fortune grows bitter.
And yet I am a man of the Demiurge, I have to turn there, where after departure, there is absolutely no obscuration; where I am clothed rather than stripped; where even if I am stripped of my gender, I am appointed to the angels; not an angel, not angeless.
No one will do anything to me,
and they'll also see him as a man then.
Chapter Thirty-Three
Finally, like an epilogue to this story, I'll share some insights that I chose to place here so they wouldn't disrupt the narrative or distract the reader with interruptions.
The editors of Ptolemy suggested presenting these differently.
His students, who even surpassed him, claimed that Bythos had a dual nature: Thought and Will.
One wasn't enough, as Thought alone couldn't create anything; but with both, it was easy.
The first union was between Only-Begotten and Truth; reflecting Thought, Truth is female, while reflecting Will, Only-Begotten is male.
The power of Will, which allows Thought to be effective, is seen as male.
Chapter Thirty-Four
Some, with a greater sense of modesty and respect for the honor of divinity, preferred not to assign any gender to Bythos, so as to avoid the disgrace of even a single marriage being associated with it.
Perhaps they use the neuter form to say "This God," rather than the masculine.
Others, however, describe it as both male and female, suggesting that the chronicler Fenestella does not believe hermaphrodites exist solely among the people of Luna.
Chapter Thirty-Five
Some people don't defend the leadership of Bythos itself, but rather something that came afterwards; they introduce the Ogdoad first, derived from the Tetrad but under different names.
First, they propose Proarche, second Anennoeton, third Arrheton, and fourth Aoraton.
From Proarche, they claim Archen emerged in both the first and fifth positions; from Anennoeton, Acatalepton in the second and sixth positions; from Arrheton, Anonomaston in the third and seventh positions; and from the invisible, Agenneton in the fourth and eighth positions.
As for the logic behind placing each entity in two positions, with such interruptions, I'd rather remain ignorant than try to understand it.
How can there be any correctness in these concepts when they are presented in such a distorted way?
Chapter Thirty-Six
How much better are those who have removed all this burden from the equation, not wanting any Aeon to be produced one from another in truly grim steps.
Instead, as they say, "throwing in the towel," they brought forth this team of eight all at once from the Father and his Thought.
They carry names based on his very movement.
When, they say, he thought to bring them forth, he was called Father.
When he brought them forth, because he brought forth truth, this was called Truth.
When he wanted to test himself, he was proclaimed Man.
Those he had pre-thought and then brought forth were then called the Church.
Man uttered the Word, and this is the firstborn Son.
With the Word came Life, and the first Ogdoad was completed.
But this burden is not small.
Chapter Thirty-Seven
Here are some more ideas from Ennius Curruca, a notable teacher, who shared his thoughts with great authority.
He said that first and foremost, there is Proarche, something unimaginable, indescribable, and unnamed, which he refers to as Monoteta.
Alongside this was another power, which he also calls Henoteta.
Monotes and Henotes, meaning Solitude and Unity, when they were one, brought forth the intellectual beginning of everything, uncreated and invisible, which is referred to as the Monad.
Attached to this is a co-essential power, which he calls Union.
These powers—Solitude, Singularity, Unity, and Union—led to the creation of the other emanations of Aeons.
Oh, the difference!
Let Union and Unity, Singularity and Solitude be altered, for even though you have defined them, they are one.
Chapter Thirty-Eight
Now more advanced, Secundus succinctly divides the Ogdoad into two Tetrads: right and left, light and darkness.
However, he chooses not to derive that leaping and failing power from any of the thirty Aeons, but rather from the fruits that come from their substance.
Chapter Thirty-Nine
How much disagreement exists about the Lord Jesus Himself?
Some believe He is formed from the essence of all Aeons, while others argue that He consists only of the ten brought forth by Word and Life.
Thus, the focus of Word and Life is directed toward Him.
Some suggest He is rather made from twelve, descended from Man and Church.
This is why they say He is called the Son of Man.
Others claim He was created by Christ and the Holy Spirit to establish the universe, justifiably as the heir to the Father's name.
There are those who believe the Son of Man should be understood differently, even though they assume the Father referred to humans with this profound name.
What more can you expect from the faith of a God with whom you now compare yourself?
Such notions thrive among them from the abundance of maternal seed.
And so, the expanding teachings of the Valentinians have now become entangled in the complexities of the Gnostics.