For the Catholic Faith
Against the Arian Bishop Pinta Book One.
by Fulgentius of Ruspe
The most faithful foundation of the Catholic faith, after Christ, is the apostles, as the integrity of faith certainly testifies:
Perhaps even when preaching ceases, some secret operation of the Holy Spirit, sown and solidified in the minds of the faithful, continues to work.
Yet who among the faithful does not know that all heresies have originated from the Catholic Church, like useless branches cut off from the vine?
The Church itself remains in its root, in its vine, in its love, and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it Matthew 16:18.
The Church is one, the true Church, the Catholic Church, fighting against all heresies.
It can fight, but it cannot be defeated.
Solomon, in the Song of Songs, speaking from Christ's perspective as he praises his bride, whom we believe to be the Church, says: "Behold, my beloved is like a lily among thorns" Song of Solomon 2:2.
The integrity of its teachings is pricked daily by the doctrines of various heresies like thorns, so that, vigilant against its enemies, it may be exercised, until it stands out like a lily, adorned with its own brightness, in the head of its spouse.
Because some, driven by their own spirit, presumed to call the followers of this faith Homousians or Unisubstantianians, we must respond to their ignorance.
For such and so great is the omnipotent God, that he can pronounce good through the wicked; just as through the wicked high priest John 11:49, he deigned to predict the sacrament of our redemption.
The author of this book, conceived with a cruel mind, thought to oppose a collection of divine testimonies from both the New and Old Testaments against the homousion.
Of such people, the Apostle foretold long ago, saying: "Not knowing what they are talking about or what they so confidently affirm" First Timothy 1:7.
If he knew what homousion means when translated from Greek to Latin, he would strive to praise it rather than reproach it.
Our fathers, three hundred eighteen in number, who devised an antidote to counteract the poison of Arius, did not use words foreign to the Gospel.
Instead, they carefully conveyed the meaning word for word to help those who did not yet understand the true faith.
The Greek term homoousios translates to "one substance." Consult the Gospel and you will find this expressed by the divine mouth: "I and the Father are one." (John 10:30)
Examine the plural and return to the singular truth of the substance.
By saying "I and the Father are one," He declared His and the Father's distinct persons. This countered Sabellius, whom He foresaw would become a heretic, by saying "are" to differentiate between His and the Father's persons. By saying "one," He equally foresaw Arius, who did not hesitate to divide the substance of divinity. Sabellius wrongly combined, and Arius wickedly separated. Sabellius needed to distinguish the persons of the Father and the Son, and Arius needed to avoid separating the substance of divinity in any way.
They consider it a great crime against the faith to associate it with the Catholic Church when they call its followers Homoousians or One-Substance believers, as if homoousios or the substance of divinity contained the name of any man.
Just as the founders of various heresies named their sects after themselves-the Simonists after Simon, the Menandrians after Menander, the Marcionists after Marcion, the Valentinians after Valentinus, the Manichaeans after Mani, the Nepotians after Nepos; and to skip the ancient and almost obsolete heresies, I will mention the newer ones: the Sabellians after Sabellius, the Arians after Arius, the Eunomians after Eunomius, the Macedonians after Macedonius, the Apollinarians after Apollinaris, the Nestorians after Nestorius, the Donatists after Donatus, the Maximianists after Maximianus, the Rogatists after Rogatus; and others who are called Christians in name only, not in deed, who, having abandoned God, revere the names of their founders.
Let him who thought homoousios should be accused among the Catholics, teach us if homoousios is the name of any man.
It seems to me that if the most brilliant summit of the Gospel had not become known to all nations more clearly than light, the Arians might have been able to eradicate the very words of the Lord from the Gospel; that is, ai and the Father are one (John 10:30).
The Fathers established the term homoousion (of the same substance) as this word was translated from the word.
What they assert among the unlearned, whether believed by many or few, is because the Nicene Council was celebrated with 318 Fathers, while they boast that the Council of Ariminum was gathered with 830.
Cunning men tried to interpolate homoousion among the unlearned.
I will briefly relate that homoousion prevailed among the few, so that it became known to other bishops throughout the world, who rejoice to be adorned by its confession.
If the later Council of Ariminum was gathered with such a multitude, as they claim, the bishops of their sect would have multiplied throughout the world, the people would have increased, and such faith would have occupied even the empires.
However, the cunning of that fraud was recognized by wise and reputable men, and homoousion was confirmed.
Today, we can barely see the remnants of Ariminum to prove the Catholics.
Let us consult the city of Ariminum itself, where this fraudulent matter was conducted or rather concocted.
I do not know if it has a bishop of that sect, but I will assert more freely about Milan, where Auxentius, a cunning artisan, spread the poisons of his sect.
His successor Ambrose, filled with the Holy Spirit, so thoroughly destroyed his doctrine that Auxentius' name was erased from the memory of the living in that very city after his death, and his name is now considered a kind of contagion.
Through Ambrose, the faith of Emperor Gratian was strengthened, and the growth among bishops and people increased more and more.
For the Almighty God, who promised the growth of His Church through all Scriptures, could not desert His promise and allow falsehood to grow.
This should be said about all heresies.
However, in the following parts, with God's help, who instructs the heart and guides the tongue, we will present testimonies about one God, the power and invisibility of the Son's equality with the Father, and the divinity of the Holy Spirit.
This Trinity, whether they acknowledge it or not, is still one God.
If they do not love the darkness of contention, they will inevitably see the light of truth.
And let no one be disturbed by our statement that the growth of the Church has been promised throughout all Scriptures.
If they claim it has been achieved through this oppression, let them know it is written in Jeremiah:
"The partridge will cry out, gather those she did not bear, she will make her wealth not justly" (Jeremiah 17:11).
This is clear evidence that the Catholic faith has always grown through tribulations and persecutions:
to fulfill what was said, "For it is through many tribulations and hardships that we must enter the kingdom of God" (Acts 14:21).
The growth of that faith is testified by the exile of the innocent, the proscription of the wretched, and the torments and oppression of captives.
But I see some objectors raising arguments, and the Donatists accusing us of persecutions, whose fury has caused violence to the laws, and they have suffered these things because of the laws.
For if the Catholic mother has received some of them with a compassionate embrace, without any harm to baptism, without any loss of burden, without any insult to the Holy Spirit:
those who were converted willingly might grieve because love was hidden from them for so long.
The first voice of God: "Hear, O Israel, the Lord your God is one God"
Deuteronomy 6:4.
In Deuteronomy: "The Lord alone led them, and there was no foreign god with them"
Deuteronomy 32:12.
Also there: "See now that I, even I, am He, and there is no god besides me"
Deuteronomy 32:39.
In Exodus: "You shall have no other gods before me"
Exodus 20:3.
Also: "Whoever sacrifices to any god, except to the Lord alone, shall be utterly destroyed"
Exodus 22:20.
Also: "You shall worship the Lord your God, and Him only shall you serve"
Deuteronomy 6:13.
Also: "There is no other god in heaven or on earth who can do such works and mighty deeds as Yours"
Deuteronomy 3:24.
In the prophet Hosea: "You shall know no God but me, and besides me there is no savior"
Hosea 13:4.
In Isaiah: "I, I am the Lord, and besides me there is no savior; I declared and saved, and there is no strange god among you"
Isaiah 43:11.
As said above: "Thus says the Lord, who created the heavens; He is God, who formed the earth and made it; He established it; He did not create it empty, He formed it to be inhabited: 'I am the Lord, and there is no other'"
Isaiah 45:18.
"By myself I have sworn; from my mouth has gone out in righteousness a word that shall not return: 'To me every knee shall bow, every tongue shall swear allegiance'"
Isaiah 45:23-24.
As said above: "From of old no one has heard or perceived by the ear, no eye has seen a God besides you"
Isaiah 64:4; and, "Before me no god was formed, nor shall there be any after me"
Isaiah 43:10.
"I am the first, and I am the last; besides me there is no god"
Isaiah 44:6.
In the Book of Psalms: "For who is God, but the Lord?"
Psalms 18:31.
Also: "Who is so great a god as our God? You are the God who works wonders"
Psalms 77:13-14.
Also: "That they may know that you alone, whose name is the Lord, are the Most High over all the earth"
Psalms 83:18.
This especially applies to the Son. In the Books of Kings, Hezekiah against Sennacherib: "O Lord, the God of Israel, you are God alone of all the kingdoms of the earth"
2 Kings 19:15.
The one above, our Lord God, save us from their hands so that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you alone are Lord.
(Second Kings, chapter 19).
Solomon, in his prayer, stretched out his hands to heaven and said: "Lord God of Israel, there is no God like you, neither in heaven above nor on earth below." (First Kings, chapter 8, verse 23).
And although two or three testimonies about one God would be enough, let those who introduce two gods to us still listen.
They confess God the Father and God the Son: this is certainly true; but whoever does not honor the Son as he honors the Father is impious.
For if sacrifice or honor is due to the Father, it is also due to the Son.
But when you claim the Father is greater and the Son is lesser, you introduce two gods: in both cases, you are sacrilegious, by not listening to "The Lord your God is one God." (Deuteronomy, chapter 6, verse 4) and by not honoring the Son as you honor the Father.
The Son did not insert any ranks.
Ask the Father about the honor due.
You strive for the disrespect of both, the Father, because his Son is not listened to, of whom the Father says, "Listen to him." (Matthew, chapter 17, verse 5) and the Son, whom you dare to despise in his command.
But now let other testimonies about the equality of the Father and the Son be proposed.
Testimonies about the Equality of the Father and the Son.
In Revelation, "And he had written on his robe and on his thigh, King of kings and Lord of lords" (Revelation 19:16; First Timothy 6:15).
If the Apostle says this about the Father, here it is clearly said about the Son.
In the same book, "Blessed and holy is the one who has a part in the first resurrection. Over these, the second death has no power: but they will be priests of God and of Christ, and will reign with him" (Revelation 20:6).
In the same book, "I am the Alpha and the Omega, the beginning and the end. To the thirsty I will give from the fountain of the water of life without payment. The one who conquers will inherit these things, and I will be his God, and he will be my son" (Revelation 21:6).
In the same book, "And I saw no temple in the city, for its temple is the Lord God the Almighty and the Lamb" (Revelation 21:22).
No difference.
In the same book, "Then the angel showed me the river of the water of life, bright as crystal, flowing from the throne of God and the Lamb" (Revelation 22:1).
One throne, not two.
In the same book, "The throne of God and of the Lamb will be in it, and his servants will worship him" (Revelation 22:3).
In the Epistle of John, "Everyone who does not continue in the teaching of Christ does not have God. Whoever continues in the teaching has both the Father and the Son" (Second John 9).
The Son first.
In the Epistle of Jude, "Denying our only Master and Lord, Jesus Christ" (Jude 4).
Both God and Lord.
In Revelation, "They call to the mountains and the rocks, 'Fall on us and hide us from the face of him who sits on the throne and from the wrath of the Lamb, for the great day of their wrath has come, and who can stand?'" (Revelation 6:16).
One, or equal judgment.
In the same book, "Salvation belongs to our God who sits on the throne, and to the Lamb" (Revelation 7:10).
In the same book, "The kingdom of the world has become the kingdom of our Lord and of his Christ, and he shall reign forever and ever" (Revelation 11:15).
He shall reign, not they shall reign.
In the same book, "And I heard a loud voice in heaven, saying, 'Now the salvation and the power and the kingdom of our God and the authority of his Christ have come'" (Revelation 12:10).
No division.
In the same book, "Then I looked, and there was the Lamb standing on Mount Zion, and with him were one hundred forty-four thousand who had his name and his Father's name written on their foreheads" (Revelation 14:1).
Does it make a difference because the Son was named before, where there is one power?
As mentioned earlier, these were purchased from among humans, the first fruits to God and the Lamb.
Revelation 14:4.
As mentioned earlier, these will fight with the Lamb, and the Lamb will conquer them because He is Lord of lords and King of kings.
Revelation 17:14.
What more does the Father have?
Let it be said.
To the Hebrews, when God promised to Abraham, since He had no one greater by whom to swear, He swore by Himself saying:
Hebrews 6:13.
If it is said about the Father, He will be visible; if about the Son, He will not be greater than Him.
The Father in the Gospel: So that all may honor the Son just as they honor the Father.
John 5:23.
And because He has the one who sent Him, this mission is not from place to place.
For even the sun sends rays, and it is not separated from itself.
Likewise, just as the Father gives life to the dead, so the Son gives life to whom He wills.
John 5:21.
Behold the Son, to whom He wills; behold the Spirit, where He wills.
The Son says to Philip: Whoever has seen me has seen the Father.
John 14:9.
And again: Do you not believe that I am in the Father and the Father is in me?
John 14:11.
Behold the equality of the Father and the Son.
Likewise, Father, glorify Your Son, that Your Son may glorify You.
John 17:1.
Equal power.
But these are enough about the equality of the Son with the Father.
Testimonies about the divinity of the Son.
In the Book of Job: "He alone stretches out the heavens and walks on the sea as on dry land" (Job 9:8).
In the Book of Jeremiah: "This is our God, and no other will be considered besides Him; He found the entire path of wisdom and gave it to Jacob, His servant, and Israel, His beloved. After this, He was seen on earth and lived among men" (Baruch 3:36-38).
Is it because the person of the Son is expressed here, by saying, "No other will be considered besides Him," that we separate the Father from divinity?
In the Book of Isaiah: "Egypt is weary, and the merchandise of Ethiopia. Many will come to you and be your servants; they will walk behind you, bound in chains; they will worship you and pray to you, saying, 'Surely God is with you, and there is no other God; we did not know. God of Israel, our Savior'" (Isaiah 45:14-15).
Here, not only the divinity of the Son but also His supreme equality with the Father is shown.
For what is said, "Surely God is with you, and you are God," is also stated in the Gospel: "I am in the Father, and the Father is in me" (John 14:11).
To the Romans: "Their ancestors are theirs, and from them comes Christ, who is God over all, blessed forever" (Romans 9:5).
The proper divinity of the Son.
To the Corinthians, second letter: "He is the image of the invisible God" (Second Corinthians 4:4).
If He is the image, He is the truth.
Where it is said: "God was in Christ, reconciling the world to Himself" (Second Corinthians 5:19).
If God is whole, not in part.
To the Ephesians: "To preach the incomprehensible riches of Christ" (Ephesians 3:8).
Are these Christ's alone and not the Father's?
To the Colossians: "For in Him, all the fullness of the deity dwells bodily" (Colossians 2:9).
Note here that it is all the fullness and the deity: where nothing can be added.
Where it is also said: "That God might show the riches of His mystery among the nations: which is Christ" (Colossians 1:27).
Behold, the riches of God is Christ.
Where it is also said: "That in the knowledge of God's mystery, which is Christ: in whom are hidden all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge" (Colossians 2:3).
Complete fullness.
To the Philippians:
Who, being in the form of God, Philippians 2:6.
You hear "form," and you deny equality?
Elsewhere: Now may our God and Father himself and our Lord Jesus Christ direct our way to you, First Thessalonians 3:11.
See, both direct: equal power.
To Timothy, first letter:
That you keep this commandment without spot, until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ, which God will bring about in his own time-God, the blessed and only Ruler, First Timothy 6:14.
Does saying "the only Ruler" exclude the Father from power?
To Titus:
For the grace of God has appeared that offers salvation to all people, Titus 2:11.
While we wait for the blessed hope-the appearing of the glory of our great God and Savior, Jesus Christ, Titus 2:13.
If the Son is the great God, nothing is lesser.
Elsewhere: But when the kindness and love of God our Savior appeared, Titus 3:4.
Here, neither his humanity nor his divinity is left unspoken.
John to the Parthians:
That we may believe in his true Son, Jesus Christ.
He is the true God and eternal life, First John 5:20.
In this testimony, anyone who denies the Son's perfection as God is the Antichrist.
Second Peter:
For in this way, the entrance into the eternal kingdom of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ will be abundantly provided to you, Second Peter 1:11.
And although these few testimonies about the deity of the Son are like drops lifted from the vast sea of the Scriptures themselves:
Since all Scripture bears witness to both his deity and his humanity assumed for our sake, as he himself says in the Gospel according to John:
Search the Scriptures, because you think that in them you have eternal life; and it is they that bear witness about me, John 5:39.
He did not say, "About us," so as not to introduce two gods.
In Luke, Jesus said to them:
These are the words which I spoke to you while I was still with you, that everything written about me in the Law of Moses and the Prophets and the Psalms must be fulfilled, Luke 24:44.
Does he exclude the Father from the testimony of the Scriptures because he says here, "About me"?
On the omnipotence of the Son in Solomon:
Your all-powerful word, Lord, came from the royal thrones of the heavens
(Wisdom 18:15).
In Zechariah:
Oh, flee from the land of the north, says the Lord: for I will gather you from the four winds of heaven.
The Lord says: In Zion, be saved, you who dwell in the daughter of Babylon.
Therefore, the Lord Almighty says this: After glory, he sent me to the nations that plundered you.
Therefore, whoever touches you, touches the apple of his eye.
Therefore, I will raise my hand against them, and they will become plunder for those who plundered them; and you will know that the Lord Almighty sent me
(Zechariah 2:2 and following).
The Almighty above, sends below:
are there two almighty beings?
The prophet Amos:
The Lord who touches the earth and makes it tremble, and all who dwell in it will mourn; and it will rise like the river of Egypt, who builds his ascent on heaven, and confirms his remission on earth: who calls the waters of the sea, and pours them over the face of the earth: the Lord Almighty is his name
(Amos 9:5).
Do not all these things apply to the Son?
Who, descending, touched the earth, moved it with his suffering, and ascended from earth to heaven, and descended upon the earth from heaven, as he himself promised in Revelation
(Revelation Chapter 3, 14):
This is what the faithful witness, the beginning of God's creation, says: He who is, and who was, and who is to come, the Lord Almighty
(Revelation 1:8).
It moves because he said, the Beginning of God's creation;
let it move because it was said, the Lord Almighty:
so that this refers to divinity; that, which was born of the Virgin Mary.
Testimonies about the Trinity.
In the Gospel:
Go, baptize the nations in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit (Matthew 28:19).
Notice it says "in the name," not "in the names."
Likewise: The kingdom of heaven is like a woman who hid leaven in three measures of flour until the whole batch was leavened (Matthew 13:33).
Here, the woman represents the Church, which hides the faith of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit in the hearts of believers.
In Revelation:
Holy, holy, holy is the Lord God Almighty (Revelation 4:8).
I hear "holy" three times, but there is one Lord God.
In the same book: And the angel said to me: These are the true words of God.
And I fell at his feet to worship him; and he said to me: See that you do not do that; I am your fellow servant, and of your brethren who have the testimony of Jesus, and the spirit of prophecy (Revelation 19:9-10).
What could be clearer to show the Trinity, except the true words of the Father, the testimony of the Son, and the gift of prophecy of the Holy Spirit?
In the Psalms:
With you is the fountain of life, and in your light we see light (Psalm 36:9).
With God the Father is the fountain of life, Christ; and because there is light in Him, the Holy Spirit is seen as the illuminator; because whoever does not have the Spirit of Christ does not belong to Him (Romans 8:9).
In Psalm 67:7: May God bless us, our God, may God bless us, and may all the ends of the earth fear Him.
I hear "God" three times, and He proclaims one to be feared.
In the Epistle of John:
There are three who bear witness in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Spirit: and these three are one (First John 5:7).
What can I say about the patriarch Abraham?
When he saw the appearance of three men, he recognized one God among them, when he said: Lord God (Genesis 18:3).
He showed hospitality to the three with bodily service; but he received the blessing of offspring from one, when it was said to him: I will return at this time, and Sarah will have a son (verse 10).
He did not say "we will return," but "I will return," so as not to introduce a multitude of gods.
To understand that the Trinity dwells together and avoids impurity together, listen to what the Lord says in the Gospel:
"Whoever loves me will be loved by my Father, and I will love him"
(John 14:21); and,
"We will come, my Father and I, and we will make our home with him"
(John 14:23).
See, the Father and the Son dwell in one home.
What about the Holy Spirit?
Listen to the Apostle saying:
"You are the temple of God, and the Spirit of God dwells in you"
(First Corinthians 3:16).
The Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are shown to dwell together; let it also be shown that the Trinity avoids impurity together.
From Solomon, you have:
"Perverse thoughts separate from God": this refers to the Father.
"For Wisdom will not enter a deceitful soul": this refers to the Son.
"For the Holy Spirit of discipline will flee deceit, and will withdraw from thoughts that are without understanding"
(Wisdom 1:3, 4, 5): this refers to the Holy Spirit.
But to understand the meaning of the Scriptures about the nature of the Trinity together, you also have in Exodus:
"I am the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob"
(Exodus 3:6).
In the Psalm:
"The Lord lives, and blessed be my God, and let the God of my salvation be exalted"
(Psalm 18:47).
Paul:
"The same Spirit, the same Lord, the same God"
(First Corinthians 12:4, 5, 6).
Does it offend the Catholic sense because the Spirit is named first?
Also, if you seek the Trinity called the Lord, listen:
"Give to the Lord glory and honor, give to the Lord glory due to his name"
(Psalm 29:2).
Because the King is the Trinity:
"Lift up your heads, you princes, and be lifted up, you everlasting doors, and the King of glory shall come in.
Who is this King of glory?
The Lord of hosts, he is the King of glory"
(Psalm 24:9).
Testimony is given, God is repeated three times, the Lord is called King three times.
Neither gods, nor lords, nor kings are distinct, because in three names and persons they are discerned: for there is one deity, one dominion, one royal power.
Whoever contradicts this truth with a desire to win wrongly, I do not say will be condemned, but is already condemned.
Testimonies about the Holy Spirit, that He is God.
At the beginning of the book of Genesis:
And
the Spirit of God was hovering over the waters
(Genesis 1:2):
He who would sanctify the waters in the figure of baptism, not who would rest by growing weary.
In Job:
The divine Spirit made me, and the Spirit of the Almighty teaches me
(Job 33:4).
In divinity, perfection.
In the Gospel:
God is Spirit, and those who worship Him must worship in spirit and truth
(John 4:24).
Also:
For God does not give the Spirit by measure
(John 3:34).
Behold, the Spirit is boundless.
To Nicodemus:
The Spirit blows where it wishes, and you hear its sound, but you do not know where it comes from or where it goes
(John 3:8).
When you hear, "where it wishes," it is its own power.
Christ himself:
The Spirit of the Lord is upon me
(Luke 4:18).
Unless a pious understanding recalls these words, the Spirit would be greater than the Son.
Also:
Jesus, full of the Holy Spirit, returned from the Jordan
(Luke 4:1).
Similar understanding.
Also:
If then you see the Son of Man ascending to where he was before.
It is the Spirit who gives life; the flesh is of no benefit
(John 6:63).
He who gives life lacks nothing of deity.
Also:
When the Advocate comes, the Spirit of truth, whom the Father will send in my name, he will guide you into all truth and teach you
(John 16:13).
God is the one who will guide into all truth.
In the Acts of the Apostles, Peter to Cornelius:
Jesus of Nazareth, whom God anointed with the Holy Spirit
(Acts 10:38).
A man was anointed, not God.
Also to Ananias:
Why has Satan filled your heart to lie to the Holy Spirit
(Acts 5:3)?
And he adds:
You have not lied to men, but to God
(Acts 5:4).
Also:
The Holy Spirit says:
Set apart for me Barnabas and Saul for the work to which I have called them
(Acts 13:2).
Here he does not introduce the persons of the Father or the Son, yet sane understanding does not separate them from the command.
Also, the Apostle to the Gentiles through a letter:
It seemed good to the Holy Spirit and to us not to burden you with anything beyond these essentials:
abstain from idols, from fornication, and from blood
(Acts 15:28).
Is this command given without the Father and the Son?
Also, the Spirit said to Peter, "Get up and go with them, because I have sent them to you" (Acts 10:19).
Does not the Creator command the creature?
Also, from Miletus, Paul sent to Ephesus and called the elders and the older men (Acts 20:17); and after much exhortation, he said: "Take care of the flock of Christ, in which the Holy Spirit has made you bishops" (Acts 20:28).
Is the Father or the Son separated from this ordination of the priest?
Paul to the Romans: "But the Spirit is eternal life and peace" (Romans 8:6).
This is the Father, this is the Son, this is the Holy Spirit; but one life, not three.
Where it says: "The Spirit is life because of righteousness" (Romans 8:10).
This is the Father, this is the Son.
Where it says: "But if the Spirit of Him who raised Christ from the dead lives in you" (Romans 8:11).
What kind of God is this who raised the flesh of the Creator from the dead?
Where it says: "For you have not received the spirit of slavery" (Romans 8:15).
No one is free except God, who is the Holy Spirit.
Where it says: "May the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, so that you may abound in hope and the power of the Holy Spirit" (Romans 15:13).
Just as Christ is the power of God, so is the Holy Spirit.
Where it says: "So that the offering of the Gentiles may be sanctified by the Holy Spirit" (Romans 15:16).
The Spirit gives life and also sanctifies.
Where it says: "For I will not venture to speak of anything except what Christ has accomplished through me to bring the Gentiles to obedience, by word and deed, by the power of signs and wonders, in the power of the Holy Spirit" (Romans 15:18-19).
Power of the Son, power of the Spirit, power of the Father; but one, not three.
To the Corinthians: "The Spirit searches everything. No one knows what belongs to God except the Spirit of God" (First Corinthians 2:10-11).
Where it says: "You are the temple of God, and the Spirit of God dwells in you" (First Corinthians 3:16).
God is the one who dwells in His temple.
Where it says: "You were washed, you were sanctified in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, and in the Spirit of our God" (First Corinthians 6:11).
Behold, the Son and the Holy Spirit cleanse together, sanctify together.
Where it is written:
"All these are the work of one and the same Spirit, and he distributes them to each one just as he determines" (First Corinthians 12:11).
He freely does what he wants and is subject to no one.
To the Corinthians, second letter:
"A letter written not with ink, but with the Spirit of the living God" (Second Corinthians 3:3).
The spirit of a person is not less than the person; how much more the Spirit of God!
Where it is written:
"The letter kills, but the Spirit gives life" (Second Corinthians 3:6).
The one who gives life is God: for the Lord brings death and makes alive (First Samuel 2:6).
To the Galatians:
"That we might receive the blessing of the Spirit through faith" (Galatians 3:14).
It is God who blesses.
Where it is written:
"Since we live by the Spirit, let us keep in step with the Spirit" (Galatians 5:25).
The one who blesses also gives life as God.
Where it is written:
"Whoever sows to please the Spirit, from the Spirit will reap eternal life" (Galatians 6:8).
In these three testimonies to the Galatians, the Spirit blesses, gives life, and grants eternal life.
To the Ephesians:
"When you believed, you were marked in him with a seal, the promised Holy Spirit" (Ephesians 1:13).
We are sealed in the name of the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
Where it is written:
"In him you too are being built together to become a dwelling in which God lives by his Spirit" (Ephesians 2:22).
Also:
"It has now been revealed by the Spirit to his holy apostles and prophets that the Gentiles are heirs together" (Ephesians 3:5).
All these are the work of one and the same Spirit: he makes us heirs.
Where it is written:
"I pray that out of his glorious riches he may strengthen you with power through his Spirit" (Ephesians 3:16).
Only God strengthens.
Where it is written:
"Make every effort to keep the unity of the Spirit through the bond of peace" (Ephesians 4:3).
Peace is Christ.
Are there two peaces?
Where it is written:
"Take the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God" (Ephesians 6:17).
The word of God is Christ; the Holy Spirit is the word of God.
Are there two words?
To the Philippians:
"Whether I come and see you or only hear about you in my absence, I will know that you stand firm in one Spirit" (Philippians 1:27), which means in God.
To the Thessalonians:
"God chose you as firstfruits to be saved through the sanctifying work of the Spirit" (Second Thessalonians 2:13).
To Timothy, first letter:
"Beyond all question, the mystery from which true godliness springs is great: He appeared in the flesh, was vindicated by the Spirit" (First Timothy 3:16).
Look, even the incarnation of Christ is sanctified by the Holy Spirit.
Second Timothy: Guard the good deposit that was entrusted to you-guard it with the help of the Holy Spirit who lives in us.
Second Timothy 1:11.
If God were not Spirit, the Apostle would not dare to adjure the disciple by Him.
Moreover, who lives in us.
To Titus: He saved us through the washing of rebirth and renewal by the Holy Spirit.
Titus 3:5.
Peter to the Gentiles: It was revealed to you through those who preached the gospel to you by the Holy Spirit sent from heaven, things into which angels long to look.
First Peter 1:12.
God is the one whom angels desire to look into.
Further on: Christ died for our sins, the righteous for the unrighteous, to bring you to God.
He was put to death in the body but made alive in the Spirit.
First Peter 3:18.
Further on: So that they might be judged according to human standards in regard to the body, but live according to God in regard to the spirit.
First Peter 4:6.
Further on: If you are insulted because of the name of Christ, you are blessed, for the Spirit of glory and of God rests on you.
First Peter 4:14.
The glory of the Father is Christ, the glory of the Holy Spirit.
Are there two glories?
Second Peter: Above all, you must understand that no prophecy of Scripture came about by the prophet's own interpretation of things.
For prophecy never had its origin in the human will, but prophets, though human, spoke from God as they were carried along by the Holy Spirit.
Second Peter 1:20-21.
No one inspires the gift of prophecy except God.
John to the Parthians: This is how we know that He lives in us: We know it by the Spirit He gave us.
First John 3:24.
Further on: This is how we know that we live in Him and He in us: He has given us of His Spirit.
First John 4:13.
He gave, what you hear, is the operation of power, not the separation of divinity.
In Revelation: But after three and a half days the breath of life from God entered them, and they stood on their feet.
Revelation 11:11.
What proceeds from God is God.
Further on: Write this: Blessed are the dead who die in the Lord from now on.
"Yes," says the Spirit, "they will rest from their labor."
Revelation 14:13.
The Father did not say it, the Son did not say it, but the Spirit, who by this command is shown to be God.
To the Hebrews: If the blood of bulls and goats, and the ashes of a heifer sprinkled on those who are defiled, can sanctify them for the purification of the flesh, how much more will the blood of Christ, who through the Holy Spirit offered himself without blemish to God (Hebrews 9:13-14)!
This passage teaches us about the power of the Holy Spirit, through whom the flesh of Christ is presented as spotless.
Elsewhere: Anyone who disregards the law of Moses dies without mercy on the testimony of two or three witnesses.
How much worse punishment do you think will be deserved by those who trample the Son of God, profane the blood of the covenant, and insult the Spirit of grace (Hebrews 10:28-29)?
See the kind of vengeance that awaits those who insult the Son and the Holy Spirit.
Elsewhere: God, the judge of all, and the spirits of the righteous made perfect, and Jesus Christ, the mediator of the new covenant (Hebrews 12:23).
This passage pertains to the Trinity, as the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are all mentioned here.
Because the Holy Spirit is almighty, in Solomon: The Holy Spirit is manifold, subtle, eloquent, secure, untainted, possessing all virtue (Wisdom 7:22).
And you deny he is almighty?
Because the Holy Spirit is a judge, the Lord says: If I go away, I will send him to you; and when he comes, he will convict the world concerning sin, righteousness, and judgment (John 16:7-8).
You see the judge, who even vindicates the Savior himself, and yet some dare to deny his divinity?
And what more shall I say about the divinity of the Holy Spirit?
David fears him, saying: Where can I go from your Spirit, or where can I flee from your presence (Psalm 139:7)?
To conclude, the Holy Spirit is so great and powerful that if anyone blasphemes against him, they will find no forgiveness, neither in this age nor in the age to come.
Catholic Faith.
It is impossible to express the ineffable nature of Divinity with human words:
unchangeable, immutable, impassible, simple, uncompounded, indivisible, inaccessible light, inexplicable power, limitless greatness, inconspicuous glory, desirable goodness, unparalleled beauty, which touches and moves the affection of a pure mind but cannot be indicated or explained.
Where the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are, the only nature that is not created, the power of dominion, and natural goodness reside.
The Father is the beginning of all, the cause of all, the root of the living:
from whom proceeds the fountain of life, the power, and the unchanging image of the invisible God, who is the Son begotten by the Father.
The Word, or living reason, always was, was with God, and was God.
Not made from the Father before ages, nor later assumed or adopted as a son, not by possession or creation, but the creator and maker of all:
who is everything that the Father is; to whom the Father gave everything he has by begetting.
And thus, he who gave, gave by begetting; and he who received, received by being born; not helping the needy, but the abundance itself was born.
For he who received cannot be unequal to him who gave, because he also received by being born to be equal.
For he who said: "All that the Father has is mine" (John 16:15) has nothing less than the Father.
And because he emptied himself, taking the form of a servant, not losing the form of God, in the same form of a servant he became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross;
in which he was made a little lower than the angels, so that he might remain equal in the form of God;
for that form is not changeable.
In heaven, pure intellectual spirits, in the form of God and equal to God, serve as an example.
They offer this example to fallen man, who, due to the impurity of sins and the penalty of mortality, could not see God:
God emptied himself, not by losing his divinity, but by taking on our humanity.
Taking the form of a servant, he came into this world, which was made through him John 1:10, to be an example to those looking up to God and to those marveling at man below.
He serves as an example for the healthy to remain steadfast, for the weak to recover, for the dying to not fear, and for the dead to rise again; holding the primacy in all things.
Since man ought not to follow anyone to happiness except God, and could not perceive God, by following God made man, he follows both whom he can perceive and whom he ought to follow.
Let us love him and cling to him, with love spread in our hearts by the Holy Spirit who has been given to us.
This Spirit is both life and life-giving light, illuminating; good and goodness; the upright Spirit, the principal Spirit, who is the Lord of all; sending apostles, setting apart ministers, establishing temples, inspiring at will, and distributing the gifts of the Spirit as he wills.
The Spirit of adoption, the Spirit of truth, the Spirit of wisdom and understanding, of knowledge, counsel, strength, and fear of God: through whom the Father is acknowledged, and the Son is glorified.
For it is not fitting, nor has the Son ever been absent from the Father, nor the Spirit from the Son: for the divinity would be greatly deprived and seen as inglorious and unworthy if, as though through repentance and backward planning, God had reached the fullness of perfection.
Let anyone who can accept this accept it Matthew 19:12; whoever cannot yet, let him pray to accept it, believe to accept it: because it is written: Unless you believe, you will not understand Isaiah 7:9, according to the Septuagint.