Commentary on the Revelation of Saint John
by Primasius of Hadrumetum
Book Five
Chapter Eighteen
After this, I saw another angel coming down from heaven with great power, and the earth was illuminated by his brightness.
This symbolizes the destruction of worldly wisdom, much like the fall of Jericho.
When describing the downfall of an earthly kingdom, he mentions that this angel has great power, indicating that a stronger force has come to battle a strong one.
This suggests that the true light of wisdom has arrived, overshadowing worldly wisdom, and showing the wise of the world and earthly kings who rely on their strength that it is invincible in both power and knowledge.
He says, "The earth was lit up by his brightness."
And he cried out with a loud and strong voice, saying, "Babylon the great has fallen, and has become a dwelling place for demons, and a refuge for every unclean spirit, and for every unclean and hateful bird."
I believe this signifies the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, whom Isaiah refers to as the angel of great counsel.
In his first coming, as mentioned in Matthew, "Repent, for the kingdom of heaven is near," he was dismantling the efforts of secular power.
The earth was illuminated by his brightness because he is the true light that enlightens every person who comes into this world.
However, the next part might trouble some readers, as it says, "It has become a dwelling place for demons, etc."
If Babylon has fallen, how has it become a dwelling place and refuge for demons, unclean spirits, and birds?
Perhaps it is because, by falling into many transgressions, it has made itself suitable for the habitation of demons, with its healthy part destroyed by its dissolute lifestyle.
What once rose in the sea of this world against the faith of Christ with strong waves of persecution now groans, restrained within narrower bounds, and rages enclosed like a bottled-up storm.
As we sing in the Psalm, "He gathers the waters of the sea like in a bottle, he places the deeps in storehouses."
What was once feared by Christians now fears Christians, as they witness the decrees of princes granting privileges to the religious and even to soldiers.
However, part of it has become a dwelling place and refuge for demons, where it is destroyed all around and rebuilt for the better.
It is shattered and toppled in its pride, rightfully said to have fallen to ruin.
It is signified by spiritual wickedness in the form of birds, as confirmed in the Book of Genesis, where it is said that Abraham drove away the birds descending upon the divided carcasses.
(Genesis 15)
Because all nations have drunk from the wine of her wrath and fornication, and the kings of the earth have committed fornication with her, and the merchants of the earth have been enriched by her excessive luxuries.
Here he names three kinds of vices and introduces the same number of persons who transgress: greed, which according to the Apostle is called idolatry; (Ephesians 5) lust, in the name of fornication; (Colossians 3) and gluttony, which the Lord warns against, saying: Do not let your hearts be weighed down with carousing and drunkenness.
(Luke 21)
He says the kings of the earth have committed fornication with her.
Greed is implied when he says the merchants have been enriched, although some prefer to interpret this as wealth gained through sins rather than resources, designating nations as the mixed multitude of common people.
Kings are those who seem to excel temporarily among them, and merchants are those who, longing for earthly gains, exchange their souls for temporal abundance in an unfortunate trade, acting contrary to the teachings of the Lord, who says: What can a man give in exchange for his soul?
(Matthew 16)
I heard another voice from heaven saying.
The hearing of the heavenly voice is for those whom He foreknew and predestined to be conformed to the image of His Son; (Romans 8) and, The Lord knows those who are His; (Second Timothy 2) and similar things.
Finally, it follows: Come out of her, my people, so that you do not partake in her sins.
So far, it seems to me this pertains to the first coming, where, until the end of the age, the good tolerate the evil mixed among them.
This way, they neither consider abandoning the good nor following the evil through harmful imitation.
Thus, the prophetic words are fulfilled in Isaiah fifty-two: "Depart from their midst, and do not touch anything unclean," since the righteous should not mix with the wicked, not by physical departure but by departing from the most wicked will.
It continues: "And do not be struck by their plagues, for their sins have reached up to heaven, and the Lord God remembers their iniquities, and therefore repays them double. And in the people with whom they mixed, double is mixed back to them: and as much as they glorified themselves and lived in luxury, so much torment and grief is given to them, because she says in her heart, 'I am a queen, I am not a widow, and I will never see mourning.' Therefore, her plagues will come in one hour, death, mourning, and famine, and she will be burned with fire, for the Lord who judges her is mighty."
All these things are believed to pertain to the second coming when, at the examination of the final judgment, the company of the wicked will be excluded and justly punished, so that those who sinned temporarily will be punished eternally.
This is what is meant by: "Repay her double, and double has been mixed back to her," so that those who enjoyed fleeting pleasures will be tormented with eternal suffering.
And Christ is foretold in the Psalm to free his own from usury. Psalm seventy-one says: "He will redeem their souls from usury and iniquities."
Those, however, are said to be burned with perpetual fire, afflicted by famine: then indeed, when those who now hunger and thirst for righteousness, as stated in Matthew chapter five, will receive incorruptible satisfaction.
Truly, they die because God abandons them. For just as the body dies when the soul departs, so the soul is believed to die when God abandons it.
Moreover, the mourning for them is what Christ says in the Gospel of Luke.
Woe to those who laugh now, for you will mourn and weep.
God, wanting to show His people unharmed from these plagues, says: Do not be struck by His plagues.
It is as if He were saying: Since you did not want to change your ways and be like sinners, you will not receive the same punishment.
We cannot avoid these plagues by our own strength; it is granted to us only by the grace of God.
But the Holy Spirit, keeping the proper order, wanted to declare that those who are pious in heart are not captivated and are in no way tormented by the approval of the wicked.
For the souls of the righteous are in the hand of God, and torment will not touch them.
Wisdom 3.
In this way, He outlines future events, showing that the punishments to come should not be considered as of this world, as they will soon conclude the final course, as proven by the following.
For the Lord, predicting the destruction of the world, added:
Luke 21: But the end is not immediate.
And the kings of the earth who committed adultery with her and lived in luxury will weep and mourn over her when they see the smoke of her burning.
Standing far off because of the fear of her torment, they will say: Woe, woe, the great city, Babylon, the mighty city, for in one hour your judgment has come.
And the merchants of the earth will weep and mourn over her, because no one buys their merchandise anymore.
How is it certain that the same Babylon is referred to by different names, whether from the kings of the earth, from the nations, or from the merchants, if they are said to stand far off from her burning, lamenting her not with shared suffering but with a pitiable consideration?
Unless, as I have said, we should not take this as the absolute end of the world here, but as a reduction of human affairs and the destruction of various nations.
For he says that the pomp of worldly riches will be taken away, through which, to fulfill wicked desires, the opportunities of carnal pleasures surrounded, somehow offering the occasion for importunity.
When this is removed due to deficiency and desolation imposed by divine judgments, certain survivors are reported to mourn the destruction of others.
Therefore, they are said to stand at a distance and fear similar punishment.
Perhaps this pertains to the fact that they are said to see the smoke of the fire as a sign of eternal fire.
Smoke indeed gives an indication of future flames.
It then describes if there are any things necessary for human use, if there are any things known to be useful for worldly purposes, greatly desired by the greedy and carnal, but also those things that are delightfully known to be enjoyed by the well-known five senses of the flesh, and it pronounces them to be gone, in this way:
The merchandise of gold and silver and precious stones and pearls and silk.
Up to this point, it is about the utility of places.
Thus, purple and scarlet cloth, and every kind of cedar wood and every vessel of ivory made from precious wood, and bronze, and iron, and marble.
Up to this point, it also mentions things related to the sense of sight.
The same applies to what pertains to the sense of smell, following: And cinnamon, and incense, and ointment.
From ointment, it also includes touch: and frankincense, he says.
Therefore, he added things reduced to taste and use, saying: and wine, and oil, and wheat.
Furthermore, he places beasts and cattle, and horses, and carriages, and slaves, and animals of various kinds for the sake of utility.
He also says: The desire of your fruits of your soul has departed from you.
This also refers to sight and taste.
And all those rich and splendid things have perished from you, and you will no longer find them.
Your merchants who became wealthy from it will stand at a distance because of the fear of its punishment, weeping and mourning, and saying, Alas, alas, that great city, clothed in purple and fine linen and scarlet, and adorned with gold and precious stones and pearls, in one hour such great wealth has been destroyed.
The hour here is proven to be placed for a time by the judgments of many testimonies, and every shipmaster, and everyone who sails anywhere, and sailors and all who live by the sea, will stand at a distance: seeing the smoke of its burning, saying: What city is like this great city?
They will throw dust on their heads, symbolizing their blame on their leaders who deceived them and led to their downfall.
They will cry, weeping and mourning loudly: "Woe, woe to that great city, where all who had ships on the sea became rich from her wealth, because in one hour she has been destroyed."
Since many are often moved to repentance by such destruction, if we consider those places as a warning related to the people, it makes sense that they will stand at a distance and cry out, seeing the smoke of her burning.
This implies that it's better to avoid falling with the lost and instead achieve stability through sudden conversion. Their Lord makes them stand or fall, which should be understood not as physical standing, but as a firm conversion of the mind in faith.
So, when they mourn for others who are perishing, they are understood to be doing fruitful penance. Hence, the Apostle says in Ephesians chapter 2: "When you were dead in your trespasses and sins, in which you once walked according to the course of this world, according to the prince of the power of the air, the spirit that is now at work in the sons of disobedience, among whom we all once lived in the desires of our flesh, doing the will of the flesh and the mind, and were by nature children of wrath, like the rest of mankind."
According to these words of the Apostle, this place can be applied to the persons of the converted. For no one can be found good who was not first bad. Hence, the Psalm 118: "I have regarded all the sinners of the earth as transgressors"; perhaps this follows: "Rejoice over her, O heavens and saints and apostles and prophets, for God has judged your judgment on her."
And a mighty angel took up a stone like a great millstone and threw it into the sea, saying: "So will Babylon the great city be thrown down with violence and will be found no more."
We know that the Lord said in the Gospel of Matthew...
"Woe to the world because of offenses, and to those who cause them: Woe to the person through whom the offense comes; it would be better for them if a millstone were put around their neck and they were thrown into the sea, than to cause one of these little ones to stumble. This means that the authors of offenses should be punished with such a penalty. This is not only to be taken in the context of litigious offenses but of every kind of sin, according to the rule which the Holy Scripture states, either by the Lord saying (Matthew 18:9): 'If your eye, foot, or hand causes you to stumble,' or by Paul the apostle in First Corinthians (First Corinthians 11:29): 'Who is offended, and I do not burn?
'
To this sense, the Psalm (Psalm 121:6) concurs, saying: 'The sun shall not harm you by day, nor the moon by night,' where even false beliefs about Christ and the Church, that is, about the sun and the moon, are admitted, or about the sins of adversity and prosperity, which refer to the moon or the sun, all seem to be included under the general term of offenses.
This also implies that the author of the offense, that is, any sin, should be drowned like a millstone.
The millstone here seems to represent the weight of sins, which are contracted from temporal matters.
For the Lord teaches that the millstone is placed in the circle of worldly affairs when he says: 'Two women will be grinding at the mill, and the sound of harpists, musicians, flutists, and trumpeters will no longer be heard in you.
' He had deferred the sound of those five senses, which he now fully expresses, and also predicted that they would be taken away, as if to say: 'Whatever is beautiful to the sight, sweet to the ear, pleasant to the touch, delightful to the smell, and enjoyable to the taste, will pass away from the world.
'
And not satisfied with this, he added also about those things which pertain to the use of human life, saying: 'No craftsman of any craft will be found in you anymore, and the sound of the mill will no longer be heard in you, nor will the light of a lamp shine in you, and the voice of the bridegroom and bride will no longer be heard in you.
' And he says the reason why: 'because your merchants were the great men of the earth, because by your sorceries all the nations were deceived.
'"
It's like saying: Because you misused temporal goods in your life, you will justly be deprived of them further and condemned to eternal punishments.
In you, the blood of the prophets and saints was found, along with all those killed on earth.
This makes it clear that the entire body of the devil is rebuked for its excesses in one city, Babylon.
We don't know if prophets and martyrs were killed in the same city, but there is one city in the society of the impious.
It follows.
Chapter Nineteen
After this, I heard the voice of a great multitude shouting loudly in heaven, saying:
Hallelujah.
Salvation and glory to our God, because His judgments are true and just, for He has judged the great prostitute who corrupted the earth with her immorality, and He has avenged the blood of His servants at her hands.
And again they said: Hallelujah.
The Lord testified something similar in the Gospel, saying that the blood of the righteous, from Abel the just (Matthew 23:35) to Zechariah son of Berechiah, summarizes the people and priests.
Therefore, He also mentioned the place, saying, "whom you killed between the temple and the altar," referring the temple to the people and the altar to the priests.
When they said again, Hallelujah, the Church continuously praises God for His judgments.
Hallelujah means, "praise the Lord."
It follows about the prostitute: "And her smoke rises forever and ever."
The Church, continuing in His praise of joy, sees the smoke of the wicked's destruction remain.
Just as smoke indicates the beginning of fire, so with the fire continuing, smoke is said to exist.
The Lord illustrated the example of these good and evil in the story of the rich man and Lazarus (Luke 16).
And the twenty-four elders and the four living creatures fell down and worshipped God who sits on the throne.
This refers to the Church.
It follows, saying: "Amen," which means true, faithfully.
And a voice came from heaven, saying: "Praise your God, all His servants, and those who fear Him, small and great."
With this command, He also mentions it being done, indicating that He accepted the pleasing praise of His chosen ones, approving the former and declaring it perpetual.
The great ones in the Church, of whom the Apostle says: "We speak wisdom" (First Corinthians 2:6), among the mature.
And the Lord says (Matthew 5:19): "Whoever teaches others to do so will be called great in the kingdom of heaven."
The little ones, of whom He says (First Corinthians 1:27).
Like little children in Christ, I gave you milk to drink, not solid food.
And I heard the voice of great trumpets and the voice of mighty thunder, and the sound of many waters saying: Alleluia.
These trumpets signify preaching, as Isaiah says in Isaiah 18: "Cry out, do not hold back, raise your voice like a trumpet," where the fear of divine judgment is also suggested.
I believe this is signified by the name thunder because it is fitting for humans. Therefore, many waters usually symbolize the peoples who praise God, saying: Alleluia.
Thus, the Church, when it preaches, fears, and praises, exults with trembling, as it is written: "Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoice with trembling."
For the Lord Almighty has reigned. It rightly remembers His omnipotence here. For He made out of nothing what did not exist, sought those who perished in sin, found those to be punished, and mercifully made righteous those He wanted from them. From these, He constructed the Church for Himself, giving it such a gift that He made it His bride, although it had not deserved even to be a servant.
It continues: "Let us rejoice and exult and give Him glory, for the wedding of the Lamb has come, and His bride has prepared herself. And it was given to her to clothe herself in fine, bright, and pure linen." For the fine linen is the righteous deeds of the saints.
No one of spiritual understanding doubts that all these things fit the Church of the elect. They surely prepare themselves for His spiritual marriage by always insisting on works of righteousness.
And he said to me: "Write: Blessed are those who are called to the supper of the Lamb." About this, the Lord says in Matthew 8: "And they will recline at the table with Abraham and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven;" and likewise: "He will come and serve them," indicating those who are called holy according to the purpose and pass into the fullness of the elect.
For many are called, but few are chosen (Matthew 20).
And again he said to me: "These are the true and just words of God."
Then it is divinely said to the Church when the Word of God and the same truth are revealed.
And I fell at his feet to worship him.
But he said to me, "See that you do not do that, for I am your fellow servant, and of your brothers who hold the testimony of Jesus Christ. Worship God."
At the beginning of this book, I mentioned that the Lord Christ revealed everything to John through an angelic being. Here, it becomes clear that this being does not allow himself to be worshipped as God. Instead, he identifies as a fellow servant and teaches that only God should be worshipped.
This might surprise the reader because the angel also says, "I am the first and the last" (Revelation 1).
We should understand that this was said by the angel speaking on behalf of Christ.
In Revelation 22, it states, "I, Jesus, have sent my angel to testify to you these things in the churches."
It follows, "For the testimony of Jesus is the spirit of prophecy." The entire essence of prophecy and the sanctification of the spirit lie in the testimony of Jesus Christ, to whom all law and prophecy serve.
When Jesus manifested himself on the mountain (Matthew 17; Mark 9; Luke 9) between Moses and Elijah, his face and clothing shone brightly.
He declared that he has the testimony from the law and the prophets.
For if they foretold anything, he himself testified that it serves Christ and the Church.
Speaking of Moses, he said (John 5), "He wrote about me." And when he rose, he said (Luke 24), "It is necessary for all things which are written about me in the law of Moses, the prophets, and the Psalms to be fulfilled."
Even though the mysteries of Christ might not seem obvious, they are embedded in the Scriptures. The entire series of Scripture is constructed in such a way, like an organ producing a harmonious melody. Each part contributes to the whole, creating a unified and meaningful message.
Then, summarizing more briefly, he says, "I saw heaven opened; and behold, a white horse, and he who sat on it was called Faithful and True."
This is the one who was previously said to have received the deserved crown of victory, the fair and just judge, who fights as the king of all ages fights, who always shares in the suffering of his members.
He fights when he wins, crowns himself, but provides strength to those who strive, and promises a reward to those who overcome (Wisdom 2).
His eyes were like a flame of fire, and on his head were many diadems.
In him, we will find strength (Psalm 59), and the multitude of saints is said to have a crowned beauty.
He has a great name written that no one knows except himself.
The perfect knowledge of the Word of God is revealed to those who have earned the right to be the body and members of Christ.
The head specifically grants knowledge of itself to the body, but he knows what the Church has merited to know in him.
For he who is joined to the Lord, says the Apostle (First Corinthians 6), is one spirit; for they will be two in one flesh.
This name neither Jews, nor foreigners, nor heretics have known.
For if they had known, they would never have crucified the Lord of glory (First Corinthians 2).
Furthermore, the world, he says (John 17), has not known you.
And again, he says to his disciples (John 14): You will see me, because I live, and you will live.
On that day, you will know that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you.
Therefore, the disciples also reply: Lord, what has happened that you are going to reveal yourself to us, and not to the world?
As for the heretics, he says to them again (Matthew 13; Mark 4): To you, it has been given to know the mystery of the kingdom of God, but to those outside, everything is in parables, so that seeing, they may see and not understand.
Having a great name written, that no one knows except himself.
It is important to be cautious, to avoid thinking that the name of the Son, which we're discussing now, is unknown to either the Father or the Holy Spirit.
Using this opportunity and the customary expressions of Scripture, we see clearly that just as the Son alone is said to know, the entire Trinity is also taught to know.
Similarly, if something is said to be known only by the Father, it is understood that He knows it with His wisdom, which is Christ, or with His Spirit, who is believed to be the Spirit of both the Father and the Son.
For instance, when the day of judgment is said to be known by the Father alone, it is not denied that the Son and the Holy Spirit also know.
Likewise, if the Holy Spirit alone is said to know something and the names of the Father or the Son are not mentioned, it is still declared that they know as well.
In First Corinthians chapter 2, the Apostle says, "No one knows the things of a man except the spirit of the man who is in him, so also no one has known the things of God except the Spirit of God." It is foolish to separate the Father or the Son from this knowledge.
Similarly, in Ephesians chapter 4, it says, "Do not grieve the Holy Spirit of God, by whom you were sealed for the day of redemption." Although the Father and the Son are not mentioned, their role in our redemption is not excluded, since the works of the Trinity are inseparable due to their indivisible nature.
In the Gospel of Mark chapter 13, when it says that the Son does not know the day of judgment, but only the Father knows, it is understood that by knowing something, He enables others to know, and by not knowing, He withholds that knowledge. Therefore, we understand that the name of the Son, which is said to be known only to Him, is actually known to the Father and the Holy Spirit.
It is evident when it is said of the Son, "He was clothed with a garment dipped in blood, and His name is called the Word of God." If no one is permitted to know His name, why is the Word of God openly preached? As we read in John...
No one has ascended to heaven except the one who came down from heaven, the Son of Man, who is in heaven.
We understand that if any of the members ascend, they do so because of the head and through the head, who earned the right to ascend.
He promised this to his members and will make it happen.
This means that only Christ is said to know, because his bride, the Church, is allowed to know through him and in him.
The Church is taught through him.
When he speaks of the garment of Christ stained with blood, he describes the signs of his suffering, whether in the head or in the body, which is the Church.
The Apostle teaches in the Letter to the Hebrews (Hebrews) chapter three, that from the beginning, the remission of sins is not celebrated without blood in those legal sacrifices of animals.
Regarding the Church, he also says in the Letter to the Colossians (Colossians) chapter one, "To fill up what is lacking in the sufferings of Christ in my flesh," remembering the voice he heard in the Acts of the Apostles (Acts) chapter three: "Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me?" For whatever the Church suffers, Christ is truly said to suffer.
The same Apostle says in the Letter to the Hebrews (Hebrews) chapter nine: "He suffered once to take away the sins of many." Isaiah also recalls this garment in Isaiah chapter sixty-three: "Who is this coming from Edom, with garments stained from Bozrah? This one who is majestic in his apparel, striding in the greatness of his strength. It is I, proclaiming justice, mighty to save. Why are your garments red, like those of one treading the winepress? I have trodden the winepress alone; from the nations no one was with me."
And the armies in heaven followed him on white horses. In heaven, in the Church, as though with unveiled faces, they behold the glory of the Lord as written in Second Corinthians (Corinthians) chapter three.
All those who are pure in heart, cleansed by grace beyond snow, as mentioned in Psalm fifty-one, are said to follow Christ.
They are dressed in pure white linen, which earlier was defined as the righteousness of the saints.
They distribute their own to each one, subjecting both body and soul to God.
They proceed on white horses, that is, pure in body and mind, always following in Christ's footsteps, to whom it is said in the Song of Songs (Song) (of) (Solomon) chapter one: "We will run after you in the scent of your ointments."
And from his mouth came a sharp, double-edged sword, so that with it he might strike down the nations.
He will rule them with an iron rod.
The double-edged sword could symbolize the dual nature of the testament or what we read about in the Book of Proverbs, Chapter 31: "He carries the law and mercy on his tongue," like judgment and mercy. The iron rod represents immutable justice, and he himself trampled the winepress of the wrath of the great and almighty God.
Just as, when the threshing floor is approached, the grain is separated from the chaff and stored in barns, so in the winepress, under pressure, either wine is meticulously separated from the grapes, or oil from the olive pulp, as described by the prophet in the Book of Isaiah, Chapter 5: "And I dug a winepress in it." This happens in the Church when, through the adversity of persecution or calamity, some fall like the pulp, while others shine more brightly through commendable cultivation.
He also has a name written on his robe and on his thigh: King of Kings and Lord of Lords. On his robe, which is the Church that Christ is clothed in, which, according to the Apostle Paul in Ephesians, Chapter 5, he cleansed with the washing of water through the word, to present to himself a glorious Church, without stain or wrinkle. Just as a garment is cleansed to avoid stains and stretched to avoid wrinkles.
But on his thigh, his seed's posterity is designated, in which all nations will be blessed, according to the Apostle teaching in Galatians, Chapter 3: "He did not say 'and to seeds,' as if referring to many, but 'and to your seed,' meaning one, which is Christ." To whom, like a deceased brother, according to the law of ancient custom in Deuteronomy, Chapter 25, the same Apostle, spiritually raising the seed, says in First Corinthians, Chapter 1: "Lest anyone say that you were baptized in my name," as he declares that from Jerusalem to Illyricum he has fully proclaimed the Gospel of Christ in Romans, Chapter 15. To these nations, he could truthfully say in First Corinthians, Chapter 4: "In Christ Jesus, through the Gospel, I have become your father."
In this way, therefore, in this thigh, as if in the children propagated, the knowledge of Christ is written not with ink, but with the Spirit of the living God, not on stone tablets, but on tablets of human hearts.
Second Corinthians, Chapter 3.
Those who acknowledge the King of kings and the Lord of all lords, First Timothy, Chapter 1, to whom this inscription of the thigh is attributed, believe in Him and will be blessed with the faithful Abraham.
And I saw an angel standing in the sun.
The angel signifies the Church preaching.
He rightly added "one" because my dove is one, Song of Solomon, Chapter 6, due to the mystery of preserving unity, in the sun, where it now shines clearly and no longer hides out of fear. And he cried out with a loud voice. In the loud voice, great confidence and freedom are to be understood, speaking to all the birds of heaven. Birds are sometimes understood as evil, sometimes good, depending on the context. Here, certainly, just as earlier, the appearance of a flying eagle is introduced, so now the spiritual ones are invited to the feast. About this, it was said to Peter, who bore the figure of the present Church, Acts, Chapter 10: "Kill and eat," when they are killed to become what he is, that is, faithful, and passing into the body, they are grafted into the members of Christ and reign together. For whatever we eat, we transfer into our body. "Come," he says, "to the great feast of God, to eat the flesh of kings, and the flesh of captains, and the flesh of mighty men, and the flesh of horses, and those who sit on them, and the flesh of all free and slave, small and great." The horses and those sitting on them can be understood as leaders, who were in error and those they led astray, because the Church also accepts converts from their number, free men holding celibacy, slaves, married, small people, the common and ignoble crowd, great ones, either philosophers or those elevated by birth or wealth.
And I saw the beast, that is, the devil, and the kings of the earth, and their armies gathered to make war with the one sitting on the white horse and with his army, that is, with Christ and the Church. With the explanation of similar places previously given, this place can also be recognized.
And the beast was captured, along with the false prophet, the devil, and the Antichrist, or the leaders, and the entire body of those who performed signs in its presence.
By these signs, they were deceived into worshiping the image of the beast and those who received its mark.
These two were thrown alive into the lake of fire burning with sulfur.
The head and body of the devil and his company were seized in the narrative; this was yet to come at the end of time.
The rest were killed by the sword of the one sitting on the white horse, which came out of his mouth.
One body was divided into parts to show that even those who were dead would be found alive by Christ's second coming, as we read in Second Thessalonians chapter 2: "Whom the Lord Jesus will kill with the breath of his mouth and destroy with the brightness of his coming." And all the birds were filled with their flesh.
We should not think so carnally as to believe that the saints, seeking higher things, would be filled with the flesh of the wicked. Instead, the divine equality of judgment revealed to the saints, which has determined to condemn the rest while redeeming the fullness of the elect, is said to fill them with the knowledge of this justice. This justice, which in this life one can hunger and thirst for, as mentioned in Matthew chapter 5, but not fully understand.
For Isaiah, speaking by God's command about the wicked, says in Isaiah chapter 66: "And they shall be for a vision of satiety to all flesh." I believe this satiety mentioned here refers to the birds.
For the Apostle also admits here that he has not yet fully understood, saying in Philippians chapter 3: "Not that I have already obtained it or am already perfect, but I press on to make it my own, because Christ Jesus has made me his own."
Therefore, they will not rejoice in their condemnation but because they are already filled with the light of divine justice. Alternatively, the birds in a bad sense can be understood as the fallen angels, who, having led their followers to destruction, are said to be filled with the flesh of the damned, fulfilling their evil desire by the damnation of those they led into error.
Chapter Twenty
I saw a mighty angel coming down from heaven, holding the key to the abyss and a great chain in his hand.
He seized the dragon, that ancient serpent called the devil and Satan, and bound him for 1,000 years.
We understand the angel coming down from heaven as our Lord Jesus Christ, who is called the Angel of Great Counsel Isaiah 9.
Visiting the realm of mortals, he wanted to bind the strong man to transform the vessels of wrath into vessels of mercy, doing in action what he had previously promised in preaching:
No one, he says Matthew 12; Mark 3; Luke 2, can enter a strong man's house and plunder his goods unless he first binds the strong man, that is, the devil.
The key to the abyss represents the depth of divine judgments.
For God's judgments are a great abyss Psalm 36.
It is known only to Him who calls from the multitude of sins into the fullness of understanding.
Hence, elsewhere we read, Who shut up the abyss and sealed it over.
It is said that he bound the devil with chains in that he restrained his power from deceiving those who were to be freed.
The 1,000 years can be understood in two ways:
either because this matter is conducted over many years, that is, in the sixth millennium of years, however long it is extended to the end of the age, whose final periods are now unfolding, followed by the Sabbath that has no evening, the rest of the saints which has no end, so that the last part of this millennium, remaining until the end of the age, is called 1,000 years, in the manner of speaking where a part signifies the whole;
or certainly, he set 1,000 years for all the years of this age, so that the fullness of time is noted by a perfect number.
For the number 1,000 is the square solid of the number ten.
Ten multiplied by ten makes 100, which is already a square figure but not yet full; however, to rise in height and become solid, 100 is again multiplied by ten, and it becomes 1,000.
The meaning of Psalm 105 is now clearer: "He was mindful of His covenant forever, of the word which He commanded to a thousand generations," indicating all generations. And He sent him into the abyss. This certainly refers to the devil being sent into the abyss, representing the countless number of impious people, whose hearts are deeply wicked against the Church of God. It's not that the devil wasn't already there, but he is said to be sent there because, rejected by believers, he began to possess the impious even more. The devil is more present in those who are not only estranged from God but also hate those who serve God without cause. He shut him in and sealed him so that he would not deceive the nations anymore until the thousand years were finished. He shut him in to prevent him from presumptuously going beyond what was forbidden. The sealing seems to signify that it was meant to be hidden who belonged to the devil and who did not. Some of the steadfast ones fall, and some reprobates are saved through fruitful repentance. The devil is restrained by this prohibition from deceiving the nations he used to seduce before they belonged to Christ. For God chose them before the foundation of the world to rescue from the power of darkness and transfer to the kingdom of His beloved Son, as the Apostle says in Ephesians 1. Who among the faithful does not know that the devil now seduces the nations and drags them with him into eternal punishment, but not those predestined to eternal life? For the Lord knows those who are His (Second Timothy 2).
None of these are seduced by him into eternal damnation.
For this reason, the devil is bound and enclosed in the abyss, so that he might no longer deceive the nations from which the Church is made up, which he previously deceived before they were the Church.
It does not say that he would no longer deceive anyone, but that he would no longer deceive the nations, which undoubtedly refers to the Church.
Until the thousand years are completed, he said, that is, either what remains of the sixth day which consists of one thousand years, or all the years by which this age will continue thereafter.
He used "until" not because he would then deceive only those nations from which the predestined Church is made up, from seducing which he is restrained by that chain and bond, as was already mentioned.
Likewise, in the psalm (Psalm 123): As our eyes are on the Lord our God, until He has mercy on us.
It is not to be thought that after He has had mercy, the eyes of the servants are no longer on God.
Certainly, this is the order of words: And he shut and sealed over him until the thousand years were completed, so that he would not deceive the nations anymore.
After this, he said, he must be released for a short time.
If this means that the devil being bound and the Church enclosed cannot be deceived, then will his release mean he can?
No way.
The Church, predestined and chosen before the foundation of the world (Ephesians 1), about which it is said in Second Timothy chapter two, "The Lord knows who are His," is never deceived by him. The binding of the devil means he is not allowed to exercise all the temptation he can, either by force or deceit, to seduce people into his part, either by violent compulsion or deceit.
If he were allowed, in such a long time and with the weakness of many, he would overthrow many. God does not want this to happen, including the faithful; therefore, he is bound: and then he will be released when the time is short. It is read that he will rage with all his power and that of his followers for three years and six months, and those will be such that they cannot be overcome by his great force and schemes. However, if he were never released, his malicious power would appear less, the most faithful patience of the holy city would be less tested, and finally, it would be less apparent how greatly Almighty God has used his evil for good.
This binding of the devil didn't just start when the Church began to spread beyond the land of Judea to other nations.
It is happening now and will continue until the end of the world, when he is to be released.
Even now, when people convert from the unbelief in which he possessed them to faith, the strong one is indeed bound when his possessions are taken from him.
Matthew 12; Mark 3; Luke 11
And he said, "I saw thrones in a vision and those seated on them, and judgment was given to them."
When he said that the devil had been bound for 1,000 years and that his usual power of deception had been taken away, and predicted that he would be released for a short time, he then recapitulated what the Church does or will do during these 1,000 years, saying, "And I saw thrones and those seated on them, and judgment was given to them."
This should not be understood as the final judgment but rather as the governance by the leaders through whom the Church is now governed, which has been deemed worthy by its king to hear the decree, "Whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven; and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven."
Matthew 16
Hence, the Apostle says in First Corinthians 5: "What business is it of mine to judge those outside the Church? Are you not to judge those inside?"
And he said, "the souls of those who had been slain because of the testimony of Jesus and because of the word of God."
It is implied that later he will say here, "they will reign with Jesus for 1,000 years," specifically the souls of the martyrs who have not yet been reunited with their bodies.
For the souls of the righteous dead are not separated from the Church, which is now also the kingdom of Christ; otherwise, their memory would not be celebrated at the altar of Christ in the communion of the body of Christ.
Although they are not yet reunited with their bodies, their souls already reign with him during these 1,000 years.
Hence it is said in this book, Revelation chapter 14: "Blessed are the dead who die in the Lord."
Therefore, the Church now reigns with Christ first in the living and the dead.
For this reason, as the Apostle says in Romans 14: "Christ died and returned to life so that he might be the Lord of both the dead and the living."
But he specifically mentioned the souls of the martyrs because they hold a special place after death, having fought for the truth until the end.
However, from this, we can also understand it to include the rest of the deceased who belong to the Church, which is the kingdom of Christ.
Regarding the phrase, "And those who did not worship the beast or its image, nor received its mark on their foreheads or on their hands," we should interpret this as referring to both the living and the dead.
As for what this beast represents, we must investigate carefully. However, it doesn't stray from the truth to see it as the impious city and the people of unbelievers who oppose the faithful and the city of God.
Its image seems to be a simulation, representing those who pretend to profess the faith but live unfaithfully. These individuals claim to be Christians in name but present a false image, aligning themselves with the same beast.
They are not only open enemies of Christ and his glorious city but also the weeds that will be gathered from his kingdom, the Church, at the end of the age.
And who are those who do not worship the beast or its image? They are the ones who follow what the Apostle says in Second Corinthians:
"Do not be yoked together with unbelievers."
They do not worship, meaning they do not agree or submit. Nor do they receive the mark, which symbolizes the sign of sin-on the forehead for profession, and on the hand for action.
Therefore, being free from these evils, whether still living in this mortal flesh or deceased, they reign with Christ even now in a manner appropriate to this time, signified by the number 1,000 years.
The rest did not live, it says. For now is the time when the dead hear the voice of the Son of God, as stated in John Chapter 5, and those who hear will live. Therefore, the rest will not live.
What he added, "until the thousand years are finished," means that during that time, they did not live as they should have, transitioning from death to life.
Therefore, when the day comes for the resurrection of the bodies, they will not come out of the tombs to life but to judgment, specifically to damnation, which is called the second death.
For until the thousand years are finished, whoever has not lived during this time when the first resurrection occurs and has not heard the voice of the Son of God to transition from death to life, will indeed pass into the second death with their flesh in the second resurrection, which involves the flesh.
As it follows, "This is the first resurrection. Blessed and holy is he who has a part in the first resurrection." That is, whoever has a share in it. He indeed has a share in it, who not only revives from death in sins but also remains in that revival. In these, he says, the second death has no power.
Therefore, it has power over the rest, about whom he said earlier, "The rest of them did not live until the thousand years were finished," because throughout this interval of time, which he calls a thousand years, however long each of them lived in the body, they did not revive from death.
When he said, "In these, the second death has no power," he added, "The priests of God and Christ sat and reigned with him for a thousand years," which is not said only of bishops and priests, but also of all Christians because of the mystical anointing. So, all are priests since all are members of one priest, about whom the apostle Peter says, "A holy nation, a royal priesthood" (First Peter 2).
And when the thousand years are finished, Satan will be released from his prison and will go out to deceive the nations in the four corners of the earth, Gog and Magog, and will gather them for battle, whose number is like the sand of the sea.
At that time, he deceives them to drag them into battle: for even before, he was deceiving in many ways and through various evils.
He went out, it is said, into open persecution and burst forth in the latest persecution by judgment.
Therefore, the whole Church and the cities of Christ endure this from the entire city of the devil, affecting everyone on earth.
Furthermore, some suspect that these nations, Gog and Magog, are the Getae and the Massagetae because of the first letters of their names.
But by considering the interpretation of the names, we understand them better.
For Gog means "roof," and Magog means "from the roof," like a house and the one who comes out of it.
Therefore, the nations are those in which we previously understood the devil to be enclosed, as if in an abyss. He brings himself forth from them, so they are the roof, and he is from the roof.
If we refer both to the nations, not one to them and the other to the devil, they are the roof because the enemy is now enclosed and covered in them. They will be from the roof when they burst into open hatred.
As for what he said: "And they went up over the breadth of the earth and surrounded the camp of the saints and the beloved city," it does not mean they came to one place, as if the camp of the saints and the beloved city were in one location. This represents the Church of Christ, spread over the whole world.
Wherever it will be at that time, in all nations, as signified by the term "breadth of the earth," where the camps of the saints will be, there the city beloved by God will be.
There, it will be surrounded by the cruelty of that persecution from all its enemies, pressed in the straits of tribulation, urged, and enclosed. It will not abandon its military service, which is called by the name of the camps.
As for what he said: "And fire came down from heaven and devoured them," it should not be thought to be the final punishment by which we know the wicked will be tormented, as stated in the Gospel of Matthew.
Rather, it is the fire of envy by which the adversary will be tormented because of the firmness of the saints. For it is a firmament, whence stability comes to the saints, and deservedly, it is said that fire comes to the persecutors from there.
So, we read, "Jealousy seized an uneducated people, and now fire will consume the adversaries."
This latest persecution, which will come from the Antichrist, will last for three years and six months and is forthcoming.
Although this time is short, it's debated whether it pertains to the thousand years during which the devil is said to be bound and the saints are to reign with Christ, or if this small interval is to be added outside of those years.
If we say it pertains to those same thousand years, the reign of the saints with Christ would extend for a longer period than the binding of the devil.
Surely, the saints will reign with their King, especially during this persecution, overcoming such great evils, even when the devil is no longer bound and can pursue them with all his might.
How, then, does this scripture designate both the binding of the devil and the reign of the saints within the same thousand years, when the binding of the devil is first marked by an interval of three years and six months before the reign of the saints with Christ ends in those thousand years?
However, if we say that this small period of persecution should not be counted within the thousand years but rather be added after they are completed, it can be properly understood.
For when he said, "The priests of God and of Christ will reign with Him for a thousand years," he added, "And when the thousand years are completed, Satan will be released from his prison."
This way, it signifies that both the reign of the saints and the binding of the devil will cease simultaneously.
Thus, if the time of that persecution is believed not to pertain to the reign of the saints nor to the custody of Satan, both of which occur in the thousand years, but to be added outside and counted separately, we are compelled to admit that the saints will not reign with Christ during that persecution.
But who would dare to say that His members will not reign with Him then, when they will cling to Him most firmly and strongly? At that time, as the assault of the battle becomes more intense, the greater will be the glory of not yielding, and the denser the crown of martyrdom!
Therefore, the years during which the saints reign with Christ are longer than the years of the devil's binding and imprisonment.
The saints will continue to reign with their King, the Son of God, even after the devil is no longer bound for those three and a half years.
So, when we hear, "The priests of God and Christ will reign with Him for 1,000 years," and when the 1,000 years are completed, Satan will be released from his prison. We must understand that the 1,000 years of the saints' reign do not end, but the 1,000 years of the devil's binding and imprisonment do. Each period has its own distinct length, with the reign of the saints being longer and the devil's binding being shorter.
Certainly, because the very short period of three and a half years was not counted, or because the reign of the saints seems to have more importance, as we often find in sacred scriptures.
After this, the mention of the final persecution briefly encompasses everything that, during the last judgment, the devil and his principal adversary city will suffer. For it says: "And the devil who deceived them was thrown into the lake of fire and sulfur, where the beast and the false prophet will be tormented day and night forever and ever." The beast is rightly understood to be the wicked city itself, and the false prophet is either the Antichrist or that image, that is, the falsehood spoken of here: "And I saw," he says, "a great white throne and the One seated on it, from whose face the earth and heaven fled away, and no place was found for them."
He says he saw Him seated on the throne, from whose face the earth and heaven fled away. Afterwards, when the judgment is completed, heaven and earth will cease to exist, and a new heaven and a new earth will begin, meaning the transformation of things, not their complete destruction. This world will pass away, as the Apostle also says in First Corinthians chapter 7: "For the form of this world is passing away." Therefore, the form passes away, not the nature.
"And I saw," he says, "the dead, great and small, and the books were opened, and another book was opened, which is the book of life of each one, and the dead were judged according to their deeds by what was written in the books."
He mentioned that the books were open, but he didn't stay silent about what kind of book it was.
Therefore, they are understood to be the books of the New and Old Testaments.
When it is shown what God commanded to be done, it is made clear in those books what each person has done or not done.
This book should not be thought of in a physical sense, nor imagined to contain the lives of each person written down to be reviewed at judgment.
Rather, it should be understood as some divine power, by which each person's deeds, good or bad, are recalled to memory and seen with the mind's eye with amazing speed.
This way, knowledge accuses or excuses the conscience, and thus all are judged both individually and collectively.
This divine power has taken the name "book."
In it, everything recalled through its action is, in a way, read.
To show that the dead were judged, both small and great, he mentions again, as if returning to what he had previously said but delayed.
And the sea gave up the dead which were in it, and death and hell gave up the dead which were in them.
This undoubtedly happened before the dead were judged.
Therefore, he recapitulated what he had skipped; now, keeping the order, he says: and each one was judged according to their deeds.
But who are the dead that the sea gave up, if not those whom the second coming of Christ finds in the world?
Both the good and the bad are implied by the name 'dead': the good, to whom it is said in Colossians chapter 3:
For you have died, and your life is hidden with Christ in God;
and the bad, of whom it is said in Matthew chapter 8 and Luke chapter 9:
Let the dead bury their own dead.
The dead can also be called so because they bear mortal bodies; hence the Apostle in Romans chapter 8:
The body is indeed dead because of sin, but the spirit is alive because of righteousness, demonstrating that both exist in the living person in this body.
Therefore, he says the sea gave up: because they appeared as they were found.
But death and hell gave up, because they were brought back to the life from which they had already departed.
It's not enough to simply mention "death" or "hell," so both are referenced: death for the good, who can endure death but not hell; and hell for the wicked, who suffer punishments there.
If it seems reasonable to believe that even the ancient saints who had faith in the coming Christ were in places far from the torments of the wicked, and remained in hell until Christ's blood and His descent rescued them, then surely afterward, the good and faithful, already redeemed by that precious offering, know nothing of hell until they receive their bodies and the rewards they deserve.
When he said, "and each was judged according to their deeds," he briefly added how: "Death and hell," he said, "were cast into the lake of fire." These names signify the devil, as he is the author of death and infernal punishments, along with the entire company of demons.
This is indeed what he had previously stated more clearly: "And the devil, who deceived them, was thrown into the lake of fire and sulfur." What he had added there more obscurely, saying that the beast and the false prophet, here he states more openly, "And those who were not found written in the book of life were cast into the lake of fire."
This book is not yet mentioned so that it may be forgotten, but it signifies the predestination of those to whom eternal life will be given. God does not need to read this book to know them; rather, His infallible foreknowledge is the book of life in which they are written, that is, foreknown beforehand.
But after the judgment foretold for the wicked, it remains to speak also of the good.
Chapter Twenty-One
And I saw, he said, a new heaven and a new earth.
For the first heaven and the first earth had passed away, and the sea was no more.
This will happen in the order that he previously mentioned, when he said he saw someone sitting on the throne, from whose face heaven and earth fled.
Once the wicked are judged and condemned, the figure of this world will pass away in the conflagration of worldly fires, just as the flood happened by the inundation of worldly waters.
With heaven and earth transformed for the better, the bodies of the saints will be suitably adapted to the new quality of both transformations with incorruption and immortality.
The world, renewed for the better, will be suitably adapted to men also renewed for the better.
But as for his statement: And the sea was no more, whether it will be dried up by that great heat, or even transformed for the better, I cannot easily say.
For we read that there will be a new heaven and a new earth Isaiah 55.
However, I do not recall reading anything about a new sea.
If perhaps, as is customary, prophetic speech mixes metaphors and veils what is said, he could have referred to that sea whose name is known to signify this turbulent and stormy mortal life.
For at that time, this turbulent and stormy mortal life will no longer exist, which the name of the sea represented.
And he said, I saw the great city, the new Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, prepared as a bride adorned for her husband.
And I heard a loud voice from heaven saying: Behold, the dwelling place of God is with men, and he will dwell with them, and they will be his people, and God himself will be with them.
And God will wipe away every tear from their eyes, and there will be no more death, nor mourning, nor crying, nor pain, for the former things have passed away.
And he who was seated on the throne said: Behold, I make all things new.
This city is said to descend from heaven because it is by the heavenly grace that God made it, which is why he also says through Isaiah: I am the Lord who makes you Isaiah 45.
From heaven indeed, it descended from the beginning.
Throughout this age, with the grace of God coming from above through the washing of regeneration in the Holy Spirit sent from heaven, its citizens continually increase.
But through God's final judgment by His Son Jesus Christ, such great and new glory from God's gift will appear that no traces of oldness will remain, as even our bodies will transition from old corruption and mortality to new incorruption and immortality.
Hence, He promises, saying: God will wipe away every tear from their eyes, and death will be no more, neither will there be mourning, nor crying, nor pain anymore.
All these things belong not to this life, but to the future life.
For now, in this life, the holier a person is and the fuller they are of holy desires, the more they excel in weeping during prayer.
Hence, we read in Psalm 14: My tears have been my bread day and night, and in Psalm 46: I will wash my bed every night, and similar things.
And He said to me: These words are most faithful and true, and He said to me: It is done.
These things must be believed, not explained, especially because He says it has been done in the past, so that no one may doubt the future.
I am Alpha and Omega, the first and the last.
Just as He testified this at the beginning of the book, it had to be repeated in this third part, so that no one believes there is a God before Him, as Isaiah says in Isaiah 41, nor another after Him.
I will give to the thirsty from the fountain of the water of life freely.
From this fountain, He waters the unbelievers on the way, offering them abundant drink in the homeland to those who conquer.
So that the strangers in this desert may not fail from thirst, when they become citizens, they may be continually intoxicated from the torrent of God's delights.
Both are free because, as the Apostle says in Romans 6, The grace of God is eternal life.
It follows: Whoever conquers will inherit these things, and I will be their God, and they will be my child.
Here He remembers that generation, of which the Apostle says in Galatians 4: God sent the Spirit of His Son into our hearts, crying, Abba Father.
If we are children, then we are also heirs-heirs of God and co-heirs with Christ.
But we have been saved by hope. Romans chapter 8.
When hope brings us to reality, God Himself will be the reward of eternal happiness for the chosen ones, which they will possess forever.
However, for the doubtful and the unbelievers,
this should be understood in this context, as mentioned by the Apostle James.
James chapter 1: "A double-minded man is unstable in all his ways."
And for the abominable, the murderers, the sexually immoral, the sorcerers, those who worship idols, and all liars, their part will be in the lake of fire which burns with sulfur, which is the second death.
These crimes and punishments should not simply be understood but rather considered on how to avoid them through God's grace.
And one of the seven angels, who had the seven bowls full of the last seven plagues, came and spoke to me.
Just as the number seven often represents completeness in good things, it can also represent the entirety of plagues in bad things.
If those mentioned earlier were poured out, now they are said to be full; it is surprising how the world stayed silent despite being afflicted.
Unless he preferred to briefly touch on what he had discussed in detail before, so as not to omit the mention of evils, and then quickly turn his attention to the good figure of the Church, about which it is sung.
Psalms chapter 27: "I believe I shall see the goodness of the Lord in the land of the living."
Finally, it continues: "And he spoke to me, saying: Come, I will show you the bride, the wife of the Lamb, which is the Church.
And he took me to a great and high mountain, and showed me the holy city, Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God."
This is, according to the testimony of Truth, the city set on a hill.
Matthew chapter 5.
Hence Isaiah chapter 2: "In the last days, the mountain of the Lord's house will be established as the highest of the mountains, and will be exalted above the hills."
Whether it is for the height of its righteousness about which we read.
Isaiah chapter 41: "Your righteousness is like the mighty mountains,"
or because mountains are often referred to as both apostles and prophets.
However, the Lord Christ stands out above all, like a mountain at the peak of mountains.
From His fullness, we have received grace upon grace.
And rightly so, from Heaven by God; it appears more beautiful when believed to be conceived and born through the Spirit, of which He is the bridegroom, deserving to bear the heavenly image.
Therefore, the bride, who is also the city, has the light of God's glory.
To whom the Lord says in Matthew chapter 5: You are the light of the world.
This voice applies to the whole body of Christ, which the apostles received from the mouth of Truth at that time and with prior merits.
And what illuminates her is like a most precious stone, like a jasper stone, shining like crystal.
Although jasper and crystal are different types and colors, due to their similarity, both are joined here and compared to the most precious stones.
It was meant to be understood as revealed with Christ, of whom blessed Peter says in First Peter chapter 2: The stone, a precious cornerstone, laid in the foundation.
And it has a great and wide wall with twelve gates, and at the gates twelve angels, with names written of the twelve tribes of the sons of Israel.
The wall of the Church is Christ, whom we read as great and high.
Great to the Lord and highly praised, in the city of our God, on His holy mountain, and the Lord is exalted above all nations.
Psalms chapter 48, chapter 145, and chapter 113.
About the wall, the prophet Isaiah says in chapter 26: On that day this song will be sung in the land of Judah: Our city of strength is Zion; the Savior will place a wall and a rampart in it.
Open the gates, and let the righteous nation, keeping the truth, enter; the old error has gone away.
Containing the same spirit, they seem to tell similar things.
Finally, it follows about the gates, saying: And twelve gates, and at the gates twelve angels, and names written of the twelve tribes of the sons of Israel.
Indeed, we know that through the twelve apostles, our Lord provided the beginning of the entry to faith for everyone in different ways.
However, the circumstances of this place have diverted us from our initial intention, as it mentions the twelve tribes of the sons of Israel.
It seems to first refer to the twelve patriarchs, from whose lineage the entire nation of the Israelites was propagated.
According to the Apostle Paul, the remnants were saved by the election of grace, adding that God did not reject His people.
We should understand the twelve patriarchs as being represented by the same number of gates.
Remember, it is not you who support the root, but the root that supports you.
It clearly says, the names of the twelve tribes of the sons of Israel were written.
Hence, the Apostle confidently declares: They are my kinsmen according to the flesh, who are Israelites.
To them belong the adoption as sons, the glory, the covenants, the giving of the law, the service of God, and the promises.
The fathers are theirs, and from them is Christ, according to the flesh, who is over all, God blessed forever.
The angels here signify those elders and leaders by whose guidance and governance that nation was wonderfully ruled.
If we remember that they are often called gods, it is not surprising if we believe they are called angels.
It says, they will be brought to the gods; and, I said, you are gods, and all of you are sons of the Most High, reflecting the entirety of the whole people, which consists of leaders and people.
There are three gates to the east, three gates to the north, three gates to the south, and three gates to the west.
This makes twelve, a number often sacredly suggested to us through the apostles and their seats for the fullness of the whole.
It says, you will sit with me on twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel.
For the odd number three, when multiplied by the even number four, makes twelve.
It follows: And the wall of the city has twelve foundations, and on them are the names of the twelve apostles of the Lamb.
After mentioning the patriarchs, he remembers the apostles.
Since we know that the Church has only one foundation, which is Christ, we shouldn't be disturbed by the statement that it has twelve foundations here.
The apostles deserved to be the foundations of the Church in Christ, about whom the Apostle says:
First Corinthians 3: "No one can lay any foundation other than the one already laid, which is Jesus Christ."
The apostles are also described as light in Him when it is said to them:
Matthew 5: "You are the light of the world," even though Christ, the true light that enlightens every person coming into this world:
John 1: "is the sun."
Thus, Christ is the illuminating light, and they are the illuminated light. The holy Scripture frequently hints at many things similar to those said to us.
Indeed, the Apostle James says:
James 1: "He chose to give us birth through the word of truth, that we might be a kind of firstfruits of all he created."
However, the Apostle Paul confidently says:
First Corinthians 4: "In Christ Jesus, I became your father through the gospel."
God generates through the adoption of grace, and Paul generates in Christ either through the administration of the sacrament or through the preaching of doctrine, mindful of the divine admonition that says:
Matthew 23: "Do not call anyone on earth 'father,' for you have one Father, and he is in heaven."
Similarly, with teachers, Paul also says elsewhere:
First Corinthians 1: "Was Paul crucified for you? Were you baptized in the name of Paul?" so that he might direct the intention and hope of all the faithful away from all others and firmly fix it on God with sound doctrine.
In this sense, the psalm:
Psalm 120 also sings, saying: "I lift up my eyes to the mountains-where does my help come from?" wishing the mountains to be understood as the apostles and prophets, whom Christ, the Sun of Righteousness, primarily illuminated. And lest it be thought that he trusted in names, he immediately added: "My help comes from the Lord, the Maker of heaven and earth" (Psalm 120).
Just as we should recognize the twelve foundations as apostles, they are all called in the one foundation of Jesus Christ.
This pertains to the fact that here, too, the name of the Lamb is not silent, saying: "And on them were the names of the twelve apostles and the Lamb."
The foundation of the apostles is one with Jesus.
Only Christ, without the apostles, is rightly called the foundation.
The apostles, without Christ, cannot be called the foundation of the Church.
Similarly, the principles we considered here apply for comparison.
The apostles, being faithful in Christ, deserved to spiritually nurture those whom Christ alone, if He wished, would adopt without them.
They also deserved to be teachers and shepherds of the people in Christ, but their service was devoted to the heavenly Father, their ultimate teacher and shepherd.
According to the measure of grace given to them by Christ, He possessed unique natural power.
As the Gospel says, "For God does not give the Spirit by measure" (John 3:34).
In Him, all the fullness of divinity dwells bodily (Colossians 2:9), and from His fullness, we have all received (John 1:16), and grace upon grace.
It follows: "And the one who was speaking with me had a golden measuring rod to measure the city and its gates and its walls. The city was laid out as a square, its length as great as its width." Earlier, John says a measuring rod was given to him, symbolizing the dispensation of preaching entrusted to him. Now he says the angel speaking with him had a golden measuring rod to measure the city, its gates, and walls.
This must be understood as Christ, who is the wisdom of God (First Corinthians 1:24), reaching from one end to the other mightily and arranging all things sweetly (Wisdom 8:1).
As we read in Proverbs 16:16, "Acquire wisdom like gold."
Indeed, only Christ is allowed to measure the city, distributing the gifts of grace to each of the faithful spiritually. As we read, He arranged all things in number, measure, and weight (Wisdom 11:20).
This is the dimension of the city mentioned by the Apostle when he says (Ephesians 4:7), "According to the measure of Christ's gift;" and again (Ephesians 3:8), "To me, the very least of all saints, this grace was given to preach to the Gentiles."
The city is set in a perfect square, with equal dimensions on all sides, symbolizing its perfection.
As the Apostle says in 1 Corinthians chapter one, to be perfect is to be of the same mind and to have peace, truly represented by the solid square.
This is the city built upon a mountain, founded upon itself, as the Lord declares in the Gospel of Matthew chapter five.
He also says to Peter, who represents the entire Church in Matthew chapter sixteen: "You are Peter, and on this rock I will build my Church." It's as if He were saying: "Upon myself, I will build you." For the rock was Christ: thus, from the rock comes Peter, just as from Christ comes the Christian. This teaches us to avoid human errors and to follow the strongholds of divine truth.
"And he measured," it says, "the city with a reed, twelve thousand stadia in length, width, and height are equal." This signifies the solidity of invincible truth, by which the Church of Christ is firmly supported and not swayed by every wind of doctrine, as stated in Ephesians chapter four. The number twelve, when multiplied, makes one hundred and forty-four; for twelve times twelve makes one hundred and forty-four. It continues: "The wall was measured to be one hundred and forty-four cubits, the measure of a man, which is that of an angel." The frequent references to places show that the angel often represents the Church. Since the Church consists of people and is elevated by the promises of Christ, it hopes for equality with the angels and longs for their company.
Therefore, it says "the measure of a man, which is that of an angel," either because that city partly consists of angels already dwelling there in perpetual happiness, and partly of pilgrims, that is, people, who will fully reign. Alternatively, it could mean that the number of fallen humans removed from the heavenly abode of the angels is believed to be restored by the number of the redeemed. It will easily be replaced with greater abundance, not diminished. Hence, it is sung in Deuteronomy chapter thirty-two: "He set the boundaries of the peoples according to the number of the angels of God," etc.
And the construction of its wall was made from jasper stone.
Blessed Peter exhorts the people in First Peter Chapter 2 to be built up like living stones into a spiritual house.
It continues: The city itself was made of pure gold, like clear glass.
Furthermore, it mentions things that seem inappropriate to emphasize the unique dignity of Christ, comparing Him to all other stones.
For who does not know that gold differs from glass in quality and color?
Although it is not new for the Church to be symbolized by gold, which is often described in golden candlesticks and bowls for the worship of wisdom, what stands out here is that pure gold is compared to clear glass.
I think this signifies what the Apostle said in First Corinthians Chapter 4: Do not judge before the time comes, until the Lord comes, who will bring to light the hidden things of darkness and reveal the thoughts of the heart.
For in glass, nothing is shown on the outside except what is contained inside.
Therefore, announcing that time when thoughts will be clearly revealed to each other, confidently compares gold to glass.
Whatever is in the thoughts of the saints then, will shine with the beauty of wisdom, which rightly deserves this comparison.
For now, no matter how much one excels in virtue, no one knows the innermost thoughts of a person except the spirit of the person within him, as stated in First Corinthians Chapter 2.
Alternatively, it could mean that glass, in its own way, stands out prominently in its kind.
The foundations, however, were made of every precious stone.
And in the song of Tobit, Chapter 13, we read: All your walls are made of precious stones.
And in Isaiah Chapter 54 it says: Behold, I will lay your stones in order, and I will lay your foundations with sapphires, and I will make your fortifications with jasper, and your gates with carved stones, and all your borders with desirable stones.
To explain what he was saying so that you do not think carnally about the earthly structure, he added in Isaiah Chapter 45: All your children will be taught by the Lord, and great will be the peace of your children, etc.
Blessed Paul, harmonizing with these thoughts, says in Ephesians.
Built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, with Christ Jesus himself as the chief cornerstone, the whole building grows into a holy temple in the Lord.
The first foundation is jasper.
Previously, this was mentioned, but now, listing them one by one, it elaborates on the foundations of every precious stone.
The second is sapphire; the third, chalcedony; the fourth, emerald; the fifth, sardonyx; the sixth, sardius; the seventh, chrysolite; the eighth, beryl; the ninth, topaz; the tenth, chrysoprase; the eleventh, jacinth; the twelfth, amethyst.
These stones symbolize the virtues by which each of the saints is spiritually adorned; and the entire city is described as firm in strength and adorned with variety as if made of these stones.
The twelve gates are each made of a single pearl.
We have said more than enough about the one foundation of Christ and the twelve apostles of the Lamb, which also applies to the one pearl, that is, Christ, which the merchant found and sold all to buy.
It is fitting for the reader to consider the twelve as well.
The streets are of pure gold, like transparent glass.
It has already been said that the city is of pure gold, like clear glass, or that its foundations are of every precious stone.
I think this refers to the powerful ones of the Church.
Now, he adds about the streets, saying even they are of pure gold like transparent glass, as if the streets were not part of the previously described city; but here, I infer that the little ones are signified, of whom it is now said (Psalm 139): "Your eyes saw my unformed substance; in your book were written, every one of them." Likewise (Proverbs 3), "And his conversation is with the simple," meaning that they too are not deprived of this gift, and they contemplate their thoughts in mutual exchange. Just as the streets are placed in a lower position, so these seem to be saved in a humble place: but if in the streets the breadth of charity is to be understood, he wished to signify the perfect ones with different terms.
Then, however, no one there will be unworthy.
No child or weak person will be found, although some may shine more brightly in rewards than others.
As the Apostle says in 1 Corinthians 15, "One star differs from another star in glory," so too is the resurrection of the dead.
I did not see a temple in it, for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb are its temple. Just as a body is built with individual members, so is the temple with precious stones. Since He does not want us to be attached to material structures, thinking of something physical out of habit, He says, "I did not see a temple in it, for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb are its temple."
The Church, especially with the weeds now removed, rejoicing in the chosen ones alone, remains consecrated in the Lord. It rests more securely as in a temple, so that from Him who gave it its origin and experienced the gentleness of redemption, it may also obtain a blessed dwelling. For its entire fulfillment is in these three things: to exist, to know, to love.
God created it to be formed, illuminated it when called, and blessed it when chosen, making it perfect by His promised glorification. No longer walking by faith, but rejoicing in sight. And the city, he says, does not need the sun and the moon to shine on it; for the glory of God illuminates it, and its lamp is the Lamb.
Wishing to completely detach us from the usual alternation of day and night light and to bring us back to that unchangeable light, He says, "it does not need the sun and the moon." He does not claim that the city is illuminated in the same manner, but by a much better and ineffable light, namely the Sun of righteousness, which the prophet refers to in Malachi 4: "And healing in its wings."
He is the true Son, and eternal life, and the true light that enlightens every man coming into this world, as stated in John 1.
What no eye has seen, no ear has heard, nor has it entered into the heart of man in this age, as stated in 1 Corinthians.
It couldn't be explained better than this: The brightness of the Lord illuminates it, and its lamp is the Lamb.
What greater gift could be given to the victor than to possess the giver of gifts himself?
They will enjoy the same light in their homeland that guides us on our path now.
Illuminated by this light, we distinguish between good and evil, and once blessed, we will see only what is good.
The nations will walk by its light, and the kings of the earth will bring their glory into it.
This means that the same Lamb is the way for travelers and will be life for citizens.
Whatever dignity they attain, they must honor the giver with due praises.
Here, the kings are called spiritual, as we read: He is powerful and gives strength to our kings and has exalted the horn of His Christ First Samuel 2.
And its gates will not be closed during the day, for there will be no night there.
The eternal light of the Lamb, the everlasting light itself, will be present in that city when the time of night is removed, as Isaiah says: It will be for them month after month, and Sabbath after Sabbath, signifying light in the month due to the full brightness of the moon, and perpetual rest on the Sabbath.
As if to say: light from light will be continuous, and eternal rest will follow rest.
The fact that the gates will not be closed signifies complete security.
There, it is no longer said, Matthew 26, "Watch and pray, so that you do not fall into temptation," but rather, Psalm 46, "Be still and know that I am God." There, what is seen is loved honorably, and what is loved is praised without end; there, no one withers in idleness, nor is anyone fatigued by continuous praise. They will bring the honor and majesty of the nations into it because it will be gathered from all nations. And nothing unclean will enter it, nor anyone who does what is detestable, but only those who are written in the Lamb's book of life.
The future will define the Church, a time when it will no longer tolerate the bad mixed with the good, as it does now.
Only the good will reign with Christ, staying faithfully with him in the heavenly Jerusalem, the mother of all.
It is written in the Lamb's book: Rejoice, because your names are written in heaven.
Luke 10:20
It continues:
Chapter Twenty-Two
He showed me a river of the water of life, bright as crystal, flowing from the throne of God and the Lamb, through the middle of its street.
In the heart of the city's river, the celebration of baptism isn't yet indicated, but the fruit of the sacrament itself will already be revealed.
For now, it is sown in tears, but it will be reaped in joy then.
Psalm 126.
And therefore, now the Church sows in the spirit, so that it may reap eternal life from the spirit.
Galatians 6.
When we have proven through experience, when the fruits of the benefit perceived through the grace of the sacrament find us, then it is testified in John that the river of the water of life, bright as crystal, will be manifested to the Church, that is, stability in faith.
For he who perseveres to the end will be saved.
Matthew 10, 24.
Signifying this, it follows:
And on either side of the river, the tree of life, bearing twelve kinds of fruit, yielding its fruit every month, and the leaves of the tree are for the healing of the nations, and there will be no more curse.
In the twelve months, all time is implied, and perpetuity is entirely designated.
Therefore, where there is eternal vigor, no dryness is ever signified to be present: where there is perfect and stable health, no infirmity at all interrupts.
What the prophet promises, saying:
Isaiah 35:
Joy and gladness will obtain, and sorrow and sighing will flee.
That tree is what we read is planted by streams of water.
Psalm 1,
of which Jeremiah also says (Chapter 17), that it sends its roots to the moisture, who places their hope and confidence in the Lord.
Otherwise, the river of the water of life, etc.
, is rightly known to signify the fountain of life, the Lord Jesus Christ, of whom we read:
Psalm 36:
With you is the fountain of life, and in your light, we see light.
He is indeed, as we read:
Wisdom 7,
the image of the majesty of God, all-powerful, and remaining in Himself, renews all things and rests in holy souls through the nations.
Thus, that fountain, which is the river: fountain, because it remains unchangeable in itself; river, because it generously and continually offers itself to the communion of the saints.
Even where a spring is mentioned, a stream is also named.
For when Psalm 35 says, "You will give them drink from the river of Your delights," it continues with, "For with You is the fountain of life; in Your light, we see light."
It is well said that through the middle of the street, as a common good for all the saints, it is denied to none who are worthy and granted to no one unworthy. For those who live in Jerusalem, mountains surround it, and the Lord surrounds His people Psalm 124.
Also, God, who is glorified in the council of the saints, is great and to be feared above all who are around Him. In the middle, it is as if it were an indivisible inheritance for all who see God. Hence, we read in Psalm 122: "Jerusalem, built as a city that is closely compacted together. This is where the tribes go up, the tribes of the Lord, to praise the name of the Lord according to the statute given to Israel."
If the fruits of blessed immortality are received, then the leaves of perpetual praise rightly symbolize the song, which falls into the happy lot of those now singing in health: for there, the true healing of the nations, full redemption, and eternal happiness are found.
But the throne of God and the Lamb will be in it. He did not say "they will be," nor "thrones"; for where there is natural and undivided unity, the glory of the Deity had to be most highly commended, one throne of indivisible session, which cannot be divided by the cunning of Arian depravity nor confused by the suspicion of Sabellian vanity, but only of Catholic truth, which sees the adoption and is proven to be held by the confession of right belief.
And they will see His face. Considering the vision of God, which is promised to the saints in the future, as a cause of great merit and to be held in excellent esteem. I read Saint Augustine's sayings appropriate to this place to draw from them, so that by his teaching we can undoubtedly recognize what is promised in the future.
For writing to Paulina about the vision of God, he says: Until a diligent investigation, if the Lord helps, finds out what is more probable according to the Scriptures about the spiritual body that is promised in the resurrection, in the meantime, let it suffice us that the only-begotten Son, who is also the mediator between God and humans, the man Christ Jesus First Timothy.
He sees the Father as the Father sees him.
But we should not try to bring our worldly desires into the vision of God promised to us in the resurrection.
Instead, we should strive with a pure heart to cleanse our souls and not think of a physical face.
As the Apostle says in First Corinthians 13: "Now we see through a glass, darkly; but then face to face," especially since he clearly said: "Now I know in part, but then shall I know even as also I am known."
Who wouldn't understand that in that place he wanted to signify our face, about which he says in another place, Second Corinthians 3: "But we all, with unveiled face, beholding as in a mirror the glory of the Lord, are being transformed into the same image from glory to glory, just as by the Spirit of the Lord."
From the glory of faith to the glory of eternal contemplation. For this transformation renews the inner person day by day, as stated in Second Corinthians 4. And also as the Apostle Peter advises, when he says to adorn oneself: "Do not let your adornment be merely outward-arranging the hair, wearing gold, or putting on fine apparel-but rather let it be the hidden person of the heart, which is very precious in the sight of God" (First Peter 3).
Furthermore, in the twenty-second book of "The City of God," it is said: The reward of faith is the vision of God, about which the Apostle John also says: "When He is revealed, we shall be like Him, for we shall see Him as He is" (First John 3).
The face of God should be understood as His manifestation, not a physical part like we have in our bodies, and it is called by that name.
And a little later it says: God will be known and visible to us so that He will be seen by each of us in spirit, seen by one in another, seen in Himself, seen in the new heaven and new earth, and in all creatures that exist then.
And His name will be written on their foreheads.
This temple is justified by faith, which also confers the merit of eternal life, as it declares that the name of God and the Lamb will be inscribed on their foreheads, as if to be recognized and glorified.
This faith is certainly encompassed in one name.
He did not say, "the names of God and the Lamb written on their foreheads," as if to signify a duality of persons, but to maintain the rule of that doctrine when speaking of the reigning saints, which long ago the Lord had entrusted to his wandering disciples to observe:
"Go," he said Matthew chapter 28, "baptize all nations, immersing them in the name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit."
For it was diligently commended that the saints would see and have in appearance what they believed while living by faith.
And there will no longer be night, nor will they need the light of a lamp or the light of the sun, because the Lord God will shine upon them, and they will reign forever and ever.
The frailty of our bodies now uses both the changes of time and the disturbances of the elements, so that the night's rest makes us fit for daily work, and even uses the night for the consolation of the lamp.
But then, when God will be all in all First Corinthians chapter 15, who is the true light, there will be no need for these elements, and no one will ever be subject to them. When He himself will be the light for the reigning saints, who is the author of all work, and the preaching of the divine law, which is now called a lamp in a dark place, because in the contemplation of God, with things fulfilled, the perfect promise is held.
And he said to me: These words are most faithful and true. He did not doubt John's reliability, but commended the true vision to the whole Church, in which he knew there would be even little ones.
And the Lord God of the spirits of the prophets sent his angel to show his servants what must soon take place.
Shortly, he showed that he had regarded the benefit of all in general. He himself is the Spirit of the prophets, who is also the Holy Spirit, who indeed is the Lord, and therefore a prophet.
"I will hear," he says Psalm chapter 85, "what the Lord God will speak in me," and the beginning of speaking to the Lord in Hosea chapter 1.
For the essence of the one divine Trinity, he also appropriately named the Holy Spirit here, when he had recently mentioned the Father and the Son. For what we read John
Because God is spirit, this pertains to the whole Trinity.
Behold, I am coming soon.
Blessed is the one who keeps the words of the prophecy of this book.
Here, "to keep" means to believe reverently and to uphold the intent of a purer life.
And I, John, who heard and saw these things, am providing testimony suggested to be confirmed by the judgment of man.
When I heard and saw, I fell down to worship at the feet of the angel who showed me these things. But he said to me: See that you do not do that, for I am your fellow servant, and of your brothers the prophets, who keep the words of the prophecy of this book. Worship God instead.
Either he repeated what was done once and prohibited from being repeated, or he admits that he wished to worship again, struck by the great awe of the visions, just as the prophet said: My belly trembled from the voice of my lips' supplication, and trembling entered my bones; within me, my strength was disturbed.
And he said to me: Do not seal the words of the prophecy of this book, because the time is near. Let the evildoer still do evil, and the filthy still be filthy. Here, the hidden judgments of God are shown as just, allowing evil men to progress to worse.
However, to harm here should be understood not so much as harming others, but rather themselves. Hence it follows: And let the filthy still be filthy. For who, being wicked to himself, will be good to others?
Another translation says: Let the unjust still act unjustly, and let the righteous still do right, and let the holy still be holy.
I think the reason he says, do not seal the words of the prophecy of this book, is because with the future judgment approaching, it was necessary for divine precepts, judgments, and promises to be revealed, so that the meek may acquire reward, and the negligent and rebellious incur punishment.
For he had previously said, seal up what the seven thunders have spoken; do not write them down. Now, however, do not seal the words of the prophecy of this book.
Behold, I am coming soon, and my reward is with me, to give to each according to their deeds.
Enough said. I am the Alpha and the Omega, the first and the last, the beginning and the end.
Faithful proclamation of the truth, when reinforced by frequent repetition, shapes the spirit with richer spiritual cultivation.
This is concisely but adequately expressed at the end of the book, where the divinity of the Word is assigned to Alpha and the assumed humanity to Omega, symbolizing a beginning without end.
Seeing Alpha and Omega repeated so often in this book, I recognize it was not done in vain.
Whether it is to frequently emphasize the divinity and humanity of Christ, which forms the foundation of the Christian faith, or to hint at the entire Trinity as one nature-who, through the prophet, says (Isaiah 43:10): "Before me no god was formed, nor will there be one after me. I am God, and there is no Savior apart from me"; or to whom it is said through the prophet: "You are God, and there is no other God besides you"-or if some other deeper or more secret mystery lies hidden, I do not doubt that its frequent repetition is meant to leave a fruitful understanding for the faithful.
The very elements of the Greek alphabet, Alpha and Omega, sum up to the number represented by the name of the dove in Greek. The dove, called by a name summing up to 801, rightly signifies the person of the Holy Spirit (Matthew 3), who, descending in this form, chose to appear.
This thwarts the madness of the Arians and other heretics, who assert that he is alien to the nature of the Father and the Son.
This sum of numbers reveals the heavenly revelation of the Holy Spirit as consubstantial and co-eternal with the Father and the Son, and states that their commandments are kept in washed robes.
John composed the beginning of his Gospel with the same thoughts, though in different words, saying (John 1:1): "In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God"; and shortly after (John 1:14): "And the Word became flesh." Here lies the whole sum of faith: that in one and the same Christ, perfect divinity and true humanity are believed.
Regarding moral integrity, it states: "But to all who did receive him, who believed in his name, he gave the right to become children of God," adding love to faith. This seems to narrate the reward along similar paths, insinuating Christ as the Alpha and Omega, signifying an immaculate life with white robes, and promising the same reward, saying: "That they may have the right to the tree of life."
The tree of life, however, is Christ, as we read: "Wisdom is a tree of life to those who lay hold of her" Proverbs 3.
It should not be thought that they are above Christ, for "a disciple is not above his teacher, nor a servant above his master" (Matthew 10).
However, he said here "above the tree of life," as if to say "their weakness rests upon the tree of life," that is, upon the Lord Christ, about whom the prophet also says, "And they are established upon the Holy One of Israel."
Therefore, virtue is understood to be narrated as being upon them.
In the same sense, it is said to Saint Peter in Matthew 16: "On this rock, I will build my church," that is, on me.
And the prophet, using different words but the same meaning, says in Psalm 59: "I will guard my strength for you."
And they shall enter the holy city through the gates.
About these gates, it is written, I believe in Psalm 118: "Open to me the gates of righteousness, that I may enter through them and give thanks to the Lord. This is the gate of the Lord; the righteous shall enter through it."
For that city cannot be entered by any other way except through Christ, who said in John 10: "I am the door, and no one comes to the Father except through me."
Outside, however, will remain the dogs, sorcerers, fornicators, murderers, idolaters, and everyone who loves and practices falsehood.
These people are not to be explained with diligence but should be carefully avoided.
"I, Jesus, have sent my angel to testify to you about these things for the churches."
Intending to resume the series of the book, he assigns the intention of the first relation, so that the latter may agree with the former.
"I am the root and descendant of David."
With the proclamation of Christ's divinity already presented, as I have previously explained, he also preaches the form of a servant which he took on for us, saying:
"I am the root and the descendant of David, the bright morning star."
By shining the grace of the New Testament, he reveals the time of the first resurrection, when Christ rose from the dead.
Hence, we read in Psalm 129:
"From the morning watch until night, let Israel hope in the Lord."
And the spirit and the new bride say, Christ and the Church:
"We exhort, Come."
And the one who hears, says:
"Come."
Explaining himself, he reveals the intention of his exhortation, and says:
"And let the one who is thirsty come and drink; and let the one who wishes, take the water of life freely."
How can the one who wishes take it, when he said in John 6:
"No one comes to me unless the Father who sent me draws him";
unless because from the one who did not want to be willing before, we know, by divine inspiration, he becomes willing?
For here, too, free will is suitably expressed, by saying:
"Let the one who wishes take,"
so that grace is immediately proclaimed in it, saying,
"take the water of life freely,"
therefore, without any preceding good deeds, let him take the water of life freely. For what, says the Apostle in First Corinthians 4:
"Do you have that you did not receive?"
Thus, we also freely receive from God the will to come, to whom we contributed nothing beforehand to be, how much more to be made righteous from sinners!
I, John, testify to all who hear the words of the prophecy of this book. This is what the one who commanded the testimony to be given says. The faithful witness whom he mentioned earlier, now testifies as commanded, so that the usefulness of this book, so beneficial, would not be considered contemptible, he humbly set aside his own person and opposed Christ to the despisers.
What the faithful witness fulfilled at the head, when he said in John 4:
"My food is to do the will of him who sent me,"
or similar things, let this aid in fulfilling it also for the body. If anyone adds to these, God will add to him the plagues written in this book. And if anyone takes away, the Lord will take away his part from the book of life, and from the holy city, and from the things written in this book.
And Solomon says in Proverbs...
Do not add anything to His words, or you will be rebuked and found to be a liar.
Here, He also added the fear of punishment, urging not only through the weight of authority but also through threats, to awaken the lazy or restrain the reckless.
He who bears witness to these things says: "Yes, I am coming soon." Amen. Come, Lord Jesus. The same Christ bears witness, announcing that He will come to the Church. In response, the Church, devoted like in the Song of Songs, says: "Yes, come, Lord Jesus Christ," and prays, "Your kingdom come" (Matthew 6), anticipating His perfect coming.
Since the work undertaken should conclude with a devout and proper end, and understanding that what has been spread widely and in many ways is difficult to grasp, I consider it necessary to proceed with summaries.
This way, after covering the authority of the entire book, the series of conclusions can be reviewed briefly, part by part, clearly defining the text of all five books in one place, reflecting both their division and their overall fullness.
In the seven angels of the seven churches, the unity of the universal Church is described with the necessary interposition of names.
The golden lampstands show that the bad are mixed with the good, whose different qualities are either praised for improvement or reproved for correction.
This is also described in the twenty-four elders through Christ's dispensation and the evangelists' preaching.
This indeed is in the first book.
In the second book, it is said that the worthiness of the book marked by this chapter of Christ is deservedly rewarded for the dispensation accomplished.
Christ and the Church are understood as two in one flesh (Ephesians 5), and in Him, all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge, which were hidden before, are revealed to have shone forth in their time (Colossians 2).
The same one appeared on a white horse, sent long ago, revealed in a vision.
After Christ's triumph over death, he lists future attacks on the Church and plagues upon humanity, symbolized by red, black, and pale horses.
Under God's altar, he mentions the martyrs born from these events and declares the sixth age of the world with the sixth sign, predicting a great wave of persecution at the end.
In the four angels, he testifies to the four kingdoms of the world, aligning with Daniel's prophecy.
The first ancient coming of Christ prevented harm to the number of the elect, who are counted along with the names of the twelve tribes and the number of the sealed.
To show that the Church consists of both the people of Israel and the Gentiles, he soon adds the calling of the Gentiles, telling of their works of faith and the reward for their faith.
In the third book, he describes the Church through seven angels and trumpets, mentioning that it will be tested by external and internal persecutions and dangers.
After one angel, who stood over the altar of God with a golden censer, he seems to oppose a second, third, and fourth contrary ones.
With the mention of the eagle interposed again, he says the Church will bring forth heretics from the abyss in the form of locusts and war horses, whose stings are like those of scorpions, with one woe said to have passed.
The release of the four angels with the number 80 and twice ten thousand times ten thousand, whose horsemen with fiery and sulfurous breastplates he describes as enduring heresiarchs in different ways, soon attaches the error of paganism, which is reduced to the second woe.
In the angel clothed with a cloud, the first coming of Christ is designated, whose preaching creates sweetness in the mouth from good things and bitterness in the stomach from bad things.
In the voice of the seventh angel, the end of the sixth age and the beginning of the seventh is announced.
In the two martyrs, two types of martyrdom are recognized, and he says that the third woe has come.
By mentioning the second coming, the birth of Christ is narrated in the open temple of God in heaven, which is the Church.
The Church is said to have emerged victorious from the battle with the dragon by following in the footsteps of its head.
In the fourth book, the beast is discussed.
It is said to have seven heads and ten horns, symbolizing opposition to Christ and the Church.
Although it is said to bear the signs of the Antichrist for a time, the patience and wisdom of the saints must endure it.
The mark or name of the beast, or its number, is advised to be investigated.
After this, the Church is described as steadfast in the elect, named under the Lamb, and numbered with a sacred number.
Christ is also depicted differently, sitting on a white cloud, crowned, with a sickle.
It mentions the seven plagues and reports the victory of the saints, along with the Jews' enduring hardness of heart and incomparable persecution.
It foretells the future damnation of the harlot, described with the deceitful attire of a woman, symbolizing both worldly power and hidden wickedness, with seven heads and ten horns.
In the fifth book, the same coming of Christ is suggested in a different narrative.
He is said to descend from heaven as an angel, illuminating the earth with his power and glory.
Babylon is mentioned to be destroyed, foretold to fall with many symbolic names, and shown to be punished for its iniquity.
The dignity of the saints is remembered among the elders, the wedding of the Lamb, and the clean linen.
Here, Christ is described as wearing a diadem, sitting on a white horse, battling the beast, and binding the devil with chains for 1,000 years so that he loses the power to deceive the nations.
He is seen sitting on a white throne as the form of future judgment.
The second coming of Christ is again mentioned when a new heaven and new earth are described, with the renewal of the elements and the new Jerusalem as the bride.
The Lamb, the foundation of the patriarchs and apostles, is secured by promises.
It is said to possess the reward, to be illuminated by the light of the Lamb, to drink from the fountain of life, and to enjoy its vision.
Therefore, He often refers to Himself as Alpha and Omega to signify the Trinity of one divine nature.
His future Gospel seems consistent with this book.
By repeatedly mentioning the seven churches, He clarifies the book's purpose and announces His coming to the Church.
Given the length of this work, some may complain about its supposed length, while others, passionate about divine law or reading, may demand more from its great depth.
As I debated between the impatient and the eager, I feared that excessive length might bore some, while brevity might seem envious for withholding details.
Thus, guided by the Lord, I aimed to balance my style, spending more words on the obscure parts and fewer on the clear ones, ensuring I neither deprive the hungry of what they seek nor offend the knowledgeable with my boldness.
I admit that I have not rendered as much service as the lofty dignity of the mysteries required, but have provided as much as my limited abilities, with divine help, could offer.