On the Destruction of Jerusalem
A sermon or treatise
by Walafrid Strabo, Monk of Fulda.
We can understand how much the Almighty Lord rejoices in human progress, and how much He grieves over their downfall, from many passages of Holy Scripture, especially from the present reading.
For example, when the Jews wanted to kill the Son of God and were planning His death, He, like a loving father, was lamenting their destruction.
When the Lord weeps over the Jews seeking to kill Him, He clearly shows how much He rejoices in the progress of the human race, as He was grieving then over the future, long-foreseen death of the Jews.
The text of the Gospel tells how the Son of God sent disciples for a donkey's colt, on which He rode into Jerusalem, while the crowds joyfully praised the Lord with loud voices for all the miracles they had seen, saying:
"Blessed is the King who comes in the name of the Lord, peace in heaven and glory in the highest" Luke 19.
Some of the Pharisees said to Him: "Teacher, rebuke your disciples."
He replied: "I tell you, if they keep silent, the stones will cry out."
Following these words, Luke the evangelist adds: "And as Jesus approached Jerusalem, seeing the city, He wept over it, saying: If only you had known, even you, etc."
The Lord grieved over the destruction of the treacherous city, which did not know what was coming upon it.
It should not be thought that the Lord wept over the beautiful walls of the city, its buildings, or the heights of its towers, but by a metaphor, He wept over the inhabitants of the city.
A metaphor is a figure of speech, as the expertise of Greeks and Latins teaches, through which Scripture often appears to speak; namely, by referring to the inhabitant for the inhabitant, the irrational for the rational, the inanimate for the animate.
Let's skip other things and talk about the present situation: from inhabitant to inhabitant, like here; and as the Lord says elsewhere: Jerusalem, you who kill the prophets and stone those sent to you First Corinthians Just as there, so also here, he did not weep over Jerusalem, but over the inhabitants of that city, to whom the weeping Lord says: If you, even you, had known, you would weep.
Even on this your day, the things that make for peace; but now they are hidden from your eyes.
Luke nineteen forty-two For in its own day, the perverse city had the things that made for its peace; it was exalted in honors, boasted in riches, delighted in wealth, in abundance of things, in the fertility of offspring, and in the health of bodies.
And because it had the things that made for present peace, it did not foresee future conflict.
Hence, it is rightly added: But now they are hidden from your eyes.
Luke nineteen forty-two For present joy brought tribulation.
About this tribulation, it is rightly added: For the days will come upon you when your enemies will build an embankment against you and encircle you and hem you in on every side.
They will dash you to the ground, you and the children within your walls.
They will not leave one stone on another, because you did not recognize the time of God's coming to you.
Luke nineteen forty-three to forty-four How these words were literally fulfilled in the destruction of that city and the Jewish people, the historian Josephus narrates in full.
He also mentions how two Roman leaders, Vespasian and Titus, father and son, came with a military force to destroy that city, in the forty-second year after the resurrection of the Lord and his most glorious ascension.
And rightly and deservedly, as they had denied God the Father and the Son, they were killed by a father and son.
For the Lord waited for the Jewish people after his passion for forty-two years for repentance, but for the most part, they were unwilling to convert, and thus they encountered such harsh enemies.
When the people of Rome were burning the entire surrounding region, all the inhabitants, including women and children, entered the city like one unified group to celebrate Passover.
Suddenly, the city was surrounded by a siege, preventing anyone from entering or leaving.
This happened by the will of God, so that those who had cruelly nailed the Son of God to the cross on the solemn day of Passover would be afflicted by their enemies on the same day.
Severe hunger tormented them internally, in addition to being attacked externally by the sword.
Some were so desperate that they didn't even refrain from eating their own shoes, as Josephus recounts.
Others chewed on old hay remnants, wheat chaff, and straw.
Some even tore down door frames and consumed them.
In this dire situation, all sense of shame and modesty had left them, as overwhelming hunger claimed everything.
Women were dragged by their hair to reveal hidden food; no respect was shown for the elderly, and no pity was shown for the children.
On top of everything, robbers emerged among them, tormenting them more severely from within than the enemies did from outside.
If they saw anyone's doors closed, it was a sign that those inside were eating.
They would immediately break down the doors and snatch the food from their hands.
As a result, no one dared to set a table; they ate their food in secret.
Grain was scarce in the city, and if anyone tried to go out to collect herbs, they were detained by those inside, accused of trying to make peace with the Roman army.
The bodies of young men lay in the streets, more wasted by hunger than by age.
No one was buried according to custom, as the multitude of the dying and the weakness of the survivors prevented it.
Some, while trying to bury their loved ones, breathed their last over the graves.
When a great stench and unbearable odor filled the city, they began to throw the bodies of the dead outside the walls, piling them so high that they seemed to reach the top of the walls themselves.
One day, as Titus was walking around the city—since his father Vespasian had already gone to Rome because of the empire—he saw all the trenches filled with bodies of the dead and dying, nearly level with the walls.
He called upon God as his witness, declaring that this was not his doing.
Lifting his eyes to heaven with a deep groan, he is said to have spoken:
"O Roman citizens, I will not hesitate to say what I feel; I believe that if the Roman army were to leave this pestilent city for a while, its inhabitants would either be swallowed by the earth, burned by fire like Sodom, or drowned by flood waters."
Saying this, perhaps planning to rest the army the next day, he immediately armed the soldiers, set up guards, and began again to occupy the city.
Therefore, they rightly suffered from atrocious hunger, those who had killed the bread of life.
The same Josephus also recounts an unheard-of crime committed there. There was a woman named Mary, daughter of Eleazar, very wealthy and of noble birth, who had come to the city with the rest of the crowd. Her property in the region was ravaged by enemies and burned by fire, and what she had brought with her into the city was consumed.
In this time of necessity and tribulation, she is said to have turned against her own nature. She had a small child at her breast, and placing him before her eyes, she is said to have spoken thus (I will touch on the meaning, though I will omit the words):
"O unhappy mother, and O more unhappy child, in hunger, war, and the devastation of robbers, to whom shall I save you? For even if life could be hoped for, we are pressed by the yoke of slavery. O dear child, be food for your mother! and be the fury of the robbers! a tale for the ages, and the memory of the worst famine."
Saying this, she immediately killed her son, roasted part of him over a fire, and saved the other part for later.
When the raiders, drawn by the smell of burnt flesh as was their custom, arrived, they threatened the miserable woman with death unless she revealed the food she had hidden.
Then she, with a fierce look even fiercer than the raiders themselves, said, "I have saved the best part for you."
She then uncovered the rest of the child's body, saying, "He is my offspring, my son, and my crime. Eat, for I have already eaten part of the one I gave birth to. Do not be more religious than a mother or softer than women. But if pity overcomes you and you abhor my food, I will eat again of what has nourished me."
The raiders, stunned and horrified by such a deed, reported it to the city. Everyone, seeing this before their eyes as if it were their own crime, mourned with great wailing, weeping, and loud cries.
Immediately, the city gate was opened, and Titus entered with the entire Roman army. Some he killed with the sword, others he burned with fire, and the young men he found more robust were taken into captivity.
The historian, having counted the number of those who died by famine and the sword, found it to be one million, one hundred thousand; and those dispersed into captivity were ninety thousand.
As for the number of those raiders who were killed in various ways after the city was captured, it is uncertain.
The city was so destroyed from its foundations that not one stone was left upon another.
We have recounted these things from Josephus to prove the truth of the Lord's prophecy, because he said:
'The days will come when your enemies will build an embankment against you, surround you, and close you in on every side, and level you, and your children within you, to the ground; and they will not leave one stone upon another because you did not recognize the time of your visitation.'
Luke nineteen, verses forty-three to forty-four.
In another place, the Lord also says to the disciples:
'Truly I tell you, not one stone here will be left on another; every one will be thrown down.'
Matthew twenty-four, verse two.
And elsewhere: "When you see Jerusalem surrounded by enemies, know that its desolation is near" (Luke 21).
This place is still shown today because, in the same location where it once stood, not one stone was left upon another.
Later, outside the city gate where the Lord was crucified, it was rebuilt by Aelius Hadrianus, and now it is called Aelia.
The slavery of the Jews was so cheap that one silver coin could buy thirty Jews.
It was fitting that those who bought the Lord for a low price were sold cheaply.
Then the prophecy of Ezekiel was fulfilled, as told to him by the Lord:
"And you, son of man, take a sharp sword, use it as a barber's razor, and pass it over your head and beard.
Then divide the hair into four parts: scatter one part to the wind, throw another part into the fire, cut a third part with a sword, and bind the remaining part in the edge of your garment" (Ezekiel 5).
This was all fulfilled when one part of the people was killed by the sword, another part was burned by fire, and another part was destined for captivity, which continues to this day among the unfortunate Jews throughout the world.
The part that the prophet threw into the fire represents those of the Jewish people who perished by fire or the city that was burned to its foundations.
The part cut with the sword represents those who were killed by the sword.
The part scattered to the wind represents those who were dispersed into captivity throughout various parts of the world.
The sword, which he was commanded to draw after these events, is understood to mean the general strike of the Lord on the same people.
The remnants that he was commanded to bind in the edge of his garment signify those from the same people who will believe at the end of the age.
The reason why such harsh things happened to them is added: "because you did not recognize the time of your visitation" (Luke 19).
He visited them then when he chose to be incarnated among them, which visitation the Psalmist desired, saying: "Visit us, Lord, with your salvation" (Psalms).
About this, even Zacharias says: "He has visited and brought redemption to his people." (Luke 1:68)
And "The rising sun will come to us from heaven." (Luke 1:78)
But the faithless city did not recognize this time of visitation, because when Christ appeared in the flesh, the Jewish people refused to believe in Him.
Hence, even the birds of the sky are brought as witnesses against the hardness of their hearts, as it is said:
"The stork in the sky knows her appointed seasons, and the dove, the swift, and the thrush observe the time of their migration; but my people do not know the requirements of the Lord." (Jeremiah 8:7)
The Lord not only visited them Himself, but even after His ascension, for forty-two years, He visited them with various signs, wonders, and portents, not only to visit but also to terrify them.
Indeed, as Josephus narrates, one day a heifer brought for sacrifice gave birth to a lamb.
Also, the temple gate, which was so heavy that it could hardly be moved by twenty men, opened by itself.
In the middle of the night, such a bright light shone in the temple that some thought it was midday.
Those who saw this, unaware of its meaning, thought it was a good omen, but the wise understood it as a sign of the city's destruction.
Noise and voices were also heard in the temple saying: "Let us leave these places."
Fiery chariots and soldiers were seen in the air, threatening the city's destruction.
Two years before their siege, a star that looked like a sword appeared over the city for an entire year.
And one year before their downfall, a man named Jesus, a commoner and rustic, during the solemn day of Passover, began to cry out among the people saying:
"A voice from the east, a voice from the west, a voice from the four corners of the sky, a voice against the bridegrooms and brides, a voice against Jerusalem and the temple."
Though he was severely beaten by the people, he never ceased, and as he died under the lashes, he kept saying: "Woe, woe to Jerusalem!"
Even though they had experienced many great miracles and signs that frightened them, their hearts were not softened to repentance.
Instead, they persisted in their wickedness and sins.
It was not fitting that they should remain unpunished, as they were the authors of such great crimes.
This punishment was prefigured in the acts of the prophet Elisha.
When descending from Gilgal, boys mocked him, saying, “Go up, baldhead, go up, baldhead.
” But he cursed them in the name of the Lord, and two bears came out of the woods and mauled forty-two of the boys (Second Kings 2).
By Elisha, we understand the Lord Christ, who was led by the Jews to the place called Calvary to be crucified.
Just as Elisha was mocked by the boys, so too was the Son of God mocked by the Jews when they knelt and said, “Hail, King of the Jews.
” And again, “If he is the Son of God, let him come down from the cross, and we will believe in him” (Matthew 27).
And striking him, they said, “Prophesy to us, Christ, who is it that struck you?
” The forty-two boys represent the forty-two years during which the Lord waited for them to repent, but since they refused to repent, two bears came out of the woods.
That is, two great Roman leaders, Vespasian and Titus, emerging from the forests of the Gentiles, killed them (Matthew 26).
“And entering the temple, he began to drive out those who sold and bought in it, saying to them: It is written, My house is a house of prayer, but you have made it a den of thieves.
” King Solomon built the house of the Lord to be a house of prayer, but the priests, who ought to have been guardians of the law and builders, had made it into a den of thieves by preparing goods for sale there (Luke 19).
It had been said to the children of Israel that three times a year they should gather to celebrate feasts in Jerusalem.
And the law also commanded: They shall not appear before me empty-handed (First Kings 8; Exodus 23).
Coming from distant regions and unable to bring gifts to offer, the temple ministers forced them to buy from them.
When the people gave gifts, the priests cheated them, keeping the offerings for themselves to sell again, inflating the prices for their own gain.
According to other evangelists, sheep, oxen, turtledoves, and pigeons were sold in the temple.
To ensure there were no excuses for not buying, money changers sat in the temple.
Matthew chapter twenty-one and Mark chapter eleven.
They had turned the house of prayer into a den of thieves, selling what was wrongly bought.
If anyone offered gifts, the priests would praise them greatly; but if there were none, they would beat them with whips.
To explain this to those who may not understand, we have briefly outlined this historically, and now it will be repeated with a short sermon.
What we said about the destruction of the material temple can also apply to any sinful soul.
The most merciful Lord wept over the lost city then; He weeps daily through holy teachers in the Church over the souls of the perishing.
Those who should be mourned by the teachers in the Church are those who do not know how to weep for themselves, who do not understand why they are mourned, who rejoice in doing evil, and exult in wicked deeds.
Similarly, the apostle Paul wept for the fallen disciples on behalf of Christ, saying:
"I may mourn many of those who have sinned before,"
Second Corinthians chapter twelve.
And also:
"My little children, for whom I labor in birth again until Christ is formed in you,"
Galatians chapter four.
What the Lord said, weeping over the perishing city, also applies to the perishing soul.
For the Lord said to the perishing city: "Because if you had known, even you,"
Luke chapter nineteen,
"you would weep."
If a sinful soul recognized the tribulation and distress that will grow for it in the future, where the worms do not die, and the fire is not quenched,
Isaiah.
They would rather mourn with the chosen in this world for a time than rejoice with the rejected.
"And indeed in this your day, which is for your peace,"
(Luke 19:42).
The sinful soul has its day when it rejoices in the fleeting world, inflated with honors, exalted in riches, and boasting in its abilities, but it does not foresee the scandal it will suffer on another day.
Nor does it see the future tribulation.
Hence, it is rightly added:
"But now they are hidden from your eyes"
(Luke 19:42).
Private love blinds the eyes of the heart; just as dust blinds the physical eyes, so too does the love of this world and present riches blind the mind's eye, preventing it from foreseeing future judgment.
Of its tribulation, it is rightly added:
"For the days will come upon you, and your enemies will surround you with a wall"
(Luke 19:43).
For the days will come upon you: the times of death, the days of tribulation, distress, calamity, and misery, when the unhappy soul begins to quarrel with itself, almost saying:
Why did I indulge in evil deeds?
Why did I not repent for past sins?
Why did I not engage in good works?
Then it will begin to repent, but no fruit of repentance will remain, only the strictness of vengeance.
"And they will surround you and hem you in on every side"
(Luke 19:43).
The worst enemies of an unhappy soul are unclean spirits.
The Psalmist desired to be rescued from these when he said:
"Rescue me from my enemies, O my God"
(Psalm 59:1).
And again:
"Rescue me from those who work iniquity"
(Psalm 59:2).
Therefore, the enemies surround the miserable soul with a wall when unclean spirits recall all its sins near the day of death, greatly distressing it, as those who first persuaded it to commit crimes become its tormentors.
"And they will throw you to the ground."
The unhappy soul is thrown to the ground when it loses the virtues it thought it had or when the flesh, taken from the ground, returns to the ground.
As it is written: "You are dust, and to dust you shall return." (Genesis 3)
And your children who are within you, (Luke 19)
Children, too, in the Holy Scriptures, or daughters, signify deeds, sometimes good, sometimes bad.
Good, as the Psalmist says, "And may you see your children's children, peace upon Israel." (Psalm 127)
Bad, however, as in this place, when it is said: "And your children who are within you." (Luke 19)
Truly, the children of a sinful soul are brought to the ground.
This happens not only from bad deeds but even from thoughts themselves.
Not only from lying, perjury, and grumbling, but even from idle words, we will have to give an account, with the Lord saying: "On the day of judgment, people will give an account for every careless word they speak." (Matthew 12)
And: "They will not leave one stone upon another in you, because you did not know the time of your visitation." (Luke 19)
Just as a stone is placed upon another stone in the building of a city so that the construction may grow, so too an evil thought is placed upon another evil thought.
Evil habits are joined to bad deeds, constructing a certain diabolical building.
In the destruction of the city, one stone is not left upon another, because on the day of judgment not only bad deeds but also wicked thoughts will cease and perish.
As the Psalmist says: "On that day, all their thoughts will perish." (Psalm 146)
Therefore, it is necessary that while we are in this world, and we have the opportunity, we not only abstain from evil but also strive to do good in everything.
Above all, let us keep the day of death in mind, because it is easy to despise everything when one always thinks of oneself as mortal.
Hence Solomon urges us, saying: "In all your works, remember your end." (Ecclesiasticus 7)
And again: "In the day of prosperity, consider adversity; in the day of adversity, consider prosperity." (Ecclesiasticus 11)
The merciful Lord, who patiently waits for us, will judge harshly on the day of judgment if we have not repented.
Here is the translation of the given Latin text into modern, easy-to-understand English:
"Therefore, the Gospel warns us: 'Run while you have the light, lest the darkness of death overtake you.'"
(John 12).
And again: "Settle matters quickly with your adversary, while you are on the way with him, or your adversary may hand you over to the judge, and the judge may hand you over to the officer, and you may be thrown into prison. Truly I tell you, you will not get out until you have paid the last penny."
(Matthew 5).
The apostle Paul says: "While we have time, let us do good to all."
(Galatians 6).
And again: "Behold, now is the acceptable time, behold, now is the day of salvation."
(Second Corinthians 6).
And Solomon says: "Whatever your hand finds to do, do it with all your might."
(Ecclesiastes 9).
"Because you did not know the time of your visitation."
(Luke 19).
God visits the sinful soul in many ways in this present life.
He first visited through the coming of His Son and through His miracles.
He visits daily through the preaching of teachers.
He visits through prosperity and adversity.
He visits through trials and persecution.
But the perverse soul does not recognize that with closed eyes it is heading to the fire.
It does not humble itself in prosperity, nor does it recognize itself in adversity.
The earthly Jerusalem is to be understood in four ways:
First, historically; the city situated on Mount Moriah, built by Shem, the son of Noah, and called Salem.
Second, possessed by the Jebusites, from which it derived the name Jebus.
Third, by Solomon, hence called Jerusalem, from Jebusite and Solomon, as if Jebusolyma.
Later destroyed by the Romans, it was rebuilt by Aelius Hadrianus, from whom it is now called Aelia: here it is literally.
Allegorically, Jerusalem is interpreted as the vision of peace, which signifies the holy Church.
For the heavenly Jerusalem can contain only those who are peaceful in the faith of Christ.
By anagogy, it signifies the holy soul, which always deserves to see the Lord through the contemplation of the mind.
"And entering the temple, he began to drive out those who sold and bought in it, saying: 'It is written: My house is a house of prayer, but you have made it a den of thieves.'"
(Luke 19).
Back then, what the Lord did physically by Himself, He now does spiritually in the Church every day.
The Church is the spiritual Temple of God, because it can rightly be called a house of prayer, where the Church continuously offers pure prayers to God, saying with the Psalmist, "Let my prayer be set before You like incense (Psalm 140).
"
In this temple, which is the Church, the sellers and buyers are those who seek ecclesiastical honor not for the salvation of souls, but for earthly gain or human favor. Thus, according to other evangelists, sheep and cattle, doves, and pigeons were sold in the temple (as written in the Gospels of Matthew and Mark).
In the Scriptures, the term ox sometimes refers to preachers, as the Lord said to Moses, "Do not plow with an ox and a donkey together (Deuteronomy 22)," meaning, do not join a wise person with a fool in preaching or teaching.
The sheep represents innocence or simplicity, as the sheep is the simplest of animals. Therefore, anyone who shows the holiness or innocence of God to others to seek praise from people carries a sheep for sale in the temple. About these, the Lord says in the Gospel, "They do all their deeds to be seen by others (Matthew 23).
" And again, "Truly I tell you, they have received their reward (Matthew 6).
"
The dove represents the Holy Spirit. This is why the Holy Spirit appeared in the form of a dove over the Lord at His baptism (Matthew 3).
Therefore, those who give the grace of the Holy Spirit through the laying on of hands—which they should have given freely, as the Lord said, "Freely you have received; freely give (Matthew 10).
"—not for God, but for gifts or earthly gain, are like those selling doves in the temple. About these, it is written, "Fire will consume the tents of those who love bribes (Job 15).
" And again, "Do not show partiality to a poor person in a lawsuit, because bribes blind the eyes of the wise and subvert the words of the righteous (Exodus 23:8).
"
The Lord drives out those who, although they seem to be united with the Church's body now, will be separated from it on the day of judgment, when He will say:
"Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire, which has been prepared for the devil and his angels."
Matthew 25
"And He was teaching daily in the temple."
Luke 19
The Lord teaches daily in the temple through holy preachers whenever the holy Gospel is read, the Apostle is recited, or the doctors preach. The Lord always teaches in the Church, as He Himself said:
"Without me, you can do nothing."
John 15
He said this so that no one can have any excuse for sin on the day of judgment. When the teacher announces the word of God in the Church, Christ teaches in the temple, and whoever despises the preacher's word refuses to hear Christ, as He Himself says:
"Whoever hears you hears me; and whoever rejects you rejects me."
Luke 10
Let us fear this destruction of the city as the destruction of our soul.
Therefore, let us pray to the Lord that He who allowed the destruction of earthly Jerusalem, and later planned for the heavenly Jerusalem to remain, may destroy the sins of our body and soul, so that He may lead us into the chambers of His bride, so that with Him we may endlessly see the good things that are in Jerusalem.