Letter from Pope Adrian to Charlemagne Regarding Images: A Refutation of Those Who Oppose the Second Council of Nicaea
To the most excellent lord, our spiritual son and godfather, Charles, King of the Franks and Lombards, and Patrician of the Romans, I, Pope Adrian, write to you.
Our Lord and Redeemer, who is the author of His wise counsel, descended from heaven from the bosom of the Father.
It is clear to those familiar with the Gospel that the holy leader of all apostles, Peter, was entrusted with the keys of the kingdom of heaven and the care of the entire Church by the Lord's voice.
To Peter, it was said: Do you love me?
Feed my sheep.
John 21.
It was also said to him: Behold, Satan has desired to sift you like wheat; but I have prayed for you, Peter, that your faith may not fail, and when you have turned back, strengthen your brothers.
Luke 22.
Furthermore, it is said to him: You are Peter, and upon this rock, I will build my Church, and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.
I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven.
Matthew 16.
Thus, the care and leadership of the entire Church are entrusted to him.
It is recognized that he entrusted his role to his vicars, the bishops, to carry out the care of the Church.
For he received the keys of the heavenly kingdom, and the power to bind and loose was granted to him.
Therefore, we are confidently assured that if your royal excellence, appointed by God, remains faithful in love and devotion towards His holy Catholic and apostolic Roman Church and us, as you have begun, until the end, you will not only cleanse and save it from every stain of sin but also, with its help, achieve immense victories over all barbarian nations in this world, and furthermore, attain the kingdom of heaven without end.
Moreover, we received a direct message from your most gracious and noble royal authority, through your loyal associate, Engilbert, the abbot and minister of the chapel, who was raised in your palace from childhood and included in all your councils.
Therefore, just as he is familiar to you, he should be received and honored by us appropriately.
Out of the great love we have for your esteemed royal excellence, since you sent him with immense affection and exceptional warmth, we welcomed him as he wished and in the manner he desired, with great familiarity.
We listened to him with a calm ear and an open mind, as if you yourself were speaking to us, and we entrusted him with our advice patiently for the benefit of our holy Roman Church and the exaltation of your royal power protected by God.
Among these matters, he presented us with a document against the synod held in Nicaea regarding the erection of sacred images.
Because of your sincere royal affection, we provided a response to each chapter: not defending any individual, God forbid, but upholding the ancient tradition of the holy Catholic and Apostolic Roman Church.
We follow the ancient teachings of our holy pontifical predecessors, vindicating the tradition of true faith in every way.
In the third action.
In the first chapter, it was mentioned about the phrase: "And in the Holy Spirit, the Lord and giver of life, who proceeds from the Father through the Son."
Criticism.
Tarasius is criticized for not properly believing that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son, according to the Nicene Creed's faith.
Instead, he professes in his reading that the Spirit proceeds from the Father through the Son.
Response.
Tarasius did not explain this doctrine by himself but confessed it through the teachings of the holy Fathers, whose writings we briefly share out of great respect for your most exalted and divinely protected royal excellence.
Namely, Saint Athanasius on the appearance of the Lord in the flesh, in the sermon on the human nature assumed by the only-begotten Word, among other things.
And for this reason, he breathed on the apostles' faces, saying: "Receive the Holy Spirit" as noted in the Gospel of John, chapter twenty.
This was to show that the Spirit given to the disciples comes from the fullness of divinity.
For in Christ, he says, dwells, that is, in his flesh, the entire fullness of divinity bodily, as noted in the letter to the Colossians, chapter two.
As the evangelist John also says: "We have all received from his fullness," as mentioned in John, chapter one.
In bodily form, indeed, the Holy Spirit appeared like a dove, descending and remaining upon him, as described in the Gospel of Luke, chapter three.
For in us, the first fruits and pledge of divinity dwell, but in Christ, the entire fullness of divinity.
And lest anyone thinks that he was receiving as if he did not have it: for he himself sent it to himself from above, as God, and he received it for himself from below, as a man.
Therefore, it descended from him into him, from his divinity into his humanity.
And after much more: It is clear that the Father did everything through him, through him he raises him, through him he sanctifies him, and through him he exalts him, and through him he gives life.
Also, from the same Saint Athanasius on Virginity, among other things: And in the Holy Spirit, who exists in the Father and the Son, who is sent by the Father and given through the Son.
Also from the Ecclesiastical History, book.
Eusebius of Caesarea, after much contemplation: speaks on the faith of Gregory, martyr and bishop of Neocaesarea.
He describes one God, the Father of the living Word, wisdom that exists, and His power and image—the perfect parent of the perfect, the Father of the only-begotten Son.
One Lord, the only one from the only God, the form and image of deity.
The Word that accomplishes all, wisdom that comprehends all, and the power through which all creation is made.
The true Son from the true, invisible from the invisible, incorruptible from the incorruptible, immortal from the immortal, and eternal from the eternal.
One Holy Spirit, having substance from God, who appears through the Son, the image of the perfect Son.
The perfect cause of the living, the provider of the holiness of sanctification, through whom God is known above all and in all.
And not only does this historian mention the faith of Saint Gregory, but also the great preacher Saint Gregory of Nyssa, who in a Greek sermon, wonderfully and splendidly explained how and by whom it was arranged, shown, and seen to Saint Gregory.
Likewise, Saint Hilary in Book Eight on Faith, also known as Book Eight on the Trinity, states: Since the Holy Spirit, who is also the Spirit of Christ and the Spirit of God, is shown to be of one nature, I therefore ask how they are not one by nature?
The Spirit of truth proceeds from the Father, is sent by the Son, and receives from the Son all that the Father and Son have.
Therefore, who receives from Him is the Spirit of God, but the same is also the Spirit of Christ.
And further: For the Spirit of God is in us, but also the Spirit of Christ is in us, and when the Spirit of Christ is present, the Spirit of God is present.
Thus, since what is God's is Christ's, and what is Christ's is God's, Christ cannot be anything different from God.
Therefore, Christ is God, Christ is one with God, as the gospel says: I and the Father are one, etc.
from the Book of John, Chapter Ten.
Likewise, from the letter of Saint Basil to Amphilochius, bishop of Iconium.
Regarding the Holy Spirit to Amphilochius, among other insights:
The Holy Spirit is united with the Father through the Son, completing the most praiseworthy and blessed Trinity.
Shortly after, it's stated: There is one knowledge of God, from one Spirit through one Son in one Father.
Again, natural goodness, sanctification, and royal dignity flow from the Father through the Only Begotten in the Spirit.
Similarly, Saint Ambrose in Book One, Chapter Three on the Holy Spirit, shares:
You will be baptized with the Holy Spirit.
Soon after, he emphasizes: The unity of operation and proclamation cannot be separated.
If the Spirit is separated from the operation of the Father and the Son here, because it is said, "All things are from God," and, "All things are through the Son," then it would be incorrect, as the Apostle said of Christ, "Who is over all, God blessed forever" (Romans 9), to prefer the Father, which is blasphemous to suggest; but that's far from the truth.
The Father is not among all things or among a group of His creatures.
Above all creatures is the divinity of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
The creatures serve, while the divinity reigns; the creatures are subject, while the divinity rules.
In the same way, Saint Gregory the Theologian in his Oration on the Holy Lights mentions:
For us, there is one God the Father, from whom are all things, one Lord Jesus Christ, through whom are all things, and one Holy Spirit, in whom are all things.
By saying "From whom," "Through whom," and "In whom," we do not divide the nature, as the prepositions do not alter the truth of the nature but indicate the property of each name of one nature.
This is clearly shown by the fact that this diversity is united into one; this is evident when one reads without overlooking what the Apostle himself wrote: "Because from Him, through Him, and in Him are all things" (Romans 11), and he concluded: "To Him be glory forever and ever."
Here is a passage from Saint Augustine's sermon on the Ascension of the Lord.
Among many things, he said:
The Holy Spirit was given on earth, visible and close to those nearby, by breathing onto their faces.
From this great love in heaven, He sent the Holy Spirit from above.
Receive the Holy Spirit on earth and love your brother; receive it from heaven and love God, for what you received on earth is also from heaven.
Christ gave it on earth, but the giver is from heaven.
For He gave it, the one who descended from heaven.
From the same Saint Augustine on Pentecost, among other things:
Let the foolish stop flattering and asking us: What will we receive when we come to you, since you admit we already have the baptism of Christ?
Let us answer them: You have the baptism of Christ, come so you may also have the Spirit of Christ.
Fear what is written: But if anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to Him (Romans chapter 8).
You put on Christ in the form of the sacrament, put Him on by imitating the example.
And from the same Saint Augustine in Book 4, Chapter 10, of On the Trinity, among other things:
We cannot say that the Holy Spirit does not proceed from the Son; for it is not without reason that the same Spirit is called the Spirit of the Father and the Son.
Nor do I see what else He meant to signify when He breathed and said: Receive the Holy Spirit (John chapter 20).
That breath, proceeding from the body with a physical sense of touching, was not the substance of the Holy Spirit but a demonstration, indicating that the Holy Spirit proceeds not only from the Father but also from the Son.
For who would be so insane as to say there was one Spirit given by breathing and another sent after His ascension?
There is one Spirit, the Spirit of God, the Spirit of the Father and the Son, the Holy Spirit who works all things in all (First Corinthians chapter 12).
Also, from the same Saint Augustine in Book 15, Chapter 26, of On the Trinity, among other things:
It is taught that He proceeds from both, for the Son Himself said: He proceeds from the Father (John chapter 15).
After he rose from the dead and appeared to his disciples, he breathed on them, saying,
"Receive the Holy Spirit."
(John 20)
This gesture showed that the Spirit comes from him as well.
As the Gospel tells us, it was the power that emanated from him and healed everyone.
(Luke 6)
Shortly after:
This signifies that the Lord Jesus gave the Holy Spirit twice: once on earth for the love of neighbor, and again from heaven for the love of God.
According to the teachings of Saint Cyril, Ninth Anathema, among other things:
If anyone claims that the Lord Jesus Christ was glorified by the Holy Spirit as if by an external power, which worked through him against unclean spirits and performed divine signs, and does not acknowledge that it is truly his own Spirit through which he performed these signs, let him be anathema, etc.
From the same Saint Cyril to John of Antioch, among other things:
Do not move the eternal boundaries set by your fathers.
(Deuteronomy 16)
For they were not speaking by themselves, but by the Spirit of God and the Father, who proceeds from him yet is not separate from the Son in essence.
The words of the saints who passed down the mysteries confirm this for us.
It is written in the Acts of the Apostles:
Coming around Mysia, they tried to go into Bithynia, but the Spirit of Jesus did not allow them.
(Acts 16)
The venerable Paul also writes:
Those who are in the flesh cannot please God.
But you are not in the flesh, but in the Spirit, if indeed the Spirit of God dwells in you.
If anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, they do not belong to him, etc.
(Romans 8)
From Saint Cyril on the worship of the Spirit, from the first book, among other things:
Just as it is of God, and the Father, and also of the Son substantially, proceeding from both, namely from the Father through the Son, and so on.
From the same Saint Cyril from the acclamatory book to Emperor Theodosius, among other things:
Therefore, even if it is said that wherever the Father gives life, he does this entirely through the Son by the Holy Spirit, etc.
From the encyclical letter of Saint Leo the Pope to Flavian, Archbishop of Constantinople (Letter 12), among other things:
He entered through closed doors to the disciples John 20, and with his breath, he gave the Holy Spirit.
By granting the light of understanding, he revealed the hidden meanings of the Holy Scriptures.
Also, from the sermon of the same Saint Leo, a prominent doctor, on Pentecost:
All, beloved ones, who believed in the Lord Jesus, had the Holy Spirit poured into them.
The apostles received the power of forgiving sins when, after his resurrection, the Lord breathed on them and said: Receive the Holy Spirit; whose sins you forgive, they are forgiven; and whose sins you retain, they are retained, etc.
John 20.
Therefore, the distinguished preacher and eloquent teacher, Saint Gregory the Pope, in his homily 26 on the Holy Gospel, among other things, says:
When the Comforter comes, whom I will send to you from the Father John 15.
If being sent should only be understood as being incarnated, the Holy Spirit would not be said to be sent, for he was not incarnated.
But his being sent is the procession itself, by which he proceeds from the Father and the Son.
Just as the Spirit is said to be sent because he proceeds, so the Son is not incongruously said to be sent because he is begotten.
When he had said this, he breathed on them and said: Receive the Holy Spirit John 20.
We must ask why our Lord gave the Holy Spirit once while standing on earth and once while presiding in heaven.
Also, from the same Saint Gregory the Pope's book 27 on Job, among other things:
About which John says: All things were made through him John 1.
Thus, he is called the mouth, as if by the name of mouth the Word is openly declared, just as we also usually call words the tongue, so that when we speak of the Greek or Latin tongue, we show Greek or Latin words.
Therefore, we rightly understand the mouth of the Lord as the one through whom he speaks all things to us.
Hence, the prophet says: For the mouth of the Lord has spoken this, etc.
Isaiah.
The holy Catholic and Apostolic Church, receiving the order of masses, solemnities, and prayers from Saint Gregory the Pope himself, has given us many prayers.
It teaches us to humbly ask for the Holy Spirit to be poured into us, enlightening and strengthening us through our Lord Jesus Christ.
Among the many teachings of Saint Sophronius, whose orthodox doctrines are honored in the Holy Sixth Council:
The Father has done all things through the only-begotten Son in the Holy Spirit, maintaining them with wise providence, as God presides over His works.
IN THE SAME ACTION. CHAPTER 2 - Critique.
There is a question about whether Theodore, the Archbishop of Jerusalem, is correct in his belief.
He stated that he believes the Father is completely without beginning and eternal, and, using some obscure phrase, claimed that the Son knows no other origin than the Father and has His being from Him.
Response.
Theodore, the Patriarch of Jerusalem, along with other major patriarchs, specifically Cosmas of Alexandria and another Theodore of Antioch, sent a letter of their true faith to our predecessor of holy memory, the former Pope Paul.
In this letter, they included a detailed explanation about the most sacred images, showing how they, along with our holy Catholic and apostolic universal Roman Church, and the other Eastern Orthodox bishops and Christian people, are fervent in faith with sincere affection of mind in the veneration of these holy images.
Our predecessor, the former most holy Lord Pope Stephen, received and read this letter translated into Latin at his council, which he held with various bishops in parts of France and Italy concerning the sacred images.
They were pleased with both the testimonies of various French Fathers and the creed of faith where it was made, stating:
If anyone holds a different term of faith, creed, or doctrine from what was handed down by the six holy great and universal synods and confirmed by the holy Fathers who attended them, and does not worship the image or figure of our Lord Jesus Christ, nor confess His incarnation, as He descended and was incarnate for the sake of humanity, we anathematize such an impious person and consider them foreign and estranged from the holy Catholic and apostolic Church; and other things which are too lengthy to recount.
Therefore, the aforementioned Archbishop Theodore professed in this way, following the doctrine of the holy Fathers, namely Saint Hilary of Poitiers from Book One against the Arian heresy, among other things.
Indeed, it's clear that he was born to show that he has always existed.
In him, there's not an exception to being unbegotten, but rather, an eternity of being born.
Birth has a source, and divinity is not without eternity.
Similarly, from Saint Hilary in Book Eleven on Faith: It's well understood and believed by us.
We confess through words that he was born, yet we don't proclaim he was not born.
Being unbegotten is not the same as being born; the former is from another, while the latter is from no one.
It's one thing to be eternal without a source, and another to be co-eternal with the Father, who is the source.
Where the Father is the source, there is also birth.
And where the source is eternal, there is also the eternity of birth.
Just as birth is from the source, so from an eternal source comes eternal birth.
Similarly, from Saint Gregory, known as the Theologian, in his sermon on Epiphany, also called the Oration on the Holy Lights: The Father is the Father without beginning, as there is nothing else from which the Father is.
The Son is the Son, but not without beginning, for he is from the Father.
If you consider the beginning in terms of time, he is also without beginning.
He is the creator of time and does not take his beginning from it.
The Holy Spirit is truly the Holy Spirit, proceeding from the Father, but he is not the Son: he is not begotten but proceeds.
Similarly, from the same Saint Gregory the Theologian in the sermon on the Birth of the Lord: This is the Word of God himself, who is before the ages, invisible, incomprehensible, and incorporeal; who is the beginning from the beginning, light from light, the source of life and immortality, the true and express image of the substance of God, the seal of truth, the image of the invisible God the Father.
Similarly, from the same Saint Gregory the Theologian in the second Peaceful Sermon, Oration Two on Peace: I introduce the beginning of deity without time, indivisibly, and immensely, honoring the beginning and what is from the beginning.
Similarly, from the same Saint Gregory the Theologian in the Apologetic Sermon.
When discussing doctrines and constitutions, particularly in the middle, etc.
Whose Son would he be if his origin isn't traced back to the Father?
Thus, the one who begets exists, and the one begotten comes from him.
The origin of the Father is not insignificant or unworthy, but rather of divinity and goodness.
The Father is recognized as the origin in the Son and the Holy Spirit, and is perceived in him, whether as in the Son as the Word, or as in the Spirit proceeding from him, etc.
Similarly, Saint Augustine on Genesis literally, from the first book below, etc.
When Scripture states: In the beginning, God created heaven and earth (Genesis 1:1), we understand the name of God, also referring to the Son in the name of the beginning, who is the beginning of all creation, not for the Father, but by himself, especially for spiritual creation, and consequently for all creation.
When Scripture says: And the Spirit of God was hovering over the waters (Genesis 1:2), we recognize the complete mention of the Trinity, etc.
Similarly, from the same Saint Augustine from book thirty-eight on the Gospel of John, among other things:
The Son is the Son of the Father, and indeed the Father is the Father of the Son.
The Son is called God from God; the Son is called light from light.
The Father is called light, but not from light; the Father is called God, but not from God.
If, therefore, God from God, light from light is the beginning, how much easier is it to understand the beginning as the light from which light, and God from whom God?
Isn't it absurd, my beloved, to say the Son is the beginning, and not say the Father is the beginning?
But what shall we do, shall there be two beginnings?
We must be careful not to say this.
So, if the Father is the beginning and the Son is the beginning, how are they not two beginnings?
How do we say the Father is God, the Son is God, and yet we do not say two gods?
It is incorrect to say two gods.
It is indeed wrong to say three gods.
And further: In what is said about the Spirit of the Father and the Son, there is nothing to say three; unless the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, are one God, one Almighty: therefore, one beginning, etc.
Similarly, from the same from book six (chapter).
When discussing the Holy Trinity, we often consider questions like:
How is God from God, light from light?
It's not that both together are God from God; only the Son is from God, that is, the Father.
Similarly, not both together are light from light; only the Son is light from the light of the Father.
Now, let's look at the synodical letter of Saint Sophronius, Archbishop of Jerusalem, which was presented at the holy Sixth Council, Act 11.
It states, among other things:
So, I believe, dear ones, as I have always believed, in one God, the Father Almighty, who is without beginning and eternal, the creator of all things visible and invisible.
I also believe in one Lord Jesus Christ, the only-begotten Son of God, who was eternally and without suffering born from God and the Father, acknowledging no other beginning than the Father;
and He has no existence apart from the Father himself: light from light, consubstantial, true God from true God, co-eternal.
And I believe in one Holy Spirit, who eternally proceeds from God the Father, recognized as light and as God himself.
IN THE SIXTH SESSION. CHAPTER 3 Critique
Tarasius made a mistake when he said that the Holy Spirit is a companion to the Father and the Son.
It would have sufficed to say co-eternal, consubstantial, and of the same essence and nature.
Response from Saint Sophronius himself:
Since he has sworn falsely, he should have sworn regarding the liar.
Among the choices of evils, it was better to choose the more beneficial one.
Also, from Saint Augustine in the preface to Psalm 31, among other things:
We should propose no works before faith, meaning no one should claim to have done good works before having faith.
For those works, said to be before faith, even if they seem praiseworthy to people, are empty.
To me, they seem like great strength and a very swift course off the path.
Therefore, no one should count their good works before faith.
In the Fourth Action
Chapter Fifteen Critique
This wasn't written for those who reject the worship of images, as those who do worship them claim.
As it says in the Psalm:
"How the enemy has acted maliciously against your holy ones?"
(Psalm Seventy-Three)
Response.
These words were truly spoken against heretics.
The blessed Augustine explains in his commentary on the same Psalm:
"How maliciously the enemy has acted against your holy ones, in those things that were your holy things, meaning the temple, the priesthood, and all those sacraments that existed at that time,"
etc.
Similarly, even today, the enemy's greater evils have been nullified against the sacred Catholic and Apostolic Church, which maliciously opposes the ancient and orthodox tradition of sacred images.
Furthermore, Saint Gregory of Nazianzus, also known as the Theologian, in his sermon about the philosopher Iron (Oration in Praise of Iron, around the middle), says among other things:
"How could they not boast?
How indeed did they not defile the holy temple with various intrusions?
And in all evils, an impious and unjust man prevailed, not even carrying the name of Christianity,"
etc.
In the Fifth Action
Chapter 15 Critique
The letter, reportedly from Saint Simeon Stylites to Emperor Justinian, is said to differ significantly from the divine Scriptures and the teachings of the holy Fathers, because it addresses the emperor directly:
For whom we mention and convey to your divine ears;
or because it's claimed that the emperor prohibited the use of mercy.
Here's the response.
When Saint Ambrose wrote to Emperor Gratian about the orthodox faith, did he err by calling him, Holy Emperor?
What was out of line in addressing the most Christian Emperor Justinian, expressing thoughts to his divine ears for his faith's zeal?
When referring to divine ears, it means he listens to divine words and observes them faithfully and orthodoxly, thus rightly having divine hearing.
The prohibition of mercy is misunderstood; instead, it was a plea for swift and decent retribution, not lacking mercy, but showing great love towards the images of the saints by condemning the impious.
Your God-inspired excellence surely acknowledges Saint Gregory's account in his Dialogues about the blessed Boniface, who sorrowfully struck down a wretch who, with a monkey, made cymbal sounds with his speech.
Shortly after, Saint Gregory (Book One, chapter nine) states:
The wrath of the just is fearsome because He who dwells in their hearts can enact the vengeance He desires.
Similarly, in explaining blessed Job (Book 34, chapter 10), Saint Gregory discusses the strong preachers of the holy Church, adding:
The Lord tells the prophet about good teachers: They will devour and subject to the stones of the sling (Zechariah chapter nine).
Indeed, the holy teachers, who guide others in virtue, conquer enemies by transforming them through the power of conversion.
Strong men emerge from that Church, striking fear into the hearts of the wicked as if hit by stone blows.
This is why even the mightiest Goliath falls to a stone from a sling, as told in First Samuel Chapter Seventeen, because diabolical pride is defeated by the cornerstone of the holy Church.
In the same Action
Chapter 17 Critique.
It is said that all heretics are worse than Samaritans, and those who destroy images are even worse than Samaritans, despite their ancestors being considered worse than all heretics because they destroyed images as well.
Response: In this context, the eloquent teacher, blessed Gregory the Theologian, in a sermon about the Birth of the Lord, says:
You are offended by the flesh; so were the Jews.
If you also call him a Samaritan, and to leave other things unsaid, you do not believe in the deity; even demons do not do this.
O, you are more unfaithful than the Jews and worse than the demons, etc.
Also from the edict of Emperor Justinian, it is noted:
But neither Theodore of Mopsuestia, who surpassed both Jews and Greeks in his impiety, etc.
Furthermore, the holy Pope Gregory, in his explanation of blessed Job from book 14, states:
Just as eating too much honey is not good for you, so the one who is a scrutinizer of majesty is overwhelmed by glory.
(Proverbs 25)
And below: The glory of the invisible creator, when sought moderately, lifts us up, but when examined beyond our strength, it oppresses us.
Hence, the more heretics seek to fill themselves with lofty understanding, the more they empty themselves.
For those who crave the knowledge of the supreme with unrestrained ears, the more they seek it, the more they lose it.
In contrast, those who are truly humble and well-educated in the holy Church know how to grasp some heavenly secrets and revere those they do not understand:
So that they hold reverently what they understand and await humbly what they do not yet understand.
This bold presumption is well restrained by the excellent preacher, who advises:
Do not think of yourself more highly than you ought, but rather think of yourself with sober judgment.
(Romans 12)
Therefore, their predecessors, by exalting themselves and trying to impose novelty, became worse heretics and were reduced to nothing.
In the Same Action
Chapter 18 Critique
There is no Gospel passage that describes Jesus sending an image to Abgar, contrary to some claims.
Response.
Our predecessor, the revered Pope Stephen, presiding over the council mentioned earlier, shared many true testimonies, teaching as follows:
We should not ignore what we have often heard from trustworthy reports coming from the East.
Even though the Gospel does not speak of these events, the strength of faith is not entirely unbelievable, with the evangelist himself stating:
John did many other signs as well, which are not written in this book.
(John 20).
Indeed, it is reported by some, as Eusebius documents in Book One, Chapter Thirteen, that as the time of his passion drew near, the Redeemer of mankind responded to a certain king of Edessa who wished to see him in person.
The king invited Jesus to escape Jewish persecution and share the miracles and healings he had heard about:
If you wish to see my face physically, here is an image of my face imprinted on a cloth, which can satisfy your desire and show that what you have heard about me is indeed possible.
However, after I fulfill what is written about me, I will send you one of my disciples, who will bring health to you and your people and guide you to the height of faith, etc.
Additionally, from the synodical letter of the three patriarchs—Cosmas of Alexandria, Theodore of Antioch, and Theodore of Jerusalem—which was read at the council and respected by all:
after many testimonies from the holy Fathers, Theodore, the patriarch of Jerusalem, stated:
It remains for me to recount the time concerning Abgar of Edessa, and other similar matters of the holy Fathers, which you also know well.
Keep going, most holy Father, continue with the same good faith, strengthened on the rock of faith, just as the divine voice spoke to the Apostle Peter:
"You are Peter, and on this rock I will build my Church; and the gates of hell will not overcome it" (Matthew 16).
Truly, they will not overcome it forever and ever.
We want to let you know, most holy lord, that I, humble Theodore, Patriarch of Jerusalem, along with Cosmas, Patriarch of Alexandria, and Theodore, Patriarch of Antioch, understand and believe the same thing, as it is evident to your holiness, etc.
In the same Action Chapter 19 Critique
This might seem unrelated, as it's written:
"There is no longer a prophet, and we will not be recognized anymore" Psalm 74.
Response.
For those heretics who, during the false assembly under Constantine, once a heretic emperor, claimed to know and understand something, but in reality, did not, they themselves mentioned this in the psalm.
They are likened to the Jews, about whom the blessed Augustine explained in the same psalm, saying:
"Look, these Jews, who say they are not recognized yet;"
and shortly after:
"You no longer see your signs, there is no longer a prophet, and you say: 'And we will not be recognized anymore,' because you do not recognize yet.
There is no longer a prophet, and we will not be recognized anymore: until when, God, has the enemy reproached?"
Similarly, these heretics:
"until when their leader, namely Constantine the heresiarch, was reproached, they did not understand, and therefore they were reduced to nothing."
In the Sixth ActionChapter 20 Critique
How should we understand the words in the Song of Songs: "Show me your face, let me hear your voice, for your voice is sweet, and your face is lovely" (Song of Songs 2); which have been applied, perhaps controversially, to the vision of images?
Response: They have applied it appropriately, because the vision of holy images relates to the beautiful form of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ according to the flesh, His holy mother, and the saints.
In the person of Christ and the Church, various works of the holy Fathers have interpreted the Song of Songs.
If they wish to know how it should be understood, we present the exposition of Saint Epiphanius, Bishop of Cyprus, where he mentions:
"Show me your face, let me hear your voice" meaning, do not communicate with me just through the law and prophets, but reveal yourself to me entirely: just as Moses, filled with the same desire, confidently asked God: "Show me yourself, that I may see you" (Exodus 35).
At that time, God said to Moses: "No one shall see my face and live." However, wishing to reveal Himself to His bride, He incarnated and appeared to her in the flesh, through virtue, support, and innocence, offering her a vision of piety.
He thus showed her His face, conceived in the virgin Mother of God (Matthew 5), and let her hear His voice when He taught the disciples on the Mount of Olives, and again when He spread the message of preaching through them to the whole world.
For your voice is sweet, and your face is lovely (Song of Songs 2).
His voice is indeed sweet, as it says: "Come, blessed of my Father," etc. (Matthew 25).
Your voice is sweet, as it made the blind see when He said: "According to your faith, let it be done to you" (Matthew 9).
Your voice is sweet, inviting: "Come to me all who labor," etc. (Matthew 11).
Your voice is sweet, saying to the paralytic: "Rise, take up your mat, and walk" (Mark 2).
The voice is sweet, reassuring: "Have courage, son, your sins are forgiven" (Matthew).
Your voice is sweet, saying: "Have courage, daughter, your faith has saved you; go in peace." (Luke 7) And many other things that would take too long to write out in detail.
In the Sixth Action of volume 1
Chapter 21 Critique
The passage stating, "God created man in His own image and likeness," does not relate to the worship of images.
Response: If they understand that God created man in His own image and likeness, as mentioned in Genesis Chapter 1, due to the explanation given by Patriarch Tarasius for the worship of images, they seem to lack understanding, as it is written, and they could not grasp it.
When Patriarch Tarasius rejected the council of heretics and reproached them for daring to speak against the stability of sacred images in their obscurity, he said: "To the extent that God, the Creator, sees His own handiwork perish," etc.
He said this with the understanding that the earthly man is honored as the image of God, etc.
And shortly after: They boast fiercely about the making of images and their empty deliberation, and by weaving various speeches, they judge the Church of God as if it were in error, etc.
For God created man in His own image and likeness.
Blessed Augustine, in Book 5, regarding what is read in Genesis about what was made on the sixth day, says among other things: "And now pay attention: man is set in his punishment, and consider how much of the image of God remains in him."
He destroyed that image through sin, and it is restored through grace, by which lust is worn away.
Just as a coin loses the image of the emperor when rubbed against the ground, so does the mind of man lose the image of God when rubbed by earthly lusts.
But Christ, the money changer, comes to re-stamp the coins.
How does He re-stamp the coins? By forgiving sins through grace, showing that God seeks His image.
For when they asked Him about paying taxes to Caesar: "Is it lawful to give tribute to Caesar?" (Matthew 22; Mark 12) They were testing Him, so that if He said, "Do not give," they could accuse Him through the tax collectors: "Look, He teaches us not to pay the tax"; but if He said, "Give," they could say: "Look, He cursed Jerusalem: He made it subject to tribute."
So what did He say, and what did He advise?
Why do you test me, hypocrites? Bring me a coin. And they brought it to him.
He asked, Whose image and inscription are on it? They replied, Caesar’s.
Then he said, So give back to Caesar what is Caesar’s, and to God what is God’s.
If Caesar seeks his image on the coin, does God not seek his image in man?
Similarly, the holy Severian, Bishop of Gabala, in a homily given on Saturday, spoke about the Image and Likeness from the Book of Genesis, Chapter Eight, and said:
Just as we honor the emperor's image when he is not present, creation, not seeing the invisible one made in his image, honored him.
In the Fourth Action
Chapter 22 Critique
How to understand what is written.
Abraham worshipped the people of the land, the sons of Heth, as mentioned in Genesis 23.
It is also said that Moses worshipped Jethro.
These examples are often used by those who hold councils for worshipping images to support their error.
However, neither Jacob worshipped Pharaoh, nor did Daniel worship Nebuchadnezzar the king, as they claim.
These acts are not read anywhere to have happened.
Response:
Blessed Augustine taught us in Psalm 46, saying:
The Lord our God spreads the faith, in which we live, through His books, the Holy Scriptures, in many and various ways.
He varies the sacraments of words, yet recommends one faith.
The same thing is expressed in many ways to keep the manner of speaking varied and prevent boredom, while maintaining one faith for harmony.
Also, from the same blessed Augustine about Abraham's son brought to sacrifice, among other things:
The two servants left behind and not brought to the place of sacrifice signified the Jews.
That donkey, I don't know what it signified of the Jews.
Do not be surprised because one thing can be signified in many ways.
In the Same Action
Chapter 23 Critique
This chapter isn't about the worship of images, nor is it mentioned in our translations from the Hebrew texts.
Contrary to what some say in their synod, there's no record of Jacob receiving Joseph's torn robe from his sons, kissing it with tears, and placing it on his eyes.
From the third peaceful sermon of Saint Gregory the Theologian, Oration 2 on peace:
Peace, my friend, praised as good by everyone yet preserved by few, where have you gone for so long, and when will you return to us?
I embrace the present, and I call upon the departing with many lamentations and tears.
Neither Jacob's sorrow for Joseph, the patriarch sold by his brothers and not captured by a beast as he feared, nor David's grief for Jonathan, his friend, or for his son Absalom, one of whom was torn from his heart, can compare.
A beast has taken him, Jacob cried, Joseph, a most wicked and untamed beast.
And the boy's torn garment was placed, as if he were kissing the boy’s flesh, etc.
Thus, many Fathers have included assertions from various histories in their works.
In the third book of Saint Ambrose to Emperor Gratian, Chapter 3, it is noted:
Do not conclude that because Gabriel does not die, Raphael does not die, Uriel does not die.
Indeed, in our books, translated from the Hebrew truth, Uriel is not mentioned.
Similarly, in the second book of the same Saint Ambrose on the Holy Spirit, Chapter 7:
Ezra taught us, saying in the third book.
However, the third book of Ezra is not included in our books, which are translated from the Hebrew truth; only two are included.
Additionally, Saint Gregory, the distinguished pope, mentioned it in his letter to Theoctista the patrician.
In letter thirty-nine, he mentions how powerful the forerunner of our Redeemer was, describing him not only as more than a prophet through sacred words but also as an angel.
Yet, as the story of his death reveals, after he died, his body was burned by persecutors.
The Gospel of Matthew, chapter fourteen, tells us that Saint John the Baptist's body was buried by his disciples.
Blessed Gregory recounts in history that Saint John the Baptist's body was burned.
Thus, as we've discussed, the words of the saints are never dismissed, for who can fully comprehend all of the sacred divine Scripture?
In the Same ActionChapter 24 Critique
Regarding the statement that seems ignorant and disorderly:
If you accuse me of worshipping the wood of the cross as God, why do you not accuse Jacob of worshipping the top of Joseph's staff?
It's clear that he did not worship the wood he saw, but God through Joseph's staff, just as we worship Christ through the cross.
Here's the response:
The staff, specifically the scepter, was beautifully explained by the blessed Augustine as a symbol of the cross in Psalm Thirty-Seven.
Among other things, he said:
Let us rejoice that it is already happening in the name of Christ.
Now, holding the scepter, they submit to the wood of the cross.
What was foretold is now happening: All the kings of the earth will worship him; all nations will serve him (Psalm Seventy-Two).
Now, on the foreheads of kings, the sign of the cross is more precious than the gem of a crown.
In the Same Action
Chapter 25 Critique
This doesn't relate to the worship of images, even though it is written: Jacob blessed Pharaoh.
Response.
Holy Scripture always instructs us to bless: Bless and do not curse Romans 12.
Additionally: Bless all the works of the Lord Daniel 3.
We are taught: and again, in prayer, spiritually prostrate before the Holy of Holies, we chant: May God, our God, bless us, may God bless us, and may all the ends of the earth fear Him.
Therefore, if we aim to discuss the blessings of Divine Scripture, before the discourse concludes on the page, as we presume, we add one more testimony from Saint Augustine about Jacob wrestling with the angel.
Among other things, he says: I will not let you go unless you bless me Psalm 67.
Because the Lord first blesses us through the flesh, the faithful understand what they receive, since they are blessed through the flesh:
They know they would not be blessed unless that flesh was crucified for the life of the world.
In the Fifth ActionChapter 26 Critique
This chapter discusses the vain hope of those who believe they can achieve salvation through images, claiming:
"Just as the Israelites were saved by looking at the bronze serpent, so we will be saved by looking at the images of saints."
Response.
This has already been addressed by the sacred councils of my most holy papal predecessors, as well as by the most holy Fathers.
For the understanding of unbelievers and the guidance of the Franks, it must be noted what God commanded His servant Moses, saying:
"As written in the Book of Numbers, against the plague that afflicted them: Make a serpent and set it up as a sign; whoever is bitten and looks at it will live."
So Moses made a bronze serpent and set it up as a sign; when those who were bitten looked at it, they were healed.
Numbers twenty-one.
O madness of those who rage against the Christian faith and religion, claiming not to worship or venerate images, which depict our Savior, His mother, or the saints, whose virtue sustains the world and grants salvation to humankind.
Do we believe the Israelites were freed from their calamity by looking at the bronze serpent, yet doubt that we can be saved by looking at and venerating the images of Christ our God and the saints?
Let us not succumb to the wicked audacity of such insanity: let us follow the ancient traditions of the Fathers and not depart from their teachings for any reason.
By doing so, we can obtain the full grace, just as our predecessors and fathers did.
Also, from the blessed Augustine on how God appeared, with the rod and the hand turned white, and water turned into blood:
"Just as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, so must the Son of Man be lifted up, that everyone who believes in Him may not perish but have eternal life."
John three.
This means that whoever is struck by the serpents of sin should look to Christ and will have healing through the forgiveness of sins.
Also from the same Saint Augustine on the Gospel of John, in the same sermon homily.
In the twelfth chapter, among other topics, we find this:
Brothers, let's look to Christ crucified to heal us from sin.
Just as Moses lifted up the serpent in the desert, it is said: "But may have eternal life"; and later: "That he may have eternal life."
This illustrates the difference between a symbol and the reality itself: the symbol provided temporary life, while the reality, which the symbol represented, offers eternal life.
Similarly, in Saint Augustine's book three on the Trinity, chapter ten, it states:
Just as the anointing of the stone represents Christ in the flesh, anointed with the oil of gladness above his fellows, the rod of Moses turning into a serpent symbolizes Christ becoming obedient to death on the cross.
That's why it's said: "As Moses lifted up the serpent in the desert, so must the Son of Man be lifted up, that everyone who believes in him may not perish but have eternal life."
John Chapter Three.
Just as those who looked at the serpent lifted up in the desert were saved from its bites,
our old self was crucified with him.
The serpent represents death, which was brought about by the serpent in paradise, metaphorically showing the cause and its effect.
Therefore, the rod turning into a serpent symbolizes Christ's death, and the serpent turning back into a rod symbolizes Christ's resurrection, all connected to his body, which is the Church.
Additionally, in the sermon by Saint Severian, Bishop of Gabala, on the Holy Cross, it is discussed:
Do you think it would have been right to say: "If any of you is bitten, let him look up to heaven to God, and he will be saved?"
He could not say: "If anyone is bitten, let him look at the light of the lamp, and he will be saved,"
or "Look at the table of the showbread, and he will be saved,"
or at the altar, the veil, the ark, the image of the cherubim, or the mercy seat.
Instead, the great lawgiver presented none of these, but only fixed the image of the cross, using the cursed serpent as a symbol.
As a faithful servant, consider: Do you do what you forbid? Do you build what you renounce?
You say, "Do not make carved images," yet you sculpt a molten serpent?
I established that law to eliminate sources of impiety and to save this people from idol worship.
Now, however, I create the serpent to foreshadow the Savior's plan, paving the way for the apostles.
In the fifth action
Chapter 27 Critique
Leo of Phocaea, the bishop, persistently and nonsensically spoke about the worship of images, using a verse from the Psalmist for himself, saying:
"You have turned my mourning into joy for me; you have torn my sackcloth and clothed me with joy." Psalm thirty.
Response.
Every Christian is allowed to pray with the Psalmist, so that when they come from darkness to light through the grace of Christ, they can rightly say:
"You have turned my mourning into joy for me," because when they are delivered from heresy, their sackcloth is torn.
And when they recognize the truth of the true faith, they are surrounded by the joy of the orthodox of the holy Catholic Church.
On this very matter, Saint Augustine similarly states in the explanation of the same psalm:
"You have torn the lament of my sins, the sorrow of my mortality, and clothed me with the first robe, immortal joy."
And again:
"So that I may not mourn, but sing to you, not in humility, but in my glory; because you have already exalted me from humility, and I am not troubled by the conscience of sin, the fear of death, the fear of judgment, and so forth."
In the sixth action, at the end of the first volume, Chapter 28: Critique.
This doesn't relate to the worship of images, despite what the Psalmist sang:
"Each one speaks lies to his neighbor; with flattering lips and a double heart they speak" (Psalm twelve, verse two).
Response:
It's not that they ignored what the Psalmist sang:
"Each one speaks lies," etc.;
but rather, in rejecting the nonsense of heretics in their misguided presence, they sang with the Psalmist about them:
"Each one speaks lies to his neighbor," and so on.
In Saint Augustine's explanation of the same psalm, among other points:
There is one truth by which holy souls are enlightened.
However, since there are many souls, many truths can be spoken within them, just as many images appear in mirrors from one face.
And shortly after:
Proud hypocrites are indicated, those who place their hope in their speech to deceive people, yet do not submit to God.
In the Second Action
Chapter 29 Critique
How should we understand the Psalmist's words: Mercy and truth have met together; righteousness and peace have kissed, as found in Psalm 85?
John, the presbyter and delegate of the Easterners, stated, perhaps too boldly or flatteringly, during the participation of the blessed Pope Adrian and Tarasius, that this has been fulfilled.
Response: It is rightly said because God showed mercy on the Church of Constantinople and met the truth of the holy Catholic and Apostolic Roman Church.
The Roman Church always upheld justice, as it is written: The seat of justice, the house of faith, the hall of modesty.
The Church of Constantinople embraced this justice, faith, and modesty when it turned away from error and made peace.
Only the seat of Constantinople resisted the orthodox faith.
The seats of Alexandria, Antioch, and Jerusalem always held the ancient tradition with us, namely the orthodox faith, as their synodical acts for the stability of holy images show.
Blessed Augustine, in his explanation of the same psalm, said: Because righteousness and peace kiss, they do not argue.
Why do you argue with justice?
Look, justice tells you: Do not steal, and you do not listen.
Do not commit adultery, and you do not want to hear.
Do not do to others what you do not want to suffer.
Do not say to others what you do not want to be said to you.
Peace tells you, you are an enemy of my friend, why do you seek me?
I am a friend of justice.
Whoever I find to be an enemy of my friend, I do not approach them.
So, do you want to come to peace?
Do justice.
Therefore, another psalm tells you: Turn away from evil and do good, as found in Psalm 37.
That is, love justice; and when you have turned away from evil and done good, seek peace and pursue it, etc.
In the Fourth Action
Chapter 30 Critique
This isn't about worshiping images, as some suggest, when it is written: Exalt the Lord our God; and worship at His footstool, for it is holy (Psalm 99).
Response.
In explaining this psalm, Blessed Augustine, about midway through, mentions:
I am not afraid to worship the footstool of my Lord, because the psalm instructs: Worship at His footstool;
and soon after, he adds: I turn to Christ, because I seek Him here, and I understand how the earth can be worshiped without wrongdoing, how the footstool of His feet can be revered without sin.
He took earth from the earth, as flesh comes from the earth, and He took flesh from Mary's flesh.
Since He walked here in that flesh and gave us that flesh to eat for our salvation:
no one eats that flesh without first worshiping it;
this shows how such a footstool of the Lord can be worshiped, and not only do we not sin by worshiping, but we actually sin by not worshiping.
And a little later.
Thus, any earth, when you bow and prostrate yourself, you do not regard it as just earth, but as Him who is holy, whose footstool you worship;
you worship because of Him.
So, he also adds here: Worship at His footstool, for it is holy (Psalm 99).
Who is holy, in whose honor you worship the footstool of His feet?
In the Same Action Chapter 31 Critique
The idea that the worship of images can be justified by the scripture, "Worship in his holy mountain," from Psalm 99:9, is challenged.
The response to this is found in Blessed Augustine's commentary on the same psalm, where, towards the end, he explains:
"Heretics do not worship on this mountain, because this mountain has spread over the entire earth.
They focused on a part and lost the whole.
If they recognize the Catholic Church, they will worship on this mountain with us.
Indeed, that stone, which was cut from the mountain without hands, we can see how much it has grown, how many regions of the earth it has reached, and to which nations it has spread."
Shortly after, he continues: "We see all the kingdoms of the earth broken by that stone," referring to the book of Daniel, chapter 2.
"What were all the kingdoms of the earth?
The kingdoms of idols and demons are broken.
Saturn once ruled over many people; where is his kingdom now?
Mercury ruled over many; where is his kingdom now?
They are broken; they have been brought into the kingdom of Christ, in whom he reigns."
And shortly after: "Therefore, that stone was born from the mountain without hands; it grew, and by growing, broke all the kingdoms of the earth.
It became a great mountain and filled the entire earth.
This is the Catholic Church, with which you are glad to be connected.
But those who are not connected with it, who worship and praise God outside of this mountain, are not heard unto eternal life, etc."
In the Same Action
Chapter 32 Critique
It's not because of those who scorn the worship of images, as they irrationally claim, that the prophet says:
"The Lord will lead away those who turn aside to deceit with those who do evil," Psalm one hundred twenty-five.
Response.
They spoke about heretics:
As the blessed Augustine explained in the same psalm, towards the end, among other points:
This refers to those whose deeds they imitated, because they loved present joys and did not believe in future punishments.
And shortly after, he adds:
Therefore, because Christ, the Son of God, is peace, He came to gather His own and separate them from the wicked.
Which wicked ones?
Those who hate Jerusalem, who hate peace, who want to disrupt unity, who do not believe in peace, and so on.
In the Fifth Action Chapter 33 Critique
Very absurdly and recklessly, a testimony from the holy Gospel was brought forth by those who worship images against those who disdain them:
No one lights a lamp and puts it under a basket Luke Chapter 11.
Response.
Very beautifully and appropriately, they said that a lamp is put under a basket against those who disdain images, because the lamp represents our faith, specifically that of the holy Catholic and Apostolic Church.
About this faith, Saint Ambrose, bishop of Milan, testifies in his explanation on the holy Gospel according to Luke (Book 7, Chapter 11), saying among other things:
No one lights a lamp and puts it in secret or under a basket, but on a lampstand Luke Chapter 11.
Therefore, since the Church is preferred over the Synagogue, it encourages us to place more of our faith in the Church.
For the lamp is faith, as it is written, Your word is a lamp to my feet, Lord Psalm 119.
The word of God is our faith, the word of God is light John Chapter 1, and faith is a lamp.
And shortly after: Therefore, let no one establish faith under the law.
For the law is within measure, beyond measure is grace.
The law obscures, grace clarifies; therefore, let no one confine their faith within the measure of the law, but bring it to the Church, where the sevenfold grace of the Spirit shines, illuminated by the brightness of divine majesty, lest the shadow of the law extinguish it.
Also, Saint John Chrysostom, in his interpretation of the Gospel according to Matthew (Homily 15, after the middle), says among other things:
Indeed, he says, I have lit the light: but let it be burning by your speed: not only for you, but also for those who are to come, to be gladdened by this brightness and led to virtue, etc.
In the Same Action Chapter 34 Critique
The statement by the blessed Athanasius, bishop of the city of Alexandria, should not be interpreted as those who try to apply it to the worship of images might think.
Response.
Many statements by the blessed Athanasius are mentioned in the same council, but they did not specify which statement they were referring to in this chapter.
However, just as the statements of the holy Athanasius are included among other things in the holy councils of our most holy predecessors, we faithfully present them here.
Question of Antiochus to Saint Athanasius regarding images:
The law from the prophets says, "You shall not worship statues and likenesses," so how do you justify making images and worshiping them?
He replied:
We believers do not worship images as gods; far from it, pagans do that.
Instead, we approach them with affection and love in our souls toward the appearance of the image's face.
Therefore, many times we discard the face, treating it as plain and ordinary wood, and burn what was once an image.
Just as Jacob, near death, worshiped the top of Joseph’s staff—not honoring the staff, but the one who held it, as mentioned in the book of Genesis chapter forty-seven according to the Septuagint—so too do we believers venerate images, driven by our desire for the person depicted.
And many other similar explanations follow.
In the Sixth Action
Chapter 35 Critique
The response?
They presented testimony from the holy Sixth Council to clearly demonstrate that even during the time of the holy Sixth Council, sacred images and painted histories were venerated since ancient times.
Therefore, the holy Sixth Council faithfully established in its orthodox canons, stating: In some paintings of venerable images, the lamb shown by the finger of the forerunner is designated, which was left as a sign of grace.
And shortly after, Canon eighty-one states: We decree that according to the human form and in images, it is now called a new name instead of the old lamb, etc.
And thus, blessed Augustine explained in Psalm ninety-three: If you do not worship these earthly things in Christ, although some resemblance is given to signify the saints, from whichever creature the likeness is derived, understand it as the likeness of the creature, and worship the Creator of the creature, etc.
In the Fourth ActionChapter 36 Critique
The apostles never established, either by example or word, the worship of images, contrary to what some claim.
Response.
Saint Dionysius the Areopagite, who was the bishop of Athens, was highly praised by Saint Pope Gregory, affirming him as an ancient Father and teacher.
He lived during the time of the apostles, as shown in the Acts of the Apostles.
Acts seventeen.
Therefore, his true testimonies supporting the veneration of sacred images were confirmed by our most holy predecessors, the popes, in their sacred councils, among other things:
This is embraced from the letter of Saint Dionysius, Bishop of Athens, which was directed to Saint John the Evangelist.
And further:
Is it any wonder if Christ, who is truthful, and his unjust disciples are cast out of the cities?
They rightly judge for themselves, and the wicked withdraw from the sacred.
In truth, images are the visible representations of the invisible.
In the ages to come, no one will be blamed for respecting God through various colors, allowing us to silently transition through the most sacred images with a pious mind to the simple and incorporeal.
Indeed, it is impossible to reach with our mind that incorporeal imitation and vision of the heavenly host unless we can transition from the visible to the invisible and most beautiful representation through elements, and through visible and fragrant images, the invisible is made to shine with rational tradition.
In the Same Action
Chapter 37 Critique
It's not about the worship of images, as some claim, but rather follows the teachings of Blessed Cyril in his explanation of the Gospel according to Matthew.
Response:
Saint Cyril of Alexandria and Saint Gregory of Nyssa both supported the veneration of sacred images in the story of Abraham.
In the sacred councils of our most revered pontiffs, regarding the sermon of Saint Cyril of Alexandria, bishop:
It's noted that if someone gazes at a beautiful image and admires the figure of the king depicted in it:
By recognizing this and seeing its portrayal, they are inspired to admire the king himself.
In the Sixth Action Chapter 38 Critique
It's a great rashness and an enormous absurdity to equate the often-mentioned images with the body and blood of the Lord.
Response.
They did not equate them, but rather spoke more scripturally:
For none of the holy apostles or our respected Fathers, who spoke without blood of our offering, which is done in memory of the passion of Christ our God and all His plan, called it an image of His body.
Nor did they receive from the Lord to speak or confess so, but they hear Him saying in the Gospel:
Unless you eat the flesh of the Son of Man and drink His blood, you shall not enter the kingdom of heaven.
John 6.
And there are many other teachings of the Lord and the blessed Apostle Paul.
First Corinthians 11.
We did not wish to write them all down, because it is written in order in the same synod:
For to equate, as the Iconoclast heretics say in their false writing, the venerable images with the body and blood of the Lord, they insensibly equated.
In the Same Action
Chapter 39 Critique
Tarasius and his followers are boldly and ignorantly equating sacred vessels with something else.
Here's the response.
At the council, Tarasius, the Patriarch of Constantinople, stated:
"We have various sacred vessels that we kiss and embrace, hoping to receive some sanctification from them."
The heretics, in their misguided assembly, were speaking nonsense, not consecrating the sacred prayer to sanctify it, leaving it common and dishonored, just as the painter created it.
But we, in truth and faithfulness, affirm that the practice of our holy Catholic and Apostolic Roman Church has been and continues to be that when sacred images or stories are painted, they are first anointed with sacred chrism, and then venerated by the faithful.
This follows the Lord's command to Moses:
"You shall make the holy anointing oil, a perfumed compound, according to the art of the perfumer, and you shall anoint the tent of meeting with it, the ark of the testimony, the table with its vessels, the lampstand and its utensils, the altar of incense and of burnt offering, and all the furnishings used in worship."
"And you shall sanctify them, and they shall be most holy: whoever touches them shall be sanctified."
(Exodus thirty).
In the sixth action of the second volume, Epiphanius reads. Chapter 40: Critique.
It does not relate to their parents as they say: May the Lord destroy all deceitful lips and the boastful tongue.
Psalm twelve.
Response: They spoke prophetically and sang with the Psalmist, as the blessed Augustine explained in this psalm, saying: May the Lord destroy all deceitful lips, etc.
When he said "all," who would think themselves exempt?
As the Apostle says: Upon every soul of man who does evil, Jews first and Greeks.
And the proud tongue.
Romans chapter two.
In the same action. Chapter Forty-One: Critique.
What their ancestors claimed was not fulfilled, as it is written: "The enemies have perished, their weapons destroyed, and you have ruined their cities."
Response: This verse was always spoken prophetically by the prophet in a psalm-like manner.
Thus, the blessed Augustine explained in the same psalm, saying (after the beginning): "The enemies have perished, the weapons destroyed;" not enemies in the plural, but this enemy in the singular.
But whose enemy, if not the devil's weapons that have perished?
These are understood to be various erroneous opinions.
And shortly after: "And you have ruined their cities."
These cities are where the devil reigns, where deceitful and fraudulent councils hold the place of courts, and so on.
And thus, it was fulfilled in the heretics themselves when they arrogantly removed sacred images.
In the Fourth Action
Chapter 42 Critique
How should we understand the phrase: "Lord, in your city you will bring their image to nothing" (Psalm Seventy-Three)?
This chapter, like others, is often interpreted differently than originally intended.
Response:
It's understood in relation to the wealthy of this world who are misguided, among other interpretations.
Even Saint John Chrysostom, in his homily about the Old and New Testament having one legislator, explained it by saying: "I also loved an image infused with wax, filled with piety. For I saw an angel in the image pursuing a multitude of barbarians, and David truly saying: 'Lord, in your city their images you will bring to nothing' (Psalm Seventy-Three).
Behold, the father very clearly shows how it should be understood.
"
Additionally, Saint Athanasius on the interpretation of the psalms says: "The city of the Lord is Jerusalem above; but their image is earthly. What he means is this: Because they have embraced an earthly image, and not a heavenly one, they will be brought to nothing. For at that time they will hear: 'I do not know you' (Matthew Twenty-Five), as those not clothed in the image of the Lord.
Saint Augustine, in his explanation of the same psalm, adds: "Whoever doesn't have these things, don't desire them; whoever has them, don't rely on them. Behold, I tell you: I do not say: Be condemned because you have them; but be condemned if you rely on such things, if you're arrogant because of them, if you think highly of yourselves because of them, if you ignore the poor because of them, if you forget the common condition of humanity because of vain excellence. For it is necessary that God will repay in the end, and in his city, he will bring the image of such people to nothing."
In the Same Action
Chapter 43 Critique
It is not, as they claim, said for those who worship images: "Because the Lord will not allow the rod of the wicked to rest on the lot of the righteous, so that the righteous will not reach out their hands to do wrong" (Psalm One Twenty-Five).
Response: They rightly spoke with the prophet because the rod of the wicked refers to the heretics, and the lot of the righteous refers to the orthodox, as Saint Augustine explained in the same psalm, saying: "The rod of the wicked is felt for a time on the lot of the righteous, but it is not left there; it will not be forever."
The time will come when Christ, appearing in His glory, will gather all nations before Him and separate them, as a shepherd separates the goats from the sheep.
He will place the sheep on His right, and the goats on His left, etcetera.
(Matthew Twenty-Five).
In the Fourth Action
Chapter 44 Critique
John the presbyter, while Theodosius, the abbot of the monastery of Saint Andrew, was reciting the words of John Chrysostom, said:
I saw an angel in a vision chasing a multitude of barbarians.
Who is this angel, if not the one mentioned in the Scriptures, where the angel of the Lord struck down 185,000 Assyrians in one night, Second Kings Chapter 19, around Jerusalem while they were encamped?
Response.
We have already explained why Saint John Chrysostom mentioned this vision, but the diverse multitude from which it originated has passed.
Therefore, John the presbyter, by his own judgment, believed, according to the divine Scripture, that the angel of the Lord struck down 185,000 Assyrians in one night around Jerusalem while they were encamped.
Whether this was accurate or not, he did not confirm, but simply mentioned it in a questioning manner.
In the Same Action Chapter 45 Critique
There's a statement made by John, priest of the East, which seems quite foolish and irrational.
He claims that when the emperor isn't present, his image is still honored, not dishonored.
Similarly, even though Jesus Christ, the ruler of all, doesn't appear to us visibly, his image should still be honored.
Christ is invisible to our physical eyes, yet, as God, he is present everywhere, just like the emperor is perceived through his image.
Response.
John, priest of the East, didn't make this statement on his own.
He was referencing a book by Saint Anastasius, bishop of Theopolis, which was read during the same synod.
Therefore, he stated that the Father showed that when the emperor isn't present, his image is honored, not dishonored, and what follows, as mentioned earlier.
In the Fourth Action
Chapter 46 Critique.
This concerns John, a priest and envoy of the Easterners, who is said to have carelessly tried to establish the worship of images:
Jacob set up a pillar to God, and in doing so, he blessed him.
Response:
This was said in a symbolic sense because when he woke up, he set up a stone pillar at the place where God had spoken to him.
He poured offerings on it, anointed it with oil, and called the place Bethel.
Genesis Chapter Thirty-Five.
Therefore, it seems to have multiple interpretations.
From the book of blessed Augustine, on the Treatise of Esau and Jacob:
Your holiness understands, he says, that the Church is represented in many ways.
And shortly after:
Because one thing is represented in many ways, which is none of these things in reality, but is all of them in figure, etc.
In the Same Action
Chapter 47 Critique
It's quite absurd for some to use divine law to justify images, citing that Moses made the mercy seat, the two golden cherubim, and the ark of the covenant at the Lord's command.
Response.
We've already gently explained how our holy predecessors, the popes, used divine law to affirm images in their sacred councils.
Saint Gregory the Theologian, in his Easter sermon, says:
"And the one who spoke to Moses, when he gave the law about these things, said, 'See that you make everything according to the pattern shown to you on the mountain' (Exodus 25), indicating that invisible things were made visible: and I am convinced that none of these were without reason, nor arranged irrationally, nor crawling on the ground, nor anything unworthy of both the ordinances of God and the ministry of Moses, etc.
"
Similarly, the blessed Augustine in his book on Exodus says:
"We believe the deeds, just as we read the deeds, and yet we know by apostolic doctrine that these deeds were shadows of things to come."
"Thus, we think that what has been done should be closely investigated, yet we cannot deny that they were done, etc."
Chapter 48: Criticism.
It's a significant error to interpret the Holy Scriptures incorrectly and to apply them to meanings they don't contain, just like in the erroneous council held in Nicaea during Constantine's reign, with Irene his mother mediating and Tarasius, the newly appointed bishop of Constantinople, presiding.
Response.
The following criticisms aren't taken from a council, but from the sense derived from the book of the blessed Augustine about when God appeared to Moses, where it's explained:
"Therefore, all the signs and mysteries of the future people are about our Lord Jesus Christ, and if there are any other sacraments in the old books, whether we understand them or not, they require a seeker, not a critic."
Let's ask, search, and knock so that it will be opened to us.
The future sacraments were foretold to them, but we experience the present ones in the Church.
Chapter 49 - Critique: What's the difference between image and likeness, or equality?
Response: Which of the faithful would ever think they don't understand what image, likeness, or equality means?
In the holy, catholic, and apostolic Church, grace is given to the humble.
Indeed, the mathematicians' difference in the external art of discipline looks down on maintaining the faithful, as Blessed Ambrose notes in the first book on Faith, chapter three, where he says:
We must say what is written: Beware lest anyone deceive you through philosophy and empty seduction, according to the tradition of men and the elements of this world, and not according to God.
Colossians chapter two.
For they place all the power of their arguments in dialectical reasoning, defined by the philosophers' opinion, which focuses not on building up, but on tearing down.
But it did not please God to save His people through dialectics.
For the kingdom of God is found in the simplicity of faith, not in the contention of words.
Chapter 50 - Critique: It goes against the teachings of Blessed Gregory to worship or break images, and because the Old and New Testaments, and almost all the principal doctors of the Church, agree with Blessed Gregory in not worshiping images, we should not worship anything besides Almighty God.
This is confirmed in many places by Saint Gregory the Pope.
Response: He never disrespected sacred images, but rather consistently observed and revered their representations.
As for the claim that almost all the principal doctors of the Church agree with Blessed Gregory, it was unreasonable to write this because Saint Gregory was obedient and aligned with his predecessors—the Fathers and principal doctors of the holy catholic Church.
For those who lived in this world did not know Blessed Gregory, except for the one who foreknew and predestined them.
Here’s how Saint Gregory revered his holy predecessors.
We present a letter from the same Saint Gregory (Book 7, Letter 7) addressed to Eulogius, the Patriarch of Alexandria, where, among other things, he says:
"Regarding the heretic Eudoxius, about whose error I found nothing in the Latin language, I am very pleased to have been abundantly informed by your blessedness."
"You have provided the testimonies of the brave men Basil, Gregory, and Epiphanius, and we clearly understand that he has been utterly defeated, against whom our heroes launched so many attacks," etc.
Regarding the veneration of sacred images, as Saint Gregory taught in his other letters, he also addressed this in his letter to Januarius, Bishop of Cagliari (Book 7, Indiction 2, Letter 5), which begins as follows:
"Jews coming from your city have complained to us that their synagogue in Cagliari was occupied by Peter, who, by the will of God, was led from their superstition to the worship of the Christian faith, along with some undisciplined people."
"On the day after his baptism, which was on the Lord's Day during the Easter celebration, he occupied it with great scandal without your consent, placing there an image of the Mother of God and our Lord, a venerated cross, and a white garment he had worn when he rose from the baptismal font."
"Considering your intention and judgment on this matter, we urge you to restore what was taken by force, with the image and the cross removed with the veneration they deserve."
"Therefore, the aforementioned Peter, or others who supported him in this misguided behavior, should not claim they acted out of zeal for the faith, as if it was necessary to convert people this way."
"They should be admonished and understand that they should exercise more restraint, so they may be drawn willingly and not brought unwillingly, for it is written: 'I will sacrifice to you voluntarily,' etc." (Psalm Fifty-Four)
Saint Gregory did not dare to contradict the faith regarding sacred images.
Instead, he confirmed it by saying, "Let them not be brought unwilling."
Chapter 51: Reproach. Those who curse their parents act against the Lord's command. If they believe their predecessors were heretics, they themselves are born, taught, and consecrated by heretics. Whether it's about not judging those who have passed or how their error differs from their parents' error, as some broke images while others adored them.
Response. Those who wrote this from their own understanding should heed the powerful words of the prophet Ezekiel, who says, "As I live, says the Lord, this proverb shall not be used by you anymore in Israel. Behold, all souls are mine: as the soul of the father, so also the soul of the son is mine. The soul who sins shall die."
And later: "But if a wicked person turns away from all the sins they have committed and does what is just and right, they will save their life."
And after many things: "I take no pleasure in the death of the wicked, but rather that they turn from their ways and live. Turn, turn from your evil ways, why will you die, house of Israel?"
Therefore, you, son of man, say to the children of your people: "The righteousness of the righteous will not save them when they disobey; and the wickedness of the wicked will not cause them to fall when they turn from their wickedness," etc. (Ezekiel 18 and 33).
As Saint Gregory mentions in his Dialogues, Book 3, Chapter 31, what harm came to King Hermenegild, who converted from the Arian heresy to the Catholic faith, from his father, Arian King Leovigild of the Visigoths?
We truly believe there was none.
When his Arian father killed him for his true and orthodox faith, Hermenegild became a steadfast confessor of God and a martyr.
His Arian father, however, was led into eternal fire for his Arian faith.
How could he have harmed his faithful son in any way?
The holy Catholic and Apostolic Church truly rejoices when it sees its enemies, especially heretics, return in true confession.
As the Lord says:
"There will be joy over one sinner,"
(Luke 15).
And if there is joy over one, imagine the joy over the return of thousands!
Who among the faithful would dare to resist this joy?
Also, from Saint Augustine on Psalm 84, he says:
"The sins of the parents do not belong to the children, which parents commit after their children are born.
For the children born already belong to themselves, and the parents to themselves.
Therefore, those who are born, if they follow the bad ways of their parents, must bear their own merits.
But if they change and do not imitate their bad parents, they begin to have their own merit, not the merit of their parents.
So much so that your father's sin does not harm you, if you change, nor does it harm your father, if he changes,"
(Chapter 52).
Reproach.
The Greeks tried in vain and recklessly to anathematize the Catholic Church in their synod because it does not worship images.
They should have first thoroughly examined what each part of the Church thought about this matter.
Response.
They did not anathematize the Catholic Church.
Instead, upon returning to it, they anathematized the false logic and its heretical accomplices, who shamelessly and recklessly not only removed the sacred images established in the holy Church from ancient times but even burned them.
Thus, following the tradition of the holy Catholic and Apostolic Church, having returned from heresy, they specifically anathematized it with contempt.
Also, from the letter of Saint Gregory directed to Eusebius, Archbishop of Thessalonica
(Book 7, indiction 2, letter).
We urge you to continually and diligently investigate this matter with brotherly care.
If you find them innocent of this wickedness, clear the scandal from the minds of your children by providing reconciliation and specifically anathematizing Severus and Nestorius along with all other heresies.
This is what they did, returning from their own heresy.
Chapter 53.
Reproof.
A woman should not teach in a synod, as it is said that Irene did in their synod.
Response.
At the very beginnings of Christianity, when Emperor Constantine converted to the faith, his mother Helena Augusta came to him in Rome with twelve scribes and Pharisees, as well as Jewish teachers and leaders.
Together with her son Constantine Augustus, she decided to hold a council with the Jews and Christians.
This council, presided over by the holy Pope Sylvester with many very holy bishops, expanded the Christian faith significantly through both sacred Scripture and miracles, under the Lord's protection, and they emerged victorious.
Additionally, the eminent Pope Leo, a distinguished teacher, sent his letters to Pulcheria Augusta for the sake of the holy fourth council.
Consequently, she herself sat in the holy fourth synod, alongside the most faithful Emperor Marcian.
Also, from the book of Saint Augustine, regarding what is read in Genesis on the sixth day: The earth produced grass for food and fruit-bearing trees, and likewise, people in the Church produce works of mercy.
These works were also offered to the Lord when he was in the flesh, not only by men, such as Zacchaeus, but also by women who ministered to him from their resources, etc.
Chapter 54.
Reproof.
Images should not be worshipped because, as they say, some signs seem to have been demonstrated through them, when not all things through which or in which miracles appear are to be worshipped.
Response.
Earlier, we discussed the concept of worshipping images, explaining that acts like offering a kiss and an honorable greeting to them do not constitute true worship according to our faith.
True worship is reserved for the divine nature alone.
From the book of Saint Augustine on Psalm Seventy-Six:
"You are truly a great God, performing wonders in the body, alone in the soul."
And a little later:
"Moses did it, but not alone; Elijah, Elisha, and the apostles did it, but none of them acted alone.
When they acted, you were with them; when you acted, they were not with you.
For they were not with you when you acted, when you also made them.
You are God, who performs wonders alone."
Chapter Fifty-Five: Criticism.
This chapter addresses how apocryphal and absurd ideas were inserted into their discourses.
Response: To the scorn and reproach of the heretics who made false arguments, they presented their apocryphal nonsense, highlighting the errors they attempted to introduce into the holy, catholic, and apostolic Church.
Therefore, those who returned from that heresy sang with the prophet against those heretics: "The enemy's swords have failed, etc." (Psalm Nine) and many more.
Also, from Saint Gregory the Theologian in the sermon on Epiphany (Oration on the Holy Lights), he says:
"Let us approach the light and become light ourselves by sharing in the eternal light."
And a little later:
"Do the delirious stories and obscure mysteries of pagans have anything like this, the inventions of demons, or the crazy creations of a frenzied mind, confirmed by time and praised in tales?
For those things, which they worship as true, they again teach to be false and made up through stories.
If they were true, they would certainly not be fables, since truth and fiction are opposed to each other in every way.
But they do everything as if they were truly children playing in the streets and mocking each other."
There is no assertion of manly sense or perfect reason here, nothing they can offer against the worshippers of the word of God, and many other similar things.
Chapter 56 - Criticism.
Regarding the fact that the more they disdain or despise examples and images of heretics, the more they dishonor their parents with greater insults and injuries, whom they claim to have followed in this regard.
Response.
They often refer to this very issue in this chapter, because they despised their parents and dishonored them with insults.
As we have written above, we briefly add that good parents cannot benefit bad children, nor can good children help bad parents; each will give an account to God for themselves.
Those who do not follow their parents in the most savage error and have returned to the true faith of the orthodox holy Catholic and apostolic Church are indeed much more praiseworthy.
From the book of Saint Augustine on prophecy (Tractate on the Sheep, near the end), where God speaks to the sheep, among other things:
Therefore, whoever has crossed over from heretics to the Catholic Church will not bear the reproach of the nations, nor carry the curse of dissension, because they remain rooted in unity, in the planting of love.
They will not carry the curse, and they will know that I am the Lord their God, and they my people, the house of Israel, says the Lord God.
Ezekiel chapter thirty-four.
Chapter 57 - Criticism.
That it is not against the Christian religion, as they say, not to worship and adore images.
Response.
From the book of the blessed Augustine on the treatise on the Proverbs of Solomon, among other things:
You find a man extending his hand with alms to the poor, yet not thinking of God, but desiring to please people.
A woolen garment may be seen, but it lacks an inner lining.
You find another saying to you:
"It is enough for me to worship God in my conscience, to adore God: what need do I have to go to church or to visibly mix with Christians?"
He wants to have a line without a tunic: this woman neither knows nor recommends such works.
Spiritual matters should indeed be discussed and taught without the physical, but those who receive them should embrace the spiritual and not act carnally.
Chapter 58 – Criticism.
It's a significant mistake to equate handmade images with the Ark of the Covenant, as was attempted in their synod.
Response.
Referring to the treatise of Saint Augustine on Esau and Jacob, among other things: Two Testaments are mentioned in the Law, one Old and the other New.
The Old Testament had promises of a temporal nature but meanings that were spiritual.
Pay attention, dear ones.
If the land of promise was offered to the Jews, it signifies something spiritually about that land of promise.
If the city of peace, Jerusalem, was promised to the Jews, it signifies something about the name Jerusalem, and many other similar things.
As we previously noted in the same book of Saint Augustine, one thing is signified in many ways, which is not evident but understood through symbolism.
Chapter 59 – Criticism.
Images should not be equated with the relics of holy martyrs and confessors, as attempted in their erroneous synod, because relics are either part of the body, from things in the body, or from things around the body of a certain saint; whereas images are neither believed to have been nor to be in the body or around the body of those they depict.
Response.
In the sacred councils of my most holy predecessor pontiffs, these testimonies were presented, particularly by Saint Gennadius, Bishop of Marseille, regarding the veneration of the bodies and relics of saints, chapter 40:
The bodies of the saints, especially the blessed relics, should be sincerely honored as if they were members of Christ, and the churches named after them, as places devoted to divine worship, should be visited with pious affection and faithful devotion.
If anyone opposes this decree, they should not be considered Christian, but Eunomian.
Regarding the request made by the clergy and monks of the holy Church of Antioch against Severus the heretic during the holy Fifth Council:
He showed no respect for the holy altars, even tearing apart some of the most sacred vestments and vessels, and distributing the remaining items to those who sided with him.
(In the council under Menas, act one)
He boldly seized the golden and silver doves, which were symbols of the Holy Spirit hanging above the sacred fonts and altars, along with the relics, claiming:
"It is not necessary to name the Holy Spirit in the form of a dove," and so on.
Chapter sixty – Reproach.
This assembly, which should not even be called a council, cannot in any way be compared to the Council of Nicaea, even though it occurred in the same location, as John the priest is said to have flattered:
It is known to differ from it not only in other aspects but also in the creed.
Response.
We have already mentioned above that the divine doctrines of this council are faultless, as evidenced by the wondrous works of the foremost holy Fathers.
If anyone claims to differ from the creed of the aforementioned council, they appear to differ from the creed of the six holy councils, since these did not speak of their own accord but through the constitutions of holy doctrines.
From the book of the holy Sixth Council, among other things (Act seventeen):
Indeed, this pious and orthodox symbol of divine grace was sufficient for the perfect knowledge and confirmation of the orthodox faith.
But since the inventor of malice did not cease from the beginning, using the serpent as his tool to bring poisonous death to human nature through him:
So also now, finding instruments suited to his own will, and so forth.
Also from the book of Saint Augustine on Prophecy, where he addresses the sheep, among other things:
"You pushed with your sides and shoulders, and struck with your horns, and crushed all that was weak until you scattered them abroad: and I will save my sheep."
As detestable as their iniquity and cruelty are, the mercy of our shepherd and our God is equally praiseworthy.
And a little later, it says: And over all the earth, your glory.
The groom is in heaven, the bride is on earth.
He is above all the heavens, she is over all the earth.
O heretic, do you believe in what you cannot see in heaven but deny what you can see on earth?
Let her speak, then, let her voice be heard, let her save her sheep.
And I will save, he says, my sheep, and they will no longer be in ruin:
and I will judge between one sheep and another, and I will raise up over them one shepherd, and the rest.
CHAPTER 1.
--- Rebuke.
Against those who say: Just as we have the books of Holy Scripture, we also have images for the memory of veneration, maintaining the purity of our faith.
Response.
From Saint Gregory the Pope's letter to Serenus, the Bishop of Marseilles (Book 9, letter 9), among other things:
Tell me, brother, from which priest have you ever heard of doing what you have done?
If nothing else, that should have held you back, so you would not consider yourself the only holy and wise one, disregarding the other brothers.
For it is one thing to adore a painting, and another to learn from the story of a painting what ought to be adored.
For what Scripture provides to those who read, the picture provides to the unlearned who see it:
because in the picture, the ignorant see what they ought to follow, and those who do not know the letters can read.
Therefore, especially among the nations, the picture serves as reading: which you should have greatly attended to, living among the nations.
And a little later: And because in venerable places of the saints, ancient times have allowed stories to be depicted for good reason.
And again: Because the images, which were made for the edification of the unlearned, allow those who do not know the letters to learn by attending to the story itself, etc.
Also, Sophronius, Bishop of Jerusalem, explained in his holy synodical letter, which was presented and wonderfully received at the holy Sixth Council, speaking about the Holy Spirit: Truly co-eternal with the Father and the Son, consubstantial and co-equal, of the same essence and nature.
In the same way, the Trinity of divinity is of the same essence, deserving equal honor, and is a natural and related companion, forming one divinity: unified into one common lordship, without personal confusion or substantial division.
Therefore, we believe in the Trinity in unity and glorify the Trinity as one.
Also, from the letter of Saint Athanasius to Epictetus, among other things:
Those who are believed to have the correct faith according to the holy Fathers, but who wish to change something for inquiry's sake, end up doing nothing but, as it is written: "They indeed drink folly to their neighbor": they offer no benefit, only disrupting the simple-minded.
Also, from Saint Augustine's Book Seven on the Trinity, chapter six, among other things:
Let us speak of the three persons: the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, just as some are called three friends, or three relatives, or three neighbors, in relation to each other, not in isolation.
Thus, each is a friend, relative, or neighbor to the other two, because these terms are relational.
Also, from the same Saint Augustine's Book Eight on the Trinity, at the beginning, among other things:
There is such equality in the Trinity that not only is the Father not greater than the Son in divinity, but the Father and Son together are not greater than the Holy Spirit, nor is any individual person of the three less than the Trinity itself.
These ideas have been expressed, and even if repeated in various ways, become more familiar: yet a method should be applied, and God should be approached with utmost devotion.
First Action
Chapter Four Critique
In the first section of Chapter 4, we look at Archbishop Basil.
In his expression of faith, after acknowledging the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, he included the kissing and adoration of images and relics, claiming he believed in being sanctified through them.
However, he entirely omitted the forgiveness of sins, the resurrection of the body, or the future life.
Now, let's look at the response.
Saint Ambrose, the Bishop of Milan, in Book 1, Chapter 2, on Faith, which he sent to Emperor Gratian, spoke orthodoxly about the Father and the Son.
He mentioned, among other things:
For there is the fullness of divinity in the Father and the fullness of divinity in the Son.
He didn't mention the Holy Spirit because he was only focusing on the Father and the Son.
Basil, rejecting and condemning the heresy, made a confession of the true religion of the orthodox faith, showing reverence for sacred images and relics of the saints, which he previously misunderstood.
Regarding the forgiveness of sins, the resurrection of the body, or future life, he did not err, and he didn't contradict the orthodox faith of the holy catholic and apostolic Church in these aspects, unlike those pitiable and unfortunate heretics who attempted to belittle the images and relics of the saints, contemptuously rejecting and denying them along with the sacred images themselves.
But woe to those who, by straying from the right path and walking through a misguided path full of obstacles, fell into the pit they created, and they will burn forever.
If we were to explore the veneration of the relics of the saints through the works of the divine Scriptures and the holy Fathers, who could possibly document it all?
We briefly mention a few from the many writings of Saint Basil, Bishop of Caesarea in Cappadocia, in his interpretation of Psalm 115.
He noted, among other things, that previously, priests and Nazarenes were told that anyone who touched a dead body would be unclean and should wash their clothes.
When someone touches the bones of the martyrs, they receive a portion of sanctification from the body, due to the grace present there.
The death of His saints is precious in the sight of the Lord.
(Psalm 115)
In his sermon on the Letter of the Blessed Apostle Paul to the Romans, Sermon 32, Saint John Chrysostom, Bishop of Constantinople, said:
"This is why I love Rome.
Besides its greatness, antiquity, beauty, population, power, and military skill, I bless it most for this: Paul wrote to them while living, loved them deeply, spoke to them in person, and ended his earthly life there. They have his holy body, making the city more honorable than others.
Just as a great and strong body has two shining eyes, the sacred bodies of Peter and Paul are like two bright lamps of the Roman city, shining throughout the world.
From there, Paul and Peter will be taken.
Imagine the awe: what signs will Rome witness when Paul and Peter rise to meet Christ?
What gift does Rome present to Christ?
What crowns does the city hold?
What golden chains bind it?
What fountains does it possess?
I admire the city not for its gold, columns, or splendor, but for the extraordinary peaks of the supreme Church.
Who will grant me the honor of being near Paul's body, to cling to the sacred burial, and see the holy dust of his body, in which he imitated Christ, bore the marks of Christ, and spread the Gospel everywhere?
The dust of his body, through which he appeared everywhere?
The dust of his mouth, through which Christ was proclaimed, and light shone."
From a sermon by Saint Augustine on the feast day of the holy apostles, among other things:
This most blessed Peter, a fisherman who wasn't even given the role of a caretaker but was the lowest servant, now has an emperor kneeling and worshiping him.
Also from Saint Augustine in the exposition of Psalm Forty-Five, among other things:
"The daughters of kings were delighted with your honor"
(Psalm Forty-Five); because they did not seek their fathers' honor, but sought your honor.
Show me a temple in Rome held in as much honor as I can show you the memory of Peter.
In Peter, who is honored but the one who died for us.
Also from a letter by Saint Gregory the Pope addressed to Eusebius, Bishop of Thessalonica
(Book Nine, Letter Sixty-Nine), among other things:
If Theodore the reader wishes to come here to pray to the saints at the apostles' place, let your brotherhood send him without any delay.
And there are many other such testimonies that we foresee would be too lengthy to write out in full.
In the Same Action Chapter Five Critique
Theodosius, the bishop of Amorium, was criticized for being silent about the faith of the holy and unique Trinity, yet he spoke recklessly and unusually about images:
I confess, promise, accept, kiss, and adore images.
And a little later: Anyone who does not diligently teach all the people beloved by Christ to adore and venerate the sacred and venerable images of all the saints who have pleased God since the beginning, let them be cursed.
Response.
We believe that Theodosius, with zeal for the faith, confessed to such a speech as explained in their definition.
We also find that our predecessors, specifically the most blessed pontiffs Gregory and Gregory, Zachary and Stephen, Paul, and again Stephen, were fervent in the Holy Spirit for the erection of sacred images, having zeal for the true faith.
For this reason, Lord Pope Gregory the Second, along with seventy-nine most holy bishops, presiding before the confession of the blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, strengthened the testimonies of many holy Fathers and decided in their council to venerate and adore sacred images.
Furthermore, our predecessor of holy memory, the late Lord Pope Stephen, also presiding with bishops from the regions of France and Italy in the basilica of Our Lord Jesus Christ the Savior, called the Constantinian, confirmed and embraced the venerable council of his predecessor.
He, along with all the presiding bishops, adhering to the testimonies of the holy Fathers, decided to adore and venerate sacred images even more.
Hence, the blessed Apostle Paul teaches, saying: Hold fast to the traditions you have received, from Second Thessalonians chapter 2.
And again: But even if we, or an angel from heaven, should preach to you a gospel contrary to what we preached to you, let him be cursed.
As we have said before, so now I say again: If anyone preaches to you a gospel contrary to what you received, let him be cursed, etc.
, from Galatians chapter 1.
In the Third Action Chapter Six Critique
Theodore, the archbishop, childishly and absurdly claims in the statement of faith: "God is wonderful in his saints" (Psalm sixty-seven).
He then adds: "To the saints who are on his earth, he has made all my desires wonderful among them" (Psalm fifteen), as if this verse directly follows the previous one.
Response:
They try to falsely accuse in this way because the holy Church, when rising to sing praises to God in the morning, first says: "O Lord, you will open my lips" (Psalm fifty), followed by: "Come, let us exult in the Lord" (Psalm ninety-four): and thus it begins: "Blessed is the man" (Psalm one).
Similarly, the apostle Paul, while diligently listing the prophets, mentioned David after Jephthah, and then Samuel.
We also find many works of the saints that first testify to the New and then to the Old Testament: however, no faithful person would mock such things because of this.
Moreover, Saint John Chrysostom, in his interpretation of the epistle of the blessed apostle Paul to the Hebrews (Homily seven), says among other teachings: "The Lord will not see, nor will the God of Jacob understand" (Psalm ninety-three).
And again: "Our lips are our own; who is lord over us?" (Psalm eleven).
And again: "Why has the wicked provoked God?" (Psalm nine).
And again: "The fool has said in his heart: There is no God. They are corrupt, and they have done abominable works" (Psalm thirteen).
Similarly, Saint John Chrysostom, in his interpretation of the epistle of the blessed apostle Paul to the Romans (Homily seven), notes that Matthew, when beginning the Gospel, first mentions both and then presents their ancestors in order, saying: "The book of the genealogy of Jesus Christ" (Matthew one).
He did not wait to mention Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob but placed David before Abraham, which is notable, saying: "The son of David, the son of Abraham," and then he began to list them in order, etc.
In the First Action
Chapter Seven Critique
There is a reproof for those who say, "With God's help, we decided to gather you," or, "God gathered you, wanting to establish his own council."
The response can be found at the end of the Gospel of Saint Mark, where it is written, "But they went forth and preached everywhere, the Lord working with them, and confirming the word with signs following" Mark 16.
Also, Saint Cyril, in his sermon about the Holy Mother of God, says, "Indeed, glory to you from us, holy mystical Trinity, who has called these and all of us to this calling of the Mother of God, Mary," and so on.
Moreover, from the holy synod in the eighteenth action, after the subscriptions of the bishops and the emperor, Constantine, the most pious emperor, declared, "We bring forth God as a witness."
He continued, "Since it pleased God to grant time, we invited your gathering to consider the holy Scriptures of God and to expel any new voice or assertion added to our undefiled Christian faith in these recent times by some who hold wrong views," and so forth.
In the Third Action, Chapter Eight: Critique.
This section addresses those who claim that the honor given to an image is transferred to the original form.
Response: Anyone arguing against this is contradicting Saint Basil's explanation in his Book on the Holy Spirit, Chapter Seventy-Five.
We believe no faithful person would oppose him regarding his orthodox faith.
Saint Basil explained this in his very sacred letter to Amphilochius, among other points in this chapter.
Additionally, Saint Severian, the bishop of Gabala, in a homily where he elucidated the Scriptures as explained by the Lord, said:
"If you insult the imperial garment, do you harm the one who wears it?
Don't you know that insulting the image of the emperor harms the dignity of the original form?
Don't you realize that if someone tears down an image from wood, they are judged not merely as one acting against lifeless matter, but as one who, by extending their hand against the emperor, defiles the material, separated from the emperor, without the emperor's soul?
For if an image is harmed, the injury reaches the emperor."
In the same proceeding. Chapter Nine: Critique.
It's unfortunate, and perhaps rash or foolish, that Constantine, the bishop of Constantia in Cyprus, said:
"I receive and honorably embrace the holy and venerable images, offering them in worship to the substantial and life-giving Trinity.
To those who do not share this belief or glorify in this way, I separate them from the holy catholic and apostolic Church and subject them to anathema.
I consign them to the group of those who denied the incarnate and saving dispensation of Christ, our true God."
Response:
Turning away from the wrong heresy, they made every effort to satisfy the holy catholic and apostolic Church with their confession.
Thus, they professed belief in the worship of sacred images as established in the synod's definition, among other things.
(Acts Seven): To restore the venerable and holy images, which are appropriately made of colors, metal, and other materials in the holy churches of God, in sacred vessels, garments, on walls and panels, houses, and roads:
Including the images of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, of our undefiled lady the holy Mother of God, of the precious angels, and all the saints and just men.
As these are frequently seen through imagined reformation, those who behold them are inspired to remember and love the original form.
They are to render a kiss and honorable greeting to them, but not in the form of worship which is reserved for the divine nature alone.
This is akin to the reverence shown to the sign of the precious and life-giving cross, the holy Gospels, and other sacred adornments, etc.
In the second action, Chapter Ten: Critique.
It is noted that Euthymius, the bishop of Sardis, holds views similar to the error of the aforementioned Constantine when he states:
I wholeheartedly accept the venerated images, with appropriate honor and affectionate reverence.
For I declare and announce as heretics those who think differently or oppose the holy images, considering them alien to the Catholic Church.
Response.
As mentioned above, according to the definition of the synod, they confess to making the pure confession of the Catholic Church, particularly where he says he wholeheartedly receives the venerated images and embraces them with appropriate honor and reverence.
As stated in the synod's definition: Not at all according to our true faith, which is due only to the divine nature, but just like the sign of the precious and life-giving cross, and the holy Gospels, and other sacred ornaments.
And so he said, with appropriate honor; and he promised to declare as heretics those contrary to the Catholic Church.
In the Fourth Action
Chapter 11 Critique
There's no authority or reference in any authentic books about the claim that someone was deterred from committing adultery by the image of a certain Polemon.
They try to compare this to the miracle of the fringe of the Lord's garment, which a woman touched to receive healing.
Response.
In this chapter, those who wrote these accounts aim to accuse and contradict the truth.
They cannot substantiate the claim that they dared to equate Polemon's miracle with the fringe of the Lord's garment.
However, during the council, the miracle of Polemon's image was presented as evidence from the words of Saint Gregory the Theologian, who deliberately wrote a verse, which was individually addressed by Basil of Ancyra, Tarasius the Patriarch of Constantinople, and Nicephorus the Bishop of Dyrrachium.
Bishop Basil indeed replied: Saint Gregory the God-speaking Father regarded the image of Polemon as remarkable.
The patriarch added: Indeed, chastity was achieved through it.
For if the prostitute hadn't seen the image of Polemon, she wouldn't have turned away from adultery.
Similarly, Bishop Nicephorus commented: A wonderful and very worthy image, as it was able to rescue a woman from the path of disgrace.
Following this, another reader read from the sermon of the blessed Bishop Antipater of Bostra on the flow of blood, where, after much explanation, the saint said: Having received the gift, she erected a monument to Christ, spending wealth on the poor and offering the remaining wealth to Christ.
After this, separately addressing the miracle of the woman with the flow, the patriarch responded: Just as she offers the image titled to Christ, just as the woman with the flow erected a monument.
Similarly, Bishop Basil remarked: He instructs to speak properly and extensively and accepts those who create images.
However, your divinely inspired truthful excellence can have the council read in the fourth session to verify whether this is true or not.
IN THE SIXTH ACTION. Third volume. CHAPTER 12. Critique.
Contrary to what some foolishly and irrationally believe, the lawgiver's words do not support the worship of images:
Behold, I have called by name Bezalel, son of Uri, son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah, and I have filled him with the spirit of wisdom and understanding to work with gold and silver; and I have given him as a partner Oholiab, son of Ahisamach, etc.
Exodus 31.
Response.
Our most holy predecessor, Lord Gregory II, junior pope, provided these solid examples in his sacred council, which was accepted and venerated in another council held by our predecessor, Lord Stephen the pope, along with the priests from France and Italy.
In the presence of the most holy and blessed former Lord Gregory the pope himself, he also said:
If those with contrary opinions, who seek to invalidate the ancient traditions of the Fathers, were to convert to salvation, surely what we have already said based on the testimonies or sacred documents of the Fathers would suffice.
However, because we, with sorrow, see many troubled minds attempting to disturb the established rules of the Church, we feel compelled, dear brothers, to extend the discourse and share more from ancient documents to restrain the madness of error: perhaps the restless will reconsider.
In the book of Exodus, it states:
The Lord spoke to Moses, saying: Speak to the children of Israel, that they bring me offerings; from every person who offers willingly, you shall receive them.
And these are the things you shall take, and so on, up to the two cherubim, which shall be above the ark of the testimony, all that I command you to the children of Israel.
Exodus 25.
Another testimony from the third book of Kings, also known as First Kings, is cited to silence those who chatter against God's command.
After Solomon constructed the temple, among other things, he made two cherubim of olive wood in the inner sanctuary.
Below, he carved images of cherubim, palm trees, and striking reliefs, all covered with gold.
Everything, including the cherubim and palms, was overlaid with gold.
First Kings chapter six.
Dearest brothers, let's consider what Moses did at God's command and what the wise Solomon built by divine order.
Shouldn't we, with pure hearts and minds, honor and adore Christ our God, who was depicted, along with His ever-virgin mother Mary, the apostles, and all the saints, through their holy images and likenesses, asking for their intercession for mercy and forgiveness of sins?
We create and venerate images for no reason other than the Word of God made incarnate for us.
If all handmade things are to be rejected, then neither the Ark of the Covenant nor its golden, engraved cherubim should have been accepted, as they were crafted by Bezalel and Oholiab according to God's command.
If those were accepted, then these images are also rightly accepted because they are made according to God.
Therefore, they, like the ark, perform many miracles.
Just as the ark and the cherubim were lifeless, handmade, and carved, so too are these.
But just as God worked through those and was glorified, these are made similarly, distinguished by colors according to the visions and revelations of the prophets.
If anyone presumes to criticize the veneration proclaimed by our most holy predecessors, let them know that they taught such veneration as our predecessor, the illustrious teacher and pope Saint Gregory, did in his letter.
This letter was presented at the aforementioned council by Herulph, bishop of the province of Gaul.
Among other things, he instructed Secundinus, a servant of God in Gaul, saying:
We know you do not request the image of our Savior to worship it as God, but for the remembrance of the Son of God, so that you may be rekindled in His love, whose image you consider seeing.
We don't bow down to that Divinity as if it's a god.
Instead, we worship Him, remembering Him through the image, whether He is born, suffering, or sitting on a throne.
The picture itself brings the Son of God to mind, just like a written word.
It either fills us with joy about the resurrection or comforts us regarding the passion.
So, we have sent you two cloths featuring the image of the Savior, Mary the holy Mother of God, and the blessed apostles Peter and Paul.
These are being sent with our aforementioned son, the deacon, along with a cross and a key for blessing from the most holy body of Peter, the prince of the apostles.
With these, you may be protected from the evil one, trusting in the holy wood for your safety.
In the fourth action, Chapter Thirteen. Critique
The criticism was that Bishop Theodosius of Myra acted foolishly and childishly by presenting his archdeacon's dreams at the same synod to support the adoration of images.
Response: Who can doubt that in both the Old and New Testaments, the future was revealed to many through dreams?
To highlight the best example among many, we refer to Saint Ambrose, Bishop of Milan.
In his exposition on the holy martyrs Gervasius and Protasius, Book Seven, Letter Fifty-Three, he states:
"On the third night, after fasting, when my body was exhausted, not while sleeping but in a stupor, a third person appeared to me, resembling the blessed Apostle Paul, whose face I had learned from a painting," etc.
This testimony was presented by the most holy former Archbishop Sergius of the Church of Ravenna through his deacon John at the aforementioned council of holy memory of my predecessor, Lord Stephen, in support of the veneration of sacred images.
Similarly, Saint Gregory the Theologian, in the epitaph of his brother Caesarius, "Funeral Oration in Praise of Caesarius," near the end, states:
"Then I will see my Caesarius, never leaving, never returning, never lamented, never pitied, but splendid, glorious, exalted, just as you appeared to me in a vision."
This is dear to me, brother," etc.
Moreover, Saint Gregory the Pope, in his Dialogues, mentions certain most blessed men and religious women, along with young girls, who saw the holy Mother of God Mary and the chief apostles Peter and Paul, and the holy martyrs at their passing.
How did they recognize them except through paintings, as the blessed Ambrose, as we mentioned earlier, said?
In the same action. Chapter 14. Critique
There's a nonsensical and absurd claim about someone supposedly swearing an oath to a demon and then breaking it.
The abbey leader is known to have been quite delirious, suggesting it was better for him to visit every brothel in the city than to deny worshipping the image of the Lord or His holy mother.
Response.
This testimony comes from the book of the eminent teacher Saint Sophronius, and we believe there is no orthodox Christian who would dare reject his divine teachings or any of his explanatory works.
Similarly, Saint John Chrysostom, in discussing the beheading of Saint John the Baptist, among other things, emphasized the necessity of not forbidding the veneration of sacred images.
Furthermore, in a letter from Saint Pope Gregory to Januarius, the bishop of Cagliari, as found in Book 7, Indiction 2, Letter 5, we have already addressed this issue in detail.
In the Secon Action. Chapter 2 Critique
Agapius, the bishop of Caesarea in Cappadocia, is criticized for making a statement considered useless, foolish, and worthy of ridicule because he said: It is written in our divine Scriptures.
Response.
It seems that the divine Scripture is preached by the faithful for the salvation of people.
Therefore, we believe he intended to say: In our divine Scriptures, seeking to gain glory and honor from them, and simultaneously, to express what is taught by the same sacred Scripture, as is written in the works of the holy Fathers, and so on.
Saint Augustine, in his treatise on the proverb of Solomon, stated among other things:
They also have our sacraments, they have our Scriptures, they have our Amen and Alleluia, many have our creed, and so on.
In the Fourth ActionChapter 3 Critique
It's considered useless and foolish, full of error, to claim that anyone who fears God honors, worships, and venerates Him in the same way as Christ, the Son of God, our Lord, the sign of His cross, and the image of His saints.
Response: From the book of Blessed Augustine about the son of Abraham being led to sacrifice, among other things:
You were not moved without reason when I mentioned this: The cross has horns.
For two pieces of wood are joined in such a way that they form the shape of a cross.
So, as we see in many places in the image of the cross, two horns are made, on which the hands are nailed.
I see the crucified Lord in the ram caught by its horns, etc.
In the Same ActionChapter 4 Critique
Here's what John mistakenly said:
"Through the image, which appears through colors, his strength is worshiped and glorified, and we come to remember his presence on Earth."
In response,
from the letter of Saint Gregory the Pope, Book Seven, Epistle Thirteen, addressed to Secundinus, a servant of God living in seclusion, we find:
"Your request for the image of the one you worship to be sent to you through your deacon Dulcitius greatly pleased us, because you seek with all your heart's intention the one whose image you wish to have before your eyes, so that the daily physical sight always brings the desired one closer."
"And while you see the painting, you are inflamed in your mind toward the one whose image you believe you are seeing, et cetera."
In the Fifth Action Chapter Five Critique
They say:
"He who disdains images is guilty of the same crime as Nebuchadnezzar, who disturbed the bones of the kings of Judah from their tombs, blinded the Jewish king after killing his sons, and removed the cherubim from the temple."
Response.
We have already mentioned in a letter from Pope Saint Gregory that images are not to be disdained, but venerated.
Therefore, our predecessors, the frequently mentioned most holy pontiffs, in sacred councils, made the following ruling:
"If anyone refuses to venerate the holy images of our Lord Jesus Christ, His mother, and all the saints, according to the teaching of the holy Fathers, let them be anathema."
In the same action, Chapter Six, Critique.
According to Demetrius the deacon, their parents acted recklessly and disorderly by burning two silver-plated books because they contained something about images, and cutting out two pages from another book.
Response: This is shown to be typical behavior of heretics, similar to their actions in the false council under the former heretical Emperor Constantine.
In a letter from Saint Cyril to Bishop Successus of Neocaesarea, towards the end, he mentions:
Failing to counter these reproaches, they devised something bitter and worthy of heretical impiety.
They corrupted the letter by removing some parts and adding others, making it seem as though the memorable person shared similar views with Nestorius and his followers.
Also, in the holy sixth council during the third action, it discusses:
The sermon of Menas, Archbishop of Constantinople, to the most blessed Pope Vigilius of Rome, concerning the belief that there is one will of Christ.
The apostolic see's envoys from Rome protested, saying: Most pious lord, the present book of the fifth council has been falsified.
It is also mentioned in the same holy sixth council, Act Eight, after the middle:
The holy sixth council stated: Behold, you have also destroyed this testimony of the holy Father.
It is not fitting for the orthodox to mutilate the words of the holy Fathers in this way; this is rather typical of heretics.
The heretic Macarius said: And I have already mentioned that in seeking to destabilize my intention, I have mutilated it in this way.
The holy council exclaimed: He has clearly demonstrated himself to be a heretic.
In the same action, Chapter 7 Critique.
In this section, Leontius, the keeper of secrets, upon seeing images on silver tablets, claimed he had discovered the oldest and most ingenious benefit of his mistake.
Response.
Similarly, from the same holy Sixth Council, among other things, in Act 8, after the middle:
Constantine, the most pious emperor, and the holy synod said, "Let Macarius explain why he has removed these necessary things from the testimony of the holy and reputable Father."
Macarius, the heretic, replied, "I have taken excerpts according to my own intent."
And shortly after, the holy synod remarked, "Look, most gracious lord, he has also removed this testimony."
For after the testimonies are re-read by the order of your strength, they will show that his excerpts have obscured them, etc.
In the Emperor's Letter, Chapter 8: Critique.
Regarding what Constantine and Irene wrote in their letter to the venerable Pope of the city of Rome:
We ask your fatherhood, and especially God asks, who does not want anyone to perish.
Response:
In the Holy Gospel, the Lord says: Simon, behold, Satan has asked to sift you like wheat.
But I have prayed for you that your faith may not fail; and when you have turned back, strengthen your brothers, etcetera.
(Luke 22).
Also, in the letter of the blessed Apostle Paul, among other things:
For God was in Christ reconciling the world to himself, not counting their sins against them, and he has committed to us the message of reconciliation.
Therefore, we are ambassadors for Christ, as though God were making his appeal through us.
We implore you on behalf of Christ, be reconciled to God.
(Second Corinthians 5).
Also, Saint John Chrysostom in his sermon on the Ascension of the Lord, among other things:
Learn that it was not through our pleading, as we had offended him, but through his request, who was justly angry with us, that peace was made.
For on behalf of Christ, says the Apostle, we serve as ambassadors, as though God were pleading through us.
What does this mean?
Is he the one who was wronged asking?
Indeed, he says.
For God is merciful, and like a compassionate father, he pleads.
And see who is the intermediary, who has approached as the reconciler, not an angel, not an archangel, but the very Son of the one pleading, etcetera.
Also, the same Saint John Chrysostom in the interpretation of the Letter to the Romans (Homily 5, towards the end), among other things:
What then after these things?
No longer prophets, no longer angels, no longer patriarchs, but he sent his own Son: and he was killed, and he came himself, and even then did not extinguish love but kindled it more, and remains pleading.
And below:
And Paul cries out, saying: For we are ambassadors for Christ, as though God were making his appeal through us.
We implore you on behalf of Christ, be reconciled to God.
And shortly after:
Let us consider how many times we have offended him after a thousand good deeds, yet he persisted in pleading, how many times we have transgressed against him, yet he does not neglect us, etcetera.
In the fourth action, Chapter Nine - Critique.
Regarding what John mentioned earlier: He wrestled with him in the form of a man and called him Israel, which means "a mind seeing God."
Response.
From the book of Saint Gregory the Theologian on divinity, Oration Two on Theology, after the middle, he notes:
For Jacob saw a high ladder.
And shortly after: And as though with a man, he wrestled with God.
And among other things: The struggle of faith was rewarded with a change of name, from Jacob to Israel, etc.
Also, from Saint Augustine about Jacob's wrestling with the angel, he states:
He held on and wrestled, as if wanting to embrace Jacob in a physical form, he said: Let me go physically, for behold, it is already morning, so that you may be spiritually enlightened, etc.
Genesis Thirty-Two.
In the Same Action
Chapter 10 Critique
It’s a misconception to think that those who say:
If, according to the lawful tradition of Moses, people are commanded to place purple hyacinth in the fringes on the edges of garments as a reminder to keep the commandments, then we should, even more so, use the depicted likeness of holy men to see the outcome of their way of life and imitate their faith according to apostolic tradition.
Hebrews, Chapter 13.
Now, the response.
We believe you’re aware of what Pope Gregory the Great mentioned in his letter, Book 9, Letter 9, as we have written earlier.
The wisdom of old times did not, without reason, permit the depiction of histories in the venerable places of saints.
He further elaborated on this while discussing the sacred distinction of words during his interpretation of the prophet Ezekiel in Homily 10, at the beginning:
Sacred Scripture is our food and drink.
And a little later:
For in more obscure matters, which can’t be understood unless explained, it is food.
Because whatever is explained, so it can be understood, is almost chewed to be swallowed.
But in clearer matters, it is drink.
For we swallow drink without chewing.
Therefore, we drink the clearer commands because we can understand them even when not explained.
This was also clarified in the sacred councils by my very holy predecessors, the pontiffs, that among many things promulgated concerning old histories:
If indeed those were accepted, then these images are appropriately accepted as they are made according to God.
Hence, they also have an effect.
In the Fourth Action
Chapter 11 Critique
John the priest was mistaken when he defended the worship of images by saying that Joshua set up twelve stones as a memorial to God as mentioned in Joshua, chapter four.
Response: In the book of Joshua, it is written that Joshua tore his clothes and fell face down to the ground before the ark of the Lord until evening, along with all of Israel, putting dust on their heads from Joshua, chapter seven.
Shortly after, the Lord said to Joshua: Get up, why do you lie face down on the ground?
Israel has sinned and broken my covenant from Joshua, chapter seven.
And again shortly after: Get up, consecrate the people, and tell them: Be consecrated for tomorrow, etc.
from Joshua, chapter seven.
Behold, Joshua was heard when he lay prostrate before the ark of the covenant.
From this, the eloquent holy teacher, Pope Gregory, in his letter Book 7, letter 53 which we discussed earlier, addressed to Secundinus, a servant of God secluded in Gaul, advised, saying: We do not prostrate ourselves before an image as if it were Divinity, but we worship Him whom we remember through the image, whether born, suffering, or sitting on the throne, etc.
Chapter 12.
Criticism: The worship should not be considered equal to the reverence of the prophet Nathan toward King David, as compared to the worship of images.
Response: From the book of Saint Gregory the Pope on Job Book 4, chapter 1 it is explained that when only the history is viewed in sacred scripture, nothing more than the surface is seen.
But when we engage with it consistently, we penetrate its deeper meaning, as if from the familiarity of conversation.
By connecting one thing to another, we easily recognize the difference between what the words imply and what they directly say.
However, one becomes a stranger to its deeper understanding the more one is bound to its surface alone, etc.
Similarly, in the same book, it mentions: What is represented by David, who is interpreted as strong or desirable in hand, if not our Redeemer?
What is signified by his gift, if not the Church?
And shortly after: The inquiry into the Lord's divinity is like a hidden spring; but the appearance of His incarnation is an open spring.
What is meant by Jerusalem, which is interpreted as the vision of peace, if not the holy Church itself?
In the heart of the world, they contemplate the Lord, about whom it is written:
"He is our peace, who made the two one," etcetera.
Ephesians Chapter Two.
Chapter Thirteen.
Reproof. The opinion of John of Constantinople, which is cited as evidence for the worship of images, is not understood to mean what they think.
Response.
Many statements by Saint John of Constantinople are referenced in the frequently mentioned synod, and they did not specify which statements do not align with their beliefs.
In the councils of our holy predecessor pontiffs, the opinion of Saint John Chrysostom is presented as follows, among other things:
"All things serve you, man, but even more so the image; because when imperial faces and images enter the city, the judges and senate greet them with praise and fear, not honoring the panel or the writing on the wax, but the face of the emperor.
In the same way, let us honor not the appearance of the lands, but the heavenly face of the world of people," etcetera.
In the Fourth Action
Chapter Fourteen Critique
In Chapter 14, the judges present at the council attempted arrogantly and inappropriately to elevate the art of painting.
They stated, "The art of the painter is indeed pious, and some people criticize it foolishly and wrongly. The Father Himself commends the painter who acts piously."
In response, Blessed Asterius is revered as holy throughout the East.
When he preached about the deeds of Saint Euphemia, he praised her martyrdom as he had seen it clearly depicted in order.
Similarly, they praised the painting against heretics, noting that they criticize it foolishly.
Saint Gregory the Theologian, in his sermon on blessed Gregory of Nyssa, says:
"Do you think these are enough, or shall a brief discourse also describe the man to us?
If necessary, just as diligent painters often mix colors, I will add the perfect form of speech for you, and describe to you the purest and clearest."
Similarly, Saint John Chrysostom, in his sermon at the Lord's Supper, explains:
"Just as painters shade a panel with certain outlines before perfecting it with a variety of colors, so did Christ.
At the table, He depicted the types of the Passover and revealed the true Passover."
Also, from the book of Saint Augustine on the Proverb of Solomon:
"Our mouth is open to you, O Corinthians."
He attentively opened his mouth and set the order of his tongue, praising the creature as a creature, the Creator as the Creator, angels as angels, heavenly things as heavenly, earthly things as earthly.
In the same action, Chapter 15: Critique.
John, the priest and envoy of the Easterners, makes a misleading and worthless statement, claiming that painters do not contradict the Scriptures.
Instead, he says, they depict whatever the Scripture conveys, ensuring that their work aligns with the Scriptures.
Response: We've already discussed several times above how the holy Gregory, the esteemed teacher and pope, through his sacred letter to Serenus, bishop of Marseille, taught, among other things:
Book nine, letter nine:
He suggested that paintings of images were created to educate unlearned individuals, so that those who cannot read might understand the stories by viewing the images, and so forth.
Additionally, Saint John Chrysostom, in his interpretation of Psalm fifty, says:
Painters use art to imitate nature, blending colors to create visible images of bodies.
He continues, describing how they portray an emperor seated, a subdued barbarian, a sharp sword, flowing rivers, fields adorned with various colors, and everything visible.
Through their artistry, they present a marvelous story to the viewers, and so on.
In the fifth action, it was found in the fourth. Chapter 16: Critique.
The extremely false and utterly ridiculous statement of John the priest, who seems to have been as crazed as the others in the worship of images.
For he says: "Whoever worships an image and says, 'This is Christ, the Son of God,' does not sin."
Response from Saint Augustine in his explanation of Psalm 86, after the beginning, among other things:
Almost all physical bodies have limitations and cannot be everywhere or always.
However, divinity, which is present everywhere, can be approached from all sides by likeness and can be entirely present in likenesses, because none of them are in their own properties.
Is Christ a door in the same way we see doors made by a carpenter?
Certainly not, and yet he said: "I am the door" (John 10).
Or is he a shepherd in the same way we see those who tend sheep, etc.
From the Sense. Chapter 17. Critique
Those books, the Lives of the Fathers, whose authors are unknown, are not entirely suitable for providing testimony or supporting arguments in debates.
Response.
In the book of Saint Augustine on the Questions in the Gospel according to Luke, it is mentioned: His vessels in the house are the fleshly senses by which many, in their quest for truth that the intellect comprehends, have completely erred.
The Lives of the Fathers, lacking credible authors, are seldom read in the Church.
However, those works endorsed by the orthodox are both accepted and read.
Furthermore, the sacred canons have allowed the reading of the passions of the holy martyrs in the church during their feast days.
Chapter 18.
Criticism.
Those who create images to avoid forgetting the saints, or even the Lord Himself, do not possess a good memory.
Response.
In Saint Jerome's commentary on Matthew the Evangelist, it is noted: People like this, while attempting to criticize another's ignorance, reveal their own lack of understanding.
Even though thin moisture and liquid food, once digested and processed in the veins and limbs, travel through the hidden channels of the body, known to the Greeks as "pores," to the lower parts and are expelled.
Additionally, from Saint Augustine's interpretation of Psalm Ninety-Eight: Zion is referred to as the city, which is Jerusalem.
Zion receives its name from a certain interpretation, as it is said to mean a lookout, implying vision and contemplation.
To look out is to look forward, or to see, or to focus with the intent of seeing.
Zion is every soul that aims to see the light that is meant to be seen. For if it looks at itself, it becomes darkened; if it gazes at that light, it becomes illuminated.
Since it is evident that Zion is the city of God, what else could the city of God be but the holy Church?
Question. Chapter nineteen.
Can someone point out where, in either the Old or New Testament, or within the six synodal councils, it is instructed to create images or to worship those that already exist?
As we've already mentioned, both the Old and New Testaments, along with the six synodal councils, have always revered sacred images, considering them among the holy of holies.
They should have informed us about any criticism of sacred images in those six synodal councils.
In the first holy council, it was clearly demonstrated that Saint Sylvester, the pope, and Constantine, the most Christian emperor, both venerated sacred images and displayed them faithfully and wonderfully in the name of Christianity.
From that time to now, the churches of the holy pontiffs, namely Sylvester, Mark, and Julius, of remarkable size, have been depicted among us, adorned with sacred images in mosaics and other artwork.
Similarly, in the second holy council, the elegant Pope Saint Damasus created his own church, which Saint Gregory the Pope mentions in the Dialogues, and it bears the name of its founder, Damasus.
From then until now, it has been painted with sacred stories and images.
In the third holy council, Pope Saint Celestine decorated his cemetery with paintings.
Additionally, his successor, the blessed Pope Sixtus, built the basilica of Saint Mary, Mother of God, known as Major, also called at the Manger.
He adorned it with sacred images in golden metals and various artworks.
At his request, Augustus Valentinian created a golden image with twelve gates and the Savior, adorned with precious gems, which he placed in gratitude over the confession of the blessed Apostle Peter, and it has been venerated by all the faithful among us ever since.
In the fourth holy council, the distinguished and remarkable preacher, Pope Saint Leo, also built churches, decorating them with mosaics and various artworks or images.
In the basilica of Saint Paul the Apostle, he created a larger arch and depicted our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ in mosaic, along with the twenty-four elders, adorning it with verses in his name.
From that time until now, it has been faithfully revered by us.
Regarding the Fifth Ecumenical Council, Pope Vigilius beautifully adorned the Lateran Patriarchal Basilica with paintings, featuring both historical scenes and sacred images.
His holy successors, Pelagius and John, constructed a remarkably large church for the apostles, decorating it with various mosaic stories and colorful sacred images, which have been revered by us from then until now.
Pope Gregory also created a beautiful oratory in his monastery, painting it with various stories and erecting sacred images there.
Together with Saint Eleutherius, he entered there for his stomach ailment, and their prayers were heard together, as mentioned in Book Three of Dialogues, Chapter Thirty-Three.
The holy man Eleutherius, known for raising the dead, did not hesitate to prostrate himself before those sacred images, praying for divine mercy alongside Saint Gregory.
With perfect faith, they were heard together, and they have been revered by us until now.
The church of the Arians, mentioned by Saint Gregory in his Dialogues, Book Three, Chapter Thirty, was pleasing to Saint Gregory to be dedicated in the Catholic faith.
The relics of Saint Sebastian and Saint Agatha the martyrs were brought there, and the dedication took place.
After a miracle occurred in the church, the blessed Gregory had it painted with various stories, both in mosaic and colors, and erected venerable images there, which have been revered from then until now.
If we were to list all the churches our predecessors, the popes, have built up to now, with their magnificent sacred images and painted stories, we would run out of time to name them all and describe their sacred artworks and tales.
In the Sixth Holy Council, not only did they not ignore these sacred images, but they also revered them.
They decreed, as stated in Canon 82, that the Lamb of Christ, our God, should be depicted in human form, replacing the old lamb.
Therefore, Saint Ambrose, Bishop of Milan, in the third book on Faith, Chapter 7, taught: Let us uphold the teachings of our elders and not recklessly alter inherited symbols.
Neither elders, powers, angels, nor archangels dared to open the sealed prophetic book from Revelation Chapter 5; only Christ had the privilege to explain it.
Who among us would dare to unseal the priestly book, sealed by confessors and consecrated by the martyrdom of many?
Those who were forced to unseal it later signed it with condemned deceit.
Those who refused to violate it became confessors and martyrs.
How can we deny the faith of those whose victory we proclaim?
Let no one fear, let no one be afraid.
If the heretics had not attacked the holy Catholic and Apostolic Church, the six holy synodal councils would not have been necessary.
Similarly, if the Church had not been attacked by the heretical emperors Leo and Constantine over sacred images, my most holy predecessors, the popes, would not have held councils.
Nor would we have agreed to do so later, if not for the sake of so many thousands of souls endangered in the devil's snare, remaining in heresy and perishing daily in it.
As defined by the holy Fourth Council, those who speak the true faith declared:
We must passionately uphold the faith handed down to us by our ancestors and maintain the unblemished dignity of proper veneration for the blessed apostle Peter, especially in our times.
This ensures that the most blessed bishop of Rome, to whom history has granted leadership of the priesthood over all, may have the authority to judge matters of faith and priests.
Therefore, our most holy predecessor, Pope Gregory the Younger, wrote to the heretical emperors Leo and Constantine, saying:
For sacred images, we are willing to offer everything, even our own bodies, if necessary.
We never accept novelty, nor do we deviate from the faith of our fathers for any reason.
The divine voice warns, which must be heeded above all:
If anyone gains the whole world but loses his soul, he gains nothing.
This is from the Gospel according to Matthew, chapter sixteen.
Again, in another letter concerning these sacred images, he reasonably rebuked them, saying among other things:
Pope Gelasius, in letter 10 to Emperor Anastasius, stated:
It is recorded that a most learned and venerable Father said there are two principal powers governing this world, namely the sacred authority of pontiffs and royal power.
The responsibility is heavier for priests because they must account for even kings before divine judgment.
Therefore, no one can make us transgress the boundaries set by our fathers or impose new doctrines:
By remaining in the orthodox faith we have received and embracing ancient tradition, we undoubtedly venerate and uphold the councils of our most holy predecessors, the pontiffs, regarding sacred images, without accepting any contrary speech from anyone on this matter, nor giving an account.
The holy Gregory, the eloquent doctor, emphasized the importance of maintaining these traditions in his homily on the prophet Ezekiel.
While discussing the understanding of sacred words over time, he added:
"Many will pass through, and knowledge will be manifold" Daniel 12.
The holy fathers, whom we know through sacred scripture, were saved in the knowledge of one God before the law. They possessed perfect obedience in their simple lives and often saw angels, thus experiencing a bit of contemplation.
However, once the law was given, the holy fathers were also taught through the Ten Commandments, so that through the knowledge of one God, they also practiced the works of the law.
But with the grace brought by the New Testament, all faithful people recognized that one God is a Trinity and completed the strength of the Ten Commandments in this knowledge.
Hence, we must understand that the knowledge of the spiritual fathers grew over time.
For Moses was more learned than Abraham, the prophets more than Moses, and the apostles more than the prophets in the knowledge of the almighty God.
I would be mistaken if I didn't support these claims with the testimonies of scripture itself.
"Many will pass through, and knowledge will be manifold," he says (Daniel 12).
But let's illustrate, if we can, what we said about Abraham, Moses, prophets, and apostles from the words of that same scripture.
Who does not know that Abraham spoke with God?
Yet the Lord says to Moses: "I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob: but I did not reveal my name, Adonai, to them" Exodus 3 and 6.
Behold, more was revealed to Moses than to Abraham, as he revealed to Moses what he narrates he did not reveal to Abraham.
But let us see if the prophets could comprehend divine knowledge more than Moses.
Behold, the Psalmist says: "How I love your law, Lord! It is my meditation all day long" Psalm 119; and adds: "I have more understanding than all my teachers, for your testimonies are my meditation."
And again: "I understand more than the elders."
Therefore, he who remembers meditating on the law and testifies that he understands more than all his teachers and more than the elders, demonstrates that he received divine knowledge more than Moses.
However, how can we demonstrate that the holy apostles were taught more than the prophets?
Truth clearly states:
"Many kings and prophets wanted to see what you see, and did not see it."
(Luke 10)
The apostles possessed more divine knowledge than the prophets because what the prophets heard in spirit, the apostles also witnessed physically.
Thus, the prophecy of Daniel that we mentioned is fulfilled:
"Many will pass through, and knowledge will be greatly increased."
(Daniel 12)
As the world approaches its end, the path to eternal knowledge opens wider for us, and so on.
Similarly, Saint Gregory, in his commentary on Job, Book 4, Chapter 10, says:
"Holy teachers, who instruct others in virtue, conquer enemies by transforming them within their own bodies through the power of conversion.
They subject them to the stones of a sling, because when they train strong men in the holy Church, they break the hard hearts of arrogant adversaries through them."
What does the sling represent if not the holy Church?
Just as a sling, when spun around, sends out stones to strike the hearts of adversaries, the holy Church, as it is guided through the cycles of time by tribulations, brings forth strong men from whom the stony blows strike the hearts of the wicked.
In the seventh action, Chapter 20 — Critique.
How the mystery of the Lord's cross differs from the images that some try to equate with it.
Response from Saint Ambrose, Bishop of Milan, from the book on the Incarnation, Chapter 7:
Among other things: Do we divide Christ when we worship both his divinity and his flesh?
Do we divide him when we venerate in him the image of God and the cross?
Surely the Apostle, who said about him, quote: "For even though he was crucified through weakness, yet he lives by the power of God," in Second Corinthians, Chapter 13, also said: "Is Christ divided?" in First Corinthians, Chapter 1.
Also, from the same Saint Ambrose in the book on Faith, Chapter 4:
Among other things: The Apostle speaks of an image, and Arius says it is dissimilar?
Why call it an image if it has no likeness?
People do not want paintings to be dissimilar, yet Arius claims the Father is dissimilar in the Son.
And shortly after: The prophets say, quote: "For he is the brightness of eternal light, the spotless mirror of God’s majesty, and the image of his goodness," from the Book of Wisdom, Chapter 7.
Also, from the letter of Saint Gregory the Pope sent to Leontius, former consul, Book 7, letter 34:
Among other things: We have received the oil of the holy cross and the wood of aloes: one to bless by touch, the other to give a pleasant fragrance through incense.
Therefore, it was fitting for a good man to send things that could appease the Lord’s wrath towards us.
And shortly after:
Furthermore, we sent you the blessing of Saint Peter, the prince of the apostles, and the key of his most sacred tomb, in which the blessing from his chains is included, so that what bound his neck for martyrdom may release yours from all sins.
It discusses what Constantine and Irene assert in their writings: Through Him, who reigns with us, God.
Here's the response from the Proverbs of Solomon, among other insights:
Counsel and sound judgment are mine; I have understanding and strength.
By me kings reign, and lawmakers decree what is just.
By me princes rule, and the powerful decree justice.
I love those who love me.
(Proverbs Chapter 8).
And after many reflections:
Mercy and truth preserve the king, and his throne is upheld by mercy, etc.
IN THE FOURTH ACTION. CHAPTER 22. Critique.
There's a misunderstanding about the phrase: You shall worship the Lord your God, and serve Him only, as if it refers to worship and service in an absolute sense, directed only to Him.
Response.
Saint Ambrose, Bishop of Milan, in the fifth book on Faith, says:
When we read: You shall worship the Lord your God, and serve Him only Matthew 16, do they believe that Christ should not be worshiped or served?
If the Canaanite woman, who worshiped Him, was deemed worthy of receiving what she requested, and Paul the Apostle, who declared himself a servant of Christ in the introduction of his writings, Romans 1; Galatians 1, was worthy of being an apostle, not by men or through man, but through Jesus Christ, let them decide which path to follow.
Would they rather align with Arius in his treachery, denying that Christ is the one true God because they believe He should neither be worshiped nor served, or would they prefer to side with Paul, who, by serving and worshiping even Christ, did not deny in word or feeling that He was the one true God, whom he honored with devout service?
But if anyone argues, Because the Son also worships God the Father, as it is written: You worship what you do not know; we worship what we know John 4, let them reflect on when, before whom, and with what intention they speak, etc.
IN THE SAME ACTION. CHAPTER 23 Critique
Even though God isn't confined to any specific place, some have mistakenly claimed: We honor and worship as if it were the dwelling of God.
Response.
Blessed Augustine, in his commentary on Psalm 86, mentions:
The foundation, as the Apostle says, cannot be laid by anyone except what is already laid, which is Christ Jesus.
First Corinthians chapter 3.
So how are the prophets and apostles foundations?
And how is Christ Jesus the ultimate foundation?
We can understand this by noting that, as it is clearly stated, the Holy of Holies, Daniel chapter 9, is figuratively the foundation of foundations.
Therefore, if you consider sacraments, Christ is the Holy of Holies; if you consider the followers, Christ is the shepherd of shepherds; if you consider the structure, Christ is the foundation of foundations.
And further on, he continues:
But divinity, which is present everywhere, can be approached from all directions by likeness, and can be fully represented in likenesses, because none of these is in its own properties, etc.
Similarly, in Saint Augustine's second book on the Trinity, Chapter 17, he says:
What does it mean when the Lord says: Behold, there is a place with me, and you shall stand on the rock?
Exodus chapter 33.
What earthly place is with the Lord, except that which reaches Him spiritually?
For what place is not with the Lord, who reaches from end to end mightily, and arranges all things sweetly, etc.
Wisdom chapter 8.
Also, from Saint John Chrysostom on the sermon of Saint Paul the Apostle, where he states:
What I want, I do not do.
Romans chapter 7.
And since Jacob became a figure of Christ, among other things:
He came amidst the rivers, and when he saw the dream, he said: This is none other than the house of God.
Genesis chapter 28.
For you did not see a building, but a ladder.
But because he knew that the ladder was a symbol of the Church, he said: This is the house of God, this is the Church.
And why is this house of God the Church?
Paul writes to Timothy:
I hope to come to you soon.
But if I am delayed, you will know how to conduct yourself in the house of God, which is the Church of the living God, etc.
First Timothy chapter 3.
In the same action, Chapter 25: Critique.
It's mentioned that Solomon made bulls and lions in the temple, and some argue that this could support the worship of images, as those who are eager for such worship claim.
There's also the reference in Ezekiel: Faces and cherubim up to the ceiling.
Ezekiel 41.
Response.
We have often recorded these chapters, showing how our most holy predecessors, the popes, in their sacred councils, established the veneration of images.
It's clear that their apostolic guidance should be observed and revered by us.
Also, from the book of Saint Augustine on Psalm 84, among other things:
In the Old Testament, the New Testament was foreshadowed, and this expression of truth was prefigured.
In that figure, according to a certain prophecy of future things, the land was given to those people, called the land of promise, etc.
From the book of Saint Augustine on Questions in the Gospel according to Luke, Book 2, question 41, among other things:
The Lord says: He who is on the roof, and his belongings in the house, should not go down to take them.
Luke 17.
On the roof is he who, cutting off carnal things, lives spiritually in the open air.
And shortly after: Therefore, this spiritual man's belongings are left in the house because, with a mind superior to the body, seated as if on a roof, he enjoys the clarity of wisdom like the clearest sky, etc.
Chapter 26: Criticism.
The last chapter is so that the lord apostolic and our Father, and the entire Roman Church, may know that according to what is contained in the letter of the most blessed Gregory, Book 7, letter 9, which he sent to Serenus, Bishop of Marseille:
We allow images of the saints to be created by anyone who wishes, both in the church and outside the church, for the love of God and his saints.
However, we do not compel those who do not wish to worship them.
We also do not permit anyone to break or destroy them, even if someone wishes to do so.
We openly declare that we follow the beliefs of the most holy Gregory in this letter, which pleases the universal Catholic Church in the eyes of God.
This sacred and venerable chapter stands out significantly from all the previously mentioned chapters.
Therefore, we recognize it as the rightful property of your God-preserved and orthodox royal excellence, wherein the full essence of the correct faith is entirely confessed to follow the most holy Gregory.
Your exceedingly excellent royal knowledge recalls that in Pope Gregory's letter to Bishop Serenus of Marseille, it is reported, among other things, where he admonishes the bishop, saying:
It is one thing to worship a painting, and another to learn, through the story of the painting, what is to be worshiped.
For what writing provides to readers, a painting provides to those who see it:
because even the ignorant can see what they ought to follow in the painting, and those who cannot read can understand from it.
Hence, especially for the nations, a painting serves as a form of reading; something you should have greatly considered, living among the nations.
And a little later: And because the old times allowed stories to be painted in places venerable to the saints for good reason.
Further on: Because the images were made for the education of unlearned people, so that those who do not know letters might learn what has been done by focusing on the history itself.
Again, a little later: But let your brotherhood diligently remind them that from seeing the event, they may gain a fervor of compunction and humbly bow in adoration of the holy Trinity alone.
Similarly, we briefly noted another letter he directed to Januarius, Bishop of Cagliari, concerning the veneration of sacred images.
We also mentioned a letter directed to Secundinus, a servant of God, in Gaul, in which it is stated:
We have sent the images that you requested through your deacon, Dulcitius.
We're delighted by your request because you earnestly seek the one whose image you wish to keep before your eyes.
Having a visual reminder every day keeps you constantly engaged, and when you look at the picture, your spirit is inspired by the one whose image you long to see.
We understand that you're not asking for an image of our Savior to worship as God, but as a reminder of the Son of God, so that you may grow in His love, whose image you desire to see.
Indeed, we don't bow before the image as though it were divine, but we honor the one we remember through the image, whether it depicts Him born, suffering, or sitting on the throne.
The image itself serves to remind us of the Son of God, much like Scripture does.
It brings joy to our spirit about the resurrection or provides comfort regarding the passion.
Therefore, we've sent you two cloth banners with images of the Savior, Mary, the holy Mother of God, and the blessed apostles Peter and Paul, through our son, the deacon.
Also included are a cross and a key for blessing, so you may be protected by Him from evil, armed with His sign.
May your royal, orthodox mind, inspired by God, remember and learn how Pope Saint Gregory instructed Bishop Serenus about holy images.
By witnessing the event, they may feel the fervor of contrition; looking at these holy images, they humbly worship the almighty Holy Trinity alone.
Similarly, Secundinus, the servant of God, said in Book Seven, Letter Fifty-Three:
You ask not to worship it as God, but to remind you of the Son of God, so that you may grow warm in His love, whose image you wish to see.
Indeed, we don't prostrate ourselves as before the Divinity, but we worship the one we remember through the image, whether born, suffering, or sitting on the throne.
As he advised Bishop Serenus, who, when looking at sacred images, humbly bowed in adoration only to the almighty Holy Trinity, he also instructed Secundinus, a recluse servant of God, not to worship the images as if they were God.
Instead, he taught him to bow before these sacred images—not as if before Divinity itself—but as a way to honor Him whom we remember through the image, whether it depicts Him born, suffering, or seated on a throne.
In the same way, following the blameless and orthodox beliefs of Saint Gregory the Pope, we issued a declaration during the reign of Emperors Irene and Constantine to promote the veneration of sacred images.
We stated that throughout the whole world, where Christianity exists, these sacred images are honored by all the faithful.
Through the visible images, our minds are drawn with spiritual affection to the invisible majesty of Divinity, contemplating the image portrayed in the flesh, which the Son of God deemed worthy to assume for our salvation.
In this way, we adore our Redeemer, who is in heaven, and glorify Him in spirit, praising Him, because, as it is written, God is spirit.
Let it be clear that we do not deify these images, as some might claim.
Instead, we express through them our love and devotion to God and His saints.
We keep the books of divine Scripture and these images as reminders of our veneration, maintaining the purity of our faith.
The testimonies we have recorded from the holy works of the Fathers align with the teachings of our predecessor, Saint Gregory the Pope, holding the same sense of faith and preaching it.
Those we sent, namely Peter, the archpriest of our Holy Roman Church, and Peter, a devoted priest and abbot of the venerable monastery of Saint Saba, embraced our apostolic letters and promptly arranged for a council to be held.
However, when a rebellion was sparked by heretics on the island of Sicily, our envoys returned without a response.
Later, after sending them again to Constantinople, they succeeded.
As a result, they convened this council according to our agreement and restored the sacred and venerable images to their rightful state.
Just as Saint Gregory's understanding of images and ours was upheld, they also recognized this in the same council, offering these images a kiss and honorable greeting; not as an act of worship, which is due only to the divine nature.
Additionally, they condemned the false decree made by heretics under the heretic Emperor Constantine, along with their followers and accomplices.
Returning to the orthodox faith of the holy catholic and apostolic Church, they made a confession of true faith through their written statements.
Therefore, we accepted this council: for if we had not accepted it and they had reverted to their former error, who would have been accountable for the loss of so many Christian souls before the dreadful judgment of the divine judge, if not us alone?
For if there is joy in heaven over one sinner who repents as written in the Gospel of Luke chapter Fifteen, how much more should one rejoice over so many thousands of Christians who have returned from error, and sing with the Psalmist: "Look to him and be radiant, and your faces shall never be ashamed" and so forth from Psalm Thirty-Four.
However, we have not yet given any response to the emperor regarding this council, fearing they might revert to their error.
Some time ago, when we encouraged them to set up sacred images, we also asked them to return the dioceses of both archbishops and bishops to the Holy Catholic and Apostolic Roman Church.
These were taken away along with our properties when they removed the sacred images.
They didn’t even provide any response to this.
This shows that even if they have corrected one error, they remain in the same error in two other matters.
If the canonical Churches of Christians everywhere still have their dioceses intact, how much more should the Holy Catholic and Apostolic Roman Church, which is the head of all God's Churches, hold and possess its dioceses?
This includes those of the archbishops and bishops, as well as its properties for the maintenance of lights and the support of the poor, by an unbreakable right and in every way.
Therefore, if your royal excellence, protected by God, agrees, we encourage the restoration of sacred images with the same fervor, giving thanks for their return to their original state.
However, we again admonish and remind about the diocese of our Holy Roman Church, both of the archbishops and of the bishops, as well as the properties, that if they do not wish to restore them to our Holy Roman Church, we will declare him a heretic for persisting in this error.
For we desire more to preserve the salvation of souls and the stability of true faith than to possess such worldly wealth.
We rely on your outstanding virtue, protected by God and bolstered by the steadfastness of the orthodox faith.
This firm foundation is never shaken or moved by those who are wicked and faithless.
We believe it will remain blameless forever in the teachings of the true faith, upholding the spiritual teachings of its holy mother, the Catholic and Apostolic Roman Church.
Therefore, we trust in the power of our God, as you maintain faith and love towards the Church of the blessed apostles Peter and Paul.
You always strive for its progress and exaltation with royal support.
May He graciously defend and protect you with His might in royal triumphs against hostile and unjust people.
So that, together with our spiritual daughter, your queen, and your noble offspring, you may reign in this world for a long time and, in the future, be worthy of eternal life in the heavenly kingdom.
May divine grace keep your excellence safe.