Letter on the Death of Paulinus
by Uranus the Presbyter
To the illustrious and deservedly venerable in Christ, Pacatus, from Uranius the priest.
I am urged once again by your noble letters to faithfully report the death of Saint Paulinus.
I will indeed do as you command, although I fear I may not do it as effectively as you wish, despite my desire to do so.
Nevertheless, since you command, I will do it faithfully and truthfully.
For I know it is better to hold one's tongue in silence than to tell lies that harm the soul, as Scripture says: "A lying tongue kills the soul."
Therefore, I earnestly ask your veneration to kindly pardon my lack of skill.
Otherwise, if my speech begins to displease you, you should rightly blame yourself, not me, for seeking pure water from a muddy stream.
But let these things be said briefly. Now, let us come to the matters that may provide material for you, who intend to illustrate his life in verse.
Therefore, Saint Paulinus, the bishop, was born in the town of Bordeaux in Gaul, but he passed away and was buried in Campania, near the most blessed confessor Felix, with a glorious end.
We recognize his life by the merit of his death, and we prove his death by the conduct of his life.
Indeed, three days before he was called from this world to the heavenly dwelling, when all had already despaired of his recovery, and two bishops came to visit him, namely, Saint Symmachus and the blessed Acindynus; he was so revived and refreshed at their arrival that, forgetting all bodily weakness, he presented himself to them as wholly spiritual and angelic.
And as if about to depart to the Lord, he commanded the sacred mysteries to be brought before his bed, so that, together with the holy bishops, he might commend his soul to the Lord with the offered sacrifice.
At the same time, he also recalled to their former peace those whom he had, for ecclesiastical discipline, ordered to be excluded from the communion of the sacred mystery.
And when the holy bishop had celebrated all these things with joy and perfect order, he suddenly began to ask loudly where his brothers were.
Then one of those standing nearby, thinking he was asking about the bishops present, said to him: Look, here are your brothers.
But he replied: I am talking about my brothers Januarius and Martin, who just spoke with me and said they would come to me soon.
Among them, Januarius, both bishop and martyr, illuminates the Church of Naples; Martin, a truly apostolic man whose life is known by everyone, was a bishop of Gaul.
After saying this, he raised his hands to heaven and sang this psalm to the Lord, saying:
"I lift my eyes to the mountains; where will my help come from? My help comes from the Lord, who made heaven and earth."
Then, after gathering in prayer, he was reminded by the holy priest Postumianus that forty coins were owed for the clothes given to the poor. When Saint Paulinus heard this, he smiled slightly and said:
"Don't worry, son; believe me, someone will pay the debt of the poor."
And behold, without much delay, a certain priest entered, coming from Lucania, sent by the holy Bishop Exuperantius or his distinguished brother Ursatius, who had sent fifty coins as a gift through him.
When Saint Paulinus received them, he blessed the Lord, saying:
"I thank you, Lord, for not abandoning those who hope in you."
From these fifty coins, he gave two to the priest who had delivered them; the rest he ordered to be given back to the merchants who had provided clothes to the poor.
Meanwhile, as night followed day, he allowed himself a little rest until about midnight; then, as the pain in his side grew worse, he was awakened and, exhausted by many excessive cauterizations from the chief physicians, endured a weary and panting chest until the fifth hour of the night.
Then, as daylight arrived, the holy man recognized his usual routine.
So, as he usually did, he woke everyone up and celebrated the morning service according to custom and order.
When the day had begun, he preached the inherited peace to the priests, deacons, and all the clerics, following the example of the Lord.
Then, as if awakened from sleep, recognizing the time for the evening devotion, he said with outstretched hands and a soft voice, "I have prepared a lamp for my Christ, the Lord, I have sung."
Then, after a period of silence, around the fourth hour of the night, while everyone present was vigilantly keeping watch, his small cell was suddenly shaken by such a great earthquake that those by his bed were terrified and disturbed, throwing themselves into prayer. However, those outside did not know anything about it because the quake was private and confined to his cell. He exhaled his rightful spirit to God, received by angelic hands.
We saw, most beloved son, we saw, and amidst tears and sobs, we rejoice to have seen; we saw how the righteous man is taken away, and no one understands: and righteous men are taken away, and no one considers.
It should not seem unbelievable to any Christian if a corner of the earth was specifically shaken by an earthquake at the passing of Saint Paulinus, at whose death almost the whole world groaned. And indeed, what place on earth is so remote or hidden that the passing of Lord Paulinus did not affect it? The Church clearly wept because it lost such a priest, but paradise exults because it received such a saint: people mourn, but angels rejoice: provinces of men groan, but the places of saints to which he longed to fly daily, rejoice, as he used to say: "How lovely are your dwelling places, Lord God of hosts! My soul longs and faints for your courts."
Oh, what a holy man and praiseworthy by all, who lived in such a way that he lived not just for himself, but for everyone! And therefore, because he lived for many in this world, now he lives for himself in Christ: and yet not just for himself, but also for us, because he prays for us every day.
Finally, he was a burning lamp in the house of God, not hidden under a bushel, but placed on a candlestick; so much so that he also made many lamps shine with his brilliant light.
For he was gentle and mild, even when he was involved in the pride of the world.
But when he turned to Christ, he opened his granaries to the poor and his storehouses to those in need.
It wasn't enough for him to just feed his neighbors; he also called on those from all around whom he could feed and clothe.
How many captives did he redeem!
How many debtors did he free from their creditors by paying their debts!
With one act of mercy, he both wiped away the debtors' tears and restored the creditors' joy.
When he was promoted to the highest rank of the priesthood, he didn't want to be a bishop who was feared by anyone; instead, he made himself a priest who was loved by all.
He was never so angry that he forgot mercy in his anger: for he could not be angry, as he despised insults and avoided hatred.
He never judged without mercy because he knew that mercy is better than sacrifice; that all judgment of Christians should be clothed in mercy, as the venerable Scripture says: "I will sing of mercy and judgment to you, O Lord." He tempered justice with kindness, knowing that the Holy Spirit, as much as he favors equity and justice, graciously grants the grace of mercy: and therefore, he held rigor in the examination of justice, but brought forth mercy in the final decision.
O admirable man, worthy of praise for all virtues! He followed the examples of all the patriarchs: he was faithful like Abraham, trusting like Isaac, kind like Jacob, generous like Melchizedek, provident like Joseph, and resourceful like Benjamin: for he took from the rich and gave to the poor; and yet he is known to have benefited the rich more than the poor, because he helped the poor in this world but provided for the rich in the next.
Therefore, as I began to say, he was gentle like Moses, priestly like Aaron, innocent like Samuel, merciful like David, wise like Solomon, apostolic like Peter, lovable like John, cautious like Thomas, a teacher like Paul, visionary like Stephen, and fervent like Apollos.
Moreover, in his care and concern for the churches, in faith and love, he imitated all the apostles and bishops.
He possessed all these qualities within himself and faithfully maintained them throughout his life.
And so, when he was called from this body to the heavenly dwelling, as I mentioned earlier, the earth mourned, but heaven rejoiced; the flesh wept, but the spirit exulted.
Indeed, not only Christians but also Jews and pagans gathered with immense weeping, even tearing their clothes at the funeral of Lord Paulinus.
They all mourned with us, lamenting the loss of their patron, defender, and protector.
Truly, he was such a person that he was loved by all: he lived as an example for everyone to gain salvation and as a source of comfort and consolation.
This is not just my own opinion: all the provinces are witnesses, the entire land that the Roman world encompasses is a witness; even the barbarian nations, to which the fame of Lord Paulinus had reached, are witnesses.
And rightly so, he was loved by all because he cared for everyone.
For whom lying down did his right hand not lift up?
Whom seeking his help did he not console with kind words?
He was indeed pious, merciful, humble, and kind: scorning no one, despising no one; he gave to all, forgave all: he encouraged the fearful and calmed the violent; these he built up with words, those with his example: some he helped with letters, others with financial support.
He admired no wealth or riches except those promised by Christ to His saints.
He defined gold, silver, and other wealth in such a way that generosity claimed them for giving, not greed for keeping.
To put it briefly, he possessed all good things within himself because he loved Christ.
He had faith, gentleness, and care for his neighbors.
He was always concerned for the poor and had compassion for the sick.
He sought nothing but peace and love, begging alone so that he could provide abundantly for everyone.
Is there any place on earth, any solitude, any sea, that has not felt the benefits of Saint Paulinus?
Everyone wanted to know him; everyone desired to see him.
Who did not approach him happily?
Or who left him without wishing to return?
For those who could not see him in person, at least wished to touch his letters.
He was sweet and gentle in his writings, sweet and very gentle in his verses.
What more can be said?
Faith might hardly accept whatever is said about him unless his deeds dispelled any falsehood.
Let us keep silent about his noble lineage, shining admirably in the purple of senators from his paternal and maternal origins.
Moreover, his wealth, which he gave to the poor for the sake of God.
Now let us come to those things we began to say about his death.
When Saint Paulinus returned his spirit to God, his face and entire body were affected with such snowy whiteness that everyone, amid sobs and tears, blessed the Lord our God, who brings forth His saints in magnificence, to show His servants that this is the glory of all His saints.
Let his soul be praised in God, and his works revealed to all who fear God, for he delighted in the commandments of his God, and he understood the needy and the poor, so that his offspring might be powerful on earth, and his righteousness remain forever and ever.
Concerning the merit of Saint Paulinus, your veneration should also acknowledge that Saint John, bishop of the city of Naples, was called and summoned from this life to Christ by Lord Paulinus.
Three days before Saint John departed from this world to the Lord, he reported seeing Saint Paulinus.
Paulinus appeared dressed and adorned with angelic dignity, all in white, star-like, and shining with a heavenly fragrance.
He was holding a very white honeycomb in his hand and said to John, "Brother John, what are you doing here? Break the chains of your troubles, and come to us now. For this food I hold in my hand is plentiful with us."
After saying this, he embraced John and placed a part of the honeycomb in his mouth. Saint John said he desired the sweetness and fragrance of it so much that if he had the power during that revelation, he would not have left Paulinus's side.
However, he did not delay for long. Upon waking from sleep on that same day, which was Thursday, he followed his usual custom. He rewarded all the clergy and the poor and celebrated the Lord's Supper in good health. On Friday, he devoted himself to prayer. On Saturday, at the second hour of the day, he went joyfully to the church. Ascending the platform as usual, he greeted the people, and after being greeted back, he gave a prayer. After the prayer, he breathed his last.
That night, there was a vigil in the church. The next day, which was Easter, with lamps lit and a great procession of newly baptized people, followed by a multitude, he received a glorious and praiseworthy burial.
I mention these things to your nobility so that you may recognize the merit of Saint Paulinus here as well. You have the material to speak about it, provided you have faith to believe. So, I ask your nobility, as you have promised, to hasten the work of this illustrious task. You will gain the rewards of praise and glory if you illuminate the life of this holy man in verses for the benefit of future generations. If only, before I depart, you would make me worthy of reading this work: for if it pleases Christ, I plan to sail immediately. Saint Paulinus, bishop, died on the tenth day before the calends of July, June 22, during the consulship of Bassus and Antiochus.