Saint Eucherius, Bishop of Lyons, summarizes the works of Cassian addressed to Castor of Apt in two books.
Book One On the Established Rules of Monasteries.
When you asked me, most blessed Father Castor, to explain the canonical rules of Eastern, and especially Egyptian, monasteries, which I have personally observed,
I complied with your request and sent you these few words to serve as a guide to virtue for those gathered in your new monastery with God's help.
I have also included the canons of blessed men and some others.
Therefore, it is necessary to first speak about prayer, the source of all good things, specifically how and in what excellent order it is conducted in the monasteries of Egypt and Thebaid.
When they gather for the synaxis, after the psalm is finished, they do not immediately kneel.
Instead, before bending their knees, they stand for a short time with their hands outstretched in prayer.
After that, they prostrate themselves on the ground and, following a brief prayer while kneeling, they all rise together.
Then, with their hands outstretched again, they continue their supplications for a longer and more fervent period, with no one kneeling or rising from kneeling until the one reciting the prayer has first knelt or risen.
As mentioned, when they gather for the synaxis, such silence is maintained by everyone that in such a large and almost innumerable assembly, it seems as if no one is present.
Especially during prayer times, no one spits or coughs.
There are no signs of laziness, no drowsiness, no yawning, no audible groans.
They say that anyone who prays loudly due to nausea or weakness of spirit sins in two ways:
first, because they pray sluggishly;
second, because with that undisciplined voice, they deafen the ears and distract the minds of their neighbors.
At the same time, malicious spirits attack, who, when they see us standing in prayer, burden our souls with improper thoughts, nausea, and disgust.
Why do they recite the psalms not with haste and confusion, but with thoughtful consideration?
They follow the wisdom of the one who said:
I will sing with the spirit, I will sing also with the mind.
First Corinthians 14:15.
They believe it's more beneficial to sing ten verses with attention than the entire psalter with a confused mind.
After completing the psalms and the canon, as previously mentioned, no brother dares to stand or speak with another, even for a short while.
They do not leave their cell or abandon the work they're doing, according to the apostolic precept.
Unless necessary for a work occasion that requires everyone to meet, they carry out their tasks without any conversation.
Each one focuses on meditation and psalms, fulfilling their duties.
They also avoid leaving any brother alone with another, especially a novice, or touching or embracing anyone.
If anyone breaks this rule, they are subjected to serious correction.
Regarding the canonical practice of prayers or psalms and their observance in daily gatherings, we've said enough.
Now, we need to discuss those who renounce the world, how they should enter the monasteries, and remain with humility and obedience until old age.
Their obedience and humility endure until old age, which is not found even in the first year among those who renounce the world in our monasteries.
Therefore, no one wishing to be a monk is admitted until they demonstrate and prove their love for God, humility, and equanimity through utmost obedience.
Cassian, Institutes, Book 2, Chapter 15.
Cassian, Institutes, Book 4, Chapters 1-6.
Through this testing, he is admitted and taught by them, ensuring he doesn't keep any of his goods hidden.
They know that anyone who holds onto their possessions can't remain obedient to the monastery for long or persevere until the end due to mental weakness and boredom.
When any small opportunity or affliction unsettles his mind, the hope of hidden treasure, like a slingshot stone, drives him out of the monastery.
Therefore, each person is stripped of their old possessions, and they're not even allowed to use the clothing they wore.
When all the brothers are gathered, he is brought into the middle, stripped of his own clothes, and dressed in the monastery's clothes by the abbot's hands.
This way, he understands that he has been stripped of all worldly things, arrogance, and pride, and has embraced the poverty of Christ, counting himself equal with the brotherhood.
The clothing he is stripped of is taken and kept by the monastery's steward and stored separately until he has shown progress and patience in various trials.
If he perseveres and continues with the same zeal and fervent intention he began with, he is counted among the other brothers.
But if he is found guilty of murmuring or any sin of disobedience, he is stripped of the monastery's clothing, re-clothed in worldly garments, and expelled.
Thus, after such careful testing, it is not easy for anyone to enter or leave the monastery at their own will.
If someone declares they do not wish to remain, they are completely stripped of the monastery's clothing.
Cassiodorus, Institutions, Book Two, Chapters Seven through Nine.
Since the person who has been admitted and tested with the accuracy we mentioned is found without fault, he is not immediately allowed to join the gathering of brothers.
Instead, he is handed over to the one in charge of guests and is ordered to fully devote himself to the service and care of guests.
After he has taken care of the guests blamelessly for an entire year and has been shaped in humility and equanimity through this task, he is finally counted among the gathering of brothers and is entrusted to one of the elders.
This elder's responsibility is to teach the disciple the paths he must take to achieve perfection in virtues.
First and foremost, he teaches him the importance of overcoming his own desires and pleasures by instructing him to do things that are against his will.
The Fathers say that no one can suppress their pleasures, anger, or sadness, truly obtain humility, or be properly completed in the community of brothers unless they first mortify their own will through obedience.
With these rules and teachings, like certain basic elements and letters, once they have brought the disciple to a more advanced state, they then teach him to not hide his thoughts.
As soon as thoughts come to him, he should reveal them to his father as soon as possible and not trust his own heart's judgment and examination of them.
He should know that something is good or bad based on his father's judgment after examining the matter.
In this way, anyone who is being trained in virtue can avoid all the enemy's deceptions, as the inexperienced person is unaware of the enemy's tricks.
The holy Fathers say that it is a clear sign of the devil's craft and deceit when he persuades disciples to hide their thoughts from their fathers.
This comes either from the prideful belief that they are capable of making appropriate decisions on their own or from vanity, as they are ashamed to reveal their thoughts.
(Cassian, Institutes, Book 4, Chapters 10-12)
Their obedience is so profound that no one dares to leave their cell, even for a moment, without the abbot's command.
They follow his orders as diligently as if God Himself were commanding them.
While they sit in their cells, they devote themselves to manual work, meditation, and prayer with great focus.
If they hear someone knocking on their cell door, whether it’s for communal prayer or manual labor, they immediately leave everything and hurry to the task assigned to them, valuing obedience above all else.
They prioritize it over manual work, reading, and even peaceful dwelling in their cell, indeed over all virtues, setting everything else aside.
Cassian's Institutes, Book Four, Chapters Thirteen to Sixteen
It's unnecessary to mention that none of them owns more than a tunic, a cloak, a sandal, a blanket, and a mat.
They find it disgraceful to say "my book," "my brush," or claim anything as "mine." Each of them contributes enough from their own labor and sweat to the monastery, not only for their needs but also to serve guests and the poor.
As they work, they remain humble, without arrogance or pride. No one demands more for their labor and sweat than what the abbot provides for their needs. They do not acquire possessions, viewing themselves as strangers and pilgrims in the world. They see themselves as servants and ministers to their brothers rather than masters of any earthly thing. If anyone breaks or loses an item, they confess the incident to the abbot as a result of their own carelessness and humbly receive forgiveness through repentance.
If someone is called to any task or meeting and shows up late out of contempt, or responds harshly or insolently, or completes a task carelessly or with murmuring, or if they prioritize reading over manual work and obedience, completing assigned tasks slowly, or if they leave a meeting and don't quickly return to their work, or chat with someone unnecessarily, or touch another's hand confidently, or meet relatives without the abbot's permission and blessing, or dare to receive or send a letter without the abbot's permission; if they commit any of these offenses, they are subject to this punishment: when the brothers are gathered in the meeting, they lie down on the ground, confess, and ask for forgiveness for their sin.
For more serious offenses, such as contempt, defiance with pride, leaving the monastery without the abbot's permission, meeting with a woman, anger, fighting, enmity towards someone, holding grudges, love of money (which is a spiritual disease), possession of any item not given by the abbot, or secretly taking food without the abbot's blessing, and similar offenses, the punishment is not the one mentioned above, but a much more severe and greater one.
If they do not repent, they are expelled from the monastery.
Cassiodorus, Institutions, Book 4, Chapters 17 and 18.
However, in some monasteries, the practice of reading during mealtime is observed, not according to the Egyptians, but according to the Cappadocians, who established it not so much for spiritual exercise, but to avoid idleness and conversation.
Among the Egyptians, especially the Tabennesiots, there is complete silence observed by all when the large gathering of brothers comes together for a meal, so much so that it's hard to find anything similar; even coughing or clearing the throat is not allowed, except by the person in charge of the table, who indicates any need by knocking rather than speaking.
However, they also wear hoods that hang down even below their eyelids, so they don't look curiously at others with wandering eyes.
Instead, they focus only on the table and giving thanks to the nourishing God.
They are very careful that no one takes food outside of meal times.
Moreover, to ensure we do not omit any of the monastic rules, we must also mention the regulations handed down in other regions.
Throughout Mesopotamia, Palestine, and Cappadocia, and in the entire East, during the third, sixth, and ninth hour gatherings, if someone does not arrive before the first psalm is completed, they do not dare to enter the oratory or join those singing.
Instead, they wait at the door until the brothers are dismissed.
When everyone leaves, they prostrate themselves on the ground, doing penance and asking for forgiveness for their negligence.
Furthermore, during the nightly gatherings, latecomers are allowed in until the second psalm.
Additionally, the brothers take turns in the kitchen and other duties each week, both to lighten the load through mutual labor and to fulfill the law of charity through mutual service.
They perform these services with such humility and diligence that even servants do not show to their masters.
At the end of the week, on Sunday after morning hymns, those who are entering to serve hand over their assigned tools marked with their names.
Those who receive them guard them with such care and diligence that nothing is broken or lost, with the same care given to sacred and dedicated objects.
They prepare themselves to give an account, not only to the steward in the present time but also to God in the future, if anything is lost due to their negligence or laziness.
To further increase the credibility of what I have said, I will narrate what I have seen with my own eyes.
During a certain brother's week of duty, the steward noticed a few lentil grains scattered on the ground.
Rather than dismissing them as insignificant, he scolded the brother responsible that week and punished him for neglecting what was dedicated to God and for betraying his own conscience.
They take great care and diligence in everything, managing all things so that even what seems trivial and worthless to us is guarded with great attention.
They move misplaced vessels and pick up what is dropped, believing they will receive a reward from the Lord God for even these small acts.
We have found these weekly regulations observed throughout the East.
Among the Egyptians, however, the weekly rotation is not maintained in this way.
Instead, the kitchen's care is entrusted to one of the most proven brothers for as long as his virtue increases and his bodily strength supports the duties, provided old age or infirmity does not prevent him.
Since our discussion is about obedience and humility, through which we can reach the highest peak of virtue, I think it is worthwhile to add a few examples from the many remarkable deeds of the holy Fathers who shone in the monasteries.
A certain father named Muthius, wishing to renounce the world, approached a monastery and waited outside its doors for a long time.
Because of his great patience, he and his young son were admitted, contrary to the usual custom of the monastery.
After many labors, when they were accepted, they were assigned to various tasks and even separated in their living quarters to gradually free them from their mutual natural affection.
Through much practice and the grace of Christ, the father was freed from this affection.
To test and prove his virtue, the abbot sometimes pretended to be angry with the boy and ordered the father to throw him into the river.
Then, as if commanded by God to take away his son, he arrived at the riverbank in a hurried run.
While hastening to fulfill the order out of burning faith and fervor of obedience, he was stopped by brothers who had arrived before him and took the son away.
However, his faith and obedience were so pleasing to God that it was revealed to the abbot that he had accomplished the work of Abraham.
Shortly after, when the aforementioned abbot of the monastery passed away, he left him as his successor.
Cassianus, Institutes, Book 4, Chapter 29.
We know of another brother who renounced the world, who was also distinguished in the world.
His father was a count waging war and was wealthy.
He was moderately educated and studious in reading.
Having abandoned worldly pride, he turned to monastic life.
To test his faith and humility, the abbot ordered him to carry ten baskets and sell them in his own city, not all at once, but individually.
He completed this task with patience and humility, carrying the baskets on his shoulders and selling them one by one.
He did not consider the lowliness of the task or his noble birth; he was striving to become an imitator of Christ's humility.
Cassianus, Institutes, Book 4, Chapters 30-32.
We also saw another father, the abbot Pinophan, a man adorned with every virtue, who was an elder and the abbot of a great monastery in Egypt near the city of Panepho.
When he saw that he was being praised and celebrated by everyone, both for his way of life and for his old age and leadership, and that he could not, as he had at the beginning of his conversion, exercise himself in the pursuit of humility, he was moved by these thoughts.
Desiring the subjection in which he had been called, he secretly fled from his monastery and withdrew alone to the farthest parts of Thebaid.
Taking off the monk’s garment and putting on secular clothes, he went to the monastery of the Tabennesiotes, thinking he could hide there, both because of the large number of brothers and because it was far from the region where his own monastery was located.
After waiting for many days, he was finally received by the archimandrite.
Since he was old and not seen as useful in other ways, he was entrusted with caring for the garden alongside another brother, to whom he was subordinate.
He cherished the humility and obedience he desired.
Not content with just that task, he eagerly took on whatever duties others found hard and difficult.
For three years, he lived in secrecy, but his disciples searched for him throughout Egypt and eventually, a certain brother recognized him.
This brother, upon seeing and recognizing his facial features, still had doubts.
He tried to hear his voice, as sight alone was not enough to be sure.
He saw an old man digging the earth with a hoe and carrying manure on his shoulders to place at the root of vegetables.
When he recognized his voice, he prostrated himself at his feet, astonishing the onlookers.
They were surprised by his behavior towards someone they considered a novice who had recently left the world and was regarded as the least among them.
Their astonishment grew when they learned his name, as he was previously well-known among them.
They asked for forgiveness for unknowingly placing him among the novices.
After encouraging him with many words, they reluctantly sent him back to his monastery, as he lamented that he was not allowed to practice the beloved humility and obedience.
After a short time in his monastery, burning again with the desire for humility and obedience, he fled during the night, this time not to a foreign region.
He boarded a small boat and arrived in parts of Palestine, hoping to hide there until the end.
When he arrived in Palestine, he sought a monastery near the cave where the Lord Christ was born, and he stayed there.
However, he could not remain hidden, as the Lord said: "A city set on a hill cannot be hidden" Matthew 5:15.
When the brothers came from Egypt for the worship of sacred places, they recognized him and, after many prayers and tears, persuaded him to return to his own monastery.
So, I lived with this holy man in Egypt for a short time, and I will end my speech by recounting what I heard from him when he admitted a brother in my presence.
Cassian, Institutes, Book 4, Chapters 33-35.
"You know, brother," he said, "after how many days spent outside the monastery gate, you were admitted today. If you understand the reason for this difficulty, it can benefit you on the path you wish to take and make you a faithful servant of God.
Just as glory and honor are promised in the future to those who serve the Lord faithfully, severe punishments await those who approach this promise weakly and lazily. Indeed, it is better, according to Scripture, not to make a vow than to make it and not fulfill it. And it is also said: 'Cursed is the one who does the work of the Lord negligently' (Jeremiah 48:10).
Therefore, we rejected you and hesitated to admit you, not because we do not wish for your salvation and that of all those who believe in Christ, but so that by admitting you too hastily and without due consideration, we wouldn't suffer the punishment of excessive leniency from God while praying, and you wouldn't be subjected to harsher punishment if we admitted you easily before you learned the seriousness and care of the promise, and you later became weak and lazy.
Therefore, as mentioned above, you must understand the reason for your rejection and what you need to do.
Rejection is nothing other than the promise of the cross and death.
Know then that from this day, you are dead and crucified to the world, and the world to you, according to the Apostle; and understand what the power of the cross is: since you no longer live, but He who was crucified for you lives in you.
So, in this way, in which the Lord was suspended for us, we must also act in the monastery, as blessed David prays, asking with the fear of the Lord for his flesh to be pierced (Psalm 119:120).
Just as someone whose body is fixed to a piece of wood remains motionless, so too does someone whose thoughts are anchored by divine fear remain unmoved by any carnal desires.
Like someone nailed to a cross who doesn't think about present things, isn't guided by their own will, isn't disturbed by desire, isn't preoccupied with possessions, isn't inflated by pride, isn't ignited by contention or envy, doesn't grieve over insults, nor remembers past injuries: because they expect the end of their life soon through the cross; similarly, someone who has sincerely renounced the world and is anchored by the fear of God, expecting the end of this life daily, has all desires and carnal affections weakened and unmoved.
Therefore, take heed never to desire again the things you have renounced.
For according to the Lord's judgment: Whoever puts their hand to the plow and looks back is not fit for the kingdom of heaven.
Luke chapter 9, verse 62.
Whoever descends from a high calling of life to the vile and earthly matters of this world acts against the Lord's command when they descend from the house to take something from it.
Therefore, beware that you do not recall your old affections towards carnal parents, turn to the cares of this world, and thus be found unfit for the kingdom of heaven according to the Lord's voice.
Matthew chapter 5, verse 19.
Beware that you do not rekindle the pride you initially trampled underfoot with the zeal of humility.
When you have learned the psalter or something from Scripture; or as the Apostle says, when you rebuild what you have destroyed, do not show yourself a transgressor; but rather, as you began and professed humility, keep it before God and his angels until the end.
Similarly, the humility you showed in the monastery, when you persevered for many days with tears begging at the doors of the monastery, strive to increase it.
It would be truly unfortunate if, instead of adding to your fervor daily and climbing towards perfection with constant progress, you diminish it and fall back to lower levels.
It's not the one who starts doing good who is blessed, but the one who perseveres until the end.
The serpent, always dragged to the ground, watches our heel, setting traps for our fall and trying to trip us up until the end of our lives.
Therefore, starting well is of no benefit, and the initial fervor of obedience means nothing unless it is sustained.
The humility according to Christ, which you promised, will not be firmly established unless you maintain it until the end.
To possess it perfectly and crush the head of the dragon (Genesis 3:15), reveal your thoughts quickly from the very beginning: if you disclose the harmful thoughts of the dragon early and are not ashamed to declare them to your father, you will crush its head.
According to divine Scripture, if you come to serve God, prepare yourself (Ecclesiasticus 2:1), not for carelessness, not for idleness, but for trials and tribulations: for through many tribulations we must enter the kingdom of heaven (Acts 14:22).
The gate is narrow, and the way is hard that leads to life, and few find it (Matthew 7:14).
Therefore, pay attention to the few good people and model your life on their example; do not heed the lazy and the scorners, no matter how numerous they are: For many are called, but few are chosen (Matthew 20:16); and it is a little flock to whom the Father has pleased to give the kingdom (Luke 12:31).
Do not think it a small thing to promise perfection and then imitate the more negligent and sluggish ones.
To reach perfection, follow this path and climb these steps.
(Cassian, Institutes, Book 4, Chapters 39, 40.)
The first step of virtue and the beginning of our salvation is the fear of God.
Through it, sins are purified, virtues are preserved, and the way to perfection is obtained.
When the fear of God enters a soul, it encourages us to disregard all worldly things.
From this arises forgetfulness of relatives and the whole world.
Following this, humility, the head of all virtues and the complement of all good things, is practiced.
Humility comes from the contempt and deprivation of all things.
Humility is proven by these signs:
First, if someone has mortified their own will.
Second, if they hide nothing from their father, not only in deeds but also in thoughts.
Third, if they do not trust their own prudence but rely on their father's discretion in all things, always thirsting for, desiring, and sweetly listening to his admonitions.
Fourth, if they carry out all their father's commands without shame.
Fifth, if they not only dare not insult others but also accept insults from others with joy.
Sixth, if they attempt nothing new that neither common rules nor the examples of the Fathers permit.
Seventh, if they are content with all lowliness, give thanks for the things given to them, and consider themselves unworthy of them.
Eighth, if they consider themselves plainly inferior to everyone and are not reckless in words.
Ninth, if they are not quick to speak and their tongue is not rash.
Humility is recognized by these and similar signs.
When these are truly exhibited, they quickly lead to the height of love, in which there is no fear of hell, and through which all things are accomplished not out of necessity and labor but out of fervent love and the desire for good.
To obtain this virtue more easily, let the words of the brothers running together with you and possessing piety be your example.
Not, however, those who are more numerous and live more negligently and sluggishly.
From the imitation and emulation of the saints, great benefit comes to those striving for perfection.
(Cassiodorus, Institutes, Book Four, Chapters Forty-One to Forty-Three.)
If you want to achieve all these things and persevere in the spiritual struggle of the monastery, you need to follow what David said to maintain harmony with your brothers:
"But I, like a deaf man, did not hear, and like a man who does not hear and has no rebuttals in his mouth."
Psalm
37:14.
So, whenever you see something that's not constructive or useful, act as if you were blind; and if you hear something similar, be like a deaf and mute person, without any rebuttals in your mouth. Don't imitate those who are unfaithful, disobedient, insolent, mocking, or disrespectful; instead, be like a mute person who doesn't hear and disregard these things.
If anyone reproaches, insults, or humiliates you, remain unmoved, as if you were restrained and mute. Continuously repeat this verse from the psalms to yourself:
"I said, I will guard my ways, that I may not sin with my tongue. I have put a guard on my mouth when the sinner stands against me. I was silent and humbled."
Psalm
38:1.
Additionally, meditate on and observe this fourth thing above all, which can adorn the three previously mentioned: make yourself foolish and unwise in this world, according to the Apostle's command, so that you may be wise.
First Corinthians
3:18.
Specifically, don't judge or doubt any of the commands given to you. Be instructed in simplicity and the faith of obedience. Among all holy things, believe as holy, wise, and useful only that which is commanded to you by your father.
If you fix your heart on this purpose, you will be able to bear the yoke of Christ's obedience until the end, and no temptations or tricks of the devil will be able to dislodge you from the knowledge of life. Don't expect to establish your patience, humility, and equanimity based on the virtue of others—that is, if no one provokes, despises, or shames you. This is neither proof of your virtue nor is it within your power. But if you willingly bear insults, humiliations, and contempt, that is within your control.
So, to summarize what we discussed earlier in a simpler way, let's go over the steps to achieve perfection.
The beginning of our salvation is the fear of God.
From that comes good obedience.
Obedience leads to submission and a disregard for worldly things.
This humility results in the mortification of our own wills.
When we mortify our wills, the roots of our pleasures dry up.
This process eliminates all imperfections of the soul, allowing virtues to grow and bear fruit.
As virtues increase, we attain purity of heart.
Purity of heart leads to apostolic perfection by the grace and help of our Lord Jesus Christ, to whom be glory forever and ever.
Amen.
Book Two On the Eight Thoughts of Malice
Previously, we discussed the establishment of monasteries.
Now, with your prayers, we will begin to explore the eight thoughts of malice: gluttony, fornication, avarice, anger, sadness, sloth, vainglory, and pride.
First, we will address abstinence, which counters gluttony.
We will cover the practices of fasting, as well as the quality and quantity of food.
Our guidance is not based on our own insights but on the teachings of our holy Fathers.
They did not prescribe a single rule for fasting, a specific way of eating, or the same measure for everyone, because people have different strengths, ages, and physical conditions.
However, they did share a common goal: to avoid gluttony and the overindulgence of the belly.
They found through experience that daily fasting is more beneficial for maintaining purity than fasting for extended periods like three or four days, or even a week.
Those who fast excessively often end up eating immoderately.
As a result, the body, weakened by too much abstinence, may become sluggish in spiritual duties.
Conversely, when burdened with too much food, it can lead to laziness and a softening of the spirit.
Not everyone can tolerate vegetables or legumes, and dry bread is not sufficient for everyone.
Some people remain hungry after eating two pounds of bread, while others are satisfied with just one pound or even six ounces.
Therefore, the Fathers advised everyone to aim for abstinence: not to be misled by the fullness of the belly or the pleasure of the palate.
It is not just the quality but also the quantity of food that can ignite the fiery darts of sin.
Any food that fills the belly can generate seeds of lust.
Again, it's not just an excess of wine, but even an abundance of water and any kind of food can weigh a person down, making them sluggish and sleepy.
For the Sodomites, it wasn't the excess of wine or various foods that caused their downfall, but the fullness of bread, according to the prophet Ezekiel 16:49.
Bodily weakness does not oppose purity of heart.
So, provide for the body what its weakness demands, not what pleasure desires.
The use of food should be just enough to sustain life, not to satisfy cravings.
Moderate and reasonable consumption of food promotes bodily health and does not take away holiness.
The holy Fathers handed down this precise norm and rule of abstinence: one who eats should stop while still having an appetite.
When the Apostle says, "Make no provision for the flesh, to gratify its desires" Romans 13:14, he did not forbid necessary care for life but prohibited care that fosters pleasure. Moreover, for perfect purity of the soul, abstinence from food alone is not enough unless other virtues are also present. Therefore, humility through obedience in work and bodily affliction brings us great benefits.
Being free from greed means not only not having money but also not desiring its possession. Restraining anger, sadness, vain glory, and pride leads the soul to purity. All these contribute to overall purity of the soul. However, the particular purity of the soul, achieved through temperance, is primarily attained through abstinence and fasting. It is impossible for someone who is full to battle against the spirit of lust. Therefore, our first struggle should be to control our belly and bring our body into subjection: not only through fasting but also through vigils, labor, reading, and instilling in the soul the fear of hell and the desire for the kingdom of heaven.
Cassian, Institutes, Book 6, Chapter 1 and following.
According to us, the struggle is against the spirit of fornication and the lust of the flesh, which begins to trouble a person from an early age.
It is a great and heavy struggle, consisting of a double battle; for it is double, as it is fought in both body and soul.
Therefore, it is necessary to engage in a double fight against it.
Bodily fasting alone is not enough to achieve perfect temperance and true chastity unless there is also constant prayer to God, frequent meditation on the Holy Scriptures, manual labor, and work, which can restrain the unstable impulses of the soul and recall it from obscene thoughts.
Especially helpful in this is the humility of the soul, without which no one will be able to overcome fornication or other passions.
Therefore, it is necessary above all to guard the heart from sordid thoughts with all diligence.
Proverbs 4:23.
For from it, according to the Lord's words, come evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, and other things.
Matthew 15:19.
Fasting is not only imposed on us for the affliction of the body, but also for the temperance of the mind, so that, not being clouded by an abundance of food, it can avoid these thoughts.
Therefore, it is necessary to devote all attention not only to bodily fasting but also to the watchfulness of thoughts and spiritual meditation, without which it is impossible to reach the pinnacle of true chastity and purity.
Therefore, according to the Lord's words, it is fitting for us to cleanse the inside of the cup and the dish, so that the outside may also be clean.
Matthew 23:26.
Therefore, if we care, according to the Apostle, to compete lawfully and receive the crown.
Second Timothy 2:5, having defeated the impure spirit of fornication, let us not trust in our own strength or asceticism, but in the help of the Lord God.
For no person can end the struggle with such a demon until they truly believe that they are not freed from this disease by their own effort or labor, but by God's impulse and assistance, and ascend to the highest peak of chastity.
Indeed, it is beyond nature and somehow exists outside the body to overcome the urges of the flesh and its pleasures.
Therefore, it is impossible for a person to, so to speak, reach this peak and the prize of holiness on their own and become an imitator of angels unless God's grace lifts them from the earth and mud.
No virtue makes humans, bound by flesh, more like the heavenly angels than temperance.
Through it, while still living on earth, they have, according to the Apostle, their conversation in heaven.
Philippians chapter 3, verse 20.
This is the indication of this virtue we have acquired if no obscene images come to the mind of a sleeper.
For although such movements are not considered sin, they are a sign of a soul that is sick and not yet freed from such passion.
Therefore, we must consider those obscene fantasies occurring during sleep as evidence of preceding laziness and an indication of our weakness, revealing the disease hidden in the secret of our hearts by the cessation of sleep upon awakening.
For this reason, the healer of souls placed the remedy in the innermost parts of the soul, knowing that the causes of the disease are there, when he said: "Whoever looks at a woman to lust for her has already committed adultery with her in his heart,"
Matthew chapter 5, verse 28. Not only to correct lascivious and curious eyes but much more the soul situated within, which has improperly used the eyes given by God for good.
This is why the Wise proverb says, not, "With all vigilance guard your eyes;" but, "With all vigilance guard your heart."
Proverbs chapter 4, verse 23. For he applies the remedy to the custody that uses the eyes at its discretion.
Therefore, let this be our first safeguard in maintaining purity: when the memory of a woman, influenced by diabolic forces, enters our mind—whether she is a mother, sister, or another pious woman—let us quickly cast it out of our hearts.
If we linger too long on such thoughts, the seducer and author of evil may lead our minds into obscene and harmful thoughts through the fantasy of these faces, eventually leading us into sin.
Just as God commanded the first man to beware of the serpent's head—symbolizing the beginning of harmful thoughts that try to creep into our soul—if we allow the head, or the first incursion of thought, to enter, we may also admit the rest of the serpent's body, meaning the consent to pleasure, which can lead our minds into wicked deeds.
As it is written, we should kill all the sinners of the earth in the morning (Psalm 101:8); that is, with the light of knowledge, we should discern and destroy thoughts that lead to sin from our hearts, according to the Lord's command.
While the children of Babylon (Psalm 137:9), or evil thoughts, are still small, they must be dashed to the ground and struck against the rock, which is Christ.
For if they reach maturity through our consent, overcoming them will require great effort and suffering.
To add to the teachings from Holy Scripture, we should also consider the sayings of the holy Fathers.
Saint Basil, Bishop of Caesarea in Cappadocia, said:
"I do not know a woman, yet I am not a virgin," meaning that the gift of virginity is not only about abstaining from women physically but also about the holiness and purity of the soul and the fear of God.
The Fathers also teach that we cannot possess the perfect virtue of chastity unless we first cultivate true humility in our hearts; nor can we attain true knowledge as long as the desire for fornication dwells in our souls.
To illustrate the great power of this virtue from the Apostle himself, let us recall one of his statements, with which we will conclude our discussion.
"Pursue peace with everyone, and holiness, without which no one will see the Lord"
Hebrews 12:14.
It is clear from what he added that he is speaking about this matter when he said,
"No one should be an immoral or godless person like Esau"
Hebrews 12:16.
Therefore, the more heavenly and angelic the virtue of chastity is, the more it is attacked by severe snares from the enemy.
Consequently, we should take care not only to maintain physical temperance but also to have a contrite heart and to offer frequent prayers with groans.
In this way, the furnace of our flesh, which the king of Babylon ignites daily with the stimuli of lust, will be extinguished by the dew of the Holy Spirit's presence.
Additionally, the greatest weapon we have against such an enemy is vigilantly keeping watch for God.
Just as chastity and daily vigilance prepare for nightly sanctity, so too do nightly vigils in God prepare for daily sanctity.
The third struggle we face is against the spirit of greed.
This kind of battle is foreign and contrary to our nature and arises for a monk due to unbelief.
Indeed, the stimuli of other passions, namely anger and lust, seem to have their origin in the body and are somewhat innate, having a beginning from birth.
This is why they can only be overcome with prolonged effort.
However, the disease of greed, arriving from external sources, can be more easily eradicated with care and mental attention.
But if it is neglected, it becomes more harmful than other passions and detestable, for it is the root of all evils according to the Apostle
First Timothy 6:10.
Let us consider this in the following way: the natural movements of the body are observed not only in children, who have no discernment of good and evil, but even in the very smallest and nursing infants, who, though they have no trace of carnal pleasure, still exhibit movement in the flesh.
The feeling of anger often appears in children when they become agitated against those who trouble them.
I'm not saying this to blame nature as the cause of sin—far from it—but to show that, although anger and desire were given to humans by the Creator for good, human nature can sometimes lead to actions that go against this intention due to its own laziness.
Bodily impulses were given by the Creator for the procreation of children and the continuation of the human race, not for promiscuity.
The emotion of anger was instilled in us for our safety, so we may be angry against sin, not to incite fury against our fellow humans.
So, if we misuse these things, it is not nature that sins, nor should we blame the Creator.
Just as we shouldn't blame someone who gave necessary and useful iron if the recipient uses it to commit murders.
This is to show that the inclination towards greed does not originate from natural impulse, but solely from malice and a corrupted purpose.
This kind of disease, when it finds a lukewarm and unbelieving soul at the beginning of withdrawal, presents seemingly reasonable causes, suggesting retaining something from possessions.
It shows the monk a long old age and bodily weakness, implying that what is provided in the monastery is not enough for comfort, neither for the sick nor the healthy.
It suggests that proper care for the sick is lacking and that if no gold is secretly available, one would perish miserably.
Finally, it suggests that one cannot persevere in the monastery due to the severity of the works and the strictness of the father.
When it has filled the mind with such thoughts, so that even a single coin is retained, it then advises the person to secretly learn a skill to diligently increase the saved money.
Ultimately, it deceives the miserable person with a hidden hope, suggesting that profit will come from this skill, leading to peace and a mind free from cares.
And finally, driven by the thought of profit, he considers nothing adverse: not how great the future anger will be, nor the fury if some loss occurs; not the sadness, nor the pain, if he is deprived of the profit of his work.
Just as the belly is a god to some, so gold is to him.
Blessed Paul knew this well, and he called it not only the root of all evils but also idolatry.
Let us consider how much wickedness this disease leads a person into, even to the point of idolatry.
For when the greedy man tears his mind away from the love of God, he loves images of people engraved in gold.
A monk darkened by such thoughts, as he worsens, can no longer have any humility or obedience.
He becomes angry, indignant, complains about any task, resists, and finally, with no shame, like an unrestrained horse, rushes into danger.
Not content with daily sustenance, he ultimately declares that he can no longer endure it.
He says that God is not only there, nor is his salvation confined to that place; but that God is found by those seeking Him everywhere.
He will perish unless he leaves that monastery.
So, seeking help for his corrupted mind with hidden money, as if lifted by wings, planning his departure from the monastery, he responds proudly and harshly to all orders, considering himself a stranger and outsider.
If he sees something in the monastery that needs correction, he cares nothing—in fact, he despises it.
Then he looks for reasons for anger or complaints, so he does not seem to leave the monastery lightly and without cause.
Nor does he hesitate to act in such a way that he finds an accomplice for his sin.
Thus, the greedy man, seduced by the fire of his money, can never be at peace in the monastery or live under the rule.
When that demon snatches him away from the fold like a wolf, separating him from the flock to devour him, he then makes sure that the work he neglected at fixed times in the monastery is completed with great eagerness both day and night in his cell.
Nor does he allow him to keep to his prayers, fasting habits, or vigil routines.
Binding him with the madness of greed, he persuades him to devote all his effort and labor to his own work.
There are three ways this sickness manifests, all equally forbidden by the Holy Scriptures and the teachings of the Fathers.
The first, which we wrote about earlier, is when he ensures that the wretched acquire and accumulate what they did not even have in the world.
The second makes those who renounced money regret their decision, persuading them to seek back what they had offered to God.
The third is when he binds a monk initially with the lukewarmness of disbelief, not allowing him to fully renounce worldly things, filling his mind with fear of poverty and distrust in God's providence.
He shows him to be a violator of the promises he made when he renounced the world.
Examples of these three ways are found hidden in Holy Scripture.
For when Gehazi desired money he did not have before, he was deprived of the gift of prophecy, which his master wanted to leave him as an inheritance.
Instead of a blessing, he possessed eternal leprosy through the prophet's curse.
Second Kings 5.
Judas, when he wanted to take back the money he had thrown away to follow the Lord, not only was expelled from the choir of Apostles when he decided to betray the Lord, but he also ended his own life violently.
Matthew 27:5.
Ananias and Sapphira, when they kept back part of what they had consecrated to the Lord, paid the penalty of death with the apostle's words.
Acts 5.
Moses, in the book of Deuteronomy, gives a mystical command to those who are about to renounce the world but still cling to earthly things out of fear:
If a man is fearful and fainthearted, he should not go to war; he should go home and live comfortably there, so that he does not instill fear in the hearts of his brothers.
(Deuteronomy 20:8).
Is there anything more secure and clear than this testimony?
Don’t we learn from these words that when we renounce the world, we must do so completely and proceed to battle, so that we do not, from a soft and corrupt beginning, turn others away from evangelical perfection?
Indeed, it is well said in Scripture, It is more blessed to give than to receive.
(Acts 20:35).
Some interpret this wrongly, twisting the meaning of the letter to their own fraud and greed for money, and distort the Lord’s teaching, which says:
If you want to be perfect, sell all you have and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven; then come, follow me.
(Matthew 19:21).
They judge that having riches is happier than poverty and think that from this abundance they can give to the needy; such people should know that they have not yet renounced the world nor are walking in monastic perfection, as long as they are ashamed to embrace, like the Apostle, the glorious poverty for Christ and to support themselves and the needy by the work of their hands.
If they desire to fulfill the monastic vow in action and receive glory with the Apostle, after distributing their old riches, let them fight the good fight in hunger, thirst, and nakedness with Paul (Second Timothy 4:7).
For if the Apostle himself had considered the possession of old riches necessary for perfection, he would not have despised his former dignity: he indeed testifies that he was a distinguished citizen of Rome (Acts 22:25).
Those who sold their houses and lands in Jerusalem and laid them at the apostles' feet (Acts 4:35) would not have done so if they had known that the apostles considered it happier to be nourished by their own money than by their own labor and the work of their hands.
The Apostle explains this more clearly in his Epistle to the Romans:
"But now I am going to Jerusalem to minister to the saints.
For Macedonia and Achaia have decided to make a contribution for the poor among the saints in Jerusalem"
Romans 15:25.
He was often imprisoned and faced the hardships of travel.
Unable to provide for his own needs as he used to, he received necessities from the brothers in Macedonia, saying:
"For what I lacked, the brothers who came from Macedonia supplied"
Second Corinthians 11:9.
And to the Philippians:
"In the beginning of the Gospel, when no church shared with me in the matter of giving and receiving, except you alone;
because even in Thessalonica you sent me help for my needs once and again"
Philippians 4:15.
Therefore, according to his view, let the greedy be happier than the Apostle; since they are provided with what they need from their own resources.
But no one, unless extremely foolish, would dare to say this.
If we want to follow the evangelical and apostolic command, and the entire Church founded by the apostles from the beginning, let us not follow our own opinions, nor misunderstand what has been clearly stated.
Rejecting a lukewarm and unbelieving attitude, let us diligently study the Gospel.
In this way, we can follow in the footsteps of the holy Fathers, never departing from the knowledge and practice of the monastic life, and truly renouncing this world.
It is worthwhile to recall the words of the holy Fathers in this context.
It is said that Saint Basil, bishop of Caesarea in Cappadocia, addressed a certain senator who had lukewarmly renounced the world, and who had reserved some of his wealth, with these words:
"You have lost the senator, and you have not made a monk."
It is necessary, therefore, to carefully remove from our soul the root and principle of all evils, namely greed.
For it is well known that as long as the root remains, the branches will sprout.
Practicing virtue is difficult unless we live in a monastery, where we do not even worry about necessary things.
Keeping in mind the condemnation of Ananias and Sapphira in Acts chapter 5, let us shudder at the thought of reserving anything for ourselves from old possessions.
Similarly, let us fear the example of Gehazi in Second Kings chapter 5, who was given over to eternal leprosy because of greed.
Let us be careful not to accumulate money for ourselves in this life, which we do not truly possess in this world.
Let us also fear, considering Judas who perished by hanging, that we do not keep anything from all those things we have renounced with contempt.
Keeping all these things in mind, and always aware of the uncertain hour of death, let us be careful that the Lord does not come at an unexpected hour and find our conscience stained with greed.
He might say to us what was said to the rich man in the Gospel:
"Fool, this night your soul is demanded of you; and the things you have prepared, whose will they be?" Luke chapter 12 verse 20.
Cassian, Institutes, Book 8, Chapter 1 and following: Our fourth struggle is against the spirit of anger, so that with God's help we may remove the deadly poison of this vice from the depths of our soul. For, if it is stored within our heart and blinds the eye of the mind with dark disturbances, we will not be able to discern what is appropriate for us. We will not find the comprehension of spiritual knowledge, nor become participants of true life, nor will our mind be capable of divine and true light. For, as it is said, "My eye is troubled by anger" Psalm chapter 6 verse 8.
We will not be partakers of wisdom, even if we seem wise to ourselves, since it is written: Anger resides in the lap of fools; nor can we attain the rays of beneficial discernment, even if we are considered very wise by others, for it is written: Anger destroys even the prudent; nor can we hold the reins of justice with a watchful heart, since it is written: The anger of man does not produce the righteousness of God (James 1:20); nor can we achieve the much-praised modesty and decency, for it is written: An angry man is not modest (Proverbs 11:25).
Therefore, anyone who wishes to reach perfection, who desires to engage in the spiritual contest lawfully, must be free from all sin of anger and rage, and heed what the chosen vessel commands: Let all bitterness and anger and wrath and clamor and slander be put away from you, along with all malice (Ephesians 4:31).
When he says all, he leaves us no occasion for indignation, either as necessary or fitting.
Therefore, whoever wants to correct an erring brother or impose discipline should strive to keep himself free from disturbance and agitation; lest, while trying to heal another, he brings sickness upon himself and is told that gospel saying: Physician, heal yourself (Luke 4:23); and again: Why do you see the speck in your brother's eye, but do not notice the log in your own eye?
Or how can you say to your brother: Let me take the speck out of your eye, when you have a log in your own eye?
(Mark 7:23)
The stirring of anger clouds the eyes of the mind and prevents a person from seeing the Sun of righteousness.
Just as placing gold or lead over the eyes equally impedes the ability to see, and the value of the gold does not make any difference to blindness, so the stirring of anger clouds the soul's ability to see.
We only use indignation according to nature when we direct it against vicious and indulgent thoughts.
The prophet David teaches us this when he says: "Be angry, and do not sin" (Psalm 4:5); that is, direct your anger against your own passions and against evil thoughts so that you do not sin by acting on what they suggest.
This interpretation is made clear by what follows: "Meditate within your heart on your bed, and be still" (Psalm 4:4); when evil thoughts arise in your heart, cast them out by arousing your anger against them.
After they have been cast out, you can reflect and feel remorse, as if resting in a bed.
Blessed Paul agrees with this, using the same testimony and adding: "Do not let the sun go down on your wrath, nor give place to the devil" (Ephesians 4:26); that is, do not consent to evil thoughts, lest the Sun of Righteousness, Christ, sets in your hearts and gives place to the devil.
Concerning this Sun, God says through the prophet: "But to you who fear My name, the Sun of Righteousness shall arise with healing in His wings" (Malachi 4:2).
If we take the Apostle's words literally, we are not even permitted to keep our anger until sunset.
What then shall we say of those who, corrupted by a savage and insane disposition, not only keep their anger until the setting of this sun but also extend it for many days, abstaining from mutual conversation?
They do not express their anger in words but, by maintaining silence towards one another, ignite the poison of remembered injuries to their own ruin.
They do not realize that we must abstain not only from sin committed in action but also from sin conceived in the mind, so that the mind, darkened by the memory of injuries, does not fall away from the light of understanding and discernment and is deprived of the indwelling of the Holy Spirit.
Therefore, the Lord commands in the Gospels to leave your gift at the altar and be reconciled to your brother (Matthew 5:24); because the gift cannot be acceptable if we are occupied with anger and the memory of injuries.
The Apostle instructs us to pray without ceasing and to lift up holy hands everywhere, as stated in First Thessalonians 5:17.
He emphasizes that this should be done without anger, even in our thoughts.
Therefore, we must either avoid prayer altogether, which would go against the apostolic command, or if we aim to follow the commandments, we must do so without anger and without holding grudges.
Often, when our brothers are upset or disturbed, we tend to ignore the situation, claiming it's not our fault.
However, to root out anger from our hearts, the healer of souls commands us not only to reconcile with our brother if we are angry with him, as stated in Matthew 5:4, but also to appease his anger, whether justified or not, before offering our gift.
Why dwell on evangelical and apostolic commandments when we can also learn from the old law?
Although it seems to soften its severity, it states: Do not hate your brother in your heart, as found in Leviticus 19:17.
Furthermore, Proverbs 12:25 warns that the ways of those who hold onto grudges lead to death.
This passage teaches us not only to avoid and punish anger that leads to actions but also to address anger that lingers in our minds.
Therefore, we must adhere to divine laws and strive with all our might against the spirit of anger and the internal strife it causes.
We should not provoke anger in others and seek solitude and separation to practice even-temperedness.
It is often due to pride and our reluctance to blame ourselves for our anger that we wish to be separated from our brothers.
As long as we blame others for our weaknesses, it is impossible to achieve the perfection of even-temperedness.
The true essence of our improvement is not achieved through our neighbor's patience towards us, but through our own patience towards our neighbor and the ability to forget wrongs done to us.
When we avoid the challenge of patience and seek desert and solitude, any unhealed and unsettled passions we bring there remain hidden, not erased.
Indeed, for those who are not yet free from their passions, the desert and seclusion not only preserve their imperfections but also conceal them.
This environment prevents those affected by passions from truly feeling them and instead, they may believe they have achieved patience and humility, as long as no one is present to test them.
However, when an opportunity arises to stir and exercise these passions, the deeply hidden and long-concealed ones, like wild horses bursting out of stables, having been fed by long rest and idleness, throw the rider more violently and fiercely into ruin.
Passions, when not stirred by others, grow fiercer in idleness: and the mere illusion of patience and calmness, which we hold only in fantasy and opinion, dissipates through the idleness of solitude due to the neglect of exercise.
Just as venomous animals, resting in the desert and in their dens, show their fury when someone approaches, so do people affected by passions.
Not out of virtue, but because of the desert's necessary conditions, they spew the poison of their soul when they catch and irritate someone approaching them.
Therefore, those who seek the perfection of meekness should avoid anger not only towards people but also towards animals, and indeed even towards inanimate objects.
I remember when I was living in the desert, I got angry at my pen because sometimes it was too thick, and sometimes too thin.
I also got angry at the wood because I couldn't cut it quickly when I wanted to.
And again, I got angry at the flint for not sparking immediately when I was in a hurry to make a fire.
This shows how anger can flare up even against insensible and inanimate objects.
If we wish to achieve the blessedness of Christ, we must not only control the anger that bursts into action, but also the anger conceived in the mind.
It's not as useful to merely keep our mouths shut and refrain from saying anything furious as it is to cleanse our hearts from the memory of injuries and not to harbor wicked thoughts.
The gospel doctrine teaches that the roots of sins must be cut out rather than just the branches.
Indeed, once the root of anger is cut from the heart, no hatred or envy will reach the point of action: for whoever hates his brother is a murderer, as he kills him with the feeling of hatred.
God sees him as killed: his blood is not shed by a sword for people to see, but he is killed by the feeling of hatred.
Therefore, God will reward or punish each person not only for their deeds but also for their thoughts and intentions, as He says through the prophet: "I come to gather their works, thoughts, and meditations." And again, the Apostle says: "Their thoughts accuse or even defend them on the day when God will judge the secrets of men" (Romans 2:15).
The Lord Himself teaches that we must put away all anger, saying in the Gospels: "Whoever is angry with his brother will be subject to judgment" (Matthew 5:22).
The accurate manuscripts read this way: the word "without cause" is an addition, as is evident from the context of the preceding Scripture. The purpose of the Lord is to have us cut off the root and spark of anger entirely and not to harbor even the slightest occasion for anger within us so that even if we stir up anger for a just reason, we do not fall into the rage of a brute mind.
The complete cure for this sickness is to convince ourselves that it is never okay to stir up our anger, whether for a just or unjust cause.
If the spirit of anger clouds our mind, we will not find the light of discernment or the guidance of right counsel and justice within us.
It is impossible for our soul to become a temple of the Holy Spirit if the spirit of anger dominates.
We must always keep the uncertain hour of death in mind, guard ourselves against anger, and understand that neither asceticism, temperance, the renunciation of all material things, nor fasting and vigils will benefit us if we are seized by anger and hatred and subject to judgment.
May we be freed from this by the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, to whom be glory forever and ever.
Amen.
(Cassian, Institutes, Book 9, Chapter 1 and following.)
Our fifth struggle is against the spirit of sadness, which darkens our soul so that it cannot engage in any spiritual contemplation and holds it back from every good work.
When that wicked spirit seizes and darkens the soul, it does not allow us to offer prayers with eagerness, to engage in the beneficial reading of holy scriptures, or to be gentle and accommodating to our brothers.
It suggests hatred for all works of study and even for the profession of life itself.
Ultimately, sadness confuses all the soul's healthy plans, weakens its firmness and perseverance, makes it seem foolish and stunned, and finally binds it in the thoughts of despair.
Therefore, we should have one goal: to fight the spiritual battle, to conquer the spirit of wickedness with God, and to keep our heart with all vigilance from the spirit of sadness
(Proverbs 4:23).
Just as moths eat away at clothing and worms damage wood, sadness eats away at a person's soul.
It convinces them to avoid good company and prevents them from seeking advice from true friends or responding gently and peacefully.
Instead, sadness disturbs the entire soul and fills it with neglect.
Ultimately, it persuades the person to flee from others, as if they were the cause of their turmoil.
It doesn't allow the person to recognize that the sickness lies within, becoming apparent when faced with overwhelming temptations.
A person is never harmed by another unless they already have an inner sickness, which fuels their passions.
This is why God, the creator of all and the healer of souls, who alone knows our soul's wounds accurately, does not command us to leave human company but to eliminate the causes of evil within us.
He knows that the health of the soul is not obtained by separating from people but by engaging with them and practicing virtue.
So, when we leave our brothers for certain acceptable reasons, we do not cut off occasions for sadness; we only change them, influenced by the inner sickness according to the situation.
Therefore, our entire struggle should be against the inner passions.
With God's help, once these are expelled, not only will we live easily with others, but even with wild animals, according to the saying of the blessed Job: "The wild beasts will be at peace with you" (Job 5:23).
First and foremost, we must fight against the spirit of sadness that drives the soul to despair, casting it out of our hearts.
It was this spirit that prevented Cain from repenting after killing his brother and Judas from repenting after betraying the Lord.
Let us have the kind of sadness that leads to repentance for sins, joined with good hope, which brings the possession of heavenly goods.
About this, the Apostle said: "Godly sorrow brings repentance" (Second Corinthians 7:10).
That sadness, therefore, which nourishes the soul with the hope of repentance, is mixed with joy.
It makes a person cheerful and obedient to every good work, also making them approachable and humble.
Here is one missing page, which continues against the spirit of sadness and begins the discussion on the spirit of sluggishness.
Let's hear how wisely the Apostle shows us the causes of this sluggishness.
He calls those who do not work "disorderly" Second Thessalonians 3:6. With this single word, he reveals much wickedness.
For the idle person becomes reckless with words, quick to insult, and ultimately unfit for a peaceful life, becoming a slave to sluggishness. Therefore, he commands us to withdraw, that is, to separate ourselves from such a person, as if from a harmful disease.
Then what does he say: "And not according to the tradition they received from us" Second Thessalonians 3:6. By this statement, he shows that they are arrogant, despisers, and violators of apostolic traditions.
And again: "Nor did we eat anyone's bread without paying for it, but with labor and toil, working night and day, so as not to be a burden to any of you" Second Thessalonians 3:8.
That teacher of the Gentiles, the preacher of the Gospel, who was taken up to the third heaven Second Corinthians 12:2, who said that the Lord commanded that those who preach the Gospel should live from the Gospel First Corinthians 9:14, worked night and day so as not to burden anyone.
So what will we do, who avoid work due to sluggishness and seek only bodily rest, to whom neither the preaching of the Gospel nor the care of the Churches has been entrusted, but only the care of our own soul?
Then, more clearly showing how much damage comes from idleness, he adds: "Doing nothing but being busybodies" Second Thessalonians 3:11. From idleness comes disorder, and from disorder arises all wickedness.
Then, providing a remedy for this, he says: "To such persons we command and encourage in the Lord Jesus Christ to work quietly and eat their own bread" Second Thessalonians 3:12. With great reproach, he adds: "If anyone is not willing to work, let him not eat" Second Thessalonians 3:10.
Having been instructed by these apostolic precepts, the holy fathers of Egypt never allow monks, especially the younger ones, to be idle even for a brief moment.
They know that through the patience of work, monks can eliminate laziness, provide for their own sustenance, and assist those in need.
Not only do they work for their own needs, but they also provide for travelers, the poor, those imprisoned, and all who are needy from their own labor.
They believe that this duty is a sacrifice acceptable to God.
Furthermore, the Fathers say that he who works fights against one demon and often suffers from it; however, the idle person is captive to countless demons.
It is also worth mentioning what Abbot Moses, one of the most revered Fathers, said to me.
When I had been sitting in the desert for a short time, laziness afflicted me, so I approached him and said:
"I have been severely afflicted by laziness and greatly weakened, and I was not freed from it until I went to see Abbot Paul."
Abbot Moses replied to me:
"Understand that you have not freed yourself from it at all, but rather you have surrendered and become a slave to it. Know, therefore, that you will be more harshly defeated by it as a deserter, unless you strive to fight it through patience, prayer, and manual work."
John Cassian, Institutes, Book 11, Chapter 1 and following.
Our seventh struggle is against the spirit of vain glory, that multifaceted and subtle passion that is not even recognized by the one being tempted. For the outbursts of other passions are more evident and are easier to fight: when the soul recognizes the battle, it overcomes by resisting and praying.
But since the malice of vain glory is multifaceted, as mentioned above, it is difficult to overcome. In every endeavor of man, it presents itself, in appearance, form, gait, speech, vigils, fasting, prayer, reading, rest, and equanimity. Through all these things, it tries to wound the soldier of Christ.
For whoever cannot be deceived by extravagant clothing and led to vain glory, is tempted by the simplicity of clothing.
And whoever could not be led by honor is inflated to foolishness by the patience of disgrace.
Whoever could not be led to vain glory by knowledge is tempted to deceit by silence, as if he were a quiet man.
Whoever could not be drawn to softness by the luxury of food is led to the desire for praise by fasting.
Finally, every work, every effort provides an occasion for this demon to attack.
To those who are attacked by him, sometimes they imagine themselves to be of sacred order.
I remember an old man, who, while I was living in Scete, went to visit a brother’s cell.
As he approached the door of the cell, he heard him talking inside.
When the old man thought he was reciting something from Scripture, he stood to listen and sensed that the brother was raving in vain glory, ordaining himself a deacon, and giving dismissal to catechumens.
When the old man heard this, he finally opened the door and entered.
The brother, meeting him as usual, greeted him and asked if he had been standing at the door for long.
The old man gently replied, “I just arrived,” he said, “when you were giving dismissal to the catechumens.
” Having heard this, the brother fell at the old man’s feet to ask for prayers for deliverance from such error.
I remember this event to show into what foolishness this demon can throw a man.
Therefore, whoever wishes to fight perfectly and be crowned with the crown of justice, should strive by every means to overcome this many-formed beast, always keeping in mind the saying of Saint David: “The Lord has scattered the bones of those who please men” (Psalm 53:6).
Let him do nothing with a view to human praise, but seek a reward from God, and always reject thoughts of personal praise that invade his heart.
Let him despise himself in the sight of God.
In this way, with God’s help, he can be liberated from the demon of vain glory, by the grace of our Lord Jesus, to whom be glory forever.
Amen.
(Cassian, Institutes, Book 12, Chapter 1 and following)
The eighth struggle we face is against the spirit of pride, which is more serious and harsher than all the others.
It attacks those who are nearly perfect and strives to bring them down.
Like a deadly disease, it doesn't just affect a part of the body but destroys the whole being.
Other passions, while they disturb the soul, only combat one virtue at a time and thus obscure and trouble the soul partially.
However, the passion of pride casts the entire soul into darkness and leads it to complete ruin.
To understand this more clearly, let's examine it in this way.
The vice of gluttony tries to corrupt abstinence; fornication attacks continence; greed undermines poverty; wrath challenges gentleness; and other kinds of malice oppose specific virtues.
But when the malice of pride rules a wretched soul, it acts like a most ferocious tyrant who, having captured a large and lofty city, destroys it completely and overturns it from its foundations.
An example of this is the angel who fell from heaven because of pride.
Created by God and adorned with all virtue and wisdom, he did not want to attribute these to God's grace but to his own nature, thinking himself equal to God.
The prophet rebukes this thought, saying: "You said in your heart: 'I will sit on a high mountain, I will place my throne above the clouds, and I will be like the Most High'" (Isaiah 14:13).
But you are a man, not God (Isaiah 31:3).
Another prophet says: "Why do you boast in evil, mighty one?" and shortly after: "You loved all words of ruin, a deceitful tongue. Therefore, God will destroy you forever; he will uproot you and tear you from your tent, and your root from the land of the living. The righteous will see and fear, and will laugh at him, saying: 'Here is the man who did not make God his helper, but trusted in his great wealth and grew strong by destroying others'" (Psalm 52).
Knowing these things, let us be afraid and guard our hearts with all diligence (Proverbs).
To guard against the deadly spirit of pride, we remind ourselves of the Apostle's words when we accomplish any virtuous deed: "Not I, but the grace of God that is with me" First Corinthians 15:10. Remember also what the Lord has said: "Without Me you can do nothing" John 15:5, and what the prophet has declared: "Unless the Lord builds the house, those who build it labor in vain" Psalm 127:1. Additionally, "It is not of him who wills, nor of him who runs, but of God who shows mercy" Romans 9:16.
Even if someone is eager and diligent, if they are entangled in flesh and blood, they cannot achieve perfection unless they place their hope in the mercy and grace of Christ. As the divine James states: "Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, coming down from the Father of lights" James 1:17. And Paul reminds us: "What do you have that you did not receive? And if you received it, why do you boast as if you did not receive it?" First Corinthians 4:7.
You boast as if these gifts were your own, not someone else's. The fact that salvation comes to us by the grace and mercy of God is shown by the thief who gained the kingdom of heaven not as a reward for virtue, but by the grace and mercy of God Luke 23:43.
Understanding this well, our fathers unanimously believed that we cannot lay a firm foundation for the perfection of virtue without humility, which comes from faith, gentleness, and perfect poverty. Through these, perfect charity is obtained by the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, to whom, with the Father and the Holy Spirit, be glory forever. Amen.