A Brief Exposition on the Ancient Gallican Liturgy
by Germanus, Bishop of Paris
Introduction
After our forefathers abolished the ancient Gallican Liturgy of our Church and replaced it with the Roman Mass, it quickly became so dominant that within a few years, almost all memory of the Gallican Liturgy seemed to vanish, and its name was barely known by anyone.
Therefore, writers who dealt with liturgical matters in our time took it upon themselves to revive it from the obscurity it had fallen into.
The first to attempt this, and not without due praise, was the late pious Cardinal Bona in the first book of his "Rerum Liturgicarum", chapter 12, where he presents traces of the ancient Gallican rites from old writings.
However, these were slight given the importance and significance of the matter.
The task was much more successfully carried out by the very learned Joseph Thomasius, who published three ancient Codices of the Gallican Liturgy in Rome from the library of the Queen of Sweden, later reprinted in Paris by Mabillon with an old Gallican Lectionary he found in the monastery of Luxueil, and illustrated with learned observations.
He also made the fourth Codex of the Gallican Liturgy from the Bobbio library public in the first volume of the Italian Museum.
However, in all these books, we have only one main thing: to know the prayers that the priest celebrating at the altar would recite, along with the readings that the sacred ministers would announce to the people.
But what the choir would sing in the meantime, or in what order, has so far been hidden from us.
Some have tried to demonstrate this using the authority of the ancients, but almost entirely in vain.
For not only did they fail in many aspects, but they also made mistakes in some.
The benefit that arises from the following Exposition of the ancient Gallican Liturgy is that we fully understand its entire order and what was sung in the choir.
First, the Liturgy began with an antiphon, which the choir would chant along with a verse of the psalm and the glory of the Trinity.
The antiphon was followed by a preface or admonition to the people, which the priest would read aloud to encourage the congregation to celebrate the solemnity with due reverence.
Although some include the angelic hymn to be sung by the choir between the antiphon and the preface, this lacks authoritative basis.
The passages from Gregory of Tours cited to prove this do not establish anything conclusively but show that the hymn was sung in other public supplications.
In the Gallican Liturgy, published by Mabillon from the Bobbio Codex, the hymn Glory to God in the highest is designated to be recited privately after Mass as a thanksgiving.
Therefore, the antiphon was followed by the preface or reading, and in our subsequent Exposition, it is called the Antiphon for Reading, which precedes the preface the priest would read as an exhortation.
After the preface, the deacon would call for silence in a loud voice, a rite mentioned by Gregory of Tours in Book Seven of History of the Franks, Chapter Eight, with these words: "So it happened that on a certain Sunday, after the deacon had called for silence to the people so that the Mass could be listened to," etc. Here, "Mass" refers to prayers.
Once silence was called, the priest would greet the people, and to the people's response, he would add a collect to be devoutly listened to by all while kneeling, as evidenced by certain sermons of Saint Caesarius.
After the collect, the choir would sing the Trisagion, both in Greek and Latin, followed by the Song of Zechariah, "Blessed be the Lord, the God of Israel." However, during Lent, this song and other hymns of joy were omitted.
This was followed by readings from the Prophets and the Apostle. Besides the reading of the Gospel, two readings were sung, one from the Old Testament and one from the New Testament. This rite is seen in Gregory of Tours' Book One on the Miracles of Saint Martin, Chapter Five, where it states: "It happened that on that Sunday, after the prophetic reading had been read, he stood before the altar who would read the lesson of the blessed Paul."
During the festivals of the saints, whether martyrs or confessors, their acts were publicly read to inspire people to perform similar deeds by hearing about their virtues.
Gregory of Tours, in Book 1 of "The Glory of the Martyrs," chapter 86, narrates that the passion of Saint Polycarp was read.
After the readings, the choir would chant the hymn of the three boys, likely in the manner of a responsory. Gregory of Tours, in "History of the Franks," Book 8, chapter 3, refers to this hymn as a responsorial psalm. The ancients often called any song from the Scriptures a psalm. I believe canon 13 of the Fourth Council of Toledo pertains to this ritual, stating that in all the churches of Spain or Gaul, during the solemnities of all Masses, the hymn of the three boys should be chanted from the pulpit.
While the deacon proceeded to the ambo to sing the Gospel, the choir would chant the Trisagion, repeating it after the Gospel was sung.
After the Gospel, the bishop would deliver a sermon from the pulpit. If he was unable due to poor health or slower speech, he would have homilies-either his own or those composed by others, especially the holy Fathers-pronounced by priests or deacons.
Then the deacon would offer the designated prayers over the listeners and catechumens, as discussed in Book 1 on the ancient rites of the Church.
Once the catechumens were dismissed, the deacon would call for silence. He would then bring the body of the Lord, kept in the tower from the previous sacrifice, to the altar. This is evident from our exposition and from Gregory of Tours' book "The Glory of the Martyrs," chapter 85. The Romans would bring it from a chest, a practice also observed in some Gallican churches.
Moreover, from this ritual, we can shed some light on Canon 17 of the First Council of Orange, which almost all scholars have misunderstood until now.
When the box and cup are to be offered and consecrated with the mixture of the Eucharist, the box containing the Lord's body should be brought to the altar when the offering of the cup with the mixture or presence of the Eucharist to be consecrated is to be made in the mass.
When the Eucharist was brought to the altar, the offering of the bread and wine to be consecrated was made, and during this time, the choir sang the Sound, which is the antiphon corresponding to our offertory, or something similar.
Perhaps the Sound was nothing other than what our Exposition soon calls the Lauds.
However, in the Mozarabic Missal, the Lauds consist of an Alleluia and one verse, but in the Gallican Liturgy, the Alleluia was repeated three times to signify the three periods: before the law, under the law, and under grace, as our Exposition teaches, perhaps with a triple verse.
After the offering, the sacred diptychs were recited, which are the names of bishops and others written on a tablet placed on the altar.
I saw such an ivory tablet in the church in Bourges, which contains the names of archbishops, but today no such use remains in Bourges.
After reciting the diptychs, the priest said the Collect after the names, then the faithful exchanged the kiss of peace among themselves.
Then the priest recited the Collect for peace, followed by the contestation (which they called the preface) and the canon, which was very brief.
After the consecration, the priest recited the Prayer After the Secret, which shows that the words of consecration were spoken by the priest in secret and silence.
Then the breaking and mixing of the body of Christ was done.
In the meantime, the choir sang the antiphon, and when it was finished, the priest recited the Collect before the Lord's Prayer, followed by another Collect pronounced by the priest.
Before communion, a blessing was given to the people.
This was done with three prayers by the bishop, or with a single brief one by a simple priest, expressed like this:
Peace, faith, love, and the sharing of the body and blood of the Lord be with you always.
During communion, or after it was finished, the choir would sing the Trecanum.
However, I don't fully understand what the Trecanum was.
The word's etymology suggests it might be a triple chant.
According to the rule of Saint Aurelian, everyone was supposed to participate by singing.
Some might interpret the Trecanum as the Apostles' Creed, which explains the faith in the Holy Trinity.
In the Mozarabic Missal, it is prescribed to be said after consecration and before communion, but in the Gallican Liturgy, it was recited after communion.
Finally, the priest would say the Prayer After the Eucharist, followed by another collect.
These are most of the parts of the ancient Gallican Liturgy, which I briefly present and illustrate here to help you understand the following work.
In the second part or letter, many other noteworthy things occur, especially those concerning Lent and the tradition of the creed to the catechumens, where previously unknown rites are examined.
However, beyond the knowledge of ancient rites that we gain from the following work, there is something of far greater importance.
Two principal dogmas of the Catholic Church concerning the Eucharist are clearly asserted in it.
These are Transubstantiation and the real presence of Christ under the appearances of bread and wine: these two are especially under attack today by the heterodox.
The first is clearly stated in these words: The bread is truly transformed into the body, and the wine into the blood, with the Lord saying about his body: My flesh is true food, and my blood is true drink.
The second part says:
In ancient times, it happened to the holy Fathers that while the priest was breaking the offering, it seemed as if an angel of God was cutting the limbs of a shining boy with a knife and collecting his blood in a chalice, so that the words of the Lord saying his flesh is food and his blood is drink would be more true.
Now, let's briefly discuss the author of this work and the time it was written.
As for the author, since the old manuscript of Saint Martin of Autun from which we copied it does not bear his name, we cannot definitively say anything; we can only offer conjectures.
At the beginning, it reads: Germanus, Bishop of Paris, wrote about the Mass.
Therefore, we believe this is either the work of Germanus or an epitome of his more extensive work, written by one of his disciples, and perhaps at the monastery of Saint Symphorian in Autun, where he lived a monastic life before being elevated to the bishopric of Paris.
Regarding the time this exposition of the Gallican Mass was written, two things seem certain to me.
First, that it was after Germanus was appointed to the seat of Paris;
second, that it was before the ancient liturgy of our fathers in the Gallican Churches was abolished, which happened immediately after the Roman Mass was introduced in its place.
This was done by Charlemagne, encouraged by Pope Adrian, as commonly taught by those who have written more accurately about these matters, that is, at the end of the eighth century.
However, referring this writing to the times of Bishop Germanus is supported by the fact that after reading the homilies of the holy Fathers, it mentions prayers made by the deacon over the catechumens before their and the infidels' expulsion from the church, a rite that barely reached the times of Germanus.
Therefore, we believe that the following work was written at least in the middle of the sixth century, whose unrefined writing style and barbaric words demonstrate its antiquity; hence, we refrained from correcting anything in them.
A Brief Explanation of the Ancient Gallican Liturgy, Divided into Two Letters.
First Letter
This is how the solemn order of the Church is carried out, and with what instructions the ecclesiastical canon is adorned.
First Letter,
Germanus, Bishop of Paris, wrote about the Mass:
Therefore, the first and greatest of all gifts, the Mass, is sung in remembrance of the Lord's death,
because Christ's death became the life of the world,
so that by offering it, it may benefit the salvation of the living and the rest of the dead.
On Reading Aloud.
An antiphon will be sung before the reading, just as the patriarchs who lived before the flood foretold the coming of Christ with mystical voices.
Like Enoch, the seventh from Adam, who was taken by God and prophesied, saying:
"Behold, the Lord comes with His holy ones to execute judgment" (Jude, 14).
This testimony is recalled by Jude the apostle, brother of James, in his letter.
Just as the hand of the Lord came upon the prophets, so that they would leave remnants of the earth in the condemned; so, as the clerics chant, the priest proceeds in the likeness of Christ from the sanctuary as if from heaven into the ark of the Lord, which is the Church, to both admonish and encourage the people to cultivate good works and extinguish evil ones.
On Silence
The deacon calls for silence for two reasons: first, so that everyone can hear the word of God more clearly, and second, to free our hearts from impure thoughts, allowing us to better receive God's word.
The priest addresses the congregation with, "The Lord be with you always," and the response, "And with your spirit," makes him more worthy to bless the people, as he receives the blessing from the entire congregation, with God's favor.
On Aius
Aius is sung in Greek before the prophecy because the New Testament was spread throughout the world in Greek, except for the Apostle Matthew, who first published the Gospel of Christ in Hebrew in Judea.
Therefore, respect the language that first received the Gospel of Christ in its old age or taught the first hymn in its letters.
When the leader of the Church begins, Aius sings in both Latin and Greek to show the union of the Old and New Testaments.
The word "Amen" is said in Hebrew, just like the title that Pilate placed above the cross, inspired by God, confessing, although unknowingly, "Jesus of Nazareth," which means "Holy and King."
The three little ones who follow, saying "Kyrie eleison" in Hebrew, Greek, and Latin, represent the three ages of the world: before the law, under the law, and under grace.
On Prophecy.
The song of Zechariah, the high priest, honors Saint John the Baptist because the beginning of salvation starts with the sacrament of baptism, which John administers through God's gift.
As the shadow of the old fades and the brightness of the new Gospel rises, John is the last of the prophets and the first of the evangelists.
He shone like a lamp before the true Light.
Therefore, the prophecy his father sang at his birth is sung by the church with alternating voices.
On the Prophet and the Apostle.
The prophetic readings, especially from the Old Testament, reprove wrongs and announce the future.
This helps us understand that the same God who thundered in prophecy also taught through the Apostle and shone in the splendor of the Gospel.
On the Apostle
What the prophet foretells will happen, the apostle teaches has already occurred.
The Acts of the Apostles or the Revelation of John are read during the joyous celebration of Easter.
This follows the sequence of events, similar to the Old Testament history during Pentecost, or the stories of holy confessors and martyrs on their feast days.
This helps people understand how much Christ loved his servant, showing a sign of virtue, whom the devout faithful ask to be their patron.
On the Hymn
The hymn of the three young men, sung after the reading, symbolizes the holy ones of old who sat in darkness awaiting the coming of the Lord.
Just as the fourth angel came to them in a cloud of dew, overcoming the fires while they were silent, so too did the Son of God, the Angel of Great Counsel, appear to those awaiting Christ.
He shattered the powers of hell, bringing them the joy of resurrection, as the Evangelist teaches.
In this way, the church also maintains the order: between the blessing and the Gospel, a reading intercedes, unless only a responsory is sung by the little ones.
This resembles the innocent ones mentioned in the Gospel who are read about at the birth of Christ, or those little ones who, as the Lord hastened to His passion, cried out in the temple, "Hosanna to the Son of David."
As the Psalmist sings, "Out of the mouths of infants and nursing babies you have perfected praise" (Psalm 8:3).
On AIUS BEFORE THE GOSPEL.
Then, at the arrival of the holy Gospel, with a clear melody, the clergy once again sings AIUS in the form of angels before the face of Christ, crying out at the gates of hell:
"Lift up your heads, O gates, and be lifted up, O ancient doors, and the King of glory shall come in."
Psalm 24:7
On the Gospel.
The procession of the Holy Gospel goes forth like the power of Christ triumphing over death.
With the aforementioned harmonies, and with seven candleholders of light, which are the seven gifts of the Holy Spirit, or the five lights of the law fixed to the mystery of the cross, ascending to the platform of the pulpit, like Christ to the throne of the Father's kingdom.
From there, the gifts of life resound, with the clerics shouting "Glory to you, Lord," in the manner of the angels who, at the birth of the Lord, sang "Glory to God in the highest" (Luke 2:14) to the shepherds appearing.
On the Holy Hymn after the Gospel
The holy hymn that the clergy sing when the holy gospel returns is reminiscent of the saints, who sang a song of praise to the Lord when Jesus Christ returned from the dead.
It also brings to mind the seventy-four elders mentioned by John in the Book of Revelation, who, throwing their crowns before the Lamb, sang a sweet song.
On the Homilies
The homilies of the saints that are read are provided specifically for preaching.
This way, whatever the prophet, Apostle, or Gospel commanded, the teacher or pastor of the Church can convey to the people in clearer language.
It's about balancing the art so that the simplicity doesn't offend the wise, and the refined speech doesn't become obscure to the simple.
On prayer.
About prayer.
The practice of deacons praying for the people originates from the books of Moses.
When they hear the apostles' preaching, the deacons pray for the people, and the priests, prostrated before the Lord, intercede for the sins of the people.
As the Lord said to Aaron:
"You and your sons or the entire tribe of Levi will bear the sins of my people, not by enduring punishment, but by alleviating them through prayers."
On the Catechumen.
The deacon calls out the catechumen according to the ancient rite of the church.
Jews, heretics, or pagans who were being instructed and came for baptism were tested before being baptized.
They would stand in the church and listen to the teachings of the Old and New Testament.
Afterwards, the deacons would pray for them, the priest would say the collect, and after the prayer, they would leave.
They were not deemed worthy to stay while the offering was being brought in, so they would listen outside the door, prostrated on the ground.
It was the responsibility of the deacon or the doorkeeper to remind them to leave and to ensure that no one unworthy remained in the temple, saying, "Do not give what is holy to dogs, nor cast your pearls before swine."
For what on earth is holier than the making of the body and blood of Christ? And what is more unclean than a dog and a pig? This refers to those who have not been cleansed by baptism or have not been marked by the sign of the cross.
We are spiritually commanded to maintain silence, watching at the door. This means placing the sign of the cross before our face, refraining from the tumult of words or sins. In this way, desire does not enter through the eyes, anger through the ears, and no foul word comes out of the lips. The heart should intend solely to receive Christ within itself.
On Sound
The sound that is played when the offering is presented originates from here.
The Lord commanded Moses to make silver trumpets, which the Levites would blow when the sacrifice was offered.
This was the signal for the people to understand it was time for the offering, and they would bow down to worship the Lord until the pillar of fire or cloud appeared to bless the sacrifice.
Now, however, as the body of Christ proceeds to the altar, it is not accompanied by silver trumpets, but by the sweet melodies of spiritual voices singing the glorious deeds of Christ in the Church.
The body of the Lord is carried in towers, symbolizing how the Lord's tomb was cut into a rock like a tower, with a bed inside where His body rested, from which the King of Glory rose in triumph.
The blood of Christ is offered in a chalice because the Eucharist was consecrated in such a vessel the day before the Lord suffered, when He said, "This is the chalice of my blood, the mystery of faith, which will be poured out for many for the forgiveness of sins" (Matthew 26:28).
The bread is transformed into His body and the wine into His blood, with the Lord saying, "For my flesh is true food, and my blood is true drink" (John 6:55).
He said of the bread, "This is my body," and of the wine, "This is my blood" (Matthew 26:26).
Water is mixed in either because it signifies the union of the people with the Lord or because blood and water flowed from Christ's side on the cross, cleansing us from the stain of sins and preparing us for the kingdom of heaven.
The plate on which the offering is consecrated is called the "patena" because the Eucharist is offered in remembrance of the Lord's passion.
The linen cloth called the "palla" represents the undivided garment of Christ, woven in a circle by soldiers.
The corporal cloth is pure linen on which the offering is placed, symbolizing how the body of the Lord was wrapped in pure linen with spices in the tomb.
Covered by the sacraments, it is adorned because the resurrection of Christ surpasses all decorations, or the vault of heaven which now hides the Lord from our eyes.
Silk is adorned with gold or gems because the Lord commanded Moses to make the coverings in the tabernacle out of gold, blue, and purple, twice-dyed scarlet, and twisted fine linen; because all those mysteries foreshadowed the wounds of Christ.
The praises, that is, Alleluia, John heard being sung in the Apocalypse after the resurrection.
Therefore, at that hour, the Lord's pall is lifted as if Christ is covered by the sky.
The Church is accustomed to the angelic song: and the Alleluia itself, first, second, and third, signifies the three periods: before the law, under the law, and under grace.
The names of the deceased are recited at that hour when the pall is lifted because then there will be the resurrection of the dead when Christ comes, and heaven will be folded up as it wishes.
They proclaim the peace of Christ to each other so that through a mutual kiss they may hold onto the affection of charity, and anyone stained by discord may quickly return to grace, or ask their neighbor for forgiveness, lest by giving false peace they incur the company of the traitor.
The Eucharist received or blessing given may better progress as Christ sees their hearts are peaceful, because he commanded his disciples while ascending to heaven, "Peace I leave with you, my peace I give to you" (John 14:27), and in this, all will know that you are my disciples if you love one another.
The priest admonishes to lift up our hearts so that no earthly thought remains in our hearts at the hour of the sacred offering, and Christ may be better received in our minds as our thoughts strive to attend to him alone.
The breaking and mixing of the Lord's body was declared by the Holy Fathers in ancient times with such great mysteries that while the priest was breaking the offering, it seemed as if the Angel of God were cutting the limbs of a shining child with a knife, and collecting his blood in the chalice, so that they might more truly say, as the Lord said, that his flesh is food and his blood is drink.
During the breaking of the bread, the priest seeks to elevate the ceremony, blending the heavenly with the earthly.
Through the priest's prayer, the heavens open.
As the priest performs the breaking, the clergy humbly sing the antiphon, recognizing the profound impact of Christ's suffering and death.
The Lord's Prayer is included to encompass all our prayers.
God commanded Moses to instruct the priests to bless the people, saying: Speak to Aaron and his sons; thus you shall bless the people: The Lord bless you and keep you.
Aaron represented Christ, and his sons symbolized the priests.
Although both were commanded to bless the people, the sacred canons upheld the bishop's honor by assigning him the longer blessing, while the priest gives a shorter one, saying: Peace, faith, and charity, and the sharing of the body and blood of the Lord be with you always.
The blessing given to Moses by God stands unchallenged by the priest; for heaven and earth will pass away.
This blessing is given before communion, so the mystery of blessing enters the blessed vessel.
Christ reveals the sweetness of holy communion of soul and body through his words in the Gospel: If you remain in me, and my words remain in you, whatever you ask the Father in my name, it will be given to you.
The Trisagion that is sung symbolizes the Catholic faith, rooted in the belief in the Trinity.
The first in the second, the second in the third, and the third in the second illustrate the mystery of the Trinity.
The Father is in the Son, the Son in the Holy Spirit, the Holy Spirit in the Son, and the Son again in the Father.
Let this epistle conclude, showcasing the solemn Order, so that in the next epistle, the common office may be revealed to all, by the Lord's gift.
Who lives.
Here begins the second letter on the common office.
Since, with the Lord's favor, we briefly explained the order of the sacred offering in the previous letter, let us now outline the various gifts of the Church and how they persist, according to what the Lord has granted us to understand.
The antiphons that the Church sings with sweet ceremony originated from here.
When King Solomon built the magnificent house, he established singers who, with various instruments, sang of God's great deeds.
Among the other ornaments that shone in the temple, divine words would also be uttered sweetly, making God's word more delightful the more elegantly it was adorned by the voice.
Singing in the church is established not because of a carnal custom, but for a spiritual reason, so that those who are not moved by words might be moved by the sweetness of the melody.
Consider how great the sweetness of the heavenly song is, when in this world's dwelling, the Church so elegantly resounds with the praises of Christ.
The antiphon is called so because it is placed first, and then the verse of the psalm follows, with the glory of the Trinity being added.
There are four types of these: composed with the prophetic organ, with the sacred thunder of the gospel tympanum, or with the compassion of the Catholic Fathers according to the order of times, either by petitioning, narrating, or drumming divine praises.
The responsories, which are sung in divine offices day or night, originated from the Pentateuch of Moses.
When, after Pharaoh was drowned, Miriam the prophetess took up a timpani, leading the song, and the gathered people responded in chorus.
The rationale for these is also fourfold, as mentioned above regarding the antiphons.
The custom of leading and responding is shown not only at the Red Sea but among many nations of the Hebrews, as the history of the Old Testament narrates more fully.
Holy God of the archangels is sung on the fortieth day and not the song of Zechariah, because this modulation is an entreaty for the people, as the words of its text contain.
Because of this, prophecy will not be sung, and the baptistery will be closed, specifically because the canon instructs that baptism does not occur during Lent.
The oil blessed with chrism is referenced in the voice of the psalm, which speaks of Christ in Psalm 45:8: "God has anointed you with the oil of joy above your companions," and also in Psalm 89:21: "I have found David, my servant; with my holy oil I have anointed him."
First, they were anointed with the oil of the old, then ointment was poured over them. In Greek, oil is called "mercy" in Latin, symbolizing the grace of the Holy Spirit. God consecrated this liquid in the Church to create mystical ointments, prepare lamps, and heal the wounds of sins.
The Creed will also be given on the appointed day to the competent, just as God said, "Let there be light," signifying the illumination of belief.
On the seventh day, He blessed and sanctified it in rest; therefore, on this day, the faith of the people is strengthened. The creed and the milk of chrism nourish, as Christ's rest in the tomb is honored, and as the day declines, it consecrates the triumph of His resurrection.
When the priest comes to deliver the creed, it is spread over the chancel with soft feathers or white cloths, and the vessels of the chalice with chrism and oil to be blessed are brought, or the sacred book of the Gospel covered with a red veil. This symbolizes the people coming to faith as infants, tender and new in body, just as the catechumen is tender and new in faith.
The infant's limbs are placed on soft cushions to be better nourished. Similarly, gentle words of the Lord are spoken to the catechumen to delight him, as he cannot bear stronger precepts until he is confirmed in grace by the baptism of the Holy Spirit.
The limbs of the little one are wiped with a white, soft linen cloth to protect his skin. Likewise, the subtlety of faith is revealed to the catechumen in the creed, so that through belief he may be cleansed of all sin. First, he is anointed with gentle precepts to avoid exasperation in understanding.
By stronger commands, so that he may recover through works.
An infant is nourished by milk, and the catechumens will be anointed with chrism.
The milk is sucked from the mother's breast, and the chrism is consecrated in the bosom of the holy mother Church.
The Book of the Gospel is covered with a red veil, symbolizing the blood and the body of Christ.
In the chalice, the vessels of chrism are carried because all the sacraments of baptism are strengthened by the passion of Christ.
The glass or crystal vessels of chrism signify the clarity of baptism.
Moreover, the chrism is made from balsam.
The lentisk is a type of wood from which the resin of balsam is taken; it is said that a part of this lentisk was used for the Lord's cross, where the impious nailed the holy hands of the Lord.
Therefore, the resin of that wood has been distributed since ancient times and will continue to be.
Indeed, the angel of God descends to the secrets above the altar, as if over the tomb, and blesses the host itself, like the angel who announced the resurrection of Christ.
Then, with a free tongue and a clear voice, all the songs that were kept in silence during Lent are taken up.
We sing about the drowning of Pharaoh, the Holy One from the heavens, and alleluia with joy because the Lord has risen.
This is completed in the office at midnight because at midnight the Savior broke into hell.
Then the flesh of the Lamb is eaten by the faithful, and the blood is sweetly drunk, through which the whole world is redeemed at a precious price.
It is immediately taught that at the dawn of the coming day, the praise of the Lord's resurrection should be celebrated with clear songs and blessings.
The pallium, however, is veiled with bells at Easter, much like in the Old Testament, where the priest's tunic, full of bells, signifies the words of preaching.
The girding of the white garment that the priest wears when baptizing signifies Saint John, who girded himself and baptized the Lord.
Moreover, the white garments are worn at Easter just as the angel at the tomb was seen in white garments.
The white garment signifies exultation.
The outer garment, known as the chasuble, worn by the priest, symbolizes unity and traces back to Moses the lawgiver.
The Lord commanded the creation of a unique garment for the priest, distinguishing him from the people.
It has no sleeves because the priest's role is to bless rather than serve.
Its seamless design represents the many sacred mysteries in the Scriptures that a knowledgeable priest should keep concealed, protecting the unity of the faith and avoiding heresy or schism.
The pallium, extending from the neck to the chest, was known as the rational in the Old Testament, symbolizing holiness upon the memory of the heart, with the prophet speaking from the Lord's perspective, "The Spirit of the Lord is upon me."
And a little later, "to give them a crown of beauty instead of ashes, the oil of joy instead of mourning" (Isaiah 61:3).
The pallium signifies praises instead of a spirit of despair.
Encircling the neck, it follows an ancient tradition where both kings and priests were adorned with a shining garment, prefiguring grace.
The fringes on the priestly garments were commanded by the Lord to Moses in the Book of Numbers, so the sons of Israel would have fringes on the corners of their garments, serving as a sign of God's commandments in both their actions and attire.
The maniple, a type of sleeve, is traditionally worn by priests, similar to the bracelets worn by kings or priests.
They are made from any precious fabric, not hard metal, so all priests, regardless of worldly status, can easily obtain them.
This small garment, used only during the celebration of the sacrifice, signifies that our hands should not be burdened with worldly honors but should focus on the delicate tasks of God's commandments.
The tunic's sleeve ensures that the garment remains pristine and pure, preventing any unworthy touch of impurities on the divine sacrifices, through which the hands that offer the sacrifice move.
Albs, which deacons wear, were established by the fathers because stains don't show up as quickly on dyed garments as they do on white ones.
The minister of the altar uses them to observe and avoid any stain, ensuring that the garments of those serving remain clean even with a light touch.
These garments should be white on the outside and pure in mind on the inside.
They are made of silk or wool because the Lord commanded priests to use these materials to symbolize the hope of resurrection.
Silk is made from wood through a worm, which changes into a winged creature after death.
This symbolizes Christ, who, after resting in the tomb like a worm enclosed in a small sack, rose from the grave and ascended to the heavens.
The white wool garments symbolize the innocence of life.
The alb isn't fastened with a belt but hangs down, covering the deacon's body, because all Levitical conduct should be directed toward the heavenly homeland, free from earthly works, and not constrained by the belt of sins.
The stole that the deacon wears over the alb signifies the subtle understanding of divine mysteries.
Traditionally, wearing the stole indicated the joy of celebration.
For this reason, during Lent, it is not used as a sign of humility, just as "Alleluia," "Sanctus," and the songs of the three youths in the furnace or the song of the Red Sea are not sung in our Church during those days.
The angel appeared wearing a white stole while sitting at the Lord's tomb, announcing the solemnity of His resurrection. Therefore, during Lent, these songs are prohibited because they are heavenly and angelic. From heaven, a pillar of fire was seen at night, and a pillar of cloud by day, and the angel was heard in the fiery furnace. Thus, "Alleluia" and "Sanctus" are silent in penance, to be renewed in the Lord's Resurrection when baptism is also renewed. Therefore, the deacon should sing the heavenly song.