Explanation of Solomon's Chariot
by Hincmar of Reims
This royal chariot, which holy teachers say represents the Church, that is, the body of Christ, in whose unity each person is incorporated into Christ through faith, as we have shown above, is called by many names in Scripture: such as the Kingdom of Heaven, woman, bride, wife, dove, beloved, vineyard, sheep, fold, city, tower, pillar, foundation, house, temple, body of Christ, fullness of Christ, net, wedding, feast, and others that the reader may find.
King Solomon, meaning peaceful, Idida, meaning beloved of the Lord, Coeleth, meaning preacher of the Church itself, made this for himself.
Solomon was called by these three names because the entire Holy Trinity built the temple of the true Solomon, that is, the body of God and the Mediator of humans, in the womb of the blessed and glorious and ever-virgin mother and our lady and mistress Mary.
For the Holy Spirit came upon her, and the power of the Most High Father overshadowed her: and thus everything that was born from her, in two substances and natures in the unity of one person, is called holy, and is the Son of God, through whom glory is sung to God in the highest, and peace is on earth for people of good will; who is the beloved Son in whom the Father is well pleased, and from whose face comes knowledge and understanding, and who teaches humans knowledge, and through His Holy Spirit teaches the Church all truth.
This King of Kings and Lord of Lords made this chariot for himself from the woods of Lebanon, because he built the Church from souls strong in spirit and steadfast in heart.
The woods of Lebanon excel in height, appearance, and their incorruptible nature.
These rational and fruitful trees excel in many virtues, not by their own power, but by the grace of God.
He composed these trees into the structure of the Church through His gracious predestination and election, freely given.
He desires all men to be saved and does not want anyone to perish.
Just as He made Eve from the rib of the sleeping Adam in paradise, so, with ineffable mercy, He built the Church while sleeping on the cross, pouring out water and blood from His side to both cleanse and nourish.
He cleanses with the washing of water through the word and redeems with His precious blood, as the spotless and unblemished lamb, Christ Jesus Himself.
He sanctifies with His Holy Spirit, saving individuals who suffered for all, the whole man, both body and soul.
This happens on the Sabbath, in the rest of the unity of the Church, where the faithful strive for eternal rest through saving hope; for we are saved by hope.
The columns of this dish are two: the crowds who preceded and those who follow the coming of the Lord.
Through the faith of the Mediator Himself, the peaceful king and builder of the dish, they are saved and being saved.
They cry out with the confession of one belief, saying Hosanna.
As Peter says, "For by the grace of the Lord Jesus, we believe to be saved just as they are" (Acts 15:11).
Alternatively, the two columns of the dish represent those who persevere in the unity of the present Church with right faith and good works.
In the future, in the eternal Church, they will be filled and glorified, rejoicing without end in the inexpressible exultation of the incorruption of both soul and body.
Because God has arranged everything with measure-where quality is established, in number where quantity is contained, and in weight where balanced reason is signified-the souls of the chosen receive the weight of virtue, not of burden, by His arrangement.
According to Job, He assigned weight to the winds
Job
so that they no longer stray from God's intention with light motion, but remain firm in the stability of constancy.
Through this stability, everything stands firm by His judgment and for ages eternal.
He established, governs, and will judge the world.
He cannot be comprehended or criticized.
Having arranged everything, He will give each individual their rewards or punishments.
The first pillar of this structure consists of thirty-three chapters.
Anyone who is baptized in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, reborn from water and the Holy Spirit, must steadfastly keep the commandments of the Decalogue with faith in the Holy Trinity, if they wish to reach eternal life.
The number ten, combined with the three, is multiplied three times in these chapters.
The woman, that is, the Catholic Church, takes the leaven, which is the faith in the Holy Trinity, working through love, and hides it in three measures of flour.
She strives to preach it in Asia, Africa, and Europe, until the whole is leavened.
This signifies that the Gospel of the kingdom, received from the Lord Jesus Christ about what He began and perfected to do and teach, is preached to the whole world.
On the third day mentioned in the Gospel reading, He comes to the wedding.
That is, in the third age of the world, through the mystery of the incarnation, He joined the same holy Church to Himself.
The first age of the world was before the law, by the examples of the patriarchs.
The second age was under the law, by the writings of the prophets.
The third age is under grace, by the proclamations of the evangelists, as the light of the third day shone upon the world, in which the same Lord and Savior of ours appeared incarnate for the redemption of the human race.
But the number thirty, when multiplied in a triangle, completes the number thirty, which is significant because Christ was baptized at this age, sanctifying all waters with His baptism for us.
In the grace of this sanctification, Jesus came to baptism in His thirtieth year because after this baptism, He was destined to fulfill the old law.
Up to this age, encompassing all sins, He observed the law, ensuring that no one could claim He abolished it because He couldn't fulfill it.
Not every age is equally vulnerable to all vices.
The early years are besieged by imprudence and weakness of mind.
Adolescence is attacked more fervently by lust, and later years are mostly troubled by the desire for possessions.
Christ waited through all these stages, fulfilling the justice of the law at each point, and then came to baptism, completing all the observances of the law.
Since He began His ministry with baptism at the age of thirty, He was to cleanse the sins of the whole Church.
The mystical connection of these numbers also tells us something important: when thirty is computed by its equal parts, it yields more than twelve, which is the number of the patriarchs and apostles, and it becomes forty-two.
The parts are: thirty, one; fifteenth, two; twelfth, three; sixth, five; fifth, six; third, ten; half, fifteen; which together make forty-two.
Mystically, this indicates that the entire perfection of the Church consists in the faith and grace of Christ, first recognized by the patriarchs and then widely proclaimed by the apostles.
There is no other name under heaven by which we must be saved, just as in forty-two, there is no part that does not contain equal parts of the number thirty.
Thus, the number thirty completes forty-two with its parts, because the Lord both temporally supports the Church with the sacraments of His baptism while it labors now and eternally leads it to rest after its labors are finished.
The age of the thirty-year-old baptized Savior can also signify the mystery of our baptism, rooted in faith in the Holy Trinity and the principles of the Decalogue revealed by the grace of faith.
The deeper the understanding, the more it is taught.
The number twelve, which we mentioned is derived from parts of thirty, represents the apostles, the entire choir of preachers, consisting of three times four or four times three.
This symbolizes that faith in the Holy Trinity and the four books of the holy Gospel must be preached by orthodox teachers throughout the four corners of the world-East, West, North, and South-before the end of the world.
He taught that those to be baptized should undergo a sacred period of three years, as he said, "Go, teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit" (Matthew 28:19).
It is as if he suggested this three-year period should be multiplied by ten when he added, "teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you" (Matthew 28:20).
For three years and six months, he, by his example and teachings, dispelled the darkness of the world with love for God and neighbor, honoring both bodies and souls.
He ultimately sacrificed himself on the cross for the salvation of humanity.
This clearly shows that many in the Church are just, holding faith in the Holy Trinity, which includes the incarnation of our Lord Jesus Christ-not as a fourth person-but as one Son, both God and man, who, in the glory of God the Father, remains in the Trinity with the same Father and Holy Spirit, perfected in hope, charity, and good works.
After the dissolution of the flesh, they will be immediately received into the blessed rest of paradise, joyfully awaiting, in large choirs of those rejoicing, the moment when they shall come and appear before the face of God with their bodies restored.
In half a year, however, it becomes evident that some are chosen for the strength of the elect not because of good works, but rather due to some evil deeds.
Polluted as they exit the body after death, they are severely punished, caught in the flames of purgatory.
They are either cleansed from the stains of their sins through a long examination until the day of judgment, or they are freed from their punishments earlier by the prayers, alms, fasts, tears, and sacrificial offerings of faithful friends, and they too reach the rest of the blessed.
For three and a half years, the Antichrist will display his deceptive tricks, showing himself as if he were God with false signs and wonders, using threats and terrors of punishments.
But he will not prevail over those who persist in the right faith and perfection of good works, aided by divine grace.
He, who appeared in the flesh, born of a woman and made under the law to redeem those under the law, so that we might receive the adoption of sons.
After the thirty-third day of circumcision, he was brought to the temple, and legal offerings were made for him, who consecrates all things divinely.
The triangle of the Decalogue, the three days, and the offering brought to the temple signify those days and the sacrifice of the Church, which is the body of Christ.
About these, he himself says in the Gospel, "Look, I drive out demons and perform cures today and tomorrow, and on the third day I am perfected" (Luke 13:32).
Because demons are expelled when, abandoning ancestral superstitions, the nations believe in him, and cures are performed when one lives according to his commandments.
After renouncing the devil and this world, until the end of the resurrection, which will be like the third day and will consummate in the fullness of the angelic nature, the Church will be perfected through the immortality of the body.
Therefore, let anyone who is devoted understand this number.
Only the one who possesses the right faith, represented by the number three, and good deeds, symbolized by the Decalogue, or the number ten, will be saved from the corruption of body and soul.
Such a person will be found to be a perfect individual, to the measure of the fullness of Christ, on the day of reward.
This pillar is known to consist of 760 lines, 210 of which address ecclesiastical doctrines against those who hold incorrect beliefs, according to the teachings of scholars.
The purpose of this calculation is that we should first start from the smaller number, that is, ten, and then progress from there.
Catholic scholars have said many eloquent and powerful things about the number ten, some of which I have noted here for brevity.
They say it is consecrated in the Decalogue.
God gave the ten commandments of this Decalogue, the psalmist's ten-stringed harp, to His servant Moses on the mountain, written on two tablets of stone.
Three commandments on one tablet pertain to God, because God is Trinity, and in the mystery of our redemption, there are three who testify: the Spirit, the water, and the blood, and these three are one.
The Spirit of sanctification, the blood of redemption, and the water of baptism.
These three are one and remain indivisible, and nothing is separated from their connection.
As the blessed Ambrose sings:
"Everything threefold thrives under the majesty of the Thunderer. Three, the Father, and the Word, and also the Holy Spirit are one. Threefold is the saving form of the cross, one redeemer. The third light received the Lord returning from death. Jonah was held for three days in the belly of the whale. Three boys grew in faith in the fiery furnace. Thrice holy is the blessing sung by the Sabaoth. Thrice must be immersed in water, filled with the grace of washing. Every action is confirmed by three witnesses. Each of the seasons returns in three months. There are three ages: youth, strength, and frail old age. Three are the roles in cases: the judge, the defender, and the accuser. Three stages in life: birth, progression, and end."
Three things give hope: rest, light, and the glory of life.
The second tablet of the Ten Commandments gave seven commandments, the first of which is, as the Apostle shows, "Honor your father and mother" (Ephesians 6:2).
Furthermore, the number seven in Sacred Scripture often demonstrates its perfection, specifically because, according to Scripture, God rested from His works after creating the heavens and all their adornments in six days (Genesis 2), and the Sabbath was given as a day of rest through the law (Exodus 16).
In our leader, the Mediator between God and humanity, the man Christ Jesus, the prophet enumerated the sevenfold grace of the Holy Spirit (Isaiah 11).
Sacred Scripture also lists the seven eyes, seven lampstands, seven seals, and seven thunders as symbols of perfection, and the entire age revolves in seven days (Revelation 1, 5, 6, 10).
And with these two perfect numbers, three and seven, the number ten is formed.
It is also because the number ten is complete from one through four in order.
One plus two plus three plus four equals ten, showing that the Decalogue of the law is fulfilled through the four books of the holy Gospel.
Perhaps for this reason, those who are hired to work in the vineyard receive a denarius as their reward, which, when multiplied by itself, rises to one hundred, and the number one hundred signifies great perfection.
By doubling one hundred, the perfection of the spirit given to the elect in this life and eternal life is signified.
Hence, the Lord says to these same elect, "Everyone who has left houses or brothers or sisters or father or mother or wife or children or fields for my sake will receive a hundred times as much and will inherit eternal life" (Matthew 19:29).
Not every holy person abandons earthly things to possess them more abundantly in this world.
Anyone who leaves the earth out of earthly ambition does not truly leave the earth but seeks it instead.
Nor does someone who forsakes one wife expect to receive a hundred.
The number one hundred signifies perfection, especially since eternal life is promised as well.
Anyone who scorns temporal and earthly things for the sake of God's name attains mental perfection here, so they no longer desire what they scorn.
In the next age, they reach the glory of eternal life, represented by the number one hundred, transferred from the left hand to the right.
Therefore, this feast, or this table, namely the holy Church, speaks of its creator, the true Solomon, saying, "His left hand is under my head, and his right hand embraces me"
Song of Solomon
chapter 2, verse 6. His left hand signifies the present life, the sacraments of His incarnation, and the gifts of His presence. His right hand signifies the future life and the rewards that the chosen ones will receive in the future.
Not only is the vision of divine majesty present, but also the glory of clarified humanity of the one and same Mediator between God and humans. Hence, the bride rightly desires His left hand to be placed under her head and to be embraced by His right hand, so that now she may rest from the world's disturbances through His temporal assistance, and then enjoy His clear vision perpetually.
No storm ever interrupts the eternal rest of the saints. Thus, it is rightly said, "His right hand embraces me." For surely the divine presence of majesty will surround its own in the heavenly kingdom, ensuring that no happiness worthy of God is marred by the memory of misery or the fear of an end.
The doubled hundred also signifies that anyone who desires to attain eternal life should burn with love for God and neighbor, and strive continually to hasten to it through Catholic faith and righteous action.
In the Orthodox faith, we believe in the holy and inseparable Trinity, and in the Incarnation of our Lord Jesus Christ.
We believe with our hearts for righteousness and confess with our mouths for salvation.
In the holy Trinity, there is nothing before or after, nothing greater or lesser; all three persons are co-eternal and co-equal.
In all things, the unity of the deity in the Trinity is of persons, and the Trinity of persons is in the unity of the deity.
From the Father alone, the Son is begotten, not made, equal and consubstantial.
From the Father and the Son together, the Holy Spirit proceeds equally and consubstantially.
The Holy Spirit is worshipped equally with the Father and the Son because He is equally God, entirely the Spirit of the Father and entirely the Spirit of the Son.
The Holy Spirit proceeds entirely from the Father and entirely from the Son, and remains entirely in both.
He remains as He proceeds, and proceeds as He remains.
He naturally shares the fullness of unity with the Father and the Son, possessing the entirety of both, and is entirely possessed by both.
The Holy Spirit is equally given by the Father and the Son, and also given by Himself.
He is called the gift of God and the Paraclete, or Comforter, because He distributes the gifts of the sacraments and provides consolation to the soul.
Through Him, God's love is poured into our hearts, and the whole Trinity inhabits us.
Regarding the Incarnation of our Lord Jesus Christ, who is one person from and in the same holy Trinity, we should believe faithfully.
We believe He is true and perfect God before all ages, without any beginning, and true and perfect man at the end of the ages.
He consists of two natures and substances in one person.
By the power of His divinity, He created us to enjoy eternal life, and by the frailty of our humanity, He restored us to receive the life we had lost.
According to the truth of the Creed, He was conceived by the Holy Spirit, born of the Virgin Mary- a servant by his humanity, and the mother of the Word by his flesh.
Both the Gospel truth and the voice of Elizabeth affirm that she is both the servant and the mother of the Lord.
She is not the servant of one and the mother of another.
The flesh was not first conceived in the virgin's womb, and then later divinity entered into the flesh.
Instead, the Word, the only begotten before all ages, equal to the Father, came into the womb immediately.
The Word, preserving the truth of its own nature, became flesh.
A perfect man, truly in the flesh and rational soul, born through the working of the Holy Spirit, was born through the womb of the Virgin as the Son of God, made the Son of Man- one Christ.
He died only in the flesh for our sins, and rose again only in the flesh, because he committed no sin, nor was deceit found in his mouth.
In whatever way the soul might rise again from the death of sin.
He also ascended into heaven and sits at the right hand of the Father, in the glory of the Father's majesty.
From there, he will come to judge the living and the dead.
At his coming, all men will rise with their bodies and will give an account of their own deeds.
Those who, by the grace of God and the subsequent free will following that same grace, have persevered in right faith and good works, foreknown and predestined by God to glory, will go into eternal life.
The elect, from the mass of perdition of the whole human race made in Adam himself sinning- because Eve herself is Adam, chosen by grace, prepared by God- as the Truth itself says,
Come, blessed of my Father, receive the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world (Matthew 25:34).
And those who are not destined by God for destruction but left by Him in the mass of perdition as a just retribution will persist in unbelief or evil deeds and will go into eternal fire.
God predestined no one to this fire but prepared it as a just retribution for the devil and his followers.
As He says in the Gospel, the Apostle states, "For the wages of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life" (Romans 6:23).
And, "All the paths of the Lord are mercy and truth" (Psalms 25:10).
And, "Anger, that is vengeance, is in His indignation, and life in His will" (Psalms 30:5).
Therefore, this other column of the table, opposing those who have incorrect beliefs about what will happen in the next age, consists of thirty-eight chapters.
It is like the weak person lying in the synagogue of Satan's portico for thirty-eight years rather than in the embrace of the Catholic Church, representing the group with incorrect beliefs.
This number, which falls short of the forty-two that is fulfilled by the ten commandments of the law and the four books of the Holy Gospel, walks without the love of God and neighbor, which both the law and the Gospel commend.
If more from this group agreed to accept the truth, they would recover health in the unity of faith as if they were one.
Outside the unity of the Catholic faith, no place of salvation is open to anyone.
Whoever deviates from this unity cannot attain the salvation that comes from the One.
This eternal salvation is symbolized by the hundred verses of the column, as Isaac, the son of the promise, was born to Abraham at one hundred years old, signifying laughter or joy.
This alludes to Him who said to His disciples, "But I will see you again, and your heart will rejoice, and no one will take your joy from you" (John 16:22).
To reach the joy of eternal salvation, you must pass through the perfect number represented by the additional sixty verses.
The number sixty, being six times ten, embodies the perfection of six, illustrating the completion of works.
Just as the admirable Creator is perfect in nature, He completed His works in six days.
On the sixth day, He created man, perfect in soul and body, for whom all things were made.
In the sixth age, the Creator came to restore the man He had created on the sixth day.
The number sixty also includes ten, which is consecrated in the Decalogue, and as we've shown, it is perfected.
This demonstrates that the number sixty is perfect.
Divide sixty by ten, and you'll see that the number sixty is perfect in tens, just like six is perfect in units.
For one, two, and three make six, a perfect number in its parts; similarly, sixty has a certain perfection when divided by ten.
For once ten, twice ten, and three times ten make sixty.
Furthermore, the number fifty includes six, which represents the Jubilee year, the remission of sins, and the return to the inheritance of the eternal homeland and eternal rest.
It also exceeds the conjugal order by its doubling, symbolizing the laborious widow's continence by the impression of the finger, because those who sow in tears will reap in joy.
Containing thirty within it, this number depicts the gentle kiss of the index finger and thumb, and the spouse, producing the fruit of faith through good works.
Like the best soil, it brings forth fruit from the divine word's seed.
Just as the number one hundred, transferred from the left to the right with the same fingers, but not the same hand, signifies spouses and widows on the left hand, making a circle, it expresses the crown of virginity.
The word produces thirtyfold fruit, which builds the faith of the Holy Trinity, sixtyfold, which teaches the perfection of works, and hundredfold, which proclaims eternal life at the right hand of the kingdom.
Therefore, anyone who seeks life and wishes to see good days throughout the six days or ages of this world, in which work is permitted, should hasten to the Sabbath, the rest of the seventh day or age, when work will no longer be allowed.
This should be done with right faith and just deeds, fulfilling the commandments of the Decalogue without engaging in wrongful acts.
Departing from the body, they may rest on the seventh day or age, or in the peace of the fiftieth number, until they reach the eternal hundred on the eighth day or age with incorruptible bodies.
The golden bed of this feast is symbolized by the number eight of verses.
In this life, during these six days or ages when work is permitted, anyone who has purified themselves with the knife of Christ, following the example of the eighth day signified by circumcision, given to the ancients in place of baptism, with faith, hope, and love, not only in baptism but in every devoted action, will rest happily on the seventh Sabbath and rise glorified on the eighth.
This is our daily circumcision, the continuous cleansing of the heart, always celebrating the sacrament of the eighth day, which sanctifies us in the example of the Lord's resurrection.
This happened on the eighth day, after the seventh Sabbath, so that just as Christ was raised from the dead by the glory of the Father, we too might walk in newness of life.
This is the blessed eighth day of our complete resurrection, an eternal time when the true glory of all-encompassing circumcision shines brightly.
No longer will a corruptible body weigh down the soul, nor will earthly habitation depress the mind.
Instead, the incorruptible body will bring joy to the soul, and the heavenly habitation will lift the whole person to the vision of their Creator, renewing our youth like the eagle's.
This bed was made for us by our Solomon when he promised the faithful the hope of eternal rest.
Take my yoke upon you and learn from me, for I am gentle and humble in heart, and you will find rest for your souls.
Matthew 11:29.
He made this resting place golden, preparing for us the eternal rest of the glory of his divine vision.
It is said: Whoever loves me will be loved by my Father, and I will love him and reveal myself to him.
John 14:21.
He made the resting place golden for the faithful, because we will all rise, but not all will be changed.
Christ suffered for all and acquired resurrection for all, but the glory of incorruption of both soul and body is for the faithful.
It is said, They will rise in the resurrection of the righteous.
Luke 14:14.
Since all will undoubtedly rise.
The ascent of this resting place was made purple by Idida, meaning the beloved Son of the Father in whom he is well pleased.
True purple is dyed with the blood of sea snails.
For the living and abundant redeeming blood of the spotless and unblemished Lamb, Jesus Christ.
Conceived by the Holy Spirit, that is, by the power of the Holy Spirit, from the virgin blood of a seed-bearing nature, specifically from the immaculate flesh of the Virgin, without any carnal desire and without any male touch.
Uniquely conceived, born miraculously with the virgin womb closed, and the virgin parts intact and unsullied, he washed us from our sins.
The blood, specifically of the Lamb who takes away the sins of the world, is drawn from marine shells with iron.
This illustrates how, through the lineage of sinful humans, oppressed like the waves of the sea, as shown in the genealogy in the Gospel, He came from the line of Abraham and David.
Through the piercing with iron, namely the nails and spear, the sacraments of our redemption flowed from His most sacred body, in which God was reconciling the world to Himself and in which all the fullness of divinity dwells bodily.
These sacraments have come to us, by which the same King and our Lord, who loved us and washed us from our sins in His own blood, not only when He gave His blood on the cross for us, or when each of us is washed in the waters of baptism in the mystery of His holy passion, but also daily takes away the sins of the world and washes us from our daily sins in His blood.
This happens when the memory of His blessed passion is repeated at the altar, when the bread and wine are transformed into the sacrament of His body and blood by the ineffable sanctification of the Spirit.
Thus, His body and blood are not poured out and killed by the hands of unbelievers to their destruction, but are received by the mouths of the faithful for their salvation.
And no one ascends to this purple banquet unless they are imbued with the sacraments of the Lord's passion, because no one enters the Church unless they are initiated with these sacraments.
Hence, He said: Unless one is born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter the kingdom of heaven John 3:5.
And: Unless you eat the flesh of the Son of Man and drink His blood, you do not have life in you.
Whoever eats my flesh and drinks my blood has eternal life, and I will raise him up on the last day John 6:54-55.
The purple banquet is described in thirty verses because, according to the Apostle, whoever is baptized in Christ Jesus, who was baptized at the age of thirty, is baptized into His death Romans 6:3.
In this thirtieth part of the Decalogue, the number ten is tripled to symbolize the completion of faith and good works through the sanctification of baptism.
In baptism, all righteousness is fulfilled, encompassing redemption by the blood of Christ, sanctification by the Holy Spirit, and perfect cleansing by the water.
At this banquet, Solomon is truly at peace, having made peace through the blood of his cross, reconciling heavenly and earthly things.
By breaking down the dividing wall, he united them as one and bound them with the bond of love for the daughters of Jerusalem-the very love by which he suffered for us.
As no one has greater love than this, to lay down one's life for friends.
As the Apostle says, "But God demonstrates his own love for us in this: while we were still sinners, Christ died for the ungodly" (Romans 5:8).
Indeed, he prepared this central couch for his Church, where faithful souls can find rest, filled entirely with the love of heavenly things.
This is what he means when he adds, "For the daughters of Jerusalem" (Song of Solomon 5:10), referring to souls burning with the desire for heavenly things.
The greater the love God showed for us through his suffering, the more he inspired many to love him in return and to suffer for him.
This love, or rather our mercy, is what the Psalmist refers to, "My God, my mercy" (Psalms).
In Revelation 5:6-14, the Lamb who takes away the sins of the world is depicted as the one who washes us from our sins in His blood.
On the cross, in two verses, the same Lamb is portrayed, harmonizing with the same Lamb in one and the same letter.
On the cross, in four verses of one measure, the same letters at the beginning or end embrace everything in a circle through the four parts of the world:
the children of the promise and coheirs with Christ of the eternal inheritance.
These are the elect and predestined to life in the embrace of Christ's redemption, who suffered for all.
He proclaims to the world the measure of that cross, namely the length and width, height and depth in the love of God and neighbor.
These two and four verses together complete the number six because man was created on the sixth day, and likewise on the sixth day, he was restored through the mystery of the cross.
This number six is called perfect among the wise of the world because it is completed in its order, so that when one, two, three are counted, the number six is filled up:
or because it is divided into three parts, that is, a sixth, a third, and a half; namely into one, two, and three.
By the church doctors, it is called perfect because on the sixth day God completed all His works, and the six ages of this world are distinguished by the most well-known points of time.
In these six days, it is necessary to work and labor for God to obtain eternal rest.
After six days, the Savior showed the glory of His kingdom which He promised to the disciples because whoever desires to see God and to belong to the glory of the blessed resurrection must do the good deeds he knows for six days.
There are also six stone jars, symbolizing the strong hearts of the saints, filled with the pure and untainted knowledge of Holy Scripture, free from any heretical corruption.
Whoever wishes to be saved must not only hold a faithful belief in the Holy Trinity and the incarnation of the Lord, but must also strive to keep themselves and their listeners free from all heretical pestilence and schismatic division.
They must cleanse themselves from the stain of sin and drink from the pure fountain of divine knowledge.
This is especially true for those whose perfect life and faith serve as an example to others on how to believe and live rightly.
The preface of the feast, addressing the beloved prince, explains the feast in twenty-four verses.
These verses speak of having correct faith, good works, a life full of merit, the teachings of knowledge, love of God and neighbor, and, in all pious devotion and action, rightly understanding grace and free will.
As the Lord says through the prophet: "Your fruit is found in me" (Hosea 14:8); meaning, the gift of my grace that precedes allows you to act well, and with your subsequent free will, the fruit is found.
Thus, it is shown by the Lord that whatever good we desire, think, speak, and do comes from God through preceding grace, and from us through the subsequent obedience of free will.
Therefore, we will be rewarded and will sing of the Lord's mercies forever, while the disobedient will be justly condemned.
Hence, the writer wishes the king to live well in this world and reign with Christ forever.
For this reason, in the same preface, the number ten is doubled, which is completed by the four books of the Holy Gospel.
It is impossible to please God without faith, and faith without works is dead in itself.
In this context, the dual nature is emphasized: knowledge without charity leads to arrogance, but charity combined with knowledge builds up.
Understanding benefits all who practice it, especially when paired with the love of God, which is boundless.
We are commanded to love with all our heart, mind, and strength.
The love of neighbor is summarized in two precepts found in Tobit, Chapter 4, and Matthew, Chapter 7: "Do not do to others what you do not want done to you, and do to others what you want them to do to you."
The sum of the verses is completed with eight verses, symbolizing the eighth day of the resurrection.
Just as there are two deaths-one of the body when the soul departs, and one of the soul when sin enters-there are also two resurrections.
The first resurrection is of the soul, revived through forgiveness and repentance by God's grace, and the second is of the body, when all will rise at the Lord's coming to account for their deeds.
Blessed is he who partakes in the first resurrection, for he will not be harmed by the second death and will receive immortality and incorruption of both body and soul.
The significance of the first resurrection is rightly placed before that of higher dignity.
As Scripture says: "His father, Caleb, gave his daughter Achsah the upper and lower springs" (Judges, Chapter 1, Verse 15).
The elect soul first laments over the lower spring to avoid punishment, and then over the upper spring, as it is deferred from the kingdom.
The total of the heroic and elegiac verses of the dish consists of four hundred and forty-six, equating to ten multiplied by ten.
Having sufficiently discussed this earlier, we will not repeat it.
For indeed, a denarius, when multiplied by four, adds up to forty: because we fulfill the commandments of the Decalogue when we keep the four books of the Holy Gospel.
We preserve them more humbly if we constantly reflect on where we have fallen from and to where.
From our own region, that is, from paradise, we departed into this valley of tears by being proud, disobeying, following visible things, and tasting forbidden food.
But it is necessary for us to return to it by weeping, obeying, despising visible things, and restraining the appetite of the flesh.
Since we fell from the joys of paradise through food, we must rise again through abstinence as much as we can.
This abstinence, indicating that our entire life should be in continence from evil deeds and in the practice of virtues, is maintained by the number of forty days.
Just as the children of Israel, in whose place we have succeeded, were troubled in the wilderness for forty years after crossing the Red Sea before they came to the promised land, so we also suffer worthy penalties for disobedience in the sufferings of this exile before we return to the joys of paradise.
In this trial, after holy baptism, we are first given the long struggles of practicing virtues, and then the perpetual rewards of heavenly happiness.
Having received God's law, that is, having heard the divine word, it is clear that we should leave our old way of life and enter the solitude of the spiritual life.
If we want to enter the promised land, we should daily discipline our new way of living, and cleanse ourselves from every infection of creeping vices with the most salutary tears of compunction, just as he who said: "I wash my bed every night, I drench my couch with tears" (Psalms 6:6).
Hence, the stream of Jordan is rightly interpreted as judgment, because the elect, the more carefully they examine their conscience by judging it, the more abundant tears they shed from the depths of their heart.
As they realize they are less perfect, they cleanse the stains of their frailty with the waters of repentance.
The significance of the number 40 is evident in many ways: through the flood, in Jacob's mourning, in the trials of the children of Israel in the desert, in the preaching of Jonah, and many other examples in Scripture that point to perfection.
Moses, who was commanded by God to practice circumcision and observed it for 406 years, suspended it for 40 years in the wilderness.
Joshua then completed the circumcision with stone knives because Christ was the rock.
The law was given through Moses, but grace and truth came through Jesus Christ.
Moses also fasted for 40 days to receive the law for the people of God.
Elijah abstained for 40 days in the desert, and the author of humanity, when coming to humans, took no food for 40 days.
Why then is the number 40 observed in fasting, if not because the strength of the Ten Commandments is sustained through the four books of the Holy Gospel?
Since we have despised the commandments of the Decalogue through carnal desires, it is fitting that we afflict the flesh forty times over.
To achieve eternal life, symbolized by the number 100 and multiplied by four, it is necessary that the number 40 be multiplied by the ten of the Decalogue, thus reaching the number 400.
For ten times forty makes 400.
All the elect, destined for eternal life - symbolized by the number 100 and multiplied by four - will return to what they were created for, not only in the incorruptibility of soul and body but also in the vision of the divine majesty, with the glory of the mediator between God and humans, the glorified humanity.
They will rejoice in the true jubilee, the 50th year.
Because the holy Church, in some of its members, still labors on earth for eternal rest, while in others it already reigns with Christ in heaven after all labor is finished, our fathers established two solemn observances appropriate to religion: Lent, a time of affliction leading up to Easter, and the fifty days from the day of the Lord's resurrection, during which "Alleluia" is continuously sung.
The evangelist John reports hearing it sung by angels in the book of Revelation, chapter 19. The venerable father Tobias, understanding from an angelic vision the glory of the heavenly citizens and the brightness of the heavenly Jerusalem, said: "In its streets, Alleluia will be sung" (Tobit 13:22).
Although in the Church, divine praise never ceases.
The celebration of this fifty-day period suggests to the faithful the perfection of rest, and since the number ten symbolizes perfection, multiplying ten by fifty gives five hundred.
This clearly shows that mere abstinence from food and drink does not bring us to eternal joys unless other good deeds are added, showing a worthy abstinence to God with true devotion of mind.
For that fast is approved by God which lifts up hands of alms to His eyes, as the prophet says, "Sanctify a fast" (Joel chapters 1 and 2).
To sanctify a fast means, as we have said, to show abstinence of the flesh worthy of God by adding other good deeds.
It is in vain to afflict the flesh if the mind is not restrained from evil pleasures, and our Redeemer is not pleased with one without the other.
If a person who does good still does not forsake the stains of luxury, or if a person excelling in chastity has not yet exercised themselves in good works, the one who begins some good deed for worldly honor should by no means remain in that intention.
They should not seek the glory of this present world through good works, but should place all hope in the coming of their Redeemer.
There are indeed many who abstain and afflict their bodies through abstinence, seeking human favor from their actions, serving doctrine, and giving much to the needy.
But they are truly foolish virgins because they seek only the reward of fleeting praise.
As the Lord says, they receive the condemnable reward of their labors.
Yet, good deeds done with simple intention are pleasing to God if they are offered without the mixture of evil work, as it is written: Turn away from evil and do good.
Psalm thirty-six, verse twenty-four.
First, turn away from evil, and then do good so that it may be profitable: first, repent worthily of past sins, and then strive in good works so that they may be beneficial.
But we cannot worthily do penance unless we also know how to do penance.
To do penance is to mourn the evils committed and not to commit those that should be mourned.
For someone who laments some sins while committing others either does not know how to do penance or pretends not to.
For what good is it if someone mourns the sins of lust but still longs for the fires of greed?
Or what good is it if he now laments the sins of anger but still withers under the flames of envy?
It is also necessary for one who remembers committing unlawful acts to strive to abstain even from some lawful ones: so that in this way, he may satisfy his Creator.
He who committed prohibited acts should cut off even what is permitted and reproach himself in small things, remembering sinning in great ones.
Thus, we truly do penance if we perfectly mourn what we have committed.
Indeed, a more corrected life sanctifies those whom the cleansing affliction of tears purifies through penance.
And because we have spoken of the number of four hundred verses, it remains that we complete the account of the mentioned number of forty-six verses.
For this number of years perfectly matches the body of the Lord, by whose blood we are redeemed, by whose flesh we are nourished, and by whose blood we are given drink, through the holy mysteries of His passion, both in soul and in body, and we will be saved from sins and the very corruptions that happened because of sins.
Natural science writers say that the human body's form is completed within a certain number of days: in the first six days after conception, it resembles milk.
In the next nine days, it turns into blood.
Then in twelve days, it solidifies.
And in the remaining eighteen days, it is strengthened until the perfect outlines of all the limbs are formed.
From this point, it grows in size until the time of birth.
Six, nine, twelve, and eighteen together make forty-five: if we add one more day, which is the day when the body begins to take distinct shape with its limbs, we find that the number of days for the construction of the Lord's body matches the number of years it took to build the Temple.
When Jesus said about the Temple, "Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up," the Jews replied, "It took forty-six years to build this temple, and will you raise it up in three days?" John 2:19.
And because that human-made temple symbolized the holy body of the Lord, which He took from the Virgin, as we learn from this passage, and because His body, which is the Church, symbolized the bodies and souls of each faithful person, let us purify the temples of our bodies and hearts every day of our lives, so that the Spirit of God may dwell in us.
And as the Apostle advises: "Let us put aside the deeds of darkness and put on the armor of light. Let us behave decently, as in the daytime, not in carousing and drunkenness, not in sexual immorality and debauchery, not in dissension and jealousy. Rather, clothe yourselves with the Lord Jesus Christ" Romans 13:12-14, who lives and reigns with the Father and the Holy Spirit, God, forever and ever. Amen.
So that you lack nothing, dear Charles, the measure of the verses and the amount of the coins reveal.
The rich table of the king, also known as the feast, was laid out for you by the wise prince through the dishes of the learned.
I have compressed what was said in plain words into the rule of poetry, and I have joined the eloquent prose so that you may grasp various matters.
I have explained some things more extensively above; indeed, I have calculated some things more concisely.
If you deem it worthy to be fully explained, I am here, perhaps, if leisure time is granted to us by our prayers, so that the king may grasp what the bishop offers and demonstrate in conduct and word these things in action to all subjects in the kingdom.
May Charles live a long and happy life in this century; may he live forever honored in the blessed company of the saints.