On the Remission of Sins
by Fulgentius of Ruspe
To Euthymius, Two Books. Book Two
Chapter One
At the beginning of the previous book, I mentioned that we embarked on discussing the forgiveness of sins with the guidance and help of God, breaking it down into three parts.
We established that our Lord, the true God, is full of both mercy and justice, and we supported this with clear references from the holy Scriptures.
We explained that understanding to whom, where, and when God forgives sins would be easier for those seeking the truth.
Having covered two parts of this threefold division, I now need to explain the third part.
As for to whom and where God forgives sins, these were clearly demonstrated in the previous book, with the help of God's mercy.
It is evident that forgiveness of sins is granted only to those who have converted and are within the Catholic Church.
True conversion happens where true faith is paired with a holy way of life, and the pursuit of good living is not disturbed by any false belief.
A good life cannot truly be called good if it is corrupted by false beliefs, and the faith of someone who believes rightly is not enough for salvation if their actions are marred by immoral behavior.
Thus, just as the blessed James declares that faith without works is dead (James 2:17), Paul also confirms in his preaching that everything not from faith is sin (Romans 14:23).
Chapter Two
Now, as we receive the illumination from the true light, which enlightens every person coming into this world (John 1:9), we set out to explain when forgiveness of sins is granted to the repentant.
Sterile repentance will be deprived of the fruit of remission if the divinely granted opportunity is neglected.
For this reason, the blessed Peter says: "The Lord is not slow in keeping his promise, as some understand slowness, but is patient with you, not wanting anyone to perish, but everyone to come to repentance" (2 Peter 3:9).
I urge you, dearest Euthymius, not to hesitate to consider how significant this apostolic statement is.
It should not be taken lightly that the blessed Peter says God is patient because he does not want anyone to perish but everyone to come to repentance.
Repentance benefits the sinner because God is not quick to condemn, allowing him to grant forgiveness to those who turn to repentance.
If repentance after this life could be fruitful, the blessed Peter would not say that God is patient because he does not want anyone to perish, especially those he foreknew and predestined to be conformed to the image of his Son (Romans 8:29).
None of these will perish.
Who can resist his will?
These people are graciously anticipated by God's mercy before the end of this life.
They are healthily pierced with a contrite and humbled heart and are converted to repentance by divine gift.
They are divinely predestined by free grace, so that they, being converted, do not perish but have eternal life.
These undoubtedly are all those whom, according to the proclamation of the blessed Paul, God wants to be saved and to come to the knowledge of the truth (1 Timothy 2:4).
He who wills this, who has done whatever he willed, always does what he wills irresistibly.
This is certainly fulfilled in them, which is the unchangeable and insurmountable will of Almighty God.
His will cannot be altered, nor can His power be hindered.
No one can justly criticize His fairness, nor can anyone oppose His mercy.
Hence, our Savior reproaches the malevolence of the unbelieving city with these words:
"Jerusalem, Jerusalem, you who kill the prophets and stone those sent to you, how often I wanted to gather your children together as a hen gathers her chicks under her wings, but you were not willing" (Matthew 23:37)!
Christ said this to show their evil will, by which they tried in vain to resist the insurmountable will of God.
The good will of God can neither be overcome by those He abandons, nor can anything He wills fail to be done.
Therefore, as far as the will of that Jerusalem is concerned, it did not want its children to be gathered to the Savior.
Nevertheless, He gathered all whom He wanted.
Consequently, it tried to resist the Almighty but could not succeed, because God, as it is written, "Did whatever He pleased" (Psalm 135:6).
He converted whomever He wanted to Himself with gratuitous justification, evidently by the gift of superabundant grace, those whom He could justly condemn if He wished.
Therefore, when the apostle Peter says that God patiently bears, not wanting anyone to perish, but all to come to repentance (Second Peter 3:9), we should not take "all" to mean that there is no one who will not suitably perform repentance.
Rather, we should understand "all" here to mean those to whom God grants repentance, so that He also grants perseverance.
That is, those who are converted by the preceding divine mercy, so that by the same following mercy they do not return to the sins they renounce.
These are the ones to whom, as Paul says, God grants repentance leading to a knowledge of the truth, so that they may escape from the snare of the devil, who has held them captive to do his will (Second Timothy 2:25).
Anyone who commits to this penance in this life will find its rewards with God.
Chapter Three
Furthermore, we read in the Book of Wisdom that some will indeed repent on the Day of Judgment, but will not receive divine forgiveness.
It is written as follows:
"Then the righteous will stand with great confidence against those who oppressed them and took away their labors."
"Seeing this, they will be disturbed with terrible fear and will be amazed at the unexpected salvation, saying among themselves, repentant and groaning through anguish of spirit:
'These are the ones we once held in derision and made a mockery of.
We fools considered their lives madness and their end without honor.
How are they counted among the children of God, and their lot is among the saints?'"
(Wisdom 5:1 and following).
However, no one should think that those who end their lives in sin will ever be granted unexpected salvation by divine gift.
The unexpected salvation of the righteous, although despaired of by the wicked, is reserved for those who hope in righteousness.
Hence, the blessed David in one psalm sang of the hope and salvation of the righteous, saying:
"The salvation of the righteous comes from the Lord; He is their protector in times of trouble.
The Lord will help them and deliver them; He will rescue them from sinners and save them, because they took refuge in Him."
(Psalm 37:39-40).
This is why the wicked, destined for eternal torment, will say of the righteous:
"These are the ones we once held in derision and made a mockery of.
We fools considered their lives madness and their end without honor."
This is the unexpected salvation, because they thought the lives of the righteous were madness;
and while they themselves were insane, they believed they were sane, nor did they expect the retribution of divine justice, and therefore neglected to correct their lives.
For they delighted in living luxuriously for a few days here, not believing they would later be tormented with eternal punishments.
Therefore, when the wicked see the righteous in the glory of the children of God, as the blessed Paul says: "In which we stand and rejoice in the hope of the glory of the children of God" (Romans 5:2), they will marvel at the glory of the righteous, who are indeed the children of God.
The wicked will regret too late and groan in anguish: "How were they counted among the children of God, and how is their lot among the saints?" The unexpected salvation, which the wicked did not hope for, will be given to the righteous, not to them.
This salvation will not be given to those living wickedly and in despair, but to those who live in good hope, abstaining from carnal desires and keeping the healthful commandments of the blessed Peter, who says: "Dearly beloved, I beseech you as strangers and pilgrims, abstain from fleshly desires, which war against the soul; having your conversation honest among the Gentiles" (First Peter 2:11).
Through this good conduct, the righteous present their bodies as a living sacrifice, holy and acceptable to God (Romans 12:1).
Through their good conduct, they are also the temple of God.
The Apostle testifies that the faithful are this temple, saying: "Do you not know that you are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwells in you?" (First Corinthians 3:16).
He not only warns that this temple should not be polluted by evil works but also greatly alarms our souls, saying: "If anyone defiles the temple of God, God will destroy him. For the temple of God is holy, which you are. Let no one deceive himself" (First Corinthians 3:17-18).
For who, living wickedly, when hearing from the Apostle that if anyone defiles the temple of God, God will destroy him, does not convert and dare to promise himself any hope of future forgiveness?
Who would not tremble and collapse in fear?
Who would not, before the end of this present life, be pricked and humbled, and run to repentance?
The Apostle cries out: "If anyone defiles the temple of God, God will destroy that person." The vain man deceives himself with the most wicked thought, saying: "Even if I defile the temple of God and live wickedly until the end, I will be saved." Doesn't the Apostle say to such people, who claim: "Let us do evil so that good may come," their condemnation is just? (Romans 3:8)
Are these not the ones whom the holy Scripture calls unfortunate and declares their hope to be completely empty, saying: "Wisdom and discipline are added to the unfortunate, and their hope is empty, and their labors are without fruit?" (Wisdom 3:11)
Chapter Four
Salvation will not be given to the wicked, but to the righteous: specifically, to those who have been corrected and converted before the end of this life.
Salvation will be given to the good, who have sought friendship with God through conversion, not to the evil, who, remaining friends of the world, deserve to be rightly called enemies of God by apostolic rebuke.
For the blessed James rebukes such people: "Adulterers, do you not know that friendship with this world is enmity with God? Therefore, whoever wants to be a friend of this world is made an enemy of God"
James 4:4.
Therefore, anyone who turns away from evil and does good, who has repented for their sins in this present life and has turned to God with all their heart, renouncing evil deeds, their hope will not be in vain.
On the other hand, anyone who deceives themselves by thinking they will reach life through the wide and spacious path is mistaken:
since the Lord commands us to walk the narrow path and shows us the entrance through the narrow gate, through which one enters the kingdom.
For He says: "Enter through the narrow gate. For wide is the gate and spacious is the way that leads to destruction, and many enter through it. But narrow is the gate and difficult the way that leads to life, and few find it"
Matthew 7:13-14.
Our current life is the path, and if anyone placed on it does not consent to the word of God, they will not receive the forgiveness of sins; but will lament their punishment in weeping and gnashing of teeth without end:
nor will they justly deserve to be free from torment, who, as long as they lived here, did not want to renounce sin.
Chapter Five
Because of this, our Savior warns us, saying:
"Be agreeable with your adversary quickly while you are on the way with him, lest the adversary hand you over to the judge, and the judge hand you over to the officer, and you be thrown into prison. Truly I tell you, you will not get out until you have paid the last penny"
(Matthew 5:25-26).
A person makes the word of God his adversary as long as he does what the divine word forbids.
The Psalm says to him: "You hate discipline and cast my words behind you"
(Psalm 50:17).
If someone does not quickly agree with this divine word while on the way, meaning in this life, and is sent to the prison of eternal fire, he will find no rest.
For this is a good adversary, who persistently confronts us with beneficial opposition to drive out the deadly adversity of iniquity from us.
This is why in another place, divine Scripture urges us to convert quickly, so that deadly delay does not bring about destruction instead of salvation.
It says: "Do not delay to turn to the Lord, and do not put it off from day to day; lest suddenly the wrath of the Lord come, and in the time of vengeance, he destroys you"
(Sirach 5:8).
The divine word clearly shows that when the time of vengeance comes, conversion will no longer remove the evil through punishment, but vindictive wrath will destroy with deserved condemnation.
For that time will not be for forgiveness, but for retribution; not for mercy, but for vengeance.
This is deferred by divine patience so that the number of the saints may be fulfilled.
The blessed John in Revelation remembers that the saints asked for this vengeance, saying:
"How long, O Lord, holy and true, will you not judge and avenge our blood on those who dwell on the earth?"
(Revelation 6:10).
And to show that the time of vengeance is deferred by divine ordination for those who are to be joined with them, it follows, saying:
"Then each of them was given a white robe, and they were told to rest a little while longer, until the number of their fellow servants and brothers was completed"
(Revelation 6:11).
Blessed Paul also understood the difference between the present age and the future one.
He recognized that in the present, we can only obtain the benefit of salvation; but in the future, each person will receive the reward of justice according to the quality of their good or bad deeds.
Thus, when he cited the prophetic testimony where God says:
"In an acceptable time I have heard you,
and in the day of salvation I have helped you,"
Second Corinthians 6:2, he immediately follows with:
"See, now is the acceptable time;
see, now is the day of salvation."
Isaiah 49:8.
But regarding the future, he says:
"For we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ,
so that each one may receive what is due for what they have done in the body, whether good or bad."
Second Corinthians 5:10.
Chapter Six
Eternal life will not be given in the future unless the forgiveness of sins is granted in this world.
No one will receive forgiveness of sins here unless they renounce their sins and turn to the supreme and true God with a sincere conversion of the heart.
For that time will be one of retribution, not forgiveness.
Mercy will not justify the wicked there; instead, justice will distinguish the righteous from the wicked.
As it is written in the Psalm: The Lord examines the righteous and the wicked (Psalm 10:6).
To show that iniquities lead to the destruction of the soul, not salvation, it continues by saying: But he who loves iniquity hates his own soul.
And so that those who persist in iniquity until the end of their present life do not promise themselves any mercy, it then speaks of God in this way:
He rains traps, fire, sulfur, and a scorching wind upon sinners; this is the portion of their cup.
For the Lord is righteous; He loves righteousness.
His face beholds the upright (Psalm 11:6-7).
Therefore, anyone who hears this and does not seek God's mercy through conversion in the present time will never find it in the future.
For this is what the just judge has ordered to be declared to us through the blessed apostle James, who says: Judgment without mercy will be shown to anyone who has not been merciful (James 2:13).
The order of mercy requires that the mercy a person is commanded to show to another should first be shown to themselves, as Scripture says: Have mercy on your own soul, pleasing God (Ecclesiasticus 30:24).
Therefore, if anyone does not want to please God, they deny mercy to their own soul.
And whoever does not want to grant mercy to their own soul in the present world will in no way be able to find mercy with God.
For judgment without mercy will be shown to anyone who has not been merciful.
Thus, what is subsequently said: Mercy triumphs over judgment (James 2:13), will be fulfilled in those who now show mercy to their soul, pleasing God.
For the Lord Himself says: Blessed are the merciful, for they will be shown mercy (Matthew 5:7).
For the blessed Apostle advises that everything should be done decently and in order First Corinthians 14:40.
And this is also why it is said in the Song of Songs: "Set love in order within me" Song of Solomon 2:4.
How can one be said to hold to the order of either love or mercy if, not to mention anyone else, he himself replenishes his body with food so that it does not weaken; clothes it so that it does not get cold; takes care that it does not get sick while it is healthy; and strives to heal it when it is sick. He continuously provides his body with necessary food, clothing, and medicines with careful intention, yet by living poorly, brings ruin upon his soul. He nourishes his body with necessary foods but kills his soul with evil deeds. He denies his body harmful foods but supplies his soul with evil deeds as if they were deadly poisons. He desires to prolong the life of his body, which ends in a few days, but brings death to his soul, whose punishment will have no end.
Therefore, he who is proven to hate his own soul is also found to be a cruel adversary to his soul. Just as good deeds allow the flesh to enjoy heavenly bliss with the soul, so evil deeds cause the soul to be tormented with the flesh in eternal fire. He is thus his own most destructive enemy, whoever, living wickedly, does not change his life before it ends.
Chapter Seven
The end of this life determines the beginning of that life where whatever is rewarded never ends.
As the Apostle John rightly says:
"Whoever hates his brother is a murderer, and you know that no murderer has eternal life abiding in him"
First John 3:15.
And as Saint David says:
"But whoever loves wickedness hates his own soul"
Psalm 10:6.
If someone who hates his brother is a murderer, what is someone who loves wickedness and hates his own soul?
And if the one who hates his brother does not have eternal life abiding in him, how can the one who ends this life loving wickedness and hating his own soul reach the forgiveness of sins, through which one attains life?
Our Lord Himself clearly shows how anyone may reach life, saying:
"If you want to enter life, keep the commandments"
Matthew 19:17.
Therefore, the one who keeps the commandments will enter life.
But who keeps the divine commandments, except the one who, turned to God, has departed from past iniquities before the end of this present life?
Because of this, blessed Paul urges us to
"depart from iniquity, everyone who calls on the name of the Lord"
Second Timothy 2:19.
He said this, knowing that in this time, repentance is fruitful, in which forgiveness is granted to the repentant.
But in the future, there will be the repentance of the wicked, but it will not be fruitful: because the conversion of the wicked will be nonexistent.
They will be sent into outer darkness, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.
There they will be endlessly tortured not only by the infernal punishment of soul and body together but also by the very darkness of their wicked pleasure.
For here, such people will have their own wicked pleasure as part of their punishment's climax, for which their torment remains endless.
For they now scorn the opportunity of the accepted time; and on the day of salvation, they do not seek divine help.
During this time period, God has revealed to us through prophetic word, saying:
"In a favorable time, I listened to you, and on the day of salvation, I helped you."
When the blessed Apostle included this testimony in his letter, he followed it with:
"See, now is the favorable time; see, now is the day of salvation"
Second Corinthians
6:2.
In another place, the same Apostle clearly commends this time so that anyone enlightened by divine grace, who reads attentively and understands appropriately, may not be deceived. They should not seek another time for conversion or forgiveness, knowing that anyone who does not seek forgiveness now will not find it after this life.
Thus, the blessed Paul, writing to the Galatians, says:
"Do not be deceived: God is not mocked, for whatever one sows, that will he also reap. For the one who sows to his own flesh will from the flesh reap corruption, but the one who sows to the Spirit will from the Spirit reap eternal life. And let us not grow weary of doing good, for in due season we will reap, if we do not give up. So then, as we have opportunity, let us do good to everyone, and especially to those who are of the household of faith"
Galatians
6:7 and following.
Who, hearing these words of the Apostle, would not be stirred to the desire to do good works?
Who, straying from God, would not tremble and seek the right path?
Who would not delight in persisting in good sowing, knowing that they will receive nothing other than what they have sown at the harvest?
Chapter Eight
Therefore, we should pay closer attention to this message of apostolic preaching.
He doesn't warn us with such weighty words for no reason when he says: "Do not be deceived," and then adds: "God is not mocked."
Afterwards, he explains where he has seen some go astray, saying: "For whatever a person sows, that will they also reap."
So, whoever thinks they will reap in the future what they have not sown in the present time is mistaken.
But because the difference between sowing and reaping needed to be made clearer, he, being a skilled farmer of discernment, adds: "For the one who sows to their own flesh will reap corruption from the flesh; but the one who sows to the Spirit will reap eternal life from the Spirit."
This is the mistake he mentioned at the beginning of this message, where anyone thinks they will reap something different than what they have sown.
So, whoever sows to the flesh, from which corruption is reaped, and thinks they will reap eternal life, which is reserved for those who sow to the Spirit, is mistaken.
The Apostle then continues, saying: "Let us not grow weary in doing good, for in due time we will reap if we do not give up."
This clearly shows that the term "sowing" refers to each person's actions.
Earlier he had said: "For whatever a person sows, that will they also reap."
Now he says: "Let us not grow weary in doing good, for in due time we will reap if we do not give up."
A true disciple of the Truth, and an outstanding teacher of the nations, taught that justice would not fail in rewarding deeds.
He also distinguished between the time of sowing and reaping-that is, between work and reward.
No one should confuse these times by either demanding the future harvest at the time of sowing or hoping to start good sowing at the time of reaping.
A lazy and idle worker, trapped by sloth, or worse, someone intent on harmful sowing, does not rejoice at the harvest but mourns when he reaps the fitting results of his actions, unable to change the nature of the bad seed.
Furthermore, we should note three things from this apostolic teaching: that we should do good, that we should not grow weary, and that we will reap in due time if we do not give up.
Of these three, two are commands for work, and the third is a promise of reward.
Labor is assigned to the workers, while the promise uplifts their spirits with the hope of the future harvest.
It is common that one who hopes for a sure reward according to the quality of their labor gains more strength from the work.
Therefore, the Apostle adds perseverance to good work, so that anyone who delights in rejoicing at the harvest does not grow weary in sowing.
According to the blessed Apostle, it is necessary for those who persevere in good sowing now to reach the joy of the future harvest.
Otherwise, they greatly deceive themselves, whether by not sowing good deeds until the end of their life but thinking they will reap good things someday, or by lacking perseverance in good work but hoping for joy in the reward.
The blessed Apostle testifies that each one will receive in the harvest what they persistently sow.
Such is the skilled winnower, as mentioned in the Gospel of Matthew.
He will thoroughly clean his threshing floor to ensure there is no mistake in distinguishing between the wheat and the chaff.
He neither puts the chaff, which is destined for the fire, into the granary, nor gives the grain, which is meant for the granary, to the flames.
In the time of the future harvest, the good sowers, those who now persistently sow in tears and will reap in joy, and those who now go out weeping, carrying their seeds, will then come back in exultation, carrying their sheaves.
Psalm 126:5-6.
Just as the one who, although once sowing good seeds, did not maintain persistence in doing good, will be deprived of the joy and fellowship of the harvesters, so too will the one who delights in serving and supporting the nocturnal sower, that is, the devil.
Without rest until death, they sow those things which, when gathered and bound into bundles by the discerning angels, are destined by the Lord's judgment for unquenchable fire.
Matthew 13:25.
Because the fault of subsequent iniquity frustrates all the good labor of the past righteous one, and the merit of iniquity remains, whose labor is all evil.
For the Apostle says: Each will receive his own reward according to his own labor.
First Corinthians 3:8.
That is, in the state in which each one is found when they are commanded to depart from this present world.
Therefore, as the Apostle advises: While we have time, let us do good to everyone, especially to those who belong to the household of faith.
Galatians 6:10.
Chapter Nine
In the letter to the Hebrews, it is not only indicated that conversion is necessary in the present time, but it is also commanded that perseverance should be maintained until the end.
For it says: "See to it, brothers, that none of you has a sinful, unbelieving heart that turns away from the living God."
But encourage one another daily, as long as it is called Today, so that none of you may be hardened by sin's deceitfulness.
We have come to share in Christ, if indeed we hold our original conviction firmly to the very end" (Hebrews 3:12 and following).
Who, then, wouldn't be frightened by the example of the Apostle himself, to turn away from evil deeds and run to God in repentance and conversion, and be careful not to abandon perseverance and become disqualified?
It is worth considering for all the faithful the diligence with which blessed Paul ran, the vigilance with which he fought, and the severity with which he disciplined his body.
He says: "Therefore I do not run like someone running aimlessly; I do not fight like a boxer beating the air."
No, I strike a blow to my body and make it my slave so that after I have preached to others, I myself will not be disqualified for the prize" (First Corinthians 9:26-27).
He said this, knowing it was divinely stated through Ezekiel: "If a righteous person turns from their righteousness and commits sin and dies, they will die for their sin that they have committed" (Ezekiel 18:24).
Therefore, it is pointless for anyone to dream of forgiveness for their sins with empty thoughts if they do not persevere in the Lord's commandments until the end of their present life, or if they do not turn away from their evil ways before the end of their present life.
For it is necessary that every righteous person works out their salvation with fear and trembling (Philippians 2:12); and every wicked person should stop offering their members as instruments of wickedness to sin, but instead offer themselves to God as those who have been brought from death to life, and offer their members as instruments of righteousness to God (Romans 6:13).
They should stop performing such actions, for the wages of those actions is death, as the Apostle Paul says: "For the wages of sin is death" (Romans 6:23).
This death is also called the future wrath of God, which will be inflicted on the unjust and those persevering in evil.
John the Baptist rebukes the Pharisees and Sadducees in a way that also admonishes Christians living wickedly.
He says:
"Brood of vipers, who warned you to flee from the coming wrath? Produce fruit worthy of repentance. And do not think to say to yourselves, 'We have Abraham as our father.' For I tell you that God can raise up children for Abraham from these stones. Even now the ax is laid to the root of the trees. Every tree that does not produce good fruit will be cut down and thrown into the fire" (Luke 3:7 and following).
When the Lord's forerunner said these things, he was undoubtedly speaking to the unjust and the wicked, whom he also called "brood of vipers" due to their imitation of serpents, that is, their diabolical works. He showed them what they should do in this world and what they should fear in the future judgment. By instructing them to produce fruits worthy of repentance, he demonstrated that people can change here and move from the merit of punishment to the merit of the kingdom through the conversion of a repentant soul. Furthermore, by adding that every tree that does not produce good fruit will be cut down and thrown into the fire, he foretold the time of the future judgment. At that time, those who live a sinful life until the end, like unfruitful trees, will not be mercifully granted the remission of sins but will justly receive eternal burning.
Thus, he also predicts that our Savior will come to separate the wheat from the chaff:
"He who has his winnowing fork in his hand will clear his threshing floor, and gather his wheat into the barn, but the chaff he will burn with unquenchable fire" (Luke 3:17).
He informs every Christian through the tenor of the gospel reading to consider, with discernment, what was generously given to each in the first coming of the Savior, and what is expected to be justly repaid to each in the second coming.
Chapter Ten
Our Savior and Judge, who now comes to save, will come in the future to judge.
Now, He comes to turn the wicked into the good through merciful forgiveness,
but in the future, He will come to separate the wicked from the good through just examination.
He demonstrates the benefit of His first coming by saying:
"For the Son of Man came to seek and to save the lost"
Luke 19:10.
He reveals the fearful justice of His second coming by saying:
"The Son of Man will come, and then He will reward each according to their deeds"
Matthew 16:27.
Showing the mercy of His first coming again, He says:
"For God so loved the world that He gave His only Son, that whoever believes in Him shall not perish but have eternal life. For God did not send His Son into the world to judge the world, but to save the world through Him"
John 3:16.
Announcing the judgment of His second coming, He says:
"I have much to say about you and to judge"
John 8:26.
And in another place:
"The word I have spoken will judge you"
John 12:48.
And elsewhere:
"I judge as I hear, and My judgment is just"
John 5:30.
Again, demonstrating the benefit of His first coming, where He finds no one alive but freely raises the dead, making the wicked righteous, He intimates with these words:
"Truly, truly, I say to you, the hour is coming and is now here, when the dead will hear the voice of the Son of God, and those who hear will live"
John 5:25.
He subsequently announces the examination of His second coming, where He will judge the living and the dead, saying:
"Truly, truly, I say to you, the hour is coming when all who are in their graves will hear His voice and come out-those who have done good to the resurrection of life, and those who have done evil to the resurrection of judgment"
John 5:28-29.
Thus, the hearing of His present voice grants life to the dead, as He bestows the grace of faith on the unbelieving and makes the wicked good.
The hearing of His present voice justifies the impious with mercy, saves sinners mercifully, and illuminates the blind with compassion.
Upon hearing His second voice, He will reward the righteous with the crown of justice and punish the wicked for their wrongdoing.
At the sound of His first voice, mercy will come before sinners to redeem them; at the sound of His second voice, judgment will follow to reward the doers.
Here, it is said to all: "Come to me, all you who labor and are burdened, and I will give you rest" (Matthew Matthew 11:28).
There, however, it will be said only to the right: "Come, you blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom" (Matthew 25:34); but to the left, it will be said: "Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire" (Matthew 25:41).
There is such a clear recognition of merits in the pastoral judgment, which will separate the sheep from the goats, so that no goat will be placed on the right, just as no sheep will be placed on the left.
The merits with which people leave this life will remain with them endlessly and unchangeably in the next life, whether the good that divine kindness granted here or the evil that human injustice acquired here.
Therefore, there will be no removal of evils there, although there will be the promotion of the merits of the good.
The evil will remain in punishment, while the good will be perfected in glory.
This is the time when God, as it is written in the psalm: "He has not dealt with us according to our sins, nor repaid us according to our iniquities. For as high as the sky is above the earth, so great is His mercy towards those who fear Him. As far as the east is from the west, so far has He removed our iniquities from us" (Psalm 103:10-12).
But in that judgment, the righteous judge will give the crown of justice, as the Apostle says, to those who love His coming (Second Timothy).
For those doing evil, as Psalm twenty-seven verse four shows, He will repay them according to their deeds and the wickedness of their actions.
He will reward them based on the works of their hands, giving them what they deserve.
This is because the way each person leaves this life is the way they will be in the next life, without a doubt.
In that just judgment, they will not be transformed from corruption to incorruption if they have not already changed from wickedness to righteousness, and from a bad life to a good life in this world.
Therefore, Paul says: We will all indeed rise again, but not all will be changed.
First Corinthians 15:51
When the blessed Apostle said this, he knew it was necessary to explain to the faithful whom he referred to as those who will be changed at the time of the future resurrection, to prevent any uncertain interpretation of his words.
If he had said: We will all rise again, but we will not be changed, no one would believe that any change would happen.
And if he had said: We will all rise again, and we will all be changed; just as everyone is believed to rise again, everyone would also believe that they will all be changed in the same way.
But since he predicted the resurrection of all, yet did not assert that all would be changed, he advised us to carefully investigate who will be those to be changed in the resurrection.
Not wanting to leave this ambiguous, the blessed Paul, to prevent the wicked from sinning more freely if they heard that they would share the same gift of future change with the just, took care to show the gift of that change in his following words:
In a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trumpet:
for the trumpet will sound, and the dead will rise imperishable, and we will be changed.
First Corinthians 15:52
When he says, "we," he shows that those who will partake in the gift of future change with him are those who, in this time, are in communion with Paul and his companions in the church and in living rightly.
Indicating the nature of this change, he says: For this perishable body must put on imperishability, and this mortal body must put on immortality.
First Corinthians 15:53
Thus, just as the change of righteous retribution will follow then, now the change of gratuitous generosity precedes.
The blessed prophet David shows this change when he says: I said, now I begin; this change is the work of the right hand of the Most High.
Psalm 77:10
Chapter Twelve
So, for those who in this present life have transformed from bad to good, the reward of future transformation is promised.
Those who have turned to better things and changed their lives will also be transformed in the reward, gaining the gift of angelic equality.
The Savior himself, who is faithful in his words and holy in all his works (Psalm 145:13), promises this not to the unjust or the wicked, but only to those who live well and righteously.
Those who do not live well are not just, nor will those who despise His commandments be punished unjustly.
Those who love Him keep His commandments, as the Lord Himself says: "Whoever loves me will keep my commandments" (John 14:23).
Therefore, those who truly love God, who cannot be loved unjustly nor ever justly despised, are those who obey His precepts.
These are the ones who, according to the word of the Lord (Matthew 22:30), will be transformed and made equal to the angels of God, incorruptible and immortal by the gift of that transformation.
Not only will their soul be transformed for the better so that it can no longer sin, but their flesh, which was once corruptible and mortal, will also be transformed in the resurrection.
It will be the same as it is now, but neither corruptible nor mortal.
The flesh of both the wicked and the just, which now dies, will be resurrected.
However, the wicked will rise to eternal pain, while the just will remain in eternal happiness.
Just as the wicked will rise to torment, the just will rise to joy.
The wicked will be tormented with their soul in eternal death; the just will enjoy the blessedness of eternal life with their soul.
Therefore, the body of the just, according to the preaching of the Apostle: "It is sown in corruption, it will rise in incorruption; it is sown in dishonor, it will rise in glory; it is sown in weakness, it will rise in power; it is sown a natural body, it will rise a spiritual body" (First Corinthians 15:42 and following).
So, through grace, this is achieved in them: first, here, through justification, in which they are spiritually reborn.
The transformation by divine favor begins; and later, in the resurrection of the body, the change of the justified is completed, leading to perfect and eternal glorification.
For this purpose, grace first changes them through justification, and then through glorification, ensuring that this glorification remains constant and eternal in them.
Here, they are transformed through the first resurrection, which enlightens them to convert; that is, they pass from death to life, from iniquity to righteousness, from unbelief to faith, and from evil deeds to holy living.
Therefore, the second death has no power over them.
About such people, it is said in the Book of Revelation: "Blessed and holy is the one who shares in the first resurrection; over these, the second death has no power" (Revelation 20:6).
In the same book, it is also said: "The one who conquers will not be hurt by the second death" (Revelation 2:11).
Just as the first resurrection consists of the conversion of the heart, so the second death consists of eternal punishment.
Therefore, let everyone who does not want to be condemned to the eternal punishment of the second death hurry to become a partaker of the first resurrection here.
For those who, in this present life, are changed by divine fear and pass from a bad life to a good life, they are the ones who pass from death to life, and who will afterward be transformed from ignominy to glory.
Chapter Thirteen
However, those who are miserable and unfortunate, and who neglect to change from bad to good during their lifetime, as the most holy David condemns their stubbornness, also foretells their future punishment by divine retribution, saying:
"For they do not change and do not fear God"
Psalm
55:19.
And to prevent those who refuse to change from falsely promising themselves forgiveness of sins after this life, he continues and adds:
"He extends his hand in retribution"
Psalm
55:20.
The beginning of this retribution is when the wicked, receiving the due reward for their error in themselves, will be tormented by eternal fire justly for their iniquities.
Nor should this retribution be considered small, where the wicked, deprived of the light of justice, are allowed to wander in their darkness, judged not by the flesh, but by the blindness of the heart.
It also pertains to the fullness of retribution if the blind not only cannot receive the light but even strive to increase the darkness of their blindness with delight.
To such people, the Lord says in the
Psalms
:
"But my people did not listen to my voice, and Israel did not pay attention to me; so I gave them over to the stubbornness of their hearts, to follow their own devices"
Psalm
81:11-12.
About such people, the Doctor of the Gentiles also says:
"Therefore God gave them over to shameful passions"
Romans
1:26.
And again:
"Therefore God gave them over to a depraved mind, so that they do what ought not to be done"
Romans
1:28.
Thus, such people are first given over to their unjust desires, and later they will be handed over to just punishments.
They are given over here to appropriate deeds and later will be handed over to appropriate penalties.
For it is not because the wicked sin pleasurably that they should be considered exempt from the torment of retribution; since they are already severely punished by the very pleasure of sinning, to which they submit by consent, increasing the merit of punishment.
The more they fulfill what unjustly delights them, the more the unjust will receive to grieve even more.
If anyone here is unwilling to turn to God and change from a bad life to the pursuit of a good one, they will not be transformed in the afterlife, where immortality and incorruption are happily granted to the just who have been changed.
Therefore, the wicked or impious-those who believe perversely or live wickedly and do not depart from their unbelief or wickedness before the end of this life-will neither be immortal nor incorruptible in the future retribution.
Instead, they will be corrupted but not consumed; they will die but not be extinguished.
For the perpetual awareness of torment will remain in the dead, where the wretched are not allowed to die in their suffering.
There, the death of the wretched will be such that it does not exclude the soul from the suffering body but keeps it continuously in the suffering body, so that the soul and the body are afflicted together by the eternity of pain.
Thus, the soul will always die with its body, with which it will be forced to share eternal torment without end.
There, the death of the soul and body does not die, because the torment of the body and soul does not end.
This indeed will be the eternal death of the wicked, so they do not die in the eternal fire, ensuring they can never be free from punishment.
Nor is anything taken away from the burning body there, although the unfortunate soul is continuously burned in its body.
To ensure the whole body does not cease to burn, the entire body, along with the soul, continuously persists in the fire.
For in whatever body the soul has lived justly or wickedly, in that same body it will receive eternal punishment or endless joy.
Chapter Fourteen
It is beneficial for everyone, before finishing this present life, to turn away from the fear of future punishment if they truly do not want to be tormented without end after this life.
Consequently, the persistent wickedness of evil people in the sight of God is believed to be forgiven in vain; in whose sight the fruitlessness of good works will not go unpunished.
No one placed on the left is said to go into eternal fire because they took bread from someone eating, but because they did not give it to the hungry; not because they stripped the clothed, but because they did not give clothing; not because they drove anyone out of their own home, but because they did not receive one of Christ's least ones into their home.
So, if one goes into eternal burning for not giving their bread to the hungry, what will happen to the one who took another's bread?
And if the one who did not clothe the naked is thrown into the lake of fire and sulfur, what will happen to the cruel person who strips others of their clothing?
If the greedy possessor of their own goods will not have rest, how will the insatiable thief of others' goods, if they do not turn away in this life, later in vain promise themselves indulgence from a just judge?
Consider the miserable rich man once clothed in purple and fine linen, burning in unquenchable flames not for any other reason than because he never wanted to give even the crumbs of his banquet to the starving poor man Lazarus, being given over to deadly wickedness.
While condemned to endless torment, he remained unworthy of the refreshment of the poor man's finger, who was rejoicing in eternal rest.
The patriarch Abraham showed with a clear answer after this life that neither the good can cross over to the wicked, nor can the wicked ever cross from their punishment to the rest of the blessed.
For he says: Son, remember that you received good things in your life, and Lazarus likewise bad things.
Now he is comforted here, and you are tormented.
And in all this, a great chasm has been fixed between us and you, so that those who want to pass from here to you cannot, nor can they cross from there to us.
(Luke 16:25-26).
Chapter Fifteen
It is important for us to do good now while we have the time to work.
We should strive to be very productive during the harvest, not lazy or unproductive.
It's beneficial for everyone to address their wounds now with the remedy of conversion and repentance, while they can still receive forgiveness for their sins by turning to God.
For repentance in the future will not earn forgiveness.
Those whom God has destined for life will not be repenting then.
According to the Apostle, the sorrow that is according to God leads to stable salvation.
Second Corinthians 7:10
So, for those repenting and converting now, stable and eternal salvation will be granted in the future.
However, the repentance of those who did not repent in this life will have no end in the future.
This repentance will not come from God's generosity but from the torment of punishment.
In such repentance, there will be eternal sorrow because it will bear no fruit.
There, the evil will not turn to good through repentance.
The wicked will have repentance in punishment only to the extent that they can neither escape repentance nor punishment.
The will that kept the wicked hardened to the end here will have endless repentance for its crimes, unable to convert again or escape eternal punishment.
Not all repentance involves the sinner, overtaken by the grace of a merciful God, confessing their sins to seek forgiveness through conversion.
Otherwise, it is like someone suffering greatly from a wound who does not seek a doctor's help.
They declare their pain but do not achieve the remedy to be healed.
Therefore, not everyone who confesses their sin receives forgiveness, because our God looks beyond what we carry in our hearts.
As the psalm says: God searches the hearts and minds.
Psalm 7:10
The Savior also says: "Why do you call me, Lord, Lord, and do not do what I say?"
(Luke 6:46).
From this, we read in the divine Scriptures that some people followed sins with words.
For example, King Saul, directed by God to plunder Amalek
(First Samuel 15:3), fell into sin because he did not keep the Lord's command.
When the prophet Samuel came to rebuke him, Saul, terrified, confessed his sin but did not receive forgiveness because his heart was not right before God
(First Samuel 15:24).
His confession of sin was out of fear of punishment, not out of horror for the sin itself.
He did not hate what he had done but feared the consequences.
He did not truly repent but trembled at the threat of divine wrath.
King David, too, was overcome by the lure of carnal desire
(Second Samuel 11:4).
He not only committed adultery with his soldier's wife but also killed her innocent husband, who was unaware of his wife's violation and free of any crime.
When Nathan the prophet was sent by the Lord to him, David, terrified by the prophetic rebuke, exclaimed: "I have sinned"
(Second Samuel 12:13).
The prophet replied: "And the Lord has taken away your sin; you will not die"
(First Samuel 15:30).
Behold, Saul said: "I have sinned." David also said: "I have sinned."
So, if both confessed their sins with the same words, why was forgiveness not granted to both equally?
It is because God saw a difference in their willingness despite the similarity in their confession. He did not pay attention to the sound of their words but discerned the intention of their hearts.
One truly turned away from sin and immediately cast aside his desire, punishing his own wrongdoing with repentance. The other, though he confessed his sin with words, did not cast aside the desire to sin, bound by the vice of a perverse heart.
Chapter Sixteen
Confessing one's sins is beneficial if, after confessing, the sinner does not repeat the wrongdoing and strives to make amends through good deeds.
As the Apostle says, where sin abounded, grace abounded much more.
Romans 5:21.
However, some people do not understand the power of repentance and fail to repent with the hope of receiving divine mercy.
Instead, their repentance leads them to sin even more, as they despair of receiving forgiveness.
This was the case with Judas the betrayer.
Matthew 27:3.
His repentance did not bring salvation but led to his destruction through despair.
Ultimately, he bound himself with a worse chain of iniquity when he took his own life, which was a graver sin than betraying Christ.
The sin of betraying Christ could have been forgiven if Judas had repented while he was still alive.
But his act of taking his own life cannot be forgiven after his death.
After betraying Christ, Judas still had time to seek forgiveness through the blood that was shed for the forgiveness of sins.
Christ, who died for the ungodly, would not have denied forgiveness to his betrayer if Judas had not lost hope and taken his own life, thus ending the time granted for repentance.
Therefore, Judas did not repent correctly, nor did he accept just punishment for his crime.
Instead, he increased his punishment by taking his own life, thereby eliminating his opportunity for conversion.
By his own hand, he took away the time for repentance.
Most miserable Judas, who, after committing the crime of betrayal, compounded his sin by failing to seek forgiveness.
Thus, his repentance was worse than the betrayal itself.
The sin of betraying the Lord could have been forgiven in time.
But he was punished by his own despair, which left no room for conversion.
Therefore, he didn't help the repentant person, but killed him.
By taking away the time for conversion through killing,
he also took away forgiveness, leaving only despair.
Chapter Seventeen
The opportunity given to us in this time is incredibly valuable for the forgiveness of sins!
Although betraying Christ is far more serious than taking any person's life, those who have betrayed Christ in the present life, if they turn to God with their whole heart, can obtain forgiveness through the blood of Christ.
However, whether someone is a heretic, a pagan-who are undoubtedly punished with eternal fire-or even a Catholic Christian, if they commit murder, adultery, steal, perjure themselves, or give false testimony, and do not repent before the end of this life, they will face endless torment after death.
This is true even though their sins might seem less severe than betraying Christ.
The one who betrayed Christ can be saved if they repent in this life, but anyone who does not repent will suffer eternal torment.
This is not because their sin is greater than betraying Christ, but because the latter recognizes God's mercy and seeks forgiveness at the right time.
Conversely, those who despair of God's benevolence are condemned to eternal death.
Even if their sins seem lesser, neglecting the time granted by God's patience for repentance makes their crime worse.
Thus, it is clear that forgiveness of sins is not granted without repentance in this life, and repentance is futile if forgiveness is despaired of.
In the future, there will be no conversion for the wicked, and their endless repentance will be in vain.
Just as they will never receive forgiveness, their repentance will be eternal but empty.
Because they neglect the time when repentance is beneficial for sinners, and when divine mercy grants the forgiveness of sins.
For this reason, the Lord Himself, comforting His faithful in the Revelation to John and warning the wicked of the punishment to come, speaks thus:
"Let the one who does wrong continue to do wrong; let the vile person continue to be vile; let the righteous continue to do right; and let the holy person continue to be holy.
Behold, I am coming soon, and my reward is with me, to give to each person according to what they have done.
I am the Alpha and the Omega, the First and the Last, the Beginning and the End.
Blessed are those who wash their robes, that they may have the right to the tree of life and may enter the city by the gates.
Outside are the dogs, those who practice magic arts, the sexually immoral, the murderers, the idolaters, and everyone who loves and practices falsehood" (Revelation 22:11 and following).
Who, I ask, can be so stubborn, or who can be found so uncircumcised in heart and ears that they are not frightened, not humbled, not converted by these words?
Who would not weep?
Who would not tremble in their innermost being?
Who would not rush in fear of that righteous judgment to conversion, to find the forgiveness of sins and the grace of eternal salvation?
Woe to the one who does not hurry to transform from chaff into wheat before the time of the final winnowing!
Woe to the one who does not care to be converted from weeds into wheat before the reapers, the angels, come to gather the weeds to be burned from among the wheat (Matthew 13:39)!
For the kind warning of the divine Scripture must not be despised, which commands us to urgently convert and warns the slow of the impending wrath of divine vengeance.
For it says: "Do not delay to turn back to the Lord, and do not put it off day after day; for suddenly the wrath of the Lord will come forth, and in the time of vengeance, He will destroy you" (Ecclesiasticus 5:8).
Chapter Eighteen
To understand that only the time of this present age is granted for human conversion, let's consider the workers whom the Lord called to the vineyard.
Even though He called them at different hours, He completed the calling in the eleventh hour, which is before the end of the day.
The hours when the workers were called represent the ages of this world, during which God called those He converted to Himself with free justification to good work.
The morning of this day spans from the beginning of the world until the flood; the calling of the third hour is from the flood to Abraham; the calling of the sixth hour is from Abraham to David; from David to the people's exile in Babylon, the ninth hour was completed; and the eleventh hour was during the first coming of Christ, when He humbly came in mortal flesh and was killed for the sin of the world.
This is the last calling of the workers, which is happening now until the end of this present age, from His coming in humility to His coming in glory;
from the coming where the good was judged by the evil, so He could mercifully make the evil good, to the coming where He will justly judge both the evil and the good;
from the coming of gracious forgiveness, to the coming of just retribution;
from the coming where He freed the souls of the poor from loans and injustices (Psalm 72:14), to the coming where He will demand His money with interest from those who have found it consumed or not doubled through any good effort (Matthew 25:27).
This is the hour that the blessed John calls the last: "Little children, it is the last hour" (First John 2:18).
After this hour is complete, the Lord will no longer call workers to the vineyard but will come to give each one the reward for their work, as He says: "Behold, I am coming soon, and My reward is with Me" (Revelation 22:12).
Therefore, let him hope to receive the denarius of divine retribution, who, before the end of this present age, works commendably in the Lord's vineyard.
That operation is nothing more than the true conversion of the heart.
As the Apostle says, true conversion involves faith that works through love.
The diversity of hours should be rightly understood, as we mentioned earlier, as the distinction of the ages of the world.
However, we can also interpret this diversity of hours as the stages of each individual's life:
Morning represents a person until infancy ends,
The end of childhood marks the third hour,
The end of adolescence marks the sixth hour,
The fulfillment of youth marks the ninth hour,
The course of maturity marks the eleventh hour,
And then old age, leading to the end, marks the sunset of the whole day.
Therefore, at whatever age of this present life any unjust or impious person turns to God with all their heart, they will immediately receive forgiveness for all past sins.
Chapter Nineteen
Whoever can find in the Gospel or teach that after the end of the day any worker called to the vineyard can justly hope and confidently proclaim to any unrighteous person who has not turned in this present age that they will be granted the opportunity for good works or the grace of forgiveness in the future age.
Likewise, whoever shows that to anyone not called to the work of the Lord's vineyard before the end of the day, a denarius was given by the Lord's command, can justly and fittingly hope that the kingdom of heaven will be conferred by the Lord's generosity to anyone who has not turned before the end of the present life.
If indeed those whom the pious labor of the daytime work in the vineyard has engaged, only they received the denarius's reward after the end of the day; we too, if we wish to reach the denarius of eternal life, must labor in the Lord's vineyard in the present time.
Nor should we disregard the command of the one calling, if we do not wish to be excluded from the generosity of the one rewarding.
For whoever does not work in the vineyard before the end of the day will not be able to receive the denarius after the day has ended.
Because then there will not be a time when anyone is mercifully called to the work of the vineyard, but when the reward is given for past work.
Therefore, there will not be a pious calling there, but a just repayment.
That denarius will neither be given to the idle nor to him who works outside the vineyard.
The idle one is a Catholic who does not want to do good works, because faith without works is idle and dead in itself, as stated in James, Chapter two, verse seventeen.
However, he works outside the vineyard who, established in any heresy, indeed undertakes good works, but by believing wrongly about himself, denies himself the effect of salvation.
For the blessed Apostle Paul says, because everything that is not of faith is sin, as mentioned in Romans, Chapter fourteen, verse twenty-three.
And: Without faith it is impossible to please God, as stated in Hebrews, Chapter eleven, verse six.
Therefore, each one takes away the denarius from himself, each one makes himself a stranger from the fellowship of the workers.
This one indeed because he, established within the Lord's vineyard, did not want to be attentive to the work; that one, however, because he worked outside what he ought to have worked within the Lord's vineyard before the end of the day.
And therefore, he is not allowed into the vineyard because he did not work for his salvation, and the other because he did not work where he could receive the gift of salvation.
So, at the end of the day, neither is allowed to enter the vineyard, and the opportunity for good deeds is taken away.
The bad Catholic did not have the wedding garment at the Lord's banquet, which Paul warns the faithful to fear, saying:
"If indeed, when we are clothed, we are not found naked."
Second Corinthians 5:3.
But the heretic despised coming to the banquet at the acceptable time. So, one will be cast out, and the other will not be allowed to enter.
Now is the time for the chaff to be turned into wheat; now is the time for every sinner to hurry to become wheat from the weeds, if they do not want to be burned by the eternal fire that cannot be extinguished.
For anyone who rejects the grace of the present time, in which the Lord came not to judge but to save sinners, and believes they can remain in their sins, will find no mercy in the future judgment.
Because at the time of winnowing, the winnower will not allow the chaff to be mixed with the wheat, nor will divine severity grant the lazy, useless servant the power of the talents at the time of reckoning. Just as the chaff will then be burned by unquenchable fire, so the wicked and lazy servant, assigned to the outer darkness, will experience eternal weeping and gnashing of teeth.
What else does it mean when that servant is ordered to be tied hand and foot, if not to show that he is to be punished for the guilt of his bad deeds with his hands, and the bad intentions of his will with his feet?
Chapter Twenty
The holy Isaiah, divinely informed, recognized the opportunity of this time and urges us to conversion with these words:
"Seek the Lord while He may be found; call upon Him while He is near. Let the wicked forsake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts; let him return to the Lord, and He will have mercy on him, and to our God, for He will abundantly pardon"
(Isaiah 55:6-7).
Now, therefore, the Lord must be sought while He can be found by those who seek Him.
Now He must be called upon while He is near to those who call.
Now is the time to abandon the way of wickedness and the thoughts of iniquity.
Now is the time for the necessary conversion of the sinner, which, through divine forgiveness, can free one from the guilt of all sin.
Otherwise, he will not see the goodness of God in the land of the living
(Psalm 26:13), if anyone in this land of the dying does not receive the remission of sins.
For the Savior and judge of men Himself has ordained that those whose sins He forgives, He forgives in this land.
This is why He says to the unbelieving Jews:
"But so that you may know that the Son of Man has authority on earth to forgive sins"
(Matthew 9:6).
He did not say this because He could not forgive the sins of those who leave this earth if He wished to, but so that men might recognize the time of divine remission and retribution, unchangeably established by divine ordinance, and not vainly hope that human vanity would hear what divine truth promises.
Hence, He also granted to blessed Peter, that is, to His Church, the power to bind and loose on earth: so that we might understand that in this life, mercy is freely given in the remission of sins, but in the future, a just reward will be given to all according to the quality of their deeds.
We should not doubt that now all sins can be forgiven, and now whatever sins have not been forgiven will then be required.
Blessed David also knew this by the revelation of the Holy Spirit, to whom, as he himself testifies, the Lord had manifested the hidden and secret things of His wisdom
(Psalm 51:6), before he leaves this world.
He asks for the forgiveness of sins, saying: "Forgive me so that I may be refreshed before I go, and I will be no more" (Psalm 38:14).
Surely the blessed prophet would not so earnestly ask for the forgiveness of his sins before the end of this life if he believed that repentance after death would benefit anyone, or that divine favor would grant forgiveness to those who repent then.
Chapter Twenty-One
After this life, although the wicked will feel repentance, they will not receive forgiveness for their sins; instead, their repentance will actually increase their punishment.
This will add to their eternal torment.
The hardness of a perverse heart, which was not softened by sincere confession during their lifetime, will be endlessly burned by avenging flames and punished even more severely by its own remorse.
For what could be worse than being tormented forever by the regret of past deeds, without ever being freed from the torment of the committed crime?
It will not be considered for someone who ends their life in evil deeds that their torment will someday end just because their evil deeds have ceased.
The perversity of their wicked will, which they held onto and loved until the end of their life, will be taken into account, even if they unwillingly lose the life they lived so badly.
For if they did not care to change their evil will during their lifetime, it shows they loved their iniquities so much that, if they could live forever, they would want to remain in their sins endlessly.
Therefore, a wicked person will not be spared just because they can no longer fulfill their evil desires; they will be tortured without end because, as long as they were able to sin, they did not stop sinning.
No end will be given to the punishment of the wicked because, before their life ended, they did not put an end to their crimes.
Although someone who did not want to convert while living could not prolong their evil life as much as they wanted, they could have changed for the better if they had wanted to, before their life ended unwillingly, destined to remain in the evils of hell without end.
Therefore, it is just that the righteous Judge, who gives each according to their works, ensures that those who end their life in evil habits and deeds are tortured in eternal flames.
Indeed, His judgment is fair, as it ensures that the wicked, whose will in life was full of sin, never lack punishment.
They take more pleasure in sinning than in living; they don't sin to live forever, but they want to live forever here so they can keep sinning endlessly.
No one finishes this life securely unless they turn away from wrongdoing before it ends; otherwise, they'll regret their crimes in vain when they can no longer escape torment.
So, repentance isn't prescribed in vain for everyone in this life, and conversion isn't preached pointlessly.
Here, repentance leads to forgiveness if the sinner gives up the desire to sin while still alive.
The merciful and just Lord has set this present time for forgiveness, but He reserves the future for just retribution, where each person will receive a fitting but unending reward based on their faith and deeds.
Chapter Twenty-Two
Therefore, let every wicked person within the Church reject evil behavior and embrace a good life, so they may reach eternal life.
Let every impious person abandon their corrupt beliefs and promptly come to the Church.
Let everyone strive for righteousness if they wish to avoid the torment of the unrighteous.
Let them walk the path of justice, so they may reach the homeland of eternal rest.
Let those who provoke God with evil deeds turn to a good life, acquiring the favor of a gracious God, and receive eternal life, which He abundantly grants to the good without end.
Let no one despair of God's mercy, regardless of the severity of their sins; nor should anyone remain in sin, hoping for God's mercy.
Instead, let the hopeful seek repentance without doubt, so the humility of the penitent may avoid the deadly shipwreck of despair.
Let them love God's mercy while also fearing His justice.
Let them hope that everything can be forgiven upon conversion, but understand that nothing will be forgiven to a hardened heart.
Now, let the wicked change their ways to avoid punishment.
Let them flee from guilt and receive pardon.
For in this time, remission is granted when a change of will is accompanied by a change of merit.
Let everyone who labors and is burdened come to be refreshed by God who calls them:
let them take upon themselves the light yoke and light burden of the Savior;
let them learn from Him because He is gentle and humble in heart, if they wish to find rest for their soul;
let those who have turned away run to conversion;
let the wicked depart from iniquity, and let the wandering return to the path of truth.
Let them seek the mercy of the Lord, who does not want them to suffer misery without end.
Let them seek eternal life, so they will not die forever.
Let them come before the face of God in confession, so they will not be condemned to eternal punishment.
Right now, repentance is fruitful; forgiveness of sins is granted to those who are penitent.
The kingdom of heaven is open to those who turn to God.
It's a place where life is eternal and joy is unending: where death doesn't take life from the joyful, nor can sorrow take joy from the living.
At the end of this life, each person's faith and works determine their eternal reward.
Just as those who do not turn away from sin before the end of this life will not find rest beyond, those who obey divine precepts and turn from their sins during this life, persevering in right faith and good living within the Catholic Church until the end, will be saved.
Amen.