Letter on Blessed Echeria
The letter praising the most blessed Echeria, written by the monks of Bergidensium and delivered by Valerius, begins.
Dear holy and God-pleasing brothers, I urge you to thoughtfully consider the great efforts required to attain the rewards of the kingdom of heaven.
As we reflect on the deeds of the strongest and holiest men, we find even greater admiration for the remarkable strength of virtue found in feminine fragility, as demonstrated by the exceptional history of the most blessed Echeria, who proved stronger than all worldly men.
When the nurturing teachings of the Catholic faith and the bright clarity of sacred religion finally reached this western region, albeit late, the most blessed nun Echeria, driven by divine grace, embarked on a vast journey across the world with the Lord's help, showing unwavering courage.
With the Lord as her guide, she reached the most sacred and desired places of the Lord's birth, passion, and resurrection, as well as the sites of countless saints and martyrs in various provinces and cities, all in pursuit of prayer and spiritual growth.
The more she learned from holy teachings, the more the flame of holy desire burned inexplicably in her heart.
She diligently explored all the writings of the Old and New Testaments and sought out miraculous sites of saints documented across the world, in provinces, cities, mountains, and other remote places.
Despite many years of diligent exploration, she traversed all these places with God's help.
Finally, she reached the eastern regions, visiting with great eagerness the most glorious monasteries of the Theban monks and the holy retreats of the hermits.
Protected by the blessings of the saints and filled with the nourishing clarity, she turned her attention to all the provinces of Egypt.
She searched with great purpose for the ancient pilgrimage sites of the Israelite people, describing the abundance, fertility, and grandeur of each province, the fortifications of the cities, and their various beauties, praising the most charming ones of all.
Following this, with the grace of prayer from the most sacred mountain of the Lord and driven by the desire to follow the footsteps of the Israelites leaving Egypt, she ventured into the vast wilderness and the different deserts, as detailed in the book of Exodus.
There, where the Israelites walked for three days without water, and the Lord provided miraculous water from a rock through Moses when they complained, their faith ungrateful, in her heart, thirsty for God, a fountain of living water flowed, springing up into eternal life.
And where the multitude, hungry, received holy manna from heaven by divine provision, yet longed for the undesirable food of Egypt, she, refreshed by the nourishment of God's word, tirelessly gave thanks to God and bravely continued her journey.
While they often heard the voice of the Lord, seeing His grace go before them day and night in a pillar of cloud and fire, yet thought of turning back uncertainly, she, having once received the evangelical voice, joyfully hastened to the mountain of the Lord without hesitation.
While they, unable to endure Moses with the law of the Lord for forty days, made idols for themselves as gods, she, anticipating the coming of the Lord after the end of the world and almost seeing Him present, went to the holy mountain Sinai, from where we hope He will come in the clouds of heaven in His time.
She forgot her feminine frailty, moving with tireless steps uplifted by the divine right hand to the summit of this mountain, which reaches up to the height of the clouds.
With the help of divine grace, he reached the sacred peak of that rocky mountain where the almighty God chose to dwell when He gave the holy law to blessed Moses.
There, filled with joy and amidst frequent hymns of prayer, he offered sacrifices to God and gave immense thanks to His glorious majesty before moving on to see more.
In fact, he almost traveled across the borders of the entire world, also taking the opportunity to climb other enormous mountain peaks.
One such peak was the very high Mount Nebo, much like the often-mentioned Sinai, from whose summit blessed Moses gazed upon the Promised Land.
Another towering peak was Mount Pharam, where Moses prayed with raised arms while the people fought until victory was achieved.
He also climbed the summit of the massive Mount Tabor, where the Lord appeared glorified with Moses and Elijah before the disciples.
Another similar peak, also very large, was Mount Hermon, where the Lord taught the Beatitudes to the disciples, known as a desert place.
Additionally, there was another very high mountain called the Mount of Elijah, where the prophet Elijah lived and one hundred prophets were hidden.
Similar to these is the mountain looming over Jericho, also consecrated by the Lord.
Climbing all these with the same purpose, and since altars of holy churches were built at each of these places, he offered vows with rejoicing and thanksgiving to almighty God everywhere.
Therefore, it is clearly understood that while he fervently sought to reach the heights of the kingdom of heaven, the companionship of the holy virgins in the paradise of delights, and the rewards of grace with a passionate spirit, he bore the hardship of such great heights lightly.
Supported by the Lord, he maintained unyielding determination on these countless mountain climbs.
Can you imagine the immense fear of future judgment that gripped her heart?
How her fear, driven by the love of the highest charity, surged within her, and how intensely the fervor of divine hope and faith burned?
No journey across the world could shake her, no stormy sea or mighty river could stop her, no massive mountain or harsh terrain could lessen her resolve, and no fierce cruelty of ungodly nations could terrify her.
With the Lord's help, she undoubtedly fulfilled all her devout desires with unyielding courage to the very end.
So, dearest brothers, why aren't we ashamed, we who have physical strength and perfect health, that a woman fulfilled the holy example of the patriarch Abraham?
For the eternal reward of everlasting life, she transformed her fragile female nature into strength like iron.
Although she walked this world amidst the constraints of poverty, she reached paradise in the rest and glory of exultations.
Born on the far western shore of the ocean, she became known in the East.
While seeking remedy for her soul, she provided a remarkable example for many souls to follow God.
Here, she refused to find rest so she might confidently reach eternal rest with the palm of victory.
Here, she mortified her earthly body with earthly honor to prepare her innocent soul for the heavenly Lord.
Here, she exercised her voluntary freedom as a pilgrim, so she might inherit the heavenly realms in the choir of holy virgins with the glorious Queen of Heaven, the Mother of the Lord, Mary.
Sometimes, dear friends, those of us who have chosen to faithfully serve the Lord in religious life, even if we can't fully emulate the incredible example of such a woman, should still strive to earn the Lord's grace.
There are many paths to merit that lead to the heavenly kingdom.
As much as our strength allows, with the Lord's help, we must prepare ourselves tirelessly, day and night, through hard work, vigilance, fasting, frequent prayers, and various acts of regular service.
We must abstain from all illicit pleasures, worldly temptations, and various sins.
Otherwise, while we spend this short time in negligence, when she, along with the holy virgins, meets the coming Lord with a lamp of shining holiness blazing with oil, we might, heaven forbid, find ourselves shut out with closed doors and darkened lamps, rejected wickedly, and asking in vain for entry into life because we waited for the Lord's coming with idle lethargy.
Let us remember the words of our Lord saying: "Walk while you have the light, lest the darkness overtake you." And: "The one who perseveres to the end will be saved."
For as one exits this life, so they will be presented in judgment, and each will receive according to their works.
Epitameron of the Consummation of This Book
In order to strengthen morals and guide souls, with the gracious help of the Almighty Lord, I have obediently and confidently followed your command, most blessed Father, aiming to reveal the path of a religious life to those brothers who are unaware.
To the best of my ability, I have frequently gone through the volumes with confidence until I completed this book of the teachings of the Fathers.
Here, we hope for the radiant light of doctrine to shine brilliantly.
Just as the rising sun dispels the night's darkness with the approach of day, this light enters the dark heart of ignorance, bringing clarity.
Just as a sweet, flowing stream spreads abundantly over dry land, multiplying the earth's bounty a hundredfold,
it demonstrates that the harvest of souls is nurtured by this stream, enriching and fertilizing the most abundant and unfailing joys of paradise.
The Vanity of Worldly Wisdom
I urge you not to seek flashy decorations or get caught up in fancy language.
Don't focus on the paths of the wicked as they move through time.
The foolish often mistake the shocking madness of the wicked for wisdom, and it's truly astounding.
With trust in straightforward speech, I wish to speak to you, O gracious Father.
At the dawn of the world, after the angelic rebellion, God prepared hell with immense and terrible punishments for the devil and his angels; and created the indescribable beauty and pleasure of paradise for the first man and his descendants.
The fiercest enemy, driven by cruel zeal and inflamed by envy, sought to ensure that humans would not restore what the fallen angels lost through pride.
He ensnared humanity with the deceit of his own rebellion.
As a result, humans forgot and abandoned God, their creator, and instead worshipped empty, carved images, honoring the devil in vain.
Seeing that Almighty God recognized the ignorance and blindness of human transgression, He sent His only Son into the world.
Like the rising sun, He banished all the darkness of the world with the brightness of His splendor.
At the first coming of His incarnation, our Savior, taking on human nature from the Virgin, brought light to a world destined to perish and enveloped in the darkness of ignorance, with His shining brightness.
He nurtured it like a nurse carrying a child in her arms, fostering it with the nourishment of His teachings, comforting it with the examples of the learned Fathers, and soothing it with the wonders of miracles.
Rescued from the shipwreck of the stormy sea, He led it to the harbor of faith.
The sacred teachings of the Gospels, which He spoke with His mouth, He fulfilled in action.
He redeemed His Church through His suffering, purchased it with the price of His blood, destroyed the destruction of death by His death, and through His resurrection revealed the confidence of human resurrection and the hope of eternal life.
He foretold with the voice of the Gospel that He would come again for the terrible judgment.
Before His Ascension, He sent the assembly of His holy apostles and disciples, whom He had taught attentively and instructed perfectly, to the remaining darkness of the world's ignorance.
Following the example of their Master and Lord, they spread out across all parts of the world, filled with the Holy Spirit.
Like burning lamps through the dark blindness of the age, they illuminated the whole world, traversed the earth, preaching the word of God, and taught all nations, baptizing them in the name of the most blessed Trinity.
They expanded the Catholic Church in the order of their honor, appointing holy bishops.
With the palm of martyrdom and the victory of triumph, following in the footsteps of their Lord and Master, they now rejoice eternally in glory with Him in the heavenly kingdom.
Across the vast ranks of martyrs, from the elderly to the youngest infants, including young boys, teenagers, and adolescents, as well as virgins, widows, and married women, all turned away from worldly riches.
They saw earthly relationships and inheritances as worthless.
This wasn't limited to ordinary people but also included bishops, kings, leaders, and other powerful figures of their time.
Among them, as far as our limited knowledge allows, we'll highlight a few names.
From the heights of the papal priesthood, there were many.
In terms of royalty, there was a Caesar named Crispus, King Ermenegild of the Goths, King Aucuia of the Barbarians, Duke Hypolitus, Count George, and a queen named Alexandria.
Along with those mentioned, they relinquished their treasures and lands, and all vast wealth, as well as the ornate and luxurious displays of the world.
When severe persecution arose, they willingly offered themselves to their persecutors and executioners, enduring violent tortures, fires, beasts, racks, claws, prisons, chains, stones, whips, swords, and other punishments.
They did not spare their own bodies, surrendering their mortal and corruptible bodies to destruction, so that they might receive from the Lord a body comparable to the everlasting and immortal brightness of angels, remaining forever in eternal glory.
Therefore, rejoicing, they gave up their lives in death so that with the triumph of victory and the reward of virtue, they might ascend to the heavenly kingdom, receiving from the Lord unfading crowns and splendid robes of eternal life.
For this reason, they scorned the decay of riches and perishable treasures in this world, choosing instead to possess the immense and infinite treasure in the kingdom of heaven.
They rejected marriage, family ties, and temporary earthly inheritance, viewing them as worthless as dung.
This was all to partake in the indescribable glory of eternal life with the angels, with whom they will reign and rejoice forever.
Amen.
After their triumphant victory, monasteries were established for monks and nuns.
In these places, the nobly born of both sexes, who were wealthy in riches, scorned the pleasures of a frivolous world.
They saw the splendor of worldly delights as nothing, giving up worldly possessions and claiming nothing as their own.
They became like their own servants and various humble people, taming their hearts under the gentle yoke of the Redeemer.
Half-naked and driven by the fervor of faith, they eagerly dedicated themselves to serving the Lord.
In a similar way, others left secular life, just as the Eastern Theban Fathers had done, fleeing to deserts and vast solitudes.
They lived in small and narrow huts, remained in caves and earth caverns, wore rough skins, and survived on bread and water alone.
Some abandoned worldly vanity so completely that they fled to the desert wilderness, rejecting all human contact and assistance.
Without homes or fixed residences, they wandered alone through various solitudes among beasts and wild animals.
They settled wherever nightfall found them, subsisting on herbs and roots until the end of their present life, enduring in this state of deprivation.
Here are the individuals we mentioned earlier, living with complete self-discipline, dedicating themselves to constant vigils, fasting, and uninterrupted prayers.
They engaged in various crafts, consistently pursuing all religious practices and the duties of psalmody, humbling themselves unto death.
They chose the narrow path, leading a life of strict martyrdom, as it is written, because there are two types of martyrdom: one in secret and the other in public.
The merit of secret martyrdom lies in the virtue of being ready to suffer, burning within the soul.
Those who endure the traps of a hidden enemy, love their adversaries in this world, resist all carnal desires, reject the temptations of a wanton age, live with strict abstinence, and practice all forms of spiritual exercise by offering themselves in their hearts to the Almighty Lord, were also martyrs even during peaceful times.
They received the same palms of victory and unfading crowns as the first martyrs.
They persevered in the hidden contrition of martyrdom until the end of their lives.
What is sometimes astonishing is that back then, as the Catholic faith was beginning, people who were not yet fully instructed in the teachings of truth, but had only just begun to believe, were fervent with faith.
They strived for the trophy of perfect martyrdom and the diverse prize of confession, and triumphantly entered the heavenly kingdoms as victors.
But in our times, people who are diligently learned in the knowledge of the Old and New Testaments hear the Lord daily through the voice of the Gospel, which cries out and says: Come to me, all you who labor and are burdened, and I will refresh you.
Take my yoke upon you, and learn from me, for I am gentle and humble in heart, and you will find rest for your souls.
They're not unaware of the kingdom of heaven, the paradise of delights, the company of angels, eternal life, and the rewards for the righteous.
They surely understand that the coming of the Lord and His judgment is near.
For the worst hell-dark Tartarus, eternal fire, immortal worms, endless torments, wailing, groaning, and gnashing of teeth-awaits.
If there's any doubt about the terrors of hell, I point to sacred Scripture as proof.
On the island of Sicily, through the dreadful and terrible chasm of Vulcan's cauldron, a horrible abyss spews flames over that savage land.
So, even those who do not believe in the fires of hell should fear them when they see them.
We often hear the Gospel saying that those on the right of the Lord's fearsome majesty, placed at His terrible tribunal, are the righteous transformed to resemble angels.
Their faces will shine like the rising sun in all its strength, clothed in robes of dazzling white, shining in the presence of the Lord.
Standing in the glory of radiant whiteness, they will hear the sweet voice of the Lord, saying: "Come, blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world," and so on.
However, those on the left will hear the terrible and fierce voice of the Lord, saying: "Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels."
Then, because of the greatness of the Judge, the valley of tears, called Josaphat, will be torn apart, and a dreadful lake will appear, boiling with fire, pitch, bitumen, and sulfur among waves and storms of flames.
Filled with restless and immortal worms, prepared for the destruction of punishments, where no mercy or slightest breath of relief is found.
Into this, along with the devil and his angels, all the impious, the wicked, sinners, and unjust will be cast down.
Then, by the command of the Lord, the earth will close again from above, leaving the unfortunate in outer darkness, suffering various unjust and endless tortures.
They will burn forever, seeking an end to death, but they won't be able to find it.
This will be death without dying, unending decay, and an infinite end.
After this, a new heaven and a new earth will appear, shining seven times brighter than silver;
a radiant and immense light will shine with eternal clarity, remaining forever without any shadows of night.
Then, the holy heavenly city of Jerusalem will be revealed, glorious with pure gold, fortified with immense walls, and adorned with the transparent beauty of every precious stone.
Built square with three sets of enclosures and twelve gates on each side, each made from a single shining pearl, everyone will enter the Jerusalem of Almighty God with great joy and exultation, walking with pure and innocent steps on streets gleaming with pure gold.
Thus glorified with extraordinary beauty, they will worship their Lord and Creator, who shines on the throne of glory with indescribable brightness of His most excellent majesty.
Moreover, each individual, gathered immediately in distinguished groups according to their virtues and merits, will be placed in the bosom of the stellar dwellings there, among indescribable groves and herbs with visible greenery and beautiful fertility, blooming forever, fragrant with the nectarous scent of ambrosial aroma, and overflowing with various delightful pleasures of paradise, and all that immense glory of the heavenly kingdom, which human frailty cannot comprehend.
In this, everyone will rejoice in the first bloom of youth during the flourishing summer and shine transformed with an angelic brightness.
They will celebrate the everlasting majesty of eternal life, praising the Lord, the creator of all, with whom they will reign forever through endless ages.
Amen.
Therefore, I ask each of you who thinks sensibly to consider how foolish it is for someone to boast about having worldly wisdom.
Or how utterly poor it is to gather perishable wealth through the insatiable greed of this world, when everyone knows without a doubt that immense treasures are reserved in the kingdom of heaven as a reward for the righteous.
And eternal punishment in the depths of hell is prepared for the unjust.
Since each person on earth has been given the freedom of their own will to choose between these two paths, up or down, to possess whichever they choose, similarly, two paths have been set before us: the narrow and constricted one, which leads to the kingdom of heaven, and the wide and spacious one, which leads to the unspeakable torments of hell.
Each may walk the path they choose.
The narrow path requires a person to humble their body and break their heart with all the rigor of abstinence, rejecting everything that is evil and earnestly doing whatever is good and pleasing to God.
And whatever they do not want to happen to themselves, they should not do to anyone else, but whatever they wish for themselves, they should sincerely wish for others.
The wide and spacious path, however, is the pleasurable and detestable corruption of the flesh, along with lust and the shameful violation of decency through crimes and misdeeds, or all deadly sins.
Let us now see and consider more carefully with our hearts what this so-called wisdom of the world is, which is often praised by fools, so that they willingly abandon the path of eternal life and gladly walk the path of eternal death.
Oh, how often what the world calls wisdom is actually madness.
God's chosen ones possess true wisdom, fully rejecting the pleasures of the world as if they were nothing but filth.
By choosing the narrow path, they become followers of the highest Shepherd, rejoicing with Him now in the kingdom of heaven, where they will reign forever and ever.
Amen.
Those who have mastered the deceptive tricks of the ancient enemy, driven by insatiable and detestable worldly desires-the root of all evil-engage in alluring acts of savage crime and impurity.
They walk the broad and spacious path, following in the footsteps of the devil, eagerly rushing toward eternal fires and the harshest torments in hell, prepared for the devil and his angels.
With them, they will be severely tortured for all eternity.
I urge you not to dismiss these words as mere ravings from new apocryphal writings, for these small streams are faithfully drawn from the vast river of the holy Scriptures.
If illness troubles us, we should not be saddened if, due to physical weakness and discomfort, we cannot stand to pray and sing aloud.
These challenges help us overcome the desires of the body.
Fasting and labor are established for us because of shameful pleasures.
If this illness becomes overwhelming, be cautious in these matters.
Just as strong medicine is used to treat illness, so too is our life pruned by bodily sickness.
It is a great strength to show patience during illness and give thanks to the Lord.
If we lose our sight, let's not be overly troubled; we have lost an external service, but with our inner eyes, we behold the glory of the Lord.
If we become deaf, let's not think we've lost anything crucial.
Our hands may be weakened by some ailment, but we have fortified our inner selves against the enemy's temptations.
Even if weakness affects our whole body, health grows within our inner self.
Thanks Be to God Always
Blessed Valerius's Sayings to the Blessed
Donadeum's Writings
To clarify the two aforementioned rewards, I've decided to share something with your holiness that I recently discovered through divine arrangement in our times.
When I was a young man, eager for holy religion, I left my homeland to seek out places of peace.
I found myself staying for a while in a large and important church where a community of brothers often gathered.
Among them was a brother named Maximus, a writer of books and a meditator on psalms, who was very wise and composed in all his actions.
I felt a special connection of love with him.
During that time, he became gravely ill, suffered physically, and passed away, only to return to life after many hours.
Once he regained his health, he told me in detail:
"As soon as I left my body, an angel of light, whose beauty is beyond description, took me to an incredibly delightful place. Its beauty surpasses anything in this world, even in springtime, and no thought can compare to it.
There, a splendid light of indescribable brightness shone brilliantly."
He led me, and I followed through the delights of that paradise.
The joyful landscape was adorned with various kinds of imperishable flowers; roses of glowing red, lilies of shining white, and an array of purple, saffron, and other colors, all radiating beauty.
I was amazed to see clear streams flowing throughout the forest groves, rich in delightful admiration; the ineffable beauty of everything was blooming with outstanding brightness and adorned with the sweet fragrance of thyme. An ambrosial, nectar-like scent filled the air.
As I marveled at these incredible wonders, which words cannot describe and my heart can barely comprehend, we arrived at the heart of this celestial paradise.
There, a life-giving stream of unimaginable beauty flowed, its waters clear and shimmering over silvery sand.
The angel turned to me and said, "Taste this water." It had an exquisite, indescribable flavor and smelled like balsam. He asked, "Does your land have such water?" I replied, "My land has nothing good in it."
As he led me through these delightful places, we reached the end. He asked, "Do you like this place? Does your land have such beauty, or do you wish to live here?" I kissed his feet and replied, "I want to stay here with you forever, for my land is detestable and unspeakable, with nothing good but scandal and ruin."
Then, leading me to the edge where the land ended, he showed me a dreadful and terrifying abyss. The ground plunged down to the depths of hell. He said, "Now listen at this precipice."
Leaning toward that horrifying depth, I could see nothing, as a dark cloud rose from it, appearing like a wall of the same paradise. Listening closely, I heard nothing but wailing, groaning, lamenting, mourning, the gnashing of teeth, and a stench that was unbearable and horrifying. Terrified, I cried out, "Lord, hold me, lest I fall."
He reassured me, "Do not fear, for you will not fall now. Rise up." Trembling and afraid, I stood up, and he asked, "Which do you prefer? The beauty you saw before, or this hell you have just observed?" I replied, "I prefer to remain with you in that beauty, for I cannot even bear to look at that dreadful hell." He then said to me, "Good."
Go now, return to your home.
If you truly repent and come back to this beautiful place, I will welcome you, and you will stay with me forever.
But if you act wickedly and do not change your life through repentance, you will be cast into this terrible hell forever.
When I heard this, I fell at his feet, pleading: Lord, have mercy on me.
Please do not send me back to that wicked land, for I want to be here with you.
But I do not know where to return.
He said: If you do not know where to return, I will show you.
Do you see the path on that mountain?
Follow it.
When you have crossed the mountain, you will find three men: one writing, another dictating, and the third holding a staff.
When you reach them, greet the one with the staff, and he will show you the way you should walk.
Hearing this, and not daring to object, I set off eagerly on the path.
When I reached the three men I had been told about, I greeted the one I was instructed to, and he showed me the way.
As I quickly continued on my journey, I suddenly opened my eyes and saw my neighbors gathered around, conducting a funeral.
My body was in the middle as they performed the customary rites.
I immediately recovered from my weakness and lived for some time in this world.
Finally, after doing penance, I departed from my body again.
The Monk Bonellus
As I share these stories with you, I'm reminded of another similar event.
A religious man named Bonellus once visited me.
I'm going to tell you about the profound distress and sorrow he shared with me outside the window of my first prison cell, revealing everything.
He said: Since I was previously confined in the strictest prison, I tormented myself with harsh fasting and performed all my devotional exercises in great poverty, all while diligently fearing the judgment of the Lord.
One day, however, I was caught up in an ecstasy and guided by an angel into a most delightful place of joy.
There, he led me into a small room made of the purest gold, dazzling stones, and various sparkling gems and pearls.
The room had an incredible appearance, with shelves built on its sides and ceilings, all shining with the brilliant glow of gold and adorned with ornaments made of the most precious stones and pearls, radiating immense light.
What more can I say, or what should I think?
The beauty of this dwelling and that place is beyond estimation and comparison, as neither the words of man nor thought can adequately praise it.
Then the angel said to me: If you persevere until the end, I will receive you in this dwelling place.
After some time had passed, an evil spirit of laziness and useless wandering strongly troubled me, and I was led away by my old habits, abandoning the dwelling.
Eventually, I lost my mind and was once again caught up in an ecstasy by a malicious angel and was thrown into an abyss.
It was not an entrance to a well, but rather like a pinnacle or a piece of land cut off.
As I descended with the first impact, like a stone dropped into the deep, I stopped after a vast distance, my foot catching on a small ledge on the side of the tall wall.
As I recovered there a little, a voice said: Go!
Once again, I was thrown down an even longer distance.
I landed a second time on a slightly wider step.
There, I encountered a poor man whom I immediately recognized because he had visited me during my earlier confinement, sick and begging.
I kept him with me for many days.
With the little resources provided by the Lord's kindness to good people, I nourished his soul, which had weakened from hunger, until he regained his health.
He pleaded on my behalf with the wicked and cruel executors who were leading me, asking them to grant me just a little more time there.
As I was recovering slightly, I heard a voice shouting: "Go, go!" For the third time, I was thrown down a double height until I reached the depths of hell, where they brought me before the most wicked devil. He was terrible and fearsome, bound with the strongest chains. On his head sat an iron bird resembling a raven, to which the top of those chains was attached.
From the immense punishments, as much as I could remember, I will recount as he described.
A massive and indescribable fire burned like the thickest burning torch.
Above that fire was a nearby and not very high covering resembling brass, where the overflowing flame struck.
From that fire emerged a surging pitch-black sea, which covered an immense area.
It boiled with a cruel and most dreadful heat.
When I stood before that most atrocious judge, suddenly three most wicked angels arrived.
One of them was an enormous giant.
The second was shorter, reaching up to his shoulders.
The third was small, only up to his middle.
The first two presented two souls of sinners.
The smallest one, however, offered nothing, for which he was severely rebuked, and he ordered those who had brought the souls to throw them into that most dreadful fire, and so they did.
After these events, they led me down to that fiery sea and showed me the deepest pit of the abyss, known for being the most severe and cruel of all punishments.
Overwhelmed with fear, I couldn't bring myself to look inside, when suddenly, many archers appeared and began shooting arrows at me.
Yet, I felt their arrows as if they were just drops of cold water.
As I resisted them with the sign of the cross all around, someone came and rescued me from their unjust control and brought me back to this heavenly light.
After describing all these experiences, he said:
I want to create a retreat for myself, with just enough space for me on both sides, because I'm very afraid of falling into such a terrible ruin again.
And I told him: Start with that, which you can freely bring to completion without any danger of despair until the end.
For it is written: It's better not to start a plan than to lead it to a regrettable end.
So, he went to the city of Legion, returned to the bodies of the holy martyrs, and remains there to this day.
Heavenly Revelation
A long time ago, the blessed Fructuosus, of holy memory, began his fruitful conversion by living a hermit's life in the wilderness and vast solitudes of our shared world, among various rocks, caves, and mountain valleys.
He lived like the Eastern monks, in total abstinence and holy exercises, shining with such glorious miracles of virtue that he could easily be compared to the ancient Theban Fathers.
During those times, he had a young boy with him named Baldari, who was skilled in stonework and built a path for him through caves in inaccessible places.
I learned this directly from Baldari, who is now living in old age, as you know well.
Just a few days ago, this man, whom I want to tell you about, recounted a miracle to me, trembling and with amazement, that Almighty God recently commanded to be shown for our edification this year.
He said, "When I was lying down, overwhelmed by severe illness, as the night passed and dawn's light began to rise, my soul left my body and was taken by three very bright doves, one of which carried a banner above the head of the cross.
They swiftly carried me, and we ascended through the heights of the sky, reaching the East's expanse.
At first, we arrived above the stars of heaven.
There, they led me to a high mountain of incredible beauty, covered by a crowd of countless elders dressed in white.
They brought me to stand before the majesty of the Lord.
As I stood there, amazed and in awe, seeing him seated on the throne of his glory, surrounded by an innumerable multitude, I asked, 'Who is this powerful one who sits alone among such a host of powers?'
And they said, 'He is our Lord Jesus Christ.'
While I stood in awe, amazed by such indescribable and immense beauty beyond comprehension, the Lord said to those who had brought me:
"Return him to his body, for his time is not yet complete."
As they were taking me back, the Lord told them,
"Wait a little, because the sun will rise soon. Let it pass first, so that its rays do not scorch him."
While we waited, the sun rose from the East, passing beneath us with great speed. It glowed with fiery brilliance and shone with immense brightness, unmatched in its enormous circular shape.
In front of it flew a large red bird, its back shaded in a darker color. It beat its wings with a loud, crackling sound, cooling the sun's intense heat with the air it stirred. This bird, moving with lively speed, passed by.
After this terrifying vision faded, we began to descend. With the full gaze of my mind, I saw the entire world, varied with seas and rivers, cities with walls, churches, mountain cliffs, and different buildings adorned with great beauty, filled with people and various nations.
As I looked longer, I was suddenly back in my body, opened my eyes, and removed the sorrow from those present, giving them the joy of consolation.
The Penance of the Monks
Two brothers, troubled by the spirit of lust, left and got married.
Later, they said to each other: What did we gain by leaving the angelic order and entering into this impurity, only to face fire and torment afterward?
Let's return to the desert and repent for what we've done.
Upon reaching the desert, they asked the Fathers to accept them as penitents, confessing their actions.
They were secluded for an entire year, both receiving equal portions of bread and water.
However, they appeared different; one was pale and very sad, while the other was strong and bright.
The Fathers were amazed since they had received the same food and drink.
They asked the sad and afflicted one: What were you meditating on in your cell?
He said: For the wrongs I did, I kept thinking about the punishments I was to face, and fear made my bones cling to my flesh.
They asked the other: What were you thinking about in your cell?
He replied: I was giving thanks to God for saving me from the world's defilements and the punishments to come, bringing me back to this angelic confession.
Remembering God's mercy constantly, I was joyful.
The elders said: Both have equal repentance before God.
About the Monkhood.
A seventh kind of monkhood has recently been added, which is considered worse than the previous ones.
In the past, from the very beginning of the church's construction, there was a tremendous fervor for the Kingdom of Heaven, and the fear of the Lord deeply moved people's hearts.
This wasn't just because of the frequent gatherings of the cenobites, which multiplied the number of monks, but also because the deserts were filled with the cells of dedicated hermits.
Even in these distant western parts, a few sacred religious communities began to emerge, and monasteries were built in isolated areas by a few chosen and devoted men, with rare assistance from the Lord.
From these communities, the Redeemer welcomed many souls, purified from sins, into the heavenly kingdoms.
As the end of the world approaches, love diminishes, severe wickedness increases, and insatiable worldly desires burn stronger, while the envious hostility of demons intensifies.
In the most sacred places, only a few chosen men truly turn to the Lord with all their heart.
To prevent these monasteries from becoming desolate, swineherds are taken from their families, along with many others from various backgrounds, and children from their homes.
They are unwillingly brought up in monasteries, shaved, and tasked with duties, and are falsely labeled as monks.
Some people, who have not been long exposed to the world through active life, worldly pursuits, or work, join holy religion in monasteries not by choice but unwillingly.
In their hearts, they do not develop a true fear of the Lord or a desire for the heavenly kingdom.
They are not rooted in the humility of obedience or the love of genuine charity.
Instead, they grow with the pride of arrogance, inflated with conceit, and become insatiably immersed in greed and the love of money, given over to gluttony and excessive drinking.
They are consumed by a fierce flame of envy, so when they see anyone wholeheartedly converting and faithfully serving the Lord, performing good works that please God, they become envious and blinded by the dark shade of envy.
Those originally belonging to these monasteries, who should defend their rightful duties and possessions, rise up fueled by envy and assume a cruel hatred against the just work, striving to hinder it with various public and secret plots.
Consider, I beg you, how much their own evil will punish them, those whom even the good of others punishes.
Who can help someone who makes themselves their own executioner through envy?
How can they find salvation when they turn the good of others into their own destruction through misuse?
When they are fiercely elevated to the peak of pride, they incur the ruin of their first downfall.
It is written that when the cruel spirit of pride infects someone, it makes them like the devil; and whoever is made similar through vice will be delivered to endless torment with similar destruction.
Moreover, they are so ensnared by the hypocrisy of false religion that they display the false habit of sacred religion in the eyes of worldly observers, as if, despairing of true merit, they gained nothing but the empty name of holiness.
In response to what's been said, they create a variety of duties and perform them frequently.
They elevate this to an art form by singing melodies, and with frequent genuflections, they extend their prayers abundantly.
Both day and night, they indulge in lazy idleness and sleepy leisure, as it's written: Having the appearance of religion, but not its substance.
Like a centaur, you can't tell if they're horse or human.
As mentioned earlier, they deceitfully plot against the most faithful servants of God, inciting a cruel persecution.
They warmly embrace those they know to be thieves, murderers, and wrongdoers with a strong bond of love and charity.
From this, it's clear they despise God and serve the devil, becoming loyal to those they love and cherish.
They become enemies, outcasts, and strangers to the Lord, whose faithful servants they persecute and hate.
The Lord said: Whatever you did for one of the least of these brothers and sisters of mine, you did for me.
It's also written: He hates and despises the Lord, who not only doesn't fear God but also hates those who fear Him without cause.
Their leaders, though they might feel guilty before God, fail their flock by not preventing evil, and thus they face double condemnation for both their sins and those of their subordinates.
Here David prays: Cleanse me from my hidden faults, and spare your servant from others'.
When elders defend wrongdoers, it only encourages more defiance, making their hearts harder and more stubborn.
By delaying correction, they prevent the wrongdoer from becoming humble.
They fail to consider making amends and seeking forgiveness, instead allowing repeated offenses, as Scripture clearly states that any sin committed carelessly and without discipline by a brother will immediately fall back on the negligent elder.
The elder will have to account for both themselves and the wrongdoer.
It is rightly believed that those who share in the error will also share in eternal punishment, because:
He who has the power to forbid but chooses not to, is as guilty as if he commanded the sin.
The secretive nature of such transgressions and the widespread influence of worldly misdeeds should be thoroughly eradicated by strict divine judgment and the strong leadership of earthly powers.
This means cutting out wickedness from the hearts of wrongdoers with corrective measures and cultivating the ground with justice and truth, so they can yield a new harvest of faith and holiness for their Creator.
Let these few words about the despicable evil of hypocrisy be enough, as it is not my place to discuss more serious crimes.
I will always remember this saying: "I placed a guard on my mouth while the sinner stood against me, so that my mouth would not speak the works of men."
The just judge, who sees into minds and knows secrets, will reward the good with eternal glory and will be the true avenger of the wicked according to each one's merits.
Valerius' Narratives
To our previously mentioned Father Donadeus.
Order of Complaint Preface of Danger.
I, an unworthy sinner from the province of Asturias, spent my youth entangled in worldly temptations, chasing after material gains and empty teachings.
I allowed myself to be consumed by the darkness of worldly concerns.
Suddenly, driven by a desire for divine grace, I sought to embrace the holy path with all my strength, setting out to cross the turbulent sea of life, hastening eagerly to the monastery of Complutum.
Motivated by intense longing and fear of future judgment, I hoped to finally find the light of truth through the path of confession.
Overwhelmed by the challenges of the worldly sea and often pushed back by the devil's torment, I struggled to reach my desired destination.
Out of necessity, between the city of Astorga and the castle of Petra, I escaped to the wilderness.
In the hardness of my stubborn heart, I found a rocky place sacred to God, high on a mountain summit, far from human habitation.
It was barren, stripped of all greenery, lacking the beauty of a grove or the fertility of herbs.
Buffeted by fierce winds from all sides, and facing harsh rains, snow, and unbearable cold.
Amidst so many hardships and seeing my mind afflicted by deprivation, I endured everything patiently with a steadfast spirit.
I feared abandoning my journey and returning to old ways, for it is written that no one who turns back from avoiding the world's dangers will be saved, just as a dedicated plowman should not look back.
The cunning enemy often stirs the simple heart with various thoughts to deceive.
It's essential to resist strongly and fight back with all your might, so that neither the illusion of false justice deceives anyone, nor uncertain instability compels them to abandon what they've begun.
It is particularly challenging when striving for high goals, as reaching the top requires hard work and perseverance, overcoming struggles that a delicate spirit might not naturally desire.
The first reward of victory is conquering oneself by submitting, armed with a fervent faith and unyielding strength of future hope, even to the contempt of death.
In truth, I would say that he fought and won.
After enduring all these challenges for a long time with the Lord's help, after a few years, Christian compassion, moved by piety, began to gather a diverse crowd of people of both sexes.
They offered help to me, an unfortunate person, providing service or support.
When utmost necessity, aided by the Lord's compassion, turned into willingness, suddenly a certain barbarous man, very slippery and occupied with all sorts of frivolities, named Flainus, a priest of the same small church, driven by the goads of the ancient enemy, was inflamed with the torches of envy.
As is the custom of the wicked to envy what they do not desire, blinded by the darkness of that envy, he began to rage against my smallness, plotting hatred and often creating obstacles, frequently causing loss.
Whenever he came to the same place, with a most hideous appearance-as it is written: "a forehead black with its own darkness is revealed"-clothed savagely and gnashing like a ferocious beast, he came more to relish in my downfall than to promote peace, charity, or the mercy of piety.
As these events continued for a long time, my heart began to fill with sorrow and anxiety.
I pondered how I could avoid the rivalry of that adversary, escape the unrest of the people, and navigate through all the temptations of this world while keeping my path untainted.
Then, trusting in the strength of the Lord's mercy, I withdrew into the deepest ancient solitude I had been seeking.
While I stayed there alone for some time, the false priest continued his persecution against me.
First, he took the books I had written about the Law of the Lord and the Triumphs of the Saints, works I had crafted for my own comfort during my journey and for the correction of discipline and knowledge, and did so with great insult.
Later, whether through his cunning deceit or the skill of his instigating devil, he knows who is aware of all hidden things.
I was often devastated by the cruelty of robbers and humiliated nearly to death by various scandals, barely clinging to life.
When the most faithful Christians learned of this, they quickly came to rescue me, despite my reluctance and longing for the end of death, from the danger of this disaster, and led me to the estate in the rocky fortress called Ebronauto, to the sanctuary of the saints.
After this, desiring the familiar peace of my former solitude, my soul once again became troubled by anxiety, fearing the public dwelling.
With great determination, I chose to dedicate myself to the sacred altars in a prison cell, so that I would no longer need the solitude of peace; ensuring my foot would not step out in disturbance, and that through these present confinements, the divine hand might lift me from the eternal prison of the abyss.
While I was finally taking a break in this place after enduring repeated trials and dangers, I found myself tucked away in a corner of the basilica.
It felt like being on a ship in the sea, hidden under the hull, trapped in the dark lower decks, and battered by the winds and storms of the world.
Yet, I found a small sense of joy, as if I had managed to escape the tumult of life, even just a little.
But just as I had found some peace, the ancient enemy, driven by his envious malice, sought to disrupt good works with endless conflict.
He launched his first attack at night, surrounding me with the terrifying noise of a harsh voice, trying to frighten me.
However, when he saw that I was steadfast in the Lord's strength and could not be shaken by his threats, he rose again in notable fury.
Gathering his followers, he began to attack with even greater intensity, relentlessly persisting for nearly a year or maybe longer, always striving to bring about my downfall.
Yet, it was not through my own endurance, but through the mighty power of the Lord's rebuke, that he was finally driven away.
Realizing his malicious schemes had failed, the cruel adversary turned his attention to a distinguished man named Ric, who he knew was the lord of the estate.
When Ric was convinced that his death was near, he was incited to destroy my humble dwelling, which he swiftly did.
He tore down the hut, casting me from the heavens back to the earthly stage of the world.
While he was trying to build a sacred altar for the church on the very spot where I was uprooted, he cleverly devised a plan inspired by the approaching enemy: to appoint me as a priest, supposedly tempted by worldly desires and rewarded with wealth, aiming for the greater ruin and destruction of the church itself.
For it is written: Just as a servant of the Almighty Lord fears losing the security of their poverty, so do the greedy rich guard their fleeting wealth.
And again: I will call upon tribulation and misery.
Just as the proud call upon God, the holy and undefeated warrior seeks tribulation and misery to challenge and prove themselves.
Again: The ambition is small, and the pleasures of this world are slight.
They cannot be compared to the contemplation of future punishment.
Do not, through the troubles of this present life and minor engagements, bring upon yourself the punishment of future judgment.
For this present life is vanity, and the honor received is temporary; our stay in this world is brief, and its riches dissolve like a spider's web.
Blessed is he whom God grants to keep his soul blameless before the Creator of all, so he may approach His power sincere and innocent, presenting it unblemished, as it was when received from Him.
For the man who wishes to rejoice in this world now and later with Christ, it is indeed more blessed to leave free than to seek freedom after being in chains.
It is better to live a laborious life than to pursue a life of criminal abstinence.
Often, it is preferable to leave this world as a traveler and needy rather than fall into the snare of error through the riches of this world.
Indeed, the insatiable greed of the world frequently arises, but great and praiseworthy is the Lord's mercy, who will protect all who hope in Him with more frequent care and redeem His poor from the severe poverty of oppression, casting down the madness of the powerful from the height of pride.
And to continue the order of my story as I began it, while the above-mentioned Reccimirus was trying to complete the aforementioned church, the structure of the planned construction not yet finished, he suddenly died a cruel death and departed this present life.
And he left me in my unhappiness, often thrown back into the same shipwreck.
33.
While I was striving to reach the harbor's shore, repeatedly worn down by the anguish and sorrows amidst the stormy seas of this unstable world, that ancient enemy stirred up hatred with his usual malice and prepared the customary obstacle of latest destruction.
For he chose a most wicked man falsely named Justus, a tiny figure of insignificant stature, and with the most hideous appearance of the barbaric Ethiopian nation.
Outwardly he was filthy with pitch-black skin and a dark gaze, but in the depths of his heart he existed even blacker than a raven.
Indeed small in body, but abundant in criminal deeds.
Against my will, while I strongly resisted, they ordained him a priest.
He attained this honor for no other reason than because, through his manifold reckless madness, for the sake of cheerful jokes, he took up various buffoonery of wanton luxury, and was led by the soothing art of musical comparison to the lyre.
Through this, running through the banquets of many homes with voracious wantonness, he often obtained fame for the melody of his singing.
After recklessly and unjustly obtaining ordination to such a great honor, he even dared, through hypocritical pretense, to profane the holy religion.
For while publicly displaying holiness through a pretended appearance in the eyes of men, in secret he was working diabolical wickedness.
34.
After my most recent ordeal and warning, I found myself abandoned by everyone, left alone without any support or comfort.
The only person who stood by me was a devout deacon named Christian, whose name truly reflected his character-Simplicius.
He welcomed me into his home with great love and humility.
With utmost dedication and kindness, he took care of me, and together, we were the only ones who regularly attended church services.
However, the envious devil stirred trouble against the priesthood.
Driven by intense jealousy and malicious hatred, he schemed against us for a long time, trying to trap us with devious tricks.
But with the Lord's help, his efforts to harm us were in vain.
Enraged by diabolical fury, he publicly attacked me, repeatedly hurling unspeakable insults in front of many people.
His madness reached such a fever pitch, tangled in indescribable rage, that he wouldn't even allow me peace at night.
When I tried to escape his torment in the quiet of night, he would shamelessly disrupt my solitude.
Brazenly entering my humble home at mealtime, he attacked me with violent arguments instead of offering any comfort.
As we shared a meal in charity, he, driven by his own pride and drunkenness, raged like a rabid and jealous dog, spewing wicked insults, grinding his teeth and foaming at the mouth, trying to tear me apart with his bare hands.
Blinded by such hatred and consumed by jealous wickedness, he didn't even spare the sacred altar.
Amidst many grievous insults, he attempted to stab me with a knife in front of many, only stopped by a brother's timely intervention.
After the madness of such rage finally calmed down, he was so lost in his insanity that he forgot the unjust path he had taken and got caught up in the vulgar whirl of obscene theatrical indulgence.
With his arms flailing and his feet moving in a lascivious dance, he spun around with unsteady steps, leaping with trembling feet, singing the wicked songs of a deadly chant, indulging in the luxury of diabolical corruption.
As he was consumed by the heat of wine and buried in drunkenness, he suffered thirst and hunger even while vomiting; he was devoted to sleep and wrapped in lazy torpor, unlike those who often spent nights singing hymns to God.
Christ never considered such plagues worthy to be His servants.
Sometimes, adding to my heart's cruel sorrow, I often received the usual sustenance and charitable comfort from the same magnificent house I mentioned before, from which I had experienced upheaval and destruction.
Suddenly, by a most savage royal decree of fury, that house was immediately thrown into terrible devastation.
Its rightful heirs were captured and bound in dreadful chains of extensive captivity.
I, however, unfortunate as I was, was left not only unworthy due to the scarcity of food but also deprived of the support of comfort, leading a life of extreme necessity.
Exhausted from enduring twenty continuous years, often facing the gravest dangers and feeling my strength wane, my body finally started to give out, worn down by weakness and fatigue.
I struggled to breathe.
At last, divine mercy, which never forgets those who place their hope in it, showed compassion for my frailty.
Seeing my misery, drowning in the world's turmoil, the kind Shepherd who gave His life for His sheep directed me to the most suitable path.
He did not hesitate to rescue a lost sheep from the shipwreck of the deepest sea and guide it to the long-desired haven of the shore.
In the Bergidensi territory, among other monasteries, near a castle named Rupiana by its ancient founder, there is a monastery nestled in the valleys of the high Alps, established long ago by the blessed Fructuosus of holy memory, where divine mercy placed me to remain forever.
When I shut myself again in the cell that Saint Fructuosus had prepared for himself, the envious enemy did not stop trying to thwart my intentions.
He arrived with great fury, employing many evil and constant temptations against me.
Finally, while I was praying or lying down, he sat at my head, relentlessly breathing an unbearable and horrendous stench into my nostrils from his foulest depths.
I endured these and other temptations for a long time, and driven by his furious anger, he created such thunder and terrifying tremors that it seemed like the very rocks would shatter and scatter like salt.
When I saw the dwelling shaking from its foundations and collapsing over me in the middle of the night, with God as my only witness, I cried out in terror, trusting in the Lord: "Depart, most wicked one, why do you destroy my hut?"
At this voice, he immediately left.
Despite going through countless and indescribable trials, with the Lord's help, I remained steadfast.
However, the adversary eventually targeted Isidore, the bishop of Astorga, deceiving him into leading me to the public of Toledo under false pretenses of praise.
While Isidore was sent by the enemy to lead me to ruin and cause scandal among the brothers, by the just judgment of the Almighty Lord, he fell into the trap he set for us.
We remained unharmed, while he was consumed by eternal damnation.
Following these events, the adversary stirred such envy and hatred in the hearts of false monks that they abandoned me, leaving me imprisoned without any support.
As the enemy pursued me and destroyed my humble dwelling, their hearts hardened and burned with envy.
For three long years, they offered me no remedy or cover.
Moreover, the furious enemy filled my cell with an intolerable plague of voracious fleas, which drained my blood, leaving me almost bloodless.
When my soul was on the brink of destruction from these troubles, divine mercy intervened.
Seeing my dire need, and through the kindness of good Christians, I received the support and assistance needed to protect us from poverty.
Meanwhile, due to the arduous demands of this desert, the generous and illustrious Basilian provided two transports for me.
To clearly expose the deceitful wickedness of those in this cell and to highlight the Lord's vengeance and mercy in defending His people, I'll briefly mention some recent acts of diabolic envy.
When my servant, John the deacon, first received a horse for transport, one elder, who oversaw this cell, was consumed by greed and envy.
He ordered someone from his hometown to come and steal the horse, leading it to ruin.
As they attempted to capture it, the horse, through the Lord's just judgment, returned to us unharmed.
The thieves came back empty-handed and found their land devastated by a severe hailstorm.
When they tried to recover their livelihood, various thieves came and stole all their oxen.
They couldn't recover them, leaving only hunger and misery for the masters and their servants.
Later, when the man gave us another horse as compensation and a new elder was appointed as the monastery overseer during this year's harvest, they couldn't bear the accusations against them for the invasion.
The horses were grazing while shackled.
Below this monastery is a very deep abyss, terrifying to look upon.
The elder, driven by diabolic envy, secretly ordered the shackled horses to be thrown into the abyss.
Who would have thought their bones could reach the valley intact?
Yet, under the Lord's merciful care, they were found uninjured, without a single blemish.
Here, it's worth considering how divine compassion will cast these wicked souls into eternal ruin when, after such a fall, the innocent lives of the animals were mercifully preserved unharmed.
After this, spurred by the devil, their envious malice grew so intense that one of them murdered Deacon John, and he died.
Over a span of 20 years, I've mentioned all these events elsewhere due to my difficult situation.
Here, my unfortunate soul has endured another 22 years.
It wasn't for the sake of vain glory that I decided to share a few brief stories of countless dangers, but to show those who wish to turn to the Lord in holy faith the many challenges posed by envious and persecuting enemies, and the dreadful perversity of those who are lost.
I wanted to illustrate how someone persevering in struggle might fight to achieve victory;
so that the length of this difficult journey doesn't lead to despair, but rather that the fear of the Lord and the hope of eternal life can strengthen them to the end.
Therefore, in my misfortune, I continue to pray to the merciful Lord that He grants me triumph over the savage enemy until the end of this life, extinguishing the malice of evildoers, and not allowing me to be abandoned until death in this place which His kindness has recently granted me.
This place is so perfectly suited for peace, resembling paradise.
Although surrounded by the tallest mountains, it isn't overshadowed by darkness but is distinguished by beautiful, shining splendor and the exceptional loveliness of flourishing greenery,
far from the world, undisturbed by secular noise or encounters with women, making it clear that it is prepared for the faithful who withdraw from worldly temptations to reach the peak of holiness.
Seeing this, the enemy tries through hypocrisy to drive out God's faithful by those under his influence.
Replication of Speeches
From the First Conversion
Reflecting on the first conversion, I'll share the desolation brought by the enemy pursuing my earlier contrition, followed by the Lord's merciful consolation.
On a high mountain peak, the people, in their madness, foolishly worshipped the shrines of demons like pagans.
This disgraceful practice was eventually eradicated with the help of faithful Christians.
This place, despite its poverty, quickly answers the prayers of those who ask with true faith.
To spark a deep desire for a religious life, I'll briefly mention two matters of mystical revelation and mercy.
Once, abandoned by human consolation and struggling on the steep mountain of necessity without help, a young cleric came to me, relying on his youthful strength.
He earnestly requested to be under my guidance.
Seeing his capability for secular tasks, I appointed him to manage my work and provide for our sustenance.
After he had stocked grains and other supplies at his dwelling, I prepared to send a brother to him and remembered to give a message.
As he descended the steep mountain slope, I called out to him:
Tell that servant to give one measure of food to the blind man nearby and half a measure to another poor person.
Later that night, as I lay in bed and drifted to sleep, I suddenly found myself being beaten, with two men standing by, cruelly burning my sides with swords.
Despite waking frequently from the intense pain, I would fall back asleep, only to endure the same torment.
When I finally woke up, I prayed, saying:
"Lord, in your mercy, please reveal to me why I am suffering. I don't understand what offense has brought such great wrath upon me."
Then, I heard a voice say:
"Didn't you hear the Gospel say that your charity should be in secret, yet you give alms from the mountaintop with a voice?"
Immediately freed from the bond, I thanked the Lord for deeming it worthy to correct my foolishness for my improvement. However, a few days later, the worldly rewards that had caused such terrible wrath were burned with fire.
From then on, fearful, I not only rejected the fleeting worldly substance but also distanced myself from the one who provided it. To make my request for the Lord's mercy clear, I will briefly explain.
While raising a boy named Bonosus in a place of necessity, I had written a special book for his education. When his parents tried to compensate me, I asked the boy's mother only for a cloak made of sackcloth. After one or two years had passed, and she had forgotten her promise, as the grape harvest approached, she prepared to celebrate it. The same matron, named Theodora, then fell ill.
While she was sick and sleeping at night, it was revealed to her that she should go with her husband, little boys, and girls to the church of Saint Felix to seek safety. Because a public road ran under that mountain, as they entered it, they encountered a crowd of people driving many yokes of oxen. In the midst of them, a one-footed ox, in a frenzy, struck the matron under the shoulder with its horn, violently tossing its head up, leaving the horn, cut off at the root, embedded in her flesh.
Despite all their strength and with others passing by, they tried to pull her away, but couldn't succeed.
While they held her, barely alive, a very splendid man appeared to them, coming from the direction of the church of Saint Felix through the desert.
His face shone like the sun, and his clothes were brighter than snow.
As he approached, seemingly unaware, he asked, "What is the matter, people? What is the cause of your sorrow and trouble?"
They showed him the terrible wound and said, "Look, sir, at the disaster that has happened. The woman is dead, and we cannot help her in any way."
He replied, "You are many and cannot help? What will you give me if I, by extending my hand, help her?"
They all said, "If you request a reward, you can have it, because your glorious sanctity is so great that nothing is impossible for you."
Then he came close to her and said, "I won't help you unless you first promise me that before you go to Bergidum to collect the cilicium, you will make that cloak for Nunnius Valerius, which you promised."
She asked him, "Lord, who are you?"
He replied, "I am a servant of the Lord Felix."
Then, seized by fear and compelled by pain, she raised her hands to the church of Saint Felix and said, "By our Lord Felix himself, if you order me to be healed now, I will immediately start to make it."
After this, he removed the embedded ox horn from her body with two fingers, threw it far away, and placing his hand over her wound, said, "Behold, you are healed. If you do what you promised, you will go well to Bergidum and return well. However, if you neglect to do it, you will be responsible."
Hearing this, she became perfectly healthy, free from all pain.
As she awoke, she was filled with great anxiety, wishing for morning to come soon.
When the first rooster crowed, she immediately jumped out of bed and called her daughters and maidservants.
She cleverly planned that on the third day, after making preparations, she would personally present herself to me with many offerings.
She then told me everything she had experienced.
While I was struggling with extreme need on the often-mentioned mountain, many young men would come during peaceful times and devote themselves to my teachings.
But when the stormy winter weather approached, they all left immediately, and I was left alone, suffering from hunger to the point of death.
One poor, religious man, wanting to console me, promised to stay with me.
But when the harsh snow and bitter storm trapped us inside, that poor man died from severe hunger.
I stayed beside his lifeless body for several days, tormented by the prospect of my own impending death.
After many frequent and unbearable attacks from the ancient enemy in that place, he sought to disturb me more visibly with a great terror.
One day, while finishing the morning hymns before dawn, I wanted to leave the chapel for a necessary reason through the small door into the desert.
I found the devil standing at the door, appearing as a terrifying giant, towering like a monstrous statue up to the clouds.
Terrified with immense fear, I froze inside while he blocked the exit.
I began to think to myself: If I go back, the enemy will grow stronger because I would be fleeing in fear.
Then, with the Lord's help, I gained courage and said to him: I know you are Satan; and signing my forehead, I said: Behold, the cross of my Lord Jesus Christ, who is my strength and victory; now it will be seen whether I flee or you do.
Then, moving forward, I exclaimed: In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
When I arrived at the place where he stood, he suddenly pulled back, weakened, and humbled to the ground before vanishing and dissolving.
Though I couldn't overcome this on my own, even with the Lord's help, he attempted to trap me with another illusion.
As I was teaching a young orphan boy to read, divine providence blessed him with such a remarkable memory that within six months, he memorized the entire Psalter with songs.
One day, around noon, while I was working and he was reading in front of me, he suddenly shouted:
What is this that I see?
I asked him: What do you see?
He replied: Look, I see an angel of the Lord, whose face shines like the sun, and his clothes are whiter than snow.
He tells me: 'I have come for you, sent directly by the Lord, to lead you into His Majesty's presence so that He may repay you for your works.
'
I told him: Do not believe it, for it is not an angel of the Lord, but a demon of the devil.
Then, I called him over and asked if he still saw it.
He said: Look, it stands before us.
So, I instructed him to recite selected psalms, saying: If it is an angel of God, it will stay; if it is a demon, it will flee.
As we recited together for a long time, he said: Look, now it has moved away, dissolved, and vanished.
Seeing my soul wasting away in such great calamity and miserable desolation, Almighty God stirred up a certain young man, flourishing in the bloom of youth, named John.
When his parents asked him to find a bride, he, filled with the flame of the Holy Spirit and inspired by a desire for holy devotion, chose instead to unite himself spiritually with God.
This spiritual union begins with sorrow but leads to eternal joy, unlike earthly marriage, which starts with joy and ends with sorrow.
He immediately turned away from all worldly temptations and quickly offered comfort in my humble state.
He was so deeply rooted in the fear of the Lord that, with voluntary love, he stood by me through every trial and necessity, becoming my steadfast partner.
The most vicious enemy, envious of our love and comfort, used his usual malice to try and destroy our union with deceitful tricks.
When he was my only companion in the vast solitude of the inner desert, the enemy sent merciless robbers to separate us through their wicked acts.
He was cruelly beaten, severely weakened, and dragged back to his previous location.
After this, I was taken and moved by Christians to another place, as the earlier story explains.
When he regained his health and hurried back to serve me as before, the hearts of wicked people, fueled by the zeal of the devil, refused to let him join me again.
While I, following the aforementioned order, was led by the Lord to the same places, to the cell of the most blessed Fructuosus, he was not allowed to join me.
And because, when I left the often-mentioned mountain, he departed as well, the constant gathering of people, along with the growth from animals that once gathered there, led to a fire sweeping through the desert.
Entering through this growth, it burned down all the dwellings, including the church itself.
After this, Brother John, with the Lord's help, built a new monastery at the foot of the same mountain.
The bishop ordained him as a priest, even though he was reluctant.
While he was there alone, I felt deeply saddened by his solitude.
Then the Lord brought a young man named Saturninus from distant lands.
He was well-suited for active work and service and composed in all his actions.
John welcomed him as his first convert.
As they devoted themselves day and night to fasting, prayers, singing psalms, and various works and crafts with great discipline, Christian kindness, which had faded after I left, began to return and offer the necessary support.
After a few years of practicing these regular exercises, Brother Saturninus received a revelation urging him to join my company quickly.
He immediately obeyed the divine command.
I welcomed him with great joy and thanked God, the creator of all, for providing support in my old age and a long-sought remedy for salvation at what felt like the end of my life.
Near a rocky area below this monastery, where the blessed Fructuosus used to pray and where a wooden cross stood, Brother Saturninus began to think about building a small oratory with our limited resources.
When he shared this idea with me, I initially argued against it, saying the place was unsuitable and we didn't have the strength to do it.
But that same day, as I slept, divine mercy revealed to me how it should be done, that it was His will, and that His power would quickly bring it to completion.
Once I understood the Lord's will, whether through my own efforts or where divine providence guided me to give, many workers were employed to help.
This was possible due to the generosity of good Christians.
With their assistance and the Lord's support and strength, the task was completed.
Although the site lacked flat ground, and a massive rocky cliff loomed dangerously, they managed to split the rock there with ease.
In that very place, in the name of the holy cross, Saint Pantaleon, and the other holy martyrs, a temple was constructed for the Lord.
Though small in size, it was great in the height of its virtue.
The temple was consecrated to the Lord with utmost care by the most reverent man of God, Bishop Aurelius.
He also ordained the builder of this temple, Saturninus, as a priest with the Lord's aid.
While Saturninus offered daily sacrifices to the Lord there, he witnessed several signs of answered prayers.
I will briefly recount a few that I remember.
One day, while cutting stones from the overhanging rock, a large sharp stone suddenly broke loose and fell, striking his foot, penetrating to the bone and severing nerves and veins.
Fearing he might become weak, lose the ability to walk, or even face death, he couldn't remain in bed once the bleeding stopped.
Despite his weakness and with great effort due to necessity, he dragged himself to offer the sacrifice to the Lord as he was accustomed to, even though he was half-footed.
As soon as he offered the sacrifice before the Lord, he emerged healed, as if not even a thorn had pricked him.
Finally, when it was time to celebrate the morning service, the doors were so blocked that he couldn't open them.
Disturbed in spirit, he approached the altar window and cried out, saying:
"Is this right, holy lords, that I come to your service, and you do not allow me to enter?"
As he said this and approached the door, the bar, which was locked from the inside, was heard moving away, opening the entrance.
Seeing this, he and those with him were amazed and praised the Lord.
When he planted some vegetables in that desert, they grew abundantly and densely, thanks to the Lord's blessing.
As they ripened, he worried they might be destroyed by various creatures.
So, he blessed a small cloth over the altar as a sign and hung it in the field.
Everyone was afraid to touch anything from there, but some foolish person entered with reckless daring and began to satisfy his gluttony.
He was immediately bitten by a snake and fell down, lying unconscious until he was found.
He expelled more from his mouth and backside than he had eaten, all due to the Lord's grace, as no one else in those mountains was bitten by a snake.
At another time, a man named Basil, driven by great need and weakness, came to him because his right hand and arm had withered and become stiff due to contracted nerves.
Moved by compassion, he blessed some oil and prayed, applying it to the man's weak limbs.
With the Lord's help, the man's limbs were immediately restored to their former health.
Thus, praising God, he returned home completely well and with great joy.
While this holy man served the altar with great devotion, and I solemnly served in the cloister of the upper monastery, he became filled with the spirit of vain glory.
Hoping to gain more honorable recognition and greater veneration from the people of the world by separating himself from me, he withdrew to a tiny and narrow cell near his altar of work.
From there, he only came out to perform the daily and nightly services and frequently offer sacrifices to the Lord.
After he had been there for a while, that greedy and insatiable wolf, the pursuer of our soul, rushed to separate him from the fellowship of my unity.
Like a wandering sheep, he would easily become prey.
The wolf furiously attacked the innermost part of his heart, causing him so much distress that he couldn't find rest, day or night, as he hurried around without even a brief moment of peace.
Defeated and easily overcome, he left, loaded the donkey we used for provisions in this desert, and, rashly persuaded by the enemy, was taken captive with the books I had written for the holy altar and other items I had gathered there with God's help.
Later, still suffering from my usual pain and tribulation, my aforementioned disciple, John, who was also his first teacher, was wickedly beheaded by a most evil countryman.
This act was driven by that envious persecutor, the devil, while John was lying in prayer before the holy altar in his monastery.
At that time, although divine providence, which always carefully attends to the misery of its poor, did not leave me, the most miserable, without all means of consolation.
It moved you from my birthplace to fear him, bringing me my brother Montanus's son, John.
Compelled by a pricked conscience, he left the service of the king, his wife, children, and all he had, and, with his servant Evagrius, devoted himself wholeheartedly to the Lord's service.
He now faithfully works to provide for both cells.
With the Lord's help, who appointed him as the minister of His holy altar, he began cultivating vineyards in that very desert, alongside a vegetable garden and various small fruit trees.
He established places to live and tirelessly works each day, with God's guidance, to accomplish other necessary tasks here and there.
His goal is to continue these efforts for the rest of his life.
After enduring many hardships, hindered by enemies and facing the most bitter and sorrowful dispersions, that everlasting kindness- which seeks not the destruction of its creation-granted me a bit of peace, a long-awaited comfort, and relief after forty-two years of continuous struggle.
Furthermore, He inspired the hearts of His faithful, including the merciful, noble prince, bishops, and other Christians, who generously supported me in my poverty.
May they receive a hundredfold reward from the Lord in heavenly inheritance.
As it is written: Divine and eternal kindness brings calm after the most terrible storm, and after tears and weeping, it brings joy.
And again: Joy follows mourning; after joy, mourning.
Laughter follows weeping, and songs follow lamentation.
And Truth itself says: He who perseveres to the end will be saved.
Sometimes, while I, unworthy as I am, steadfastly preside at the altar following the holy apostles, with no suitable flat area due to the nearby mountainside, God's hand provided a little help to our frailty.
This short but suitable spot was leveled by the labor of workers.
Look now at the olive trees, yew trees, laurel trees, pine trees, cypress trees, and rosy myrtles, all enclosed and thriving with evergreen foliage.
This is why this eternal grove is fittingly named Daphne's, with diverse shrubs intertwined with young plants and vines, creating a delightful canopy of greenery.
Its charming shade refreshes even monarchs, offering a fruitful retreat from the scorching sun.
It's as if it shelters the body like caves and rocky shadows, while the gentle sound of the nearby stream soothes the ears.
The fragrant aroma of blooming roses, lilies, and other herbs fills the air, and the grove's beautiful charm calms the spirit, allowing true and sincere love to flourish without pretense.
Near this location, with the Lord's help, we added a small garden, protected by a surrounding fence of planted trees.
As time passes after my death, this protective enclosure of trees will grow stronger.
Just like a small boat battered by stormy waves finally reaches a safe harbor, I, unworthy as I am, feel resurrected from the grave or released from a dark, infernal prison.
Enjoying the splendid light after darkness, I offer immense thanks to the Almighty Lord for granting me a place of rest, which I often desired and sought.
I trust that just as He allowed me to briefly escape the abyss of the world, He will also grant me victory over my most hostile enemy, allowing me to achieve the triumph of victory.
Cleansed from the stain of all sins through lamentation and repentance, along with those destined to be my comfort, He grants the nourishing fruit of repentance and the fellowship of eternal life, who destroyed the perishable empire through the triumph of the cross.
The Remaining Complaint from the Above Follows
Once, as previously mentioned, I was forced by circumstances to be confined in a small, humble prison, similar to a worldly gathering.
I was alone in a sorrowful darkness, constrained by poverty, as if trapped in a grave.
When I emerged from this situation, as described earlier, I found myself at the Rufian monastery, isolated from worldly interactions and surrounded by mountains as high as the tallest peaks of the French Alps, so secure that it doesn't even require walls.
However, for those coming from the opposite side of the habitable land, only one ancient, man-made path is accessible.
With the rocks carved away, it forms a narrow and winding path where people walk cautiously, one by one.
Near the monastery, on a high rock, stands the oratory of the most holy Fructuosus.
With this cleared, and with the Lord's help, a holy temple was built for him, which serves as the boundary and enclosure of the monastery's dwelling since its construction.
Here, next to the altar of the holy apostles, on the upper level, it is briefly understood.
Sixty-six.
Regarding the volumes of books, both for daily offices and the annual celebration of holy festivals, as well as various holy Scriptures that aid in spiritual growth and teaching, I completed a comprehensive summary at the altars of the saints, with the Lord's help.
For these works and the gathering of good people, driven by the highest love of charity, the residents of this place undertook the most severe labor of zeal and envy.
They engaged in both public and secret hateful persecutions and unspeakable acts of diabolic nature.
Through these actions, the aforementioned individuals, and those who were publicly killed, others who remained were converted, their minds changed, disturbed, and scattered across various lands.
The holy altar I had bought has been completely destroyed, and, as the prophet Elijah says:
"I alone am left." And: "They seek my life to take it away."
Among those wicked ones is a member of a secretive, whispering faction, a dullard and ignorant babbler named Firminus, who leads that sickly flock in its ruinous downfall. Recently, in his madness and folly, because he had nothing to accuse my misfortune of, he attempted to publicly defame me solely for accepting, loving, and cherishing good Christians.
He claimed that before me, there were two priests in this confinement who welcomed neighbors, acquaintances, and friends into the little courtyard and accepted those coming from afar through the window. Jealously envying their supposedly better conduct, after his slanderous accusations, he was the first of those confined to be defeated and wickedly overcome by the devil's persuasion and wanton desire, departing to return to worldly vanity; the other stayed so idle that he left no admirable work for others to follow.
From this, however, the Apostle James preaches, saying:
"Faith without works is dead."
Meanwhile, I, always observing the twofold variation of charity, both inward and outward, as taught by the holy Apostle Paul, remember his saying:
"I have become all things to all people, that I might save some."
To this, I will briefly add a few teachings from the Fathers. Blessed Arsenius, though noble by birth and exalted by the wealth of his people, was seized by the fear of the Lord and abandoned everything. Poor and almost naked, he entered the desolate wilderness of Scythia and enclosed himself in a small, narrow cell.
While he remained there for a long time, the man of God, Theophilus, the Archbishop of Alexandria, desired to see him and sent word saying:
"If I come to you, will you open for me so I can see you?"
To which he replied:
"If you come, I will open to you. But if to you, then to everyone."
At the start of his conversion, he organized his life so that he could attend church alongside the congregation, accompanied by many other Fathers with the usual solemnity.
He warmly welcomed many visitors, showing so much love that a noble religious woman from Rome, eager to meet him, sailed to see him.
When she sent messengers to request a meeting and he declined, she confidently stated, "I trust in God that I will see him." With determination and following the Lord's guidance, she found him outside his cell. She fell at his feet and remained there until he lifted her up.
It turned out that, although he had previously refused to meet a bishop, he later, by the Lord's will, accepted a faithful woman in love, albeit reluctantly. For in the future judgment, the Lord will not be concerned with closed or open places, not with monasteries, towns, villages, attire, or gender, but will reward each according to their own deeds.
On the Institution of a New Life
Dear son, embrace your tears and don't hold them back.
Be just as willing to cry as you were eager to sin.
Let your dedication to repentance be as strong as your desire was to sin.
As deeply as you fell, so should you rise again.
Don't let anything make you feel secure in your sin.
Avoid being deceived by false security or flattery.
Always keep both hope and fear in your heart - hope and fear together, fear and trust.
Let the hope of forgiveness uplift you, but let the fear of hell always keep you in check, and let fear guide you.
The fear of the Lord helps drive away sin and destroys vice.
Without fear, life falls into disorder.
I wish for you to have more strength in spirit than in body.
Physical adversity can be a remedy for the soul.
If prosperity lifts you up, don't let it make you proud; if slander comes your way, don't lose heart.
Remember, you're tested in prosperity, not elevated by it, and take both the good and the bad with a calm mind as they come to you.
If you can avoid anger, do so; otherwise, endure it or temper it.
Learn to endure wrongs rather than commit them.
Rise above the errors of detractors by ignoring them, and surpass their insults with patience.
Be quick to raise the shield of patience against harsh words.
Even if someone mocks, provokes, insults, injures, or offends you with words, stay silent and ignore it.
Practice silence; don't respond to insults or retaliate against abuse.
Learn modesty from Christ, learn tolerance; having suffered injury for us, he left us an example: even though he was struck with palms, beaten with lashes, mocked with spit, nailed with nails, crowned with thorns, and condemned to the cross, he always remained silent.
It is a great virtue not to harm those who have harmed you, and a great glory to spare those you could hurt.
Respond to the one who curses you with a blessing.
Strive to turn away anger with patience.
Overcome the wrongs of others with your own good actions, because you won't receive forgiveness unless you give it.
Even if the other person doesn't ask for forgiveness, and even if they don't request to be forgiven, you should forgive from your heart and let go from your mind.
This way, your Father in heaven may also forgive you, just as you forgive those who owe you, meaning those who persecute you, curse you, and slander you.
Don't hold onto the pain caused by someone else's wickedness.
Envy devours good things with its harmful heat; envy eats away at the soul like a moth.
It burns the heart, affects the mind, and consumes a person's heart like a plague.
Let kindness counteract jealousy, and let love be your defense against envy.
Always maintain the bond of consistency.
In all your actions, imitate good people, emulate the saints, and keep the examples of priests in front of you.
Let the teachings of the Fathers motivate you; don't let favoritism mislead you or criticism break you.
The one who does not seek praise does not feel insulted.
For what good is it if you're called good while you're bad?
Judge yourself by your own standards, not someone else's; be the kind of person you want to be seen as.
Show your profession not in your attire but in your conduct.
Let simplicity be in your approach, purity in your manner, gravity in your bearing, and let honesty shine in your conduct, with nothing frivolous.
Let your actions not offend others, nor give them a reason to speak ill of you.
Avoid wicked and unjust people, especially those inclined to vice.
Surround yourself with good companions, because if you're in the company of good conversations, you'll also be in virtue.
Reject indecent talk, for idle talk is a sign of an empty conscience.
The mind of a person is revealed by their tongue; and the kind of speech shown, the mind is proven.
Speak not whatever, but what is necessary.
Do not stain your mouth with the wrongs of others: focus on your own judgments, not those of others.
Do not inquire into what doesn't concern you, nor desire to know what people say among themselves.
By fulfilling these words of the law, you will achieve eternal life.