Sermon on Baptism
by Pacian, Bishop of Barcelona
I want to explain how we are born through baptism and how we are renewed.
I'll speak plainly, brothers, so you don't think I am boasting with fancy words, and so you can understand this mystical matter.
I hope I can make it clear.
I seek no glory, for the glory belongs to God alone.
My concern is for your well-being, especially for the newly baptized, to help you understand the great joy of this sacrament.
So, I will explain what paganism was before, what faith brings, and what baptism grants.
If my words reach your hearts as I hope, you will see that no other preaching has offered us more.
So, listen, dearest ones, to the state of a person before baptism.
You know the old story: Adam was destined to an earthly origin, which was a condemnation that imposed the law of eternal death on him; and this death ruled over all his descendants, bound by one law, from Adam to Moses.
Romans chapter 5, verse 14.
Through Moses, only one people were chosen, namely the seed of Abraham, if they could keep the commandments of righteousness.
Meanwhile, we were all held under sin, so that we were the fruits of death, destined for unclean works, under the rule of evil angels.
Under their rule, we could neither do nor know righteousness, for obeying such masters compelled us.
Consider how we were freed from these powers and this death.
After Adam sinned, as I mentioned, the Lord said, "You are dust, and to dust you shall return."
Genesis chapter 3, verse 19.
He was condemned to death.
This condemnation flowed to the whole human race.
For all have sinned, urged by nature itself, as the Apostle says: "Through one man sin entered, and through sin death, and so death spread to all men, because all sinned."
Romans chapter 5, verse 12.
Sin ruled, and we were dragged as captives towards death, which is eternal death.
This sin, however, was not understood before the times of the Law, as the Apostle says:
"For until the Law was given, sin was in the world, but it was not counted as sin because there was no law."
Romans 5:13.
It became apparent with the coming of the Law: it was revealed, but almost no one kept it.
The Law said,
"You shall not commit adultery, you shall not murder, you shall not covet,"
yet desire, with all its vices, persisted.
Thus, this sin, before the Law, secretly killed man with a hidden sword, but the Law made it clear.
So what hope was there for man? Without the Law, he perished because he could not see the sin; and with the Law, he perished because he fell into what he could see.
Who could free him from destruction?
Listen to the Apostle:
"Wretched man that I am! Who will deliver me from this body of death? Thanks be to God through Jesus Christ our Lord."
Romans 7:24-25.
What is grace? The forgiveness of sin, that is, a gift. Grace is indeed a gift.
Therefore, Christ, coming and taking on human form, presented that very man to God pure and innocent, free from the power of sin.
Isaiah says:
"Behold, a virgin will conceive and bear a son, and shall call his name Emmanuel. He will eat curds and honey before he knows how to refuse the evil and choose the good."
Isaiah 7:14-15.
And again concerning him:
"He committed no sin, nor was deceit found in his mouth."
Isaiah 53:9.
Under this protection of innocence, as soon as Christ began to defend the name in the very flesh of sin, the parent of disobedience, who had once deceived the first humans, began to hurry, to be anxious, to tremble.
For he was to be defeated by the breaking of the law of sin, by which alone he had either held or could hold man.
Therefore, he arms himself for a spiritual battle against the spotless one; and first, with the same trick by which he had conquered Adam in paradise, he approaches under the guise of dignity, and as if concerned about heavenly power, says:
"If you are the Son of God, command these stones to become loaves of bread."
Matthew 4:3
So that, while he was ashamed or unwilling to hide that he was the Son of God, he might fulfill the tempter's command.
Here, he does not remain silent, suggesting that if he were to throw himself from a height, the angels, commanded by the Father, would catch him to prevent him from striking his foot against a stone.
The Lord aims to prove that he is the one about whom the Father had given this command, by doing what the tempter urges.
Finally, the snake, almost as if yielding, promises the kingdoms of the world, which he had taken from the first man.
He believes he has conquered the Advocate of man by receiving the dominion he defended, thinking he might incline to the dignity spoken of by the impious one, and thus eventually sin.
But in all these trials, the enemy is overcome and dissolved by heavenly power, as the Psalmist says to the Lord, "That you may destroy the enemy and the avenger, because I will see the heavens, the work of your fingers" (Psalms 8:3-4).
The devil should have yielded, but he does not stop.
He incites the scribes, Pharisees, and all that crowd of wicked people with known plots, stirring them with fury.
After various schemes and deceitful hearts, when they achieved nothing, they finally attacked him with open robbery and the most cruel kind of suffering.
They hoped that through the indignity of the events or the pain of the punishments, he might do or say something unjust, thus losing the man he was carrying, and his soul would be left in hell.
For the sting of death is sin (First Corinthians 15:56).
Therefore, Christ persisted, and he did not sin, nor was deceit found in his mouth (First Peter 2:22).
Not even when he was led to the sacrifice.
This was victory, to be condemned without sin.
For the devil had taken power over sinners, which he claimed over the immaculate one.
Thus, he himself was overcome, decreeing over the Just One what was not allowed to him by the law he had accepted.
Hence, the prophet says to the Lord, "That you may be justified in your words and prevail when you are judged" (Psalms 51:4).
And so, just as the Apostle says, when the powers were transferred, Christ condemned sin in the flesh by nailing it to the cross and canceling the record of debt.
(Colossians 2:14-15) That is why God did not abandon His soul in the underworld, nor did He let His Holy One see decay.
(Psalms 16:10) That is why, having trampled the sting of death, He rose on the third day in the flesh, reconciling it to God and restoring it to eternity, with sin conquered and erased.
But if only He won, what did He contribute to the rest of us?
Listen briefly.
Adam's sin passed to all humanity: For through one man, as the Apostle says, sin entered, and through sin, death; and so it spread to all people.
(Romans 5:12) Therefore, it is necessary that the righteousness of Christ also passes to humanity: Just as Adam lost his offspring through sin, so Christ revives all His lineage through righteousness.
The Apostle insists on this, saying: Just as through the disobedience of one man many were made sinners, so through the obedience of one man many will be made righteous; and just as sin reigned in death, so grace might reign through righteousness to eternal life.
(Romans 5:19, 21)
Someone might say to me: But Adam's sin rightfully passed to his descendants because they were born from him; are we born from Christ, so that we can be saved through Him?
Do not think in merely physical terms: you will see how we are born from Christ as our parent.
In the last times, Christ certainly took a soul with flesh from Mary: He came to save this, He did not leave it in the underworld, He joined it to His Spirit and made it His own.
And these are the Lord's marriages, united in one flesh, that according to that great sacrament, two would become one in flesh, Christ and the Church.
(Ephesians 5:32) From this marriage, the Christian people are born, with the Spirit of the Lord coming from above; and the substance of our souls, immediately infused and mixed with heavenly seed, grow in the womb of the mother and, being born from her, we come to life in Christ.
Therefore, the Apostle says: The first Adam became a living being; the last Adam, a life-giving spirit.
First Corinthians 15:47.
In this way, Christ generates in the Church through his priests.
As the same Apostle says: For in Christ Jesus I became your father through the gospel.
First Corinthians 4:15.
And so, Christ's seed, which is God's spirit, stirs the new man in the womb of the mother and is received at the font by the hands of the priest, with faith acting as the marriage attendant.
For no one can be seen as grafted into the Church who has not believed, nor born of Christ who has not received the Spirit.
It must be believed that we can be reborn.
For Philip says: If you believe, you can.
Acts 8:37.
Christ must be received to generate, because the Apostle John says: To all who received him, he gave the power to become children of God.
John 1:12.
These things, however, cannot be fulfilled otherwise, except through the sacraments of washing, chrism, and the bishop.
For sins are cleansed by washing; the Holy Spirit is poured out by chrism; and both of these are granted by the hand and mouth of the bishop.
Thus, the whole person is reborn and renewed in Christ; so that as Christ was raised from the dead, we too might walk in newness of life.
Romans 6:4.
That is, having cast off the errors of the old life-servitude to idols, cruelty, fornication, lust, and other vices of the flesh and blood-we follow new customs in Christ through the Spirit: faith, chastity, innocence, and purity.
And just as we have borne the image of the earthly man, let us also bear the image of the heavenly one; for the first man was from the earth, earthly; the second man is from heaven, heavenly.
First Corinthians 15:49.
Doing this, beloved, we will no longer die.
Even if we dissolve in this body, we will live in Christ, as he says: Whoever believes in me, even though he dies, will live.
John 11:25.
We are certain, finally, by the testimony of the Lord himself, that Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, and all the saints of God live.
Indeed, concerning them, the Lord says: They are all alive; for God is not the God of the dead, but of the living.
Luke 20:38.
And the Apostle says about himself:
"For to me, to live is Christ and to die is gain: I desire to depart and be with Christ" (Philippians 1:21).
Moreover:
"As long as we are in this body, we are away from the Lord. For we walk by faith, not by sight" (Second Corinthians 5:6-7).
This is what we believe, dearest brothers.
Furthermore:
"If in this life only we have hope, we are of all men most miserable" (First Corinthians 15:19).
The life of the world, which, as you can see, is shared by cattle, wild animals, and birds, is either common with us or longer.
And that which is unique to humans, which Christ gave through His Spirit, is eternal life, but only if we no longer sin.
For just as death is acquired through sin, it is avoided through virtue; similarly, life is lost through sin and retained through virtue.
Therefore, the wages of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord (Romans 6:23).
Above all, remember, little ones:
All nations, as we said before, were once delivered to the rulers of darkness and powers; now, through the victory of Jesus Christ our Lord, they are liberated.
He is the one who redeems, forgiving all our sins, as the Apostle says, and erasing the record of debt that stood against us with its legal demands; he took it away, nailing it to the cross.
Having disarmed the powers, he made a public spectacle of them, triumphing over them in himself (Colossians 2:13-15).
He frees the bound and breaks our chains, as David said:
"The Lord lifts up those who are bowed down, the Lord sets prisoners free, the Lord gives sight to the blind" (Psalms 146:7-8).
And again:
"You have freed me from my chains; I will sacrifice a thank offering to you" (Psalms 116:16-17).
Therefore, freed from our chains, when we gather at the sign of the Lord through the sacrament of baptism, we renounce the devil and all his angels, whom we once served; so that we may no longer serve them, being freed by the blood of Christ and His name.
But if anyone, forgetting himself and ignorant of his redemption, returns again to the servitude of angels (Colossians 2:18) and.
.
(Galatians).
Having moved beyond the weak and poor elements of the world, he will be bound by the old shackles and chains, essentially the bonds of sin; and his final state will be worse than the first.
As it is written in Luke chapter eleven, verse twenty-six: "Because the devil, as if having conquered him in flight, will bind him more violently; and Christ will no longer be able to suffer for him, because He who rose from the dead will no longer die."
As Romans chapter six, verse nine says: "Therefore, beloved, we are washed once, we are freed once, we are received into the immortal kingdom once: blessed are they whose sins are forgiven and whose sins are covered."
Psalms chapter thirty-one, verse one states: "Hold firmly to what you have received, keep it joyfully, and do not sin anymore. Keep yourselves pure and spotless for the day of the Lord."
Great and infinite are the rewards promised to the faithful; which no eye has seen, no ear has heard, nor has it entered into the heart of man.
As it is written in First Corinthians chapter two, verse nine: "To receive these, strive with works of justice and spiritual prayers. Amen."