On the Individual Feasts of the Year
On the birth of Christ.
Today, the Creator and Redeemer is born,
Christ, made human from the Virgin Mary.
He came so that we might partake in the holy Divinity,
cleansed from sins and pleasing in merits.
On the Octave of the Lord
On the eighth day, he was named Jesus after being circumcised, marking the moment a cleansed man became a child of the Lord.
On Epiphany
He appeared, accepting gifts from those deemed worthy.
Now, coming to us in mercy, he sees our offerings.
On the Feast of the Presentation (of the Lord)
During Jesus's presentation at the temple, the sinless one presented at the altar calls us sinners to his home.
His mother is there, an everlasting virgin, glorified by her son.
On Septuagesima. We are getting ready to celebrate the upcoming feasts.
This time helps us prepare our hearts in holy ways.
On Lent,
following the Lord's example, we begin fasting with our bodies.
Let our minds also abstain from sins.
On Palm Sunday
The crowd laid down their cloaks for the pious Christ,
so that He could sit on them.
We offer our bodies in a similar way.
On the Passion.
He endured the cross, wounds, slaps, and harsh spitting, demonstrating how much we should be willing to endure.
On the Resurrection
Plundering the underworld, conquering death, and rising again to give life to those who have fallen.
He died so that we might be freed from sin.
He rises to bring us to the threshold of life.
On the Ascension
He ascended to the heavens, triumphing over the ages,
So that He may call us, as victors, to the highest stars.
On Pentecost
The Spirit of the Lord descended to the earth in fire,
giving the apostles fiery hearts.
He comforts them with His presence,
seeing their souls burning with pure love.
On the Nativity of Saint John the Baptist
The holy Baptist John is born today,
May the Lord's right hand help us through his prayers.
On the feast day of Saint Boniface we celebrate the joys of this day.
Saint Boniface, may they save us by the Lord's grace through your merits.
On the Assumption of Saint Mary.
The Virgin Mother of God, taken from her pure body, has passed into the rest of the Lord.
May she help us with her prayers to enter that rest.
May the gracious offspring of the eternal virgin grant this.
On the Apostles
They were the ones who were chosen first by divine selection from the entire world and were given a place of honor.
Those who consistently follow the teachings of their faith will be granted the kingdoms of heaven through their prayers.
On the Confessors
The perfect confession to their King granted them companionship in heavenly rest.
Through their examples and words, we find peace.
They teach us to love the path of supreme peace.
On the martyrs
Through their own blood, they earned heavenly rewards, which God has given them.
They remind us to endure hardships with ease and to bear reproaches for Christ, preparing us for the holy kingdoms.
On virgins
Strength has flourished in the so-called weaker sex, which embraces the duty of virginity.
We are reminded of this: even if the world's challenges are not present, let the pious mind battle its own vices.
On the Feast of Saint Martin
This holy teacher of God, revered by the world, set examples of life and assists with prayers.
Whoever reads this, seek forgiveness, remember Strabo, and call upon all these for help.