In the year of our Lord 922, Hervaeus was the Archbishop of Reims.
Historical Notice. From Gallia Christiana, volume nine.
The prelate, whom Flodoard refers to as Heriveus, was appointed from the king's court to the bishopric in the year 900.
He was of noble birth, specifically the nephew on his sister's side of Count Hucbald.
As a young man, he was elevated to this honor, with his ordination properly conducted and celebrated by Riculf, the bishop of Soissons; Dodilo of Cambrai; Otgar of Amiens; Mancion of Châlons; Rodulf of Laon; Otfrid of Senlis, and other diocesan bishops who gave their consent and confirmed the decree of this ordination.
He immediately endeavored to prove himself worthy of this rank, endearing himself to all good people and setting an exemplary standard with his behavior: a kind lover of the poor, a generous comforter of the religious, and very merciful, bringing joy to those in mourning.
He was highly skilled in church songs and excellent in psalmody, refined in this practice, cheerful in spirit and expression, gentle and very mild, remarkable in every virtue, a father to the clergy, and a pious protector of all the people; slow to anger and quick to show mercy; a lover of God's churches and a very strong defender of the flock entrusted to him by God's power.
He eventually reclaimed various properties and estates of the Church that his predecessor had leased out to different people, either temporarily or permanently.
His diligent pursuit of spiritual matters provided him with abundant temporal goods, which he wisely managed, allocating them to suitable episcopal ministers, while he himself remained constantly devoted to prayer.
On the day of his consecration, July sixth, a proclamation was read in the church of Blessed Mary of Reims excommunicating the people of Baldwin, Count of Flanders, for the murder of Fulco committed by them.
On December twenty-ninth, 901, the body of Saint Remigius was transferred from the cathedral church to its monastery, in the presence of King Charles and Richard, Duke of Burgundy.
Flodoard continues: This bishop repaired and fortified the walls of the castle at Mosamum.
He restored the church there, which had been ruined, and rededicated it in honor of the Holy Mother of God as it was before.
He placed the bones of Saint Victor, found not far from the castle, in the church.
He also established and strengthened a fortification at Codiciacum in a secure location.
Additionally, he constructed another fortification at Sparnacum over the Maternus River.
He restored and consecrated several churches that had been destroyed during the Norman persecution.
In the Vosges, on the property of Saint Remigius, he built a church and dedicated it with the consent of the bishop of Mainz, offering gifts of the same saint there.
At Reims, he consecrated a church in honor of Saint Dionysius outside the city wall, built by the city's canons.
He placed the relics of Blessed Rigobert, bishop, and Saint Theodulph, abbot, there for safekeeping.
He also consecrated a crypt under the main church, which had long been filled with earth, where Blessed Remigius is said to have secretly prayed to God.
He cleaned and decorated it in honor of the same holy bishop.
He adorned the church at Reims with many gifts, illuminating it with silver crowns and lamps of both gold and silver.
He enriched it with other vessels made of precious metals and jewels.
Moreover, he erected and dedicated an altar in the middle of the choir in honor of the Holy Trinity, surrounding it with silver-covered panels.
He covered a large cross with gold and decorated it with gems and sacred relics.
He adorned the sacred hall with many silk ornaments.
He also generously gave many good things to me, as well as to other clerics, canons, monks, nuns, and everyone who sought him out for various needs.
With the Normans establishing a foothold in France amid the discord among rulers, Herveus took it upon himself to seriously address their conversion, hoping that by embracing Christ, the fierceness of the people would be softened, putting an end to pillaging and violence.
There's a letter from Pope John the Ninth to the same prelate, written around the year 901.
It addresses a consultation about the Normans, who had recently converted to the faith.
He mentioned that they should be treated with leniency and that the strictness of the canons shouldn't be enforced against them.
This was to prevent them from rejecting unfamiliar burdens and reverting to their former impiety.
In 905, he held two synods with the bishops of his diocese.
During these meetings, he wisely and appropriately discussed the peace and religion of the holy Church of God and the state of the Frankish kingdom.
At the request of Vithon, who was then the Bishop of Rouen, he compiled and gave twenty-three chapters from various authorities of the Holy Fathers to the same archbishop on how the Normans should be treated.
In 909, on the sixth day before the Kalends of July, he held a council at Trosly.
Around 910, after the death of Anscheric, Bishop of Paris, he became the chief chancellor of the king.
He made significant progress in instructing the Normans in the faith.
After the war that Count Robert waged against them at Chartres, they finally embraced the Christian faith at Rouen.
Some maritime districts were granted to them along with the city of Rouen, which they had nearly destroyed, and others subject to it.
When the Hungarians were ravaging the Lotharingian kingdom, and Charles had called upon the Frankish nobles to aid him against that nation, this prelate alone, among all the leaders of this kingdom, came to the defense of the Church of God with the king in 919, reportedly having fifteen hundred armed men with him.
In 920, when nearly all the Frankish nobles, defecting from their king Charles at the city of Soissons because of Hagano, his counselor, whom he favored and honored above all other princes despite his humble origins, had completely abandoned him, this faithful and pious bishop, always steadfast in danger, fearlessly received the king from that place and led him to his encampment.
From there, he brought him to the city of Reims, accompanying and supporting him for almost seven months until he restored his counts and the kingdom to him.
He then excommunicated Erlebard, the count of the district of Castricum, due to the troubles he caused the bishopric.
He also reclaimed the fortresses of Altimont and Maceriae, which had been taken from the Church of Reims.
He presided over and signed the synod at Trosly in the year 921, in the presence of King Charles, where Count Erlebard was excommunicated but later absolved after his death.
Shortly after, he withdrew from the service of Charles, to whom he had been very loyal and favored until then.
As our Mabilio speculates, this was because the position of chief chancellor, promised to him the previous year, was instead given by Charles to Roger, the Archbishop of Trier.
Finally, after a brief illness, he passed away on July 2, 922, three days after the consecration of King Robert, and just four days before completing the 22nd year of his bishopric.
He was buried with solemn funeral rites attended by several bishops who had arrived in Reims on the day of his death.
Andreas Quercetanus, in his "Genealogical History of the Castellionean Family," where Hervé's eulogy can be found, writes that he was the brother of Odo of Castillon, from whom the entire family line descends. For his writings, see our Rivet, "Historical-Literary France," Volume 6, page 185.
LETTER OF HERVAEUS OF RHEIMS TO WITO, ARCHBISHOP OF ROUEN.
What kind of penance should be imposed on unbaptized pagans, baptized, and rebaptized individuals who later devastate churches like pagans and destroy Christianity?
This is drawn from the teachings of the Fathers, the canons, and the decrees of the Roman pontiffs.
(Ecclesiastical Province of Reims, vol. 1.)
To the most reverend and beloved brother and fellow archbishop WITO, HERVAEUS, Archbishop of Rheims, wishes abundant salvation in our Savior and the happiness of eternal bliss.
You have asked me to seek guidance from the divine oracles for those who have been rebaptized and have returned to pagan ways, like pigs returning to their wallowing and dogs to their vomit, indulging in shameful pleasures in pagan rites.
You also inquired about those who have not yet received baptism.
I have tried to fulfill your request as best as I could, given the limited time.
To make each chapter easier for you to find, we have organized them in this document.
Since the earth is full of the mercy of the Lord (Psalm 33), to whom the Church also prays: You have mercy on all, Lord, and you hate nothing that you have made, overlooking the sins of men for the sake of repentance (Wisdom 11); we deemed it worthy and marvelous to briefly present to you the remarkable and merciful deeds of the blessed John the apostle and evangelist, indeed the most pious work of the Lord himself, as you are very well aware, and more broadly arranged in ecclesiastical history.
Let's talk about Saint John the Evangelist.
After returning to Ephesus and enlightening the surrounding areas, he noticed a young man who was full of spirit.
He entrusted this young man to the local bishop, who baptized him.
However, relying too much on the grace he had received, the young man began to take things lightly.
Unfortunately, with this newfound freedom, he strayed down a corrupt path.
He started with small thefts and other misdeeds, and before long, he became a leader of robbers.
When John returned to the area after some time, he inquired about the young man he had entrusted to the bishop.
Upon learning of his absence, John quickly mounted a horse to search for him.
When he found him and the young man tried to run away, the Apostle called out, "Stop and trust me, because Christ sent me."
Hearing this, the young man stopped.
Trembling, he cried bitterly and fell at the feet of the elderly man who had come to find him, expressing his remorse through sobs and tears.
He was baptized again in tears, hiding only his right hand.
The Apostle, pledging that he would seek the Savior's forgiveness for him, knelt down and kissed the right hand, which had weighed heavily on his conscience, as if it had already been purified.
John brought him back to the church, praying constantly for him and fasting often with him, seeking the forgiveness from God that he had promised.
He didn't stop until he had set him right in all things and even appointed him as a leader in the church.
(Eusebius, Ecclesiastical History, Book 3, Chapter 23).
Let's talk about Saint Silvester and Emperor Constantine.
It's important to recall the significant act of Pope Silvester with Emperor Constantine, particularly regarding the week-long fast he imposed on him.
Saint Silvester told the Emperor, "Commit to a week of fasting, set aside your royal garments, enter your room, wear sackcloth, and lie on the ground.
Confess that you were wrong due to ignorance in persecuting Christians.
Proclaim and believe in Jesus Christ, the Savior of both bodies and souls, and repent for having killed many of God's saints."
He further instructed, "Ensure that alms are given throughout the week, provide aid to those in need, and appoint trustworthy people to carry out these tasks."
Later, Saint Silvester placed his hand on Emperor Constantine's head, blessing him and making him a catechumen.
Then, he gathered all the priests, deacons, and the entire clergy, declaring a fast for the whole church, saying:
"If the people of Nineveh, through Jonah's preaching, escaped God's promised wrath by fasting for three days, how much more will we, through the preaching of our Lord Jesus Christ, escape persecution.
We save souls, acquire God's peace for the churches, and put an end to idolatry.
We do these things with fasting and prayer to obtain these blessings from God."
Gregory, in his homily on the Gospel to the people
(Homilies 19 and 20 on the Gospel), says,
"If you did not choose to live for God during your childhood and youth, at least repent in your old age and return to the right path.
Even if you can no longer do much work, come at last."
He continues after a few words, "Often, such people are rewarded first because they enter the kingdom before those who seemed to be called even in their childhood.
Did the thief not come at the eleventh hour? Even though he didn't have it by age, he found it later through suffering, as he confessed God on the cross;
and almost with the voice of a sentence, he breathed out the spirit of life.
The master began to give the denarius from the last because he led the thief to the rest of paradise before Peter."
Again he says, "The kingdom of heaven wants to be seized by our tears, which is not owed to our merits.
Therefore, let no quality or quantity of our sins break the certainty of our hope.
The venerable thief, who is not venerable because he was a thief, gives great confidence in forgiveness.
For he was a thief through cruelty, venerable through confession.
I urge you to consider how incomprehensible the depths of mercy are in Almighty God.
This thief, with bloody hands, was snatched from the edge of the journey and was hung on the cross.
There he confessed, there he was healed, there he deserved to hear: 'Today you will be with me in paradise.' And so on."
From the same author to Bishop Peter.
Writing again to Bishop Peter of Corsica, he states in Book Seven, Letter Two:
Your brotherhood should diligently strive, with the Lord's help, to complete the work you have begun.
Hurry to bring back to the faith those who once believed but have returned to idol worship out of negligence or necessity.
Assign them a penance for several days, so they may mourn their wrongdoing and hold more firmly to what they return to with the Lord’s help, fully grieving what they leave behind.
For those who are not yet baptized, urge them, beg them, frighten them with the coming judgment, and explain why they should not worship wood and stone.
May your brotherhood hurry to gather them for the Almighty Lord, so that when He comes and the solemn day of judgment arrives, your holiness may be found among the saints.
For what could be more useful and noble than focusing on the revival and gathering of souls, bringing eternal gain to your Lord, who has given you the place to preach?
From the same letter to Abbot Mellitus:
And elsewhere to Abbot Mellitus, Book Nine, Letter Seventy-One:
The English people have a tradition of sacrificing many oxen to demons, so we should adapt part of this custom.
On the day of dedication or the birthday of the holy martyrs whose relics are placed there, they should build tents around these churches—converted from pagan temples—using tree branches, and celebrate with religious feasts.
Instead of sacrificing animals to the devil, they should prepare the animals for their meals in praise of God and give thanks to the giver of all things for their abundance.
This way, while enjoying some external pleasures, they may more easily come to embrace inner joys.
It's undoubtedly impossible to immediately eliminate everything from stubborn minds.
Just as someone trying to reach a high place climbs using steps or stairs, not by jumping.
Similarly, the Lord revealed Himself to the people of Israel in Egypt, but He reserved for His own worship the practice of sacrifices they used to offer to the devil, instructing them to sacrifice animals in His service.
Thus, by changing their hearts, they would abandon some aspects of sacrifice while retaining others.
Even if they offered the same animals they were used to, by sacrificing them to the true God and not to idols, those sacrifices would no longer be the same.
Bishop Ambrose, speaking on the gentle acceptance of those who repent, writes in his book "On Repentance" (Chapter 1):
"Someone aiming to correct human weaknesses must bear them on their shoulders and support them, not reject them.
For the gospel shepherd is described as carrying the weary sheep, not casting it aside."
And Solomon says: "Do not be overly righteous" (Ecclesiasticus 17).
Justice should indeed be tempered with moderation.
How can you treat someone with disdain, someone who feels like an object of contempt rather than compassion from their healer?
Thus, the Lord Jesus showed compassion to draw us to Him, not to deter us.
He came gentle and humble, saying: "Come to me, all you who labor, and I will give you rest" (Matthew 11).
Therefore, the Lord Jesus restores, does not exclude or cast aside, and rightly chose disciples who would gather God’s people as interpreters of His will, not reject them.
It is clear that those who favor harshness over gentleness, arrogance over humility, are not to be considered among Christ’s disciples.
While they seek the Lord's mercy, they deny it to others, like the teachers of the Novatians, who call themselves pure.
What could be more arrogant than this?
Scripture says: "No one is pure from sin, not even a newborn" (Job 14); and David cries: "Cleanse me from my sin" (Psalm 50).
And shortly thereafter: "No one can genuinely repent unless they hope for forgiveness."
Augustine.
Blessed Augustine gives us a brief lesson on how those in authority should handle wicked people, saying:
"We shouldn't lose hope in the wicked. Instead, we should pray more earnestly for them to become good, because the number of saints has always grown from the ranks of the impious."
Section eight: About Saint Remigius the Bishop.
In the book of the Life of Blessed Remigius, Apostle of the Franks, written by Hincmar, it describes the conversion of King Louis and his people, among other things.
Saint Remigius, filled with great joy, instructed the king and the people in clear and simple words on how they should renounce the devil, his works, and his displays, and believe in God.
As the day of Holy Easter was approaching, he prescribed fasting for them according to Christian custom.
Section 9. About Saint Vedastus, Bishop.
In the life of the blessed Bishop Vedastus, there's a story of how, while on a journey with the king and his people, Vedastus, a man of God, gave sight to a blind man, leading the king to embrace baptism.
In the city of Reims, Vedastus was entrusted to Saint Remigius.
The king, having been deeply taught by Vedastus in the Gospel's teachings, and strengthened in his faith by this miracle, wasted no time on the road.
With great joy and eagerness, he hurried to meet the holy Bishop Remigius.
There, through the sacred ministry and the work of the Holy Spirit, he sought to be cleansed in the living waters of Catholic baptism for the forgiveness of sins and the hope of eternal life.
He stayed with Remigius for several days to fulfill the church's requirements, first cleansing himself with tears of repentance, as the apostolic command from Blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, states:
"Repent, and let every one of you be baptized in the name of our Lord Jesus" (Acts, Chapter 2).
And thus, he received the baptism of the heavenly mystery in the name of the Holy Trinity.
From the life of Saint Basil, there is a story about an apostate.
It's found in the miracles of Saint Basil, Bishop of Caesarea, about someone who denied Christ in writing and surrendered himself to the devil as proof of his denial.
The remarkable man Basil asked him, "Do you wish to return to the Lord our God?"
The boy replied, "Of course I want to, but I can't."
Basil asked, "Why?"
The boy answered, "I denied Christ in writing and pledged myself to the devil."
Saint Basil reassured him, "Do not worry: our God is kind and will accept you if you repent. He understands our wrongdoings."
After some time, the saint asked the boy, "Do you believe you can be saved?"
The boy replied, "I believe, Lord, help my unbelief."
Then immediately, Basil held his hand, made the sign of Christ on him, and prayed. He enclosed him in the inner sacred place, providing guidance and working with him for three days.
After some time, on the fortieth day, the saint returned and asked, "How are you, brother?"
The boy responded, "I am well, holy one of God. I saw you today in a vision fighting for me and defeating the devil."
The next morning, Basil called the clergy, the monasteries, and all the people loved by Christ, and said, "My dearest children, give thanks to the Lord: behold, the lost sheep is brought back on the good shepherd's shoulders and offered to the church."
Therefore, it is fitting for us to keep vigil at night and ask for His kindness, so the corrupter of souls does not prevail in this matter.
Together, with the gathered people throughout the night, they petitioned God with tears, crying out, "Lord, have mercy."
Early, with the multitude of people, the saint took the boy and, holding his right hand, led him into the holy church of God with psalms and hymns.
Behold, the devil, casting a spell on everyone's eyes, came with all his harmful power to a life of sorrow, and invisibly grabbed the boy, trying to snatch him from the saint's hand.
The boy began to cry out, "Holy one of God, help me."
Once again, the holy man turned to the devil and said,
"Most wicked one, corrupter of souls, father of darkness and ruin, isn't your own destruction enough for you, which has affected you and those under you, without also trying to harm the creation of my God?"
After a few words were exchanged, the holy man of God said to the devil,
"The Lord rebuke you, devil."
The devil replied,
"Basil, you judge me unfairly. I did not go to him; he came to me. He denied Christ and declared his allegiance to me. Look, I have a written document, and on the day of judgment, I will bring him before the common judge."
The holy man of God responded,
"Blessed is the Lord my God. These people will not lower their hands from the heights of heaven until you return the document."
Turning to the people, he said,
"Raise your hands to heaven, crying out with tears, 'Christ, Lord, have mercy.'"
As the people stood for a long time with their hands extended to heaven, behold, the boy's document was carried through the air, seen by all, and was placed in the hands of our memorable father and shepherd.
Receiving it and giving thanks to God, he was very joyful and said to the boy in front of all the people,
"Do you recognize these letters, brother?"
The boy replied,
"Yes, holy man of God, it is my document."
Tearing up the document, Saint Basil led him to the church and made him worthy of the holy ministry, the communion of mysteries, and the gifts of Christ.
In the story of Blessed Lawrence, the archdeacon and martyr of Christ, there's a remarkable account.
A man, who had been imprisoned for a long time, had lost his sight from crying after losing his eyes.
He was a non-believer.
Blessed Lawrence spoke to him, " If you believe in the Son of God, the Lord Jesus Christ, I will baptize you, and He will enlighten you."
Immediately after his confession and baptism, his eyes were opened, and he began to shout, " Blessed is the eternal Lord God, who has enlightened me through Blessed Lawrence, because I was once blind and now I see."
Following this, he also catechized the blessed Hippolytus in the usual way, then took water, blessed it, and baptized him.
In a similar fashion, he baptized the soldier Romanus, who, after being baptized, was soon crowned with martyrdom.
About Saint Sebastian.
The account of Saint Sebastian's martyrdom tells us that when everyone who initially sought to deceive the saints, including Mark and Marcellian, came to believe in Christ with a unified spirit, Nicostratus and his wife urged them, saying, "I will not eat or drink until the mystery of the Christian faith is revealed to me."
To this, Saint Sebastian responded, "Change your stance, and choose to be more of Christ's scribe than the prefect's.
Listen to my advice: gather all those confined in prison, those held by chains, and those exhausted by labor.
Once you do this, I will bring a priest of the holy law, so you can receive the sacrament of the mystery with all who wish to believe.
If the devil has tried and continues to try to take away Christ's saints, how much more should we, with compassion, care for those whom the devil has unjustly claimed and restore them to their Creator?"
Nicostratus then asked, "How can the holy things be entrusted to the wicked and criminal?"
Saint Sebastian replied, "Our Savior found it worthy to present Himself to us for sinners and revealed the mystery that removes all sins and crimes from people, while bestowing all virtues of the Lord."
After much discussion, Saint Sebastian went to see Saint Polycarp, the priest who was hiding due to persecution, and told him everything that had happened.
Upon hearing this, Polycarp gave thanks to God and accompanied him to the house of Nicostratus.
Seeing the gathering of believers, he greeted them with great joy and said, "Blessed are you all who have heard the voice of our Lord Jesus Christ, saying, 'Come to me, all you who labor and are burdened, and I will give you rest.
Take my yoke upon you and learn from me, for I am gentle and humble in heart, and you will find rest for your souls.
For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.'" (Matthew 11:28-30).
Therefore, my brothers, you who have been cleansed by the waters of baptism and made beloved children consecrated to Almighty God.
Because you attempted to turn the most blessed soldiers of Christ away from their holy purpose, you needed repentance to receive forgiveness.
But now, since you've reached such glory that you even desire to gladly embrace the suffering you once tried to deter others from, this is an ancient strategy of Christ.
For the very one He deemed worthy to be His chosen vessel and wanted to make the teacher of the nations, who not only turned the hearts of the faithful away from their devotion but even buried those unwilling to depart from Christ under stones: this apostle the Lord Himself has given to us.
He transformed Saul into Paul for us, making an apostle out of an apostate, and giving the Church a leader from a persecutor.
He who was once the author of persecution became a lover of suffering; and he who once rejoiced in the afflictions of others, later rejoiced in his own persecutions.
He who then exercised this power in His apostle has now rescued your souls from the very jaws of hell, from the very mouth of dragons.
As you now return from darkness to light, He has opened the gates of eternal life for you.
Because all the demons, who are children of darkness, are saddened; and all the holy angels, who are children of light, rejoice.
Let each one come forward and give their name, so that with fasting leading us through today until evening, the festive sacrament of baptism may find an opportune time.
The whole family that was in the house of Nicostratus, a total of 33 souls of mixed gender and age, along with all who were bound and brought from the filth of the prison, 16 souls, all these 49 were baptized by Saint Polycarp the priest and received by Saint Sebastian.
Thirteen. Words of Lord Bede in John chapter 3.
According to the life-giving and firm doctrine of the Catholic faith, which must be observed unanimously and faithfully by everyone around the world:
What is true of physical birth must also be understood about spiritual birth:
Namely, that it cannot be repeated once it has been completed.
Whether it is a heretic, a schismatic, or a criminal, anyone who baptizes in the confession of the Holy Trinity:
The person who is baptized this way cannot be rebaptized by good Catholics,
So that the confession or the invocation of such a great name does not appear to be annulled.
Pope Leo.
For those who are unsure if they have been baptized, they need to be reborn, as stated in the decrees of Pope Leo in his letter to Rusticus.
If there's no evidence from family, laypeople, clergy, or neighbors showing that someone has been baptized, they should be reborn.
This ensures they do not visibly perish, as reason does not allow assuming something has been repeated if it cannot be shown to have been done.
However, those who remember going to church with their parents might recall if they received what their parents gave them.
If even this is beyond their memory, it seems appropriate to bestow upon them what is unknown to have been given.
There is no rash presumption where there is careful devotion.
Fifteenth: Also Leo.
For captives who eat sacrificial foods out of necessity, penance should be granted according to the decrees of Pope Leo, as mentioned in his letter to Nicetas.
Regarding those Christians who, while captured, are reported to have been defiled by consuming sacrificial foods:
We believe the answer to your charitable inquiry should be that they are cleansed through the satisfaction of penance, which should be guided not so much by the duration, but by the sincerity of their contrition.
And whether this was done out of fear or driven by hunger, there should be no doubt about abolishing it, since such consumption is out of fear or need, not out of respect for the religion.
From the Council of Nicaea, concerning laypeople who denied God and those who renounced and then returned to worldly ways, as stated in canon 11:
Regarding those who lapsed without necessity, whether due to loss of property, danger, or similar circumstances under the tyranny of Licinius: the synod decided that, although they may be deemed unworthy of kindness, they should still be shown goodwill.
Therefore, anyone who shows genuine repentance should be placed among the faithful listeners for three years.
For six years, they should humble themselves in every way.
And for two years, they may join the people in prayer during the offering.
Bishop Gratus said:
If it pleases you, let's first consider the topic of rebaptism.
Therefore, I ask your holiness to share your thoughts about someone descending into water,
being asked about the Trinity according to the faith of the Gospel and the teaching of the apostles,
and who has confessed a good conscience toward God regarding the resurrection of Jesus Christ:
Is it permissible to be questioned again in the same faith and to be baptized again in water?
All the bishops said: No, no, we declare rebaptism to be forbidden,
and it is quite contrary to sincere faith and Catholic discipline.
Eighteen. From the Council of Ancyra.
(Council of Ancyra, canon 1.)
This concerns those who, out of fear, participated in pagan rites.
Anyone who entered the temples wearing mourning clothes and ate while sitting among others, crying; after completing three years of penance, may be received into communion without making an offering themselves.
However, if they were taken to the temples but did not eat, they should remain in penance for two years; in the third year, they may communicate, but again without offering, so that in the fourth year they may achieve full reconciliation.
The bishop must exercise discretion in considering each individual's sins and, based on their behavior, assign the appropriate standard and rule for conversion.
This means acting with compassion to either shorten the penance period based on their conduct or extend it if necessary for correction.
The past and present lives of all these individuals should be examined.
In this way, priestly kindness should guide their governance.
From the same source, in the same place, Canon 6.
This concerns those who frequently sacrificed to idols, as discussed at the Council of Ancyra:
For those who participated in feasts during pagan festival days in remote areas and even brought and ate their own meals there:
It has been decided that after two years of penance, they may be allowed back.
However, whether they should be received with an offering or only admitted to communion should be decided by each bishop, who should assess their lives and consider both their past and present conduct.
From the same source, Canon 7, concerning those who were forced to sacrifice to idols from the same council:
Those who sacrificed a second or third time under coercion should undergo penance for four years.
For the following two years, they should participate in communion without offering, and in the seventh year, they will receive full communion.
Pope Leo the Twenty-first.
Regarding those who have joined in feasts with pagans and eaten food offered to idols, and the decrees of Pope Leo in his letter to Rustic.
If they have only joined in these feasts and eaten such food, they can be cleansed through fasting and the laying on of hands.
This allows them, by avoiding idol offerings, to partake in the sacraments of Christ.
However, if they have worshiped idols, or have been involved in murder or fornication, they should only be admitted to communion through public penance.
Pope Leo addresses those who have been compelled to undergo a second baptism due to force or fear, stating they should be guided through the path of penance.
In his message to Rusticus, Bishop of Narbonne, Pope Leo says:
Those whom you have asked us about, who have been forced to repeat baptism out of fear or have been misled by error, and now understand they acted against the sacrament of the Catholic faith, should be brought back into our community only through penance and the laying on of the bishop's hand to restore unity of communion.
The duration of penance should be decided by your usual judgment, considering the devotion in the hearts of those who have converted, as well as the factors of old age and the necessities that arise from various dangers or illnesses.
In situations where someone is under severe pressure and, while still repenting, there is little hope for their salvation, it is crucial to extend to them the grace of communion through priestly care.
From the Acts of the Apostles.
In the Acts of the Apostles, it mentions that some people who came down from Judea were teaching the believers that they needed to be circumcised and adhere to the law of Moses.
However, the apostles and elders, along with the entire Church, decided not to place any additional burden on them, except for abstaining from food offered to idols, from blood, from what is strangled, and from sexual immorality.
(Acts chapter fifteen).
Section 24. From the Council of Africa.
Regarding the Donatists, who were condemned by all Catholics and the entire world, it was decided that a gentler approach should be taken, according to the Council of Africa, year 401, canon 3.
After careful discussion and consideration of what would benefit the Church, and with the agreement and guidance of the Spirit of God, we chose to deal gently and peacefully with these individuals, even though they were separated from the unity of the Lord's body due to ongoing disagreements.
We want it to be widely known throughout all the African provinces, to everyone involved in their communion and society, how unfortunately they are caught in error.
Perhaps, as the Apostle says, while we correct those who think differently with gentleness, God may grant them the repentance needed to recognize the truth and recover from the devil's traps, having been captured by him to do his will.
No one should be denied the chance for final repentance, as stated in the letter from Pope Celestine to the bishops of Gaul.
We've heard that some are being denied repentance as they are dying, and we cannot agree with those who refuse this remedy for the soul at a person's final hour.
It's shocking to think anyone could be so heartless as to doubt God's mercy, as if He couldn't help anyone who turns to Him, even at the end, to save them from the weight of their sins.
Isn't this like adding death to someone already dying, and cruelly preventing their soul from being freed?
God is always ready to help, calling for repentance, and promises: "Whenever a sinner turns, their sins will not be counted."
And again: "I do not want the death of a sinner, but that they turn and live."
So, denying repentance to a person at death takes away their salvation, and doubting God's mercy means not believing He can help even in those final moments.
The thief on the cross would have lost his reward at Christ's side if he hadn't received the benefit of one hour of repentance.
Even while being punished, he repented, and with just one confession, he earned a place in paradise, as God promised.
Therefore, genuine conversion to God in one's last moments should be judged by the sincerity of the heart, not the time left, as the prophet says: "When you turn and groan, then you will be saved."
Since the Lord examines hearts, repentance should never be denied to anyone who seeks it, for they are accountable to the judge, who knows all hidden things will be revealed.
Chapter 26. From the Penitential of Bede.
In the booklet titled The Penitential of Bede, the venerable priest explains in the preface about remedies for sins:
We strongly advise every learned priest of Christ to carefully consider the gender, age, condition, status, person, and even the heart of the penitent in all the matters discussed here.
Based on these observations, they should judge each situation as they see fit.
For some, this might involve abstaining from certain foods.
For others, it could mean giving alms or frequently kneeling in prayer.
Some may need to stand at the cross or engage in other suitable acts for the cleansing of sins; many will need to do all these things.
It's essential to correct mistakes, all of which should be carefully weighed by a discerning judge.
May your esteemed and cherished brotherhood always thrive with successful outcomes in Christ, and may it flourish in all good things, remembering us in their prayers and in the prayers of the whole Church.