The Decrees of Sixtus the Second
From Gratian,
If anyone feels wronged by their metropolitan, they should seek judgment from the diocese's primate or the pope of the universal apostolic Church.
When it comes to appeals, judges from a different province shouldn't hear the case.
If a cleric is accused of a crime, the proceedings should take place in the province where the accused resides.
The accuser shouldn't consider taking the cleric to a court in a different or more distant location.
Letters Pertaining to Sixtus the Second, Pope and Martyr.
Letters One
Fragments of Dionysius of Alexandria, Bishop, to Pope Sixtus
Dionysius mentions the letters he wrote to Pope Stephen, as well as to Dionysius and Philemon, the priests, regarding the baptism of heretics and the Sabellian heresy.
Previously, Stephen had indeed written letters concerning Helenus and Firmilian, and all those established throughout Cilicia and Cappadocia, as well as the neighboring provinces, stating that he would withdraw from their communion for the same reason: because they were rebaptizing heretics.
Consider the seriousness of the matter.
In fact, I've heard that it was decreed in the greatest councils of bishops that those coming from heresy should first be taught the doctrine and then cleansed from the impurities of the old and impure leaven through baptism.
I sent letters requesting and urging him about all these matters.
And a little later, Dionysius continues.
To our beloved fellow priests, Dionysius and Philemon, who initially agreed with Stephen and had written to me about these matters, I replied with a few words earlier, but now I have much more to say.
In the same letter about the Sabellian heretics, Eusebius mentions in his History, Book 7, Chapter 6, that he informs Xistus with these words:
"Regarding the doctrine that recently emerged in the city of Ptolemais in the Pentapolis, which is impious and full of blasphemy against Almighty God and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, and filled with disbelief and treachery towards His only-begotten Son, the firstborn of all creation, the Word made man, and which diminishes the understanding of the Holy Spirit:
when letters were brought to me from both sides and brothers came to debate, I wrote certain letters, explaining as clearly as God enabled me; I have sent you copies of these."
Letters Two
Bishop Dionysius of Alexandria to Philemon Priest of Sixtus, Fragments
I was deeply engaged in reading the books and learning the traditions of heretics.
Though my mind was temporarily tainted by their detestable ideas, I gained the ability to refute them to myself, growing to detest them even more.
When a certain brother from the order of priests tried to dissuade me, fearing I might be drawn into the same wickedness—he truly believed my mind would be contaminated—I was strengthened by a vision sent by God.
A clear message came to me, instructing: "Read everything that comes into your hands, for you are capable of correcting and testing each thing: and from this, you first found a reason and opportunity to believe."
I accepted this vision as it aligned with the apostolic voice, addressing those more powerful: "Be skilled money changers" (First Thessalonians 5:21).
Then, Eusebius mentions that after discussing all the heresies, some additional points are added.
He says, "I received this rule and form from our blessed Pope Heraclas."
For those coming from the heresies, whether they had defected from the Church or not, even if they appeared to be attending gatherings of the faithful but were accused of listening to false teachings, he would not allow them back into the Church until, after many prayers, they publicly and openly recounted everything they had heard from their opponents.
Only then were they admitted into gatherings of the faithful, and he never asked them to be baptized again.
For they had already received the Holy Spirit from him previously.
Once this question was thoroughly discussed, he adds,
furthermore, I learned that this custom was not only recently introduced among the Africans, but it existed long before in the times of earlier bishops in the most populous churches.
It was also approved by the councils of brothers held at Iconium and Synada, as well as by many others.
I do not wish to overturn their decisions and cause arguments and disputes.
For it is said:
You shall not move your neighbor's boundary marker, which the fathers have set.
Deuteronomy 19:14.
I also learned that this was not introduced only now by those in Africa, but also long ago during the times of the bishops before us in the most populous churches.
It was approved by the councils of brothers in Iconium and Synada, and by many others.
I will not endure overturning their plans and causing strife and contention.
For you shall not move, it says, your neighbor's boundary marker, which your fathers have set.
Letters Three A Fragment from Bishop Dionysius of Alexandria to Dionysius—then a presbyter under Sixtus and later his successor.
Novatian should be opposed due to his actions causing a schism, promoting ungodly doctrine, and his practice of re-baptizing those who come to him.
It's right for us to reject Novatian because he divided the Church and led some of the brothers into impiety and blasphemy.
He brought a highly ungodly teaching about God into the world and falsely portrays our most merciful Lord Jesus Christ as unmerciful.
Moreover, he dismisses the sacred washing as invalid and undermines the faith and confession that come before baptism.
He completely drives the Holy Spirit away from them, even if there's a hope that it might still be with them or could return to them.
Letters Four A Fragment from Bishop Dionysius of Alexandria to Pope Sixtus II.
This is about a man who wanted to join the Church through baptism, claiming he had been baptized with different words and practices among heretics.
Honestly, brother, I need your advice and opinion to ensure I don't make a mistake regarding a situation that has come my way.
One of the brothers, who regularly attends church gatherings and has long been considered faithful—and, if I'm not mistaken, was part of the assembly of the faithful before my ordination and even before Heraclas's episcopate—came to me after witnessing a recent baptism.
He heard the questions and responses and approached me, weeping and lamenting his situation.
He fell at my feet, confessing and swearing that the baptism he received among the heretics was nothing like ours, having no commonality: it was full of impiety and blasphemy.
He said his soul was pierced with the deepest pain, and he didn't even dare to lift his eyes to God because he had been initiated with those wicked words and deeds.
So, he begged to receive the grace of this pure washing.
I didn't dare to do this; instead, I told him that his long participation in communion was sufficient for that.
For he who has heard the thanksgiving, responded "Amen" with the others; stood at the sacred table, extended his hands to receive the holy food, and participated in the body and blood of our Lord Jesus Christ for a long time—I would not dare to renew him completely again.
I urged him to have courage, approach the Holy things with firm faith and a good conscience, and become a partaker of them.
However, he continues to mourn, shuddering to approach the table, barely enduring to attend prayers when asked.
Truly, brother, I need counsel, and I am asking for your opinion on this matter that has come to me, fearing that I might err.
A man, considered trustworthy and ancient, even before my ordination and before the blessed Heraclas was established, joined the gathering of brothers.
He was present at the baptisms and heard the questions and answers.
He came to me, crying and lamenting about his situation.
Falling at my feet, he confessed and renounced the baptism he received from the heretics, claiming it was false and that he had no part in it because it was filled with impiety and blasphemies.
He expressed that his soul was deeply wounded, and he couldn't lift his eyes to God due to those unholy words and deeds.
He begged for genuine purification and acceptance of grace.
I hesitated, saying that his long-standing communion should be enough for him.
Having heard the thanksgiving, said "Amen," stood at the table, extended his hands to receive the holy food, and partook of the body and blood of our Lord Jesus Christ for a long time, I couldn't dare to undo it from the beginning.
I encouraged him to be confident and to approach the holy things with firm faith and a good conscience.
However, he couldn't stop mourning and didn't dare to come near the table, barely enduring the encouragement to stand with the prayers.