LETTER ABOUT THE CYNOCHEPHALI, WRITTEN TO RIMBERT THE PRIEST.
by RATRAMNUS, MONK OF CORBIE
To the venerable priest RIMBERT, honored by the gifts of divine grace and greatly loved in Christ,
RATRAMNUS sends eternal greetings in the Lord Jesus Christ.
Your letter brought me great joy, sharing what you have learned about the nature of the Cynocephali.
I want to explain why I did not respond to your questions earlier; it was not due to negligence, but rather because the messenger was not available, causing a delay.
Now, with Brother Sarward visiting us and then returning to you, I have the opportunity to briefly share my thoughts on your inquiry.
You ask what you should believe about the Cynocephali, specifically whether they are descendants of Adam or if they have the souls of beasts.
This question can be answered concisely.
If they are considered part of the human race, there should be no doubt that they descended from the lineage of the first man.
It is not proper to believe that human origin comes from anywhere other than the substance of the first parent.
But if they are counted among the beasts, then they only share the name "human" and not the nature.
It should be known, however, if we follow the opinion of our ecclesiastical teachers, that they are to be counted among the beasts rather than humans, since both the shape of their heads and their barking like dogs show them to be similar to beasts, not humans.
Humans, with their rounded heads, look up to the sky, while dogs, with their elongated heads and snouts, look down at the ground. And humans speak, while dogs bark.
The truth is, the letters sent by your kindness have taught us things that seem to align more with human reasoning than animal sensitivity.
They observe certain social laws, and their village cohabitation bears witness to this.
They practice farming and gather their crops.
Unlike animals, they cover their private parts with modesty, indicating decency.
They use not only skins but also clothes, as you mentioned.
All these behaviors suggest that they possess a rational soul.
A city is a gathering of people living together under the same law, and these beings live in village communities, suggesting a similar structure.
They form a community through their gatherings, which requires some form of law.
Where there is law, there is unity of minds through agreement.
Such a law could not exist without moral discipline.
Cultivating fields, plowing the land, and sowing crops demonstrate skill in agriculture, which is a rational pursuit.
Reason seeks to understand what makes the land fertile and what causes crop abundance, knowledge necessary for proper farming.
Making coverings from skin, wool, or linen is also a rational activity, requiring skill and knowledge.
Covering private parts is a sign of decency, sought by a mind that distinguishes between shameful and decent.
One can only feel shame with an understanding of decency.
Here, however, only someone lacking reason would deny that all these qualities are unique to the rational soul.
The ability to distinguish between what is honorable and what is shameful, to excel in the knowledge of the arts and sciences, and to establish laws of peace and harmony—all of these require the judgment of reason and the sharpness of intellect.
Therefore, when you attribute such qualities to the Cynocephali, you acknowledge that they possess a rational mind.
Indeed, humans are distinguished from beasts by reason.
This trait, which appears to be present in those we discuss, suggests they should be considered humans rather than beasts.
This intelligence is supported by the book about the martyrdom of Saint Christopher.
According to that book, it is known that he was from this race of people, whose life and martyrdom are highly praised for notable virtues.
It is believed that he received the sacrament of baptism divinely, with a cloud ministering to him, as the book itself testifies.
It is also widely reported that many signs suggest this kind of people possess reason.
Isidore, when discussing the variety of portents descending from the human race in the books of Etymologies, said:
Just as there are certain monstrous individuals among each nation, so in the whole human race, there are certain monstrous nations, such as Giants, Cynocephali, Cyclopes, and others.
By saying this, he clearly indicated that he believed the Cynocephali originated from the lineage of the first human.
Just as in each nation certain individuals seem to be created against the law of nature, such as people with two heads, people with three hands, dwarfs, hermaphrodites, or androgynes, or many others, these occurrences do not happen against the law of nature but come about through their own certain disposition, since the law of nature is the disposition of Divinity.
Similarly, those monstrous births of humans mentioned earlier seem to introduce a bizarre element to the natural order of humanity.
These include various strange beings, such as Pygmies and Anticaudae, who are said to be about one cubit tall, and others with feet turned backward and eight toes on each foot.
There are also Hippodes, who have a mix of human and horse features, Macrobii, who are nearly twice the height of ordinary humans, and a tribe of women in India who conceive at five years old and do not live beyond eight years, along with many other absurd and unbelievable beings.
Although it is said that these beings originated from humans, we should not hastily conclude that they possess rational human thinking.
As for the Giants, who are counted among these marvels, almost no one doubts that they were born from humans, as this is confirmed by the holy scriptures.
When the Cynocephali are included among them, it is also believed that they originated from humans, especially if the stories about Saint Christopher are true, as popular legends suggest.
However, just because these beings are said to come from humans, it does not mean that they all possess human reason.
For example, if a calf or a snake is born from a woman, I would not agree that such a calf or snake possesses a human or rational soul.
Similarly, the monstrous birth during the time of King Alexander, from a woman whose upper part resembled a human but the lower part took on various forms of living beasts.
Yet, I do not believe that those beasts, although created from human seed, possessed a rational soul, except for one devoid of reason.
Therefore, I do not believe that these beings, just because they originated from humans, immediately possess a rational mind, unless what is written or said about them convinces me otherwise.
Now, however, what's being said about this seems so significant and compelling that to either not believe it or to want to contradict it would appear more like stubbornness than wisdom.
Additionally, your writings indicate that all kinds of domestic animals found in our regions are also present among them.
This could only happen if these creatures had a non-rational and bestial soul, which I find hard to believe.
For, according to Genesis, animals were divinely subjected to man.
But for beasts to care for creatures of a different kind, especially domesticated ones, and to show them diligence, and compel them to obey and serve, is unheard of and unbelievable.
However, the Cynocephali, who are said to have many domestic animals, do not align with the ferocity of beasts, whose domestic animals are tamed by gentleness.
These are my thoughts on the Cynocephali.
However, whether others feel the same way or differently, is not for us to judge.
Regarding the book of the blessed Clement that you asked about, it does not hold full authority among scholars, though it is not entirely dismissed.
Some things in it do not fully align with our ecclesiastical doctrine.
However, what is written about the deeds of the apostle Paul is accepted, as it does not contradict Christian doctrine.
We always rejoice in your blessedness in Christ, and we pray that you remember us.