On the Prophet Amos
by Haymo of Halberstadt
The Prophet Amos, whose name means "good," prophesied in Samaria and Jerusalem. He described the sins of the nations using the image of the whole world.
He foretold the coming of Christ with the voice of the Lord, saying:
"I make thunder, and create the Spirit, and announce Christ among humans."
The rest of what he says about Amaziah and Jeroboam, or Israel, should be understood as referring to heretics.
Chapter One
These are the words of Amos, one of the shepherds of Tekoa, which he received about Israel during the days of Uzziah, king of Judah, and Jeroboam, son of Joash, king of Israel, two years before the earthquake.
Amos means "a people carried away." Uzziah means "the power or strength of the Lord." Jeroboam means "indictment or cause of the people." Joash means "the Lord's memory or temporality."
Tekoa, which means "trumpet," signifies the prophecies of the prophets.
And he said, "The Lord will roar from Zion and raise his voice from Jerusalem. The beautiful places of the shepherds will mourn, and the top of Carmel will dry up."
From Jerusalem, where the temple and God's religion resided, where Christ arose, like a lion, through the preaching of the Gospel, he raised his voice.
The beautiful places of the shepherds represent the people of the Jews. The top of Carmel symbolizes the temple, kingdom, or priesthood of the Jews.
This is what the Lord says: "For three crimes of Damascus, and for four, I will not turn away its punishment, because they have threshed Gilead with iron sledges. I will send fire upon the house of Hazael, and it will devour the palaces of Ben-Hadad."
The three and four crimes of the nations, which are repeatedly mentioned, are these: The first crime is that all die in Adam. The second is that, forgetful of reason by the innate law of nature, they did not understand. The third is that those who were given the law did not obey it. The fourth is the refusal of those who did not believe in Christ.
After listing the crimes of the nations, Judah is accused in the seventh place of breaking the law, and Israel in the eighth place for their impiety towards Christ.
Alternatively, the three and four crimes can be seen as thinking, consenting, acting, and not repenting; or thinking, speaking, acting, and defending one's sin.
The first sin is to have thought what is evil, the second is to have agreed with those thoughts, the third is to have acted upon them, and the fourth is not to have repented afterwards.
Hazael means "work of God."
"I will break the bar of Damascus, cut off the inhabitant from the Valley of Idolatry, and remove the one who holds the scepter from the house of pleasure. The people of Syria will go into exile to Kir," says the Lord.
Damascus means "drinking blood" or "approving blood," a symbol of this world.
This is what the Lord says:
For three crimes of Gaza, and for four, I will not turn back, because they took away an entire captivity to deliver them up to Edom.
I will send fire upon the walls of Gaza, and it will consume its palaces.
I will destroy the inhabitants of Ashdod and the one who holds the scepter from Ashkelon.
I will turn my hand against Ekron, and the remaining Philistines will perish, says the Lord God.
Gaza means "his strength."
This is what the Lord says:
For three crimes of Tyre, and for four, I will not turn back, because they delivered an entire captivity to Edom and did not remember the covenant of brothers.
Tyre means "tribulation" or "narrowing."
It represents the doctrines of heretics, which try to capture the truth and confine it to earthly senses.
I will send fire upon the walls of Tyre, and it will consume its palaces.
The fire seems to signify the impiety of heretics, which devours their gatherings, like walls or houses, that is, their consciences.
It may also signify future damnation.
This is what the Lord says:
For three crimes of Edom, and for four, I will not turn back, because he pursued his brother with the sword and violated his mercy, holding onto his fury and keeping his indignation forever.
Edom, which means "red" or "earthly," represents the people of the Jews and heretics persecuting their brother, that is, Christ in his members.
I will send fire upon Teman, and it will consume the palaces of Bozrah.
The Lord will send fire upon Teman, that is, in the dry and barren Judah, so that with all literal sense collapsing, the Church of Christ the Lord may be built upon foundations.
This is what the Lord says:
For three crimes of the children of Ammon, and for four, I will not turn back, because they ripped open the pregnant women of Gilead to enlarge their border.
And I will set fire to the wall of Rabbah, and it will consume her houses amid wailing on the day of battle, and in the storm on the day of upheaval.
And Melchom will go into captivity, he and his princes together, says the Lord.
Gilead, for instance, is interpreted as a heap of testimony.
Because the whole congregation of the Church serves as a testimony to the truth through confession, it is fitting that the Church is represented by Gilead, which testifies to the truths of God through the actions of all the faithful.
The souls that conceive the understanding of the Word from divine love are called pregnant, as they will give birth to the conceived understanding through the demonstration of their works when they reach the perfect time.
Therefore, the heretics cut open the pregnant women of Gilead to expand their own territory, because they destroy the minds of the faithful, who already perceive some understanding of the truth, through perverse preaching.
They extend the name of knowledge to themselves while they tear apart the hearts of the little ones, already pregnant with the conception of the Word, with the sword of error, and make a reputation for themselves as if they were teachers.
Chapter Two
This is what the Lord says: For three crimes of Moab, and for four, I will not turn away his punishment, because he burned the bones of the king of Edom to ashes.
So I will send fire upon Moab, and it will consume the fortresses of Kerioth.
Moab will die with a loud noise, to the sound of the trumpet.
I will destroy the judge from their midst and kill all their princes with him, says the Lord.
Moab means "from the father," referring to the devil. Kerioth or Kiriathjearim translates to "village of forests." This symbolizes the Jews or heretics, represented by Moab, who crush the bones of the king of Edom - representing the chosen ones of Christ or the spiritual meanings in divine books - through carnal understanding, reducing them to ashes.
This is what the Lord says: For three crimes of Judah, and for four, I will not turn away his punishment, because they have rejected the law of the Lord and have not kept His commandments. Their idols have led them astray, just as their fathers walked. So I will send fire upon Judah, and it will consume the fortresses of Jerusalem. What is said of Judah refers to the Church, which is the true confession, and it is reproved for despising the law of the Lord and not keeping His commandments.
This is what the Lord says: For three crimes of Israel, and for four, I will not turn away his punishment, because they sold the righteous for silver, and the poor for a pair of sandals. They trample on the heads of the poor as upon the dust of the ground and turn aside the way of the humble. This rightly refers to Christ, whom the Jews sold for silver. The Jews and heretics trample on the heads of the poor like dust on the ground because they crush the understanding of humble believers with their earthly perspective and turn aside the way of the humble. Jesus said, "I am the way and the truth and the life," but they despise walking in it.
A man and his father go to the same girl to defile My holy name. The father represents the Jewish people; the son represents the Christian people. The person who enters the girl with the father is the one who, coming to the Church, wants to keep the law alongside the Gospel, thereby committing fornication and defiling the name of God.
They lay down beside every altar on clothes taken as pledges and drank the wine of the condemned in the house of their god.
The priests of the Jews had so much contempt for God that they spread out their clothes, in which they had slept or fornicated, beside the altar with earthly cords, making coverings behind which they fornicated in the temple where no one could see.
I destroyed the Amorite before them, whose height was like cedars and who was strong like an oak.
I destroyed his fruit above and his roots below.
I am the one who brought you up from the land of Egypt and led you through the desert for forty years, so you could possess the land of the Amorite.
I raised up prophets from your sons and Nazirites from your young men.
Is this not so, sons of Israel, says the Lord?
But you gave the Nazirites wine to drink and commanded the prophets, saying: Do not prophesy.
This was fulfilled according to history when, after the seven nations were eradicated from the land of the Canaanites, the people of the Jews took possession of their seats.
Look, I will make a noise over you, like a wagon loaded with hay creaks.
For the life of the carnal is like hay, as it is written: All flesh is hay, in that the Lord endures the life of the carnal, testifying that He carries hay like a wagon.
To creak under the load of hay is to complain about the weights and iniquities of sinners.
The swift will not escape, the strong will not hold onto their strength, the mighty will not save their lives, the archer will not stand, the swift of foot will not save themselves, the horse rider will not save their lives, and the strong-hearted among the mighty will flee naked on that day, says the Lord.
This was fulfilled according to the truth of history when, due to the merit of their sins, they were handed over to the Assyrians or other nations for plunder.
Generally, this threatens all sinners, and it will come on the day of judgment.
Chapter Three
Listen to the word that the Lord has spoken against you, children of Israel, against the entire family that He brought out of the land of Egypt, saying,
"I have known only you out of all the families of the earth; therefore, I will punish you for all your iniquities."
This message applies not only to the Jews but to all the chosen ones whom Almighty God, like a father, disciplines in this life.
Can two walk together unless they have agreed?
These two who agree and walk together on the path of Christ represent both peoples, those of the circumcision and those of the uncircumcision.
Will a lion roar in the forest if it has no prey?
Will a young lion cry out from its den if it has caught nothing?
The lion symbolizes the devil; the young lion represents the multitude of unclean spirits capturing their prey, which are the souls of the damned who lose the unity of faith through discord and are dragged with them into the abyss of damnation.
Will a bird fall into a trap on the ground without a fowler?
Will a trap spring up from the ground unless it has caught something?
The trap or the fowler symbolizes the devil, who captures the chosen ones like birds through earthly deeds or discord of unity.
If a trumpet sounds in a city, will not the people be afraid?
If there is a disaster in a city, has not the Lord caused it?
For whatever is in the holy Scriptures, the threatening trumpet signifies the affliction and suffering of people.
For the Lord God does nothing without revealing His secret to His servants the prophets.
This does not mean that God reveals all things to the prophets, whether they are to happen in heaven or have already happened, but only those things that are to happen on earth.
The lion has roared; who will not fear?
The Lord God has spoken; who can but prophesy?
I know of someone who has written in his commentaries that the roaring lion is to be understood as the devil, roaring at those who are perishing.
But God, who speaks through the prophets, should be referred to as the Savior God.
Just as those who hear the lion's roar in a bad way and are taken to death, the saints may hear God's command in a good way and be saved.
Listen in the houses of Ashdod and in the houses of the land of Egypt, and say: Gather on the mountains of Samaria, and see the many insanities in its midst, and those suffering oppression in its innermost places.
They did not know how to do right, says the Lord God, storing up iniquity and plunder in their houses.
Ashdod is interpreted as fire; it exhorts the nations to gather over the people of the Jews, to see the evils they themselves have done, so the Jews do not think they have just complaints against God for handing them over to plunder.
They also suffer oppression in its innermost places, or the simple believers are oppressed.
Heretics, in the name of truth, want lies.
They altogether do not know how to do right because they have lost the path of truth and do not believe in Him who says: I am the truth.
Therefore, this is what the Lord God says: The land will be troubled and surrounded, and your strength will be taken away from you, and your houses will be plundered.
Heretics, who think in earthly terms, will be troubled on the Day of Judgment.
All their strength will be diminished, and the things they had taken by plunder will be taken away, so the people they deceived may be freed.
Or indeed, they will be troubled daily by ecclesiastical men with the testimonies of the Scriptures.
The strength of their arguments and sharp words, with which they had strengthened their doctrine, will be taken away, so that those who were taken from the Church may return to the Church.
This is what the Lord says: Just as a shepherd rescues from the lion's mouth two legs or a piece of an ear, so will the children of Israel who live in Samaria be rescued from the corner of a bed and from the couch of Damascus.
This, according to history, was undoubtedly fulfilled during the devastation of the Jews.
Allegorically, it refers to the calling of the Gentiles, whom the good shepherd, who lays down his life for his sheep, rescued from the mouth of the lion (that is, the devil).
"The legs" signify the teachers, and "the tip of the ear" represents the listeners. "Listen and testify against the house of Jacob," says the Lord of hosts, "because on the day I begin to visit the transgressions of Israel, I will also visit the altars of Bethel, and the horns of the altar will be cut off and fall to the ground. I will strike the winter house along with the summer house, and the ivory houses will perish, and many buildings will be destroyed," says the Lord.
Historically, we believe this was fulfilled among the Jews. In a higher sense, it refers to the heretics, who, ignoring the altar of the Lord, which is the unity of faith, build many altars for themselves, not for God. The winter house or summer house, along with Israel and Judah, certainly prefigures the people of the Jews and the heretics.
Chapter Four
Listen to this, you fat cows on the mountain of Samaria, who oppress the needy and crush the poor, who say to your masters, "Bring, and let us drink."
The Lord God has sworn by His holiness that surely the days will come when you will be taken away with hooks, and your remnants with boiling pots.
He calls the fat cows the leaders of the Jews or the rich people of this world.
Spiritually, Samaria, which means watchtower, signifies the pride of heretics who falsely claim to be the guardians of God's commandments.
What He says about lifting you with hooks historically happened to the leaders of the Jews.
Tropologically, it represents heretics joined with churchmen through divine judgments or indicates future damnation.
And you will go out through the breaches, one after another, and you will be cast out toward Harmon, says the Lord.
According to history, this was fulfilled when the Jews were taken into captivity divided.
Spiritually, it means heretics departing from the unity of faith and dividing into various sects against each other, thrown into destruction through pride.
Come to Bethel and commit wickedness at Gilgal, and multiply your transgressions: bring your sacrifices every morning, your tithes every three days, offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving with leaven, and call for voluntary offerings, and declare it.
For so you loved to do, O children of Israel, says the Lord.
According to history, He speaks ironically against the Jews, that they should not commit crimes, but according to their transgression, they accumulate sins for which they are punished more severely.
Heretics, coming to Bethel, which is the house of God, act wickedly when they sacrifice to the devil what is due only to God, and provoke others to their impiety by announcing it, while seeking human approval with the leaven of false doctrines.
Therefore, I gave you empty stomachs in all your cities and a lack of bread in all your places.
Yet, you have not returned to me, says the Lord.
If anyone eats sour grapes, which symbolize iniquity, their teeth will be set on edge, so they do not misuse the testimonies of the Holy Scriptures by consuming them unripe and without sweetness.
I also withheld rain from you three months before the harvest.
I rained on one city but not on another.
One part was rained on, while the part where I did not rain dried up.
Two or three cities staggered to one city to drink water, but they were not satisfied.
Yet, you did not return to me, says the Lord.
The Lord also withholds spiritual rains and all the dew of divine knowledge and understanding of the Holy Trinity from the Jews and heretics.
However, the Lord rains on the city of true confession, the Church, but He does not rain on the city of the assemblies of heretics.
Two or three cities go to one city where water abounds in hope, faith, and love, but they are not satisfied because they come not willingly but out of necessity to seek divine grace.
I struck you with scorching wind and mildew.
The multitude of your gardens and vineyards, the locust devoured your olive groves and fig trees.
Yet, you did not return to me, says the Lord.
The heretics have gardens and vineyards, or olive groves and fig trees, representing false virtues, but the locust or other pests of the devil undoubtedly gnaw and consume them.
I sent plagues among you as I did to Egypt.
I killed your young men with the sword along with captured horses, and I caused the stench of your camps to rise to your nostrils.
Yet, you did not return to me, says the Lord.
Therefore, the Lord sends death into Jacob so that we may mortify our earthly members.
He also handed the horses over to captivity so they do not fall into the depths of hell, so they recognize their sins, feel the stench, and cease to sin.
The Lord overthrew you just as He overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah, and you became like a burning stick snatched from the fire, yet you did not return to me, says the Lord.
Therefore, Israel and all heretics, who have the works of Sodom and Gomorrah, are overthrown and are like a burning stick snatched from the fire, saved by the grace of God.
This is what I will do to you, Israel.
After I do this to you, prepare to meet your God, Israel.
For behold, I am the one who forms the mountains and creates the wind, and declares His thoughts to mankind, who makes the morning mist and walks on the heights of the earth-the Lord of hosts is His name.
After I do these things to you, which I testify I will do, prepare to call upon the Lord your God, or prepare to meet your God.
The spirit mentioned in this place is not the Holy Spirit, as heretics suspect, but we understand it to mean the wind or the spirit of man.
After Christ has been proclaimed, the light of truth is revealed to us, though not completely, because now we see in part and know in part.
The mountains or heights of the earth refer to the apostles or all spiritual men, under whom the Lord walks.
The morning mist refers either to His incarnation or certainly to the preaching of the Gospel, which, when not believed by unbelievers, is not seen at all.
Chapter Five
Listen to this word, which I lift up over you as a lament:
The house of Israel has fallen; it will not rise again.
The virgin Israel is cast down on her land; there is no one to raise her up.
Literally, the ten tribes called Israel were taken into captivity and never returned to their land.
Symbolically, it rebukes both the Jews and certain sinners of the Church who do not wish to return to repentance after committing evil.
Because this is what the Lord says: The city from which a thousand used to go out will have a hundred left; and from which a hundred used to go out will have ten left in the house of Israel.
This is what Isaiah said: If the number of the children of Israel were like the sand of the sea, only a remnant will return from them.
Because this is what the Lord says to the house of Israel: Seek me, and you will live.
Do not seek Bethel, do not enter Gilgal, and do not cross into Beersheba, because Gilgal will go into captivity, and Bethel will become useless.
Do not seek Bethel, where the golden calf was, and do not enter Gilgal, which is given to idolatry, and do not cross into Beersheba, the well of the oath, where sometimes the tribe of Judah went astray and worshipped idols.
Seek the Lord, and live, lest the house of Joseph be burned like fire, and it will be devoured, and there will be no one to extinguish it.
Bethel, you who turn justice into wormwood, and leave righteousness on the ground.
This is the fire kindled not by someone else, but by the sinners themselves, of which the Lord says elsewhere: Walk in the light of your fire, and in the flame you have kindled.
He who made the Bear and Orion, and turns darkness into morning, and changes day into night, who calls the waters of the sea and pours them out on the face of the earth, the Lord is his name.
According to the truth of the story, the Lord, who is the Creator of all, threatens future captivity on Samaria and brings devastation on the mighty kingdom.
But understand the Bear and Orion as the Church, or all the saints.
In the morning, the Lord turned darkness into light by leading people from unbelief to the light of faith.
He also turned day into night by abandoning the Jewish people, who relied on their own righteousness, to the blindness of their hearts.
He laughs at the destruction of the strong and brings devastation upon the powerful.
This laughter signifies anger, because even we sometimes laugh when we are angry.
They hated the one who reproved at the gate and abhorred the one who spoke perfectly.
The gate where the prophet reproves wrongdoers represents the door of vices.
The prophet stands at the gate, at the beginning of virtues, and is hated by those he reproves.
For anyone who does not receive the prophet does not receive the one who sent him.
It is undoubtedly Christ the Lord who is meant by the one speaking perfectly.
Because you plundered the poor and took the chosen spoil from him, you will build houses of hewn stone but will not live in them; you will plant delightful vineyards but will not drink their wine, because I know your many crimes and strong sins.
The poor can be understood as Christ in His members: heretics try to plunder Him through hidden snares.
Enemies of the righteous take bribes and oppress the poor at the gate.
Therefore, the prudent will keep silent at that time, for it is an evil time.
The enemies of the righteous are understood to be all the enemies of Christ.
Heretics are the worst of all, as they try to oppress the humble of the Church at the gates of faith.
Seek good and not evil, that you may live, and the Lord God of hosts will be with you, as you have said.
Hate evil and love good, and establish justice at the gate; perhaps the Lord God of hosts will be gracious to the remnant of Joseph.
If you seek good, you immediately repel evil.
The Lord Himself is truly good.
To establish justice at the gate is to reject iniquity and accept truth.
To establish judgment at the gates means that the leaders of the churches, within the holy Church, which is the gate of the kingdom of heaven, should teach the people with true discernment of good and evil.
Therefore, thus says the Lord God of hosts, the ruler:
In all the streets there will be mourning, and in all the places outside, it will be said, "Woe, woe."
They will call the farmer to mourning, and those who know how to lament to lamentation.
In all the ways, there will be mourning, because I will pass through your midst, says the Lord.
The desolation of the Jews was prophesied not only in their dwellings but also in all the places outside.
For those who are in the Church will not hear woe, but punishment is the last thing.
If they sin, lamentation will be taken up over them.
Farmers and those who know how to lament are ecclesiastical men, who call sinners to repentance before the coming judgment.
Woe to those desiring the day of the Lord.
Why is it to you?
The day of the Lord is darkness and not light.
The Jews, like heretics, or many from the Church, trusting in their righteousness, profess to desire the day of the Lord, that is, the day of judgment, as if they were secure from crimes, but they should have feared it.
Just as if a man flees from the face of a lion, and a bear meets him, or he enters a house, leans his hand on the wall, and a snake bites him.
The lion, or bear, or snake, in this place should be understood as the devil.
The house, too, for each wrongdoer is their own conscience, in which things are not well for them.
Is not the day of the Lord darkness and not light, and gloom with no brightness in it?
I hate and reject your festivals, and I will not accept the smell of your gatherings.
If you offer me burnt offerings and gifts, I will not look upon them, and I will not accept the fat of your sacrifices.
Take away from me the noise of your songs, and I will not hear the melodies of your lyres.
Judgment will be revealed like water, and righteousness like a mighty stream.
He speaks of the sacrifices of the Jews and heretics, which are not approved by God.
And also the songs of the Levites, with which they praised God, he calls noise and confused sound, similarly to those of heretics.
The judgment and justice of God, which He will pass on His people, will be clear to everyone, like a powerful torrent that sweeps away everything in its path and allows nothing to stand in its way.
Did you offer sacrifices and offerings to me in the desert for forty years, house of Israel?
You carried the tabernacle of Moloch, your idol, and the image of your idols, the star of your god, which you made for yourselves.
I will make you migrate beyond Damascus, said the Lord God of hosts, is His name.
The people of Israel were seduced by the worship of idols, and what they offered to God, because they did it not willingly but out of fear of punishment, was considered as if it wasn't done.
The star refers to the star that the infidel Saracens once worshiped.
Chapter Six
Woe to you who are rich in Zion and trust in the mountain of Samaria, the leaders of the people, entering pompously into the house of Israel.
The rich in Zion refers to the leaders of the Jews, or the teachers of heretics, who boast of their own righteousness as if trusting in the mountain of Samaria.
For according to another version, they are those who despise Zion, that is, the Church of God, says the Lord.
Cross over to Calneh and see; and go from there to the great Hamath, and go down to Gath of the Philistines, and to the best of these kingdoms.
Historically, he rebukes the leaders of the Jews, or the rich of the Church, who live dissolutely, following the broader paths of this world, through which unbelievers walk.
They do what David did in the worship of God, but they do it for their own will and luxury.
For they are separated in the gods of Moloch, that is, on the day of judgment, from the society of the saints.
Is their boundary larger than your boundary, you who are separated unto the evil day, and approach the throne of iniquity, who lie on beds of ivory, and indulge in your couches, who eat lambs from the flock, and calves from the midst of the herd, who sing to the sound of the harp?
They think they have the musical instruments of David, drinking wine in bowls, and anointed with the best ointments, and they do not grieve over the ruin of Joseph.
According to the allegorical interpretation, the prophetic speech is directed against the heretics, who are separated in the evil day, that is, in the present time, or on the day of judgment, from the fellowship of the Church.
They consider their songs, that is, their false proclamations of Christ's preaching.
For the divine speech exhorts them to reflect upon the philosophies of all nations, and find narrower boundaries in the terms of the holy Scriptures.
Therefore, they will now migrate at the head of the exiles, and the faction of those indulging will be taken away.
The Lord God has sworn by His soul, says the Lord God of hosts.
I abhor the pride of Jacob, and I hate his houses.
According to the truth of history, He speaks of the Jews who were taken into captivity.
And I will deliver up the city with its inhabitants.
If there are ten men left in one house, they will die.
A relative will come to take them out and burn them to remove their bones from the house.
He will ask the one who is in the inner parts of the house, "Is there anyone else with you?" and he will answer, "No, it's over."
According to historical records, this was fulfilled among the Jewish people when Jerusalem was destroyed by the Romans. In a moral sense, it refers to heretics; if ten men are left in their gatherings, they will all die the death that leads to hell. The bones of the righteous will be buried by their relatives and family members, of whom it is said, "Let the dead bury their dead."
The one who is outside and does not enter the house, but instead throws the dead out, commands the one who burns the dead, reduces them to ashes, and crushes their bones, to be silent and not to profane God's holy name with a dead mouth. He will say to him, "Be silent and do not mention the name of the Lord, for the Lord has commanded it. He will strike down the great house into ruins and the small house into fragments."
The great house and the small house are thought to signify the Jewish people and the Church gathered from the Gentiles. If this Church ever sins and is struck by the schisms of heretics, it will be disrupted just as the Jewish people were brought to ruin.
Can horses run on rocks, or can oxen plow the sea? For you have turned justice into bitterness and the fruit of righteousness into wormwood. Since wild oxen are untamed due to their wildness and refuse to plow the earth, you, proud and arrogant, have changed the worship of God, turning sweet into bitter, even though horses and oxen cannot change their nature.
You who rejoice in nothing, who say, "Have we not taken horns for ourselves by our own strength?" Behold, I will raise up a nation against you, house of Israel (says the Lord God of hosts), and they will crush you from the entrance of Hamath to the stream of the desert.
Chapter Seven
The Lord God showed me this.
This is the voice of all the proud, who, relying on their own strength, might have temporary power that they could only receive from God.
But they attribute it more to their own virtue than to God.
And behold, the creator of the locust at the beginning of the late rain sprouting, and behold, the late rain after the shearer of the flock.
And it happened when he had finished consuming the grass of the earth, and I said: Lord God, be merciful, I beg you.
Who will raise Jacob, for he is small?
The creator of the locust and the creator is God.
They come at the beginning of the late rain, which is in the springtime when everything flourishes.
But these locusts were followed by countless caterpillars, which came after the late rain and were called the shearer or the shearing of the flock.
This undoubtedly signified the two kings of the Assyrians and the army of the Chaldeans, who devastated the nation of the Jews.
Otherwise: Gog, king of the locusts, who according to the Septuagint interpreters is called, means "roof," signifies a certain proud and arrogant strength of the Antichrist. At the end of the world, coming with an innumerable multitude of unbelievers, like in the late rain, he will consume all the grass of the earth, that is, all the weak and tender aspects of the human race. Hence, the prophet intercedes with God for the people of Israel, because they are small in understanding, so that, with a changed judgment, at least a remnant of them may be saved. But the Lord had mercy on this. It will not be, said the Lord.
The Lord God showed me this, and behold, the Lord God will call judgment to fire, and it will devour the great abyss and consume a part of it. And I said: Lord God, cease, I beg you. Who will raise Jacob, for he is small? The Lord had mercy on this. But this too will not be, said the Lord God.
The Lord God showed me this. Judgment is indeed called to fire when the sentence of justice for eternal burning is shown. And it devours the great abyss because it burns the wicked and incomprehensible minds of men, which now even shine before men with the miracles of proud deeds.
But part of the house is consumed, because hell also devours those who now pride themselves on being among the elect through supposedly holy acts.
And behold, the Lord stands on a wall plastered, and in His hand is a trowel.
The Lord said to me: What do you see, Amos?
I said: A trowel.
The Lord said: Behold, I will set a trowel in the midst of my people Israel.
I will not add to them again.
The high places of the idol will be demolished, the sanctuaries of Israel will be desolated, and I will rise against the house of Jeroboam with the sword.
The trowel signifies the Lord's protection, which He has taken away from His people Israel, as from the former building.
The diamond, a very hard, unbreakable, and unattractive stone, prefigures our Lord and Savior, who, though He was in the form of God, did not consider equality with God something to be grasped, but emptied Himself, taking the form of a servant.
He stands on a diamond wall, that is, on the incorruptible building of the Church.
And Amaziah, the priest of Bethel, sent a message to Jeroboam, king of Israel, saying: Amos has conspired against you in the midst of the house of Israel; the land cannot bear all his words.
For Amos says: Jeroboam will die by the sword, and Israel will surely go into exile away from their land.
Amaziah said to Amos: Seer, go, flee to the land of Judah.
Earn your bread there, and prophesy there.
But do not prophesy any more at Bethel, for it is the king's sanctuary and the house of the kingdom.
All that is contained in this prophecy about Amaziah, Jeroboam, and Israel should be interpreted metaphorically as referring to heretics.
Amaziah, the priest, sometimes sends messages to Jeroboam, the king and patron of heretics, accusing holy men and preachers of faith before him.
He orders teachers not to preach in Israel so they do not go against the king's will.
Because Bethel, which means the house of God, and the false Church is the king's sanctuary and the house of the kingdom.
They often say: The emperor supports us, and if anyone resists him, they are immediately slandered.
So, you act against the emperor, you despise the commands of Augustus.
And Amos replied to Amaziah: I am not a prophet, nor the son of a prophet; I am a herdsman and a tender of sycamore figs.
The Lord took me from following the flock and said to me: Go, prophesy to my people Israel.
Some argue that sycamores should be called sycamines, a type of tree that grows in the plains of Palestine and produces wild fruit.
If these fruits are not tended, they become very bitter, and the tree is ruined.
However, since the wilderness where Amos lived does not grow such trees, it seems more likely he was referring to bushes that bear berries, helping to sustain the hunger and needs of shepherds.
Others assert that sycamores symbolized all fruitful trees.
Now listen to the word of the Lord: You say, do not prophesy against Israel and do not preach against the house of idols.
Because of this, the Lord God says: Your wife will be unfaithful in the city, and your sons and daughters will fall by the sword; your land will be measured out and divided, and you will die in a defiled land, and Israel will go into exile from its land.
This is what the Scripture recalls the apostles did; when the scribes and Pharisees warned them not to teach in the name of Jesus, they responded, saying: We must obey God rather than men.
This is also what the prophet Amos did.
Amaziah, who now boasts of his priestly power, will die in a land defiled by idols and will not die before he sees the people he deceived serving as captives.
Amaziah, whose name means strong and rigid, is rebellious and fierce, forbidding a true ecclesiastic man and prophet from speaking God's word and correcting the erring people.
He undoubtedly displayed the arrogance of heretics.
The wife of these heretics, which is the false Church, will be revealed to all the faithful as an adulterous people, and their sons and daughters born in error will be struck by the Lord's indignation or by their own impiety.
The land and all its possessions will belong to demons.
They will perish in a polluted land, abandoned by God.
Chapter Eight
The Lord God showed me this: a basket of summer fruit.
And the Lord said, "What do you see, Amos?"
And I replied, "A basket of summer fruit."
(At this point, all the copies we had access to are missing Haymo's words in chapters 8 and 9.)