Notice regarding the two following sermons.
These two sermons, previously unpublished, were transcribed from a Vatican manuscript by the distinguished Luca Holstenius in the past and sent here by the eminent Cardinal Barberini.
Since it was not possible to publish them in sequence with the other sermons of Saint Fulgentius, it seemed fitting to include them here at the end of his works.
We have little doubt that the first sermon truly belongs to Fulgentius; however, we believe the second should be attributed to another author, who is indeed respected, although possibly later than Fulgentius.
We have not yet discovered who that author is.
SERMON ONE. On the Circumcision of the Lord.
Every year, we celebrate and honor the mystery of the divine incarnation, the extraordinary sacrament of our reconciliation.
This remembrance of such a blessing highlights what has been given to us, who are unworthy, and reminds us of what we owe to such glory.
So, brothers, the more we understand that the Lord Jesus Christ was humbly lowered for our sake, the more we should recognize His indescribable glory.
In Him, God the Only Begotten clearly showed His unwavering love for us.
He took on the humility of true flesh and true death for us, not because He had to, but out of compassionate goodness.
What good had we done, brothers, to deserve such a great benefit?
What were our good deeds that made the Only Begotten God deem it worthy to become man, for the Most High to humble Himself, for the unfailing bread of angels to be nursed at a woman's breast, for the King of the ages to endure insults, for eternal life to patiently face death?
Therefore, reflect, O man, on the kindness of such condescension, so that you may humbly offer thanks.
Understand that you give not honor but insult to divine grace if you begin to doubt the greatness of such a benefit.
Instead, let us believe without hesitation that all we have heard about the humility and humanity of the Lord Savior is true.
Thus, let us give even more thanks, brothers, for when we deserved punishment, we received grace.
Through this grace, while death was justly owed to the lost, life was freely given to the unworthy.
The humility of the Most High Savior did not bring Him any loss, but it brought us a great gain.
It did not bring down the exalted, but lifted up the humble.
To complete the work of our redemption, the Son of God chose to be born in true human form from the flesh of a Virgin, even though He is the Creator of all flesh.
The maker of man became truly human.
He was wrapped in cloths, laid in a humble manger, circumcised on the eighth day, and carried by human hands to His temple.
O most merciful goodness of God!
O exalted humility of the highest God!
He, who was nourished as an infant by His mother, also created her in His vastness.
As a small child, He was carried by His parents to His temple, where holy people worshiped Him as the great God.
He commanded a sacrifice to be offered for Himself, even though He came to be sacrificed without sin for our transgressions.
Therefore, consider, O man, what you owe to the one who is exalted and humbled for you; to your exalted Creator, to your humbled Redeemer.
However, dearest ones, the integrity of the Christian faith has always maintained that whatever we read or hear was done by Christ according to the canonical narration of the Evangelists.
We first believe without doubt that the history is true, and then we seek spiritual understanding in the historical truth.
For when the history of the divine text is believed to be true, the Manichaean is confounded in his severity.
While he does not believe in the truth of the flesh of Christ, the Son of God, he attempts to impose falsehoods on the holy Scriptures, both old and new.
He miserably curses the divine history of the Old Testament, and in the New Testament, he denies himself the remedy.
He does not wish to believe that human flesh was molded by God, nor that the circumcision of the flesh was commanded by God to our holy fathers, nor that sacrifices from the flesh of animals were offered to the living and true God in ancient times, nor that the Sabbath was observed by the command and will of God, nor that a temple was built for the Lord at God's command.
Thus, while he does not discern the quality of times in the holy Scriptures, he scorns and despises the most beneficial truth of the Lord's incarnation.
To convincingly challenge and convert the Manichaean, let's hope he is persuaded by today's gospel reading.
We must defend the truth of the Old Testament to clearly demonstrate that the God of both the Old and New Testaments is one!
As the holy Gospel reveals, we've learned that Christ, the Son of God, was truly circumcised, and a sacrifice of flesh was offered for Him, according to the customs of that divine institution at the time, whether it was the circumcision of the flesh or the rule of fleshly sacrifices established in the Old Testament.
Why, dear friends, should you not rightly believe in the Old Testament, when it is said that man was formed by the hands of God, especially since in the New Testament, to save man from eternal loss, the Only Begotten God became truly human for us?
Why should it not be believed that God commanded circumcision at an appropriate time to signify something important, when the Son of God himself had it done to His own body?
And why wouldn't our God have commanded the Jewish people in the past to offer symbolic sacrifices of flesh, when God Himself, the Only Begotten, born of the Jews, saw it fit to offer Himself for our sins according to the flesh?
Therefore, let the Manichaean pay attention to the clear and harmonious truth of both Testaments, and turn away from his vanity.
Let him see the Old Testament as a foreshadowing of future events, and the New Testament as the revelation of past ones.
In the Old Testament, Christ, God of both Testaments, promised what He would fulfill, and in the New, He fulfilled what He had promised: neither a liar in promise nor deceitful in giving; but always good, always just, always holy, always powerful, always merciful.
In the Old Testament, He is the most powerful creator of both flesh and soul, and in the New, the most merciful receiver of the same flesh and soul; thus, He becomes the savior of flesh and soul first.
Let the Manichaean hear these things, reflect on them, recognize them, and believe.
And in believing, let him return to the Catholic Church, where he will find the blessing of true salvation.
Through these actions that the Lord carried out in His physical body,
He aimed not only to demonstrate the harmony of both the Old and New Testaments
but also to beneficially shape the behavior of Christians.
He intended for us to observe His physical actions for our salvation and then imitate them spiritually.
Therefore, Christ was born as a small child on earth to teach Christians humility.
He was obedient to His earthly parents so that every Christian would always show respect to their father and mother.
Christ was wrapped in humble clothes so that Christians would not take pleasure in expensive clothing.
Christ chose to appear poor on earth so that wealthy Christians would learn not to love earthly riches;
instead, by giving alms to the poor, they could store their riches in heaven.
For this reason, Christ was placed in a narrow manger, despite the vastness of His mind,
so that those who believe in Him would have spiritual nourishment,
and Christians would learn not to covet the homes or possessions of others.
How could any Christian not be content with even the humblest home or their own means,
when the narrowness of a small manger sufficed for Christ, the Son of God?
Through the circumcision that the Son of God underwent in the flesh,
He foreshadowed the spiritual circumcision of our hearts.
This circumcision is indicated to us by the word of the law, as Moses says,
Circumcise the foreskin of your heart, and be circumcised to your God
(Deuteronomy 10:16).
This command aligns with the blessed Apostle, who says,
A person is not a Jew who is one only outwardly,
nor is circumcision merely outward and physical.
No, a person is a Jew who is one inwardly; and circumcision is circumcision of the heart,
by the Spirit, not by the written code.
Such a person's praise is not from other people, but from God
(Romans 2:28-29).
Therefore, Christ underwent circumcision in the body so that Christians might have it spiritually in the heart.
For this reason, the one who was without sin removed the foreskin of the flesh, so that we might cast off the desires of wickedness.
Christ was carried by hands to the temple, so that a Christian might ascend to heaven through good works.
Christ desired a sacrifice to be offered for him, so that a Christian might offer himself at the altar of the Lord.
Above all, let him hasten to offer himself by living well.
If he delights in presenting a pure sacrifice to divine eyes, we recognize a certain spiritual sacrifice in the very essence of that offering: "A pair of turtledoves and two young pigeons" as mentioned in Luke Chapter Two, Verse Twenty-four.
In this type of birds, dearest brothers, a great sacrament of the Catholic faith is commended to you. In the dove, love is recognized; in the turtledove, chastity is found.
For the turtledove remains faithful to one mate; the dove does not abandon the unity of those living together. Therefore, a Catholic Christian truly becomes a spiritual turtledove if he preserves the true faith of the Trinity with firm belief and rejects the sense of heretical wickedness as the stain of fornication.
He will truly be a dove if he remains patiently in the Catholic community until the end and withstands temptations and scandals with unshakable firmness, so that neither heretical fornication corrupts the chastity of faith in the heart, nor bitter dissension abandons the unity of ecclesiastical chastity.
This is the legitimate Church that keeps faith with one God as with a legitimate husband and multiplies the congregation of children in love.
In this turtledove and dove, dearest brothers, remain diligently, guard it with all your vows, so that neither an Arian violates it, nor a Donatist tramples it, nor a Manichaean pollutes it.
For they, like evil hawks, desire to scatter the unity of the dove and to violate the chastity of the turtledove. For the Manichaean does not believe in the true flesh of Christ, the Arian diminishes his true divinity, and the Donatist scatters the unity of the Catholic body.
Manichaeus doesn't recognize the Redeemer's sacrament, the Arian overlooks the greatness of the Savior, and the Donatist, like a ravenous wolf, didn't hesitate to scatter the flock of the good Shepherd.
So, as I mentioned, they pursue those who seek compassion and are unaware of the truth, like evil hawks, wishing to harm them.
They reject the love of doves, despise the purity of turtledoves, and if possible, they either devour with their mouths or tear with their claws.
Therefore, dearest brothers, keep the Catholic truth in faith and preserve the Catholic peace in love.
A sacrifice pleasing to God is offered by those who preserve the true sacrament of the Catholic faith with brotherly love.
Where one God, one Trinity is worshiped; the Father is not greater than the Son, nor is the Son lesser than the Father in divinity; and the substance of the Holy Spirit is not distinguished from them, for He is naturally one God with the Father and the Son.
The power of the holy Trinity is one, because in three persons remains one natural substance; there is one power, one majesty, one eternity, and one dominion of the Creator, as there is one condition of the creature.
For whatever the Father created, He made through the Son and established in the Holy Spirit.
The Son is born of the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from Him who remains.
Yet the Son does not divide the Father by being born, nor does the Spirit diminish God by proceeding, because He does not increase by adhering.
Therefore, the Son is not diminished by being born, nor is the Spirit separated by proceeding.
For the blessed Trinity remains as it is, because there is substantial unity: and since nothing is created in the divinity of the Trinity, nothing is indeed separated there.
Hold these truths faithfully, dearest brothers, and continue in them.
Let this be the thought in your heart and the confession with your mouth.
Hold the faith you have received in the name of the Trinity.
Preserve the unity of the spirit in the bond of peace, like the turtledove and dove, so that you may always be spiritual in the house of God.
May He grant this, who lives and reigns with the Father and the Son, God.
Sermon Two: On the Purification of the Blessed Virgin Mary
This feast honors the same person as those and is equally important.
We will clearly demonstrate this with evidence in this sermon.
The solemnity of this day, though unknown to some Christians, is highly honored by many above other feasts of the year.
Especially in the place where the Catholic Church has its leader, it is observed with such reverence that on this day, the entire city gathers together, their candles shining brightly, to celebrate the solemnity of the Mass.
No one enters the public place without holding a light, as if they were to present the Lord in the temple, or rather to receive Him; they show the light of faith, which shines within, through the outward sign of their offering.
Today, according to the law and the gospel, forty days after Christ's birth, the Lord was presented in the temple by His parents.
Today, He was received by Saint Simeon and offered to the Father with sacred gifts.
Today, Simeon and Anna proclaimed the redemption expected by the people of Israel.
Oh, what a loving sight, which only the devout truly enjoy!
Here stands the virgin and mother, not of just anyone, but of God.
Here the child, the virgin's son, is received, whose divinity the world cannot contain.
Here prophets come forward, and both men and women prophesy about the child.
An offering is made for the child, not to cleanse sins but to declare the sacraments.
And because I wish to elevate the praise of this day, I would like to go through the Gospel reading in conversation, knowing these things are narrated, so that what I say may correspond with it; indeed, so that my words of exhortation may align with what it narrates.
Finally, Luke, the evangelist, offers a more detailed and orderly account of Christ's incarnation than the other evangelists.
After the angel's announcement in the year 669, the birth heralded by angels, and the circumcision on the eighth day at his parents' home, Luke continues:
"When the days of her purification according to the Law of Moses were completed, they brought him to Jerusalem to present him to the Lord, as it is written in the Law of the Lord, 'Every male that opens the womb shall be called holy to the Lord'"
(Luke 2:22-23).
It's clear to all believers that the Redeemer's mother was untouched by any stain from his birth, as she didn't need purification by staying away from sacred places during that time.
Because, without human desire or corruption of the flesh, the virgin gave birth and remained a virgin forever; thus, no male was born from her to open her womb.
Yet, while narrating the law, the evangelist doesn't reveal the divine incarnation's mystery to the impious but shows the mother observing the law.
It's not surprising that she would follow the law her Son came not to abolish, but to fulfill.
She knew how she conceived and who she had given birth to.
But by observing the common law, she awaited the purification day, concealing her son's majesty.
That's why, when she found him in the temple at age twelve, she referred to him as Joseph's son, saying:
"Son, why have you done this to us? Look, your father and I have been searching for you in sorrow"
(Luke 2:48).
She undoubtedly knew she conceived him without Joseph's involvement and gave birth without any loss of her virginity.
But why did she conceal the mystery of his conception and birth, knowing he was the boundless God?
Did she envy others when she brought him to the temple and entrusted him to the holy elder?
Certainly not.
Perhaps, filled with the spirit of prophecy, she chose not to reveal the world's redemption to the impious.
For she already knew, full of grace and inspired by divine spirit, that if the rulers of this world had recognized him, they would never have crucified him for our salvation.
So, present him, most blessed Virgin, as one who follows the law, in the temple, whom you brought forth, so that not everyone but only a few may know who it is you have given birth to.
Let the humble stone, cut from the mountain without hands, be revealed, so that it may be rejected by the builders until it strikes the statue on its feet, grows into a great mountain, and fills the entire world.
Oh, how small, oh, how great is he whom you have given birth to!
Small in humanity, great in divinity; small in the kingdom of the Jews, great in the kingdom of the nations.
Yet not everyone in the kingdom of the Jews considers him small.
For even you, who gave birth to him, grew from the same people of Israel into a branch.
You rose as a branch from the root of Jesse and blossomed.
Like Aaron's rod, you blossomed and bore fruit.
Because you recognized his vastness above all, although you saw him born very small from you, without a doubt, you trembled and worshiped the Almighty God whom you bore as a baby.
Worshiping, you trembled.
Yet, because you recognized him as your son according to humanity, you nursed, cherished, and nurtured him.
Who, do you think, could reveal to us the feelings of your heart in such service, O most blessed Virgin?
When, on one side, you saw the tiny infant born from you, and on the other side, beheld the immense God; here the created, there the creator; here the weak, there the very strong; here needing to be fed, there feeding; here not speaking, there teaching angels.
Who, I ask, can reveal to us the secrets of your heart, in what ways you turned your thoughts to both, as you held in your hands the one and the same Son of God and man, worshiping him as Lord on one side and kissing him as a little child on the other?
Who would not be amazed at such an ineffable miracle?
Who would not almost be rendered speechless?
A young girl gives birth to her creator and the creator of all, nourishes her nurturer and the nurturer of all, brings to the temple her ruler and the ruler of all.
Oh, what a wondrous sight, at which not only human but even angelic nature is amazed!
To this, dearest brothers, lift your eyes of faith; to this, come with the affection of piety.
Receive Christ, who is humbled in the flesh for you, but worship Him as the exalted God in His divinity.
Embrace the child, yet consider His immensity.
Love the humbled one, and fear the exalted one.
Now truly, beloved, if we seek to understand the mystical meaning of why our Redeemer wanted to be carried by His mother and relatives from His own city to the temple of the Lord in Jerusalem, we find that the glorious mother and virgin, along with her relatives, represented the Church that believed in the apostles from among the Jews.
For when is the Church not a virgin?
The Apostle addresses its members, saying:
"I am jealous for you with a godly jealousy, for I have promised you to one husband, to present you as a pure virgin to Christ" Second Corinthians chapter eleven, verse two.
When is she not a mother? As it is said through the Psalmist:
"And of Zion it shall be said, 'This one and that one were born in her'" Psalm eighty-seven, verse five.
And the Lord in the Gospel says:
"For whoever does the will of my Father in heaven is my brother and sister and mother" Matthew chapter twelve, verse fifty.
When are the chosen ones not relatives, who are called brothers and sisters? Therefore, the mother and relatives of our Redeemer carry Him from Nazareth to the temple of the Lord in Jerusalem, because that early Church in the first disciples, rejected by the Jews, brought the knowledge of the same redemption to the nations.
For the Church is rightly called Jerusalem, meaning Vision of Peace, not only from the Gentiles but also from the Jews, of which it is said through the Psalmist:
"Jerusalem is built as a city that is closely compacted together" Psalm one hundred twenty-two, verse three.
She is also the temple, as it is said to the faithful through Paul:
"The temple of God is holy, which you are" First Corinthians chapter three, verse seventeen.
Therefore, when the apostles come from Judea, announcing Christ to the nations, Jerusalem indeed meets Jerusalem, and the temple meets the temple, for they all are one city, Jerusalem, and one temple. In this city, and in this temple, Christ is presented by the apostles.
Hence the Church itself speaks with the voice of the Psalmist, saying:
"We have thought on your steadfast love, O God, in the midst of your temple" Psalm forty-eight, verse nine.
Imagine yourself in the heart of the church, which is your temple.
Whether you look at it from a historical perspective or a mystical one, the reason Christ was brought by his parents to the holy city and temple is clarified when we hear:
To offer a sacrifice as stated in the law of the Lord, a pair of turtledoves or two young pigeons.
(Luke 2:24)
The law commanded that if someone couldn't afford a lamb, they could offer either a pair of turtledoves or two young pigeons to God.
This offering was equally acceptable.
In this offering of birds, we see a foreshadowing of the ultimate sacrifice for the world's salvation, namely the Lord's passion, through which we are reconciled to God.
Paul speaks to the faithful about this sacrifice:
Walk in love, as Christ also has loved us and gave himself for us as an offering and a sacrifice to God, a sweet-smelling aroma.
(Ephesians 5:2)
And again: Who loved me, he says, and gave himself for me.
(Galatians 2:20)
Since all the chosen are members of Christ, this offering of birds also symbolizes the mortification of the chosen ones, to whom the apostle says:
I urge you by the mercy of God to present your bodies as a living sacrifice, holy, pleasing to God.
(Romans 12:1)
An offering of mortification is only acceptable to God if there is true faith and unity.
Thus, it is significant that the sacrifice, mystically offered for the Lord, is described as coming from turtledoves and doves.
In the turtledove, chastity is found, and in the dove, unity is valued.
The turtledove remains faithful to one mate, and the dove does not abandon the unity of the group.
Therefore, a Catholic Christian becomes a spiritual turtledove when they hold firmly to the true faith of the Trinity and reject heretical teachings as they would the impurity of fornication.
Then there will truly be a dove if it remains patient in the Catholic community until the end and stands firm against the challenges of temptation.
This means that neither heretical corruption taints the purity of faith in the heart nor bitter disagreement disrupts the unity of the Church's chastity.
This is, indeed, the Catholic Church, which holds its faith with one Lord like a lawful husband and grows the congregation of many in faith.
It continues: "And behold, there was a man in Jerusalem whose name was Simeon; this man was just and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel, and the Holy Spirit was upon him. And it had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit that he would not see death before he had seen the Lord's Christ. And he came by the Spirit into the temple" (Luke 2:25-27).
Nothing less is attributed to this particularly holy man, who resides in Jerusalem, meaning the vision of peace.
He is just through his works of faith, devout in reverence, attentive to the consolation of Israel, filled with the Holy Spirit, and strengthened by the Spirit's response regarding the command of the incarnate Word.
Oh, with what fervent desire did this man await, according to the promise of the Holy Spirit, to see the Redeemer in the flesh!
What urgency do we suppose was in his prayer that deserved to be assured by a divine response about the things he asked for?
What were his continuous words of lament in holy preaching?
For he did not cease to ask until he received a response regarding the things he sought.
Indeed, in past times, many were filled with a similar desire, as the Lord testifies to the disciples, saying: "Many kings and prophets wanted to see what you see and did not see it; and to hear what you hear and did not hear it" (Luke 10:24).
But this was granted only to those who appeared at the last in the fullness of these times.
But if we attentively consider the desire of the following saints, for whom to live is Christ and to die is gain (Philippians 1:21).
We see that they are just as eager to witness the divinity of the same Savior, much like his desire to be seen in the flesh.
This is why Paul says, "I desire to depart and be with Christ, which is much better" (Philippians 1:23).
Similarly, the Psalmist expresses, "My soul thirsts for the living God. When shall I come and appear before the face of God?" (Psalm 42:2).
Who can see in one Simeon the many, where one represents all the elect; those who are now righteous through faith and action, reverent with future hope, and in awe of the coming consolation?
The Holy Spirit is recognized as dwelling within them, as the Apostle says, "The love of God has been poured out into our hearts through the Holy Spirit who has been given to us" (Romans 5:5); and it is also said to the faithful, "Your bodies are temples of the Holy Spirit, who is in you, whom you have received from God" (First Corinthians 6:19).
They also receive a promise from the Holy Spirit that they will not see death before seeing the Lord's Christ.
In this still imperfect life, with the grace of the Holy Spirit, they see with the eyes of faith the one who promised to be with them until the end of the age (Matthew 28:20), not as a small child in the flesh, but immeasurable in divinity.
They echo the Apostle, "Though we have known Christ according to the flesh, yet now we know him thus no longer" (Second Corinthians 5:16).
They dwell in Jerusalem and, in the Spirit, come to the temple where Christ is presented.
Truly, they are Jerusalem who dwell in Jerusalem; they are the temple who come to the temple, in whom and through whom Christ is received.
Briefly, brothers, we discuss these matters to avoid becoming a burden as we strive to highlight the sacraments of this day, and what is holy and pure.
It goes on: "And when his parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him according to the custom of the law, he took him in his arms and blessed God, and said: 'Now you dismiss your servant, Lord, according to your word in peace'" (Luke 2:27, 28, 29).