In the name of the Lord,
begins the martyrology for the year by our holy father Notker, known as the Stammerer, a monk of Saint Gall.
January. The month of January has 31 days, while the lunar cycle is 29 days.
January 1st marks the eighth day of the birth of the Lord, the day on which He was circumcised according to the law of Moses and received the name Jesus, as foretold by the angel before His conception, as mentioned in the Gospel of Luke, chapter 2.
In Rome, it is the feast day of Saint Almachius, a martyr who was killed by gladiators on the order of Alipius, the prefect of the city.
He declared, "Today is the eighth day of the Lord's birth, cease from idolatrous superstitions and polluted sacrifices."
Also in Rome, we remember Saint Martina, a virgin and martyr who suffered various tortures for her faith in Christ under Emperor Alexander, ultimately being struck down with a sword.
Through the Holy Spirit within her, she tamed a lion, destroyed idols through prayer, and converted many to the Christian faith.
In revenge for her, the emperor met his own end by harming himself.
On the same day, in the city of Spoleto in Tuscany, we commemorate the martyrdom of Saint Concordius, a Roman priest from the title of Pastor, who, during the reign of Emperor Antoninus, was sentenced to death by Count Torquatus for refusing to sacrifice to idols.
Also in Rome, on the Appian Way, we remember the martyrdom of Corona and thirty soldiers who were deemed worthy of martyrdom under Emperor Diocletian for confessing the Christian faith.
In the metropolis of Caesarea in Cappadocia, we honor the death of Saint Basil, a bishop known for writing the Rule for brothers and many other significant works.
Among his many miracles, he retrieved a contract a man had made with the devil, delayed his death for the conversion of Joseph the Hebrew, and even after his death, abolished the record of a certain heinous crime.
In Africa, we celebrate the feast day of Saint Fulgentius, bishop of the Church of Ruspe and confessor.
During the Vandal persecution, he faced great hardship from the Arians because of his Catholic faith and remarkable teachings.
He was exiled to Sardinia for a long period but was eventually allowed to return to his church.
Distinguished by his life and words, he passed away peacefully in a holy manner, having served as a bishop for twenty-five years and lived for sixty-five years.
In Alexandria, Saint Euphrosyne, a virgin, was born to her once-barren mother through the prayers of her father, Paphnutius.
At a young age, she secretly cut her hair and chose a monastic life, adopting the name Smaragdus.
She lived in holiness for twenty-eight years, and sensing her death was near, she revealed herself to her father, who had been searching for her with tears.
Her name and life are celebrated among the Romans as a symbol of pure virtue.
January second—The Octave of Saint Stephen.
In Rome, Pope Telesphorus established that fasting should be observed for seven weeks before Easter.
He decreed that Mass should be celebrated on the night of the Nativity of the Lord, and the angelic hymn, "Glory to God in the highest," should be sung. At all other times, no one should presume to celebrate Mass before the third hour, the time when the Lord was crucified. He was also crowned with martyrdom and buried next to the body of Saint Peter in the Vatican.
In Antioch, the abbot Macarius.
In Tomis, a city in Pontus, the three brothers Argeus, Narcissus, and Marcellinus, children. Also in Tomis, Bishop Philip, who, when captured under Caesar Licinius among the recruits, refused to serve as a soldier, was beaten to death, imprisoned for a long time, placed in a stock, and then drowned in the sea, thus achieving martyrdom. His body was washed ashore and laid to rest by religious men, shining with great virtues.
In Vienna, the passing of Blessed Florentius, bishop.
In the territory of Lyon, at the monastery of the Jura, Saint Eugendus, abbot, whose life was full of virtues and miracles.
January third—The Octave of Saint John the Apostle.
In Rome, Pope Antherus, a martyr and the twentieth successor of Saint Peter, led the Church for 12 years.
He was dedicated to collecting the acts of the martyrs.
He suffered under Maximian and was laid to rest in the cemetery of Callistus on the Appian Way.
In Paris, Saint Genevieve, a virgin consecrated to Christ by Saint Germanus, Bishop of Auxerre, became renowned for her exceptional virtues and miracles, dedicating 80 years to serving Christ.
January 2nd - Octave of the Innocents.
In Crete, we celebrate the birth of Saint Titus, a disciple of the apostles.
In Africa, we honor Saints Aquilinus, Geminus, Eugentius, Martian, Quintus, Theodotus, and Tryphon, the most illustrious martyrs.
On the same day in Rome, the holy martyrs Priest Priscus, Cleric Priscillian, and the devout woman Benedicta suffered martyrdom by the sword during the reign of the impious Emperor Julian.
Also in Rome, blessed Daphrosa, the wife of the martyr Fabian, was first exiled after her husband's condemnation and then ordered by the wicked Julian to be executed by beheading.
On the same day, the martyr Theogenes was martyred under the rule of Licinius Caesar through the tribune Licentius.
In Hellespont, he was first stretched between four columns and beaten with clubs, then sent to prison to die of hunger.
However, through the Lord's mercy, he was nourished with invisible food for 40 days and remained in constant praise of God.
Ultimately, he was thrown into the sea and martyred.
Eutychus, Eustochius, and Zoticus retrieved his body from the seashore and buried him in the marketplace of Hellespont.
On the same day, we remember the martyrdom of Peter, known as Balsamus, who was suspended and torn with claws under Emperor Maximian and the governor Severus, and finally struck down by the sword, being buried in the city of Aulona.
On the same day, we commemorate Lucian, a priest and martyr sent from Rome to preach the word of God in Gaul.
After converting many to Christ in those regions, he was beheaded under Emperor Julian.
Many miracles and healings occur at his tomb.
January 5th - Vigil of Epiphany.
In Jerusalem, we commemorate the burial of Saint Simeon the prophet, who, through the revelation of the Holy Spirit, recognized the Lord Jesus Christ and took Him into his arms from His parents.
He prophesied not only about Him but also about His mother with a mystical speech.
Luke Chapter 2.
In Antioch, we remember the burial of Saint Simeon the monk, a man of admirable virtue.
At the age of thirteen, he renounced the world and sought the solitude of the monastery.
There, with remarkable abstinence, he allowed himself food only on the seventh day and learned the Psalms in just four months.
Then, with great focus on subduing his body, he tied a rope of palm fiber around his waist, causing himself severe wounds.
After that, he confined himself in a well, but was forcibly brought back to the monastery by his brothers.
Secretly fleeing, he sought the desert, where he stayed for a long time.
There, atop a high column, he fervently devoted himself to holiness, refusing to be seen by any woman, not even his own mother.
Even today, no woman enters the basilica of that column.
A certain woman, dressed in men's clothing, tried to enter, but as soon as she touched the threshold, she fell back dead.
In Africa, we commemorate Felix, Secundus, Honorius, Lucian, Candidus, Januarius, Telesphorus, Jocundus, and Anastasia.
On January sixth, we celebrate the Epiphany of the Lord, which means manifestation.
Among the Romans, this same feast is called Theophany, signifying the appearance of God, as shown by the composition of the name.
On this day, the magi, according to the prophecy of Balaam, whose successors they were, said: A star shall rise out of Jacob, and a scepter shall rise out of Israel, and shall strike the chiefs of Moab and destroy all the sons of Seth, and Edom shall be his possession.
Numbers Chapter 24.
And again: One from Jacob shall have dominion and destroy the remnants of the city.
When a previously unknown star appeared at the time of the Lord's birth, the wise men saw it in the East.
Upon reaching Jerusalem, they were guided by the prophecy of Micah to learn the location of Christ's birth.
Following the star to Bethlehem, they found the child Jesus with Mary, his mother, and worshiped him with mystical gifts.
It's believed that this was divinely inspired so that nearby nations could begin to understand the teachings of the Lord's birth and prophetic doctrine.
However, there is also a historical context and a temporary arrangement concerning Christ.
This was so the leaders of Moab could gain favor with the parents of the newly suspected king by offering gifts, which in turn assisted in their journey to Egypt.
The magi were not Chaldeans, Indians, or Persians, as some suggest, nor did they come to worship him in the second or third year after his birth.
Rather, they were Moabites, Ammonites, or Midianites, as confirmed by Saint Jerome.
On the thirteenth day after his birth, they found him not exalted in Jerusalem as they expected, but humble in Bethlehem, and they were deemed worthy to receive spiritual reward through their devotion.
On the same day, Saint Macra, a virgin, was martyred.
When Governor Ricovarus ordered her to be tortured and thrown into the fire, she remained unharmed.
Despite having her breasts cut off and being tormented in prison, she was rolled over sharp shards and hot coals.
She prayed and then departed to the Lord.
In Africa, Florus, Jocundus, Peter, Marcus, Acutius, and Januaria are commemorated.
In Syria, Saint Anastasia is remembered.
The birth and ordination as bishop of Medonis and the passing of Saint Melani, bishop and confessor, are noted.
His body was found unharmed, with a cloth placed over it amid the flames.
January 7th marks the return of the child Jesus from Egypt.
Today, we remember Saint Lucian, a priest and martyr from the Church of Antioch.
Known for his wisdom and eloquence, he was martyred in Nicomedia for his faith in Christ, being cut into four pieces.
Each piece was tied to stones and thrown into the sea.
Miraculously, the next day, his entire body, along with the stones, was found at Helenopolis in Bithynia and was given an honorable burial.
The city, originally called Drepana, was later rebuilt by Emperor Constantine and renamed Helenopolis in honor of his mother.
In Antioch, we also honor the blessed martyr Clerus, a deacon who endured torture seven times for his faith in Christ.
After suffering long in prison, he achieved martyrdom by beheading.
We also remember the martyrdom of Saint Fausta, a virgin during Emperor Maximian's reign.
Her patience and faith converted her torturer, Evilasius, a palace officer, as well as the prefect ordered to torture her.
She was first suspended and torn with tools, then thrown to beasts, but they did not harm her.
Nails were driven into her head.
Then, she was thrown into a boiling tar pan but remained unharmed.
Ultimately, along with Evilasius and the prefect, she surrendered her spirit.
Hearing of this, the Christian community buried the bodies of these saints.
On January 8th, we commemorate Poliectes and Palladius in Greece.
In Naples, Campania, we celebrate the birth of Saint Severinus, a bishop and confessor, and the brother of the blessed Victorinus, renowned for his miracles.
After living a life full of holiness and performing many virtues, he found rest.
He was buried where he had led a very abstinent life before becoming a bishop.
In Greece, we also remember Rusticus, Timothy, and Jocundus.
We honor the memory of Saint Lucian, a companion of the blessed Dionysius.
We also remember Messianus.
In Metz, we commemorate Patient, the bishop.
On January 9th, in Mauretania, in the city of Caesarea, we remember the martyrdom of Saint Martiana, a virgin and martyr.
In Antioch, the feast of Saint Julian the martyr and Basilissa the virgin is celebrated on this day.
They were cherished by their wealthy parents and, being their only children, were reluctantly joined in marriage, but only in appearance.
They upheld a holy vow and remained together in virginity for several years.
With their wealth, they established numerous monasteries in the districts of Antioch, with Julian becoming the father of ten thousand monks, and Basilissa the mother of many virgins.
Basilissa sent them ahead to the kingdom of heaven and then followed herself.
Later, Julian was sought by the governor Martian.
During this time, under Diocletian and Maximian, the persecution of the saints intensified, forcing many priests and ministers of the Church of Christ to seek refuge with Julian due to the severity of the persecution.
Captured with this vast multitude, Julian awaited the governor's hearing, while the other servants of God were consumed by fire on the spot, by the order of the ruthless leader.
In their honor, choirs singing to God were reportedly heard at the third, sixth, ninth, and evening hours.
Blessed Julian was first beaten with harsh clubs.
During the beating, an official necessary to the governor lost an eye, which he regained immediately through Julian's prayer.
Believing in Christ, he was promptly beheaded by the irrational judge.
Blessed Julian was then taken to the temple of demons, where about five hundred statues were shattered into dust.
For this, he was locked in a deep, dark prison with young Celsus, the governor's son.
However, they were granted a pleasant fragrance and miraculous light.
Seven brothers and twenty soldiers who visited them were first thrown into the fire, and then the soldiers were slaughtered by the sword.
Moreover, Julian, along with the boy Celsus, the priest Anthony, and Anastasius, suffered various torments, and they, along with the matron Marcionilla, were killed by the soldiers.
January.
This marks the birth of Blessed Nicanor, one of the first seven deacons, who was gloriously crowned in Cyprus and honorably buried there.
In the Thebaid, we remember Saint Paul, the first hermit.
He lived in solitude in the desert from the age of sixteen until he was ninety-three.
Anthony witnessed his soul being carried to heaven by angels among the choirs of apostles and prophets.
In Rome, Bishop Melchiades decreed that the faithful should not fast on Sundays in the Church.
Pope Hyginus organized the clergy and distributed ecclesiastical ranks.
January eleventh.
This day marks the departure of the Lord from Egypt, celebrated by some on January ninth and by others on January fifth, due to the lengthy journey.
In Alexandria, we honor the holy confessors, Peter, Severus, and Leucius.
In Africa, we commemorate Saint Salvius the martyr, on whose feast day Saint Augustine preached to the people of Carthage.
January twelfth.
In Achaia, we remember Cyriacus.
In Egypt, Philoromus is honored.
In Arabia, Saturus, who, upon passing by a temple of an idol, blew upon it and made the sign of the cross on himself, causing it to fall immediately; for this reason, he was beheaded by the local judge.
On this same day, we celebrate the birth of Saint Arcadius the martyr, famous for his lineage and miracles.
January thirteenth.
The octave of the Epiphany.
In Rome, on the Lavican Way, we remember Secundina, Corona, and forty soldiers under Emperor Gallienus.
In Poitiers, we commemorate the burial of Saint Hilary, bishop and confessor, who, under the heretical Emperor Constantius, was exiled for four years in Phrygia for the Catholic faith.
Among his other virtues, it is said that he raised the dead through prayer.
January fourteenth.
In Antioch, we remember Glycerius the deacon, one of the ancients, who suffered many torments and was drowned in the sea.
In Campania, in the city of Nola, we honor Felix the priest.
During persecution, his bishop, Maximus, fled to the desert in fear, and blessed Felix was captured, bound in chains, brought before the governor, and beaten with rods.
Then, tortured on the rack, chained in prison, and placed on screws and shards: at night, an angel of the Lord broke the chains and split the beam that held his feet, instructing him to seek out his priest.
When he finally found him, the priest was burdened with age, weakened by hunger, stiff from the cold, with closed eyes and clenched teeth, barely alive and scarcely breathing.
He had nothing to offer the old man, but suddenly, he marveled at a grape hanging from the bushes.
He squeezed it into the mouth of the confessor, reviving him, and carried him on his shoulders to the city, where he secretly fed him under the shelter of a widow.
Then, captured and sent into exile, he converted many there through the display of signs.
Returning later, when sought again for torture, he was hidden by divine providence and stood out gloriously in Nola for his many virtues, so much so that all the people asked for him to be their bishop.
He did not consent, but with another appointed in his place, he nonetheless continued in the service of God for 12 years and, having completed the mysteries on a Sunday, departed to Christ.
He was buried not far from the city of Nola, in a place called Pincis.
In the city of Spoleto, the birth of Pontianus the martyr, who suffered during the time of Emperor Antoninus under the judge Fabian.
When he refused to sacrifice to idols, he was ordered to be beaten very cruelly with rods.
Then he was made to walk barefoot over burning coals, and later, two lions were set upon him.
When they did not harm him, he was poured over with molten lead; and when he was not harmed by this either, he was beheaded.
On the 15th of January in Palestine, the burial of the prophet Habakkuk, whose remains, along with the bones of the prophet Micah, were found through the Lord's revelation during the reign of Arcadius and Honorius, the emperors.
Also, the commemoration of Macarius the abbot, a disciple of Saint Anthony.
Also, the blessed Isidore, renowned for his holy life, faith, and miracles.
On the 16th of January in Rome, on the Via Salaria, in the cemetery of Priscilla, the birth of Saint Marcellus the Pope.
He established cemeteries along the Salaria Road and set up twenty-five locations in Rome for baptism and repentance, aimed at those converting from paganism, and for the burial of martyrs.
By order of Emperor Maximian, he was first beaten with clubs and expelled from the emperor's presence after rebuking him.
When Maximian learned that the house of Saint Lucina, which he had confiscated because she had given her property to Christians, was being used to create a church and hold Masses, he ordered boards to be laid in the middle of the city, in the same church, for animals from the public stable.
He assigned the bishop to serve the animals under public watch.
After many years of serving there, dressed in rough garments, he died and was buried with spices by Priest John and Blessed Lucina in the cemetery of Priscilla.
In Arles, there is Saint Honoratus, a bishop and confessor who, among other miracles, is said to have driven a dragon from the island of Hilarina through prayer and founded a monastery there.
In the region of Mandensis, at the Perona monastery, we have Saint Fursey of Ireland.
Taken from this world, he witnessed many wonders and, upon returning, shared these amazing experiences with others before ultimately passing away in severe austerity.
On January 17th, in Egypt, at Thebaid, we remember the burial of Blessed Anthony the monk.
Though he had no formal education, he is said to have memorized the divine Scriptures by listening and understood them through wise thinking.
His life was unparalleled, marked by miracles from childhood to old age, and he left behind many disciples of his holiness, celebrated throughout the Christian world.
He died peacefully under Emperor Constantine at the age of 105 and was buried in the desert by his disciples, as he had instructed, in secret.
His body was later found by divine revelation under Emperor Justinian and taken to Alexandria to be interred in the church of Blessed John the Baptist.
The birth of the holy twins Speusippus, Elasippus, and Melasippus took place in Lingonis.
At the age of twenty-five, they, along with their grandmother Leonilla, Jonilla, and Neon, were martyred during the reign of Emperor Aurelian.
The twins were hung on a single tree, their hands tied upwards and their feet downwards, stretched so much that it seemed their joints might separate.
They were then thrown into a fire but remained unharmed by the flames.
In prayer, they peacefully passed together to the Lord.
Jonilla, witnessing these events, declared her Christian faith.
She was seized by the crowd, hung by her hair, and tortured severely.
Refusing to renounce Christ, she and Leonilla were killed by the sword.
Neon, who documented these events, also confessed the name of Christ and was martyred.
The priest Benignus, sent from the East by Blessed Polycarp, Bishop of Myra and a disciple of the Apostle John, taught and baptized these twins.
He traveled to Gaul with fellow priest Andochius and deacon Thyrsus.
The twins were buried two miles from the city of Lingonis.
Turbon, who also chronicled the victories of those confessing the Lord, suffered martyrdom shortly after.
On January 18th, we remember the Chair of Saint Peter the Apostle, marking when he first sat in Rome.
Peter, the chief of the apostles, initially preached the Gospel in Jerusalem, Caesarea, and other Jewish cities.
Later, he was sent to preach to the Gentiles, arriving in Antioch where he established and led the Church for several years.
He then traveled to Rome in the second year of Claudius Caesar's reign, fervently preaching the Gospel and serving as bishop of the city for twenty-five years.
In Rome, we also honor the birth of Saint Prisca, the virgin and martyr.
In Pontus, we remember the holy martyrs Moses and Ammonius, who, as soldiers, were first sent to the mines and ultimately condemned to fire.
On January 19th, in Jerusalem, we commemorate the holy sisters Martha and Mary, sisters of Lazarus.
In Smyrna, we honor the holy martyr Germanicus, who was condemned to face the beasts.
In Africa, we remember the martyrs Paul, Quintus, and many others.
In Carthage, for Picaria, Pia, and thirty-eight others, on January 20th.
In Rome, Pope Fabian, who led the Church for twenty-five years, was martyred during Emperor Decius's reign and buried in the cemetery of Callixtus.
He organized the Church by dividing regions among deacons and appointed seven deacons to oversee notaries, ensuring the deeds of martyrs were properly documented.
He also commissioned many buildings in the cemeteries.
During his election, it's said that the Holy Spirit appeared to many in the form of a dove.
Also in Rome, on the same day, the birth of Saint Sebastian the martyr, who was so valued by Emperors Diocletian and Maximian that they gave him command of the first cohort.
When Diocletian discovered Sebastian was a Christian and couldn't sway him from his faith, he ordered him to be tied in a field as a target for arrows.
Shot by soldiers, Sebastian was left for dead, standing like a hedgehog with arrows.
However, at night, a woman named Irene came to retrieve his body and found him alive.
She took him home, cared for him, and once he recovered, he fortified many in their faith.
Sebastian then confronted the emperors, rebuking them.
Diocletian ordered him to be taken to the palace hippodrome and beaten with rods until he died.
His body was discarded in the main sewer, but he appeared in a dream to Saint Lucina, a noblewoman, telling her, "Near the circus, you'll find my body hanging on a hook. When you retrieve it, take me to the Catacombs and bury me in a crypt near the apostles' footsteps." That same night, she followed his instructions with her servants.
On the same day in Rome, the holy martyrs Marinus and Martha, along with their sons Audifax and Ambacuc, nobles from Persia, came to Rome to pray during Emperor Claudius's reign. After suffering beatings with clubs, the rack, fire, and having their hands cut off, Martha was drowned in a pool, and the others were beheaded.
January 21st.
In Athens, Bishop Publius, who, after being shipwrecked with the Apostle Paul on an island, showed great kindness.
After healing his father of fever and dysentery, he was converted to Christ through Paul's preaching.
He grew so much in God's grace that he was ordained as a bishop for the Athenians by the Apostle himself and was later crowned with martyrdom.
In Rome, Saint Agnes, under the prefect of the city, Symphronius, refused to marry his son out of love for Christ and her vow of virginity.
She was taken to a brothel for humiliation and stripped, but her own hair covered her, and then she was clothed in a heavenly garment.
She revived the prefect's son, who had pursued her indecently and was strangled by the devil, through the power of prayer.
After this, she was cast into flames, which were extinguished due to her holiness, and then she was struck by a sword.
Later, she appeared to her parents among a multitude of virgins dressed in garments woven with gold, openly proclaiming the glory of God, which she enjoyed in the heavens, on earth.
In Spain, in the city of Tarragona, the birth of Saints Fructuosus, the bishop, and the deacons Augurius and Eulogius.
During the time of Emperor Gallienus, under the governor Aemilianus, they were first thrown into prison and then cast into flames.
Their bonds were consumed, and with their hands spread in the form of a cross, they prayed to be burned, and they accomplished it.
Soon, some of the brothers and the governor's daughter, who was present, saw the souls of the saints ascending to heaven crowned.
At Troyes, the suffering of Saint Patroclus, martyr.
In Spain, the birth of Saint Vincent, deacon and martyr, who, with his bishop Saint Valerius, was taken in heavy chains from the city of Caesarea Augusta to Valencia by order of Dacian.
There he was long tormented by hunger and the filth of the prison, tortured with the rack and the horrendous tearing of claws, and burned for a long time on an iron bed, sprinkled with drops of fat and crackling salt.
After this, he was thrust into a most foul prison, with his legs stretched in a shackle, and thrown onto sharp fragments of pottery.
A great light appeared at night, and by God's power, the martyr was freed.
Among the angels, who visited him, he sang a hymn, leading even the prison guard to believe in Christ.
When morning came, Datianus called for him and ordered that he be laid on a very soft bed so that, after a slight refreshment, he could be tortured more severely once again.
He returned his tireless spirit to Christ.
Then Datianus ordered his body to be thrown into the field to be exposed to wild beasts and birds.
However, a divinely sent raven was sent to guard him, keeping away other birds and driving off a fierce wolf from the holy body.
When Datianus heard of this, he ordered the body to be sewn into a sack and drowned in the sea with a heavy stone weight.
Yet, by God's power, he first floated on the waves, was carried to the shore, and was buried in the sands before the rowers reached the port.
Later, when the holy martyr revealed himself to a faithful old woman and the persecution subsided, Christians reverently took him and buried him in a church.
The birth of Saint Anastasius, a monk and martyr from Persia:
He endured many torments of prison, beatings, and chains in Caesarea of Palestine by the Persians and was ultimately afflicted with numerous punishments in Persia, finally being beheaded by their king Chosroes along with seventy others.
His relics were first brought to a monastery in Jerusalem, then transferred to Rome, where they are venerated in the monastery of the blessed apostle Paul called "ad Aquas Salvias."
On the same day in Gaul, in the city of Ebredunum, the holy martyrs Vincent, Orontius, and Victor.
January twenty-third—The birth of Saint Parmenas, one of the first seven deacons:
Entrusted with God's grace by the brothers, he faithfully fulfilled the duty of preaching and achieved the palm of martyrdom, resting in Philippi.
In Rome, the virgin and martyr Emerentiana, who was a milk-sister of Saint Agnes, was stoned while praying at her tomb and defending those praying with her from the harm of pagans.
In Mauretania, in the city of Neocaesarea, the birth of Saint Severian and his wife Aquila, who were burned in fire.
January twenty-fourth.
In February, we remember the birth of Saint Timothy, a disciple of Saint Paul the Apostle.
He was ordained as a bishop in Ephesus by the blessed Apostle and, after many struggles for Christ, passed away peacefully.
In the twentieth year, his body was moved to Constantinople, along with the relics of the blessed Andrew and Luke.
In Antioch, we honor Saint Babylas the bishop and three children, who glorified the Lord through his sufferings and tortures, bravely ending his glorious life in chains.
He was buried not far from the Castalian spring, silencing Apollo in the place famous for his oracles.
In Neocaesarea, we remember the holy martyrs Mardonius, Musonius, Eugene, and Marcellus, who were all given over to the fire, with their remains scattered in the Axum River.
On January twenty-fifth, in Rome, we commemorate the transfer of Saint Paul the Apostle and his conversion at Damascus.
Here, we also remember the birth of Saint Ananias, who baptized Paul.
Elsewhere, we honor Saint Proiectus the martyr.
In Constantinople, we remember Gregory the Theologian.
In Gabala, we honor Saint Severianus the bishop, known for his admirable holiness and doctrine.
On January twenty-sixth, we celebrate the birth of Saint Polycarp, a disciple of the blessed Apostle John.
He was ordained by John as bishop of Smyrna and became a leader of all Asia.
During the reign of Marcus Antoninus and Lucius Aurelius Commodus, in the fourth persecution after Nero, he was brought to the flames by the proconsul in Smyrna.
The fire, however, curved like a vaulted ceiling, appearing like the sail of a wind-filled ship, standing over the body of the martyr.
The body did not appear as burning flesh but as if gold or silver were glowing in a furnace.
Those standing by perceived a fragrance like incense or the most precious burning ointment.
Finally, seeing that the fire could not consume the body, the executioners were ordered to pierce it with a dagger, which the fire had spared.
When this was done, so much blood poured out that it extinguished the pyre.
Alongside twelve others from Philadelphia, they were martyred in the aforementioned city.
During this time, the remarkable athlete of Christ, Germanicus, willingly faced the beasts and embraced his fate, swiftly earning the crown of eternal life.
On the same day, the holy martyrs Theogenes and thirty-six others were honored.
Similarly, in Bituriges, the blessed bishop and confessor Sulpitius was commemorated.
January 27th—In Africa, we celebrate the birth of Saint Julian, Vincentia, and thirty-two others.
This day also marks the birth of Saint John, bishop of Constantinople, renowned for his exceptional teaching, earning him the name Chrysostom, meaning "golden mouth" in Latin.
Through his many struggles, he achieved eternal life.
We also honor Marius, abbot of the monastery of Badocensis, celebrated for his virtuous life.
In Bethlehem of Judah, we remember the passing of Paula, mother of Eustochium, a virgin dedicated to Christ.
Coming from a noble Roman senatorial family, she renounced worldly wealth, gave to the poor, and embraced the poverty of Christ, becoming the mother of a virginal monastery in that town, glorified on the Lord's nativity.
Saint Jerome, writing about her life, attests that she was crowned far beyond with martyrdom.
In response to her requests, he composed many works.
January 28th—The octave of Saint Agnes, or as some believe, her true birth.
In the city of Apollonia, we remember the martyrs Leucius, Thyrsus, and Gallinicus.
During the reign of Emperor Decius, under the governors Cymbricius, Sylvanus, and Baudo, they endured various torments; the first and last were beheaded, while the middle, called by a heavenly voice, surrendered his spirit, completing their martyrdoms in Greece.
On the same day, in Alexandria, we honor the blessed bishop Cyril, a distinguished defender of the Catholic faith.
In the monastery of Reomanensis, we remember the presbyter Hicanis, a man of God.
January 29th—In Rome, we commemorate the birth of Papias and Maurus, soldiers during the time of Diocletian. Inspired by the steadfastness of the martyrs Saturninus and Sisinnius, they converted to the faith.
Laodicius, the prefect of the city, immediately ordered that their mouths, which confessed Christ, be crushed with stones and that they be thrown back into prison, where Pope Marcellus baptized them.
Twelve days later, he commanded that they be brought out, laid on the road, and beaten with clubs.
Then, they were lifted from the ground and beaten with lead weights until they died.
John the priest collected their bodies at night and buried them on the Via Nomentana, at the springs of blessed Peter, where he baptized.
This is written in the acts of blessed Pope Marcellus.
On the same day in Trier, the burial of blessed Bishop Valerius took place.
He was a disciple of Saint Peter the Apostle.
January thirtieth—In Antioch, the passion of Saint Hippolytus occurred.
He was initially misled by a new schism, but the grace of Christ corrected him, bringing him back to the love of the Church.
For this, and within the Church, he later achieved a glorious martyrdom.
In Jerusalem, the burial of the most blessed Bishop Matthias is remembered.
Wonderful and faithful deeds are narrated about him: he was the eighth to lead the Church after James, and after enduring much for Christ, he finally ended his life in peace.
Also remembered is blessed Alexander; during the Decian persecution, he was brought before the courts for confessing the faith and was imprisoned.
Despite his venerable gray hair, he frequently glorified the Lord through his sufferings and torments, moving repeatedly between chains and tribunals.
In the midst of these alternating torments, he peacefully found his end.
Also, in the Malbode Monastery, the birth of the virgin Adelgunda is celebrated.
During the times of King Dagobert of the Franks, she was born of noble lineage, chose the vow of virginity, and remained steadfast in it.
She often received angelic visions, encouraging her to stay true to her vow.
Finally, she passed into eternal life with great heavenly light.
January thirty-first—In Alexandria, the martyrdom of Saint Metranus occurred.
The pagans seized him and demanded that he speak impious words.
When he refused, they beat his entire body with clubs.
They pierced his face and eyes with sharp reeds and expelled him from the city with tortures.
And there, the last of his spirit was cast out with stones.
Also in Alexandria, there were Tarsicius, Zoticus, and Ammonius.
In Africa, we remember Victor, Publius, Saturninus, and Polycarp.
Additionally, Thyrsus, Gelasius, and Gallinicus are noted.
On the same day in the city of Trent, we honor the blessed bishop and martyr Vigilius.
February. The month of February has 28 days, and 29 in a leap year.
On February first, at Antioch, we remember Saint Ignatius, a bishop and martyr.
In Greece, we honor Polycarp, another bishop.
In Ravenna, we celebrate Saint Severus, also a bishop.
In Smyrna, we commemorate the birth of Saint Pionius, a martyr who, during the persecution under Antoninus Verus, showed incredible resolve.
He endured the harshness of prison, where he encouraged many to embrace martyrdom.
Ultimately, after facing severe tortures and being nailed with spikes, he was placed on a burning pyre, achieving a blessed death for Christ.
Fifteen others suffered alongside him.
On the same day, we remember blessed Ephrem, a deacon of the church of Edessa.
In Ireland, we celebrate the birth of Saint Brigid, a virgin known for her remarkable holiness.
It's said that when she touched the wood of the altar as a testament to her virginity, it turned green.
On the same day, we honor Saint Paul, the bishop of Troyes, whose life was marked by virtue and whose death was renowned for miracles.
February second marks the Presentation of the Lord, or the purification of blessed Mary.
On this day, she presented the Lord Jesus with offerings in the temple, as per the law.
Simeon and Anna, inspired by the Holy Spirit, recognized Him as the Christ and proclaimed this to those awaiting the redemption of Jerusalem, as documented in the book of Luke, chapter 2.
In Caesarea, we remember the birth of the blessed Cornelius, the centurion.
An angel revealed that his prayers and alms were accepted by God.
Following the angel's guidance, he sent for Saint Peter the Apostle to seek salvation.
Peter, instructed by a heavenly vision not to reject the Gentiles, went to him.
He shared the faith in Jesus Christ with the Gentiles, and seeing that they received the Holy Spirit through the gift of tongues, he baptized them, dedicating these firstfruits from the Gentiles to God, following the conversion of many thousands among the Jews.
Cornelius, leaving his military career, was elevated to the honor of bishop in the same city and eventually rested in peace.
In Rome, Saint Apronianus, a clerk baptized by Sisinnius, a deacon of Pope Marcellus, was beheaded by Laodicius, the city's prefect, during the reign of Emperor Maximian.
Also in Rome, at the Forum of Symphronius along the Flaminian Way, 163 miles from the city, celebrations were held for Lawrence, Hippolytus, and the birth of Saint Fortunatus.
In Africa, there were Victor, Maurinus, Honoratus, Urban, Hilary, Perpetuus, Julian, Privatula, and 74 others.
At Orleans, the burial of Blessed Flosculus, bishop and confessor, and Sicharia, a virgin, took place.
On February 3rd, in the city of Sebaste in Cappadocia, Saint Blaise, the bishop and martyr of Christ, was beheaded under Governor Agricolaus, along with two young boys, sons of one woman.
Among the seven encouraged by his preaching, who were martyred under the same governor.
In Africa, the blessed Celerinus, a deacon and confessor, and the holy martyrs Celerina, his grandmother, Laurentinus, his uncle, and Ignatius, his relative, were celebrated.
At Lyon, the burial of Saint Lupicinus, bishop, took place.
On February 4th, at the Forum of Symphronius, the birth of the holy Geminus, Gelasius, Mannius, Aquilinus, and Donatus was commemorated.
In the Egyptian city of Thynius, the passion of the blessed Phileas, bishop of that city, and Philoromus, a Roman military tribune, who admired and praised the bishop’s steadfastness, resulted in their beheading together.
With them, a countless multitude of faithful from the same city followed in their pastor’s footsteps and were crowned with martyrdom during the persecution.
On February 5th, in the city of Patras, the ordination of Saint Andrew the Apostle to the episcopacy took place.
In Sicily, in the city of Catania, the passion of Saint Agatha, a virgin, occurred under Emperor Decius and proconsul Quintianus:
after being struck and imprisoned, tortured on the rack, having her breasts cut off but healed by the Lord, and rolled on potsherds and coals, she finally completed her suffering in prison.
At Vienne, blessed Avitus, bishop, was celebrated.
Through his faith, diligence, and admirable teaching, during the time of King Gundobad, the Gauls were defended from the harassment of Arian heresy.
In Rome, along the Appian Way in its cemetery, we remember the suffering of Saint Soteris, a virgin and martyr.
At Caesarea in Cappadocia, we celebrate the birth of Saint Dorothea, a virgin.
She was challenged to endure life's trials alongside her two sisters, Christe and Calliste, who had recently abandoned their faith, in an attempt to sway her from Christ.
However, she successfully brought them back to Christ.
As a result, they were sent by the governor into a boiling cauldron, thus achieving the reward of martyrdom.
Later, under the rule of Governor Sapricius, she was first tortured on the rack, then beaten with palms for a long time, and finally sentenced to death.
As she was being led out of the court to her execution, a scholar named Theophilus called out to her, "Hey, bride of Christ, send me apples from the paradise of your Christ."
She promised to send them immediately.
When she reached the place of execution, after praying, she took out her handkerchief and, calling a six-year-old boy to her, sent it to Theophilus, saying, "Tell him: Dorothea, servant of God, sends you apples from the paradise of her Christ."
Upon receiving it and giving thanks for her fulfillment of his request, he began to wipe his face.
He was suddenly filled with such sweetness that he was completely transformed in spirit, and with great joy and a loud voice, he repeatedly declared, "Blessed be the name of the Lord Jesus Christ."
For this confession, he was soon seized and suspended on the rack, tortured with such cruelty that all those standing around were horrified.
Finally, he completed his martyrdom by being beheaded.
On the same day, we honor Antholianus, who was crowned with martyrdom near the city of Arvernus.
In Gaul, in the city of Aderato, we remember the passing of Saint Vedast, a bishop and confessor.
In the monastery of Hellone, we commemorate the passing of Saint Amandus, a bishop and confessor.
In Britain, we remember Saint Moses or Moyses, a venerable bishop.
He initially led a solitary life in the desert, and through his merits, virtues, and the signs performed by the Lord through him, he became widely known.
Afterwards, at the request of Mauvia, the queen of the Saracens, he became the bishop of her people.
He upheld the pure fellowship of the Catholic faith, converting many to Christianity.
Thus, perfected in virtues, he rested in peace.
February 8th—In Lesser Armenia, we commemorate the saints Dionysius, Aemilian, and Sebastian.
On the same day in Alexandria, we remember Saint Cointha the martyr.
She was seized by pagans and forced to worship idols.
When she refused, they tied ropes to her feet and dragged her through the streets, subjecting her to horrible torture.
In Rome, we honor the burial of Saint Paul the bishop and Pope Julius.
February 9th—In Cyprus, we celebrate the birth of Alexander, Ammon, and thirty-seven others.
In Alexandria, we remember the virgin Apollonia, whose teeth were all knocked out by her persecutors.
When threatened to be burned alive unless she spoke impious words, she bravely broke free and willingly leaped into the fire.
February 10th—In Rome, we honor the holy martyrs Zoticus, Irenaeus, Hyacinth, and Amantius.
Also in Rome, on the Lavican Way, ten soldiers are remembered.
On the same day in the East, we commemorate Saint Soteris the virgin, who endured severe beatings and other punishments, completing her martyrdom by the sword.
In Campania, we honor Saint Sylvanus the bishop and confessor.
In Bethlehem, under King Herod, we remember the suffering of the saints Andrew and Aporius.
In Saintes, we celebrate the burial of Saint Trojanus the bishop and confessor, and Baldegundis the abbess.
On the same day, we commemorate the burial of Saint Scholastica the virgin, whose soul was seen by her brother, Saint Benedict the abbot, ascending to heaven in the form of a dove.
He shared this vision with the brothers after the morning hymns and gave thanks to God.
February 11th—In Rome, we remember Calocerus and Parthenius.
In Apamea, we commemorate Paeonius and Euphrasius.
In Lyon, Bishop and Martyr Desiderius, a blessed man, suffered in the villa of Prisciniac, in the region of Lyon, on May 23.
However, he was later transferred to Vienne, the city of his bishopric.
In Alexandria, the passing of Saint Euphrosyne, known in the monastery for her remarkable virtue of abstinence and miracles, is commemorated on February 12.
In Spain, in the city of Barcelona, the birth of Saint Eulalia, a virgin and martyr, is celebrated.
She suffered during the time of Emperor Diocletian under the governor of Spain, Dacian.
During this time, in Barcelona, Saint Cucufas, and in Girona, Saint Felix, are also known to have received glorious crowns of martyrdom.
In Africa, the passion of Saint Damian, a soldier, is remembered.
In Alexandria, the children Modestus and Ammonius are commemorated.
In Rome, Pope Gregory the Second, who led the Church for 16 years during the reigns of Emperors Leo and Constantine, is honored.
He was a chaste man, learned in the Holy Scriptures, and through Bishop Boniface, he preached the word of salvation in Germany.
This same pope instituted fasting and the celebration of Mass on the Thursday of the Lenten season, which was not previously done.
February 13.
In Antioch, the birth of Saint Agabus the prophet is noted; he is mentioned in the Acts of the Apostles, chapter 11, verse 21, for foretelling a great famine and the suffering of the Apostle Paul.
In Melitene, Armenia, the birth of Saint Polyeuctus, a martyr whose name means "much praying" in Latin, is celebrated.
In Lyon, the death of Bishop Stephen is remembered.
February 14.
In Rome, the birth of Saint Valentine the priest, who after many acts of healing and teaching, was beaten with clubs and then beheaded under Emperor Claudius, is commemorated.
On the same day in Rome, the passion of Saint Valentine, Bishop of Terni, is also remembered.
He was seized by pagans, beaten with rods, and after prolonged beatings, imprisoned.
When he could not be overcome, in the silence of midnight, he was taken out of prison and beheaded by the order of the furious Placidus, the city's prefect.
When his disciples Proculus, Ephebus, and Apollonius brought him back to their city, and this was reported to the consul Leontius, he ordered them to be beheaded.
Those who are buried not far from the body of Saint Valentine.
Also in Rome, on the Via Ardeatina: Felicula, Vitalis, and Zeno.
In the city of Aegea, Saint Julian.
At Alexandria, the holy martyrs Bassus, Antonius, and Protolichus were drowned in the sea.
Also, Cyrion the priest, Moses, Bassianus the reader, and Agathon the exorcist were all burned by fire.
Dionysius and Ammonius were beheaded.
February 15th—in Rome, the martyrdom of Crato, who had a son named Chaeremon suffering from a severe illness.
Crato called upon Blessed Valentine, bishop of Interamna, to heal him, promising that if the boy were healed, he and his whole household would become Christian.
After the boy was healed, Crato fulfilled his promise; he, his wife, and entire household were baptized, and not many days later, he was martyred.
In Interamna, Saint Agape the virgin.
In Brescia, the martyrdom of Faustinus.
In Antioch, Joseph the deacon.
At the city of Sebaste, the suffering of Saint Blaise the bishop.
He performed many miracles under the governor Agricolaus, enduring long beatings, imprisonment, and suspension on a wooden frame where his flesh was torn with iron combs.
Afterward, he faced another terrible prison, was thrown into a lake but miraculously floated and emerged safely.
By order of the wicked judge, he was eventually beheaded along with two boys and entered the blessed kingdom with them.
While he was still struggling, seven blessed women who gathered the drops of blood from his most blessed wounds were discovered to be Christians.
After being thrown into a fiery furnace where lead was poured over them, enduring iron combs that tore their flesh, and wearing burning bronze tunics, they were finally sentenced to be struck by the sword, thus earning eternal life with the price of their blood.
February 16th—the birth of Saint Onesimus, for whom Blessed Paul the apostle sends personal letters to Philemon.
The blessed apostle ordained him as bishop, entrusted him with the word of preaching, and left him in the city of Ephesus.
After Blessed Timothy, he also served as bishop.
He was taken to Rome, where he was stoned for his faith in Christ and became the first martyr for Christ, later being buried there.
His body was eventually brought back to the place where he had been ordained as bishop.
In Cumae, we commemorate the birth of Saint Juliana the virgin.
During the time of Emperor Maximian, she was severely tortured by her father, Africanus, and then by the prefect Eleusius, to whom she was betrothed.
She endured being stripped, beaten with rods, hung by her hair, and having molten lead poured on her head, before being thrown back into prison, where she openly fought with the devil.
When summoned again, she overcame tortures involving wheels, fire, and a boiling pot, and completed her martyrdom by beheading.
She suffered in Nicomedia but was transferred to Campania shortly after, according to God's plan.
On the same day in Egypt, Julian and five thousand others.
In Spain, in the city of Barcelona, Saint Cucufas the martyr.
In Africa, Saint Maximus.
Also Secunda, Saul.
On February 17 in Persia, we remember Blessed Polychronius, the martyr and bishop of Babylon and Ctesiphon.
In the presence of Emperor Decius, he was struck with stones in his face, his hands outstretched, and his eyes raised to heaven, and he gave up his spirit, as written in the passion of Saint Lawrence.
In Africa, the saints Donatus and Secundianus.
In Aquileia, Chrysanthos, Eutychius, Concordia, Justus, Romulus, Saloninus, Sylvanus, and eighty-four others whose names are known to God.
Elsewhere, Januarius and many others.
On February 18 in Jerusalem, Blessed Simeon, bishop and martyr, is said to have been a relative of the Savior according to the flesh.
He was known to be the son of Cleopas and the brother of Joseph.
On the same day, we remember the holy martyrs Claudius and his wife Praepedigna, and their sons Alexander and Curius, and Claudius's brother Blessed Maximus.
Though of very noble birth, they were baptized by Blessed Gaius, the Roman pontiff, under the guidance of their brother Gabinius, a priest.
And afterward, they were arrested by the order of Diocletian, under the judge Julius.
Claudius, along with his wife and children, was sent into exile; then they were burned, offering to God the fragrant sacrifice of martyrdom.
Later, they were cast into the sea at Ostia.
Their remains were diligently sought by Christians and buried near the city.
In Africa, there were Rutulus, Sylvanus, Classicus, Secundinus, Fluctulus, and Damasus.
At Interamna, Paul and many others.
On February 19th, in Rome, we remember the birth of Saint Gabinius, a priest and father of the blessed Susanna, who, after enduring long periods in chains under Diocletian, achieved the joys of heaven through a precious death.
In Africa, we celebrate the birth of Blessed Publius, Julian, and Marubius, along with Julian, Barachius, Paul, Marcellus, Tullius, Lampasius, Majulus, and Julius.
On February 20th, in Rome, on the Appian Way, in the cemetery of Callistus, the burial of Bishop Caius is commemorated.
In Cyprus, we remember the birth of Potamius, Nemesius, and Didymus.
Elsewhere, we honor Victor, Corona, and twenty others.
In Tyre, a large and renowned city of Phoenicia, the blessed martyrs, whose number only God knows, suffered.
Ordered by Diocletian, Veturius, the military commander, killed them through various tortures.
First, the martyrs of God were scourged all over their bodies; after this, they were handed over to beasts: lions, bears, leopards, and wild animals, even horses and bulls.
Their ferocity was further provoked with iron and fire.
But when none of the wild beasts harmed them, the fury turned to humans.
When they couldn't kill them with beasts, they even threw the bodies of the slain into the sea.
The leaders among them were Tyrannio and Sylvanus, bishops, who shortly afterward completed their martyrdom by the teeth of beasts; and Peleus and Linus, bishops, who were consumed by fire with many clerics.
The venerable priest Zenobius was also beheaded.
On February 21st, in Sicily, seventy-four martyrs suffered under Diocletian.
Through various torments, they earned the crown prepared for their confession from Christ.
In Africa, we honor the saints Verulus, Secundinus, Servulus, Syricius, Felix, Jocundus, Saturninus, Fortunatus, and seventeen others.
Elsewhere, we remember Victorinus, Mappalicus, and many other martyrs.
Additionally, we commemorate the burial of Bishop Eucherius.
On February 22nd —
In Antioch of Syria, we celebrate the chair of Saint Peter the Apostle.
In Alexandria, we remember Bishop Abilius, the second bishop after Blessed Mark, who served for 13 years.
In Hierapolis, we honor Bishop Papias, a listener of Saint John the Apostle, and Blessed Aristion, one of the seventy-two disciples of Christ.
In Nicomedia, we recall the birth of Saint Thecla, a virgin and disciple of Saint Paul the Apostle.
Under Emperor Nero, she was subjected to fire for the name of Christ but remained unharmed.
Later, she faced wild beasts and snakes without injury.
Ultimately, in Seleucia, she passed away peacefully, preserving her virginity and virtues.
In Rome, on the Tiburtine Way near Saint Lawrence, we remember Saint Concordia, who was martyred during the persecution under Decius.
February 23rd —
In Smyrna, we honor Saint Synerius, a monk who, during Emperor Maximian's time, boldly reproved inappropriate behavior in his garden.
Arrested, he confessed his Christian faith and was beheaded.
Seventy-two others also suffered there.
In Rome, we commemorate Saint Polycarp the priest, who, along with Blessed Sebastian, converted many to the faith of Christ, leading them to martyrdom.
In Smyrna, we acknowledge the birth of Saints Erotes and Carpophorus.
In Pannonia, we honor the saints Senerotus, Antigonus, Rutulus, and Libius.
In Africa, we remember Grysionius, Zenon, and many others.
February 24th —
In Palestine, we celebrate the birth of Saint Matthias the Apostle, chosen to replace Judas the traitor among the seventy disciples.
He preached the Gospel in Judea.
Additionally, we recognize the discovery of the head of the Lord’s forerunner during Prince Marcian's time, revealed by the forerunner to two monks.
It's known that he was beheaded as the Easter festival approached, as the Gospel indicates.
The following year, when Easter came around again, the mystery of the Lord's Passion was fulfilled.
In the Book of Sacraments, his birth is recorded as the fourth day before the Kalends of September.
In the Martyrology, marked with the names of Eusebius and Jerome, it states that on August 29, in the city of Emessa in the province of Phoenicia, Saint John the Baptist's birth is noted on the day he was beheaded.
However, this refers not to the day of his beheading, but to the day his head was found in that city and placed in the church.
Two Eastern monks traveled to Jerusalem to worship and see the holy sites.
Through a revelation, the Lord's forerunner instructed them to go to the former dwelling of King Herod, find his head there, and bury it with honor.
Malicious women had kept it in their room, separated from the body, so it couldn't accuse them of their wickedness again.
The head was found and taken by the mentioned brothers through divine grace.
However, it was taken by their companions and passed from place to place, and from person to person, until it was brought to Emessa.
It was ignobly stored in a cave in an urn under the ground for some time until it revealed itself again to a religious priest named Marcellus, while he was living in the same cave.
From that time, the beheading of the blessed Forerunner began to be celebrated in that city on the day his head was found or raised.
Elsewhere, the finding of his head is celebrated on September 24, the day he is said to have been conceived, but some celebrate it on August 29.
He was beheaded in a castle in Arabia called Machaerus, and his body was buried in the city of Samaria, now known as Sebaste, while the head was buried in Jerusalem.
Over time, his bones were moved to Jerusalem and then to Alexandria.
They are now housed there in a church dedicated to his honor.
Additionally, his head was taken from Edessa to Constantinople by Emperor Theodosius and is now visited in a richly adorned church outside the city.
It's believed this was done by divine providence so that by distributing the relics of the blessed martyr to various places, many signs of virtue would manifest.
Many people would be drawn to the faith and love he preached through the memory of his teachings and life, leading to conversions to the faith that justifies and saves.
Also, in Rome, Absalon.
In Caesarea of Cappadocia, the martyrs Herolus, Lucius, and Sergius.
In Africa, Julian, Julia, and many others.
In Nicomedia, the priest Lucian.
On February 25th, in Egypt, the saints Victor, Victorinus, Nichophorus, Claudian, Dioscorus, Serapion, and Papias were martyred during the reign of Emperor Numerian, under Duke Sabinus.
Victor was placed in a hollow wooden ball with holes and pierced through each hole for a long time.
When too much blood flowed out, he was taken from the ball and beheaded.
Victorinus had his hands and feet cut off, was put into the same ball, endured the same torture, and was finally killed with a sword.
Nichophorus, who willingly entered the ball, was ordered by the judge, in anger, to be taken out and roasted on a gridiron with hot coals.
When he persisted in his confession, he was taken from there and cut to pieces with a sword, passing away.
Of the remaining four, Claudian and Dioscorus were burned with flames, while Serapion and Papias were killed with a sword.
In Africa, the saints Donatus, Justus, Rutulus, Hireneus, and Pision.
In Pamphylia, Nestor and Casta.
February 26th.
In the city of Perge in Pamphylia, the blessed Bishop Nestor was born.
During the persecution of Decius, while praying day and night for the protection of Christ's flock, he was captured by Irenarchus, the chief of the city council.
He was brought before Governor Pollio like a spotless ram.
When he boldly and eagerly confessed the name of Christ and declared the gods of the nations to be evil demons, the governor ordered him to be suspended on the rack and tortured cruelly.
Joyfully, he sang, "I will bless the Lord at all times; His praise shall continually be in my mouth" from Psalm Thirty-Four.
Amazed by his endurance and trying to persuade him gently to abandon his faith, the governor asked, "Do you want to be with us, or with your Christ?"
Saint Nestor joyfully replied, "With my Christ, I was, I am, and I will be."
Angered, the governor sentenced him, declaring that anyone who confessed Jesus, crucified under Pontius Pilate, should suffer the same fate and be nailed to a cross.
Nestor encouraged the Christians present to remain steadfast in their faith and love for Christ and to suffer willingly so they might be glorified together.
He then asked the entire crowd of faithful to kneel and pray with him.
After finishing the prayer, and as everyone said, "Amen," he gave up his spirit.
He completed his martyrdom on the fifth day of the week, at the third hour.
On the same day, in Alexandria, the blessed Bishop Alexander, a venerable old man, removed Arius, his priest, corrupted by heretical impiety, from the Church. Later, Arius was condemned among three hundred and eight Fathers at the Council of Nicaea.
Also in Alexandria, Felix and his companions.
February Twenty-Seventh---In Seville, Spain, Saint Leander, a bishop, was born. The blessed Gregory wrote the books of Moralia for him.
Through his preaching and diligence, the entire Gothic nation was converted from Arian impiety by King Reccared.
He also converted his brother, King Erminigild, from the Arian heresy to the Catholic faith while their heretic father was still alive, and through his encouragement, led him to glorious martyrdom.
On the same day in Alexandria, the birth of Saint Julian the martyr is commemorated.
Despite being so constrained by gout that he could neither walk nor stand, he was brought on a small chair by those carrying him to the judge.
One of them immediately renounced the faith, but another, named Eum, remained steadfast with the old man Julian in confessing the Lord.
They were ordered to be placed on camels and paraded around the city while being whipped, with the crowd surrounding them, until they succumbed to the beatings.
In Lyon, Saint Baldemer, a man of God, whose tomb is graced with frequent miracles, is remembered.
On the day before the Kalends of March—in Alexandria, the holy martyrs Celeris, Pupillus, Gaius, and Serapion are commemorated.
In the verdant places of the territory of Lyon, the blessed Romanus, an abbot who was the first to lead a hermit life there and was renowned for many miracles and virtues, became the Father of many monks.
March has 31 days, including 30 lunar days.
This month marks the first fast for the Ember Days.
On March 1st in Rome, 260 holy martyrs were condemned during the time of Claudius for bearing the name of Christ while working on the Via Salaria.
Claudius ordered them to be sent to a brick kiln outside the city walls at the Salaria Gate.
Enclosed in the city's amphitheater, they were killed by soldiers' arrows.
In the same place, Pope Simplicius, who led the church in Rome for 15 years, condemned Acacius, the bishop of Constantinople, and Peter, the bishop of Alexandria, for following Eutyches.
Also, at Angers, Bishop Albinus is remembered.
On March 2nd in Rome, along the Via Latina, the martyrs Jovinus and Basileus suffered under the emperors Gallienus and Valerian.
On the same day, numerous martyrs suffered under Emperor Alexander, who, after long tortures, sentenced them to death.
March 3rd in Spain, in the city of Calahorra, marks the birth of the holy martyrs Emeterius and Celedon.
As soldiers in the city of León in Galicia, during a period of persecution, they endured many torments for confessing Christ's name.
They were brought to Calahorra, achieved martyrdom, and were crowned.
When their heads were severed by the executioner, a great miracle appeared to the people.
The ring of one and the scarf of the other were lifted by a cloud and carried into the heavens.
All present witnessed this, following the brightness of the gold and the whiteness of the linen in awe.
Aureolus writes about this in the book of the crowned.
At Caesarea in Palestine, the holy martyrs Marinus the soldier, and Asterius the senator, suffered during Valerian's persecution.
Marinus was accused by fellow soldiers of being a Christian and, when asked by the judge, declared in a clear voice that he was a Christian, and was given three hours to deliberate.
After leaving the courts, he found great strength in his faith from the blessed Theotecnus, the bishop of the city.
Returning to the judge's court, he boldly declared, "We must obey God rather than men" (Acts 5:29) and was immediately martyred by beheading.
Asterius, mentioned earlier, honored the martyr by catching his headless body on his shoulders and spreading his garment beneath it.
He also received martyrdom shortly after.
This is recorded in the seventh book of Ecclesiastical History.
February 28 —marks the birth of Saint Lucius, pope and martyr.
He decreed that two priests and two deacons should accompany each bishop for ecclesiastical testimony.
During the persecution by Valerian and Gallienus, he was exiled for his faith in Christ but, by divine will, returned to his church.
He was martyred by beheading and later buried on the Appian Way near Saint Sixtus.
His tenure as bishop lasted three years, three months, and three days.
Also in Rome, on the Appian Way, the burial site of nine hundred holy martyrs in the cemetery of Saint Cecilia.
On the same day, Saint Caius of the Palatine was drowned in the sea.
March 5 —In Antioch, Saint Phocas, a martyr, endured numerous injuries for the name of our Redeemer, Christ.
His victory over the ancient serpent is still celebrated.
When someone is bitten by a snake in that area, they touch the door of his basilica in faith, and the venom's power is nullified, saving them.
Also on this day, Eusebius, Palatinus, and eight other martyrs were remembered.
In Antioch, Saturninus, Castus, and Syria are commemorated.
Also, Saturninus, Martinus, Peter, and many others.
March 6 —In Nicomedia, Saints Victor and Victorinus were born.
They suffered torment alongside Claudianus and his wife Bassa for three years and were imprisoned, ending their lives in captivity.
In Nicopolis of Paphlagonia, martyrs Alexander and Diodorus are remembered.
In Italy, in the village of Fagonia, Victorinus and Sylvanus are honored.
MARCH 7TH
In Mauretania, in the city of Tiburbitanorum, the holy martyrs Perpetua and Felicitas, along with Revocatus, Saturninus, and Secundulus, faced martyrdom.
Secundulus passed away in prison.
The others were sent to face the beasts under the ruler Severus, on his birthday.
While still imprisoned, and with Felicitas pregnant, the prayers of their holy companions were answered, allowing her to give birth in the eighth month.
Perpetua was granted a state of mind that distracted her from the physical ordeal, enduring the attack of a cow without awareness of her suffering.
In Antioch, Leucius, Saturus, and Nestor.
In Thrace, Dandus, Eunice, Secundus, Sergius, and Optatus.
MARCH 8TH
In Carthage, the holy deacon Pontius, of the blessed bishop Cyprian, endured exile with him until his martyrdom and left behind an outstanding record of his life and martyrdom.
By glorifying the Lord through his sufferings, he earned the crown of life.
In Nicomedia, Bishop Quintilus and Capitulinus.
In Africa, Rogatus and Felix, and the birth of Cyril the bishop, Silvanus, and Manilius.
MARCH 9TH
In the city of Misena, Saint Gregory the bishop, brother of the blessed Basil of Caesarea, was famed for his great learning and eloquence.
In Barcelona, Bishop Pacianus, notable for both his life and speech, passed away at a very old age during the reign of Emperor Theodosius.
In Africa, Felix and Philip, Marianus, Rogatus, Concessus, Gorgonius, and Esychius.
MARCH 10TH
The holy martyrs Alexander and Gaius of Eumenia were crowned with martyrdom at Apamea during the persecution by Antoninus Verus.
Apollinaris, the bishop of Hierapolis, documented this in a book against the Cataphrygians.
In Persia, forty-two holy martyrs were celebrated.
In Antioch, Agape the virgin and Marina.
In Nicomedia, the martyrs Palatinus, Firmanus, and Rusticus.
In Alexandria, Heraclius, Zosimus, Alexander, and Gaius.
In Italy, at the monastery of Bobbio, the memory of Saint Attala, an abbot and disciple of the blessed Columbanus, renowned for his remarkable holiness, is celebrated on February 27.
In Sebaste, a city in Lesser Armenia, the birth of forty martyrs is commemorated.
During the time of Emperor Licinius, Governor Agricolaus, and Duke Lysias, they were crowned with martyrdom for the name of Christ.
When Governor Agricolaus couldn't persuade them to worship idols, he ordered them to be buried with stones.
However, the executioners, striking each other with stones, couldn't harm the martyrs.
Duke Lysias, filled with anger, picked up a stone to strike one of the saints, but by God's wondrous will, the stone struck the governor's face instead.
Enraged, he ordered the saints to be thrown into a frozen lake.
By divine will, the ice melted, and the frigid water turned as warm as a bath, so that, strengthened by the Holy Spirit, they burst into praise of God.
One of them, becoming faint-hearted, fled to a nearby bathhouse, but as soon as he felt the heat, he collapsed and died.
Meanwhile, as all who were assigned to guard them fell asleep, only the jailer stayed awake.
Hearing their prayers and seeing an immense light and the ice thawed, he looked around to see where the light came from and saw crowns descending upon the saints, numbering thirty-nine.
He began to wonder, "There are supposed to be forty; where is the crown for the last one?"
After confessing Christ, he jumped into the lake, completing the designated number.
In the morning, finding them unharmed, their captors broke their legs with clubs and burned their bodies, throwing them into the river.
However, by divine dispensation, their remains were revealed to religious men in the depths of the water and were buried with due honor.
In Nicomedia, the memory of Eunicus, Gorgonius, Firmus, and Agapitus is celebrated on March 12.
In Rome, the blessed memory of the pontiffs Gregory, the teacher, and apostle of the English, is commemorated.
Through the faithful evangelists Augustine, Mellitus, and John, he converted the English to the faith of Christ.
He served as bishop for 13 years, 6 months, and 10 days.
Similarly, there was Innocent, who led the Church for 15 years, 2 months, and 21 days.
He issued a decree regarding the Church of God, condemning Pelagius and Coelestius as heretics, and established that anyone born to Christian parents should be baptized.
Pelagius, however, condemned this.
This was the work of Innocent.
Gregory indeed enhanced it, particularly in the Canon's prayer: arrange our days in your peace.
In Nicomedia, there was the blessed martyr Peter, one of the companions of Dorotheus and Gorgonius, who served in the king's chamber.
Under Diocletian's orders, he was tortured for speaking out against the torment of martyrs, being hung on the rack and whipped.
His skin was stripped away, and he was drenched with vinegar and salt.
Despite enduring such torture with strength and resolve, he was placed on a gridiron over coals, not to be burned quickly, but gradually, to prolong his suffering.
Thus, Peter was crowned with martyrdom, truly becoming an heir of Peter's faith and name.
Similarly, in Nicomedia, holy Egdunus the priest and seven others were suffocated on separate days to instill fear in others.
On the same day, there was the passion of the martyr Maximilian and many others.
On March 13th, in Nicomedia, there was the birth of the holy Macedonius the priest, his wife Patrica, and their daughter Modesta.
In the city of Nicaea, there were holy Theusea and her son Horis, along with Theodora, Nymphodora, Marcus, and Araba, who were all delivered to the fire.
Likewise, there were Julius the bishop and Alexander.
Similarly, in Nicomedia, there were many martyrs.
On March 14th, in Rome, there were forty-seven martyrs, baptized by the blessed apostle Peter, while he was imprisoned in the Mamertine prison with his fellow apostle Paul, where they were detained for nine months.
Likewise, there was Zacharias the pontiff, who served in Rome for 10 years.
Here, in the residence of Blessed Gregory, a martyr, his head was found stored in a box.
Inside, there was also a document inscribed with Greek letters.
He was buried in the church of the Blessed Apostle Peter.
In Carthage, the martyrs Donatus, Eufrosius, and Fronimus.
In Nicomedia, the martyrs Felicissimus, Dativus, and Frontina.
In Africa, the martyrs Diona, Alexander, Peter, Mammarius, and Naboth.
On March 15th, in Cappadocia, the holy martyr Longinus witnessed the Lord's Passion.
After piercing His side with a spear, he saw the earthquake and signs, believed in Christ, and repented.
He served Christ for 38 years, converting many to the faith, and eventually achieved martyrdom in Cappadocia under the governor Octavius.
Though initially struck with physical blindness, he was enlightened after his martyrdom.
In Thessalonica, holy Matrona, a servant of a widow named Plautilla, secretly worshiped Christ and attended church daily with private prayers.
When discovered by her mistress, she was tied to a bench and whipped nearly to death, then left locked up overnight.
The next day, she was found miraculously untied and praying with great grace.
Again, she was tied and beaten until she was mute, left for three days, but found miraculously untied and praying on the third day.
Finally, she was beaten with sticks until she died, giving up her spirit in the confession of Christ.
In Nicomedia, Lucius, a bishop and martyr.
In Carthage, Paul and Salutaris.
Also, Alexander and Theophilus.
On March 16th, in Rome, the martyr Cyriacus, ordained as a deacon by Blessed Pope Marcellus, performed many miracles with Sisinnius under the emperors Diocletian and Maximian.
He expelled demons from possessed bodies and, after enduring many severe tortures, was finally beheaded by the order of Maximian through Carpasian, the deputy.
In Aquileia, Hilary.
In Nicomedia, we have Castor, Dionysius, and Nonnus.
In Greece, Cyriaca, Florentius, and Jovian are notable figures. It's March 17th.
In Aquileia, we remember Largus, Tatian, Cato, and Dativus.
In Rome, there's Alexander the bishop and Theodulus the deacon.
In Scotland, we celebrate the birth of Saint Patrick the bishop, a Briton by nationality, who was the first to preach the name of our Lord Jesus Christ to the Scots on the island of Ireland, converting them to the true faith through his miraculous works.
On the same day, we remember the martyrdom of Saint Mary the martyr.
She was a servant to a distinguished man named Tertullus and refused to take part in the feasts for his son's birthday, choosing instead to fast in the Christian way.
For this, she was severely whipped by her master.
However, since she couldn't be turned away from her service to Christ back to idol worship, she was handed over to the public judge for punishment.
When the executioners attempted to burn her, the prayers of the people granted her a three-day reprieve.
After those three days, just as they were about to punish her again, she was miraculously saved by God's mercy.
After she prayed to God, a large stone in front of her split in two, enveloping her completely and protecting her from her enemies' wrath.
When the people were ordered by the leader to destroy the stone, a thunderbolt and lightning struck from the sky, killing many of them.
In total, two thousand seven hundred were destroyed by divine judgment, while the few who survived converted to the Lord and remained steadfast in the Christian faith.
On the same day, we celebrate the birth of Saint Gertrude, the virgin.
It's famously told that on her birthday, an elderly woman recently entering the monastery wouldn't break her fast because of the upcoming Easter festival.
Her daughter, who went to draw water from the cloister's well, fell in and was pulled out dead.
Through the merits of the holy virgin, she was brought back to life, bringing joy not only to her mother but also to the entire congregation.
This significantly enhanced the celebration of both Saint Patrick and Gertrude with her recovery.
March eighteenth marks the birth of Saint Alexander, a bishop.
From the city of Cappadocia, he traveled to Jerusalem, eager to see the holy places, where Narcissus, an elderly bishop, was leading the Church.
It was revealed to Narcissus and many of his clergy that the next day a bishop would arrive to assist in the priestly duties.
This prediction came true, and with everyone in Palestine gathered, especially with Narcissus's support, he took on the leadership of the Jerusalem church with him.
During the persecution under Decius, when he was already of venerable old age, he was taken to Caesarea, imprisoned, and crowned with martyrdom for his confession of Christ.
In Alexandria, the deacons of the College and Colytus are recognized.
In Nicomedia, Aprilis and Servulus.
In Campania, Quinti, Rogatus, and Ingenua.
In Mauretania, Timothy and Salda.
March nineteenth - In the city of Pinarus, we remember the blessed John, a man of great holiness.
Originally from Syria, he came to Italy, where an angel of God showed him a place to stay not far from the city.
Found by hunters under a tree covered in leaves during winter, he became well-known to the people through this fame and established a monastery.
For forty-four years, he served as the Father of many servants of God, and resting in peace, he shone brightly with daily miracles.
On the same day in Sorrento, Quinti, Quintilis, Quartilla, Marcus, and nine others are commemorated.
In Caesarea of Cappadocia, there was Theodore, the holy and pious priest.
In Africa, there were Bassae, Lucilla, Fuscianus, and many others. March 20th.
At Colossae, there was Archippus the bishop, a fellow soldier of the blessed apostle Paul.
In Antioch, Saint Joseph was honored.
In Syria, Paul, Cyril, Eugenius, Serapion, Victoricus, and others were recognized.
In Britain, Saint Cuthbert, who went from being a hermit to becoming the bishop of the Church of Lindisfarne, led a life full of miraculous signs from childhood to old age.
After his body was buried for 11 years, it was found incorrupt, as if he had just died, along with the clothing that covered it.
Saint Bede the priest documented his life in a booklet.
March 21st.
In Alexandria, Saint Serapion the monk was remembered.
Also noted were Joseph, Volutianus, and Philocalus.
At the castle Cassinum of the city of Beneventum, Saint Benedict the abbot was celebrated.
His life, glorious with virtues and miracles, is detailed by the blessed Pope Gregory in the Dialogues books.
He is also praised for writing the rule for monks with great discretion and clear expression.
In the territory of Lyon, Saint Lupicinus, the abbot of the Virenses, was known.
He, along with his brother Romanus, after leading a very austere hermitic life from youth, became the founder of monasteries and a guide for souls, both being performers of miracles.
After many struggles against the devil and his angels, and after faithfully serving Christ for many years, they knew their labors were ending and their rewards were near.
Lupicinus decided that they should be buried together in a secluded monastery.
Romanus, being of a gentler nature, declined this out of compassion and, with charity preserved, asked to be buried at the entrance of the oratory for the benefit of the poor and especially women in distress.
Initially, the body of Blessed Lupicinus started attracting visitors to the Laconense monastery in the Vesontian territory for reasons that were unclear.
March 22.
In the city of Narbonne, which gave its name to the region of Narbonensis in Gaul, Saint Paul was born.
The blessed apostles ordained him and sent him to the city as a bishop.
It's said that he was the same Sergius Paulus, the proconsul, a wise man, from whom the apostle Paul took his name after converting him to the faith of Christ.
He diligently carried out his preaching duties in the region, became renowned for miracles, and was honored for his confession of Christ, and was buried there.
In Africa, Saturninus and nine others.
March 23.
The holy martyrs Victorian, Frumentius, another Prumentius, and two brothers were all tortured with terrible punishments during the Vandal persecution under the Arian king Henry for their steadfast Catholic faith.
They were gloriously crowned in the regions of Africa.
Also in Africa, Fidelis and twenty others.
In Antioch, Theodore the priest.
In Caesarea, Achatius and Alexander.
March 24.
In Africa, Agapitus and Romulus.
In Mauretania, Secundulus, Verulus, Felix, Saturninus, and many others.
In Rome, Saint Pigmenius the priest.
He raised Julian the Apostate from childhood and also instructed him in holy writings.
When Julian became emperor and turned away from piety, he learned that Pigmenius had buried the bodies of the holy martyrs he had executed.
He ordered Pigmenius, saying: Go where you wish, for your life will not be spared here.
Yet, I acknowledge your services.
Then Saint Pigmenius went to Persia.
After four months, he returned and, while climbing the Sacred Way with a boy asking for alms, he encountered Emperor Julian in a golden chariot.
Seeing Pigmenius from afar, Julian summoned him and said: Glory to my gods and goddesses, because I see you.
To this, Pigmenius, a man of God, immediately replied: Glory to my God Jesus Christ the Nazarene, crucified, because I see you.
At the command of an angry Julian, he was ordered to be thrown into the Tiber River from a bridge.
His body was later found, collected, and buried in the cemetery of Pontian, not far from the saints Abdon and Sennen.
This event is commemorated on March 25.
In the city of Nazareth in Galilee, we remember the Annunciation of the Lord.
Outside the gate of Jerusalem, our Lord Jesus Christ was crucified, revealing many hidden truths of the prophets.
On Mount Moriah, we recall the sacrifice of Isaac.
Also in Jerusalem, the passion of Saint James, the brother of the Lord, who testified to Christ during the Passover celebration to the Jews.
He was thrown from the temple's pinnacle and struck with a fuller's club.
In Rome, Cyrenius, killed by Claudius and thrown into the Tiber, was found on the island of Lycaonia and buried in the cemetery of Pontian.
This is recorded in the passion of Saint Valentine.
In Smyrna, we remember the birth of Saint Irenaeus, bishop, who, during the time of Emperor Maximian under the governor Probus, endured the harshest tortures and was imprisoned for many days.
He was eventually beheaded.
This is observed on March 26.
In Rome, on the Via Lavicana, in his cemetery, we commemorate the birth of Saint Castulus.
As noted in the acts of Saint Sebastian, he was a notary of the palace and a host to the saints.
Captured by persecutors, he was hanged three times.
Persisting in his confession of the Lord, he was thrown into a pit, and a mass of sand was poured over him.
Thus, he achieved the palm of martyrdom and went to Christ.
On the same day, in the Pentapolis of Libya, we honor Bishop Theodore, Deacon Irenaeus, and Readers Serapion and Ammonius.
Also in Smyrna, the birth of Saint Montanus, a priest, who, along with his wife Maxima, was captured and thrown into the river.
Their bodies were found nine miles from the city.
This is commemorated on March 27.
In Jerusalem, we celebrate the resurrection of our Lord Jesus Christ.
In Africa, we remember Romulus, Acutius, Pinarius, Missia, Matutina, and others.
Also, Donatus, Saturninus, and Martianus.
In Egypt, we honor the blessed John the Hermit, a man of admirable holiness.
Filled with a prophetic spirit, he not only performed many miracles but also foretold victories over the cruelty of tyrants to the most Christian Emperor Theodosius.
On March 28th, in Caesarea of Palestine, we remember the birth of the holy martyrs Priscus, Malchus, and Alexander.
During the persecution by Valerian, while living on a small farm near the city, they were offered heavenly crowns of martyrdom.
Inspired by divine fervor for their faith, they voluntarily approached the judge to question his rage against the blood of the pious.
In response, he immediately sentenced them to be devoured by beasts for the name of Christ.
Also in Rome, there was Pope Sixtus, who served for eight years.
He personally buried his accuser Bassus, who died by divine will, using linens and spices, near Saint Peter.
In Chalon-sur-Saône, King Cunderammi of the Franks was a religious man who dedicated himself to spiritual acts.
Abandoning worldly grandeur, he distributed his treasures to churches and the poor.
On March 29th, in Nicomedia, we remember Pastor, Victorin, Saturnin, and Julian.
In Africa, the holy confessors Armogastus, Archimimus, and Satyrus.
During the Vandalic persecution under the Arian King Geiseric, they were distinguished members of the Church of Christ and often criticized the errors of the Arians with Catholic freedom.
They endured many severe punishments and insults for their confession of truth, completing their glorious struggle.
In Burgundy, we commemorate the burial of the blessed Eustasius, abbot and disciple of Saint Columbanus.
He was the father of nearly six hundred monks and shone with holiness of life, also becoming renowned for miracles.
In the city of Pisa, we honor Saint Torpetis, martyr.
On March 30th, in Rome, we remember Quirinus, tribune and martyr under Emperor Trajan.
After following orders to imprison Blessed Pope Alexander and Prefect Hermes, a man's daughter developed a goiter around her neck.
Hearing the prayers of Blessed Hermes and witnessing the miracles the Lord performed through martyrs Alexander and Hermes, he brought his daughter to them for healing.
Blessed Alexander told him, "Take the collar from my neck and place it on her."
When the father did this, by divine will, she was immediately healed. Her name was Balbina.
Consequently, her father Quirinus, along with her, everyone in custody, and their entire household, were baptized.
When the clerk informed Judge Aurelian about this, Aurelian became angry and summoned Quirinus, saying, "I loved you like a son. Yet you mock me, deceived by Alexander."
Quirinus replied, "I have become a Christian. Do you want to kill me? Beat me? Burn me? I will not change. I made all those in prison become Christians, and they refused to leave."
Enraged, Aurelian had his tongue cut out and then hung him on a rack.
When Quirinus did not yield to Aurelian's torture, he ordered his hands and feet to be cut off, and then had him beheaded and thrown to the dogs.
However, Christians retrieved his body and buried it on the Appian Way in the cemetery of Praetextatus.
In the city of Thessalonica: Domninus, Philopolus, Achaicus, Palatinus.
Elsewhere: Victor, the virgin Aquilina.
Aurelian, the deposition of the holy Pastor.
On March thirty-first—in Rome, Saint Balbina the virgin, daughter of the martyr Quirinus.
She often kissed the collar of Blessed Alexander, through which she was healed, but was advised by him to stop kissing it and to seek out the chains of Blessed Peter and kiss them instead.
With great desire and effort, she found them and gave them to the most devout Saint Theodora, sister of Saint Hermes, the prefect and martyr.
Following Blessed Alexander's guidance, Balbina remained in virginity, full of good works. After overcoming the world, she was buried next to her father Quirinus, the martyr.
In Africa, we have the saints Anesius, Felix, Diodulus, Protus, Cornelius, and Valeria, along with their companions.
April. The month of April has thirty days, with the new moon on the twenty-ninth.
April first: In Rome, we remember the birth of the blessed Theodora, sister of the renowned martyr Hermes.
She was taught, baptized, and guided in the Christian faith by the blessed Pope and martyr Alexander.
She was martyred under the rule of Aurelian and laid to rest beside her brother on the Salaria Road, near Rome.
In Armenia, we honor Parthenius, Quintianus, Victor, and Secundus.
On this day, we also remember Saint Venantius, bishop and martyr.
In the Jumnoense region, we celebrate Saint Wiolaricus the confessor, whose tomb is famous for frequent miracles.
April second: At Caesarea in Cappadocia, we commemorate the martyrdom of Saint Theodosia, a virgin.
During the time of Diocletian, at the age of eighteen, she joined the holy confessors in prison willingly.
Captured by Urban, the prefect, she endured torture on a rack, was burdened with iron, and thrown into prison, where by God's power, her bonds were broken.
She was then tied to a rock and cast into the sea but returned unharmed to the shore, and was thrown to wild beasts in the amphitheater, yet remained untouched.
She completed her martyrdom by beheading.
In Africa, we honor the birth of saints Amphianus, Victor, and fourteen others.
In Lyon, France, we remember the burial of Saint Nicetius, bishop and confessor.
His life was marked by miracles, and his precious death was also remarkable for miracles.
April third: In Thessalonica, we remember the holy virgins Agape, Irene, and Chionia under Diocletian.
They were tormented in prison and thrown into the fire, yet remained unscathed after praying to God and surrendered their souls.
In Scythia, in the city of Tomis, we remember saints Evagrius and Benignus.
In Taurominium, Sicily, we honor Saint Pancras.
In Nicomedia, we remember Donatus and Amplianus.
April fourth: In Thessalonica, we commemorate saints Agathon the deacon and Theodulus.
Elsewhere, we remember Paul, Matutinus, Urban, Saturninus, Quintilian, Publius, Victor, Successus, and Julian.
In Milan, we honor the burial of Blessed Ambrose, bishop and confessor.
Thanks to his dedication, among the many signs of teaching and miracles, all of Italy was converted to the Catholic faith during the time of the Arian heresy.
Appointed to this role by the grace of the office, while he was still a catechumen, he was chosen as bishop by a nursing child during the deposition of the albs.
Guided by angelic suggestion, he spoke to his listeners, expelled demons, performed healings, and even raised the dead.
By enduring all kinds of hardships, he truly earned the reputation of being an imitator of the ancient martyrs and apostles.
April 5th - In Thessalonica, the birth of Saint Irene, who, after enduring imprisonment, was struck by an arrow from Count Sisinnius.
Her sisters, Agape and Chionia, also became martyrs under his rule.
All of them were imprisoned by Dulcitius, their predecessor, in a very dark cell filled with pots for baking.
Overcome with lust for them, he sneaked in at night, only to clumsily roll around with the pots, pans, and kettles.
Deprived of his disgraceful intentions by the holy virgins, he became abominable in the eyes of his servants and those around him.
Seeking revenge by approaching the imperial palace, he was instead expelled due to his intolerable filth, oblivious to his state with his eyes metaphorically closed, and was stripped of all remaining honor.
In Egypt, the birth of Saints Martian, Nicanor, and Apollonius.
In Caesarea of Lycia, the birth of Saint Amphian.
In Cilicia, the birth of Saints Tarachus, Andronicus, and Probus, who endured many torments.
After the third interrogation, their bodies were so severely mutilated that they couldn't walk and were carried by soldiers to the amphitheater to be devoured by beasts.
However, none of the beasts could be provoked by anyone, not even by the martyrs themselves, to harm the saints.
Consequently, Maximus, the governor, ordered gladiators to kill the holy martyrs of God with a sword.
After this happened, Maximus left the amphitheater, leaving behind ten soldiers to mix the bodies of the martyrs with those of the gladiators.
Not long after, there was an earthquake accompanied by thunder, lightning, and a mighty storm with heavy rain pouring down.
The guards fled in terror, and some religious brothers hiding nearby, guided by a star, found the bodies of the saints and hid them in a cave in a nearby mountain.
Although little is noted about their long history, it's fitting to recount the end of gladiatorial games on the occasion of those saints killed by the gladiators.
Among the many foolish and sacrilegious customs of the ancients, this one also mocked mortals: the more prominent among them seemed more distinguished if they sent well-fed men into the arena, who after killing either wicked people or even holy martyrs, cruelly perished by mutual wounds.
This folly, which couldn’t be abolished even with the rise of Christianity due to its antiquity, was encountered by a monk from the East who came to Rome for prayer and unexpectedly ran into the gladiators fighting.
Pitying them, he tried to stop the slaughter but was crushed by a shower of stones from the organizers of the spectacles.
Because of his undeserved death, the devout emperor, driven by zeal for God, banned those ill-fated games from being held any longer.
In Alexandria, of Saint Didymus the priest, on April 6th.
In Rome, of Pope and martyr Sixtus, who led the Church for ten years, two months, and one day, and suffered during the reign of Emperor Hadrian.
He decreed that sacred mysteries should only be conducted by sacred ministers, and any bishop summoned to the apostolic see returning to his diocese should not be received unless he brought formal letters of greeting from the apostolic see to the people.
It was established that during the Mass, Holy, holy, holy would be sung.
In Sirmium, we celebrate the feast of Saint Irenaeus, bishop of the same place.
In Africa, it's the feast of Saints Epiphanius, bishop; Donatus, Sixtus, Rufinus, Modestus, and eleven others.
In Nicomedia, the feast of Timothy and Theogenes is observed.
In Pentapolis of Upper Libya, we commemorate the martyrdom of Saint Theodore, bishop, along with many martyrs.
April 7th marks the burial of the very holy man Hegesippus.
He lived near the apostolic times, documenting church history from the Passion of the Lord to his own era, compiling many useful writings for readers.
He composed five books in simple language to accurately portray the character of those whose lives he chronicled.
In Alexandria, we honor the feast of Saint Pelusius, priest.
In Nicomedia, we celebrate the birth of Saint Cyriacus with ten others.
In Scotland, it's the feast of Finian, confessor.
April 8th in Rome marks the burial of Pope Celestine, who led the Church for eight years.
He established that the 150 Psalms of David be sung antiphonally before the sacrifice.
Previously, only the apostolic Epistles and the Holy Gospel were read.
In Tours, we celebrate the feast of Saint Perpetuus, bishop, a man of admirable holiness.
Through his efforts, a temple was completed over the revered bones of Blessed Martin, bishop, and his sacred body was moved from its original burial place to where it is now worthily venerated, following an angelic revelation.
In Africa, it's the feast of Saints Januarius, Macharius, Maxima, Concessa, and many others.
April 9th marks the birth of blessed Prochorus, deacon, one of the first seven, renowned for his faith and miracles, who was martyred in Antioch and rests there.
In Sirmium, we celebrate the birth of seven virgins, who were all crowned together.
We also honor the birth of five virgins.
Elsewhere, we remember Demetrius, deacon, Hilary, and Concessus.
April 10th celebrates the birth of blessed Ezekiel, prophet.
In Rome, we remember the feast of many blessed martyrs, baptized by blessed Pope and martyr Alexander while he was imprisoned, and who were exiled together with him.
All of these people were put on an old ship by the leader Aurelian.
They were taken out to the deep sea, and there, with stones tied around their necks, he had them drowned in the depths of the sea.
In Alexandria, we have the priest Apollonius.
In Antioch, there's Saint Theodore the priest.
In Thrace, the birth of Saint Gaianus is remembered.
In Africa, there are the sixteen martyrs, whose names are known to God.
April 11th.
In Crete, in the city of Cortyna, we celebrate the birth of the blessed bishop Philip.
He was renowned for his life and teachings during the times of emperors Antoninus Verus and Lucius Aurelius Commodus.
In Mauretania, we have Salon, Maximus, and Concessus with other saints.
In Salona, Dalmatia, we remember Bishop Domnio and eight thousand others.
In Africa, we honor Fortunatus, Donatus, and two hundred forty others.
In Rome, we remember Pope Leo, who was the forty-seventh after the blessed Apostle Peter.
He served as bishop for twenty-one years.
He uncovered two heresies and, by sending a delegation to the Catholic leader Martian, gathered a synod of two hundred fifty-six bishops in Chalcedon at the martyrdom site of Saint Euphemia.
There, they explained, according to the Catholic faith, the two natures in one Christ the Lord: human and divine.
They condemned the heretics Eutyches and Nestorius.
April 12th.
In Pergamon, Asia, the birth of the holy Polycarp the bishop, along with Paul, Isaac, and Agathon.
In Rome on the Aurelia Road, at the third mile, in the cemetery of Calepodius, we honor the birth of Saint Julius the pope and confessor.
He suffered tribulations and exile for ten months under Constantius the Arian, son of Constantine.
After his passing, Julius returned to his seat with great glory.
He established that no cleric should conduct any legal matters except in the church.
The record of faith should be gathered by notaries.
Whether it be pledges, documents, donations, exchanges, traditions, wills, allegations, or manumissions, they should be celebrated by clerics in the church.
In the city of Verona, Saint Zeno, a martyr, is celebrated.
Saint Pope Gregory shares one of his miracles: when the Adige River flooded up to the upper windows of the church where his body was buried, the water could not enter, even as a crowd of the faithful gathered inside.
April 13th—In the city of Pergamum in Asia, we remember Saints Carpus, a bishop, Papylus, a deacon, and Agathonice, a noblewoman, along with many others who were martyred for their faith.
Among them was the remarkable Justin, a philosopher.
While dressed in his philosopher's robe, he worked tirelessly for the Christian faith.
He even presented a book against the pagans to Antoninus Pius, his sons, and the senate, unashamed of the cross's disgrace.
Later, he presented a second book to the successors of Antoninus Pius, Antoninus Verus and Aurelius Commodus, defending our religion, and ultimately received the reward of martyrdom for his faithful speech.
In Chalcedon, we honor Saint Euphemia and Eucarpia, who found rest after enduring many tortures.
In Spain, we remember the blessed Hermenegild, whom his father, Leovigild, an Arian and king of the Goths, imprisoned and shackled for his steadfast confession of the Catholic faith.
On the night of the Lord's Resurrection, under his treacherous father's orders, he was struck on the head with an axe, exchanging an earthly kingdom for a heavenly one as both king and martyr.
Blessed Pope Gregory writes about this in his Dialogue.
April 14th—On the Appian Way in Rome, at the cemetery of Praetextatus, we commemorate the birth of Saints Tiburtius, Valerian, and Maximus, under the prefect Almachius.
The first two were beaten with clubs and executed by the sword; the last was scourged with leaded whips until he surrendered his spirit.
In Interamna, we honor Saint Proculus, a martyr, and also Saint Domna, a virgin, crowned alongside her fellow virgins.
At Alexandria, we remember the blessed Fronto, a monk of Nitria, who led seventy monks into the desert with him to devote themselves to divine contemplation, away from the world.
When they ran out of food, the Lord guided a wealthy head of a household to ensure food was sent to his servants who were suffering from hunger.
Although he didn't know where they lived, he was advised by wise friends to send seventy camels loaded with provisions into the desert without any human guidance, trusting that Almighty God would lead them wherever He wished through His providence.
The camels, taking a direct route, reached the dwelling of the holy men through remote and pathless areas.
When the discerning Fronto saw them, he gave thanks to God and, avoiding greed, took half of everything for himself and his companions, sending the other half back to their owner with the camels.
Astonished by the miracle and the benefit, he provided provisions to God's saints in the same way every year.
Sustained by these and the help of other devout people, they continued devotedly in God's service.
April 15th.
—In Persia, in the city of Cordula, the births of the noble Olympias and Maximus.
When Emperor Decius commanded it, they were beaten with clubs, then with leaded whips, and finally their heads were struck with axes until they breathed their last.
In Tuscany, the births of the holy martyrs Maron, Eutyches, and Victorinus.
Along with the blessed Flavia Domitilla, they spent a long exile on the island of Pontia, offering her pious support in her confession of Christ.
Due to the envy and persecution of her fiancé and persecutor Aurelian, whom she had rejected for Christ, they were eventually handed over to Aurelian as servants by Emperor Nerva.
Aurelian divided them among his estates as slaves, ordering them to dig the land during the day and eat meager food in the evening.
When they converted many to the Christian faith and increased the number of believers, Aurelian, filled with rage by the devil, sent people to kill them through various tortures.
Eutyches was ordered to be beaten in the middle of the road until he breathed his last.
The body was taken by the Christian people.
Victorinus, at a place called Cotiliae where sulfurous waters flow, was hung upside down and tortured for three hours.
After enduring this for three days in the name of Christ, he passed away to the Lord.
One day after his burial by order of Aurelian, Christians from Amiternum came and took his body to their territory.
Aurelian also ordered Maron to be crushed by a large stone through his friend, Turgius.
However, under the Lord's protection, they could not harm him at all.
A consul, following Aurelian's orders, eventually killed him.
Christians then took his body and buried it with due honor in the city of Picenum on Mount Aureus.
In Spain, in the city of Zaragoza, the birth of eighteen holy martyrs is remembered: Optatus, Lupercus, Successus, Martial, Urban, Julia, Quintilian, Publius, Fronto, Felix, Ceciliani, Evotius, Primitivus, Apodemius, and the remaining four, all called Saturninus.
April 16th.
In Achaia, in the city of Corinth, the holy martyrs Callistus, Charisius, Leonides, Christiana, Galla, and Theodore were all drowned in the sea.
In Mauretania, Saint Basilia.
In Rome, Pope Anicetus, who served as bishop for eleven years and was crowned with martyrdom during the times of Severus and Marcus, was buried in the cemetery of Callistus.
He decreed that the clergy should not grow long hair according to apostolic instruction.
April 15th.
In Antioch, the birth of the holy martyrs Peter the deacon, Hermogenes, Peter, Fortunatus, and Marcianus.
In Africa, Saint Mappalicus, who was crowned with many others, as the blessed Cyprian wrote in his letter to the martyrs and confessors, saying among other things:
May you now follow this most blessed martyr and other leaders and companions of the same gathering, steadfast in faith, patient in suffering, and victorious in trial, and I both wish and urge you to do so.
May those bound by confession and the fellowship of imprisonment also be united in virtue and receive the heavenly crown.
On April eighteenth, in Mesene, a city of Apulia, we honor the holy martyrs Eleutherius, a bishop, and his mother, Anthia.
Eleutherius, ordained as bishop in Aquileia, first converted his companions Felix and Correnus to Christianity.
Taken to Rome under Emperor Hadrian, he was celebrated for his holy life and miraculous powers.
Despite enduring a bed of burning iron, a grill over a fire, and a pan boiling with oil, pitch, and resin, he remained unharmed when thrown to lions, who were miraculously tamed.
Ultimately, he was beheaded along with his mother.
In Rome, Parthenius and Calocerus.
Also in Rome, Apollonius the senator: under Emperor Commodus, he was betrayed by a slave for being a Christian and wrote a notable book to explain his faith to the emperor, which he presented in the senate.
Nevertheless, by the senate's decree, he was beheaded for Christ, as an ancient law required that Christians brought to judgment could not be released without renouncing their faith.
In the city of Thessalonica, we commemorate the birth of Saint Septimus the deacon.
In Africa, Victor and his companions.
On April nineteenth, in Corinth, we remember the blessed Timon, one of the first seven deacons.
In Armenia, in the city of Melitene, we honor the holy martyrs Hermogenes, Gaius, Expeditus, Aristonicius, Rufus, and Galata, who were all crowned on the same day.
In Caucoliberi, Spain, we celebrate the birth of Saint Vincent the martyr.
On April twentieth, in Rome, we honor Saint Victor, a bishop, who was the thirteenth to lead the Church after blessed Peter for ten years and was martyred under Emperor Severus.
He established that the holy Easter should be celebrated on a Sunday and observed from the fifteenth to the twenty-first of the first month's moon.
Before this, it had been celebrated on the sixth day before the Kalends of April without regard to the day of the week or the moon's phase.
He established that, when necessary under Christian confession, people coming from pagan backgrounds could be baptized in rivers, seas, or springs.
In Rome, the holy martyrs Sulpitius and Servilianus were converted to the faith of Christ through the preaching and miracles of the blessed Flavia Domitilla.
She also inspired their fiancées, Theodora and Euphrosyne, to embrace the hope of eternal life and to remain steadfast in holy virginity.
They were beheaded by the city prefect, Anianus, during Trajan's persecution because they refused to sacrifice to idols.
Christians, taking their bodies, placed them on their estate along the Latin Way, at the second mile marker.
On the same day in Gaul, in the city of Évreux, Saint Marcellus, the first bishop and confessor of that city, was born.
By divine command, he came from Africa with his holy companions, Vincent and Domnius.
They converted a large part of the Maritime Alps to the faith of Christ with their words and remarkable signs, which continue to shine to this day.
The baptistery he built in that city was, by divine power, unexpectedly filled with water on the holy nights of the Easter feast each year, and the grace remained overflowing for the seven days of the same celebration.
His venerable companions, buried in the city of Digne, are also renowned for their glorious miracles.
April twenty-first:
In Asia, we remember Saint Maximinus the martyr, who was brought before the proconsul named Optimus during the reign of Emperor Decius.
When he was compelled by torture to sacrifice to idols and refused, he endured long suffering on the rack and was finally crushed with stones.
In Alexandria, we honor the saints Fortunatus, Arator the priest, Felix, Silvius, and Vitalis, who found peace in prison.
In Rome, Saint Soter, the pope, served as bishop for nine years and was buried in the cemetery of the blessed Callistus.
He decreed that no nun should touch the sacred pall in church or place incense.
In Persia, we celebrate the birth of Saint Simeon, bishop of the royal cities of Seleucia and Ctesiphon.
During the persecution by Saphor, the king of the Persians, he was captured and shackled on the king's orders.
Despite enduring severe hardships and being brought before the king, he bravely and steadfastly testified about the Lord Jesus Christ.
Initially, he was imprisoned for a long time along with one hundred others, including bishops, priests, and clerics of various orders.
After all the others were killed before him, he was finally executed and attained the crown of martyrdom.
This occurred on Good Friday of Holy Week, a time when the annual remembrance of Christ's Passion is observed before the feast of the Resurrection.
Among those who suffered with him were Ustazadis, the king's caretaker and chief of the royal household, and the venerable elders Abdella and Ananias, as well as Pusitius, the chief of the royal craftsmen.
When he saw the elder Ananias trembling under the sword, he confidently exclaimed, "Close your eyes for a moment, old man, and be assured, you will soon see the face of Christ." His daughter, a consecrated virgin, was also killed. This took place on the 22nd of April.
In Rome, on the Appian Way, at the cemetery of Callixtus, the birth of Saint Caius, the pope, is commemorated. Having led the Church for 11 years, 4 months, and 12 days, he was crowned with martyrdom under Emperor Diocletian. His brother, the blessed priest Gabinius, had already achieved his glorious triumph through many sufferings under the same wicked ruler on the 19th of February. He established that anyone deserving to become a bishop should first progress through all the ranks, beginning as a doorkeeper, and then serving as a reader, exorcist, subdeacon, deacon, and priest. He also wrote a very useful book on the Incarnation of the Lord.
Also mentioned is Pope Agapitus, who served in Rome for 11 months. He traveled to Constantinople to meet Emperor Justinian and deposed Anthimus, the bishop of Constantinople, who denied the two natures in Christ, and consecrated Menas, a Catholic, in his place.
In Persia, in the city of Cordula, we remember the birth of the holy priests Parmenius, Helina, and Chrysotelis, along with the deacons Luke and Mark from Babylon.
Notably, the first of them could speak even after his tongue was cut out.
They all endured being stretched on the rack and pulled apart with bonds.
Then, with burning plates applied to their sides, they were scorched and torn with nails, and finally, they were killed by the sword in front of the persecutor Decius.
This is documented in the passion of Saint Lawrence.
Also in Persia, many holy martyrs, by the order of Sapore, king of the Persians, are celebrated on the anniversary of the Lord's Passion throughout the entire region.
They were seized and killed by the sword for the name of Christ.
In this conflict of faith, Bishop Milesius also suffered, known for his holiness and the glory of miracles.
Bishop Acepsimas, along with his priest Jacob, and bishops Mareas and Bicor, with nearly 200 clergy and 50 monks, as well as many consecrated virgins, were martyred.
Among them, the sister of the holy bishop and martyr Simeon, named Tarbuam, along with her maid, were cruelly killed by being tied to stakes and sawn apart.
In Lyon, France, Saint Epipodius, during the persecution of Antoninus Verus, was seized with his dear colleague Alexander, who was meanwhile thrown into prison, after the glorious struggles of 48 martyrs who suffered in the same city.
First, he was beaten with hard punches, then tortured on the rack, and finally completed his martyrdom by beheading on April 23.
In Persia, in the city of Diospolis, we commemorate the passion of Saint George the martyr.
Under Dacian, a very powerful king who ruled over 70 kings, he was famous for many miracles and converted many to the Christian faith, including Alexandra, the wife of Dacian, encouraging her to martyrdom.
After many unheard-of trials, he was ultimately beheaded, completing his martyrdom by shedding his blood.
Although his suffering is recorded among the apocryphal writings, the Church of God still honors his distinguished martyrdom among the crowns of the martyrs.
In Rome, Saint Nabor.
In Alexandria, the martyr Corona.
In Gaul, in the city of Valentia, there were Felix the priest, and Fortunatus and Achilleus the deacons.
They were sent by the blessed Irenaeus, bishop and martyr of Lyon, to preach the word of God.
After converting a large part of the city to the faith of Christ, they were imprisoned by Duke Cornelius and severely beaten with harsh nerve-whips.
Later, with their hands tied behind their backs, their loins and legs were broken, and they were tied to wheels, enduring the bitterness of smoke day and night without cease.
They were stretched on the rack and eventually killed with a sword.
At the monastery of Fontenelle, Saint Wolfram, a bishop renowned for his miracles and teachings.
April 24.
In Babylon, the capital of the Chaldeans, Ananias, Azarias, and Misael, who were renamed Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, were saved from the fiery furnace.
In Alexandria, Victor and Zoticus with many others.
In Africa, Faustinus, Victorinus, and many other martyrs.
At Lugdunum Clavatum, the birth of Saint Alexander the doctor, a citizen of Pergamon.
He was brought out of prison three days after the suffering of Epipodius.
He was beaten so cruelly that his ribs were exposed, and his internal organs were completely revealed.
Then, he was fixed to the crossbeam of a cross and released his blessed spirit.
Thirty-four others suffered with him.
In Britain, the burial of Mellitus the bishop, who was the third to govern the Church of Canterbury after Augustine, the first bishop of the English.
April 25.
At Alexandria, the birth of Saint Mark the Evangelist.
He was a disciple and interpreter of the apostle Peter, and at the request of the brothers in Rome, he wrote the Gospel.
After writing it, he went to Egypt and was the first to proclaim Christ in Alexandria.
Peter also mentioned this Mark in his first letter, symbolically referring to Rome under the name of Babylon: "The church that is in Babylon greets you, and so does my son, Mark."
After establishing and strengthening churches throughout Libya, Marmarica, Ammoniaca, Pentapolis, Alexandria, and all of Egypt, he was eventually captured by the remaining pagans in Alexandria. They saw him holding mass on the holy day, April 24th, and put a rope around his neck, dragging him to the place called Bucolia by the sea under the cliffs where a church was built.
While dragging him, they mockingly said, "Let's drag the ox to Bucolia," referring to his tall stature. From the extreme torture, his flesh fell to the ground, and the rocks were stained with his blood. In the evening, they put him in prison, where around midnight, he was comforted by an angelic visit, then called to the heavenly kingdom by the Lord Himself appearing to him.
In the morning, as he was being dragged to Bucolia, he gave thanks, saying, "Lord, into your hands I commend my spirit," and died, and was buried by religious men in a place of carved stone with honor. He had appointed Anianus as bishop in Alexandria in his place and also appointed other bishops, priests, and deacons for churches far and wide. He suffered in the eighth year of Nero.
In the city of Syracuse in Sicily, the birth of the saints Evodius, Hermogenes, and Callista is commemorated. In Persia, Saint George the martyr is celebrated, according to the calendar of the learned Jerome. His passion is famously observed among the Romans and nearly everyone else on April 23rd, as noted earlier.
I thought it necessary to mention this so that our patriarch Hatto of Mainz, who this year also, from the incarnation of the Lord, received the head of Saint George and another part of his body along with many great relics of saints from the apostolic Formosus, and brought them to his new monastery in Germany. On the feast of Saint George, let him proceed with caution, because many have been accustomed to celebrate his birthday on this day.
The feast of Saint Mark the Evangelist was set by Saint Jerome on the day before April 24th, under the authority of Eusebius of Caesarea.
In Rome, this occasion is known as the Greater Litanies.
As for the reason behind this, we, being barbarians and on the world's edge, are unaware of it, or what might have been established before the Lord's ascension for religious purposes.
If any guilt or impurity was accumulated during indulgent times, it could be cleansed by this three-day fast.
We thought it valuable to share the reason according to our ancestors' tradition.
Saint Avitus, Bishop of Vienne, mentions in a homily about the Rogation Days that these days, observed before the Lord's ascension, were instituted by Mamertus, the bishop of Vienne.
He led the city during a time when it was frightened by many signs.
The city was often shaken by earthquakes, and wild deer and wolves entered through the gates and roamed fearlessly, as he wrote.
Throughout the year, as these events unfolded, the people devoutly awaited God's mercy during Easter, hoping the solemn days would end this terror.
But on the eve of that glorious night, as Masses were being celebrated, the royal palace within the walls suddenly caught fire with divine flames.
Terrified, everyone left the church, fearing the entire city would either burn or the earth would open up.
The holy priest, prostrate before the altar, pleaded for the Lord's mercy with groans and tears.
What more can be said?
The prayer of the illustrious bishop reached heaven and extinguished the fire in the palace with a stream of tears.
As the Lord's ascension approached, as mentioned earlier, he proclaimed a fast for the people, established a way of praying, a sequence of eating, and a cheerful administration of almsgiving.
With the terrors ceasing, the fame of this event spread across all provinces, encouraging priests everywhere to follow the example of the priest's faith.
This litany is celebrated in all churches in the name of God with heartfelt contrition and spiritual humility.
On April 26th, in Rome, we commemorate the birth of Saint Anacletus, pope, who was martyred during Domitian's persecution after two years.
He built a memorial for Blessed Peter and created burial places for bishops.
Ordained as a priest by Blessed Peter, he was initially led to sacrifice to idols but later repented and was beheaded for confessing the true faith.
On the same day, we honor Saint Marcellinus, pope, who led the Church for nine years and four months during the reign of Diocletian and Maximian.
He was beheaded for his faith in Christ by Diocletian, along with Claudius, Cyrenius, and Antoninus, and buried thirty-five days later on the Via Salaria by Marcellus the presbyter and deacons with hymns.
During this time of great persecution, seventeen thousand were martyred within a month.
In Gaul, we commemorate Saint Richarius, bishop and confessor.
On April 27th, in Rome, we remember the birth of Saint Anastasius, pope, the forty-first after Blessed Peter.
He served as bishop for three years and ten days, condemned the Manichaeans in Rome, and decreed that no one from overseas could join the clergy without the signature of five bishops.
In Nicomedia, we honor Saint Anthimus, bishop and martyr, who achieved martyrdom by beheading during Diocletian's persecution for confessing Christ.
Nearly his entire flock followed him as a good shepherd leading the way to martyrdom.
The tyrant, residing in the city, ordered some to be beheaded, others burned with fire, and others placed in boats to be drowned at sea.
The faithful, inspired by God's grace, voluntarily rushed into flames or offered their necks to the swords, as recorded in Ecclesiastical History, Book Seven.
In Tarsus of Cilicia, we remember the birth of Saint Castor.
In Lydia, Genesis, Sodalis, Zotici, Elpidius, and Eutychius. April 28th.
At Ravenna, we remember the birth of Saint Vitalis the martyr, along with Saints Gervasius and Protasius.
Vitalis entered Ravenna as a soldier with the judge Paulinus.
When he saw a Christian named Ursicinus, a doctor by profession and originally from Liguria, sentenced to death after enduring extreme torture, he stepped in.
The place where Christians were executed was known as "at the Palm" due to the ancient palm trees there.
After suffering severe torture, Ursicinus was brought to the Palm to be executed. He was afraid and hesitated. Vitalis called out loudly, saying, "Do not, Ursicinus, the doctor who once healed others, wound yourself with the dart of eternal death. Having come through extreme suffering to the Palm, do not lose the crown prepared for you by the Lord."
Upon hearing this, Ursicinus knelt and urged the executioner to strike, repenting for his fear, thus making himself a martyr of Christ. Immediately after, Blessed Vitalis took his body and buried it within the city of Ravenna, refusing to willingly appear before the judge.
Consequently, he was held by the consul Paulinus, and after being tortured on the rack, he was commanded to be brought to the Palm. A deep pit was dug until it reached water, and he was placed in it face-up, then crushed with earth and stones.
His blessed wife Valeria, while heading to Milan after her husband's death, encountered people sacrificing to Sylvanus. When they urged her to eat from the idol sacrifices after taking her down from her mule, she testified that it was entirely forbidden for her because she was a Christian. She was beaten so severely by them that her people could barely bring her to the city of Milan, and within two days, she passed to the Lord.
At Alexandria, Saint Theodora the virgin, refusing to sacrifice, was handed over to a brothel but was miraculously rescued by God's favor.
As a group of shameless young men gathered at the cell door, a brother named Didymus, full of faith and divine inspiration, donned a soldier's outfit.
He was the first to rush into the brothel and explained to the holy virgin why he was there.
He gave her the soldier's clothes, and he himself dressed in her virgin's attire.
In this way, the virgin left without being recognized and made her escape to the city.
Didymus was brought before the governor, and after boldly explaining everything, he confessed that he was a Christian.
He was executed by beheading and his body was burned.
The blessed virgin, having fled the brothel to preserve her purity, returned to the arena out of a desire for the crown and was executed alongside Didymus, and they were honored together.
In Pannonia, there was Bishop Eusebius, along with Tiballus and Pollion.
In Africa, in the province of Numidia, the saints Manilius, Donatus, Maurilius, Lucian, Victorinus, the virgin Narcia, and seventy-two others.
Also, Lucian with two hundred seventy others.
In Tarsus of Cilicia, Malina with one hundred seventy others and many more.
On April twenty-ninth, in the city of Paphos on the island, the birth of Saint Tychicus, a disciple of the apostles.
In Alexandria, the birth of Saints Germanus, a priest, and Prosdocus, a deacon.
In Perugia, Tuscany, Valentine and Martian.
In Bologna, Vitalis and Agricola.
In Numidia, at the colony of Cirta, the holy martyrs Agapius and Secundinus, bishops.
During the persecution under Valerian, after a long exile in the city, where the pagans' blind fury and military duties tested the faith of the righteous, they became renowned priests and glorious martyrs.
With them suffered the soldier Aemilian, the sacred virgins Tertulla and Antonia, and a certain woman with her twins.
On April thirtieth, in the city of Saintes, the birth of Saint Eutropius, a martyr.
He was consecrated as a bishop by the blessed Clement, the successor of the apostles, and sent to Gaul to preach.
After fulfilling this mission, he was killed by a blow to the head with an axe by rising pagans, who were stirred by envy and did not believe.
In Alexandria, we celebrate the birth of Saint Aphrodisius the priest, along with thirty others.
In Rome, we honor the burial of Bishop Quirinus.
We remember the trials of Saints Marianus and James—Marianus, a lector, and James, a deacon.
Although they had already triumphed over the Decian persecution by confessing Christ, they were captured again with their beloved colleague in the colony of Cirta.
Enduring severe and brutal tortures, Marian was cruelly suspended by his thumbs with heavy weights on his feet.
While the others weakened in prison, they found wonderful comfort in divine revelations.
Later, they were sent to the city of Lambese to face the governor, where they endured a long stay in a prison workhouse but were once again uplifted by divine revelations.
Ultimately, they were executed by the sword alongside many others.
May. The month of May has thirty-one days, while the moon has thirty.
May 1st. This day marks the passing of the prophet Jeremiah.
It's also the beginning of our Lord Jesus Christ's preaching.
Additionally, it's the feast of the apostles Philip and James.
Philip, who converted almost all of Scythia to the faith of Christ, appointed deacons, priests, and bishops there before returning to Asia.
He continued preaching for several years, bringing many to Christ through his dedicated service.
He passed away in the city of Hierapolis in Asia, having extinguished the heresy of the Ebionites, who denied Christ's existence before his incarnation, and he was buried in peace.
James, also known as the brother of the Lord, is said to have been the son of Mary, the maternal aunt of Jesus, and was surnamed the Just.
After the Lord's passion, the apostles immediately appointed him as bishop of Jerusalem.
He was holy from birth.
He never drank wine or strong drink, ate no meat, never shaved, nor anointed himself with oil, nor used a bath.
He alone was permitted to enter the Holy of Holies.
He wore linen garments instead of woolen ones.
When publicly pressured in the council to deny that the Lord Jesus Christ was the Son of God, he boldly declared to the people: "Why do you ask me about the Son of Man? Behold, he sits at the right hand of power and will come on the clouds of heaven."
After being thrown from the pinnacle of the temple, with his legs broken, he still managed to lift his hands to heaven and said, "Lord, forgive them, for they do not know what they are doing," before being struck on the head with a fuller’s club and dying.
This is the one about whom the apostle Paul writes to the Galatians: "I saw none of the other apostles, only James, the Lord's brother" (Galatians chapter one).
The Acts of the Apostles frequently attest to this.
The Gospel according to the Hebrews, translated into Greek and Latin by the blessed Jerome, reports that after the resurrection of the Savior, the Lord came to James the Just and appeared to him.
Jacob had vowed not to eat bread from the moment he drank from the Lord's cup until he witnessed His resurrection.
Then, shortly afterward, the Lord said, "Bring the table and the bread." Immediately, it is added: "He took the bread, blessed it, broke it, and gave it to James the Just, saying, 'My brother, eat your bread, for the Son of Man has risen from the dead.'"
Some believe this is why it is written in Paul's First Letter to the Corinthians that He appeared specifically to him: "Then He was seen by James" (First Corinthians 15).
James led the Church of the Jerusalemites for 30 years, until the seventh year of Nero, and was buried near the temple where he had been cast down.
However, he wrote only one letter, which is included among the seven canonical ones.
In Gaul, in the Vivarais region, Saint Andeolus, a subdeacon, was sent from the East by Saint Polycarp, Bishop of Smyrna and a disciple of the blessed Apostle John, along with the blessed Benignus and Andochius, presbyters, and Thyrsus, a deacon, to preach the word of God in Gaul.
When Caesar Severus learned of their preaching, he ordered Andeolus to be cruelly whipped with thorny rods and thrown into prison.
The next day, seeing that he could not be overcome, he ordered a sword to be made from the hardest wood, in the shape of a cross, and had his head split.
After this was done, his brains were dashed to the ground, and he was gloriously transferred to eternal life.
Likewise, in Jerusalem, there was the passion of Saint Jude, also known as Quiriacus, a bishop to whom the wood of the Lord's cross was revealed, and his mother Anna, who was tortured by all kinds of sufferings.
Also, in Gaul, in the region of Sidonia, at the place of Agaunum, the passion of King Sigismund, son of King Gundewald of the Burgundians.
Seeing that he could not resist the Franks, he fled alone, shaved his head, adopted the religious habit, and devoted himself day and night to fasting, vigils, and prayers.
He was captured by the Franks along with his wife and sons and was drowned in a well.
Afterwards, he was revealed to a certain abbot who buried him with reverence.
He remains well-known for his miracles, especially as those suffering from chills often seek a special remedy from him, and those who faithfully seek it are never left wanting.
On May 2nd, we commemorate the birth of our Holy Father Athanasius, bishop and confessor of Alexandria.
He endured numerous plots from the Arians, particularly from Emperor Constantius.
He spent six continuous years hiding in a dry cistern, never once seeing the sun, while the full might of the empire conspired against him.
He was betrayed by a maidservant of the homeowner who sheltered him, but, saved by divine grace, he was restored to his position through the intercession of Constans, the prince of the Gauls, alongside his brother Constantius.
Again, after the death of Constantius, because of his unwavering commitment to the Catholic faith, he was exiled until the reign of Jovian.
He was then summoned back with honorific and most respectful letters, regaining authority over the churches and restoring his position.
In the fortieth year of his priesthood and beyond, after enduring many struggles and earning many crowns of patience, he passed away peacefully during the reign of Emperors Valentinian and Valens.
He left behind the life of Saint Anthony, the anchorite, written in elegant language and filled with great wisdom, benefiting future generations.
Also, in Alexandria, Saturninus and Neopolis rested in prison.
In Auxerre, there were Optatus the bishop and Sanctianus the priest.
On May 3rd, in Jerusalem, the discovery of the Holy Cross of our Lord Jesus Christ by Queen Helena took place, two hundred thirty-three years after the passion of the Lord, during the reign of Emperor Constantine, her son.
After a long time, it was discovered through divine revelation and confirmed by the resurrection of the dead.
It became visible to the entire world, with one part left in Jerusalem at the site of the Lord's passion, so it wouldn't be far from the East and South.
Another part was taken to Constantinople for his son, making it somewhat closer for the North and West to visit.
This Lord's cross, in its lifeless material, holds a living and undeniably powerful force.
From that time on, it has nearly daily fulfilled the prayers of countless people without experiencing any loss, remaining almost untouched.
It is continually divided among those who take from it and always appears whole to those who venerate it.
It is believed to have received this incorruptible power and indestructible firmness from the blood of the one who, after suffering death, did not see corruption, but instead provided immortality and incorruption to all who believe in him.
On the same day, in Rome, on the Nomentana Way, at the seventh milestone, was the birth of Pope Alexander.
He served as the bishop of the Roman Church, the fifth after blessed Peter, for ten years, two months, and ten days.
Incomparable in holiness and most renowned in faith, he converted a large part of the city's senators to the Lord.
He established that water with salt should be blessed in the homes of the faithful and incorporated the Lord's passion into the preaching of priests when celebrating Mass.
When Emperor Trajan ordered it, Alexander was imprisoned by Aurelian, a commander of the army.
From there, through a heavenly messenger, he was brought to the house of Quirinus the tribune,
where the blessed Hermes, a prefect, was held in custody.
After he healed Quirinus's daughter, Balbina, of a neck swelling in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ,
and gave sight to her nurse, he strengthened Quirinus himself in the Christian faith and freed those who
were imprisoned by baptizing them.
Among these, Quirinus, still a pagan, had also held two very holy priests,
Eventius and Theodolus.
After all these apostolic deeds and many others, Alexander was brought before Aurelian along with the
two aforementioned priests.
He was lifted onto the rack, tortured with claws, and severely tormented
with lamps.
When he did not utter any cries, Aurelian asked him,
"Why are you silent?" Saint Alexander replied, "Because during prayer, a Christian speaks with God."
Then, after he was taken down, Aurelian ordered Eventius and Theodolus to be brought in and asked him,
"Who are these?" Saint Alexander said, "Both are holy men, both are priests."
When he found them steadfast in their confession of Christ, he ordered the furnace to be fiercely heated
and the blessed Alexander and Eventius to be thrown in while tied in the middle. The unyielding Theodolus
willingly leaped into the flames, and when they were not harmed by the fire, Aurelian ordered the most
blessed Alexander to be pierced repeatedly until he died, and the two holy priests to be executed by the sword.
Their bodies were collected by the devout woman Severina, who carefully laid Alexander and Eventius in one
tomb and Saint Theodolus in another.
On the same day, the birth of Saint Juvenal, the bishop, was commemorated.
In Asia, Saint Hermogenes of ancient times. In Auxerre, the burial of the saints Eusebius the priest
and Avitus the deacon. On the same day, Heraclius the martyr. April 2nd.
May second.
In Palestine, in the city of Gaza, Saint Sylvanus, bishop of the city, was martyred during the persecution under Diocletian, along with many of his clergy.
Also, at the mines of Phanessa, the holy forty martyrs were all beheaded together.
In Jerusalem, Bishop Cyriacus, also known as Jude, after discovering the Lord's Cross and growing in the faith of Christ, was appointed bishop of Jerusalem by the blessed Eusebius, bishop of the Roman city.
When Julian the Apostate heard of his fame, as he was heading to the Persian war, where he was divinely slain, he ordered Cyriacus to be brought to him.
When he couldn't sway Cyriacus's confession of Christ with threats or promises, he ordered his right hand to be cut off, saying, "With this hand, writing many letters, he has led many away from offering sacrifices to the gods."
Seeing him remain steadfast and unwavering in Christ, Julian ordered boiling lead to be poured into his mouth, intending to melt his internal organs.
When even this didn't weaken his resolve, he ordered a bronze bed to be brought, and had the holy man laid on it with coals placed underneath, salt and fat sprinkled over him, and beaten with rods from above.
As for his mother, who witnessed all these things steadfastly, not only unafraid but resolute, encouraging her son with maternal affection, the tyrant ordered her to be hung by her hair for nearly three hours, scraped with claws, and have great torches, burning with flames, applied to her sides.
Persisting in thanksgiving amidst such immense torture, she surrendered her unsullied spirit to God.
Then the wicked Julian ordered a deep pit to be dug and called many snake charmers to bring the most wicked serpents and throw them into the pit, and Saint Cyriacus to be thrown in among them.
When the serpents were divinely killed, and Ammon, the snake charmer, believed in the miracle, he was beheaded.
Julian, as was his habit, urged the blessed Cyriacus to renounce the Crucified One.
After Cyriacus appropriately rebuked him, Julian ordered a large pot filled with oil to be heated and for Saint Cyriacus to be thrown into it.
When the pot became so hot that those nearby couldn't bear the heat, the saint said, "Step back, little ones, so that none of you are harmed," and after making the sign of the cross on his forehead, he entered the pot as though it were a bath.
Even then, he remained unharmed, so the tyrant ordered him to be struck in the chest with a sword.
He was struck while voicing his confession and gave up his spirit, reaching Christ in the triumph of martyrdom.
Some say the day of his passion is celebrated here, but according to the Martyrology of Saint Jerome, it is held on May 1st.
On the same day, in Nicomedia, we celebrate Saint Antonina.
She endured severe torture, was hung by the arm for three days, and imprisoned for two years, until she was finally burned by fire on the orders of Governor Priscillian.
On the same day in Lauriacum, near Nicor, we celebrate the birth of Saint Florian.
During the reign of Emperors Diocletian and Maximian, under the cruel Governor Aquilinus, he was ordered to be thrown into the River Anisus with a stone tied around his neck after enduring severe beatings and mutilations.
When the executioners, struck by divine fear, hesitated at the wicked act, a particularly bold and unfortunate young man among them threw him from a bridge into the river, and immediately his eyes burst.
However, a wave carried the body of the holy martyr to a secluded spot against a prominent rock, where an eagle guarded it until it was revealed to a devout woman, who was instructed to transfer his body.
May 5th.
From Bethany, on the Mount of Olives near Jerusalem, we commemorate the ascension of our Lord Jesus Christ into heaven.
The church, built with royal splendor, stands where His incorruptible body last stood and ascended to the heavens.
It's believed that this place is sanctified by the imprint of divine majesty.
Even unbelievers notice it, as it never allows a roof above or marble or any other flooring below.
In the center of the church, the footprints of God and man are always visible in the sand.
Visitors to this place can justifiably burst into prophetic praise:
"We worshiped at the place where His feet stood"
Psalm 132.
In Alexandria, we mark the birth of Saint Euthymius, a deacon resting in prison.
In Thessalonica, the burning of Irenaeus, Peregrinus, and Irene took place.
In Gaul, known as Provence, in the city of Arles, there was Saint Hilary, a bishop who was a great, learned, and distinguished man.
He loved poverty and was diligent in providing for the needy, not only with his piety but also through his own labor.
To help the poor, he even engaged in farming beyond his strength and experience, despite being of noble birth and raised very differently.
He didn't neglect spiritual matters either, as he had the grace to teach and offered correction to all without favoritism.
He particularly worked to correct the Pelagian heresy in the "Collator."
Among his works for the benefit of many, he composed the "Life of Saint Honoratus," his predecessor, with immortal genius.
He passed away during the reign of Emperors Valentinian and Marcian.
In Vienne, Nectarius and Nicetius served as bishops.
In Auxerre, the martyrdom of Saint Jovian, a confessor, is remembered.
May 6th.
In Rome, outside the Latin Gate, the martyrdom of Saint John the Apostle is commemorated.
After being brought from Ephesus, where he usually stayed, to the city of Rome by order of Domitian, the brother of Titus, during the second persecution of Christians, which he carried out after Nero, John was placed before the Senate in a vat of boiling oil at the Latin Gate.
This was done by the wicked emperor, a fierce persecutor of Christians, to weaken the less steadfast members of the Church by removing such a strong leader.
However, the blessed apostle emerged from this terrible punishment unharmed, just as he remained free from physical corruption.
Then, exiled to the island of Patmos, he saw and wrote the Book of Revelation.
To honor his worthy memory and his apostolic steadfastness in the faith and confession of our Lord Jesus Christ, Christians built a church, glorious in his name and memory, at the aforementioned place before the Latin Gate.
This site continues to attract an annual festival gathering on the 6th of May, a tradition that is also observed with reverence in many places of the Catholic Church.
After the death of Domitian, when all his decrees were annulled by the judgment of the Senate, among others, the blessed apostle John, condemned for various reasons and sent into exile, was released by the favor of Emperor Nerva and allowed to return to Ephesus.
There, he brought joy to the Church, which had been distressed and deprived by his absence, and strengthened it forever with his teachings and writings.
Furthermore, due to Domitian's extreme cruelty and wicked deeds, historians report that both the house and name of the Caesars ended with him.
Nevertheless, the ancient custom of calling Roman rulers "Caesars" persisted, especially among barbarian nations.
On the same day is the birth of the blessed Evodius, bishop of the Antioch Church, who was the first to be ordained bishop there by the apostles. Regarding him, Paul himself wrote to the Philippians: "I plead with Evodia and I implore Syntyche to be of the same mind in the Lord Jesus Christ"
from Philippians Chapter Four.
Also, the birth of the blessed Lucius of Cyrene, who was appointed as the first bishop of Cyrene by the holy apostles.
He is mentioned by Saint Luke the Evangelist in the Acts of the Apostles, Chapter Thirteen, among the list of the most perfect men.
Also, Marian and James and many others, according to some.
In Auxerre, the burial of Saint Valerius the Bishop.
On May Seventh, we commemorate the birth of Saint Juvenal the martyr and the most blessed and illustrious servant of God, Flavia Domitilla.
She was the niece of Flavius Clemens the consul, through his sister, and was dedicated to purity with a sacred veil by Saint Clement.
During the persecution under Domitian, in the fifteenth year of his reign, she was exiled to the island of Pontia because of her testimony for Christ, where she endured a long martyrdom with many others.
Eventually, she was transferred to Terracina, a city in Campania, by her fiancé Aurelian, whom she had rejected for Christ and by whose accusation she was exiled.
There, through her teachings and miracles, she converted her foster sisters and fellow virgins, Euphrosyne and Theodora, and then others to the faith of the Lord.
Among these great deeds, the aforementioned Aurelian, her most relentless persecutor, was struck down by divine power.
Luxurius, his brother, set fire to the room where she and the virgins were confined, and she completed her glorious martyrdom during the persecution under Trajan.
The next day, a holy deacon named Caesarius found the bodies of the saints unharmed: they had departed while praying to the Lord, lying on their faces.
This same holy deacon and renowned martyr placed their bodies together in a new sarcophagus and buried them deep in the earth.
Luxurius, as he hurried to a feast, was killed and left swollen as a spectacle and example to the unfaithful when a snake entered his heart through the neck of his garment from a tree branch.
Also in Rome, the burial of Pope Benedict, who served for ten months during the reign of Constantine.
From a young age, he served in the Church and was always a lover of poverty.
He was buried near Saint Peter.
In Nicomedia, we remember the suffering of the holy martyrs Flavius and Augustine, along with the three brothers Marcellinus, Macrobius, and Eutychius.
In Africa, we honor Celerinus, Maximus, Victurius, Potentilla, Faustina, and countless others.
At Autun, we commemorate the burial of the blessed Bishop Placitus.
May 8.
In Milan, we celebrate the feast of Saint Victor.
Born a Moor, he embraced Christianity from an early age.
Even as an older man serving in the imperial army, Emperor Maximian forced him to sacrifice to idols.
Victor bravely stood firm in his faith, enduring imprisonment for six days without food or drink.
He was severely beaten with rods and whips, and even covered with molten lead but remained unharmed.
Ultimately, he achieved glorious martyrdom by beheading.
His body was left for the beasts and birds in the forest called Ulmos, yet it remained untouched for an entire week.
Later, Saint Materno, the bishop, collected and honorably buried him.
Victor was a fellow citizen of the saints Narbor and Felix, who were beheaded in Africa and later brought to Milan along with Januarius and Marinus.
In Constantinople, we remember Agathus the soldier and many others.
In Egypt, we honor Victor and Stephana.
In Saintes, we commemorate the burial of Saint Martin the priest.
In Auxerre, we remember Helladius the bishop.
May 9.
In Axiopolis, we honor Quirillus, Quindeus, and Zeno.
In Tarsus of Cilicia, we remember Aphrodisius.
In Constantinople, we mark the transfer of Saint Timothy.
In Persia, we honor three hundred and ten holy martyrs.
At the town of Nazianzus, we commemorate the burial of the blessed Bishop Gregory, known as the Theologian.
He was noble and educated in Athens, a colleague of the blessed Basil, who later became the bishop of Caesarea in Cappadocia.
Fully dedicating himself to God's service, Gregory had such confidence in his love for Basil that he removed him from the teacher's chair and took him to a monastery.
There, they devoted thirteen years solely to studying the divine Scripture, setting aside all secular Greek books.
Later, he was ordained as a bishop in the town of Nazianzus and dispelled the storm of heresies with the calmness of faith.
When he was called to Constantinople to address certain issues, he willingly took on the responsibility.
After strengthening the Catholic faith there, he returned to his humble position to avoid being seen as someone seeking wealth, and he spent the rest of his life there.
As he grew older and his health declined, he appointed a successor so that someone else could govern the church, allowing him to enjoy a more leisurely old age.
On May 10th the day marking the burial of the blessed prophet Job.
In Rome, there were Falto, Piniana, and Anitia, along with Lucina, his wife, and many other martyrs.
Also in Rome, the elderly priest Calepodius was executed under Emperor Alexander, who ordered Laodicius to kill him and have his body dragged through the city and thrown into the Tiber River on the first of May.
Fishermen found his body, informed Bishop Callixtus, who then wrapped it in linens and buried it with spices in his cemetery on the Via Aurelia, three miles from the city, in a crypt, on May 10th.
Then, Palmatius the consul was beheaded by Alexander along with his wife, children, and forty-two others, including the senator Simplicius, who had recently been baptized through the teachings of Pope Callixtus and Priest Calepodius.
This account is documented in the Passion of the Blessed Pope Callixtus.
On the same day, we commemorate the feast of the blessed martyr Gordian, who suffered under the rule of the impious Emperor Julian.
When the tyrant ordered Gordian, his deputy who was still a pagan, to carefully examine the priest Januarius to see if he could turn him away from the Christian faith, the holy Januarius instead converted Gordian, along with his wife Marina and their household, totaling fifty-three or more people, and baptized them all.
Hearing this, the wicked Julian, filled with anger, condemned the holy priest Januarius to exile and placed Gordian in public custody, entrusting him to a man named Clementian, whom he had appointed as his deputy.
Additionally, he forced Gordian's wife Marina into labor at Aquas Salvias.
When Clementian realized he couldn't sway Gordian from his faith, he ordered Gordian to be beaten with lead weights and then beheaded, and his body to be thrown before the temple of Apollo.
When the Christians heard of this, they retrieved his body under the cover of night and placed it about one mile from Rome in a crypt in the cemetery of Praetextatus, where the body of the blessed martyr Epimachus had already been buried.
It is said that he was one of the seventy disciples of the Lord Jesus Christ, on the ninth of May.
The martyrdom of the holy Evellius, once an advisor to Emperor Nero, is also noted.
Witnessing the steadfastness of the Christians and their martyrdom, especially the patience of the holy Torpetis and the miracles through him, he believed in Christ and suffered for Him as well.
In Rome, on the Via Salaria, at the twenty-second mile marker, Saint Anthimus.
In Africa, Majolus, Victorinus, Fortunatus, and many others.
In Asia, the birth of the holy Demetrius and Thaddeus.
In Vienne, the blessed bishops Martin and Maternus.
We note that Maternus instituted solemn litanies before the Ascension of the Lord due to impending disasters.
The burial of Nepotian, a priest and nephew of Bishop Heliodorus through his sister, is remembered for the epitaph's consolation written by Saint Jerome, turning the world's attention to the mourning and lamentation for its evils and calamities.
This is commemorated on May twelfth.
In Rome, at the cemetery of Praetextatus, we remember the holy brothers Nereus and Achilleus.
They were eunuchs of the blessed Flavia Domitilla and endured a lengthy exile with her on the island of Pontia for their faith in Christ.
Later, under Aurelian, Domitilla's fiancé, who she had rejected for the love of Christ, they were subjected to severe beatings and handed over to Moninius Rufus, the consul.
Despite being tortured with the rack and flames to force them to sacrifice, they remained steadfast, declaring they had been baptized by the blessed apostle Peter, and refused to sacrifice to idols.
They were then beheaded.
Their bodies were taken by their disciple Auspicius, caretaker of the holy virgin Domitilla, and buried in the sand crypt on the Ardeatine Way, one and a half miles from the city wall.
Also commemorated on the Aurelia Way, at the second mile, is Saint Pancras the martyr.
At just fourteen years old, he completed his martyrdom under Diocletian by beheading.
His venerable body was secretly taken at night by the distinguished woman Octavilla, embalmed with spices, and buried.
On the same day, we remember the blessed Denis, uncle of Saint Pancras.
Through his diligence, Pancras was baptized, strengthened in the fear of God, and inspired for martyrdom.
Denis, beloved and worthy of God, was peacefully rewarded with heavenly honors at the end of his life.
We also recall the martyrdom of the noble virgin Sotheris under Emperor Diocletian.
Alongside her, the martyrdom of Saints John, Achillas, Moses, Aphroditius, and others, totaling five hundred and four.
In Cyprus, we honor our holy father Epiphanius, bishop of Salamis.
May thirteenth marks the birth of Saint Mary at the Martyrs.
The reason for this feast is significant: Under Emperor Phocas, blessed Pope Boniface dedicated a church to the blessed Mary ever virgin and all the Martyrs, after cleansing the old Pantheon temple of idolatry.
The most sacred day of its dedication is celebrated in Rome on May 13th.
The festival of all Saints is observed with great religious devotion worldwide on November 1st.
On that same day, there's a commemoration for Saint Servatius, bishop of the Church of Tongeren.
During the time when the Huns were ravaging Germany, he was warned by divine revelation to move to the village of Maastricht to avoid the destruction of his city and Church.
There, he passed away and was buried in the middle of the public road.
To demonstrate his merit to the people, while everything around was covered in snow during winter, his tomb remained uncovered until a basilica was built over it, thanks to the efforts of the citizens and his successor, Munolf.
In Auxerre, the burial of Saint Marcellianus, bishop.
In Alexandria, the commemoration of Aphrodisius, Agrippa, and many martyrs.
In Pollentia, the passion of Saints Victor and Saturninus.
On May 14th, in Egypt, the burial of our holy Father Pachomius.
He was notable for his apostolic grace and was the founder of monasteries in Egypt.
He wrote the monastic Rules, which he learned through the dictation of an angel, and also about the timing of Easter.
In Syria, under Emperor Antoninus and with Sebastian as the leader of Alexandria, the birth of Saints Victor and Corona occurred.
Victor was a soldier from Cilicia.
During his confession of faith, Sebastian ordered Victor's fingers to be crushed and pulled from the skin, then to be thrown into a furnace, where he remained unharmed for three days.
He was then ordered to drink poison but did not die; instead, he converted the poisoner to faith.
Then, it was ordered to remove the nerves of his body and pour boiling oil on his private parts.
After this, burning torches were applied to his sides while he was suspended.
Then vinegar and lime were mixed together and poured into his mouth.
His eyes were then gouged out.
He was hung upside down for three days.
Even while still breathing, the judge ordered him to be flayed.
At this time, Corona, who was the wife of a certain soldier, began to praise Saint Victor for the glory of martyrdom.
As she did so, she saw two crowns fall from heaven, one sent to Victor and the other to herself.
As this was announced to everyone listening, she was seized by the leader.
They ordered two palm trees to be bent toward each other, and Corona was tied to them with hemp ropes by her hands and feet.
When the trees were released, Corona was torn in two.
She was just 16 years old.
Then Victor was also beheaded, and having triumphed in all things, he received the crown of everlasting life and the palm of martyrdom, together with Corona.
In Asia, blessed Maximinus.
In Milan, Victor, Nabor, Felix, and Rusticus.
Also, 400 saints who suffered with Saint Cyriacus.
In Africa, Secundianus and many martyrs.
May 13.
In Spain, the birth of the blessed confessors Torquatus, Ctesiphon, Secundus, Indaletius, Caecilius, Hesychius, and Euphrasius.
They were ordained as bishops in Rome by the holy apostles and sent to Spain, which was still entangled in pagan errors at that time, to preach the word of God.
When they arrived at the city of Acci and were taking a brief rest from their journey, they sent disciples into the city to buy food.
Soon, a crowd of pagans, who were celebrating a festival for their gods, pursued them to the river.
There, a bridge of remarkable size and strength had been built, and as the saints were crossing, by the will of God, it collapsed completely with the entire crowd of pursuers.
Terrified by this miracle, others followed the example of a certain great lady, Luparia, who, divinely inspired, received them kindly and believed, abandoning their idols and believing in Christ the Lord.
After this, they preached in different cities, converting countless multitudes to the faith of Christ.
Torquatus rested in Acci, Ctesiphon in Vergium, Secundus in Abula, Indaletius in Urci, Caecilius in Iliberis, Hesychius in Carcesa, and Euphrasius in Illiturgis.
To this day, the illustrious miracle remains, in memory of their precious deaths.
For on the same feast day in the aforementioned city of Acci, an olive tree miraculously blooms and bears ripe fruit at the tomb of Saint Torquatus.
On the island of Chios, we have the story of Saint Isidore the martyr.
It's said that in his basilica, there's a well where he was thrown.
Those who drink from this well, especially if they are possessed or suffering from fever or other ailments, often find healing.
In Lampsacus, we remember the martyrdom of Saints Peter, Andrew, Paul, and Dionysia.
In Sardinia, there's Simplicius.
On May 16th—In Isauria, we honor Saints Aquilinus and Victorianus.
In Auxerre, we commemorate the martyrdom of Saint Peregrine, the first bishop of that city.
In the city of Piceno, we remember Florentius and Diocletian.
At Ephesus, there were Miogenes, Gaianus, and Jovinus.
In the city of Cortina, Vincent and others are remembered.
At Château-Thierry, the burial of Fidulius the priest is celebrated.
In the district of Fréjus, in the village called Calidianus, Saint Maxima the virgin, who was renowned for many virtues, peacefully passed away.
On May 17th—In Tuscany, in the city of Pisa, we celebrate the birth of Saint Torpes the martyr during the reign of Emperor Nero.
Initially a high-ranking official serving Nero, he was baptized by the blessed priest Antoninus and taught the faith of Christ.
When Nero discovered he was a Christian, he handed him over to a relative, Satellicus, to force him to sacrifice.
Yet, strengthened by the Spirit of God, the blessed man remained unwavering in his faith.
Satellicus had him beaten and tied to a column, whipping him until blood flowed.
Suddenly, while the martyr was being beaten, the column fell, crushing the judge and fifty men with him.
Then, seized by the officials, he was placed on a wheel and thrown to wild beasts by Satellicus's son, but he remained unharmed.
Seeing his steadfastness and virtue, a counselor of Nero named Evellius came to believe in Christ, was baptized, and was soon beheaded in Rome, earning the crown of martyrdom.
Blessed Torpes, on the order of Sylvius, was taken outside the city of Pisa and completed his martyrdom by beheading on April 29th.
His feast and the gathering of citizens are celebrated on May 17th.
It is said that a massive machine, constructed by Nero, the enemy of God, in imitation of the heavens, was cast into the river Auxarum through his merits and prayers, never to be seen again.
In Alexandria, we commemorate Victorius and Basilius.
In Rome, we remember blessed Parthenius.
In Levidunum, we honor Heraclius, Paul, and others.
Also, the burial of blessed Praeandinus the confessor is remembered.
On May eighteenth—in Alexandria, we commemorate Potamon, Hortasius, and Serapion, the priests.
Also, in Egypt, we remember Dioscorus the reader, who endured many tortures from the governor, including having his nails gouged out and his sides burned with torches.
However, the brightness of heavenly light frightened the servants, causing them to fall down.
Ultimately, he completed his martyrdom after being scorched with burning metal sheets.
In Constantinople, we commemorate Hesychius and Eustachius.
On May nineteenth—in Rome, we celebrate the birth of Saint Pudentiana the virgin, daughter of Pudens, a disciple of Saint Paul the Apostle, from a distinguished lineage.
Her mother was Sabinella, sister of Praxedes.
Their devout father, Pudens, taught them in all aspects of Christian religion and dedicated them as virgins to Christ.
After their father's death, they grew in piety, serving the Lord day and night with hymns and prayers along with their household.
The blessed Pius, bishop of Rome, baptized the entire family, confirming them with anointing and daily exhortation.
The blessed virgins of Christ, after numerous struggles and tending to many martyrs' burials, dedicated all their wealth to the care of the poor, and faithfully committed to Christ, finally moved from earth to the heavenly realms.
Pudentiana was laid to rest on May nineteenth in the cemetery of Priscilla, on the Via Salaria.
Praxedes followed on July twenty-first.
They maintained the purity of their baptism, received in Christ from the apostles, until the end of their lives.
Also in Rome, we remember the birth of saints Calocerus and Parthenius, eunuchs of Decius the Emperor's wife.
When they refused to sacrifice to idols, both the head of the chamber and the chief scribe were executed by Decius and buried by Christians near the Appian Way.
In Alexandria, Saint Irenaeus, the deacon.
In Africa, Saints Quintus, Primulius, Salustius, and many other martyrs.
On May 20th, in Rome, on the Via Salaria, we remember the birth of Saint Basilia, a virgin and martyr of Christ.
She was of royal lineage and engaged to a distinguished man named Pompeius.
Through the blessed Eugenia and God's holy men, Protus and Hyacinth, she converted to Christianity.
Her fiancé accused her of being a Christian before Emperor Gallienus, who was then a fierce persecutor of the Church.
He decreed that she must either return to Pompeius or face death by the sword.
When confronted, she declared that her true fiancé was the King of Kings, Christ, the Son of God.
After making this declaration, she was executed by the sword.
In the city of Nemausus in Gaul, the martyrdom of Saint Baldelius occurred.
He was captured by pagans during their sacrifices but refused to renounce his faith in Christ.
Despite beatings and torment, he remained steadfast and achieved martyrdom, shining brightly through numerous signs.
At Bourges, the burial of Austregisilus, a bishop and companion.
On May 21st, in the city of Caesarea in Mauretania, we commemorate the birth of Saints Timothy, Pollius, and Eutychius, deacons who spread the word of the Lord and were honored to be crowned together.
At Caesarea in Cappadocia, we remember the saints Polyeuctus, Victorius, and Donatus.
In Britain, Timothy the deacon is commemorated.
At Auxerre, the burial of the blessed Valis, a priest, who inspired the name Valens for our people.
On May 22nd, in Rome, we celebrate the birth of Saints Faustinus, Timothy, and Venustus with their companions.
In Corsica, we honor Saint Julia, who was crowned with the punishment of the cross.
In Africa, we remember Castus and Aemilius, who completed their martyrdom through the fire of passion.
Blessed Cyprian wrote about them in his book concerning the Fallen.
In Auxerre, we remember the burial of the blessed Helena, a virgin.
On May 23rd.
At Langres, we remember the martyrdom of Saint Desiderius, the bishop.
When he saw his people being devastated by the army of the Vandals, he went out to plead with their king on their behalf.
He was immediately ordered to be killed and willingly offered his neck for the people entrusted to him.
Struck by the sword, he departed to Christ.
Soon after, his attacker was struck with madness and died.
This blessed martyr was buried in a basilica within the city walls.
The faithful people, entrusted to him by Christ, ensured this was done with great love and devotion to protect the citizens, against the terrible custom of some who believed that a city is for the living, not for the dead.
Several others from his flock suffered with him and were buried in the same city.
On the same day, in Vienne, we celebrate the birth of Saint Desiderius, the bishop of the same city.
He suffered in the Lyon region, in the village of Prisciniacum, over the river Calaronus.
Now, he is buried and honorably preserved in the church of Vienne.
Since the venerable Father Ado, the bishop of that church in our time, thought it unnecessary to say anything special about him, as he was well-known to all, we, according to what that apostolic man wrote in the year eight hundred seventy, in the third indiction, through the most holy man, Berold, a priest native to those places but now serving Christ in the castle of Zurich, with the relics of the holy martyr Desiderius and other holy pledges, have taken care to briefly convey some things about him to those unaware of these matters.
Brunichildis, the most immoral queen, was proud of her wealth from Spain and was corrupted by the poison of Arianism and all vices.
After she expelled the chosen travelers, pilgrims of the world but citizens of the saints and household of God, namely Columbanus and his disciples, including our prominent Gallus, because they could not tolerate her crimes, from the borders of the Franks, Saint Desiderius, without their support, no longer tried to correct a wandering sheep but an untamable beast.
For his good deeds, he was sent into exile.
There, for four years, though weary from various labors, he was continually supported and relieved by the grace of God, which accompanied him everywhere.
Not only did he lack nothing necessary, but he also provided abundantly to all who sought him with devoted kindness.
A man, completely afflicted with leprosy, was restored to health by the touch of the holy man, in the presence of the people.
A lamp, which he had lit with his own hand upon his first entry to the island where he had been exiled, burned without failing throughout that time, demonstrating the holiness of the servant of God to the inhabitants.
Its oil restored complete health to many who were sick.
A small vessel of wine, which his minister carefully preserved for refreshing the poor of Christ, was feared to have been emptied by the many who came by his order, yet was joyfully found refilled by divine generosity.
When he was long desired by his fellow priests and returned to his seat, he did not allow the fountain of evil to flow freely but tried to contain it within lawful boundaries.
However, like a raging river, Brunichildis exceeded all limits of justice.
She committed him, the defender of truth, to the workers of iniquity and ordered him to be taken to the city of Lyon, supposedly for a council, but in reality for punishment.
While some pretended not to notice the killing of the man of God, others, even more cruel, ended his suffering by first striking him severely on the head with a stone while he was praying.
Then they pierced his neck with a sharp stake, releasing him from this miserable life through extreme cruelty.
Saint Desiderius suffered without being accused of any crime, but he was hated by those guilty of wrongdoing.
On the mentioned day, in the village of Prisciniacum, during the reign of Emperor Maurice and King Theuderic of the Burgundians, he was killed at the instigation of Brunhilda—not a queen but a harlot—with the support of Counts Betto, Ephan, and Gasifred.
In the time of his successor Etherius, he was moved to Vienna with great honor.
Outside the city, in the church of the most blessed apostles Peter and Paul, he was buried among his predecessors, martyrs, and confessors on February 11th.
He continues to appear each day with signs and miracles and lives on.
On the same day, in Spain, Epictius and Saint Basil were remembered.
In Africa, Quintus, Lucius, and many others were honored.
May 24th marks the birth of Saint Manaen, foster brother of Herod the Tetrarch, a teacher and prophet, who rests in grace under the New Testament at Antioch in Christ.
Also remembered is the most blessed Joanna, wife of Chuza, Herod's steward, mentioned in the Gospel of Luke chapter eight, verse three.
In the Roman port, Saint Vincent the martyr is celebrated.
In the city of Nantes in Gaul, the passion of the holy brothers Donatian and Rogatian is commemorated.
They were imprisoned in chains by an impious governor and confined in a prison workshop.
When brought out, as they could not be forced to deny the name of Christ, they were suspended on a rack and tortured for a long time.
When even this did not sway them to consent to idols, they were finally martyred, having their necks pierced by a soldier's lance, and their heads were cut off by a sword.
Because they were unexpectedly summoned to the governor's court due to a common accusation, Rogatianus couldn't undergo baptism.
I thought it was not just useful but necessary to share what Augustine, the very cautious Church teacher, wrote about this:
"Those who are to be initiated into the sacraments of baptism," he says, "typically first renounce the devil and all his works and pomp. Then, after confessing the one true God—the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit—they are either immersed in water or sprinkled with it.
Similarly, martyrs, who have rejected and renounced idols for the same confession, are plunged into fire or even water, or they are sprinkled with their own blood.
It is customary for those baptized to be anointed with sacred chrism and confirmed by the invocation of the Holy Spirit.
Without the same Spirit's anointing, martyrs wouldn't approach their struggles, nor would they steadfastly endure various tortures.
Baptized and faithful individuals are incorporated into the same by receiving the body and blood of the Lord, and when martyrs suffer for the Lord, they become His body.
Therefore, martyrs obtain all ecclesiastical sacraments more perfectly, as they are taken from this miserable life immediately after receiving them without any contamination.
On the same day, in Istria, the feast day of Saints Zoellus, Servulus, Felix, Sylvanus, and Diocles is celebrated.
On May 25th, in Rome, on the Nomentan Way, in the cemetery of Praetextatus, we observe the feast day of Saint Urban, pope and martyr, whose teachings during Alexander's persecution led many to be crowned with martyrdom.
He decreed that Christians should not reject any food that is reasonable and human.
In Milan, we commemorate the feast day of Saint Dionysius, bishop and confessor.
He was condemned to exile in Cappadocia for his Catholic faith by Emperor Constantius, an Arian, and there he passed away.
The relics of his body were received by Saint Basil, bishop of that city, and were buried with due honor by Saint Ambrose.
Some say he was exiled to Armenia, in the city of Reditium, where he died.
However, he was later moved to Milan by Saint Aurelius, the bishop of that city.
It's believed that Aurelius, who fell ill and died there, was buried in the same tomb as Saint Dionysius, just as they had agreed in life.
In Rome, during the time of Pope Eleutherius, who was bishop for 15 years, he received letters from Lucius, the king of the Britons, asking to become a Christian under his guidance.
Timothy, a holy man, reports that Lucius, having rejected worldly pursuits, traveled freely and unburdened.
He is thought to have converted part of the Bavarians and all of Rhaetia, located in the Alps, to Christianity through his miracles and preaching.
The tomb of the one resting in Rhaetia, whether it be the former king or a servant of God, is famous for frequent displays of virtue.
On the same day, in Moesia, in the city of Dorostorum, we honor the birth of the holy martyrs Pasicrates, Valention, and two others who were crowned together.
On May 26, we celebrate the birth of Saint Quadratus, a disciple of the Apostles.
Appointed as bishop of Athens in place of the blessed Publius, he gathered the Church, which had been dispersed by great fear, through his faith and diligence.
When Hadrian spent the winter in Athens, visiting Eleusis and initiating many of the sacred rites of Greece, it allowed those who hated Christians to harass them without the emperor's command.
Quadratus presented him with a book composed for our religion, full of reason and faith, worthy of apostolic teaching.
He demonstrated the antiquity of his age, claiming to have healed many who had been afflicted by various calamities in Judea during the time of the Lord.
He was renowned, along with the daughters of Philip, for his prophetic grace.
In Africa, on the feast of Saint Quadratus the martyr, sermons by Saint Augustine are known to have been delivered.
In Rome, the priest Symmitrius and twenty-two others were executed by order of Emperor Antoninus for their faith in Christ.
Their bodies were gathered by the blessed Praxedes at night and buried in the cemetery of Priscilla.
In Todi, Tuscany, there were Felicissimus, Heraclius, and Paulinus.
In the territory of Auxerre, Saint Priscus was martyred before a large crowd.
In Britain, Saint Augustine, bishop and confessor, passed away.
He was sent by the blessed Pope Gregory as the first to preach the Gospel of Christ to the English people, and he rested in peace, renowned for his virtues and miracles.
On May 27th—In Alexandria, the birth of the saints Aquilus the priest, Evangelus, and twelve others.
In Tomis, Elijah, Lucian, Zoticus, Martial, Victor, and Maurinus were born.
In Sardinia, Salustian was born.
In Moesia, in the city of Durostorum, Saint Julius was born.
During a time of persecution, he was a veteran and retired soldier.
He was captured by officials and brought before Governor Maximus.
Refusing to sacrifice to idols and steadfastly confessing the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, he was sentenced to death.
As he was led to the place of execution, a soldier named Hesychius, who was also detained for his faith in Christ, asked him, "Remember me, for I will follow you soon."
He also asked him to greet Pasicrates and Valentine, servants of God, who had already preceded them to the Lord through their good confession.
Julius, kissing Hesychius, said, "Brother, hurry to come; those you greeted have already heard your message."
Then, having received a cloth, he covered his eyes and accepted the palm of martyrdom as the sword struck.
In the city of Orange in Gaul, Saint Eutropius, bishop, was known for his virtues and miracles, which were eloquently described by Bishop Verus.
On May 28th—In Sardinia, the martyrdom of Saints Aemilius, Felix, Priamus, and Lucian.
In Rome, the birth of Saint Pope John.
Because he was orthodox and had been warmly welcomed by Justin, the orthodox emperor, during his visit to Constantinople, Theoderic, the Arian king, detained him on his return to Ravenna and led him to his death along with other equally Catholic men.
Saint Gregory mentions him in the Book of Dialogues.
His body was moved from Ravenna and buried in the Basilica of Saint Peter the Apostle on May 28, with Olibrius serving as consul.
At that time, King Theoderic also killed two distinguished senators and former consuls, Symmachus and Boethius.
Theoderic died suddenly on the ninety-eighth day after Pope John passed away and was thrown into Vulcan’s pot, never to be seen again.
Also, in the city of Paris, we remember the deposition of Bishop and Confessor Germanus.
He was born to noble parents and faced numerous malicious plots, but divine grace protected him.
Not only did he escape alive and unharmed, but he also grew in strength, virtues, and wisdom to the point that he was ordained a priest by Saint Nectarius and reluctantly appointed abbot of the monastery of Saint Symphorian.
In his leadership, he pleased both divine judgment and human decision to such an extent that he received the keys to the city gate of Paris, first in a vision from the Lord and later through the people's election to the episcopate.
He administered his office with authority, and following the example of Blessed Martin, he maintained the purpose and virtue of a monk.
Therefore, living in the flesh but seeking the heavens in spirit, he appeared similar to Martin in all aspects through the display of miracles, and at the age of eighty, he passed away to Christ, called by Him, full of holiness.
On May 29, in Rome, on the Via Aurelia, we remember the birth of Saint Restitutus.
On the Via Tiburtina, the seven Germans.
At Iconium in the province of Isauria, Saint Conon and his son were martyred under Emperor Aurelian, with Judge Domitian.
Renowned for their faith, when presented to the judge with his twelve-year-old son, they manifested the Holy Spirit dwelling in them through true confession.
First, they were placed on a hot iron, then on a gridiron with coals underneath, and oil was poured over them.
Then, thrown into a frying pan, they endured everything in the name of Christ.
Afterward, they were suspended, and with a strong fire applied below, their hands were crushed with a hot hammer as they praised the almighty God while giving up their spirit.
On the same day, in the region of Anagnia, near the city of Trento, the martyrdom of Saints Sisinnius the Deacon, Martyrius the Reader, and Alexander the Doorkeeper took place.
Sent by the blessed Vigilius, the Bishop of Trento, to preach in nearby areas, they converted many to the faith of Christ.
However, those who preferred to remain in the error of paganism killed them in various ways.
The blessed Sisinnius, along with the others, was killed after prolonged torture, struck on the head with a brass trumpet, and pierced with axes, lying near the threshold of the church.
Saint Martyrius was also wounded in the head with axes and pierced with stakes, giving up his spirit.
Then, the pagans took the bodies of Saints Sisinnius and Martyrius, along with Saint Alexander, who was still half-alive, to the altar of Saturn, where a large fire was burning, intending to burn them.
They beat Saint Alexander with whips and, unable to force him to sacrifice to idols, threw him alive into the fire, completing his martyrdom and receiving the palm of glorious suffering.
After their death, a shadow covered the entire region, accompanied by frequent lightning strikes, so much so that even the impious confessed this happened because of the saints.
When the relics were later received with great devotion by the people of Milan, a blind man from the Dalmatian coast, divinely inspired, came and, upon touching the shrine, regained his sight, as the blessed Paulinus writes in the Life of Saint Ambrose.
In Trier, the burial of Saint Maximinus the Bishop took place.
His priestly garments were found incorrupt in a bronze urn up to our time, or rather the time of the Normans, as a testimony to his holiness.
Saint Athanasius, while fleeing from Constantius's persecution, was welcomed with honor.
However, because some people, either out of fear or blasphemy, were misinterpreting his flight, I felt it was important to share what the devoted steward of the Church, Augustine, thought, using his own words.
Augustine addressed this in a letter to Honoratus, a bishop who asked for guidance on whether bishops should flee their posts during times of persecution:
In your letter, you ask: If we stay in the Churches, how will we help ourselves or the people?
Men will fall before our eyes, women will suffer, churches will burn, and we will face torture when they demand what we don't have.
Augustine replied: God can indeed listen to the prayers of His people and prevent these feared events.
Yet, because of these uncertainties, we shouldn't abandon our duty, as without it, the people face certain destruction—not in this life, but in the next, which requires much greater care and attention.
If these feared evils were certain to occur in the places we are, then everyone we need to stay for would flee first, freeing us from the need to stay.
No one would suggest that ministers should remain where there are no longer people to serve.
Some holy bishops from Spain fled after part of their congregations had already fled, been killed, besieged, or scattered by captivity; but many more stayed, enduring the same dangers for those who remained.
If some left their congregations, we say this should not be done: for they were not guided by divine authority but were either misled by human error or overcome by fear.
Why do they believe they should follow commands without thinking critically, especially when reading about fleeing from city to city, and not avoiding the hired hand who runs away at the sight of the wolf because he doesn't care for the sheep?
Why don’t they try to understand these two true statements of the Lord in a way that shows they are not contradictory?
How can this be understood unless we consider, as I’ve mentioned before, that Christ’s ministers should leave places where they’re persecuted if there’s no Christian community to serve?
Or even if there is a community, and others can fulfill the necessary ministry without the need to flee?
Just as the Apostle was lowered in a basket and escaped when specifically targeted by the persecutor, while others there didn’t face the same necessity, so the ministry to the Church should not be abandoned.
Just as Saint Athanasius, the Bishop of Alexandria, fled when Emperor Constantius sought to capture him, leaving the Catholic community in Alexandria supported by other ministers.
But when a community remains and ministers flee, withdrawing their ministry, isn’t that a disgraceful escape like that of a hired hand who doesn’t care about the sheep?
The wolf arrives, not as a human, but as the devil, who often convinces the faithful to become apostates when they lack the daily ministry of the Lord’s body.
The weak will perish, not because of your knowledge, but because of your ignorance, brother, for whom Christ died.
As for those who aren’t mistaken but are overcome by fear: why don’t they, with the Lord’s mercy and help, bravely face their fears to prevent far more serious evils from occurring?
Let this happen where the love of God burns, not where worldly desires smolder.
For love says: Who is weak, and I am not weak?
Who is led into sin, and I do not burn with indignation?
First Corinthians Chapter 11.
But love comes from God.
Let us pray, then, that it is given by Him who commands it.
Through this, may we fear more that Christ's flock is harmed by spiritual wickedness in their hearts, rather than being physically slain, wherever, whenever, with whomever, and by whatever kind of death they are destined to die.
Let us fear more that, with a corrupted inner sense, the purity of faith is lost, rather than women being violently assaulted in the flesh.
Physical violence does not violate chastity if the mind remains intact; it is not violated in the flesh when the sufferer's will does not disgracefully use the body, but endures what is done without consent.
Let us fear more that the living stones are neglected and extinguished, rather than seeing earthly buildings of stone and wood set on fire before us.
Let us fear more that the members of the body of Christ, deprived of spiritual nourishment, are killed, rather than our own bodies' members being tormented by the enemy's assault.
Not because these things shouldn't be avoided when possible, but because they should be endured when they can't be avoided without impiety.
Unless perhaps someone argues that it isn't impious for a minister to withdraw necessary piety when it's most needed.
Do we not consider, when faced with these extreme dangers and no way to escape, the rush within the Church from all genders and ages?
Some demand baptism, others seek reconciliation, and some even seek penance itself, all searching for comfort and the preparation and distribution of the sacraments.
If ministers are absent, what a loss occurs for those who leave this world without being reborn or bound!
How great is the faithful's grief over losing their children, who they will not have with them in eternal life!
Finally, how great is the groaning of all, and how great is the blasphemy of some over the absence of ministries and ministers!
See what the fear of temporary evils does, and how much it increases the acquisition of eternal evils.
However, when ministers are present, they help everyone as much as God allows: some are baptized, others find reconciliation, and no one is denied communion with the body of the Lord.
Everyone is comforted, strengthened, and encouraged to pray to God, who can prevent all that is feared.
They are ready for any outcome, so that if they cannot escape this trial, they accept that His will be done, as He cannot wish anything evil.
You now realize what you wrote but did not see before: how much good Christian people do when Christ's ministers are present during tough times.
You also see the harm in their absence, as they may seek their own interests instead of those of Jesus Christ, lacking the love described as, "It does not seek its own" from First Corinthians Chapter Thirteen. They do not imitate the one who said, "Not seeking my own benefit, but that of many, that they may be saved" from First Corinthians Chapter Ten.
He would not have avoided the plots of that persecuting leader unless he wanted to preserve himself for others who needed him. For this reason, he says, "I am torn between the two, having the desire to depart and be with Christ, for that is far better; but to remain in the flesh is necessary for your sake" from Philippians Chapter One.
However, some might say that God's ministers should flee such impending dangers to preserve themselves for the church's benefit in more peaceful times. This is rightly done when there are others who can fulfill the ecclesiastical ministry, ensuring it is not abandoned by all, as we mentioned earlier about Athanasius. The catholic faith, defended against the Arian heretics by his words and care, knows how necessary and beneficial it was for the Church that he remained in the flesh.
We include this summary of the holy Father Athanasius here for its great benefit to the readers, as I believe it will encourage them to explore the entire work, due to its engaging nature.
May thirtieth---Rome, on the Aurelia road, in the cemetery of Saint Felix the Pope.
After leading the Church for five years during Emperor Claudius's reign, he was martyred.
He established that masses should be celebrated over the tombs of martyrs.
In Antioch, Saints Isychius and Palatinus, as Saint Jerome writes, endured many tortures for the name of Christ.
In Turribus, Sardinia, were the holy martyrs Gabinus and Crispulus.
In Nicomedia, there were many martyrs.
On May 31st in Rome, we remember the birth of Saint Petronella, a virgin and daughter of the blessed Apostle Peter.
At the request of the faithful, he cured her of paralysis.
However, after demonstrating this miracle of healing in the name of Christ, he instructed her to return to her bed for the salvation of her soul.
As she grew in the fear of God, not only was she saved, but she also brought healing to many through her prayers.
Because of her great beauty, Count Flaccus wished to marry her.
The holy virgin requested a three-day delay, which she spent fasting and praying with her nurse Felicula, who was also a holy virgin.
When Saint Nicomedes the priest came to celebrate the mysteries of Christ, as soon as she received the sacrament of the body and blood of the Lord, she departed to eternal joy.
On the same day in Aquileia, we commemorate the passion of the holy siblings Cantius, Cantianus, and Cantianilla, who achieved martyrdom under Diocletian's reign.
In Turribus, Sardinia, we honor Saint Crescentianus.
In Spain, in the city of Gerunda, we remember the holy Germanus, Victurius, Sylvanus, Telesphorus, Victorinus, and many others.
June: The month of June has 30 days.
In the second week, there will be a celebration of the Fasts.
June 1st
In Rome, we commemorate the dedication of Saint Nicomedes, a priest and martyr, whose martyrdom is celebrated on September 15.
Also in Rome, we recognize the birth of Lycia, a virgin, and Auceias, a king of the barbarians, along with Rogatus, Germanus, Sylvanus, and more than 300 others.
In Thessalonica, we celebrate the birth of Saint Octavius.
In Antioch, we remember Zosimus and Thecla.
At Caesarea in Palestine, we honor the passion of Saint Pamphilus, a priest known for his admirable faith and holiness.
He was crowned with martyrdom during the persecution of Maximinus.
His life was recorded by Eusebius, Bishop of Caesarea, in three books.
The blessed Jerome also writes that he found some volumes written in Pamphilus's hand:
"These," he says, "I embrace and cherish as if they were the treasures of Croesus.
For if it is a joy to have even one letter from a martyr, how much more to have so many thousands of verses, which seem to be marked with the traces of his own blood."
On the same day, we remember the burial of Saint Caprasius, abbot of the monastery of Lerins.
In Vienne, we commemorate Claudius and Helladius, bishops.
June 2:
In Rome, we celebrate the birth of Saints Marcellinus, a priest, and Peter, an exorcist.
They converted many in prison to the faith of Christ, and after enduring severe imprisonment and many tortures, were beheaded during the persecution of Diocletian, under the judge Severus.
Their executioner witnessed their souls, beautifully adorned, being carried to heaven by angels, and, repenting, was baptized by Pope Julius in his old age, taking the name Dorotheus.
Of the many who, through their teaching, believed in Christ and were baptized, 300 men and even more women, Artemius was beheaded along with his wife Candida and daughter Paulina, who was freed from a demon by the blessed Peter the exorcist.
Also in Rome, we remember 180 martyrs and many more, whose names are known only to God.
At Lyon in Gaul, we honor the birth of 48 martyrs during the times of Marcus Aurelius Verus, Antoninus, and Lucius, his sons.
During a time when persecutions against Christians were fiercely stirred up across many provinces of the Roman Empire due to public outcry and unrest, countless thousands of martyrs arose in various places.
In the cities of Lyon and Vienne in Gaul, the treatment of God's servants surpassed all descriptions of torture and suffering.
Initially, they were forbidden to live in their homes, then they were denied the use of wine and baths.
Eventually, they were prohibited from appearing in public or private places at all.
Finally, when a certain tribune and the city's leaders were present, the Christians were seized by the people's shouts and thrown into prison until they could be brought before the governor.
The governor showed such cruelty to each of those who arrived that no one could fully describe the forms of his brutality.
Among these martyrs, although all were found to be faithful and brave in Christ, certain individuals stood out before God and humans: Photinus, the bishop, who was burdened with ninety years of age, was taken from the church to the tribunal and then to prison.
After enduring extreme beatings and injuries, he soon after peacefully passed away.
Zacharias, the priest, gave his life in defense of his brothers, following Christ's example.
There was also Repagatus, who, being very noble and learned, was killed as an advocate for Christians.
A deacon, holy in name and deeds, suffered unheard-of tortures, such as having burning copper and iron plates applied to the most sensitive parts of his body and being placed on an iron chair with fire underneath.
Yet, he could not be swayed from his faith in Christ.
Along with Attalus and Maturus, who were beheaded, they achieved the crown of martyrdom.
Blandina, a woman whose fragility was a concern for everyone, endured tortures from dawn until evening.
Eventually, her torturers admitted defeat; even after a second round of torture, she remained unbroken.
On the third day, she was tied to a stake, stretched out like a cross, and prepared as food for the beasts.
However, when none of the beasts dared to touch her, she was returned to prison.
On the fourth day, she endured beatings, burns on grates, and many other hardships, before finally being killed by the sword.
There was also a 15-year-old boy named Ponticus, who endured various torments alongside her.
Strengthened by her maternal encouragement, he achieved martyrdom before she did.
Alexander, a physician by profession and Phrygian by birth, overcame all types of torture and went victoriously to Christ.
You can read more about him in the fifth book of Church History, from which these accounts are drawn.
The names of these martyrs include: Photinus the bishop, Zacharias the priest, Sanctus the deacon, Vetitius, also known as Repagatus, Macharius, Asclepiades, also called Alcibiades, Silvius, Primus, Ulpius, Vitalis, Comminus, October, Philominus, Geminus, Vilia, Albina, Grata, Rogata, Aemilia, Potamia, Pompeia, Rhodana, Biblis, Quarta, Matema, Elpis, also called Ammas.
These individuals were killed in various ways.
Those thrown to the beasts included: the aforementioned Sanctus, Maturus, Attalus, Alexander, Ponticus, Blandina, Aristeus, Cornelius, Zosimus, Titus, Julius, Zoticus, Apollonius, Geminianus, Julia, Ausonia, Aemilia, Jannica, Pompeia, Domna, Justa, Throphima, and Antonia.
The remains of all of them were burned and scattered into the Rhone River.
However, through revelations by the martyrs themselves, they were gathered and placed in the Church of the Apostles, where they are said to live before God with frequent miracles.
The citizens of Lyon celebrate this feast joyfully, gathering from all directions and moving down the river with hymns and songs of thanksgiving.
They hold a festive mass in the church, dedicating it to the Lord, and refer to this day as the Day of Miracles, following ancient tradition.
The location of their suffering is called Athenaco, which is why they are known as the Athenacian martyrs.
On June 3rd in Rome, we remember the holy martyrs Marcellus, Avidius, Gaius, Donatus, and more than 150 others.
In Africa, we honor Quirinus, Abidianus, Neophorus, Pambo, Januaria, Demetria, Zincus, and 149 others.
In Aritium, a city in Tuscany, the holy martyrs Pergentinus and Laurentinus, who were brothers, are remembered.
During Decius's persecution, under Judge Tertius, while still children, they endured severe tortures and performed many miracles before being beheaded and buried in the same city, along with over 400 others.
In Campania, we remember blessed Erasmus, bishop of Antioch and martyr.
He led an eremitic life on Mount Lebanon for seven years, performing many wonders there.
Later, he was captured by Emperor Diocletian, who ordered him to be cruelly beaten with lead whips and tortured for a long time with clubs.
Afterwards, he was covered with melted resin, sulfur, lead, pitch, wax, and oil, yet miraculously appeared unharmed.
Seeing this, many people turned away from idols and embraced the Christian faith.
Then, bound with heavy iron weights, he was imprisoned under harsh conditions, but was freed by an angelic visitation.
However, his fame reached Emperor Maximian, and he was tortured again with even harsher punishments, including wearing a heated bronze tunic and being thrown into a boiling pot of lead, pitch, wax, resin, and oil.
Yet, through the power of the Lord, he emerged unharmed and, supported by angelic guidance, reached Campania, where he continued to strengthen others.
He strengthened many in faith or converted them to Christianity.
Called by the Lord, he rested in peace, known for his martyrdom.
The burial of Saint Leifard, a priest, took place in Orléans on June 4th.
In the city of Novidunum, there were Zoticos, Attalos, Eutyches, and many others.
In Sicily, the holy martyrs Expergentius and Cista were celebrated.
In Pannonia, in the city of Sabaria, Rutulus and two others were recognized.
In Illyricum, in the city of Fiscia, Saint Quirinus, a bishop, was born.
During the persecution under Maximian, for his faith in Christ, he was tied to a millstone and thrown into the river.
He spoke for a long time to those around him, encouraging them not to be frightened by his example.
Through prayer, he finally obtained his wish to be submerged.
His remains were transferred to Rome and placed in the Catacombs.
On June 5th, in Egypt, the holy martyrs Marcian, Nicander, and Apollonius were born.
In Rome, at the seventh milestone, Felicula and Felicitas, along with many others, were commemorated.
In Istria, Zoilus, Satyrus, Tymon, Saturninus, Servulus, Felix, Sylvanus, and Fortunatus were remembered.
Also in Rome, Saint Boniface, a martyr under Diocletian and Maximian, suffered at Tarsus in Cilicia but was buried in Rome on the Via Latina.
He was the steward of a noblewoman named Aglaes.
While in a sinful relationship with her, both were eventually moved by divine prompting and decided to send Boniface to seek the bodies of the martyrs.
They hoped that by serving and honoring them, they might deserve to be saved through their merits.
After several days, he arrived in Tarsus and rushed to the site where the holy martyrs were facing their trials.
He saw one person hanging by their feet over a fire, another stretched out on four pieces of wood enduring prolonged suffering, another being torn with claws, another with their hands cut off, and another with a stake fixed in their neck, lifted from the ground.
Witnessing these various tortures arranged by the cruel executioner, he was filled with love for Christ and began to call out to the great God of the holy martyrs.
He ran to them, sat at their feet, kissed their chains, and said,
"Fight on, martyrs of Christ, trample the devil, persevere a little longer. The labor is indeed small, but the rest is great, and the satisfaction afterward is indescribable."
Judge Simplicius, seeing this, ordered him to be brought before the court and asked,
"Who are you?"
Saint Boniface replied,
"I am a Christian, and my name is Boniface."
The judge, angered, ordered him to be hung and his body to be scraped with claws until his bones were visible. Then, sharp reeds were driven under the nails of his hands. Despite this, the holy martyr, looking up to heaven, cheerfully endured the pain.
Seeing this, the cruel judge ordered his mouth to be opened and boiling lead to be poured in. The holy martyr said,
"I thank you, Lord Jesus Christ, Son of God."
Then, the judge ordered a pot to be brought and filled with pitch, and the holy martyr to be thrown headfirst into the boiling pitch. But since he was unharmed, the cruel judge ordered his head to be cut off with a sword. After this was done, a great earthquake occurred, causing many unbelievers to witness the power of Christ in the martyr and believe.
His companions took his body, anointed it with spices, and brought it to the city of Rome. An angel of the Lord appeared to his former mistress, informing her of the blessed martyr's deeds. She immediately met the holy body with all reverence, built a worthy memorial for it, and laid it to rest five miles from the city of Rome.
Blessed Aglae gave up the world's vanities, distributing all her possessions to the needy and monasteries, and freeing her entire household from servitude.
She gained such grace from the Lord that she became renowned for virtuous signs in His name.
Living in a nun's habit for 13 years, she completed her life with pious deeds and was buried near the same martyr.
Blessed Boniface was martyred on May 14th in the city of Tarsus, Cilicia's metropolis, but was buried on June 5th in Rome.
On the same day in Frisia, Saint Boniface, the bishop, also suffered martyrdom.
He came from Britain, preached the Christian faith, and converted many in Frisia to Christianity.
Ultimately, he was slain by the remaining pagans with a sword, achieving martyrdom alongside Bishop Eoban and other servants of God, named Wintrug, Walthere, Skirwald, Bosan, Hamund, Hethere, Wacchar, Gundachar, Willehere, and Hadovolf.
Among them was Willibald, a priest renowned for his virtues and teachings, and his sister Waldburga, noted for her holiness.
On June 6th is the commemoration of Saint Philip, one of the first seven deacons ordained by the apostles along with blessed Stephen, right after Christ's passion.
According to the Acts of the Apostles, chapter six, verse eight, he performed signs and wonders, converting the Samaritans to Christ's faith through his preaching.
He baptized the eunuch, a diligent student of the Scriptures under Queen Candace of the Ethiopians, at a spring near the village of Betsura, in the tribe of Judah, on the road from Elijah to Hebron, at the 20th milestone.
He later rested in Caesarea, where his three daughters, virgins and prophets, are buried, while his fourth daughter, filled with the Holy Spirit, died in Ephesus.
However, some believe they are buried in Hierapolis, where Philip the apostle, one of the twelve, is also buried.
Some writers have thought these were his daughters.
The authority of blessed Luke challenges their opinion by recounting this story:
We entered the house of Philip, the evangelist, who was one of the seven; he had four unmarried daughters who prophesied.
(Acts chapter twenty-one)
In Tarsus of Cilicia, twenty people were martyred under the judge Simplicius during the reign of Emperors Diocletian and Maximian, glorifying God through various tortures.
This was previously mentioned in the passion of blessed Boniface.
In Rome, the saints Artemius, his wife Candida, and their daughter Paulina.
Artemius, who was the keeper of the prison, held the blessed Peter the exorcist in custody.
After his only daughter Paulina was freed from a demon, he believed in Christ and was baptized by the blessed presbyter Marcellinus along with his household and many others.
The judge Serenus, troubled by this news, ordered that Artemius, Candida, and Paulina be buried under a great weight of rubble.
Thus, the saints were led to their place of passion; blessed Artemius was struck by the sword, while holy Paulina and Candida were buried beneath stones in a crypt.
In Noviodunum, Amantius, Lucius, and blessed Alexander.
In Alexandria, Donatus and Peregrinus.
June seventh—In Caesarea of Cappadocia, the martyrdom of blessed Lucian.
In Byzantium, the birth of saints Primus, Fortunatus, Macer, and Macarius, monks.
In Constantinople, formerly Byzantium, the birth of Saint Paul, bishop of the city.
During the time of Arian conflict, he was expelled by Emperor Constantius to a small town in Cappadocia called Cucusus for his Catholic faith and was strangled by Arian plots, ascending to the heavenly realms.
In Africa, Victurius, Evasus, Privitus, Januaria, Donata, Spisma, and Quirillus.
June eighth—In Egypt, the birth of Saint Marcian.
In Caesarea of Palestine, Cristus.
In the city of Doroscoro, the birth of Saint Mark.
In Nicomedia, Eutychius, Nestorius, and Marina.
In Sardinia, the birth of Saint Salustian.
In Gaul, in the city of Soissons, the feast of Saint Medard, bishop and confessor, is celebrated.
His life, filled with virtues, was nobly chronicled in both prose and verse by Fortunatus, the bishop of Paris.
Saint Medard was generous in charity, distinguished in virtues, and renowned for his prophetic spirit.
He led the bishopric of Vermand for fifteen years and indeed guided the entire West with his examples and teachings.
His soul was taken to heaven by angels, and his body was brought to Soissons, where it was honorably buried and is famed for miracles.
In Angers, the feast of Saint Licinius, bishop, is also observed.
On the same day, the celebration of Carlenius, confessor, takes place.
On June 9th in Rome, on the Caelian Hill, we remember the birth of the holy martyrs Primus and Felician under the emperors Diocletian and Maximian.
These glorious martyrs, steadfast in the Lord, were accused by temple priests before the emperors for being Christians.
As Roman citizens, they were brought before the emperors, who ordered their imprisonment, bound with iron, where an angel of the Lord came to comfort them.
After several days, the emperors summoned them again and instructed the soldiers to take them to the temple of Hercules.
If they refused to sacrifice, they were to be severely tortured.
However, unable to change their minds, as they preferred to die for the name of Christ, the soldiers stretched them out and beat them harshly with rods.
When the soldiers reported this to the emperors, they were enraged and commanded that they be handed over to Promotus, the governor of Nomentum, to be executed with various tortures.
The soldiers took them along the road called Nomentana, at the thirteenth milestone, bound with iron, and imprisoned them near the city forum, where they were once again uplifted by an angelic visitation.
After a long time, Promotus ordered that the holy men of God, Primus and Felician, be brought before his tribunal.
During their first, very public questioning, the governor ordered the blessed Felician to be beaten with leaded whips.
When Felician remained steadfast despite the torture, the governor had him tied to a post with spikes driven into his hands and feet.
He was tortured for a long time without any food or water for three days.
Throughout those days, Felician continuously praised God.
The governor then ordered him to be beaten with whips again, taken down from the post, and locked up.
Later, in the presence of Felician, the holy Primus was brought forward.
After Primus endured severe beatings with clubs, he was placed on the rack and laid on a bed, where the governor ordered boiling lead to be poured into his mouth.
Yet the holy, unconquerable martyrs persisted.
Frustrated, the governor ordered them to be taken to the amphitheater, where two lions were released upon them.
However, the lions fell at the saints' feet, and when fierce bears were let loose, they too lost their ferocity because of the martyrs' strength.
Witnessing these miracles, nearly fifteen hundred people, who had come for the spectacle, believed in the Lord.
However, seeing the martyrs' invincibility, the governor ordered their execution by the sword.
That night, Christians took their bodies and buried them near the Nomentan arches within the sandpit on the ninth of June, thirteen miles from the city of Rome.
In Gaul, in the city of Agen, at the place called Pompeiaco, the martyrdom of Saint Vincent, deacon and martyr, is noted, as mentioned in the Book of Miracles by Gregory of Tours.
Also in Rome, the martyrdom of fifteen soldiers.
In Scotland, on the island of Ireland, the burial of Saint Columba, also known to his people as Columbkille, is significant because he was the founder, builder, and leader of many monasteries and churches.
He was so influential that the abbot of the monastery he last led, and where he is buried, is considered, against usual ecclesiastical practice, as the foremost of all the bishops of Ireland, and rightly so.
This same saint, through the presence of the Holy Spirit, is believed to be unrivaled after the apostles and the remarkable Martin in prophecy, teaching, miracles, and angelic visitation.
This can be understood even from these few stories.
While he was on a certain island writing, and a very tall house was being constructed on another, someone began to fall from the top of this enormous structure.
In the face of this sudden danger, he called out to the angel of God standing by him, Help, help!
And behold, in the blink of an eye, the falling man was saved by the angel, as if the angel was more focused on the builder than on the writer.
When a severe illness, or rather an unbearable plague and pestilence, was devastating nearly all the people, he blessed a stone from the shore and instructed that wherever it was placed in water, the water should be given to the sick to drink or be sprinkled on them.
The stone, placed in water and floating against its nature like foam, testified to having received divine blessing in this way, healing all diseases and making it more precious than gold and all jewels, and more effective than all medicines.
To add to the miracle, during that time, no one destined to die could ever find it, no matter how diligently and carefully they searched.
With this miraculous healing in mind, I wish to recall another instance of miraculous provision during times of scarcity, so that the wise reader may learn to appreciate from these two examples.
To a certain poor person, lacking all necessities, the saint sharpened a stick into a spit, which he instructed him to place in the woods and waters.
While he was doing this, he became so wealthy that his house couldn't contain all his riches.
His wife, tired of both land and sea pleasures, had the same food prepared by her husband, but to her own detriment.
Blessed Columba, through his teachings, matched all those before him and is rightly considered to have surpassed them in this regard.
During the last three days of his life, all the mysteries of the holy Scriptures were revealed to him.
These mysteries were either completely hidden from previous mortals or, as the Apostle says: "Through a glass, darkly" known but needed to be discovered and clarified.
They were not written down either due to the absence of Battheneus, his closest disciple, or because of the unworthiness of humanity.
Moreover, he surpassed all mortals in the gift of prophecy, able to perceive things hidden from others, whether near or far, past or future, in a single, unavoidable glance.
A vessel filled with milk was presented to him for a solemn blessing.
When he blessed it, the vessel immediately cracked, and he scolded the servant for not marking it with the sign of the holy cross before pouring, to prevent the ancient enemy from having any place in it.
Similarly, he blessed something resembling milk, extracted from a bull’s testicles, from afar, transforming it into its proper nature, which is blood.
He foresaw and sometimes quelled the wars of neighboring kings, and at other times supported those with just causes, while, united with divine justice, he ignored and did not help the unjust.
He also foresaw the sudden destruction of the city now called Nova in Italy, through an earthquake or as a sign of heavenly wrath, and announced it to others, who marveled at his vision.
He also predicted that French sailors, as indeed happened, would report the same event in Scotland that year.
On the last day of his mortal life, which was a Saturday, he had reached the thirty-third psalm in his writings, up to the verse: "Those who seek the Lord shall not lack any good thing" (Psalm 34:10).
He then said to those present:
"Let Baitheneus write what remains," so that the one who was to succeed him in leading the brothers would not only teach but also draw the disciples to himself through writing: "Come, children, listen to me; I will teach you the fear of the Lord" (Psalm 34:11).
He added: "This day is called the Sabbath, meaning rest, in the Holy Scriptures, in which eternal rest is prepared for me. For this night, I go to the Lord Jesus Christ, the author of the great resurrection. And know this: for a continuous number of days, the sea will be closed by a great storm, so that my burial may be celebrated not superstitiously by common crowds, but religiously by my holy brothers."
Though he had many disciples or companions equal to his holiness, he left one, namely Comgell, known as Faustus in Latin, the teacher of the most blessed Columbanus, our master, lord, and Father Gall, as his sole heir, following the example of Isaac.
On June 10th, on the Via Aurelia in Rome, at the thirteenth milestone, the birth of Saint Basilides, martyr, Tripodis and Mandalis, occurred under Emperor Aurelian, with Platon as governor, alongside twenty other martyrs. However, in some manuscripts, instead of Tripodis and Mandalis, it is written as Tripolis Magdaletis.
On the same day, blessed Getulius the martyr, during the time of Emperor Hadrian and under the judge Licinius, was known for his deep knowledge of divine law. Through his teaching, many were instructed in the faith of Christ. Hearing of his fame, Emperor Hadrian sent the deputy Cerealis to capture him: but upon hearing his words of truth, he believed in Christ and was baptized by blessed Pope Sixtus. Through the instruction of Saint Getulius, he was strengthened in the faith of Christ.
When Hadrian learned of this, he sent the consul Licinius to capture the deputy Cerealis.
When the blessed Getulius, his brother Amantius, and their very holy friend Primitivus were discovered, they were all arrested together.
By the order of Licinius, they were stripped, beaten, and then imprisoned for 27 days.
Upon reaching Rome and informing Hadrian of these events, they received orders to be burned with fire.
However, Saint Getulius survived the fire and completed his martyrdom when his head was struck with clubs.
The blessed martyrs were martyred on the estate of Capreolis, on the Via Salaria, about 13 miles from Rome, above the Tiber River, in the Sabine region.
Their bodies were gathered by the blessed Symphorosa, the wife of the martyr Getulius.
She was martyred not long after with her seven sons on the 27th of June.
She buried them in her family estate in the sandpit, in the place and town mentioned above.
In Nicomedia, the feast of Saint Zacharias.
In Auxerre, the burial of Saint Censorious, bishop.
On the third day before the Ides of June, in Cyprus, the birth of Saint Barnabas the Apostle.
Although named Joseph by his parents, he was called Barnabas, or son of consolation, by the apostles because he sold a field he owned and laid the money at the apostles' feet to comfort the poor.
Though he was a Jew by ethnicity, a Levite by heritage, and from Cyprus by nationality, he worked not only to convert other Jews to the faith of Christ but also to unite the Apostle Paul, who was called by Christ from heaven but viewed with suspicion by Christians due to his previous persecution, with the company of apostles.
With whom he was ordained as an apostle to the Gentiles, he endured many wrongs from unbelievers.
Yet, due to an issue with Mark, their common disciple, or rather by divine dispensation, he was separated from him in body but united in spirit, nevertheless fulfilling the work of evangelical preaching assigned to him.
One testimony from the blessed Luke should suffice for believers regarding his sanctity: he was a good man, full of the Holy Spirit and faith, as written in the Acts of the Apostles, chapter eleven.
The body of this person was discovered during the reign of Emperor Zeno.
It was revealed by him, and he is said to have written a letter for the edification of the Church, which is considered apocryphal.
On the same day in Corinth, we remember Sosthenes, a disciple of the blessed Apostle Paul.
After being mistreated by the Jews, with Gallio the proconsul showing indifference, he converted to Christianity and was honorably mentioned by the blessed Paul in the apostolic letters in First Corinthians chapter 1.
Also in Aquileia, we commemorate the holy martyrs Felix and Fortunatus, who suffered under the persecution of Emperors Diocletian and Maximian, with Euphemio as governor.
These brothers, fervent in their faith in Christ, were betrayed by Apamius, one of the governor's officials, and brought in chains before Judge Euphemio in Aquileia.
There, as they steadfastly professed Christ, they were first placed on the rack with burning torches set beside them.
However, when the martyrs began singing psalms, the torches were extinguished.
They were then covered in burning oil over their stomachs.
Finally, while they persisted in their confession of Christ, they were taken outside the city and beheaded near the river close to the city.
Later, their bodies were secretly taken by devout men of that city, wrapped in spices and linen, and buried.
Citizens from Vicetia attempted to bring their bodies to their city.
Though the people of Aquileia resisted, a divine intervention resolved the pious dispute: Vicetia would have Felix, and Aquileia would keep Fortunatus, but Aquileia would retain the head of Saint Felix, and Vicetia the head of Saint Fortunatus.
This arrangement remains in praise of our Lord Jesus Christ to this day.
In Rome, we commemorate Pope Anacletus, who first constructed and built the memorial of the blessed Apostle Peter.
He was ordained a presbyter by Peter and was buried next to him.
June 12th in Rome marks the birth of Saint Cyrenius.
Under the order of Emperor Claudius the Second, after losing all his possessions and enduring a lengthy imprisonment, he was beheaded at night, and his body was thrown into the Tiber River.
It was later found on the island of Lycaonia and was honorably buried by the faithful.
We don't know exactly how or when it was brought to Rome, but we believe it wasn't unknown to the blessed Gregory.
In Rome, Nabor and Nazarius, along with the martyr Gorgonius, who I believe is mentioned in ecclesiastical history, were transferred from Rome to Gaul with the permission of Pope Paul of Rome.
More precisely, they were taken to ancient France by Ruodgang, Bishop of Metz, in the year of our Lord seven hundred sixty-five.
He placed Saint Gorgonius in a monastery called Gorzia, Saint Nabor in another monastery called Nova Cella, and Saint Nazarius in a monastery called Loresham, where signs and miracles, particularly in restoring health to the sick and weak, are often witnessed.
On the same day in Milan, the birth of the holy martyrs Nazarius and the boy Celsus is celebrated.
Blessed Nazarius' father was African, and his mother, Perpetua, was baptized by the blessed Apostle Peter.
Saint Nazarius himself was taught and baptized by Saint Clement.
During the frenzy of persecution stirred up by Nero, Anulinus kept Nazarius and the blessed boy Celsus, whom he had raised, imprisoned for a long time before ordering their execution by the sword.
Christians secretly buried their bodies on July twenty-eighth outside the gate known as the Roman Gate in their own gardens.
The blessed martyrs revealed themselves to a man named Caeratius, whose wife was Fortunata, and through a vision, warned him to hide them due to the persecution incited by the wicked Nero.
They remained hidden until the time of the Emperors Honorius and Arcadius.
Through God's revelation, the blessed Ambrose discovered them.
When the tomb where the body of the blessed Nazarius lay was opened, those present saw something remarkable.
As Saint Paulinus writes, the martyr's blood appeared so fresh that it seemed as if it had been shed that very day, even though the time of his suffering was unknown until then.
His head, which had been severed by the wicked, remained intact and incorrupt, with hair and beard so perfectly preserved that it looked as if it had been freshly washed and arranged in the tomb at that very moment.
The fragrance that filled the air was so exquisite it surpassed the sweetness of all perfumes.
Once the body was lifted and placed on a bier, the holy bishop went immediately to the martyr Saint Celsus, who was also in the same garden, for prayer, and then transferred both to the Basilica of the Apostles in Rome.
They were discovered and moved on June twelfth.
Their martyrdom is commemorated on July twenty-eighth.
However, their most celebrated public commemoration is held on the day of the holy martyrs Protasius and Gervasius, as if they were companions from the same era.
In Antioch, Saint Marina the virgin endured many tortures for the name of Christ under the prefect Olibrius.
These tortures included chains, imprisonment, scourging, and the rack.
The devil, appearing as a dragon and an Ethiopian, tried to attack and defeat her, but she drove him away using the sign of the holy cross.
Eventually, she was beheaded by the same prefect, ending her mortal life and receiving true and eternal life from Christ.
In Ravenna, there were Macharius, Felix, Aemilius, and Crispinus.
On June 19th, in Milan, we remember the holy martyrs Gervasius and Protasius.
These blessed individuals, taught by Saint Paul the Apostle, spent ten years confined to a room, devoted to reading, prayer, and fasting.
In the tenth year, they were betrayed by the temple priests to Count Astatium, who captured and interrogated them.
Their path to martyrdom unfolded as follows: when threats and flattery failed to make them deny their faith, Gervasius was beaten with leaded whips until he died.
Protasius was beaten with clubs and then beheaded.
Their bodies were secretly taken by a devout man named Philip and his son, and they were buried in a marble coffin at his home.
Years later, during Emperor Theodosius's reign, the blessed Ambrose discovered their graves through divine revelation, and their bodies were found uncorrupted, as if they had died that very day.
When their remains were brought into the city, a man who had been blind for a long time regained his sight by touching their bier.
Also, in the same place, according to the Martyrology of Saint Jerome, we remember the birth of Saint Nazarius and the boy Celsus.
In Ravenna, Saint Ursicinus the martyr remained steadfast in confessing the Lord, despite severe tortures under the judge Paulinus.
He completed his martyrdom by beheading and was buried in the city by the blessed Vitalis, the father of Saints Gervasius and Protasius.
In Rome, Pope Sylvester served for one year.
With the consent of Emperor Justinian, he was deposed by the patrician Belisarius, became a monk, and died as a confessor in exile.
On June 20th—In Rome, we remember the passing of Blessed Novatus, the brother of the priest Timothy, both of whom were taught by the blessed apostles.
Pastor mentions Novatus in the accounts of Pudentiana and Praxedis, the virgins, stating that after Blessed Pudentiana's death, he was visited by Blessed Bishop Pius and Saint Praxedes, along with many martyrs, before departing to Christ.
In the city of Tomis, we honor Paul, Cyriacus, Paula, Feliciana, Felix, Aemilius, Vitalis, Crispina, and Martyria.
We also commemorate the translation of Saint Zeno the martyr.
On June 21st—In Sicily, in the city of Syracuse, we celebrate the birth of the holy martyrs Rufinus and Martia.
In Rome, we remember Saint Demetria, a virgin who was the daughter of Blessed Faustus.
When brought before the impious Julian for her faith in Christ, she gave up her spirit in her confession and was buried by Blessed John the priest, next to her mother Dafrosa and her sister Viviana, near the Licinian Palace.
At the city of Mainz, we celebrate the birth of Saint Alban the martyr, who, under Emperor Theodosius, traveled from the island of Namsia with Saint Theonestus and Ursus to Milan.
From there, with the help of the Lord, he reached Gaul and, remaining dedicated to the Lord and ready for martyrdom in the Savior's name, after Blessed Ursus completed his martyrdom in the city of Augusta, Saint Alban and Theonestus arrived in Mainz.
While preaching the word of God there, he fulfilled his martyrdom and was buried near the city.
In Caesarea, we commemorate the passing of Saint Eusebius the bishop.
On June 22nd—In Antioch, we celebrate the birth of the holy martyrs Agathalica, Julian, Graph, and another 814 whose names God has in the book of the living.
In Britain, we remember Saint Alban the martyr, who during the time of Diocletian in the city of Verulamium, after being beaten and severely tortured, was beheaded.
As his head fell to the ground, the eyes of the one who struck him also fell.
One of the soldiers suffered alongside him because he was ordered to strike him but refused, being terrified by a divine miracle.
He witnessed the blessed martyr, on his way to martyrdom, make a river crossable through prayer.
At that time, a severe persecution reached Britain, condemning Aaron and Julius, along with eight hundred and eighty-nine others, to death with joyful sacrifice.
In the city of Nola in Campania, Saint Paulinus served as bishop.
During the time of the Vandals, after everyone else had been taken, he offered himself to the barbarians in exchange for the son of a widow.
Identified by their king because of a frightening vision, he secured the release of all the captives from his city.
Returning from Africa with ships full of grain, he came back to his position with great honor.
He was renowned not only for his wisdom and holiness but also for his power over demons.
On the same day, we remember the deposition of blessed Nicetius, bishop of the city of Rome.
June 23rd — In Nicomedia, the suffering of the holy virgins Pistis, Elpis, and Agapis, known in Latin as Faith, Hope, and Charity, and their mother Sophia, meaning Wisdom, along with many others.
In Rome, Saint John the priest was ordered to be beheaded by the wicked Julian on the Via Salaria Vetus, before the statue of the Sun.
His body was collected by the blessed Concordius the priest and buried next to the council of martyrs.
In Britain, we commemorate the deposition of Saint Etheldreda, virgin and queen.
Her body, buried for ten years, was found incorrupt.
Also, the vigil of Saint John the Baptist.
July 8th — In the province of Palestine, in the city of Sebasta, formerly Samaria and known as Shechem many centuries earlier, we celebrate the nativity of Saint John the Baptist.
Though his body was beheaded in the fortress of Machaerus in Arabia, it was buried there by his disciples.
Indeed, according to the Gospel of Saint Luke and the Book of Joshua, he is believed to have been born and raised in the city of Hebron in Judea, a designated refuge for priests, the descendants of Aaron.
The holiness of his life, the austerity of his conduct, the quality of his preaching, and the depth of his suffering for the defense of truth are celebrated not only in the writings of the evangelists but also through the testimony of the Lord Himself, the true judge.
In Ephesus, we commemorate the resting place of the blessed John, apostle and evangelist.
Although his praises are more fittingly proclaimed on the sixth day before the Kalends of January, when his feast is celebrated throughout the Church, some of them are also remembered here for the benefit of readers.
So, in the sixty-eighth year after the Lord's passion, knowing the day of his departure was near, he gathered his disciples and, during the sacred solemnities of God's Masses, persistently advised them about the disdain for the world and its desires, as well as the importance of mutual love.
He repeated and spoke about these matters so often that, even when they grew weary of hearing the same message, they asked him to speak of other things because these were more than sufficient for them.
To which he replied: Because the keeping of holy and pure love is either scarcely preached worthily by any mortal or maintained unblemished amidst worldly scandals until the end.
Having said this, he gave peace to all, and after receiving the sacrament of the Lord's body and blood, both for himself and them, he lay down in the tomb as if in a bed, believed to be as free from the pain of death as he was from the corruption of decay.
At Autun, the burial of Saint Simplicius, bishop, along with Festus and Lucerius, is observed on the seventh day before the Kalends of July.
At Berea of Pyrrhus, we commemorate the birth of Saint Sosipater, disciple of the blessed Paul the apostle.
In Alexandria, Saint Gallicanus, a martyr and leader of the Roman army, when besieged by the Scythian people in the city of Philippopolis of Thrace, on the advice of Saints John and Paul, renounced the worship of idols and entrusted himself to the defense of the Lord Jesus Christ, and both he and all of Thrace were freed from the enemy's attack.
Upon returning to Rome and embracing Christianity, he freed five thousand of his servants, granting them freedom as Roman citizens, along with land and houses.
He distributed all his possessions to the poor, except for the inheritance rights of his daughters, Attica and Artemia, who had been converted to Christianity by the devout virgin Constantina Augusta.
He joined a holy man in Ostia named Hilarinus and helped expand his dwelling to accommodate travelers, supporting them in many ways.
With the assistance of his servants, whom he had already freed and thus drawn closer to him, he continuously provided services of holy devotion to all in need and to the sick.
When Julian the Apostate became Caesar and decreed that Christians could own nothing, Gallicanus, in the few houses he had reserved for serving the poor, was regarded as having Christ as his defender.
Anyone attempting to maliciously enter or claim these houses for the treasury was immediately afflicted, either possessed by the devil or covered in leprous spots.
When this reached Julian, he ordered Gallicanus to either sacrifice to the gods or leave Italy.
Blessed Gallicanus soon left everything and went to Alexandria, joining the confessors of Christ for a year.
Later, he retreated to the desert, where Raucianus, a count, forced him to sacrifice to the gods.
When he refused, he was struck with a sword and became a martyr of Christ, joyfully going to the Lord in triumph.
A basilica was immediately built in his name, where the martyr's benefits have been abundant from then until now and forever.
In Rome, the virgin Luceia and King Auceia, along with twenty-two others, were crowned together in martyrdom.
On June 26th, in Rome, the feast of Saints John and Paul, brothers, is celebrated.
John was the steward, and Paul was the chief officer of the virgin Constantia, daughter of Emperor Constantine.
Every day, they provided support to groups of Christians with resources left by the most sacred Virgin of Christ, Constantia.
This eventually caught the attention of the wicked Emperor Julian.
When he couldn't persuade them to abandon their love for Christ and worship idols, even with threats or persuasion, he gave them a ten-day period to turn towards his gods.
During this time, the holy ones of God invited Christians to join them and prepared to leave behind all they could.
Throughout the ten days, they continuously performed charitable acts, both day and night.
At the end of the tenth day, while praying inside their house at dinnertime, they were captured by Terentianus, the commander.
No matter the reasoning or threats, they remained steadfast in their love for Christ.
Through Terentianus, they were beheaded, and they were buried in a pit made inside their house.
Rumor spread that they had been exiled by the Emperor's order.
Demons were expelled from possessed bodies inside the house of John and Paul, confessing their holy suffering.
This even led to Terentianus's only son, who had executed them, entering the saints' house, where a demon declared through his mouth that John and Paul were tormenting him.
Then Terentianus, moved by divine grace and reborn in Christ, prayed over the saints' bodies until he obtained healing for his son.
In Alexandria, there were Agathon, Diogenes, and Bigatus.
In Africa, there were Gaudentius, Felix, Agapitus, and Emerita.
This occurred on the fifth day before the Kalends of July.
In Galatia, there was the birth of the blessed Crescent, a disciple of the blessed Apostle Paul.
He traveled to Gaul, converting many to the faith of Christ through his preaching.
Returning to the nation where he was appointed bishop, he strengthened the Galatians in the Lord's work until the blessed end of his life.
In Tibur, a city in Italy, was the birth of Saint Symphorosa, the wife of the blessed martyr Getulius, along with her seven sons, Crescent, Julian, Nemesius, Primitivus, Justin, Stacteus, and Eugene, with whom she suffered under Emperor Hadrian's rule.
He ordered Symphorosa to be beaten with palms and then hung by her hair.
When he couldn't overcome her, he commanded that she be thrown into the river with a stone tied to her.
Her brother, Eugenius, an official of the Tiburtine court, collected her body and gave her a proper burial.
In the morning, the emperor had seven stakes set up, and her sons were stretched on racks:
Crescent was pierced in the throat, Julian in the chest, Nemesius in the heart, and Primitius through the navel.
Justin was stretched through his limbs and cut through each joint and node of his body.
Stacteus was pinned to the ground with countless spears until he died.
Eugenius was split from the chest to the lower parts.
The priests of the sacred rites named that place "to the seven Bithanatos," where their bodies rest on the Tiburtine Way, nine miles away.
On the same day in Spain, in the city of Cordoba, the saints Zoellus and nineteen others were born.
At Ephesus, the feast of the Seven Sleeping Brothers is celebrated:
Maximian, Malchus, Martinian, Dionysius, John, Serapion, and Constantine.
These brothers, fleeing the Decian persecution after enduring many severe tortures, hid themselves in a large cave on Mount Caelius and remained there in constant prayer.
Upon hearing this, Emperor Decius ordered the cave's entrance to be sealed, leaving them to perish inside.
After 372 years, in the thirtieth year of Theodosius' reign, the son of Emperor Arcadius, when a heresy arose intending to nullify the hope of faith and the resurrection of the dead, these seven brothers were awakened by divine providence from their long sleep.
They were discovered because they brought very ancient coins from their time to the market to buy their daily sustenance.
Brought before the people of that age, they were compelled to return what they were thought to be holding, as if they had discovered ancient treasures.
After much struggle and severe tribulation faced by the saints, they suspected that they had left the city in the evening and returned in the morning, although it seemed different to them.
Eventually, when Marinus, the bishop of the Ephesians, arrived, it was difficult to uncover the truth of the matter.
They were freed from the hands of the violent, and when Emperor Theodosius was summoned from distant parts of the world, they served as a testimony to the future resurrection and returned to their original resting place.
In the city of Amiens, the bodies of the saints Fuscian, Victoricus, and Gentian were discovered on June 28.
In Lyon, Gaul, Saint Irenaeus, the bishop, was born.
He succeeded the blessed Pothinus, who was nearly ninety years old when he was crowned for his martyrdom in Christ.
It is known that he was a disciple of the most blessed Polycarp, who was a disciple of Saint John the Apostle, priest, and martyr.
During the persecution of Severus, almost all the people of his city were gloriously crowned with martyrdom, and he was buried by the priest Zacharias in the crypt of the basilica of Saint John the Baptist under the altar, with Epipodius on one side and Alexander, the martyr, on the other.
On the same day in Alexandria, the passion of the holy martyrs Plutarch, Serenus, Heraclides, and Hero occurred.
Also, Serenus, Potamiena, Marcella, and the catechumen Hera received baptism through martyrdom.
Among them, Potamiena was the foremost, a virgin who endured immense and countless struggles for her virginity and later suffered exquisite and unheard-of tortures for Christ's martyrdom.
Ultimately, with her venerable mother Marcella, she was consumed by fire's torments and ascended from earth to heaven.
On the same day, the burial of Saint Leo, Pope, took place.
He was the forty-seventh to sit in the city of Rome after the blessed Apostle Peter, serving for 21 years, 1 month, and 13 days.
He was abundant in teaching and explaining the Catholic faith with many bishops, condemning the Eutychian and Nestorian heresies, and through his efforts, the most holy Council of Chalcedon was convened.
Here, he decided to stay within the action: the holy sacrifice, and not accept the blessed head covering for a nun from a bishop unless her virginity was proven beforehand.
In Africa, Fabian and Felix, along with many other martyrs.
The vigil of the most holy apostles Peter and Paul.
June 29th—in Rome, we celebrate the birth of the blessed apostles Peter and Paul, who suffered under Emperor Nero during the consulship of Bassus and Tuscus.
Peter, after converting many thousands of Jews to the Lord Jesus Christ, following the calling of Cornelius and many Gentiles, after leading the Church of Antioch and preaching to the believers from the circumcision in Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia in the second year of Claudius, was directed by God to confront Simon Magus and to enlighten the Western people.
He came to Rome as a remedy for those suffering in soul and body.
There, he held the priestly chair for twenty-five years until the last year of Nero, by whom he was crucified, crowned with martyrdom, with his head turned to the ground according to his request, and his feet facing upwards, because he believed himself unworthy to be crucified in the same manner as his Lord.
He was buried in the same city, in the Vatican, near the Triumphal Way.
He is venerated worldwide and helps in countless ways all who seek him with faith.
He wrote two Epistles, which are called Canonical.
The second is denied by many due to its stylistic differences from the first, but it is truly recognized as his by all sound-minded people.
He ordained two bishops, Linus and Cletus, who performed all the priestly duties in Rome for the people or visitors.
He devoted his efforts to prayer and preaching, just as in Jerusalem, where deacons were appointed for the ministry of widows and orphans, he was always dedicated to prayer and the word with the other apostles.
Paul, after the Lord's passion in the twenty-fifth year, which was during the second year of Nero, spread the Gospel of Christ from Jerusalem all the way to Illyricum.
He was sent to Rome in chains but was miraculously freed by God.
He was placed under house arrest and, as he writes in the Second Letter to Timothy, chapter four, was saved from the lion's mouth, referring to the fierce persecutor Nero.
He preached the Gospel of Christ in the western regions as well and, in the fourteenth year of Nero, on the same day as Peter, was beheaded in Rome for Christ and buried on the Ostian Way in the thirty-seventh year after the Lord's passion.
He wrote nine, or rather ten, letters according to the Decalogue of the law, to seven churches:
one to the Romans, two to the Corinthians, one to the Galatians, one to the Ephesians, one to the Philippians, one to the Colossians, two to the Thessalonians, and one to the Hebrews.
Although some have doubted the letter to the Hebrews due to differences in language and ideas and because his name is not in the title, it is now undoubtedly considered among the canonical Scriptures as from the blessed apostle Paul.
Furthermore, there are four other letters to his disciples: two to Timothy, one to Titus, and one to Philemon.
Some also read a letter to the Laodiceans, which is considered worthless by the wise.
Having mentioned what pertains to his apostleship or martyrdom, let us briefly recall, although out of order, some aspects of his genealogy, education, and election for the benefit of scholars.
Saul, therefore, or rather Saul in Hebrew, was from the tribe of Benjamin, where his name was prominent because of King Saul.
He was born in the town of Giscala; when it was captured by the Romans, he and his family moved to Tarsus in Cilicia.
They sent him to Jerusalem for his studies.
Gamaliel was highly skilled in ancient law and later embraced the Gospel of Christ.
He was so well-educated that he was called the chosen vessel by the giver of spiritual gifts himself.
Even though he agreed with the Jews who persecuted Christians, including the execution of Stephen, the first martyr of Christ, he fiercely opposed all those associated with this name throughout the region.
As he admits, he persecuted the followers of Jesus of Nazareth even in foreign nations.
On his way to Damascus, the capital of Syria, he was compelled by a sudden revelation, a fitting punishment, to convert to faith, transforming from a persecutor into a teacher of the nations.
When Sergius Paulus, the proconsul of Cyprus, first believed through his preaching, Paul took his name after converting him to the faith of Christ.
Since we've mentioned a few things about the origin or calling of the blessed Paul, let's share some details about the other apostles for the instruction of the curious.
First, it's important to know that although the twelve apostles were chosen by the Lord, the homeland, tribe, or even the calling of some of them isn’t clearly expressed.
However, by carefully examining the pages of the divine Scripture, these details can be found by those who seek them earnestly.
Concerning Peter, Andrew, and Philip, they were from Bethsaida, a place that symbolically represents our hunters; anyone who reads the Gospel is aware of this.
Luke also hints at this about James and John when he mentions they were companions of Simon, who, because of his steadfast faith, was called Peter by the Lord.
Regarding James the Lesser, often called the brother of the Lord by both the faithful and the Jewish historian Josephus, and his brothers Simon and Jude, or Thaddeus, it's undeniable that they were from the tribe of Judah.
As for the calling of Matthew, although it's clearly described by three evangelists, his tribe or homeland seems to be unmentioned.
However, while Mark and Luke refer to him as Levi—without explicitly mentioning his name—or Dionymon according to some, or from the tribe of Levi according to more thorough sources, they make this clear.
Furthermore, regarding Bartholomew and Thomas, there's little else noted in certain apostolic writings except that they were chosen from among the many disciples for the apostolic rank.
But if anyone delves deeper into these texts, exploring the profound treasures of sacred Scripture, they will marvel, rejoicing at uncovering the riches of Jerusalem.
As sung in the psalm about the resurrection and ascension of the Lord, the gifts of the Holy Spirit, the preaching of the apostles, the belief of the nations, or the cruelty of the persecutors, in Psalm Sixty-Eight: In the churches, bless God the Lord from the fountains of Jerusalem.
There, Benjamin, the young man, namely Paul, as Luke also mentions, is beside the feet of the young man, in Acts Chapter Seven;
—in a state of mental ecstasy, as he himself professes: Whether we are out of our mind, it is for God; whether we are in our right mind, it is for you, in Second Corinthians Chapter Five.
—Leaders of Judah, their chiefs, namely James, Simon, and Judas.
—Leaders of Zebulun, leaders of Naphtali.
Undoubtedly, all the others, except Judas Iscariot, which means meditation of death, can be appropriately understood, even by changing the letters, because from the tribe of Issachar, which in Latin means reward, he is expressed.
His birth and the heir of that name, by destroying himself, is commended by the Gospel writers.
Having briefly mentioned these things in detail, let us return to the subject.
On the same day, that is, on the third day before the Kalends of July, which is the day before those Kalends, at Rome, the suffering of nine hundred seventy-six martyrs.
In Persia, the birth of the holy apostles Simon and Jude.
On the second day before the Kalends of July—at Rome, or rather throughout the world of Christ, the feast of Saint Paul the Apostle.
Today, we celebrate the birthday of the blessed Lucina, who was baptized and taught by the apostles.
She generously shared her resources with the saints, always striving to support those in chains and jail, and devoted herself to respectfully serving their burials.
By sharing in their merits, she also achieved a precious death through her confession of Christ, and by fulfilling her vows to the Lord, she earned her place in the heavenly Jerusalem.
In Rome, she was honorably buried in the remarkable crypt she constructed for the interment of the martyrs.
In Africa, we celebrate the feast of Timothy and Zoticus.
In Agrippina, it's the feast of Asclepius and Pamphilus.
In Limoges, we commemorate the burial of Saint Martial, bishop and confessor.
July. The month of July has 31 days.
July 1st—On Mount Or, it marks the burial of Aaron, the first priest under the law.
In Rome, we commemorate the birth of Saint Caius, pope, alongside many other martyrs.
In Mesopotamia, Zoellus is remembered with many others.
Uronis and Monegunda, a most holy woman, were enclosed near Saint Martin, and are famous for their miracles.
In the Lyon region, at a place called the Valley of Vebrona, we remember the burial of the man of God, the blessed Domitian, an abbot who was the first to live a hermit life there.
He gathered many in the service of God, founded a monastery, and was known for great virtues and remarkable miracles.
He lived to a good old age.
On the same day, we remember the burial of Areleffus, a confessor.
Dedicated to God since childhood, he sought a monastic life and was ordained a priest by Saint Maximin of Orléans.
Along with his companion Avitus, he yearned for a solitary life, but his growing merits made it impossible for him to remain hidden by divine will.
He built monasteries in various locations and was renowned for many virtues both during his life and after his death.
The term "virtue" sometimes refers to holiness of life and sometimes to the power of miracles. One of the miracles attributed to his holiness is worth mentioning in this brief ecclesiastical history to caution against reckless behavior.
A certain woman named Gunda, hearing that Saint Areleffus had forbidden women—often seen as softening male strength—from entering his monastery, disguised herself in men's clothing to mock the holy man.
Thinking she had succeeded, she mingled among the men at the convent; but suddenly, she lost her sanity and began exposing herself, which is shameful to describe.
Like Lot's wife, though not turned into a pillar of salt, she became a warning through her punishment, instilling fear of curiosity in those present and those who would come after.
July 2nd.
July.
In Rome, the saints Processus and Martinianus began to marvel at the wonders performed by the Lord Jesus Christ through His blessed apostles, Peter and Paul.
At that time, the esteemed apostles were entrusted to a distinguished man named Paulinus, who was in charge of the Mamertine Prison on the Tarpeian Rock.
There, they made water flow from the rock through their prayers.
Then, Processus and Martinianus were baptized by the blessed apostle Peter, along with forty-seven others of both genders.
When Paulinus heard about this, he sent soldiers to arrest them and ordered them to be thrown back into custody.
The following day, they were brought out, and with steadfastness.
.
Here, several pages are missing in the manuscript.
On the other hand, Rusticus remarked, "Now, we see that you are irreligious, an enchanter, and a magician who eats in the morning, milks deer, and hangs clothes from the sun's rays unless you make the child speak in the name of God."
Finally, after much resistance, the holy man, compelled to set aside his humility somewhat and reveal his power, turned to the child and said, "I adjure you by Jesus Christ, the Son of the living God, to declare before everyone who your father is and who your mother is."
The little child, endowed with the power to speak by the author of all, responded in the most perfect speech, "My father is this bishop Rusticus, and my mother is that nun."
Thus, that stubborn bishop was exposed in his crime, received counsel for repentance from God's true servant, and the holy priest Goar, glorified by Christ, returned to his place and rested in peace, growing in virtue day by day.
On July 7th, in Alexandria, Egypt, we celebrate the birth of Saint Pantaenus, an apostolic man adorned with all wisdom.
He was so dedicated and loving toward the word of God that he set out with zeal and devotion to preach the Gospel of Christ to all nations hidden in the farthest reaches of the East, reaching as far as India.
There, he found that Bartholomew, one of the twelve apostles, had preached the coming of the Lord Jesus Christ according to the Gospel of Matthew.
Returning, he brought with him the text written in Hebrew letters to Alexandria, where he concluded his illustrious and noble life with a blessed end.
There also are the saints Heraclius, Helias, Apollonius, and Publius, along with twenty others.
In Rome, we remember the martyrdom of the blessed martyrs Nicostratus, the first of the treasury, Claudius the commentator, Castorius or Castulus, Victorinus, Symphorian, or, as contained in the Book of Sacraments, Sempronian.
We used to think we celebrated their birthday on the sixth day of the Ides of November, until the venerable Father Ado suggested others to be honored for them.
We'll discuss this more conveniently in due time, life permitting.
Blessed Sebastian taught them to believe in Christ, and Saint Polycarp the priest baptized them.
While searching for the bodies of the saints by the Tiber, they were captured and brought to Fabian, the prefect of the city.
He spent ten days trying to persuade them with threats and flattery to sacrifice to idols.
But since he couldn't sway them from their steadfast faith, he reported them to the emperors Diocletian and Maximian.
They ordered them to be tortured, and when they couldn't be compelled to yield by any means, they ordered them to be thrown into the sea.
Weighted down with heavy burdens, they were cast into the waves of the sea, so that in a pure place among the waters, they might be deemed worthy to receive the crown of martyrdom.
On July 8th, in Asia Minor, the birth of Saint Aquila and his wife Priscilla is commemorated.
It's recorded in the Acts of the Apostles, chapter eighteen, that the blessed apostle Paul stayed and worked with them because they shared the same trade, after they came to Achaia from the city of Rome.
In Palestine, Saint Procopius the martyr was taken from Scythopolis to Caesarea, and after his first bold response, he was beheaded by the angry judge Fabian.
In Nicaea, Senator Sostratus, Severus, and Honoratus, along with many others.
In Tauromenium, Sperus and Cornelianus, with sixty others.
In the district of Austria, at the castle or rather the city known in German as Wurzburg, located near the Main River, the martyrdom of Saint Kilian, the first bishop of that city, and his two disciples, the priest Colonatus and the deacon Totnan, is remembered.
Coming from Hibernia, the island of the Scots, and having received authority from the pope of the Apostolic See, they preached the name of Christ in that place and its surroundings.
When many people were being converted to the Lord by this apostolic man through signs and preaching, he was killed by the local duke, Cozpert, who was upset because he tried to stop Cozpert from marrying his brother's wife.
This act was carried out with the help of the highly incestuous Geila and her equally zealous companions.
Numerous miracles always occur at their memorials, but their sacred deaths were first made known through these signs.
The person who killed them while they were praying in the quiet of night went mad, running around, shouting that he was guilty of killing the saints, and biting himself because he felt consumed by an invisible fire from Saint Kilian.
He confessed his crime.
Geila was also possessed by an evil spirit, and her unworthy life ended with a well-deserved death.
Cozpert, however, was killed by his own servants with a sword, and his son was expelled from the kingdom by the people.
To further prove the sanctity of the martyrs, when their remains were uncovered for transfer many years later, their books and clothes, buried with them, were found undamaged, as if they had been stored above ground, which was surprising given the region's extreme dampness.
On the 9th of July—In Rome, at Gutta, which flows continuously, we commemorate the birth of Saint Zeno and ten thousand two hundred and three others.
Also remembering Florian and Faust.
In the city of Tyre, not far from Rome, during the reign of Emperor Decius, there was Anatolia, who healed many sick, lunatics, and possessed people in Picenum.
She was taken by order of Faustinus to the city of Tyre, tortured with various wounds, and locked in with a snake for a whole night but remained unharmed.
Moreover, she saved Marsus, who had released the snake, named Audax, from being devoured by his own snake in the morning and converted him to the faith of Christ.
After confessing the truth, he was imprisoned and soon received the crown of martyrdom.
The Virgin of Christ herself was pierced by a sword while she stood with outstretched hands in prayer.
The sword, entering through her right side, exited through her left.
She suffered on the seventh day before the Ides of July and was buried in the morning by the citizens of Tyre.
In Milan, we celebrate the birth of Saint Mochimus.
In Egypt, Bishop Cyril faced a trial by fire when he was thrown into flames by the leader Lycus.
Remarkably, he emerged unharmed, and, amazed by this miracle, the judge released him.
When Cyril resumed preaching the word of God and converting many to the faith of Christ, the judge, overtaken by impiety, ordered his beheading, and Cyril achieved the desired end of martyrdom.
Similarly, in Egypt, we honor Saint Serapion, a bishop and confessor.
In the city of Martulana, Saint Bricius, also a bishop and confessor, was struck on the mouth with a stone and cruelly tortured on the rack.
Despite being thrown into prison, he persevered in his confession of the Lord.
That night, a severe earthquake struck the city, killing many, including Martianus.
Strengthened by a holy angel and the blessed Apostle Peter, the confessor of Christ was inspired to preach the Gospel, leading many to believe in Almighty God, and he rested in peace.
His soul was seen by those present being received into heaven in the form of a snow-white dove.
On the sixth day before the Ides of July in Rome, we remember the birth of seven brothers, sons of Saint Felicitas: Januarius, Felix, Philip, Sylvanus, Alexander, Vitalis, and Martial.
Under the city prefect Publius, during the reign of Emperor Antoninus, they were subjected to various tortures by different judges.
Of these, Januarius, after being beaten with rods and imprisoned, was killed by leaden whips.
Felix and Philip were beaten to death with clubs.
Sylvanus met his end by being thrown off a cliff.
Alexander, Vitalis, and Martial were sentenced to death, but even in death, they remained united in the love of Christ and the unity of faith.
In Rome, at the tenth milestone on the Plautilla estate known as Buxo, the holy sisters Rufina and Secunda, daughters of the esteemed Asterius and Aurelia, were martyred.
During the persecution by Valerian and Gallienus, under the judges Junius the prefect and Archisilaus the count, they were beheaded at this location because they refused to marry their fiancés who had renounced Christ.
In Africa, the holy martyrs Januarius, Marinus, Nabor, and Felix were beheaded for their steadfast Christian faith; their bodies were later transferred to Milan.
On July 9th, in Rome, the passion of the holy martyrs Stephen, Leontius, Maurice, and many others took place.
In Africa, the martyrdom of Marianus and Januarius occurred.
In Lesser Armenia, in the city of Nicopolis, the holy martyrs Januarius and Pelagia were tortured on the rack, with claws and shards of pottery for four days, and achieved martyrdom.
The transfer of Saint Benedict the abbot from the fortress of Cassino or Cassiani to Gaul or Aquitaine took place.
After his monastery was devastated by invaders, as he had predicted during his lifetime, he pleaded with Almighty God that only the men would be spared due to his intercession.
His body was discovered by some religious men, revealed by the Lord, and was transferred to Gaul, where it was worthily buried in the territory of Orléans, at the monastery called Fleury, and has been continuously honored by the devotion of many faithful.
The bones of the blessed virgin Scholastica, his sister, were also transferred and buried in the area of Le Mans with the devotion of the religious.
The same man of God saw her soul leaving the body and entering the secrets of heaven in the form of a dove, and he ordered her body to be placed in the same sepulcher with his, so that their bodies would not be separated in burial, just as their minds had always been united in God.
But woe to those unfortunate ones, because their actions have caused things that were meant to be united by the will of the Holy Spirit to be separated.
However, the place, honored with the relics of the saints, did not remain empty of the faithful for long.
The brothers who managed to escape the enemies gathered once more, and with others joining in place of those dispersed, they grew in number.
They cared for the sacred ashes with great reverence, acting more cautiously, until recently they were scattered in all directions due to the threat of the Saracens.
On July twelfth at Aquileia, we commemorate the birth of Saint Hermagoras, or as ancient texts say, Hermechora, the first bishop of that city and a disciple of Saint Mark the Evangelist.
Also remembered is Fortunatus, about whom Bishop Fortunatus remarked, "And Aquileia boasts of its own Fortunatus."
In Cyprus, we honor Blessed Nason, an early disciple of Christ.
In Rome, at the Vatican, we remember the burial of Saint Pius, the Pope, who served as bishop for eighteen years.
During his time, Hermes wrote a book called "The Shepherd," because an angel appeared to him as a shepherd.
In Milan, we recall the transfer of the holy martyrs Nabor and Felix, who were beheaded on July tenth in Africa along with Januarius and Marinus, and on this day were brought to Milan.
It is believed that Blessed Victor, in his passion, prayed: "Do not separate me, Lord, from my fellow citizens, your martyrs Nabor and Felix."
In Lyon, France, we remember the burial of Viventiolus, the bishop.
On July thirteenth, we commemorate the passing of Ezra, the restorer of divine law.
In Alexandria, we remember Serapion, Evangelus, Zeno, and others, along with the virgin Trophima.
In Rome, we honor Saint Cletus, the Pope, who served as bishop for twelve years.
As the deputy bishop of Blessed Peter the Apostle, by his command, he ordained twenty-five priests in the city of Rome and was buried next to his body.
In Africa, we celebrate the birth of the holy confessors and the most victorious martyrs: Eugenius, the Bishop of Carthage, who was renowned for his faith, virtues, and miracles, along with all the clergy of the same Church.
Nearly five hundred of them, including many readers and even children, were joyfully exiled in the Lord, having suffered through slaughter and starvation.
Among them were the noble archdeacons, Salutaris and Mauritta, who were second in the order of ministers.
They endured many punishments for their Catholic confession and, having become confessors for the third time, were honored with the title of glorious perseverance in Christ.
In Antioch, we remember the martyrdom of Margaret the virgin.
Consul Olybrius, attempting to sway her from the faith of Christ, subjected her to many torments.
These included being hung on a rack and torn with sharp claws.
Later, she was thrown into a dark prison, where she overcame many temptations of the devil, which appeared to her in the form of a dragon and an Ethiopian, all in the name of the Lord Jesus.
Ultimately, she was beheaded and entered eternal rest.
On July twelfth, in Alexandria, we commemorate the holy martyrs Mammarius, Peter, and others.
In Africa, Donata stands out.
In Pontus, we honor Saint Phocas, or Phocatis, the Bishop of Sinope, who, under Emperor Trajan and the African prefect, overcame imprisonment, chains, iron, and fire for Christ.
His relics are kept in the Basilica of the Apostles in Vienne, France.
In Lyon, France, we remember Saint Justus, bishop and confessor, who, filled with divine contemplation, passed away in a hermitic life and was gloriously brought back to his city, leaving noteworthy works in the Song of Songs.
We also honor Saint Amicus, bishop.
On July thirteenth, in the city of Nisibis, we celebrate the birth of Saint Jacob, bishop, a man of great virtue, whose prayers often delivered the city from danger.
This was one of the confessors during the persecution under Maximinus and one of those who opposed the homoousion at the Council of Nicaea, condemning the perversity of Arius.
By the order of Emperor Constantine, he was buried within his city's walls for protection and security.
However, due to the zeal of Julian the Apostate, he was moved and reburied outside the city.
Shortly after, the city, deprived of the relics of such a great patron, fell to Persian rule.
Even while alive, he performed many signs, and he alone was granted the sight of Noah's Ark on Mount Ararat in Armenia, which no one else among his companions was allowed to see.
In the Roman port, there were Eutropius, Zozima, and Bonosae, sisters.
At Alexandria, the saints Philip, Zeno, Narses, and ten children.
At Carthage, the saints Catulinus the deacon, Januarius, Florentius, Julia, and Justa, who are placed in the Basilica of Faustus.
In Sirmium, Agrippinus, Secundus, Maximus, Fortunatus, and Martialis.
On July 16th—In Ostia, we commemorate the birthday of Saint Hilarinus, a joyful supporter and sustainer of the saints.
During Julian's persecution, when he refused to sacrifice to idols, he was beaten with clubs and achieved martyrdom.
At Antioch in Syria, Saint Eustathius, the bishop and confessor, was exiled to Janopolis, a city of Thrace, under Prince Constantius for his Catholic faith.
It was there that he first rested.
Also, Theodosius, Dionysius, and Theodotus.
In Caesarea of Cappadocia, Saint Paul, whose deeds were known to Saint Jerome, as he confessed, but are unknown to our slowness.
In the same city, we remember the passion of Saint Mammatus, who, called divinely to Mount Sinai and receiving a staff fallen from heaven to perform miracles, touched the earth with it, and immediately the Gospel sprang forth.
As he began to read it, all kinds of wild animals became gentler than tame ones, with nursing females offering themselves to be milked.
After pressing the curds into cheese, he went to Caesarea of Palestine and ministered to widows, the weak, and other poor people.
When the Jewish people of Jerusalem, who were envious of all good things, saw this, they reported him as being involved in magic to the governor of Cappadocia.
This governor had been appointed by the tyrant Alexander to manage those regions.
When the governor sent soldiers to arrest him, Saint Mamas welcomed them with kindness.
After their meal, he read the Gospel to them.
A large number of wild animals gathered, making the soldiers fear they couldn't escape.
The kind man gently reassured them and sent them ahead, while he commanded the fierce lion to follow him to the theater, trailing closely behind the soldiers.
He was handed over to the governor, cruelly interrogated, and even more cruelly torn with claws on the rack, then thrown into prison.
There, he found forty others suffering from hunger and thirst.
He revived them with honey and milk sent to him from heaven by a dove and invisibly absolved them with the keys of his merits, while he remained alone in the prison.
He was brought again before the governor, thrown into a fiery furnace, and after five days was found unharmed among the choir of angels.
He was exposed to an excessively cruel bear, which rushed at him with great force but suddenly retreated and sat down, as if accusing itself of its boldness by divine command.
A leopard was also released on him but was more obedient than harmful.
Then the governor, full of anger, ordered a very fierce lion to be brought to devour him.
And behold, the Arab lion, rushing into the theater with great speed, was tamed by the constant reading of the Gospel and spoke to blessed Mamas with these words:
"Greetings, proven servant of God, in whom the Holy Spirit has made a sweet dwelling for itself. Behold, by angelic command, I have been given a voice for a time; your faith has surpassed the laws of nature, and for you, the human voice is granted to mute animals. I fulfill my duty to the shepherd, remembering whom we obeyed on the mountain."
As he spoke, the theater doors were shut by angels.
Suddenly, he started raging through the crowd with terrifying expressions.
He gently tore some, caught others with his mouth, crushed some with his embrace, broke others with his claws, and consumed some with fear alone.
Once all the pagans or Jews were wiped out, life was granted to the governor and his duty, by Mamma's command.
Returning injury for favors, he ordered the release of the lion, believing all hope of his victory lay with it.
But as the beast came closer, it licked the saint's feet, seeking forgiveness, and rolled at his knees.
Then everyone attempted to stone him, but to no avail, as the blows, flying here and there, didn't harm the martyr.
Thus, he left unharmed, fulfilling his vows to God.
And behold, a voice came from heaven, saying: "Ascend, Mamma, heaven is open to you, and all the gates of paradise are unlocked. Now the Lord rejoices for you, rewarding you for your triumphs: Now Christ awaits you with a crown, hurry with the Holy Spirit, who guides you."
Hearing these victorious words, the martyr joyfully prayed and rested in peace.
On July 17th—in Carthage, the birth of the holy martyrs of Scillium, namely Speratus, Martialis, and Narthalus, Aquilinus, Cythinus, Beturius, Felix, Lactantius or Lactatius, Januaria, Generosa, Bessia, Donata, and Secunda. Under the prefect Saturninus, they were brought from their city Scylla to Carthage, and after their first confession of Christ, they were sent to prison and nailed to wood, then beheaded by the sword in the morning.
Their remains, along with the bones of Saint Cyprian and the head of Saint Pantaleon, were transferred from Africa to Gaul and are venerated in Lyon at the basilica of Saint John the Baptist. In Milan, Saint Marcellus. In Auxerre, the burial of Saint Theodosius the bishop.
July 18th.
August eighth — In Rome, on the Tiburtine Way, at the eighth milestone, marks the birth of the holy martyr Symphorosa and her seven sons, who lie buried with her.
The names of her sons are Peter, Marcellian, Januarius, Dionysius, Sympronius, Clement, and Hireneus.
In Carthage, we remember Saint Gudene, who, during the consulship of Plutio and Reto, was ordered by Rufinus the proconsul to endure torture on the rack four times, was horrendously torn with claws, and suffered long in the squalor of prison.
She was ultimately killed by the sword.
In the city of Metz, we commemorate the burial of Saint Arnulf, a bishop renowned for his holiness and miraculous grace, who cherished the hermit life even as a bishop, and found rest in a blessed end.
July nineteenth — In Spain, we celebrate the birth of Saint Justus.
In the city of Seville, we honor the holy Justa and Rufina, who were captured by the governor Diogenian, tortured on the rack and torn with claws, then thrown into prison to suffer hunger and pain.
The governor ordered that wherever he went, they were to follow him barefoot.
Eventually, Justa died in prison.
Her body was thrown into a well and later retrieved by Bishop Sabinus and buried in the cemetery of Seville.
Rufina's neck was broken, and her body was consigned to the flames; her remains were cared for by the faithful.
In Egypt, we remember our Father Arsenius, of whom it is said in the Words of the Elders that he always had a cloth in his bosom or hand to wipe away his abundant tears.
In Alexandria, we honor Saint Sisinnius.
In Antioch, Lucian and his companions.
In Constantinople, Daria.
In Spain, Justus.
In Lyon, France, we remember the burial of Saint Rusticus, priest and confessor.
In Italy, in the city of Tyro, we celebrate the birth of Saint Christina, a virgin according to some.
July twentieth — We commemorate the birth of the blessed Joseph, surnamed Justus, who was appointed by the apostles along with blessed Matthias to complete the number of twelve.
When Matthias took the place of Judas the traitor, the blessed Joseph continued his mission of preaching and holiness.
He endured many persecutions for his faith in Christ from the Jews and eventually passed away in Judea, achieving a most victorious end.
It is said that he drank poison but suffered no harm because of his faith in Christ.
In Damascus, we commemorate the feast day of saints Sabinus, Maximus, Julian, Macrobius, Cassius, and Paula, along with ten others.
In Corinth, we honor Cyriacus with many others.
In Rome, we remember the holy ones Passeria, Macrinus, Saturus, and Aemilius.
On July 21st, we observe the burial of the holy prophet Daniel.
In Rome, the holy virgin Praxedes is remembered.
She, alongside her sister, the blessed Potentiana or Pudentiana, was educated in chastity and divine law by their most holy father Pudens, who was taught in the faith by the blessed apostle Paul.
After their father's death, she devoted herself to vigils, prayers, and fasting.
With her blessed sister, she gave away her entire inheritance to support the poor and the saints of Christ.
In the church dedicated by their father Pudens in the name of the blessed Pastor, she and her sister, guided by the blessed Pius, bishop of the holy and apostolic see, endeavored to build a baptismal font so their household could be baptized on Easter Sunday.
Blessed Pius baptized ninety-six of them in the saving waters.
After countless acts of charity and many burials of martyrs, this most blessed virgin departed to the Lord to receive the crown of righteousness from the just Judge.
She was buried in the cemetery of Priscilla, on the Salaria Road, next to her sister and father Pudens.
In Gaul, in the city of Marseille, the feast day of Saint Victor is celebrated.
During the persecution by Diocletian and Maximian, though he was a soldier, he refused to serve or sacrifice to idols.
Initially, he was imprisoned by his tribune Austerius, but each night, an angel would bring him out to visit and console the sick.
Then, on orders from Prefect Eutychius, his arms were tied with thin leather straps, his feet bound with rope, and he was dragged through the middle of the city.
After this, he was brutally beaten with clubs, hung up, and tortured with whips.
When they brought out an altar for him to sacrifice on, he couldn’t bear to look at it and kicked it away from the priest’s hand.
The governor ordered his foot to be cut off.
In the end, he remained steadfast in his faith in Christ and was sent to a flour mill, where animals usually suffer from dizziness and weariness.
There, he was crushed and completed his martyrdom.
Three soldiers suffered with him: Alexander, Felician, and Longinus.
A boy named Deuterius also died while praying at his tomb.
In the city of Cesena, the birth of the saints Adrian, Helio, Victor, Patroclus, and others.
In Verona, the relocation of the remains of Saint Zeno the martyr, about whose holiness Pope Gregory the Blessed remarked.
When the Adige River overflowed up to the upper windows of the church where his venerable body rested, the water did not enter the church, even though the doors were open.
It did not deny its access to the enclosed places inside.
July twenty-second — The birth of Saint Mary Magdalene, from whom, as the evangelists report, the Lord expelled seven demons.
She was also privileged, among other distinguished gifts, to be the first to see Christ risen from the dead and to proclaim this to the apostles.
The burial of Saint Syntyche, who rests in Philippi.
The blessed Apostle wrote to the Philippians about her: "I urge Euodia and I plead with Syntyche to agree with each other in the Lord."
In Antioch, Cyril the bishop, Andrew, and Actebellus.
In Ancyra in Galatia, Saint Plato.
July twenty-third — In Ravenna, the birth of Saint Apollinaris, bishop and martyr.
He was ordained in Rome by the blessed Apostle Peter and sent there.
He also preached the Gospel of Christ confidently in Aemilia, parts of Corinth, Mysia, the banks of the Danube, and parts of Thrace, where he was exiled.
Wherever he went, he showed countless virtues and endured many sufferings.
Due to relentless and frequent torment, he suffered for an extended period.
He was subjected to being barefoot on burning coals, hung on a rack, and tortured very cruelly.
His mouth was smashed with a rock, and he was imprisoned in a dreadful jail with a heavy iron weight.
He was stretched on a wooden frame.
While neglected by people, he was publicly fed by an angel.
Later, he was chained and sent into exile, where he was beaten and wounded with clubs once again.
He was sent back to prison and beaten, thus completing his martyrdom under Emperor Vespasian, with Demosthenes the patrician present.
He led the Church for 28 years, 1 month, and 4 days.
On the Tiburtine Way in Rome, at the 18th milestone, is the birthplace of Saint Vincent.
On the Acula Way is Saint Primitiva.
In Laodicea of Phrygia are Miniseus and Isichius.
On July 24th is the birth of Saint Victorinus in Rome.
In the city of Amiternum, there are 83 soldiers.
In Tuscany, near the city of Tyre, which is next to Lake Bolsena, is the martyrdom of Saint Christina the Virgin.
While still very young, strengthened by the faith and grace of Christ, she destroyed the golden idols of her father Urban, the prefect, and gave them to the poor.
For this, by her father's order, she was slapped, torn by whips, loaded with iron, and thrown into prison.
After being tortured for a long time and very cruelly, she threw pieces of her flesh into her father's face.
When she was bound to a wheel with fire set beneath and oil poured over, a flame burst out and killed a thousand pagans.
Again given to prison, she was healed and restored by an angel's visit.
Then, thrown into the sea with a heavy stone, she was saved by angelic protection.
Her father's successor, Dion, afflicted her with many tortures again; but as she prayed, the statue of Apollo, which she was ordered to worship, was suddenly reduced to ashes.
With this miracle, three thousand people were converted to the faith of Christ.
Recently, Julianus, the successor of Dion, faced a blazing furnace where she remained unharmed for five days.
She later encountered serpents sent by a sorcerer but overcame them through her faith in Christ.
Even after her tongue was cut off, she was ordered to be pierced with arrows.
Thus, the blessed virgin completed her martyrdom at just ten years old.
In the city of Emerita in Spain, Saint Victor, a soldier, along with his brothers Stercatius and Antinogenes, endured various tortures and completed their martyrdom.
On the same day, we celebrate the feast of Saints Nicaea and Aquilina.
They were converted to Christ through the preaching of the blessed martyr Christopher and received the palm of martyrdom by beheading.
July 25th marks the Feast of Saint James the Apostle, son of Zebedee and brother of John the Evangelist.
He was beheaded in Jerusalem by order of King Herod, as recorded in chapter twelve of the Acts of the Apostles.
The sacred bones of this blessed apostle were transported to Spain, laid to rest at the farthest ends of the land facing the British sea, and are venerated with great honor by those nations.
This reverence is fitting because it is said that through his presence, teachings, and miracles, these people were converted to the faith of Christ.
To affirm their faith, the apostle Paul also promised to visit them.
In the province of Lycia, in the city of Samona, we commemorate the birth of Saint Christopher.
He was beaten with iron rods but was saved by Christ's power from the flames of a raging fire.
He was eventually pierced with arrows and completed his martyrdom by beheading.
In Spain, in the city of Barcelona, the martyr Cucufas, originally from the city of Scillitana, suffered under the rule of proconsuls Galerius, Maximian, and Rufinus.
Initially, he was severely tortured and beaten, then bound in chains, stretched on a grill, and covered with vinegar and mustard, with orders to roast him.
When he appeared unharmed by the fire and flames, the wicked judge ordered him to be taken outside the city and thrown into a large fire again.
When the fire was extinguished by divine will, he was bound with iron once more and thrown back into custody.
Comforted by divine brilliance, he was once again cruelly beaten with iron thorns and bulls, and finally met his end by the sword.
His body was initially buried by Christians of the time, but was later moved.
Not far from the city of Paris, it was laid to rest in the church of the blessed martyrs Dionysius, Rusticus, and Eleutherius, and was honored until the time of the Normans.
In Rome, Pope and martyr Eutychian made a decree that only beans and grapes were to be blessed on the altar.
During his papacy, he personally buried three hundred forty-one martyrs in various locations.
He also declared that no faithful person should bury a martyr without a dalmatic or purple tunic until it was reported to him.
July 26th:
The birth of blessed Erastus, who was left as bishop by blessed Paul in Philippi and was crowned with martyrdom there, resting in peace.
In the Roman harbor, Hyacinthus, under consul Leontius, Luxurius from the city of Terracina, handed him over.
Cast into the fire, he was unharmed: then thrown into a strong torrent, he emerged safely on the bank.
When this was reported to Leontius, he sent a spearman with soldiers to strike him with a sword.
A matron named Julia then collected his body and buried it with honor on her estate.
In Laodicea of Phrygia, the commemoration of Jovian, Julian, Aemilius, Felix, Martian, Maxima, Saturninus, and Gloriosa.
July 27th:
In Nicomedia, the birth of blessed Hermolaus the priest, whose teachings converted the blessed Pantaleon to the Christian faith.
This holy priest, held by Maximian, was sentenced to death for confessing Christ.
Likewise, the passion of the saints Julia, Jocunda, and Januarius occurred there.
In Sicily, the memory of monk Simeon.
In the city of Nola, the remembrance of Saint Felix, regarding the ordination of the bishopric, where many miracles occur.
At Auxerre, the burial of Saint Aetherius, bishop.
July 28th:
In Laodicea of Phrygia, the birth of the saints Auxentius, Prudentius, Theophilus, Philip, Alexander, Zoticus, Byssia, Secunda, and Macarius.
In Nicomedia, Saint Pantaleon, a young boy, was studying medicine under the orders of Maximianus.
He was converted to Christianity by the priest Hermolaus and performed many miracles, eventually bringing his father, Eustorgius, a senator, to the Christian faith.
Because of this, Maximianus subjected him to torture on the rack and burning lamps.
However, during these torments, the Lord appeared to him, and he was cooled.
Finally, he met his martyrdom by the strike of a sword.
In Milan, we remember the saints Gervasius and Protasius, Nazarius, and Celsus, a young boy.
In Lyon, Peregrinus, whose blessedness is confirmed by the glory of miracles.
In Rome, Pope Victor, a martyr, who established that wherever the Catholic Church had need, anyone converting from paganism to the Christian faith could be baptized, whether in a font, river, or sea, after making a true declaration of faith.
Also, Pope Innocent, who made decrees about the entire Church, monastic rules, Jews, and pagans.
He discovered many Cataphrygians and exiled them to monasteries; he also found the heretics Pelagius and Celestine and condemned them.
He established that those born to a Christian must be reborn through baptism, which Pelagius condemned.
In Milan, we commemorate the holy martyrs Gervasius and Protasius, Nazarius, and Celsus, a young boy.
On July 29th, in Rome, on the Via Aurelia, the birth of Saint Felix, Pope, under Constantius, son of Constantine.
Emperor Constantius, supporting the council of heretics and Valens and Ursatius, Arians, as he himself was an Arian rebaptized by Eusebius of Nicomedia, expelled Saint Felix, the bishop of the city, from his episcopal seat.
A great persecution arose among the clergy, leading to the martyrdom of many priests and clerics.
The deposed and most blessed Pope Felix lived on his small estate on the Via Portuensis.
But later, due to the actions of the heretics, he was brought into the city and beheaded, becoming a martyr.
On the same day, we commemorate the holy martyrs Simplicius, Faustinus, and Beatrice, during the reign of Diocletian and Maximian.
After enduring many different torments, they were sentenced to death by beheading, with stones tied around their necks, and were thrown from the bridge commonly known as the Stone Bridge, but referred to by scholars as the Lepidus Bridge, into the Tiber River.
Their bodies, discovered by God's will, were retrieved by their blessed sister Beatrice and the most blessed priests Crispus and John, and were buried in a place called the Sixth Philippi, on the Portuense Road.
Upon learning of this, Lucretius, a neighboring landowner, had Saint Beatrice strangled at night and, believing no one could stop him, seized the possessions of the saints.
While a certain woman was nursing her young son, the infant, as Lucretius and his accomplices were feasting, suddenly spoke these words:
"Hear, Lucretius: you have killed and seized, and behold, you are given into the possession of the enemy."
At these words, Lucretius was possessed by an evil spirit right there at the feast, tormented for three hours, and then died, earning eternal death.
We also remember the resting of the blessed Bishop Lupus of Troyes.
He traveled to Britain with the blessed Bishop Germanus of Auxerre, and after serving as a priest there for fifty years, ascended to Christ, whom he always loved, victorious over the world and the devil.
Among other miracles, during the time of King Attila, who ravaged Gaul most cruelly, as sung in his hymn:
"While wars destroyed everything, by praying, he protected Troyes."
We also honor Prosper, Bishop of Orléans, a very holy and learned man, who wrote many works for the benefit of the Church, and especially took care to defend the grace of God against the pride of heretics.
On July 30th, in Rome, in the cemetery of Pontianus, at the Bear with a Cap, we celebrate the birth of the holy martyrs Abdon and Sennes.
Decius had them captured in the Persian city called Cordula.
They were bound in chains and brought to Rome, adorned with gold and precious stones.
Presented in the temple of Intelludi to Decius and the senate, they became a spectacle for all the Roman people because they were noble sub-leaders and divinely enlightened by the Lord Jesus Christ.
Then, in anger, Decius ordered Prefect Valerian to let them be devoured by wild beasts if they refused to worship the god Sol.
He took them before the statue of Sol near the amphitheater to sacrifice.
But when they refused and spat on the statue, Valerian commanded they be beaten with lead whips.
Then, when they were brought into the amphitheater, two lions and four bears were released upon them.
The animals roared but came to the saints' feet and did not harm them; instead, they protected them.
Valerian, filled with fury, ordered gladiators to enter, kill the blessed sub-leaders, bind their feet, and throw them before the statue of Sol.
There, the bodies of the saints lay for three days.
After three days, a subdeacon named Quirinus secretly collected the bodies at night, placing them in a leaden box in his home on the third day before the Kalends of August.
They remained hidden there until the time of Constantine.
Then, the blessed martyrs were revealed, lifted, and transferred to the cemetery of the blessed Pontian.
In Africa, in the city of Tyburbolucernaria, the martyrdom of the holy virgins Maxima, Donatilla, and Secunda took place.
Under the persecution of Gallienus, they suffered at the hands of the judge Anulinus.
He tried to force them to deny Christ through prolonged hunger and thirst, but when scorned, he ordered them to be given vinegar and gall to drink.
As they were cruelly beaten before him, he commanded lime to be sprinkled and rubbed on their wounds.
They were stretched and tortured on the rack and offered a drink called 'stativa.
'
Afterward, they were laid on a griddle over burning coals, and burning coals were brought over their hair.
Finally, they were thrown as a spectacle in the theater and trampled by all.
When he realized they were unbeatable in all things, he condemned them to face the beasts, and, bound in chains, ordered them to be brought back into the theater for the people's spectacle.
As they entered the center of the arena, they kissed each other to embrace their martyrdom in peace.
A ferocious and savage bear was released, but it became gentle and began to lick their feet.
Then Anulinus, filled with rage, commanded the holy martyrs of God to be killed by the sword.
Also in Africa, Rufus, Priscus, Paterna, Septima, Option, Ammonius, Justus, Julia, Potamia; and also Maxima.
At Auxerre, the burial of the blessed bishop Ursus.
On July 31st, at Caesarea, we remember the passion of Saint Fabius the martyr.
When he refused to carry the official standards, he was first thrown into prison for several days.
Then, brought before the tribunal and questioned repeatedly, he continued to confess Christ.
Soon after, he was sentenced to death by the furious judge, and his body was denied burial for three days.
Later, enclosed in a net, it was sunk separately into the depths of the sea along with the head.
But by the power of the Lord, the net broke, and the limbs were reunited with the head, with the neck joining the shoulders, marked by his passion.
Thus restored to wholeness, the body was carried by a gentle wave to the coastline of Cartagena, where it was buried with fitting honor by the faithful in a church.
In Africa, in the city of Sinnada, we commemorate the birth of the holy martyrs Democritus, Secunda, Dionysius, and Thyrsus.
At Auxerre, we remember the burial of Saint Germanus, bishop and confessor, renowned for his many virtues, teachings, and moderation, who also defended the faith of the Britons against the Pelagian heresy on two occasions.
However, his feast is more widely celebrated on October 1st among the Gallican Churches.
August has 31 days; the moon has 29.
August 1st.
In Antioch of Syria, the birth of the seven Maccabee brothers with their mother is commemorated.
As blessed Augustine says, they were found faithful, being tested with various sufferings before the times of revealed grace.
The cruel forerunner of the Antichrist, Antiochus, exiled them from their homeland and consecrated their native land with the shedding of holy blood, out of envy and ignorance.
In Rome, there is a station at Saint Peter in Chains.
This church was the first one he built and consecrated in Europe.
In this church, the chains with which he was bound in Jerusalem and from which he was released by angelic visitation, have been placed by the care of the faithful and are sought and venerated by the devotion of the whole world, as an ancient couplet also testifies about them.
In Arabia, in the city of Philadelphia, a synod of martyrs is celebrated.
There, also, the birth of the holy martyrs Cyril, Aquila, Peter, Domitian, Rufus, and Menander, who were crowned together on the same day.
In Italy, in the city of Vercelli, we remember Saint Eusebius, bishop and confessor.
He was exiled by the prince Constantine to Scythopolis of Arabia, and then to Cappadocia, for confessing the Catholic faith.
Under the emperor Julian, he returned to his church, and finally, while the Arians were persecuting, he suffered persecution by being dragged over stairs, but he was saved by the protection of Jesus Christ the Savior.
He completed his confession in peace within the Church.
Previously, it had been revealed in a vision that he would fly from mountain to mountain on the first of August.
The Fathers interpret this as him being lifted by the grace of the Holy Spirit from the humanity of Christ, whom he confessed on earth to be the true God made man for us, to the vision of God the Father in heaven on the same first of August.
In Spain, in the city of Gerunda, we honor Saint Felix, a martyr.
He was originally from the city of Scillitana, and when he heard about the persecutions against Christians in Spain, he quickly embarked on a merchant ship out of love for martyrdom and hurried to them.
After spreading the word of God in Barcelona, Empúries, and Girona, and strengthening many in the faith of Christ, his fame spread widely.
By the order of Dacianus, he was suddenly arrested by Rufinus, the official.
As he steadfastly confessed the name of Christ, he was first beaten with clubs and thrown into a deep prison cell.
With his hands and feet tied, and denied food and drink, he was cast into a filthy place.
After this, he was bound with heavier chains and dragged through the streets by wild mules, nearly torn to pieces.
Then he was sent to prison, where he was visited and freed by an angel at night, and healed.
When day came, he was called back to endure trials.
He was flayed with claws and hung upside down from the third hour until evening, yet he felt no pain.
Rufinus then ordered him to be taken back to prison, where throughout the night a great light shone, and the voices of angels singing were heard.
When the guards reported this to Rufinus, he ordered that, with his hands tied behind his back, he be plunged into the depths of the sea.
His bonds were immediately broken, and with angels holding his hands, he walked over the waves and reached the shore.
Rufinus ordered once more for his skin to be stripped with claws, and then to be torn to the bone, with his wounds renewed until he gave his unconquered spirit to Christ.
His body was laid to rest in Girona in the monument he had prepared for himself on the 5th of August.
In France, in the city of Bourges, the deposition of the blessed Bishop Arcadius took place.
On the 2nd of August, in Rome, in the cemetery of Callistus, the birth of Saint Stephen, Pope and Martyr, occurred under the emperors Valerian and Gallienus.
He decreed that priests and deacons should not wear sacred garments in daily use, except only in church.
When fierce persecution raged, he gathered all his clergy and encouraged them to eagerly accept the crown of martyrdom for Christ.
He ordained three priests, seven deacons, and sixteen clerics, with whom he continuously taught about the kingdom of God.
By God's grace, many Gentiles, including respectable individuals, came to be baptized by him.
Among them was Nemesius, a tribune, with his entire household, and his daughter Lucilla, who was blind but received sight through the blessed Stephen.
Also, Olympius, another tribune, along with his wife Exuperia, their son Theodulus, and many others.
Later, they achieved the glorious reward of martyrdom through their confession of faith.
The blessed Stephen celebrated Masses and held councils in the catacombs of the martyrs.
Valerian and Gallienus, with great effort, sent soldiers to search for him and captured him, along with a multitude of clergy, priests, and deacons.
When brought before Valerian's tribunal, he entered alone and, condemned to death, was taken by soldiers outside the walls of the Appian Gate to the temple of Mars.
There, he was given the choice to either worship the image of Mars or face death.
While the blessed Stephen prayed to his God, a great thunderclap occurred with terrifying lightning, causing a large part of the sacrilegious temple to collapse, and the frightened soldiers fled.
He, along with all the Christians, went to the cemetery of Saint Lucina, and after consoling them with many words, offered a sacrifice to Almighty God for them.
Hearing of these events, Valerian sent many soldiers to punish the blessed Stephen.
Upon arriving, they found him offering a sacrifice to God; fearless and steadfast at the altar, he completed his service, and they beheaded him in the same place, in his own seat.
In Antioch, the nativity of the relics of Saint Stephen, the first martyr of Christ and the first deacon in the Church, is commemorated.
It is said that one of the stones that struck him during his martyrdom is there, and many healings occur through it.
On the same day, the passion of Saint Theodota with her three sons took place in the province of Bithynia, in the city of Nicaea, during the time of Diocletian, under the count Leucadius.
He sent her bound in iron with her sons to the consul of Bithynia, Nicetius.
He ordered her firstborn son, Evodius, who boldly confessed Christ, to be beaten with clubs in his mother's presence.
While the devoted mother continued to encourage her son with sacred exhortations, Nicetius ordered a man named Hirtacus to first mock her and then place her among public prostitutes.
When he tried to seize her, an angel of God struck him on the nose, causing a severe nosebleed, and he retreated.
Then, in a fit of great fury, Consul Nicetius ordered a large fire to be lit and for the blessed Theodota and her three sons to be thrown into it.
Thus, having completed her confession of Christ, she ascended to heaven.
In Italy, in the city of Verona, the birth of Saints Felix and Nicetius is commemorated on August 3.
In Jerusalem, the discovery, or rather the taking, of the body of Saint Stephen, the first martyr of Christ, is remembered.
He was stoned by the Jews and for a time was not allowed to be buried by Christians.
Eventually, through the compassion of the blessed Gamaliel, he was taken and buried on Gamaliel's estate and mourned, as Gamaliel himself later revealed in a divine vision to a priest named Lucian in the seventh year of Emperor Honorius.
Saint Luke also briefly mentioned it, saying Acts 8: "Devout men took care of Stephen and made great lamentation over him."
We will more conveniently reveal the details of this vision, God willing, at the appropriate time, on the seventh day before the Kalends of January, when his sacred body was uncovered and transferred to Jerusalem.
Some readers, not fully understanding this revelation, think it happened at this time, but it began in early December and was undoubtedly completed by the end of the same month, so that the celebration of the first martyr of Christ would precede the birth of Jesus Christ.
In Rome, the birth of Saints Diogenes and Stephen, martyrs, is commemorated.
In Constantinople, Saint Achillas is remembered.
In Autun, the deposition of Saint Euphronius, bishop, is commemorated.
On August 4, the feast of Saint Aristarchus is celebrated, about whom the Apostle Paul writes to the Colossians: "Aristarchus, my fellow prisoner, greets you" (Colossians 4).
Regarding this captivity, I've discovered that some scholars of the Holy Scriptures have made a significant error, believing that souls are taken from heaven and condemned to bodies.
Others, with a more pious but historically inconsistent view, interpreted that the blessed Apostle Aristarchus was called a fellow prisoner by Paul because he alone truly felt and endured the captivity that we all experience.
What I've learned from my predecessors, I will pass on to future generations without envy: When the Jews rebelled against the Romans, the Romans, as usual, pretended to ignore the insult but spared Judea while devastating Bashan and Galilee or Gilead, and invading Giscala, the homeland of blessed Paul and Aristarchus.
They transported the children and their parents to Cilicia.
Thus, the Apostle, feeling like a stranger in many ways, constantly longed with the holy Fathers for the heavenly Jerusalem, yet frequently visited the earthly one to learn, as we have indicated.
In Rome, in a sandy crypt, the blessed martyr Tertullinus, whom blessed Pope Stephen consecrated as a priest in his white garments after baptism, was seized by the prefect Marcus two days later and brought to Emperor Valerian.
Valerian ordered him to be stretched out and beaten with clubs.
While he gave thanks to Christ amid the beatings, Valerian commanded fire to be placed at his sides.
Even as he remained joyful and steadfast, he was handed over to Sapricius, the prefect, who first ordered his mouth to be smashed with stones, then stretched him on the rack, tortured him with tendons for a long time, and finally roasted him with fires.
Strengthened by the grace of the Holy Spirit, he confessed Christ the Lord.
Sapricius reported this to Valerian, who sent back the order for Tertullinus to be beheaded.
Sapricius then commanded that he be taken down from the rack, led along the Via Lavicana to the second milestone, and there beheaded.
Pope Stephen and the clergy gathered his body, and after singing hymns of thanks to God, they buried it in the same place in the sandy crypt.
In Rome, on the Tiburtine Way, Crescentian and Justus are commemorated.
We also remember Justin the priest, who, as recounted in the passion of Saint Lawrence, converted many to Christianity and buried the bodies of numerous martyrs.
In Lyon, France, the arrival of the body of Saint Justus, a bishop from the desert, is celebrated.
On August 5th in France, in the city of Châlons, we remember the burial of Saint Memmius, the bishop and confessor.
It is said that he was ordained by the blessed Apostle Peter and sent to France with Saint Denis and Eucherius to preach the word of God.
After living an extraordinary life and performing many miracles, he moved on to eternal life.
In Rome, Pope Hormisdas, who served for 17 years, organized the clergy and taught the psalms, and was buried in the church of the blessed Peter.
In Augusta Euphratensis, we celebrate the birth of Saint Afra, the martyr.
Due to the similarity of names, Augusta and Afra, some believed that on this day in Augsburg, Recia, or Vindelica, the passion of Saint Afra was fulfilled, about which we will speak more in the future, God willing.
In Autun, we commemorate the burial of Saint Cassian, the bishop.
Elsewhere, we celebrate the birth of Saints Florian and Celestine.
On August 6th in Rome, on the Appian Way, in the cemetery of Callixtus, we commemorate the birth of Saint Sixtus, the bishop and martyr.
Also remembered are the deacons Felicissimus and Agapitus, in the cemetery of Praetextatus, under the Emperor Decius and Prefect Valerian.
They captured the most blessed elder, Saint Sixtus, the Roman bishop, along with all his clergy, and held them in public custody for many days.
Later, Decius ordered the blessed Sixtus, along with the two deacons, Felicissimus and Agapitus, to be presented to him in the temple of Intellus, and when they refused to sacrifice to idols, they were placed in private custody.
When they were presented again to Decius and Valerian, on Valerian’s suggestion, Decius ordered them to be taken to the temple of Mars, and if they refused to sacrifice, they should be executed there.
When they were brought to the temple, the blessed Sixtus spoke to the temple of Mars: May Christ, the Son of the living God, destroy you.
And when all the Christians responded, Amen, suddenly part of the temple collapsed and shattered.
The blessed Lawrence cried out, saying, Do not abandon me, Holy Father, because I have already spent the treasures you entrusted to me.
The soldiers who heard about the treasures seized the blessed Lawrence, the archdeacon, and led the holy Sixtus, Felicissimus, and Agapitus to the hill of Mars, where they were beheaded.
That night, the clergy and many Christians gathered to collect the bodies of the saints, and they were honorably buried in the mentioned places.
Also beheaded with them were four others: Januarius, Magnus, Vincentius, and Stephanus the subdeacons, as recorded in the papal acts.
Saint Quartus also suffered with them, as noted by the great scholar Cyprian.
This blessed Sixtus was born and educated in Athens; initially a philosopher, he later became a disciple of Christ.
He served as bishop for one year, ten months, and thirty-three days.
In Rome, there were one hundred sixty-five soldiers, and the martyrdom of Saint Afra the virgin.
On the same day in Spain, in the city of Complutum, Justus and Pastor, brothers, who were still children in school, threw down their tablets and ran voluntarily to martyrdom.
They were immediately ordered to be held by Count Dacian, and with mutual encouragement, they strengthened each other and were led outside the city to be executed in the Field of Praise.
On August seventh in Rome, the passion of twenty-five holy martyrs occurred.
Likewise, the holy martyrs Peter and Juliana, with eighteen others, were commemorated.
In Tuscany, in the city of Arezzo, the birth of Saint Donatus, bishop and martyr, is celebrated.
He was raised by the holy priest Pigmentius under the title of the blessed Pastor and was well-educated in both divine and human letters.
Together with him, Julian grew up and was ordained a subdeacon.
However, later, he rejected this rank, became an apostate, and aspired to power.
At that time, the blessed Pigmenius was imprisoned in Rome, and the holy parents of Donatus were killed by the sword.
Donatus, a reader, fled to the city of Arelium and lived with the devout monk Hilarinus, serving the Lord with constant prayers and fasting.
A woman named Suranna, a non-believer and pagan who was blind, along with her only son, Herculius, sought out the cell of the blessed Hilarinus, where Donatus was staying.
Hilarinus and Donatus led her, instructing her in the faith of Christ, to the blessed bishop Satyrus.
He accepted her faith, gave thanks to God, and prescribed a fast for her, asking her to humble herself in sackcloth and ashes.
He then instructed her in the faith and baptized her and her son.
Immediately, Suranna's eyes were opened.
Upon hearing this, Apronianus brought his demon-possessed son to the blessed Donatus.
When Donatus prayed with the blessed bishop Satyrus and the blessed Hilarinus, the demon was cast out, leaving the boy healthy.
Not long after, a man named Eustasius, the governor of Tuscany and tax collector, found himself detained while his enemies arrived.
His wife, Euphrosyna, hid the tax money, and a few days later, while her husband was still away, she passed away.
Upon his return, Eustasius was summoned for the tax money and went to the blessed Satyrus and Donatus, explaining his anxiety.
Donatus stood over his wife's grave and cried out: "Euphrosyna, by Christ crucified, I adjure you to tell us what happened to the tax money, because your husband is greatly troubled by the collectors because of it."
She immediately responded from the grave: "The money you seek is hidden at the entrance of the house, buried underground."
After recovering the money, Eustasius was freed from the accusation.
With the return of the blessed Satyrus and his fathers, the blessed Donatus took on the priesthood in his place.
One day, after celebrating mass for the people, and when the congregation was reverently refreshed by the body and blood of Christ, a deacon named Anthimus was distributing the sacred blood of Christ.
Suddenly, due to a rush by pagans, he fell and shattered the holy chalice.
Both he and the followers of Christ were deeply saddened.
The Lord quickly lifted their sadness through the blessed Donatus.
The fragments of the Lord's chalice were gathered and brought to the blessed man.
Receiving them with tears, he prayed and restored the vessel to its original form.
Amazed by this miracle, the pagans, along with the Christians, acknowledged the divinity of Christ.
Around seventy-eight souls, believing in Christ, were saved through baptism.
The Lord, glorifying His holy one with many signs, led him to the crown of martyrdom.
Eventually, during the time of Emperor Julian, he was arrested by Quadratianus, the prefect.
Along with him, the man of God, Hilarinus, was ordered to sacrifice to idols.
Faithfully resisting, Quadratianus ordered Anthimus's mouth to be crushed with stones, while Hilarinus the monk was beaten with clubs in his presence until he gave up his spirit.
Then the blessed Donatus was thrown into custody.
While the Lord performed countless miracles through His servant, Quadratianus sent for him and struck him with a sword on the seventh day before the Ides of August.
The Christians buried his body with reverence near the city, and the bones of the martyr Hilarinus are kept in the city of Ostia.
In Milan, Saint Faustinus was martyred during the time of Aurelius Commodus.
In the province of Rhaetia, in the city of Augusta, was the birth of Saint Afra.
Although she was a pagan and a prostitute, through the teachings of Saint Narcissus, bishop of Girona, and guided by God's grace, she converted to Christ and was baptized with her entire household.
For confessing the Lord, she was handed over to the fire with her mother Hilaria and the girls, Digna, Eumenia, and Euprepia, on the eighth day before the Ides of August.
In Rome, the birth of Saint Cyriacus.
After a lengthy imprisonment under Maximian, alongside his fellow deacon Sisinnius, Largo, and Smaragdus, he performed numerous miracles.
This included healing and baptizing Diocletian's daughter, Artemia, from demonic possession at the emperor's request.
He was also sent by Diocletian to Persia to similarly free and baptize King Shapur's daughter, Jobia, along with the king and 330 others.
Upon returning to Rome after Diocletian's death, he was arrested by Maximian's son for converting his sister to Christianity.
Maximian ordered that on the day of his procession, he be dragged naked and chained in front of his carriage.
Afterwards, he was taken from prison with his companions Largo, Smaragdus, and Crescentianus, and by the order of the deputy Carpasius, his head was covered with pitch.
Four days later, he was taken from prison again, stretched on a rack, tortured, and beaten with rods.
A few days after that, on Maximian's orders, he was beheaded along with Largo, Smaragdus, and 20 others.
Their bodies were collected at night by the priest John and buried on the Via Salaria on the 15th of March.
Eight days later, the blessed Bishop Marcellus, along with the devout matron Lucina, anointed the bodies of the saints with spices and linens.
They then transferred them to his estate on the Via Ostiensis, seven miles from Rome, and personally reburied them in stone sarcophagi on the 8th of August.
Meanwhile, the deputy Carpasius seized the house of Cyriacus, which had been given to him by Emperor Diocletian, and Maximian immediately granted it to him.
Upon entering, Carpasius found the place where Saint Cyriacus the deacon had built a fountain, consecrated by the blessed Bishop Marcellus, where those coming to the faith were baptized by the blessed Cyriacus.
Carpasius set up a bath for himself at this location, and while he and nineteen others laughed at the Christian faith, they suddenly fell down and died.
In Nicomedia, we celebrate the feast day of Saints Nazarius, Julian, and the virgin Agape, along with Eutychianus, Philadelphia, and Leonidas.
In the city of Vienne in Gaul, we remember the birth of Saint Severus, a priest and confessor.
According to his story, he was of Indian origin, fervently dedicated to the faith of Christ, and undertook a challenging journey to preach the Gospel, eventually reaching Vienne.
There, through his words and miracles, he converted many pagans to the Christian faith.
When he passed away peacefully, he was buried in the basilica of Saint Stephen, renowned for his signs and deeply honored by the faithful.
August ninth marks the Vigil of Saint Lawrence.
On the same day in Rome, we celebrate the feast of Saint Romanus the martyr.
Inspired by the confession of Saint Lawrence, he asked to be baptized by him; and immediately, by the order of Decius, he was beaten with clubs and beheaded.
In the city of Verona, Firmus and Rusticus suffered during the reign of Emperor Maximian and his advisor Anulinus.
In the East, we remember the suffering of many martyrs.
In Cologne, Faustinus, Marcellinus, Secundianus, and Verianus, according to the Martyrology of Saint Jerome, were baptized by blessed Sixtus because of the continuation of times and are said to have been killed by Decius.
August tenth—In Rome, on the Via Tiburtina, we commemorate the birth of Saint Lawrence, archdeacon and martyr under Emperor Decius.
Blessed Sixtus left all the Church's properties and treasures to him as he went to receive the crown of martyrdom.
Lawrence generously distributed these to the weak, the poor, widows, and those in need.
Upon hearing this, Emperor Decius ordered him to be brought before him and handed him over to Valerian, the city prefect, who entrusted him to a certain Hippolytus, who imprisoned him with many others.
There, blessed Lawrence healed the widow Cyriaca, restored sight to Crescention, and made Lucillus, a blind man, see in the name of Jesus Christ.
Many other blind people, hearing of this, came to blessed Lawrence and were given sight.
Seeing this, Hippolytus believed, was instructed in the faith, and was baptized.
After completing three days during which, with the permission of Hippolytus, now a Christian, the blessed Lawrence distributed all the Church's resources to the poor, he presented himself at the Sallustian palace.
Decius, angry, ordered him to be stripped and beaten with scourges.
Later, the blessed Lawrence, bound in chains, was taken to the palace of Tiberius to be heard there.
Full of rage, Decius ordered him to be beaten while naked.
As he was being beaten, he cried out to Caesar, Look, wretch, even now recognize that I do not feel your torments.
Then Decius ordered the rods to be increased and red-hot iron plates to be applied to his sides.
The blessed Lawrence said, "Lord Jesus Christ, God from God, have mercy on me, your servant, because I did not deny you when accused; when questioned, I confessed you as the Lord Jesus Christ."
And while he was being beaten for a long time with leaden whips, he said, "Lord Jesus Christ, who for our salvation deigned to take the form of a servant to free us from the service of demons, receive my spirit."
And a voice was heard: "Many struggles still await you."
Then, stretched out on a rack and severely beaten with scourges, smiling and giving thanks, he said, "Blessed are you, Lord God, Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has granted us mercy, which we do not deserve: but you, Lord, in your kindness, grant us grace, so that all those standing around may know that you comfort your servants."
Then one of the soldiers, named Romanus, believed in the Lord Jesus Christ, and said to the blessed Lawrence, "I see before you a most beautiful man, standing with a linen cloth, wiping your wounds. I implore you by Christ, who sent his angel to you, do not abandon me."
The blessed martyr was then lifted from the rack and released, returned to Hippolytus, only in the palace. Romanus came with a pitcher, threw himself at the feet of the blessed Lawrence to be baptized; and soon after being baptized, having proclaimed himself a Christian with a public voice, he was taken outside the walls of the Salaria Gate and beheaded.
Decius Caesar went to the baths near the Palace of Sallust at night.
When Saint Lawrence was brought before him, they displayed all sorts of torture devices: lead whips, clubs, metal plates, claws, beds, and sticks.
Decius said to the blessed martyr, "Now abandon your deceitful magic arts and tell us about your noble heritage."
Lawrence replied, "As for my heritage, I am Spanish, educated and raised Roman, and a Christian from birth, instructed in every holy and divine law."
Decius commanded, "Sacrifice to the gods, because if you do not, this night will be spent on you with tortures."
Lawrence replied, "My night has no darkness, but shines entirely in the light."
As stones were being thrown at his face, he laughed and felt strengthened, saying, "I thank you, Lord, because you are the Lord of all things."
A bed with three ribs was brought, and the blessed Lawrence, stripped of his clothes, was stretched out on an iron grid.
While being scorched with iron forks from above, he said to Decius, "I have offered myself as a sacrifice to God for a sweet fragrance, because the sacrifice to God is a broken spirit."
The executioners urgently applied hot coals, placing them under the grid and pressing down on him with iron forks.
Saint Lawrence said, "Learn, wretched one, the power of my Lord Jesus Christ, my God, for your coals bring me refreshment, but for you, they bring eternal torment."
"The Lord knows that I did not deny when accused, and when questioned, I confessed Christ. Roasted, I give thanks."
With a beautiful face, he said, "I thank you, Lord Jesus Christ, for deeming me worthy to be strengthened by you."
Lifting his eyes to Decius, he said, "Look, wretched one, you have roasted one side; turn me over and eat."
Giving thanks and glorifying God, he said, "I thank you, Lord Jesus Christ, for allowing me to enter your gates," and he released his spirit.
At the first light of dawn, as it was still twilight, Hippolytus took his body, wrapped it with linens and spices, and sent word of this to Justin the priest.
Then, the blessed Justin and Hippolytus, filled with sorrow, took the body of the blessed martyr Lawrence and went to the Via Tiburtina, to the estate of a widow named Cyriaca, in the Verano field.
This was where the blessed martyr had stayed at night and to whom he had given a cloth to wipe the saints' feet.
There, in the evening, they buried him on August 10.
They fasted while keeping vigil for three days with a multitude of Christians.
The blessed Justin, a priest, offered a sacrifice of praise, and everyone participated.
On the same day, Claudius, Severus, Crescentius, and Romanus suffered, just as the blessed Lawrence did, three days after the martyrdom of Saint Sixtus.
In Rome, on that day, one hundred and forty-five soldiers perished.
On August 11, in Rome, between the two laurels, was the birth of Saint Tiburtius, son of Chromatius, the city prefect, who was highly educated.
He was taught in the faith by the blessed Sebastian and Saint Tranquillinus, and the glorious priest Polycarp, who renewed him in the sacred font of baptism and baptized his household of mixed gender, numbering one thousand four hundred with him.
Due to the severity of the persecution, Tiburtius, along with his father and a large number of Christians, went to Campania following the advice of Pope Caius.
Burning with the love of martyrdom, he remained in the city of Rome.
While he was there, engaged with the blessed Pope Caius in fasting and prayers, he encountered a man who had fallen from a height and was so injured that those concerned were only considering his burial.
Tiburtius approached him and began to slowly recite the Lord's Prayer and the Creed over his wounds, and the man was healed, as if nothing had happened to him.
Then Tiburtius took his relatives aside from the crowd and revealed to them the power of Christ.
Seeing their hearts firmly set in the fear of the Lord, he brought them to Pope Caius, who baptized the healed young man and his thankful parents together.
Meanwhile, as the storm of persecution grew more severe, a man named Torquatus, pretending to be faithful, joined the true servants of Christ.
He cunningly planned for the pagans to capture Saint Tiburtius while he was praying.
After being captured and brought before Fabian, the prefect of the city, Tiburtius steadfastly confessed his faith in Christ.
Fabian ordered burning coals to be placed in front of him and said, "Choose one of two things: either offer incense to the gods on these coals or walk over them with bare feet." However, Tiburtius made the sign of the cross and confidently walked over the coals with bare feet, saying, "Abandon unbelief and learn that the God we confess is the only one who rules over all creation. For in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, it feels as though I am walking over rose petals, because creation itself obeys the Creator's command."
Fabian replied, "Who doesn't know that Christ taught you magic?" Then the blessed Tiburtius shouted, "Be silent, wretched one, and do not force your vile words upon my ears by using the sweet and holy name with a rabid mouth." Angered, Fabian pronounced a death sentence, ordering him to be killed by the sword.
The glorious martyr Tiburtius was led away on the Via Lavicana, three miles from the city, struck with a single sword blow, and passed away. He was buried in that same place by a Christian relative on August 11th.
On the same day in Rome, Saint Susanna, a virgin and martyr, suffered under the emperors Diocletian and Maximian, with Macedonius as the judge. She was the daughter of the esteemed priest and martyr Gabinius, brother of Pope and martyr Caius, and was born of a noble lineage. Her father had raised her with great care and taught her divine literature.
Hearing about the girl's exceptional beauty and wisdom, Diocletian sent a cousin of his, named Claudius, to ask Gabinius for her hand in marriage to his son, Augustus Maximinus.
Despite objections from his daughter, father, and especially his uncle, even Claudius, guided by the blessed Gaius, was baptized along with his wife, Euprepia, and their children, Alexander and Cutia.
His faith grew so strong that he sold all his possessions and gave them to poor Christians.
Upon hearing this, Diocletian sent his brother, Maximus, to deal with the girl Susanna.
Maximus, also guided by the blessed Gaius and Gabinus and baptized in Christ, began to sell his possessions.
Through a friend named Thrason, a very devoted Christian, he ministered in villages and prisons.
When Diocletian learned of this, he sent Julius to punish Claudius, Maximus, Euprepia—also known as Praepedigna, a name derived from Greek and Latin—Alexander, and Cutia.
He ordered his son Maximinus to mistreat Susanna in his house as he wished.
Upon entering the house where the holy virgin was praying, Maximinus saw a great light over her.
Terrified, he ran back to the palace.
Hearing this, Diocletian sent Macedius to confine her in her father's house.
He began to beat her with clubs after stripping her.
The blessed virgin, steadfast in her confession of Christ, was struck with a sword and surrendered her pure spirit to the Lord.
Her body was secretly collected by Serena Augusta, a covert Christian.
She wrapped it in spices and linens with her own hands and placed it next to Saint Alexander on August 11th.
She wiped the blood with a sea veil and placed it in a silver box in her palace, where she devoted herself to secret prayers day and night.
The martyrdom of many saints in Nicopolis on August 12th.
In the city of Catania in Sicily, the feast day of Saint Euplius the Deacon, under the emperors Diocletian and Maximian.
When he declared himself a Christian outside the curtain of the secret chamber, he was brought into the auditorium by the order of Consul Calvisianus.
As he steadfastly confessed his faith there, Calvisius, filled with anger, ordered him to be tortured more severely and finally pronounced the sentence, saying: "We order Euplus to be executed by just judgment."
Blessed Euplus, giving thanks to God, knelt down, prayed, and prepared his neck to be beheaded on August 11.
His body, embalmed with spices, was buried in a revered place in the city of Catania on August 12.
On the same day, the martyrdom of Hilary, the mother of the blessed Afra, occurred.
While she was keeping vigil at her tomb, she, along with Digna, Emenia, and Euprepia—holy maidens of Afra—was delivered to the fire for the faith of Christ by persecutors.
This is part of the history of Saint Julian and his companions.
In Syria, in the village of Magarito, the feast day of Saints Macarius and Julian is celebrated, where many monks gather in devotion.
On August 13, in Rome, we commemorate the birthday of Saint Hippolytus, who, during the time of Emperor Decius, was tied by his feet to the necks of wild horses and dragged through rough terrain until he gave up his spirit.
Also remembered is Concordia, his nurse, who was martyred before him by being beaten with lead-weighted scourges.
And nine others from his household, who were beheaded together.
We also remember Dorosilla and Saint Cassian.
When Cassian refused to worship idols, he was asked by the persecutor about his profession, and he replied that he taught children writing.
Immediately, stripped of his clothes and with his hands tied behind his back, he was placed in the middle, and the children, whom he had angered by teaching, were given the opportunity to kill him.
As much as they hated learning, they took delight in taking revenge; some hit him with tablets and boxes, while others wounded him with styluses.
The weaker their hands were, the longer the punishment of martyrdom was prolonged, delaying his death.
This account was written by the poet Prudentius.
The burial of Queen Radegund at Poitiers marks a significant event.
Once residing in the palace, she devoted herself to pleasing God through fasting, prayers, and charitable acts.
Later, she was consecrated as a nun by Saint Medard, the bishop of Soissons, dedicating her life as a living sacrifice to Christ.
She endured numerous hardships for His love, even having her holy arms bound with bronze rings, a custom of non-believers.
However, the rewarder of the faithful deemed her worthy of compensation in this life, granting her everything she requested in His name.
August fifteenth—The Eve of the Assumption of Saint Mary.
In Rome, we remember the burial of Saint Eusebius, a bishop and confessor.
Before Emperor Constantius, an Arian, he steadfastly defended the Catholic faith, lamenting that Pope Liberius had agreed with Arian treachery.
By Constantius's order, he was confined in a small room in his house, measuring just four feet wide, where he persevered in prayer for many days.
After seven months, still confined, he passed away on August twenty-third.
His body was gathered by priests Gregory and Orosius and buried in a crypt next to the blessed Bishop and Martyr Sixtus, on the Appian Way, in the Cemetery of Callistus.
They inscribed his title as: Eusebius, man of God.
When Constantius learned that Gregory and Orosius had buried the blessed Eusebius in the same crypt, he ordered Gregory to be imprisoned alive.
However, Orosius, the priest, managed to rescue him while he was still half-alive, and later, he buried him next to Saint Eusebius after he passed away.
A severe persecution ensued against the Catholic Church by the Arians, during the time Liberius held the apostolic seat.
In Syria, the birth of Saint Fortunatus is noted.
In Africa, Demetrius.
Elsewhere, Eutychius, Paul, Eraclius, Possessor, Parmius, Disseus, Hermas, Prospolinus, Prosalamus, Hermias.
Also, Heraclius with three others.
In Aquileia, the birth of Saints Felix, Fortunata, and Vincentia is remembered.
Also elsewhere, Eusebius, founder of the Title.
August sixteenth.
The Assumption of the Blessed Mary, Mother of God.
Although this event is often referred to as the passing, deposition, or sleep of other saints, or even their birth, it's worth mentioning for the benefit of our viewers what the venerable Father Gregory of Tours, a bishop, thought about this particular assumption in his Book of Miracles.
After the glorious ascension of the Lord, which inspired the faithful to focus on heavenly matters by defeating evil, the holy apostles of our Lord and Savior, along with the Blessed Mary, His mother, gathered in one house.
They shared everything, and no one claimed anything as their own.
Instead, they held everything in love, as the sacred apostolic account narrates.
Following this, they dispersed to various regions to preach the Word of God.
Finally, when Blessed Mary had completed her earthly life and was called from this world, all the apostles gathered from different regions at her home.
Upon learning that she was to be taken from the world, they kept vigil with her.
And behold, the Lord Jesus came with His angels, took her soul, entrusted it to the archangel Michael, and departed.
At dawn, the apostles lifted her body, placed it in a tomb, and watched over it, awaiting the arrival of the Lord.
And behold, the Lord stood by them again, and He ordered the holy body, taken up in a cloud, to be carried to paradise.
There, reunited with her soul, she rejoices with His chosen ones, enjoying eternal good without end.
Up to this point, Gregory.
If anyone wonders how Gregory, situated in the West, learned of events that occurred in the East, they should recognize from his other writings that people from all over the world would gather at Saint Martin’s, much like they would with philosophers, and that holy places in Judea were often visited by those from the western parts of the world.
This continued to be customary up until the times of the Norsemen.
But lest the same Catholic and venerable Father seem to have thought against the Apostle, where he says: Christ has risen from the dead, the firstfruits of those who have fallen asleep.
Since death came through a man, the resurrection of the dead also comes through a man.
Just as everyone dies in Adam, so in Christ, everyone will be made alive, but each in their own order: Christ is the first, then those who belong to Christ at his coming.
First Corinthians chapter 15.
It's important to understand that the special assumption of the body of the venerable mother of God, Mary, or those who are said to have risen with the Lord and are believed to have ascended to heaven, supports apostolic authority rather than opposes it.
It is fitting that the body in which God chose to become incarnate should be taken up to heaven quickly, and that those who are witnesses of our true resurrection and ascension should precede us, without a doubt.
Since very learned scholars seem to disagree among themselves about these matters, it is not my place to define them in such a brief work.
However, we certainly believe and confess with the universal Church that if that most revered body in which God was made incarnate is still hidden somewhere on earth, its revelation is surely reserved for the destruction of the Antichrist.
On the same day in Nicomedia, the birth of the saints Straton, Philip, and Eutychianus, with their companions.
In Rome, Saint Tarsicius, a martyr.
When the pagans found him carrying the sacraments of Christ's body, they began to question what he was doing and carrying.
But he, judging it unworthy to betray the pearls to the swine, was beaten with clubs and stones until he gave up his spirit.
When his body was turned over, the sacrilegious attackers could find nothing of Christ's sacraments in his hands or clothing.
The Christians collected his body and buried it in the cemetery of Callistus on the Appian Way.
Seventeenth of August.
In Nicaea of Bithynia, the birth of Saint Ursatius, a confessor under the persecutor Licinius.
He then left the army and led a solitary life in a certain tower of the aforementioned city, becoming so famous for his virtues that he is said to have expelled demons and killed a huge dragon through prayer.
This is written in the fifth book of the Tripartite Church History.
In Rome, we have Saint Serena, the former wife of Emperor Diocletian.
In Alexandria, Saints Orion, Aemilius, and Agnatus were born.
Thyrsus and his companions hail from Persia.
This all occurred on August seventeenth.
In Caesarea of Cappadocia, Saint Mamas, also known as Mammas, was born.
During the reign of the tyrant Aurelian, amidst severe persecution of Christians, he, just a ten-year-old child, abandoned everything to live in the mountains with his sheep, surviving on their milk.
While there, a divine vision revealed to him how he would suffer for Christ.
Wild beasts would approach him, yet he would calmly read the Gospel each day, and they were gentle around him.
With their milk, he provided food for himself and other impoverished people.
When the governor, Alexander, heard he was living among wild animals, he suspected magic and summoned him, subjecting him to numerous tortures, like stretching him on the rack and casting him into a fiery furnace, but the flames did not harm him.
Later, he ordered him to be stoned until his body was almost completely covered with stones.
Thinking he was dead, the persecutor left.
However, the Lord preserved his martyr unharmed and eventually called him to the heavenly kingdom, where he peacefully surrendered his spirit and entered eternal rest.
In Africa, we remember the holy martyrs: Liberatus the abbot, Boniface the deacon, Servius and Rusticus the subdeacons, Rogatus and Septiminus, who were monks, and Maximus, the boy.
During the Vandal persecution, under the orders of the cruel and impious King Henry, they were taken from their monastery near the city of Capsa and brought to Carthage.
There, for professing the Catholic faith and defending the one baptism, they were first imprisoned, burdened with heavy iron weights, and confined to dark places.
Day and night, they strengthened the Christian people in their steadfast faith.
Enraged, the tyrant ordered a ship to be filled with bundles of wood.
He had them all tied up to be burned in the middle of the sea by setting it on fire.
When the fire was kindled in the wood, according to the wicked king's will and his cruel ministers, their hands and feet stretched out and lifted, it was immediately extinguished by divine command, visible to all.
Every time the fire was rekindled, the flames were extinguished again and again.
In his fury and shame, the tyrant ordered them to be killed with oars, crushing their skulls like dogs.
They completed their beautiful course of struggle, crowned by the Lord.
Their bodies were thrown into the sea, but at the same hour, they were returned unharmed to the shores.
They were reverently taken by the Christian people, led by the clergy with solemn hymns, and continuously buried in the monastery of the basilica called Celerinae.
Blessed Victor, the African bishop, writes in the history of the Vandal persecution, which he endured along with others, with a faithful and illustrious style.
In Alexandria of Orion, on August 19th—In the city of Praeneste, 33 miles from Rome, the feast of Saint Agapitus the martyr was held under Emperor Aurelian and Governor Antiochus.
At fifteen years old and fervent for martyrdom for the love of Christ, he was arrested by the emperor's order.
He was beaten for a long time with raw sinews, then handed over to the governor to be forced to sacrifice.
He was locked in the harshest and darkest prison and denied all food for four days.
Then, when brought from prison before the governor, he was ordered to have burning coals placed on his head.
As the martyr gave thanks to God, he was beaten with whips and hung upside down over harsh smoke.
He told the governor, "Your wisdom and vanity work in smoke," and was whipped again by four men taking turns.
Then, the servants of the devil poured boiling water over his stomach.
Meanwhile, the judge fell from his seat and, after being helped by his assistants, was laid on a bed.
Sensing the power of God in the martyr, he soon lost his sad life.
News of the blessed Agapitus reached the emperor, who ordered that the holy man be thrown to the lions.
However, the tamed beasts bowed down and licked the martyr's feet.
Seeing this, the wicked servants removed the holy martyr from the crowd and took him to the city of Praeneste, where there are two columns, and there they struck him with a sword on that day.
His head looms like a mountain before me, causing me to tremble.
So, he was handed over to others, and filled with joy, he washed his hands with water, knelt, humbly lowered his neck to the ground, and offered a prayer, embracing martyrdom.
In Capua, we commemorate the birth of Saint Rufus, a martyr, who was taught and baptized by Blessed Apollinaris.
In Tomis, we honor the holy martyrs Marcellinus the tribune, his wife Mannea, their son John, Serapion the cleric, and Peter the soldier.
In Gaul, in the city of Arles, we remember Saint Caesarius, the bishop and confessor.
In Autun, we celebrate Saint Syagrius, the bishop and confessor.
On August 28, we remember the most blessed Hermes, a martyr.
While he was a prefect, he was baptized by Alexander the pope and martyr, along with his sons and household.
Then, imprisoned by Emperor Aurelian, he converted Tribune Quirinus and his entire household to the faith.
Upon hearing this, Aurelian ordered the beheading of Blessed Hermes.
On the same day, in Africa, we commemorate the passing of Saint Augustine the bishop, a man remarkable in all knowledge.
Having converted from the heresy of the Manichaeans to the grace of Christ through the teaching of Bishop Ambrose, he became a most worthy bishop of the Church of Hippo.
His venerable body, previously moved from his city to Sardinia because of the barbarians, was recently brought back to Pavia and honorably interred by Liutprand, King of the Lombards.
On the same day, in Emmonia, a city in the province of Carnia, we recall the suffering of Saint Pelagius the martyr.
During the time of Emperor Numerian, under the judge Velasius, he was first burdened with an iron weight on his neck and hands for the faith of Christ and thrown into prison.
Upon being brought out, he was beaten with rods, then clubbed, later suspended on a rack, torn with claws, had boiling oil poured into his belly, dragged over fragments of pottery with his hands and feet bound, and finally beheaded.
On the same day, in the town of Brillat, we mark the birth of Saint Julian, who was killed by having his throat cut by persecutors for confessing Christ.
In Constantinople, we remember Saint Alexander, bishop and confessor, whose prayer caused Arius to burst open, spilling his intestines onto the ground.
On the same day, in Saintes, we honor Saint Vibiana, a bishop.
August 29th—In Rome, we commemorate Sabina, a martyr who suffered under Emperor Hadrian, with Elpidius as the city prefect.
All her possessions were designated for either the church or public titles.
She was laid to rest in the tomb where she had placed the blessed martyr Seraphia, her teacher in faith, near the arch of Faustina, close to the Vinditian area in the town of Vindinum.
On the same day, the beheading of Saint John the Baptist is remembered, initially buried in Samaria and now in Alexandria.
Additionally, his head was moved from Jerusalem to the city of Edessa in Phoenicia.
August 30th—In Rome, on the Ostian Way, we remember the martyrs Felix and Adauctus.
Felix was forced to sacrifice to various gods, but when he blew over the statues of Serapis, Mercury, and Diana, they fell.
For this act, he was hung on the rack and, while still alive, taken down and ordered to be beheaded.
As he was being led away, a Christian met him and, inspired by divine intervention, cried out: "And I worship the same Lord Jesus Christ whom this holy priest confesses."
He was immediately arrested and beheaded alongside the blessed Felix.
Later, Christians referred to him as Adauctus because his name was unknown, as he was added to the martyr Felix for the crown; thus, the crown of martyrdom was increased by his confession of faith.
August 31st—In Trier, we honor Saint Paulinus, bishop and confessor.
During the Arian persecution, he was exiled by Emperor Constantius for his Catholic faith and endured until death, receiving the crown of blessed passion in Africa.
On the same day in Athens, blessed Aristides, renowned for faith and wisdom, presented books on the Christian religion to Emperor Hadrian, eloquently arguing in his presence that Jesus Christ was truly God.
September has thirty days, but the moon has twenty-nine.
September first—Joshua and Gideon.
Today, we remember the birth of the most holy virgin Verena, of Theban descent.
Her parents entrusted her to a bishop named Chaeremon for her education, and he was later martyred.
She traveled to Lower Egypt with other believers and joined the blessed legion, including Maurice and his companions, who served as soldiers for Diocletian and Maximian.
Desiring to serve Christ as a virgin in Italy, she went to Milan and visited places where holy martyrs were kept, performing acts of piety and offering herself for martyrdom.
She was detained by a holy man named Maximus.
Upon hearing that the holy Theban legion, including Victor, whom she dearly loved, had been martyred, she crossed the Alpine mountains to Agaunum to witness the event.
There, she lived near the River Aar, close to the fortress of Solothurn, practicing remarkable discipline through fasting, vigils, and prayers both day and night.
She enclosed herself in a very narrow cave for some time to discipline her flesh.
Nearby lived an old Christian woman who sold whatever the holy virgin made, providing sustenance for the saint.
Pagan worship was still prevalent among the Alamanni.
However, through many signs performed by the Lord through His servant, the Alamanni began to be moved towards the faith of Christ.
The virgin's fame grew due to her miraculous deeds, and she became the mother of virgins, revered by all for her discernment and piety.
The devil, envious of her praiseworthy life, incited a tyrant under Roman power to afflict the virgin of God, placing her in public custody.
In prison, a young man of exceptional brightness appeared to her, and she asked who he was.
When he mentioned his name was Maurice, he was immediately surrounded by a group of courtiers and taken away from the view of the maiden who was praying.
That same night, the tyrant was struck by a severe fever.
However, after calling the maiden to him, he was quickly healed through her prayer and was then sent back with the praise of everyone to the place of the maidens.
One day, when the bread ran out, there were complaints about it.
She reminded her sisters to trust in God's divine generosity and prostrated herself in prayer for their urgent need.
And behold, unexpectedly, forty sacks full of the purest flour were found at the door of the cell, which sustained the congregation for several years.
As her life was nearing its end, weakened in body yet steadfast in her purpose, she lay on her bed.
As she awaited the end of her life, the Virgin Mary, the Mother of God, appeared, leading countless choirs of virgins.
Verena, with full devotion, asked why she deserved this honor.
The Mother of God replied: "I have come," she said, "so that you may be rewarded by Him whom you have faithfully served."
After these words, the blessed soul departed from her body.
The blessed virgin was buried in a place called Zurzach.
In Capua, we remember the birth of Priscus the martyr, one of the early disciples of Christ.
On the same day in Sens, we commemorate Lupus, the bishop, renowned for his holiness and miracles.
Also, in Caesarea of Cappadocia, we remember Longinus, a soldier and martyr, who is said to have pierced the side of the Lord with a lance.
After being baptized by the apostles, he was seized by the governor Octavius, and despite having his tongue cut out and teeth knocked out, he was beheaded for Christ.
Alongside him, Aphrodisius, the notary, received the crown, who even after his tongue was cut out, spoke of Christ fluently.
September 2nd marks the birth of Saint Justus, the bishop of Lyon, who secretly left his episcopate and traveled to Egypt, accompanied by a lector named Viator.
There, he spent several years with monks, ending his life in holy conversation.
His body, along with the bones of Saint Viator, his servant, was transported by the devout citizens of Lyon to the basilica of the Seven Maccabean Brothers.
On the same day, in the aforementioned city, was Bishop Elpidius.
At Apamea, the blessed martyr Anthony.
On September 3rd, in Rome, Seraphia, a virgin, suffered under Emperor Hadrian, with Berillus as the judge.
She, originally from Antioch and staying with Saint Sabina, was seized and brought before the governor.
When she bravely reproached him with words of faith, the enraged governor ordered her to be handed over to two young men, intending to violate her purity.
As they attempted to touch her, they suddenly fell to the ground, lifeless.
When the virgin was brought back, the young men were also presented before the governor.
Approaching them with a prayer, the virgin restored them to life.
After this, by the governor's order, she was beaten with clubs, and a splinter from them struck the tyrant's eye, instantly blinding him in one eye.
He then sentenced her to be executed by the sword.
She was buried next to her companion Sabina.
On September 4th, Moses the prophet is commemorated.
And at Ancyra in Galatia, the holy martyrs Rufinus, Silvanus, and Vitalicus are remembered.
At Chalon, we celebrate the birth of Saint Marcellus the martyr.
During the time of Antoninus, he was one of the fifty martyrs imprisoned in Lyon.
After the prison was miraculously opened, he left and converted the man who hosted him, along with his entire household, to the Lord.
Later, when he came to Chalon, he was tortured by the governor Priscus with many torments, then buried up to his waist in the earth; thus, on the third day, he surrendered his soul to God.
On September 5th, Victorinus the martyr is commemorated in the suburbs of Rome.
He and his brother Severinus grew in virtue through mutual service, living in poverty and solitude for a long time, and after giving their possessions to the poor, they entered the solitude of the desert for God.
While he was diligently practicing all these virtues, a demon, disguised as a woman, appeared at the man's door, lamenting:
"Oh, woe is me," she cried, "lost in the woods, wandering in the darkness, about to be devoured by beasts! Save me, whoever you are, resident of this place, because if I am to live, it will be yours, and if I am to die, it will be yours."
As she cried out these and even more pitiable things, Victorinus opened the door. Shortly after, among other movements of the body, the image extended a foot, touched the man of God, inflicted a harmful heat, wounded him, and knocked him down.
The demon, now victorious over Victorinus, exclaimed:
"What are you doing, most perfect man? Why are you joining another, having left your brother?"
After many boasts and mocking insults, the deceiving demon vanished from sight.
Victorinus, having fallen, became like one lifeless. Finally, coming back to himself, he returned to his brother Severinus, at first remaining silent out of shame, then revealing the cause, and even imposed a punishment on himself.
He split a tree, inserted his hands through the cracks, and bolted it with wedges, sealing the scar of the tree. He did not consent to be released from this punishment even by the bishop, to whom the matter was revealed by his brother, but he endured it for three whole years.
Only on Sunday, compelled by his brother, did he take a little bread and water, while his brother also tortured himself with similar fasting for him. Finally, barely persuaded by the bishop to abandon the punishment, he lived a life of all holiness and was later chosen as the bishop of the city of Amiternum.
As time went on, under the rule of Nerva, he was examined with tortures by the judge Aurelian for a long time, and at a place called Cotialis, he was ordered to be hung upside down in stinking and sulfurous waters for three hours. As this was done for three days, he was crowned with martyrdom and departed to the Lord.
Also, in Rome, Saint Herculanus. In Capua, Quinctius, Acontius, and Donatus, Eutyches and Maro.
September sixth—The birth of Saint Magnus, confessor, disciple, and companion of the blessed Gallus, a wonderful and most holy man. Also, Zechariah the prophet, and the natal day of Onesiphorus, a disciple of the apostles.
In Africa, the birthdays of the holy confessors and bishops Donatian, Praesidius, Mansuetus, Germanus, and Fusculus are celebrated.
During the Vandalic persecution, they were brutally beaten with clubs and sentenced to exile by order of the Arian king Hunneric.
One bishop, named Laetus, was consumed by fire.
At that time, the same tyrant closed all the churches in Africa on one day and gave all the bishops’ property to his own bishops.
On September 7th, in Nicomedia, the birth of Saint John is celebrated, noted for his noble and honorable worldly dignity.
During the reign of Maximian and Diocletian, driven by his faith, he tore apart their book of impious laws in front of the people.
When the tyrants discovered this, they ordered him to be tortured in every cruel way imaginable.
Yet, even as the executioners raged against him, they could not bring sadness to this holy martyr, despite their harsh punishments.
September 8th marks the birth of the holy Mother of God, Mary.
On the same day in Nicomedia, Saint Adrian and twenty-three others were martyred.
While their story is widely read, a brief account seems necessary to aid memory.
The blessed martyr Adrian held a position of duty during Maximian's time.
Seeing the severe tortures endured by the saints, he asked what reward they expected for such suffering.
When the twenty-three martyrs explained they endured martyrdom for the unfailing joy of the heavenly kingdom, he immediately joined them and was noted among the confessors and athletes of God.
When Maximian heard Adrian’s name was listed among the saints, he ordered him to be bound in iron and taken to prison with the other saints.
Adrian was twenty-nine years old at the time.
Upon hearing this, his wife, Natalia, a devout Christian, joyfully ran to the prison and exhorted him not to withdraw from the company of the martyrs for any earthly honor or fear of impending punishment.
Adrian, who was brutally beaten on the orders of an enraged ruler, had his ribs opened, exposing his insides.
Afterwards, he was thrown back into prison with others.
When their flesh was nearly gone, they were ordered to have their legs broken with a large iron bar.
After breaking everyone's legs and cutting their feet, Adrian's hands were also cut off.
Sent to Christ in this way, Natalia sailed to Byzantium, where the saints' bodies were taken.
A few days later, she also passed away in the Lord on September 8th.
The suffering of the holy martyrs Dorotheus and Gorgonius occurred in Nicomedia under Emperor Diocletian.
They were masters of palace duties and overseers of the royal chamber.
As followers of the Christian faith, when they saw someone being horribly tortured one day, they said, "Why, Emperor, are you persecuting him, since we also worship the same?" The Emperor summoned them, ordered them to be hung, torn with whips, drenched in salt and vinegar, then placed on a grill for torture, and finally strangled by hanging.
In Sabine, 30 miles from the City, is the feast day of the holy martyrs Hyacinth, Alexander, and Tiburtius. On the same day, Pope Sergius, who served as pope in Rome for 13 years, is remembered. He found a remarkably large piece of the cross of Christ in the sanctuary of Saint Peter. He decreed that during the breaking of the Lord's body, the Agnus Dei should be sung; and that on the days of the Annunciation of the Lord, the Dormition, the Nativity of Saint Mary, and Saint Simeon, which the Greeks call the Hypapante, litanies should go out from Saint Adrian's, and the people should gather at Saint Mary’s.
On September 10th, in Africa, the feast day of the holy bishops Nemesian, Felix, and Lucius is celebrated. Also remembered are Felix, Litteus, Polyanus, Victor, Jader, and Dativus. Under Decius and Valerian, they were severely beaten with clubs for their faith in Christ, chained, and sent to work in the mines, where they completed their martyrdom. On the same day in Chalcedon, Saints Sosthenes and Victor, who fought for Christ's name with blessed Euphemia, were thrown into prison.
They were brought out and tied to a post.
A bear and the fiercest lion were then set upon them.
Yet, when the beasts did not harm them, Proconsul Priscus decided they should be burned.
Meanwhile, they focused on prayer, exchanged the kiss of peace, and passed away.
September 11 marks the birth of the holy martyrs Felix and his sister Regula.
Their feast is celebrated with great honor among us, and the account of their suffering is well-known to many.
I don't think it's necessary to add more to what has already been written.
Suffice it to say, these martyrs, part of the company of Maurice and his companions, traveled through the vast desert called Darona and arrived in the region of Germany.
There, by the river Lindimacus, they dedicated themselves to vigils and prayers with great devotion.
While engaged in these activities, messengers sent by the wicked Maximian arrived, instructing them to force the saints to sacrifice to idols or face various tortures.
The blessed martyrs boldly resisted the sacrilegious demands, confessing to be companions of the saints Maurice, Exuperius, Candidus, and Victor.
They were tied to burning iron wheels and suffered unspeakable tortures.
The most blessed Regula was placed on boiling pitch, and the executioner was ordered to give her boiling lead to drink.
When they could not be torn away from Christ by any harsh punishments, they were ordered to be beheaded.
After this, the beheaded martyrs carried their severed heads in their hands for 50 cubits from the place where they were beheaded.
On the same day, on the Salarian Way, in the cemetery of Basilla, are the martyrs Protus and Hyacinthus, who were eunuchs of the blessed virgin Eugenia.
They lived for some time in a monastery of God's servants in Egypt, and then returned to Rome with the most blessed virgin.
Under Emperor Gallienus, they were severely beaten for their faith in Christ and then beheaded together.
How blessed Eugenia, disguising herself as a man for the sake of God, led a truly holy life.
When detained by Nicetas, she reduced the statue of Diana to dust through prayer.
Even with a heavy stone tied to her shoulders, she completed her trial of passion by being thrown into the Tiber.
This story is thoroughly explained in the Book of Her Deeds.
On September 12th, in the city of Ticinum, also known as Pavia, we remember the holy confessors Syrus and Juventius.
Sent by the blessed Hermagoras, bishop of Aquileia and disciple of the blessed Mark the Evangelist, they rested in peace after fervent preaching and many miracles.
On September 13th in Alexandria, Egypt, we honor Bishop and Martyr Philip.
Initially a prefect, he was called by divine grace to become a bishop.
Under Volusianus and Gallienus, he was martyred by Prefect Perennis, achieving the palm of martyrdom.
On the same day, Saint Anianus, a priest and abbot of the monastery of Saint Romaric, led a life marked by miracles and virtues, following a path of remarkable abstinence and hermitic living.
On September 14th, in Rome, at the cemetery of Callixtus, we commemorate the birthday of Saint Cornelius, bishop, who was exiled to Centumcellae during the Decian persecution.
Later, when brought before Decius and unable to be swayed from the Catholic faith, he was ordered to be beheaded.
As he was being led away, he was asked to visit the wife of the soldier Cerealis, who had been paralyzed for five years.
At the prayer of Saint Cornelius, she stood up and was healed.
Witnessing this, many were baptized, and along with blessed Cornelius, twenty-one others were martyred, including Cerealis and his wife Salustia.
On the same day in Africa, we remember the blessed Cyprian, bishop and martyr, who, under Valerian and Gallienus, was exiled by the proconsul Aspasius.
Later recalled from exile, he was executed by the sword by Maximus, the proconsul who succeeded Aspasius, due to his unwavering faithfulness, and went to the Lord.
With him suffered Crescentianus, Auctor, Rosula, and Generalis.
The bones, along with the sacred head of Saint Pantaleon and the limbs of Martyr Speratus, were brought back by the envoys of Emperor Charlemagne from Aaron, the king of the Persians.
These relics of the blessed martyrs, granted by the emperor, were placed in his city by the bishop of Lyon.
On the same day, the Exaltation of the Holy Cross:
This cross, discovered by Helena, was divided so that one part remained in Jerusalem and the other part was taken to Constantinople.
After many years, the Persian people, led by their king Khosrow, invaded many Roman provinces, including Jerusalem.
From there, they seized many valuable ornaments and took away the Lord's cross.
Khosrow placed it in a silver tower and prepared a golden seat for himself in that tower, where he sat as if he were a colleague of God.
Consequently, the Roman Emperor Heraclius waged war against the Persians, killed Khosrow, and brought back the venerable wood with great reverence.
On that same day, many blind, paralyzed, leprous, and possessed people were healed, and even the dead were brought back to life.
On September 15—the feast day of Saint Nicomedes the Martyr, whom Count Flaccus ordered to be beaten with lead weights until he died because he buried the body of Saint Felicula the Martyr and refused to sacrifice to idols.
His body was thrown into the Tiber, collected by his deacon, and honorably buried.
On the same day, in the territory of Cavaillon, the feast day of Saint Valerian the Martyr.
On September 16—in the city of Chalcedon, the feast day of Saint Euphemia.
Under Emperor Diocletian, she was handed over with forty-nine others to the proconsul Priscus, and after imprisonment and tortures involving wheels, beatings, fires, the weight of cornerstones, axes, and fiery pans, she was brought to the theater and thrown to lions and beasts.
Then, as the blessed virgin prayed, one of the beasts approached and bit her holy body, and thus the holy soul of God departed.
On the same day, in Rome, Saints Lucia and Geminianus.
The blessed Lucia, who served God as a virtuous virgin for 36 years, was accused by her son Euprepius and forced to sacrifice to idols during Emperor Diocletian's reign, under the judges Apofrasio and Megasio.
She refused, and after enduring imprisonment and severe beatings, she was thrown into a pot of boiling pitch and lead.
Emerging unharmed, she was dragged through the city streets, weighed down with iron and lead.
When she passed by the house of a powerful man named Geminianus, a heavenly miracle—a dove resting over her head—inspired him.
He sought baptism and was killed by the sword alongside her.
Fifteen days before the Kalends of October, in Britain, it is the feast of Socrates and Stephen.
At Noviodunum, it's the feast of Valerian, Macrinus, and Gordian.
In Rome, we commemorate the birth of Saint Justin the priest, ordained by the blessed Sixtus, to whom the blessed Lawrence entrusted himself through his prayers while washing his feet.
This same Justin was responsible for burying the bodies of saints Hippolytus, Concordia, Irenaeus, Abundius, and Cyrilla, the daughter of Emperor Decius, and during the persecution by Decius, Gallus, and Volusianus, he was renowned for his confession of faith.
Also in Rome, we remember the martyrs Narcissus and Crescentionis.
In the diocese of Tongeren, we celebrate the birth of Saint Lambert the bishop.
While rebuking the royal house with religious zeal, he was killed within the church's house, and his tomb is known for frequent miracles.
Fourteen days before the Kalends of October, we honor the birth of Saint Methodius of Olympus in Lycia, who later became the bishop of Tyre and was martyred under Diocletian at Ebacide.
In Vienne, we celebrate the feast of Saint Ferreolus.
As a tribune, he was cruelly beaten for his faith in Christ, bound with chains, and imprisoned; but by God's will, he was freed from his bonds, pursued to Brivate, and beheaded.
Thirteen days before the Kalends of October, in the city of Naples in Campania, we celebrate the birth of Saint Januarius, the bishop of Benevento, along with Sosius the deacon of Miseno, the deacon Festus, and the reader Desiderius.
As they were being led to their deaths, they saw Proculus, a deacon from the city of Puteoli, along with two laymen, Eutyches and Acutius.
These men asked why the righteous were being ordered to be killed.
Realizing they were Christians, the judge ordered them to be beheaded alongside the others.
On the same day in Palestrina, it was the feast day of Saints Mark, Paul, and Nilus, bishops who, during the persecution by Diocletian, were consumed by fire along with many clergy for Christ.
In Niceria, the feast of Saint Felix and Constantia, martyrs who suffered under Nero, was observed.
In the region of the city of Lyon, Saint Sigon, a priest, is remembered.
September 20th—In Cyzicus, the feast of Saint Fausta, a virgin, and Evilasius under Emperor Maximian, is celebrated.
Evilasius, the palace's chief officer, ordered her head to be shaved, then had her suspended and tortured, even attempting to cut her in half like wood.
When the executioners failed to harm her with saws, Evilasius, astonished by this, came to believe in Christ.
When the emperor learned of this, he ordered Evilasius to be subjected to even harsher torture, while Fausta was brought out of prison naked, with nails driven into her head and body.
Afterward, a frying pan was heated, yet as she sang, it cooled down.
During these events, called by a heavenly voice, they surrendered their spirits.
September 21st—The feast of Saint Matthias, apostle and evangelist, whose passion story is well known.
September 22nd—In Spain, in the city of Sidon, at a place called Agaunum, the feast of the holy martyrs Maurice and his companions is commemorated.
They set out from the city of Thebes in the East under Emperor Maximian, with their legion of six thousand six hundred men, and were slaughtered for the faith of Christ.
They had come at Maximian's request for help, but when they refused to participate in sacrilege, to influence others to comply, he ordered every tenth man to be executed in front of them.
This decimation was carried out twice, yet the remaining men steadfastly stood by their decision, all willingly offering their necks to be slaughtered in the same way.
Maximian faced fitting punishment.
Caught plotting against his son-in-law, Constantius, he was strangled, ending his wicked life with a death he rightly deserved.
September 23rd — Sosius the deacon, about whom you can learn more on September 19th.
On this day, the virgin Thecla, resting at Seleucia, was guided by the blessed apostle Paul from the city of Iconium.
Her mother, seeing her embrace Christianity and reject marriage, accused her before the judge.
The holy Thecla was brought in and thrown onto a pyre, but after making the sign of the cross, a rainstorm extinguished the flames.
Later, she was stripped and repeatedly exposed to lions and bears, yet was protected by divine power.
She was then submerged in a pit full of water and serpents, from which divine grace delivered her unharmed.
Subsequently, she was tied to two fierce bulls, which were prodded with red-hot iron to tear her apart, but the ropes broke, and the bulls scattered, leaving the martyr unharmed.
Then the virgin was released, strengthening Tryphaena, a devout woman who witnessed her martyrdom, along with her whole household in the faith of Christ.
Thecla went to Seleucia, where she rested in peace.
September 24th — Conception of Saint John the Baptist.
At Autun, Saint Andochius the priest, Thyrsus the deacon, and Felix, who were sent by Bishop Polycarp to teach in Gaul, were flogged by Emperor Aurelian, thrown into fire, hung by their hands, and finally struck on the neck with beams, completing their martyrdom.
September 25th — Birth of the blessed Cleophas, to whom the Lord appeared on the road after His resurrection.
September 26th — The holy martyrs Cyprian the bishop and Justina the virgin.
A philosopher named Agladius in Antioch, upon seeing the blessed Justina, was inflamed with passion for her and promised the magician Cyprian two talents of gold if he could make the virgin Justina fall in love with him.
Cyprian the magician, after summoning demons, tried to lead the holy woman of God astray through them.
But when the demons couldn't accomplish this and admitted they were repelled by the sign of the Crucified, Cyprian, losing faith in the devil's power, asked Bishop Anthimus to teach him the Catholic mysteries.
Soon after, he was ordained as a deacon, and as he grew in virtues and performed miracles, he was elevated to the rank of bishop.
Bishop Cyprian and the virgin of Christ, Justina, were later arrested and chained.
The bishop was hung and tortured with hooks, while the holy woman was cruelly beaten with raw thongs after being slapped.
They were then roasted in a pan with pitch, fat, and wax, and ultimately beheaded with a sword.
A man named Theognotus was also punished alongside them under Emperor Diocletian, by Judge Eutelm.
On September twenty-seventh, in Aegea, we remember the holy martyrs Cosmas and Damian during the persecution of Diocletian, under Governor Lysias.
Originally from Arabia, they were skilled in medicine.
Their brothers were named Antimius, Leontius, and Euprepius.
Rejecting idol worship, they were tied by their feet and severely tortured.
Chained, they were thrown into the sea but saved by an angel of God.
Later, they were thrown into a burning fire, which extinguished as they prayed, and they were suspended and tortured again.
Enduring with patience, they were lifted onto a cross, stoned, and shot with arrows.
However, they were unharmed, and many of those who attacked them were struck.
Finally, the governor ordered them to be killed by the sword.
On September twenty-eighth, in Spain, in the city of Cordoba, Faustus, Januarius, and Martial were tortured on the rack.
After having their eyebrows shaved, ears and noses cut off, and upper teeth knocked out, they were disfigured and completed their martyrdom by fire.
On September twenty-ninth, on Mount Gargano, we commemorate the blessed Archangel Michael, where a church is dedicated in his name.
A wealthy man named Garganus, after whom the mountain is named, had an immense number of animals.
One day, the bull didn't return home from the pasture.
Its owner searched every path until he finally found it at the top of a mountain, standing at the entrance of a cave.
When he shot an arrow at it, the arrow bounced back with force and struck him.
Upon hearing about this, the bishop declared a three-day fast for the citizens, advising them to seek the reason for the man's death from God.
After the fast, Saint Michael appeared to the bishop, explaining that it was by his will.
He said, "I have decided to dwell in this place and claim it as my own."
He stated that there was no need for a church to be dedicated there by humans, as it was already built and consecrated by him.
He only instructed them to enter and visit the place with devout prayers.
Through heavenly miracles shown by the holy archangel, the citizens were granted victory over their enemies, and the location and numerous miracles are documented in many books.
On September thirtieth—in the town of Solothurn in Gaul, we remember the martyrdom of the holy martyrs Victor and Ursus from the Theban Legion.
By the order of Maximian, they endured dreadful punishments by Hirtacus, were thrown into the fire, and finally killed by the sword.
On the same day in Bethlehem of Judea, we commemorate the burial of Saint Jerome the priest.
He was born in the town of Stridon, which was once on the border of Dalmatia and Pannonia, to his father Eusebius.
He received the robe of Christ as a child in Rome, where he was educated in Greek and Latin literature from an early age.
He also imitated the lifestyle and deeds of the most esteemed monks.
He was ordained a priest of the Roman Church and was considered by many to be worthy of the highest priesthood.
However, after being driven out of Rome by the envy of his rivals, he went to Gregory of Nazianzus, the bishop of Constantinople, to learn.
From there, he traveled to Syria, spending four years in harsh solitude in deserted places.
Then, he settled himself wisely in the town of Bethlehem, choosing to remain in the stable of the Lord.
The dedication and perseverance he showed through vigilance and fasting, as he worked tirelessly to make the Hebrew libraries accessible to Latin audiences, is known to the one he dedicated his efforts to.
Ultimately, after living a life pleasing to God, he peacefully passed away at the age of ninety-eight in the town of Bethlehem, on September 30, during the twelfth year of Emperor Honorius.
He completed his works over a span of fifty-six years.
October. The month of October has 31 days, but only 30 lunar days.
October 1st—In Auxerre, it's the feast day of Saint Germanus, a bishop.
He was sent to Britain by the Gallic bishops to challenge the Pelagian heresy.
While traveling across the sea, a great storm arose, threatening those on board.
However, by invoking the name of the Lord, he calmed the storm.
Once in Britain, he quashed the heresy and performed miracles like restoring sight to a girl blind for ten years, extinguishing a nearby fire, and overcoming his own infirmity through divine intervention.
During a conflict between the Saxons and Picts against the Britons, Germanus led by prayer rather than force, causing the enemies to flee.
After many notable deeds, he traveled to Ravenna to advocate for peace for the Armorican people and was received with honor by Valentinian.
Shortly after, he passed away, and his body was returned to his city.
In the city of Tomis, we remember the saints Priscus, Crescentius, and Evagrius.
In Reims, Saint Remigius, a bishop and confessor known for his exceptional virtue and holiness.
He converted the Frankish people from idolatry to Christianity, starting with the baptism of their king.
Among his many deeds, he once resurrected a girl from death.
He served as a bishop for nearly seventy years.
October 2nd—Pope Eusebius, who was bishop for seven years, was buried along the Appian Way in the cemetery of Callistus.
During his time, the Lord's cross was discovered.
He reconciled heretics in the city through the laying on of hands.
In Nicomedia, we honor the birth of Saint Eleutherius, the martyr.
During Diocletian's reign, a fire broke out in the palace, and the emperor, suspecting Christians, ordered their capture, leading to some being executed and others burned.
The first among them, and the one who encouraged everyone to martyrdom, was Leudegarius.
Some were cast into flames, others were killed by the sword, and many were drowned in the sea.
However, the blessed Eleutherius, after enduring long and terrible torture, was finally thrown into flames and achieved the palm of martyrdom.
In Atratis, at the villa Syrricinio, the passion of Saint Leodegarius, bishop of Autun, took place on October 3.
The birth of Saint Dionysius the Areopagite, who was converted to the faith by the apostle Paul and ordained by him as the first bishop of Athens, occurred under the rule of Emperor Hadrian.
After a glorious confession of faith and enduring severe tortures, he was crowned with martyrdom.
Among the ancient Saxons, we remember the feast of Saints Edil and Evald, priests who came to Germany with Bishop Willibrord.
They went to the Saxons, and while preaching the word of God, were killed by pagans.
A light appeared at night over their bodies, signifying their worthiness.
October 4.
At Corinth, we remember Crispus and Gaius, whom the apostle Paul mentions in his First Letter to the Corinthians.
In Egypt, the holy martyrs Marcus and Marcellian, brothers, and with them countless others of both genders: some were handed over to flames, others drowned in the sea, some starved to death, and some were crucified, earning heaven.
October 5.
In Sicily, we remember Placidus, Eutychius, and thirty others.
In Gaul, in the city of Valence, Bishop Apollinaris was distinguished by his virtues and martyrdom.
At Eumeneia, the martyrdom of Bishop Thraseas was completed.
He was among those who claimed, as a tradition from earlier times, that the Savior instructed the apostles not to leave Jerusalem before the twelfth year.
October 6.
At Capua, we remember Saints Marcellus, Castus, Aemilius, and Saturninus.
In Gaul, in the city of Agen, the virgin and martyr Faith inspired the blessed Caprasius to martyrdom through her example.
On the same day, we commemorate the martyrdom of Sagaris, bishop of Laodicea, who was one of the disciples of the blessed apostle Paul.
October 7.
OCTOBER 6 - In Rome, on the Appian Way, we celebrate the feast day of Saint Mark, bishop and confessor.
He served as bishop for two years, nine months, and thirty days, and established that the bishop of Ostia, who consecrates bishops, should wear the pallium.
On the same day, Saints Julia, Sergius, and Bacchus were martyred under Emperor Maximian.
In the emperor's palace, Sergius held the position of chief officer and Bacchus was the second officer.
When they were accused before the emperor and found to have rejected idol worship for the true God, they stood firm in their faith despite threats or flattery.
By the emperor's command, they were stripped of their cloaks, dressed in women's robes, and dragged through the city with chains around their necks.
Finally, under the orders of Duke Antiochus, they were martyred.
Bacchus was beaten with rawhide whips and died, while Sergius was beheaded after enduring many torments.
Christians took their bodies and buried them honorably together, where the virgin Julia, who suffered under the governor Martian, rests with the martyrs.
On the same day, Saints Marcellus and Apuleius were also martyred.
They initially followed Simon Magus but, after witnessing the wonders performed by Apostle Peter, they left Simon and committed to apostolic teaching.
Following the apostles' passion, they too achieved martyrdom.
OCTOBER 8 - In Crete, in the city of Gortyna, we honor Blessed Philip, bishop, known for his great virtues.
In Thessalonica, Saint Demetrius was martyred.
Also, the birth of Reparata, a virgin and martyr, who suffered in Caesarea of Palestine under Emperor Decius.
After enduring boiling lead and having her breasts cut off, she was thrown into a burning furnace; yet when unharmed by the fire, she was beheaded, and a white dove was seen flying from her neck.
OCTOBER 9 - We celebrate the feast day of the patriarch Abraham.
In Paris, we remember the martyrdom of Bishop Dionysius, Priest Eleutherius, and Deacon Rusticus.
This blessed bishop was sent by the Roman pontiff on a mission to Gaul and arrived in the city of Paris.
For several years, when miracles helped strengthen people's faith, he worked to guide them towards the path of truth.
He was eventually arrested by the governor and, along with Rusticus and Eleutherius, was martyred.
In Cologne, we celebrate the feast day of Saint Gereon and 319 others, who are believed to have been from the legion of Blessed Maurice.
They defied the rule of the deadly Maximian and willingly faced the sword for their true faith.
October 10th: The prophet Lot.
In Crete, Bishop Pinytus, who left a lasting memory through his writings.
Also, in Cologne, the holy martyrs Mallosius and Victor.
In Britain, Paulinus, Bishop of York, was ordained by Blessed Justus, whom Saint Augustine, the first bishop of the English, consecrated.
He converted the Northumbrian people, the English living north of the Humber River, to the faith.
October 11th: In Tarsus, the major city of Cilicia, we commemorate the presbyter Tharacus and the martyr Andronicus.
During Diocletian's persecution under Governor Maximus, they endured imprisonment, whipping, stones, burning, jaw fractures, and leg torture.
They suffered vinegar and mustard poured into their noses and, though thrown to bears and lions, remained unharmed by any beasts.
Finally, they were beheaded and thrown among the slain.
That night, a bright star from heaven revealed them to Christians, leading to their proper burial.
October 12th: In Ravenna, we remember Saint Edistus.
In Africa, we honor the holy confessors and martyrs, 4,976 in total, who suffered under the brutal Moors by order of Hunneric, the Arian king, during the Vandalic persecution.
Among them were Cyrianus and Felix, chief priests of the Lord.
Some were pushed forward by spear points, while others, with their feet bound, were dragged over the roughest terrain, enduring terrible torture until they breathed their last in the hands of their captors.
In Rome, it's the feast day of Saint Bedistus, a martyr.
In Syria, we remember Eustatius, a priest, along with Eucharistius, Burrus, and Bonatus.
In Campania, we honor Patria and Fortunata.
October 13th — At Troas, we commemorate Carpus, a disciple of the Apostle Paul.
In Antioch, we remember Theophilus, the sixth bishop of the church after the apostles, known as a very learned man.
He established a tradition to fast three times a year on the Sabbath, involving grain, wine, and oil, as foretold by prophecy.
In Spain, we honor Faustus, Marcus, and Adrian.
In Chalcedonia, we remember Marcellus.
In Alexandria, we commemorate Saint Anastasius, a bishop.
October 14th — We celebrate the birth of Saint Callixtus, a pope who was martyred under Emperor Alexander.
After baptizing Palmachius, the proconsul, and Simplicius, the senator, along with their families and many others, he was arrested by Alexander, tortured by hunger, beaten with clubs, and imprisoned.
During his imprisonment, his priest Calepodius, already martyred, visited and consoled him; there, he also healed a soldier named Privatus from sores, bringing him into the Catholic faith.
Angered by this, Alexander ordered the blessed Callixtus to be thrown from a window of a house, with a stone tied to his neck, to be drowned in a well, and rubble to be piled upon him.
Rescued by his followers, he was buried in the cemetery of Calepodius.
In Cordoba, we honor Saint Lupus and Aurelia.
At Lyon, we remember the translation of Justus, bishop and confessor, who, living as a hermit, predicted by prophetic spirit what would come after him.
October 15th — In France, near Cologne, we remember the holy Moors from the soldiers of the Theban Legion.
Although they numbered fifty, they were martyred and buried in the same city.
In Capua, we honor Libulus and Saint Fortunata.
On the same day, at Lyon, we remember Antiochus, a bishop.
October 16th — In Asia, at Cereae, we commemorate significant events.
In Africa, we remember two hundred seventy who were crowned together.
Also, of the holy martyrs Martian, Satyr, with their two brothers, and Maxima the virgin.
Under King Geiseric the Arian, they were first beaten with knotted clubs until their bones were exposed.
Then, they were tightly bound, but by divine power, they were freed and immediately made whole.
Maxima, a servant of Christ, was released and became the mother of many virgins.
The others, by the order of the most impious tyrant, were tied by their feet to the backs of running chariots and torn apart among thorny places, dying in the Lord.
On the same day among the Alemanni, also known as the Suebi, near the Rhaetian Alps, the passing or birth into eternal life of the most blessed Gallus the confessor is celebrated festively.
He came from the island of Hibernia, located between Britain and Spain, driven by divine love to travel with his teacher and abbot Columbanus through Gaul and into Alemannia.
Arriving in the wilderness between the Rhaetian Alps and the shore of Lake Constance, he was detained by illness while his father Columbanus went to Italy.
This illness, healed by the divine hand, was overcome, and regaining health, he desired to lead a solitary life, embracing the solitude of the wilderness, devoted to God alone.
King Sigebert, upon hearing that he was staying on public lands, ordered a document of confirmation to be made so that the holy man could hold the place he lived in with authority.
Giving him weights of gold and silver, he instructed Duke Cunzon to provide him with the means to build a cell if he wished to dwell in solitude.
Thus, the athlete of God, about to build a spiritual edifice, devoted himself to frugality, prayers, and vigils.
He called the people back from the error of idolatry, destroyed their idols, and confirmed his preaching with the effect of signs.
He has a vast number of followers because the story of his life and virtues is widely available and read everywhere.
Even today, it's expanded by miracles from the past.
We'll skip over some details for now and just mention this: divine mercy made the blessed Gallus an apostle to the people of Alemannia.
He found the nation steeped in paganism, infused it with the truth of faith, and guided it from the darkness of ignorance to the light of righteousness, which is Christ, like a wise traveler on God's paths.
He transformed a place, once inaccessible and inhabited only by wild beasts, serpents, and demons, into a dwelling place for divinity after driving out these enemies.
It's important to observe and respect that the tabernacle of God, which the holy man established with divine demonstration and much effort, and which is set apart by royal authority as God's inheritance, should not be attacked by human presumption.
Let greed not take over what was cleansed from the rage of demons and the savagery of beasts.
Finally, no human audacity should disturb the resting place of Gallus's remains, where they were brought by untamed horses.
October 17—Martha, sister of Lazarus, and Aristion, one of the seventy disciples.
Also, the feast of Heron, who succeeded Saint Ignatius in leading the Church of Antioch, a role revealed to Ignatius himself as he faced his passion.
Heron became an imitator of his master in both life and martyrdom, as he was a deacon of Ignatius.
In Gaul, the city of Orange, Bishop Florentius, renowned for many virtues, rested in peace.
In Nicomedia, Alexander.
In Mauretania, Ninus, Victurius, Nobilitanus, Marianus, Lucius, Mittinus, Crescentianus.
Also, the translation of the body of Saint Gallus and the dedication of his splendid basilica, built between the mountains Cirrus and Walthrammesberg, with the Steinach River to the south and the Necker River to the north.
This place is named after the blessed Gallus as the Monastery of Saint Gallus.
Where the Lord showcases His power, miracles unfold: the blind gain sight, the deaf hear, the disabled walk, the mute rejoice in speech, the lame find guidance, and those possessed are freed.
The bedridden and crippled receive healing, toothaches are cured by the wood's power, and other ailments are alleviated.
October eighteenth—Saint Luke, the historian and evangelist.
His life, profession, and death are detailed in Paul's Letter, the Acts of the Apostles, and the preface of his Gospel.
In Rome, Tryphonia, wife of Emperor Decius, after the deaths of Callixtus and Lawrence, received baptism with Decius' daughter Cyrilla and passed away the following day.
On the same day, Asclepiades, bishop of Antioch and martyr under Emperor Decius.
October nineteenth—In Antioch of Syria, the birth of Saint Berenice, Pelagia, and fifty-nine others.
Pelagia, once a prostitute under pagan customs, converted to Christianity and was baptized through the grace of God and the teachings of Saint Nonnus, the bishop.
She gave all her possessions to the poor, left Antioch for the Mount of Olives, built a small cell where the Lord ascended to heaven, and lived a monastic life in male attire until her death.
On the same day, the blessed martyrs Tholomeus and Lucius.
Tholomeus, imprisoned and tortured for his faith by a centurion, was presented to Judge Urbicius, who questioned him about his beliefs.
Tholomeus declared: "He who denies what is, judges what he denies to be blameworthy."
Urbicius immediately ordered him to be taken away.
Witnessing this, a Christian named Lucius asked the judge: "Why is this man, accused of no crime but only professing Christianity, sentenced to death?"
Urbicius responded: "Are you also a Christian?"
Upon Lucius's confession, he too was ordered to be executed.
Additionally, a third person was punished for the same reason.
These martyrs suffered under Antoninus and were buried in Alexandria.
In the city of Agen in Gaul, there was the martyr Caprasius.
He hid in a cave to escape persecution.
However, upon hearing that the blessed virgin Faith was fighting for Christ, he found courage and received the reward of martyrdom.
On October 20 in Nicomedia, the holy martyrs Dasius, Zotikos, and Gaius, along with twelve thousand others, were honored.
Also, Simplicius, whose commendable life was a source of salvation for many, leading to the baptism of three thousand people who were welcomed into the embrace of Mother Church.
On the same day, our father Hilarion, whose virtuous life was documented by Jerome.
As he lived a life of constant labor, when he sensed his end was near and all his living senses were fading, he opened his eyes and said:
"Go forth, go forth, soul, why do you fear? Why do you hesitate? For nearly seventy years you have served Christ, and do you fear death?"
With these words, he breathed his last.
On the same day, Saint Asterius the priest and Saint Callistus, who, after burying his father's body that had been raised from the well, was ordered by Alexander to be thrown from a bridge.
Also, the translation of blessed Viator into the wilderness, companion of Saint Justus.
October 21 – In Jerusalem, Mark, the first bishop from among the Gentiles, was martyred.
Also, blessed Salome, who was involved in the burial of the Lord, along with other women.
In Thrace at Adrianople, the holy ones, Bishop Philip, Priest Eusebius, Priest Severus, and Deacon Hermes.
They were crowned with martyrdom for opposing the plundering of churches by the wicked.
October 22 – In Antioch, Syria, the birth of Theodoret the priest.
During the persecution by Julian the Apostate, he endured cruel torture with the rack and torches.
However, the soldiers who tormented him were terrified by an angelic vision, fell on their faces, and believed in Christ.
The tyrant ordered them to be drowned in the sea.
Blessed Theodoritus said to them, "Go ahead, brothers. I will follow you to the Lord after defeating the enemy." He was then killed by the sword and achieved martyrdom. He also predicted the death of Julian in Persia through a prophetic spirit.
In Spain, Servandus and Germanus endured beatings and imprisonment, traveling a long journey weighed down by chains. Ultimately, they fulfilled their passion by having their heads cut off.
October 23 - In Venusia, a city in Apulia, we celebrate the feast day of Saint Felix, bishop, along with Audactus and Januarius, priests, and Fortunatus and Septimus, readers. They were killed by the sword during the time of Diocletian. Also, there's Venantianus the abbot, who is known for realizing that the solemn celebrations of the masses were being completed in heaven. Once, during the Lord's Prayer at mass, he heard someone from the tomb responding to the priest: "But deliver us from evil."
October 24 - In Nicomedia, it's the feast day of Severus and Dorotheus. In Caesarea, Cappadocia, it's the day of Longinus, more about him later.
October 25 - In Rome, we remember the suffering of Chrysanthus and Daria, who maintained perpetual chastity under the guise of marriage. Chrysanthus converted Daria from paganism, and under Emperor Numerian, after enduring many tortures, they were thrown into a deep pit with their wife and children, and they gave up their souls to God.
In Gaul, in the city of Soissons, Crispinus and Crispinianus were tortured under Maximian and Diocletian. They were stretched on racks, beaten with clubs, and had stakes driven into their nails. In the winter, with millstones around their necks, they were submerged in a river, covered with molten lead, boiling oil, pitch, and fat, yet they were delivered from all these by divine intervention. When their torturer Retivapus saw that no torture could harm them, he furiously threw himself into the fire. Maximian, upon hearing of his soldier's demise, ordered them to be killed by the sword.
On the same day, in the city of Perigueux, we honor Saint Frontonus. He was ordained a bishop by the blessed apostle Peter and was sent with Gregory the priest to preach the Gospel.
He converted a great nation in the city to the faith and profession of Christ.
He also brought his companion Gregory back to life, who had died on the journey, by placing on him the staff of the apostle Peter, and Gregory rested in peace.
In Rome, 46 soldiers were martyred after being baptized together by Pope Dionysius and were beheaded by order of Emperor Claudius.
There are also 121 other martyrs buried with them, including Theodosius, Lucius, Marcus, and Parus.
Pope Boniface decreed that a servant could not become a cleric nor be subject to the court.
On October 26, in Africa, the holy martyrs Rogatianus the priest and Felicissimus suffered under Decius and Valerian.
On the same day, the holy bishops Vedastus and Amandus are commemorated.
Vedastus was serving as a priest in the town of Toul, but after King Clovis became victorious over the Alamanni, he remembered the vow he made during the battle.
He took the blessed Vedastus from Toul and hastened to the city of Reims to Saint Remigius for the grace of baptism.