How to Observe Fasting Throughout the Year
by
Bertharius of Monte Cassino
Each of the four seasons has its own designated fasting periods.
In the first month, during the first week, you should fast on Wednesday, Friday, and Saturday, with twelve readings, until evening.
In the fourth month, which is June, during the second week, you should fast on Wednesday, Friday, and Saturday, with twelve readings, until the ninth hour.
In September, the seventh month, during the third week, you should fast on Wednesday, Friday, and Saturday, with twelve readings, until the ninth hour.
In the tenth month, during the fourth week, you should fast on Wednesday, Friday, and Saturday, with twelve readings, until evening.
Observing these twelve legitimate fasts throughout the year compensates for sins equivalent to one hundred gold coins.
If diligently observed, these fasts will free the soul.
Additionally, the Prior may declare fasts for any tribulation.
Regarding the remaining fasts: On the eves of Saint Matthew, Christmas, and Epiphany, fasting should be observed until evening.
On the eves of the Ascension of the Lord, Pentecost, Saint John the Baptist, Saint Peter, Saint Lawrence, and Saint Mary, fasting should be observed until the ninth hour.
After Mass, they may eat.
If these eves fall on a Sunday, fasting is not required.
On the octaves of Christmas and Epiphany, the Purification of Saint Mary, and also the feasts of Saint Scholastica, Saints Faustinus and Jovita, Saint Germanus, the dedication of Saint Benedict above, and the dedication of the Lord Savior and Saint Mary below, fasting is not observed until evening, unless it coincides with the feast of Saint Scholastica, Saints Faustinus and Jovita, or Saint Matthias the Apostle during Quinquagesima, or during Lent.
If this happens, fasting should be observed as on other sacred fasting days.
For the offices and all other matters concerning these festivals, they are to be conducted as we have stated, just like on a Sunday.
On the feasts of Saint Gregory, Saint Benedict, and the Annunciation of Saint Mary, twelve readings are done, and the brothers do not kneel in prayer but observe fasting until evening.
However, after Vespers, they may have a meal with cooked food and wine.
On the feasts of Saint Stephen and Saint John the Evangelist, and on the second and third days after Easter, nine readings are done, and the Mass is conducted as on a Sunday.
On all these festivals, "The Lord Reigns" is always sung at Matins. There is no kneeling, and the chapter and reading are not done in the evening.
For all other saints' days, there are nine readings, and the morning and Mass are conducted as on regular days, with kneeling and fasting until the appointed time.
"Have mercy on me, God" is not sung at Vespers, Matins, and Prime; in other hours, it is sung, except if it falls on a Sunday, in which case it is celebrated like a Sunday.
The division of Matins and nighttime prayer is conducted as follows: From November 1st until the eve of the Lord's Supper, as Saint Benedict prescribed. Additionally, on the vigil of Christmas and on all saints' days and Sundays, it is not permitted to divide the prayers.
From Christmas until Epiphany, kneeling is not performed; "Have mercy on me, God" is not sung in public prayers for any office until the octave of Christmas.
Similarly, from Easter until the octave of Pentecost; afterward, it is sung.
In the refectory, everything should be done as Saint Benedict says, whether in summer, winter, or Lent, all according to their appropriate time.
Besides the custom, whether above or below, they do not eat at the ninth hour until they have finished the grape harvest. When they are free from the harvest, they eat at the ninth hour and have a snack and drink again after Vespers, which is not written in the rule.
Similarly, during the fiftieth day after the meal, according to custom, they drink for the whole week before the reading is read, which is also not mentioned in the rule.
When they perform the commandment, if the Lord has given an abundance of wine, they always drink; if it is scarce, they abstain.