Letter of Gottschalk to Ratramnus.
Come, I beg you, Clio,
return with a faithful heart.
Hurry, swift heroine,
return, wise descendant;
whose brother is Apollo.
Because of this, as if flying,
bring joyful greetings to my friend Ratramnus,
Lord, Father, teacher,
with an unpolished verse,
which I willingly send to him,
the famous and bright man.
I truly love him deeply,
with a pious and kind spirit,
that it may be granted to me, the wicked one,
by God who gives good things
to everyone who asks.
Without whom nothing is possible for anyone,
as is clear to the disciple.
Therefore, as you were asked,
go without any delay.
May you be held and see
the beautiful face of my companion.
For you come twice from that
wonderful teacher,
taking away bitterness, imprinting sweetness,
you refresh the disciple's mouth
with sweet food, pleasant aroma.
Where you see him sitting,
teaching others well,
praying to the powerful God
to give them pious peace;
I ask you to give constant greetings.
On the seventeenth day of August, as the Sun's horses breathed sweet fire through the clouds, their heads and manes wet from the ocean waves, they hurried to steer their chariot back to its usual course.
The bright stars had already vanished from the sky.
The pale Moon had also yielded to her brother, Phoebus.
Now, he alone was driving the chariot with swift reins, spreading his lovely light over the world.
He was shining with new brilliance and a splendid glow, restoring everything to its true form with his clear light.
All the earth rejoiced as the darkness was driven away.
My mind, as if it foresaw something good, was more joyful than usual, leaping with happiness and feeling a stronger sense of cheerfulness throughout my entire being.
Then, suddenly, verses were gifted to me from the high throne of the King, delivered by a companion, sweeter than honey and more radiant than sunlight.
Just as someone thirsty loves to be refreshed by the sweetness of a pure spring under the star of Cancer,
and a sick person wants to be revived with bread when hungry:
just as someone cold desires a fire, and a naked person longs for clothing;
an exile yearns for their homeland, or a shipwrecked person for dry land:
so does someone in darkness crave the nurturing gifts of light.
My poverty now desires the excellent poems, my friend, that your nobility has produced:
Distinguished, beautiful, sweet, graceful, charming, clear in expression, and truly pure in their pledge.
Strong in figures of speech, shining with metaphorical charm, praised for their simplicity, adorned with humble piety.
Seasoned with wit, polished with the love of peace; which indeed I believe a holy inspiration dictated to you.
Indeed, without a doubt, nothing arises from this, most humble man, since I have all good things, they are given to the needy recipient.
Therefore, I must lift up this equal and pious Creator, the triune and one God, with humble prayers throughout the ages.
With whom I am united under your protection, not through my merits: He did this freely, who wished to restore you with His shed blood.
Enriched with wisdom, and indeed with special honor, endowed with various virtues, loving in beauty.
He is worthy of the favor of praise throughout the ages of life, if He would grant to accomplish it, in equal and unending measure.
Certainly to be loved with sincere love always; and to be feared everywhere with chaste and holy fear, as He persistently seeks, who is to be exalted with holy trembling.
If our hearts could give Him anything: He is in need of nothing from us, who surely gains no benefit; He does not need obedience, nor service, nor hymns.
For this reason alone, He holds the true name of Lord.
And yet He Himself is the author of these, and of other goods, be widely and ours, O good teacher.
Therefore, with a humble mind, if He grants, I am certain to bless, what He has given us, such a pledge of love as you, who wishes to preserve and compose the words of poetry.
Which are inspired by the Holy Spirit, not inflated with cheap noise, with sweet-spoken utterance, renowned and brilliant narration.
It soothes the mind, needing this melody, and comforts it, sick with various sorrows.
You sing poems for various ills with diverse songs.
Just as the most famous harper once studied to calm the heart of a man by playing melodious strings.
Indeed, a man now deprived of the honor of the kingdom, whom the cruel dragon and wicked serpent vexed.
And truly deservedly, because he had willingly forsaken the Lord, raised up by excessive pride, and by the cunning of ferocity.
To the Psalmist, to this I say, a fellow lyre player,
I would often call you, sacred friend, noble poet;
Who, through your playing, eases the heavy heart of your student.
Oh, if only I could sing in prose as sweet, beautiful, bright, pleasant, elegant, pious, peaceful, and most importantly, as true to me as the kindness of a magnificent friend desires!
Here, however, I follow what I hope to return to elsewhere, written with God's favor, although I may not be able to do so as quickly as I'd like, for many reasons, the first being the charm.
I want your people to know that I hardly have an hour to spare for my simplicity to rest, so that I might at least compose three short letters.
The command of the Father urges me to accomplish something: first this, then immediately that, and therefore I cannot.
But I must add this: that I am too afraid to respond to you with what I hold deep in my heart, because I am dull in spirit, full of ignorance, and wrapped in many errors, unpolished in speech, and also free from ancient law, despite using it for a short time.
I have scarcely been under instruction for a year, nor did I learn afterwards, wavering on uncertain paths, the leader of fools, rushing headlong through everything.
No one guided me, so light was barely revealed, enclosed by sins, as much as heavenly kindness granted freely, to which be virtue, glory, and praise.
This rarely happens through me, but I ask that it may happen more frequently through you.
Therefore, since a small spark of knowledge can hardly be present in me, I dread what the highest friend might scorn, with keen senses and a very sharp tongue.
Indeed, through day and night practice under this, you have long since reached the very summit.
Considering, weighing, and reflecting on this, putting aside inflating virtue, preferring to build joy, I have decided to remain silent until, with the Lord's help, I might be able to achieve something certain, to soothe the ears of the noble, and to move the heart of a companion: lest filth creep into it, and I offend again if I perhaps utter trivialities.
For this to be possible, my diligent mind demands, and I humbly ask that your kindness demands the same.
Finally, there are many teachers, blessed with abundant talent, situated in this region by the Lord’s gift; hence, many dwell in the palace court.
To those and others situated throughout barbarian kingdoms,
I've eagerly sent letters during these days,
Praying greatly for a quick response,
As I am in great need.
So, I sent the words of the blessed Augustine to them,
Asking the author to clearly explain it.
Indeed, I endeavored to convey the proper meaning of these three:
Matcaudo, Jonah, and Lupus, with radiant speech,
Urging them earnestly to report the truth.
The question was posed to all the others.
I truly opposed it, for it is argued on both sides,
But no one, except for one cautious and clever person, has responded to me,
Who is also moderate;
Thus balancing his threefold response in his book,
So that it fits neither side fully,
I have decided to recite these to you,
While others hasten to respond with sharp minds,
So that you, dearest, may consider more carefully,
If you see something that agrees with what you do not have,
Yet I continuously ask you to pray with me with constant devotion,
And remember to pray earnestly with all your heart,
That they may be granted fitting words,
And, with the vigor of salt, the holy bonds of peace.
I rejoice in the past, indeed, venerable poet,
Since you shine with humble honor, though you are lofty:
And though you ascend to the heavens, you mark yourself as crawling on the ground.
For this pleases Him, as you know, splendid man, the King,
Who deigned to be exceedingly humble for your sake,
To the point of death, which was worse than all else.
You will do this as you speak, if you strive to accomplish it with your heart.
You will truly stand at the pinnacle of all virtues.
For it is easy for a man to confess his misery with his voice,
Whether he is a pretender, but to hold what is within his heart,
Is for the poor, ruling with a high mind in Olympus.
For the wicked often do it with groaning.
But the chosen, indeed from the beginning of the world;
Therefore, not by merits, but truly by the Father's gift.
Happy, brother, happy, noble master,
Whom the Father chose in Christ with kindness:
None of whom are lost, whom the wave of blood redeemed.
The heavenly Lamb, who bestowed life upon them.
Happy is the lamb who is the last among them.
Neither lion, nor thief, wolf, dragon, nor robber
shall ever snatch anyone from here, either by force or deceit.
Indeed, everything that the Father gives comes to him.