The Life of Saint Odo
by Osbern, Monk of Canterbury
Preliminary Observations.
While the author of this Life might seem ancient due to the manuscript, the Thuano-Colbertinus codex, from which we transcribed this Life, does not name or date him.
I believe the author to be Osbern, a monk of Canterbury under Archbishop Lanfranc.
Pits notes that Osbern wrote a book on the Life of Odo, Archbishop of Canterbury.
It's unclear whether William of Malmesbury referred to this booklet when he composed the eulogy of Odo in Book One of the "Deeds of the Bishops of the English."
The reason for doubt is that William does not fully agree with Osbern-if we may call him that for now-on some points, although these are of lesser importance.
Osbern claims that Odo, hesitant to be elected to the See of Canterbury, only agreed after sending legates to Fleury to summon the abbot, because he had begun his monastic life there.
William, however, states that Odo, after crossing the sea, received the monastic habit at Fleury.
Gervase of Canterbury supports Osbern, while Bromton agrees with William.
Osbern also mentions that after Odo's death, he appeared to the church's guardian to rebuke Elfsin, who had been placed in the Canterbury chair through simony.
William attributes this apparition to Elfsin himself.
Moreover, William mentions events like the translation of Saint Wilfrid by Odo, and several other things about which Osbern remains silent.
Both agree that, after the death of Wulfhelm, the bishop of the Cantuarians, when the king and the people's wishes converged on Odo, he resisted more firmly, as he had not yet taken monastic vows and did not want to disrupt the elders' customs out of ambition.
Until that time, according to William, no one had been archbishop without wearing monastic garb, a point which Osbern also notes in different words.
However, Godwin, a dissenter, calls this an error and asserts that it is certain that Nothelm and several other secular priests had presided over the Church of Canterbury before Odo.
Godwin can't learn this truth with any more certainty than Odo himself or William, who were closer to those early times.
It's unclear if Nothelm was a monk.
Bede, in the preface to the "History of the English," only refers to Nothelm as a devout priest of the Church of London. However, monks often used this term for priests, and Bede even calls him "our venerable brother Nothelm the priest" in a letter. This suggests he was more likely a monk than a secular priest.
Odo embraced the monastic life and professed it in the year 937, when the monastery of Fleury was being reformed to stricter rules through the efforts of Odo, the abbot of Cluny. Thus, Odo might have adopted the monastic habit, bypassing Canterbury and other English monks, whose observance wasn't as highly regarded at that time.
This same motivation led Oswald and other Englishmen to the monastery at Fleury, from where Abbo was sent to England for both piety and learning. Among Odo's notable acts, not mentioned in the following booklet, is the translation of the body of Saint Wilfrid, Bishop of York, which he arranged to be moved to Canterbury.
This is recorded by William in his account of Odo, and by Eadmer in the book "Life of Saint Wilfrid," found in the first part of the Third Century of Benedict, pages 226 and 227. William adds that Odo arranged for Wilfrid's life to be written in heroic verse, accomplished by a certain Fridegod, whose poem we include in our Patrology, volume 133.
William also notes a synodal letter from Odo to his suffragans during King Edmund's reign, urging them not to be indifferent and negligent in the care of souls. In this letter, Odo showed not only notable literacy, as William observed, but even more so, a deep sense of piety and pastoral concern.
This letter was written by him, I believe, after the decrees he issued under the same king, published by Spelman, which outline the responsibilities of the king, clergy, and magistrates.
In chapter six, he urges monks to diligently fulfill their vows with humility and obedience, both day and night, staying in the fear of God within the churches to which they have committed themselves through their vows.
They should not be wanderers or gyrovagues, who seek the title of monk but neglect its duties.
Instead, they should emulate the apostles through humility, manual labor, sacred reading, and continuous prayers.
Eadmer, in the prologue to the Life of Saint Wilfrid, refers to Odo's booklet about Wilfrid's life and conduct.
Undoubtedly, this booklet is none other than Fridegod's poem, which is preceded by Odo's letter in some manuscripts.
These words are found within:
"So, I reverently received the most venerable relics of the blessed confessor of Christ, Wilfrid, which had been neglected in an unworthy, foul, and stagnant pit, indeed (which is terrible to say) ignored by the horror of the prelates, when some people, with God's favor, transferred them from the place of his tomb, and I placed them within the bounds of the metropolitan church, which by the grace of God I preside over.
Therefore, delighted by the proximity of such a great and God-worthy relationship, I decided to adorn them with a higher casket and, by extracting blooms from his book of life, to embellish them with a new work in verse, that is, through Fridegod: which, however, Eadmer and perhaps some others attributed to Odo.
I do not know if what Pitseus has about other writings of Odo is more certain, who additionally attributes to him one book to the monks of Fleury for his nephew Oswald; another on the real presence of the body of Christ in the Eucharist, as well as a book of letters, and another of various poems.
"
Furthermore, Eadmer, William of Malmesbury, Matthew of Westminster, and others call Odo a saint, and after them, Cardinal Baronius in volume ten of the Annals, although Odo does not have a place in the Roman Martyrology.
Eum is believed to have passed away on the fourth of July, as noted by Capgrave and other English writers, according to Maiheuvius, not on the seventh of February, which is the day Molanus discusses Saint Odo in his Additions to Usuard.
He is especially praised in the following Life of Saint Dunstan by Osbern.
The revered confessor of Christ, Odo, was born to noble but pagan parents.
He blossomed like a rose among thorns, or a precious scent from humble vessels.
It's said that he descended from a group of senators who once accompanied the notorious pirate Inguar and were brought by ship into the kingdom of the English.
Despite his origins and being raised with utmost care, he eagerly sought out Christian gatherings and listened with great delight to the divine words spoken there.
When he returned home, he enthusiastically shared what he had learned with his parents.
His father, angered by these early interests in goodness, strictly forbade him from mentioning Christ or changing the family's beliefs with the Christian religion's reverence.
However, Odo disregarded his father's command and visited the Church more frequently, absorbing the seeds of the divine Word with a focused mind, and fearlessly shared what he learned at home.
Once again, his father, more exasperated than ever, subjected him to severe punishment and stripped him of his inheritance as the firstborn.
Rejoicing in the Lord for enduring such rejection for His name, Odo saw this as his enrollment in heaven.
He left behind his parents and their wealth, fleeing naked and deprived of all worldly glory.
Athelmum is a student of literature.
He sought out a leader named Athelm, who lived during King Eluvred's time and was a devout Christian.
Among the English nobility, Athelm was one of the most esteemed.
Athelmum requested Athelm's protection and authority to shield him from his parents' anger.
Athelm, pleased with the young man's virtuous nature and finding it inappropriate for him to serve pagan rituals under his father's rule, welcomed him with fatherly care.
He safeguarded him and provided both essential and additional support.
Athelm then placed him under the tutelage of teachers to learn Greek and Latin, languages widely used at the time among the English, having been passed down by the students of Archbishop Theodore's blessed memory.
Athelmum became highly proficient in both languages, able to craft poetry, write prose, and express any idea with great eloquence.
He joined the ranks.
After this, reborn through the sacrament of baptism and adorned with the clerical tonsure, he was guided by his lord to the role of subdeacon.
In that position, he excelled for several years with such holiness and sincerity in his preaching that anyone who knew him believed he was a temple of the Holy Spirit.
Everyone agreed he deserved to advance to higher ministries within the Church, even though his age, according to the regulations of the canons, would usually have been a barrier.
His lord persuaded him to embrace the priesthood so he could hear the divine office daily from someone whose life he admired for its chastity and purity.
Initially, he resisted, citing his young age.
Eventually, swayed by reason and the authority of ancient examples, he gave in to his religious calling.
He wore the deacon's stole on his shoulder, and soon after, he was also entrusted with the highest mysteries.
From that time on, both the duke and almost all the other princes of the royal palace held him in the highest regard.
They confided the secrets of their troubled lives to him and willingly sought his counsel for their correction.
He travels to Rome with Athelmus and heals him, then returns to England.
Meanwhile, the duke expressed to the king his desire to visit Rome and pray to the holy apostles there.
The king quickly granted him permission and support.
Accompanied by the venerable priest Odo, he set off with a large group.
Shortly into the journey, he was struck by a severe illness and began to suffer greatly, barely able to breathe.
For six days, his condition worsened, and their provisions dwindled.
On the seventh day, he instructed the group to continue, keeping only Odo with him, whose help he desperately needed.
After the others had left, he called Odo to him and, in a sorrowful voice, asked him to pray for his recovery, believing that divine mercy would not refuse Odo's request.
Odo, raising his spirit to God, prostrated himself on the ground, shedding tears in prayer.
After rising, he asked for a cup of wine.
Making the sign of the cross over it, he handed the wine to the man and advised him to trust in the Lord.
The man drank from the cup, and as soon as he returned it, he felt completely healed.
Grateful, he bowed at the priest's knees, thanked him, mounted his horse, and quickly caught up with his companions the next day.
Seeing him, everyone wept for joy, and recognizing the source of his healing, they marveled even more.
They continued to Rome and then joyfully returned home, bringing immense happiness to the king and everyone at the palace upon their arrival.
He became dear to King Athelstan.
After some time, both the leader and the aforementioned king passed away.
Edward, the son of the same king, succeeded to the kingdom and ruled it very wisely for many years.
During his reign, the venerable Odo, known for his priestly duties and holy life, was well-regarded by the king and admired by everyone.
He spread kindness and gentleness to all, adapting to the ways of everyone, much like the apostles, so that he might win everyone over to Christ.
When King Edward reached the end of his life, Athelstan, his son, took over the reins of the kingdom.
As mentioned, the admirable Odo lived a life full of virtues and was held in high regard by all.
Just as a city set on a hill or a lamp on a stand cannot be hidden, neither could his virtues.
As a result, the fame of his holiness grew daily, and with great praise, it reached the ears of the distinguished King Athelstan.
Recognizing him as a true servant of God, the king called him to his side, included him among his friends, and entrusted him with his secrets above all others.
He becomes the bishop of Sherborne.
Meanwhile, the bishop's seat, which was in Sherborne at the time but is now in Salisbury, was left without a leader.
Recognizing that King Odo's life made him worthy of the bishopric, the king urged him with determination to accept the position and become the spiritual shepherd of God's flock in place of the deceased.
Why delay?
Ultimately, overwhelmed by the requests from both the church and the king, he agreed to take on the episcopal responsibilities, which he admitted were a heavy burden for him, and became the bishop at the Sherborne Church.
At that time, the capable and energetic Wlfelmus was overseeing the Church of Canterbury with dignity, authority, and responsibility.
He willingly consented to the election by the king, clergy, and people, and with due honor, consecrated him to the episcopal office to which he had been elected.
Consecrated and adorned with priestly insignia, it is hard to describe how gloriously he served as a dwelling for God, or how dedicated he was to the souls entrusted to him, no matter how insightful one might be.
Therefore, I do not wish to elaborate on what a pure mind might perceive about these matters.
I simply aim to reflect on the works of the merciful God, who chooses to fulfill His will through the simplicity of His servants.
In the year 938, the pagans faced the superior power of Athelstan.
During this year, in the fourteenth year of Athelstan's reign, the most victorious king, a massive army of pagans gathered against the English kingdom.
Their aim was to weaken it by imposing their profane laws, ultimately seeking to destroy the sacred Christian laws that the English followed.
This renowned prince, surrounded by a strong band of armed men, confronted them and engaged in battle.
The fight was long and extremely fierce on both sides.
Leading his forces, the king relied more on the merits of the holy Odo, whom he brought with him, than on the strength of his troops to secure victory over the enemy.
Amidst the fierce slaughter, a sorrowful event occurred.
The king's sword broke near the hilt, leaving him nearly defenseless against the enemy.
Meanwhile, Odo stood at a distance from the battle, praying to Christ with both his voice and heart for the salvation of the Christian army, tirelessly raising his face, hands, and eyes to the heavens for this purpose.
At this critical moment, the king was unsure of what to do, as he felt it wrong to disarm any of his men to arm himself.
A portion of the enemy force, noticing the king standing unarmed with a broken sword, turned back from their retreat to attack with renewed ferocity.
Suddenly, the heavens echoed with the clamor of the multitude calling for God's help, and the venerable Odo quickly approached in response to their cries.
He rushed forward and asked the weary king what he wanted him to do.
Upon hearing the king's plight, he said, "What is this? Where are you going? Your sword hangs intact at your side, and you complain it is broken? Return to yourself, reach for the sheath, draw it out, and behold, the right hand of the Lord will be with you. Do not fear, for the sun will not set until your enemies, who have risen against you, are overcome by flight or destruction."
To everyone's great astonishment, as they listened with lowered eyes, they saw something new: a sword hanging at the king's side.
Empowered by God, the king seized the sword and used it to either disable, chase away, or completely destroy anyone who opposed him.
As God's servant had foretold, by sunset, the king had triumphed over his enemies.
Who can truly describe the gratitude, praises, and vows offered to God through His faithful servant Odo, the king, the victorious army, and throughout the entire kingdom where news of this great victory spread?
The magnificence of this event will educate those who hear of it, as not everyone can easily comprehend it.
From that point on, glorious Odo was admired by all and was truly recognized as a distinguished Israelite.
Eadmund, when encouraged to become the Archbishop of Canterbury, refused to accept the position unless he first became a monk.
Eight years after this significant victory, Ethelstan passed away peacefully, and his brother Eadmund ascended to the throne.
Following his brother's admirable example, he deeply valued virtuous people and, by making them close companions, listened to them sincerely and willingly on matters appropriate for a Christian king.
Among these trusted individuals was the blessed Odo, who gained his friendship and was loved by him with a pure heart.
During this time, Wlfelmus, the Archbishop of Canterbury, passed away as all must.
To ensure that such an important position would not remain vacant for long, the king approached the venerable Odo, urging him to take on the pastoral care of the Church.
Odo resisted and did not agree.
He claimed he was unworthy of such a position; and even if he had some aspiration, he argued that church laws prohibited a bishop from leaving his own church to move to another.
In response, the king highlighted Odo's well-known virtues to everyone and mentioned that the blessed leader of the apostles, Peter, had moved from Antioch to Rome, and that many others, according to ancient writings, had changed their positions when necessary.
He also added, "We have a clear and fitting example of this among us, namely the holy men, Mellitus, the bishop of London, and Justus of Rochester, who were transferred to Canterbury in a similar manner to what we are urging you to do."
The holy bishop, overwhelmed by these arguments, presented another reason for his reluctance.
He said, "When the first Fathers of this Church, who brought Christianity to the kingdom of the English, and all who succeeded them until now, as everyone knows, were monks; should I change, break, or abolish such an ancient, holy, God-accepted custom, supported by the authority of so many Fathers?"
God forbid; let everyone in Britain and the surrounding islands know that I will never agree to lead the Church of Canterbury in clerical attire, because no one who wasn't a monk has ever led there before.
However, since not only you but many others are urging me to become a bishop there, it's not my place to resist completely, as I don't want to offend God who dwells within them.
So, I entrust my conscience to God, free from any ambition for this honor.
The holy purpose of monastic life, which I have desired since my early years but have not been able to achieve due to various obstacles, I will embrace at least this once, even if only temporarily.
As for the bishopric you're discussing, may He who knows all the secrets of hearts decide and appoint the one He deems suitable for this role through His wisdom.
The monk receives clothing from the monks of Fleury and then becomes an archbishop.
The king was greatly uplifted by this man's opinion, praising his holy purpose, his admirable and exemplary humility, and his steadfast courage.
After this, messengers were promptly sent to the abbot of the monastery of Saint Benedict at Fleury to obtain the religious clothing necessary for the bishop's duties, as per the prescribed task.
At that time, the reputation of the very religious lifestyle at Fleury was widely known and was thriving everywhere.
In contrast, interest in the same religion had started to decline in England due to various events, prompting people to seek the desired religious effect from there.
And so it happened.
Upon hearing the news, the abbot of that place became very happy, took some of his brothers with him, crossed the sea successfully, and arrived in England.
He eagerly approached Bishop Odo, who was striving to please God in all things, and devoutly gave him the clothing of the holy purpose he sought.
Thus, the distinguished Bishop Odo became a monk by habit, having long been adorned with the sacred acts of monastic life.
He was invited, or rather compelled, by the king and the kingdom to take up the yoke of the Lord over all England, becoming the Archbishop of Canterbury.
He could no longer refuse.
Those who wish to know how he carried out the duties of the office he received can refer to the account of his life, which describes what he was like before and during his priesthood.
As I believe, they can perceive.
He was indeed praiseworthy for his holiness, admirable for his wisdom, and singular for his steadfastness.
Eadred is anointed king.
He converts opponents of the Eucharist through a miracle.
After King Edmund was tragically killed in his own home, his brother Eadred assumed royal authority and was anointed as king by the renowned Odo, the Archbishop of Canterbury.
During this period, Dunstan, a man of exceptional virtue and the most esteemed abbot of the Glastonbury monastery, was highly regarded by the king and respected by all the people.
Blessed Odo, both wise and mature, strong in faith and diligence, and remarkable in authority and modesty, wisely governed the entire kingdom with Christian laws.
The king himself, fearing God, cherished all good people with a special sweetness of love and strongly opposed the wicked, ensuring they did not disturb the good with their tyranny, thus embodying the qualities of a good leader.
Around this time, certain clerics, misled by a dangerous error, attempted to claim that the bread and wine placed on the altar remained in their original substance after consecration, being merely symbols of the body and blood of Christ, not the true body and blood of Christ.
Wanting to eradicate this great heresy, blessed Odo, on a particular day, devoutly attended the solemn celebration of the holy mass in front of all the people, praying with tears to Almighty God for His mercy to be present in his ministry, to reveal the true nature of the divine mysteries and dispel the errors of men.
When it came to breaking the life-giving bread, oh the ineffable mercy of God, oh the visible manifestation of eternal majesty!
For immediately, in the hands of the bishop, who was holding the fragments of the body of Christ, blood began to drip.
The bishop, standing there with tears of joy, signaled to the attending ministers to bring forward those who had recently wavered in their faith.
They quickly approached when called and, struck by the sight of such a miraculous event, exclaimed in trembling voices:
"Oh, how fortunate you are among men today, to whom the Son of God has chosen to reveal Himself in the flesh!"
Once again, they asked, "Please, Father, pray to the majesty of the Lord,
so that this blood here might be transformed back to its original form,
and we avoid any divine punishment due to our disbelief."
So the priest prayed, and after his prayer, he looked at the altar.
Where he had left the blood, he now saw the familiar appearance of wine.
After partaking in the heavenly sacraments, everyone who witnessed these amazing events rejoiced.
The bishop then ordered all the poor from the area to gather for a feast prepared for them,
as a testament to such incredible power.
He and his followers celebrated with great thanksgiving,
as all doubts about the Lord's body were erased from the hearts of his people.
They no longer questioned that the bread on the altar was the true body of Christ,
having seen the real blood flow from it.
The restoration of the church was truly remarkable.
Another truly divine miracle occurred in the church under his leadership.
In fact, he didn't accomplish it on his own; it was done through him by the one who alone possesses divinity.
The church's roof, decayed from age, was hanging with many broken parts.
He wanted to renew it and elevate the walls to a greater height, so he gathered craftsmen and instructed them to completely remove the loose parts above and raise the walls that lacked height.
However, since the clergy and people couldn't be without divine service, and there was no other temple large enough to accommodate the crowd, the bishop prayed to the Lord that until the work was finished, no rain or wind would enter the church to disrupt their divine service.
And so it happened that during the three years while the church walls were being raised, the entire structure remained open above.
Remarkably, not only within the church but also within the entire city, no rain fell that could hinder the clergy from their duties or stop the people from coming to the church and beginning their work.
It was astonishing to see all the orchards in the city drenched with water, yet the city's walls remained untouched by any rain.
Edwy, the lustful king, tries to reform himself first through Dunstan and then by his own efforts.
However, when King Edred passed away, Edwy, the son of the late King Edmund, was chosen as king.
Being young both in behavior and age, he soon began to rely on the advice of the young men he had chosen as his companions and attendants, ignoring the older men known for their great experience, conduct, and authority.
Thus, he was corrected by the strong soldier of Christ, Odo, and restrained himself for a while, fearing that if he didn't listen to him at all, the blessing of royal dignity would be delayed beyond his wish.
But once he received that blessing, he immediately became uncontrollable, following all the desires of his heart.
He became a lover of pleasures more than God, of luxury more than sobriety, and of lust rather than chastity.
Therefore, he acted according to the desires of his heart and was praised by his followers for his wicked deeds.
Moreover, on the day he was crowned in the presence of the entire Church, he brought upon himself a serious mark of infamy along with such great glory.
After the church service, when he was already seated for lunch with the archbishops, bishops, abbots, and other leaders of the kingdom, he suddenly leapt up, left the company of all, and withdrew to a more private chamber.
There, inflamed by passion, he sought the unspeakable company of two women who were lying there: this act cast down the minds of those who trusted him with great shame and sorrow.
After holding a council about what needed to be done, the archbishop and the leaders sent the venerable abbot Dunstan, who was mentioned earlier, to pull the king away from his illicit embraces and bring him back to the royal seat among the leaders; which was indeed done.
Because of this, the king, disturbed by intense anger, condemned Dunstan to exile, stripped him of all his possessions, and sent him across the sea outside of England.
He also committed countless other wrongs, which, although detailed elsewhere more extensively, I thought it sufficient to mention only a few here.
Odo, a soldier of Almighty God, couldn't patiently endure these injustices and became a public enemy against them.
When he realized he couldn't persuade the king to change his ways through advice, pleas, or rebukes, he decided to use his episcopal authority.
He had one of the women, whom the king had dishonored with excessive power and shamelessness, removed by soldiers from the king's court.
She was publicly disgraced, branded with a hot iron, and exiled to Ireland for life.
However, after some time, when her body had healed into a scar, but her shameless mind still bore its deformity, she left Ireland, returned to England, and arrived at Gloucester, filled with the darkness of a blinded heart.
There, she was captured by the servants of God, and to prevent her from wandering around like a prostitute, she was crippled, and after a few days, she died a miserable death.
Indeed, Archbishop Odo was a man of strong virtues, supported by the maturity and steadfastness of old age, and an unyielding opponent of all injustices.
Neither the temptations of any worldly joy, threats from people, nor the suffering of any loss could deter him from righteousness.
Thus, because he neither hoped for anything nor feared, he disarmed the anger of all the powerless.
King Eadgar was crowned by Dunstan.
In contrast, Eadwig, who could hardly be considered a true king since he lacked the ability to govern himself or others, was expelled from the kingdom for his crimes and met a miserable end.
Eadgar, his brother, was established as the king over all of England.
He excelled beyond most of his predecessors in character, suppressed the injustices that arose during his brother's reign, overturned them, and did his utmost to eradicate them.
Moreover, upon ascending the throne, he recalled the respected abbot Dunstan from exile and elevated him to the bishopric of Worcester.
When Dunstan was chosen to be a bishop, he traveled to Canterbury for consecration as per tradition, seeking it from the bishop of that seat, the blessed Odo.
Odo agreed without hesitation.
To dispel any doubt about this holy bishop's prophetic spirit, he promoted the man destined to be the bishop of the Wiccians to the bishopric of Canterbury through the Holy Spirit's influence.
When questioned by those present about his actions, he explained, "I know, my sons, I know what God is working within me.
This man will indeed serve as the pastor of Worcester while I live, but once I am gone, all of Britain will celebrate him as its leader; for the Holy Spirit's gift is not constrained by law."
The Church of God, which greatly rejoiced under his leadership as the holy bishop had foretold, is well aware of how true this prophecy proved to be, and it remains strengthened by his most sacred intercession to this day.
He died.
Having been blessed by the Lord with such gifts of goodness, the distinguished Odo did not boast about his own deeds but always strived to improve.
Forgetting what was behind and reaching forward to what was ahead, he pursued the prize of God's heavenly calling.
He daily nourished the people entrusted to him with heavenly teaching, like abundant crops receiving rain-like grace, until the king brought his soul into his chamber and filled him with the joy of his pleasure.
Thus, Odo, the brightest star of the city of Canterbury, was taken from this world and, with the angels rejoicing, sought the seat of the heavenly and most glorious city.
There, he rejoices with eternal exultation and gazes upon the face of Christ with the sweetness of indescribable delight, now secure in his reward and concerned for the salvation of his children.
He died in the presence of all the children of the Church of Christ, to whom he promised while they wept that the Lord would provide a good shepherd for them after his death.
Elfsinus the simoniac succeeded him and insulted the deceased.
Saint Odo gave instructions to the guardian of the church about Elfsinus, who met a miserable end.
After his passing, Elfsinus, the bishop of Winchester, nicknamed Lippe, attained the position of high priest by giving money to the chief nobles in King Edgar's palace.
Even before Odo, there was a strong desire to seize the priesthood, but it was hindered by the steadfastness of good bishops.
When he was received in Canterbury with a solemn procession on the day of his arrival, he approached the tomb of the man of God.
Standing over it, he insulted the deceased with furious words, saying: "Foolish one, see, you are dead and lie rotting under the earth, and I will triumph over you whenever I want.
While you lived, I could not be the highest bishop of the English, but with your passing, I have become what I long desired. And for that, wretched and decrepit old man, you have no thanks, because if you could have lived longer, you would not have wanted to grant me or anyone else a share in your honor."
Thus he openly said in the presence of those who were there, and striking the tomb of the saint with his staff, he left, inflamed by a threefold fury.
But that same night, while mortals were granted rest, the blessed Odo appeared to the worthy guardian of the Church of the Savior, having a face like milk and a garment of rose color, addressing the man thus: "Are you asleep or awake?"
"I was sleeping," he said, "venerable elder, but now I am awake as you speak."
And he said, "Go to the bishop Elfsinus, elected but not by God, and deliver this message in my name: This is what the servant of Christ, Odo, commands you. I am not dead, but I live with my almighty king, God.
And so that you may know this for certain, be aware that just as you could not achieve the archbishopric of Canterbury because of me while I was still living in the flesh, in the same way, you will soon lose the honor you have seized from me now that I live in the heavenly kingdom."
Listen, then, to what I say.
Yesterday, you mocked me with harsh words and struck my grave with your staff.
I warn you, you will cross the sea and climb the Alps, but you will never obtain the mantle of the patriarchate of the holy Church of Canterbury, nor will you ever sit in its apostolic seat.
The person who witnessed these events, fearing the bishop's anger, hesitated to report them.
The following night, the holy man of God appeared to him again, repeating his earlier message, but the man still did not dare to deliver it.
On the third night, the man of God appeared once more, adorned with episcopal dignity, and rebuked the man's hesitation, saying:
If you wish to protect your well-being, I advise you not to conceal from your bishop what you have heard from me for the second time.
If you do, you will find that you have brought punishment upon yourself.
Very frightened, he woke up, and when morning came, he went to the bishop.
Bowing low before him, he said:
Honored Father, the glorious Odo, your predecessor, appeared to me like a beautiful angel of God and commanded me to deliver this message to you:
Because, he told me the day before yesterday, you mocked me with derisive words and struck my grave with your staff, I warn you that you will cross the sea and climb the Alps, but you will never obtain the mantle of the patriarchate of the holy Church of Canterbury, nor will you ever sit in its apostolic seat.
After hearing these words, the bishop dismissed the reporter of the vision, considering the message as foolish threats, as he called them.
But after some days, everything happened just as the holy man of God had predicted.
After crossing the sea to fetch the mantle and traveling successfully for a while, as soon as he ascended the mountains, he was overwhelmed by extreme cold.
He ordered the horses accompanying him to be killed and put his feet into their stomachs, thinking this might drive away the excessive cold.
But since the divine wrath that tormented him did not cease, he blasphemed the majesty of the Lord in his impiety, and thus, in the midst of flames, he breathed his last polluted breath.
Blessed Odo truly showed that he was living in Christ, despite the unfortunate Elfsinus daring to believe he was completely dead.
When Birthelm was removed, Dunstan succeeded him.
A dove appeared over the tomb of Saint Odo, known as Segode.
After Birthelm, the bishop of Dorset, a man of great piety and simplicity, passed away, he was appointed as the bishop for the people of Canterbury.
However, when it was found that he did not effectively carry out ecclesiastical disciplines, he was asked to step down from his responsibilities and humbly returned to rest with his flock.
To affirm the word of the Lord and the prophecy of His servant, the blessed Odo, Dunstan, already the bishop of the church of London, was chosen by the king and the kingdom.
He was appointed as the most worthy successor to the glorious Odo, becoming the patriarch of all Britain.
A sign of the holiness and blessedness of Dunstan and Father Odo was that on Pentecost, when Dunstan was celebrating mass at the altar of the Lord Savior in Canterbury, the Holy Spirit appeared above him in the form of a dove.
After the sacrifice was completed, it moved to the southern part of the altar, where the venerable Odo was buried, and rested over his tomb in front of many onlookers.
This event was held in great reverence by Dunstan himself, and he never passed Odo's tomb afterward without kneeling.
He also affectionately called him "good" in his native tongue, Odo Segode, meaning Odo the Good. This nickname is still used today by the English, especially by the people of Canterbury.
With this account, we conclude the narrative and praise God, who is the culmination of all good things, in harmonious voice. He glorifies His name in every nation so that whoever fears Him and works righteousness is acceptable to Him. To Him, therefore, be praise and thanksgiving through endless ages of ages, amen.
As a rose from thorns, Odo arose from the pagans, bearing no marks of treachery from any ancestor.
Despite the wishes of his ancestors, he embraced the plow of faith.
Like a dedicated farmer, he tilled the soil of the heart.
Raised by blood, and even more elevated by moral values.
Renowned by birth, and even more by his words.
A man free of crime encountered the wicked.
Eager to expand the kingdom of the highest Father.
A phalanx of virtues guarded his heart, preventing any vice from taking root in him.
With prayers offered, he drove away hostile forces.
He who attacks us with his teeth will strike down the boar with prayer here.
You who are renowned above the stars, Odo, pray for us, in this region of varied disaster.