Some Sermons by Saint Eucherius, Bishop of Lyons
Homily One
To the Monks
The divine word urges us to move forward while we have the light, before darkness overtakes us.
We possess the light if we advance in faith; we sit in darkness if we stop progressing.
May the final moment find us prepared, as it often surprises those who are not ready.
The uncertainty of life should make us anxious; we should be wary of the danger that can come at any time.
How late will the miserable soul regret its actions when, on the last day, it finds itself separated from the body.
When it sees eternal night closing in and its unfortunate companion, the deceiver, lying before it, devoid of salvation and light, it will lament.
When it starts to cry out in vain, separated from its body, it will question: Where are your desires and passions that burned within you and now condemn you to eternal fire?
Behold, all those things have passed like a shadow, the pleasures are gone, and only the regrets and sins remain forever.
Woe is me, O soul, to such a ruined state.
Whether I want to or not, I must return, and for fleeting pleasures, I am condemned to eternal suffering.
What will happen when the relentless collector of souls begins to drag it to its final judgment, determined by an unchangeable law, and the dreadful faces of infernal beings press upon it from all sides?
What will happen when it is separated from the agents of death, led through the dark paths beyond the day, embarking on an irreversible journey through places where even light fails?
The soul, accompanied by the weight of its sins, will see itself falling into the void, entering the great abyss that separates life and death, losing the essence of its nature as an exile.
As one bids a final farewell to the affairs of human life, facing death and leaving life behind, they are drawn into that dreadful and barely visible abyss, chained by various crimes of greed and malice.
The punishment they will receive will be as great as the value they have lost.
When they reach those cruel places of custody, where they will rage in anticipation of the future judgment of punishment, grief alone, without any comfort, will torment their soul.
Thought alone will torture their despair.
Fear alone will examine their shock.
And because there will no longer be any concern for preparing food or clothing, no occupation of labor, military service, or business, no ambition for wealth or honor, the intolerable terror of giving an account will fill their mind, empty of all other cares.
The entire weight of judgment will press upon their captive senses.
And what of when they are ordered to return to the prison of their body and, through resurrection, to resume it for the company of the wicked?
What will they do when they have to present before the pure eyes of angels with the foul marks of their wounds and give an account of each one before the King of Ages?
If these were now placed before us, they would undoubtedly be unable to bear their guilt, oppressed by the shame of great confusion.
What state of mind will they have then, seeing others there receiving the reward of an unblemished and whole faith from the Lord, the treasure of purity, the fruits of mercy, the talents of justice?
When they see the first becoming last and the last becoming first, the poor exalted above the rich, the servants above the masters, and each one rewarded with the light of immortality according to their merits, promoted from human status to that of angels, and their once earthly body placed above the heights of the heavenly kingdom, and enriched with the wealthy inheritance of God, the parent of majesty, among the sons of majesty; while they, left with their sins, return from the spectacle of others' happiness carrying the wounds of their own sorrows?
What then?
When she sees herself in such a wretched condition, stripped of all comfort, cast into outer darkness, and separated from the blessed Church by perpetual excommunication, cut off from the very root of life, how can a trembling and guilty speech explain it?
When the flesh, unable to be cleansed, and the marrow, tainted with sins, begin to be penetrated by the fierce fires of hell, and like boiling and melting metals, the entire substance of man is filled within with an unquenchable heat, bodies and souls are partially consumed, partially nourished by the devouring flames.
In the midst of the fiery globes, the damned nature provides fuel and receives growth.
If by chance the sin, long ago sprinkled on consciences, and the adulterated mixture of brass and lead, is ever burned away in the boiling pools of a heaving gulf, the magnitude of the punishment will be the delay in crossing the fiery ford due to the greatness of the sin.
Crimes will provide food for the fires, and the command of both the author and the judge will remain that the organs, subject to pain and consecrated only to torture, will be consumed by the fire not to be devoured, but to perish in order to be continually destroyed.
The work and formation of our body, dead in ancient crimes and revived only for torments, will not find an end at the brink of destruction, but the exhausted virtue of endurance will perish in such a way as to rise again.
For that burning is not accidental, but rational and punitive, because it is commanded to seek out guilt, it does not know how to consume substance.
And because, like a light burning through canvas, that very purification is, the flame pursues not so much the criminal as the crime.
If there is a measure of sins, there will be a measure of tortures.
But if the excess of deadly crimes has completely occupied and enveloped the entire nature, since the cause does not receive a remedy, the punishment will lack an end.
As the punishment ends and life-giving judgment begins, the material world will endure for ages.
It will be able to be restored but will never completely escape evils, as the end is always elusive.
Even after immense periods, it cannot promise itself any hope.
The torments of future ages will already be felt in the present.
Thus, the immortality imposed on the conscience will intensify the pain of death.
Woe to those who, in the future, find these lamentable things laughable!
Woe to those who must experience these things before they believe in them!
Therefore, my beloved, all these things that cannot be ended there can be redeemed here through correcting one's former life, through alms, through tears, through humility of heart, through chastity of the body, and through acts of justice and mercy.
Given this, we rush toward death through so many errors, even though we have been given so many paths to salvation.
Through Jesus Christ, our Lord, who lives with the Father and the Holy Spirit.
Homily Two
We must understand, dear ones, the benefits that holy activities bring us, even in the present.
Sacred texts tell us that clean animals are those that chew the cud.
What it means to chew the cud is clearly taught by the divine word, saying:
"His delight is in the law of the Lord",
and on his law, he meditates day and night
(Psalm 1:2).
And again:
"The meditation of my heart shall be before you always"
(Psalm 48:4).
In the same way, as we spiritually chew the food of salvation, we shut out improper thoughts with closed minds.
We take pleasure in praising God, and we feel that our inner selves become clean through holy exercises.
By guarding against improper desires, we satisfy our souls with heavenly food, so that the prophetic saying can be applied to us as well:
"He gave them the bread of heaven."
"Man ate the bread of angels."
The bread of angels is Christ, whose food we partake in when we engage our minds in his praises. Behold the true food, which nourishes and does not diminish but grows with use and increases with expenditure. We are refreshed by this bread while hungering and fed by fasting, imposing a certain force on our vices and desires, so that it may be said of us:
"The kingdom of heaven suffers violence",
and
"the violent take it by force"
(Matthew 11:12).
We must understand who the violent are.
We know that the human mind, enticed by various worldly temptations and desires, avoids labor and seeks pleasure.
It is hardly brought to exclude the habits of its former life.
But when it begins to think of the necessity of the last day, spurred by the weight of future judgment—either by the hope of reward or fear of punishment—it declares a voluntary war on its passions, forces its former pursuits, and strives to conquer itself violently by changing to a better life.
It's impossible to move from abundance and riches to hunger and thirst, to abstinence and the cross, without some degree of struggle.
To subject a body that loves sleep and leisure to hardship and sleeplessness requires effort.
Each person must forcefully exchange anger for patience, pride for humility, and abundance for a love of poverty and sufficiency.
It's about choosing sobriety over drunkenness, chastity over luxury, and transforming oneself into a different person.
This kind of change takes effort, and it's through this struggle that the kingdom of heaven is taken by force.
There are two kinds of abstinence and the cross: physical and spiritual.
Physical abstinence involves refraining from drink and feasts, controlling the appetite for gluttony, and withdrawing from sensory pleasures.
Spiritual abstinence is more profound; it involves governing the movements of the soul, calming its disturbances with modesty, curbing the impulses of pride, and fighting daily against one's vices.
This inner battle requires stern self-discipline and a kind of strict virtue.
By breaking through the wall of passions, one forcefully ascends to the kingdom of heaven.
May He who reigns forever and ever, who lives in His fear, guide you on this path.
Amen.
Homily Three
The divine teaching guides and encourages us on how to prepare ourselves to seek His promises and attain those blessings that cannot be seen, heard, or understood by thought.
"Ask, and you will receive; seek, and you will find; knock, and it will be opened to you"
Luke 11:9.
This means we should ask through prayer, seek through our efforts, knock with our desires, knock through progress, and knock with perseverance.
We should be so driven by the hope of heavenly promises and so passionate in our feelings that the greatness of our desires matches the worthiness of the rewards.
Our God does not want His blessings to be cheapened by being too easily found; precious and desirable rewards require a passionate lover and an eager seeker.
Therefore, the One who promises such great gifts does not want you to be lukewarm in His work; He despises the indifferent, rejects the unwilling, and spurns the undevoted.
To seek the grace of divine gifts slowly and with little gratitude is a great insult to the Rewarder.
Even if we exert ourselves with all the efforts of our soul and body, and practice with all the strength of our obedience, we will still not be able to offer anything worthy of heavenly goods.
The services of this present life cannot be compared to the joys of eternal life.
Even if our bodies grow weary from vigils and our faces pale from fasting, the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory that will be revealed in us
Romans 8:18.
Therefore, dear ones, let us knock as much as we can, because we cannot knock as much as we should.
The future happiness can be obtained but cannot be estimated.
Unless we do God's work with eagerness, goodwill, and joy, we should know that we are perishing in God's sight.
Do we think, dear ones, that the soul that presumes to respond to a light command from the elder by saying, "Are we your servants? I have done my part, let him do his," is seeking worthily and knocking in such a way that it will be opened to it, when it is commanded, "Do not seek what is yours?"
And again:
Not looking to their own interests, Philippians 2:4.
This is expected not only to fulfill their own reward but also to invade, preempt, and seize others'.
We believe that one should ask to receive, seek to find, and knock to have it opened.
Who, when corrected for negligence and disciplined, does not strive for improvement but rather stubbornly says, "I desert and depart, I cannot endure this, I am a free man."
First of all, he who boasts of being free before the superior or abbot does not realize that he was bought.
He who claims to be free while serving in Christian duty almost denies that he was bought with the blood of Christ.
Saying "I am free" is like telling the Lord, "I owe nothing."
About such people, the Apostle said: "When you were slaves of disobedience, you were free with regard to righteousness" Romans 6:20.
He is not truly free who is oppressed by the servitude of vices.
Instead, he insults discipline and sins against his soul by saying: "I prefer to leave rather than amend, to satisfy, to fulfill what you command."
This is nothing but shaking off the yoke of Christ from a rebellious neck.
Such people have forgotten why they came here.
They do not ask rightly but are wrongly driven by vices.
They knock not in faith but are knocked by infidelity.
What good is it to leave when you are bound by the chains of passions, surrounded by your vices on all sides?
What good is it to leave when wherever you go, you carry yourself with you?
You would rightfully leave if you could escape yourself anywhere.
Someone would worthily depart if he could go to a place where the devil could not find him.
No one should deceive himself by fleeing the adversary from place to place, but rather from vice to virtue, from passion to amendment.
If you flee in this way, he will follow you.
Amend yourself, and he will flee from you, as the Apostle says: "Resist the devil, and he will flee from you" James 4:7.
Not obeying and wanting to leave means doing the devil's will in two ways: it brings damnation upon oneself, even in the present.
For those who commit serious offenses among us, there is no harsher or more bitter sentence than being cut off from the body of the congregation and leaving without peace.
Isn't it a kind of madness for someone to seek this as a remedy, which even a leader wouldn't impose except for the most serious crime?
Therefore, let us understand, dear ones, that these indignities and contradictions are orchestrated by the enemy.
Since he cannot absolutely remove anyone from the place of salvation, he first sends opportunities and causes, igniting the passion of disobedience, which is always accompanied by infidelity.
When this captures and ensnares the mind, even small and light things become intolerable and impossible.
Indeed, there is no doubt that strength is divinely withdrawn from the disobedient.
Just as the one without necessary faith devotion had even what he had taken away, disobedience hardens the mind it has captured, so it is not swayed by authority or reason to accept commands.
Worst of all, it believes only in itself, follows its own intentions as the sole reason, and considers right only what it has conceived with a hardened heart.
It becomes like the one of whom the divine word declares: "The ways of fools are right in their own eyes" (Proverbs 16:25); and again: "There are ways that seem right to a man, but their end is the way to death" (Proverbs 14:12).
Finally, it will happen to such souls as it did to the house built upon the sand (Matthew 7:26).
This parable especially applies to the disobedient.
We read: "Everyone who hears these words and does not do them will be like a foolish man who built his house on the sand: the floods came, and so on" (Matthew 7:26-27).
When the drops of suffering pour in, when torrents and tribulations come from our many negligences, and when the winds blow—those winds that hover in the air, ready to winnow Christ's threshing floor, seizing and scattering the chaff for their mockery—then they will rush into that house built without the foundation of obedience, and its ruin will be great.
But someone might ask: Is it immediately a ruin to leave this place?
I say, dear ones, there is little hope if it is like a ship in the waves.
Although it may not perish, it suffers a huge loss of its cargo and goods, arriving at the port empty and void.
Similarly, it is not a great joy if someone in the world seems to keep the name and habit of their profession, but their soul wastes away and decays due to neglect.
What is more serious than being suddenly uprooted like a bird from the place where your Lord had called you, where He first enlightened you, and led you from the evils of the world as if to a port from a severe storm?
To suddenly forget brotherhood, companionship, and consolation; to forget that place where you first shed your old worldly habit and name?
Even birds love their nests; wild animals love the places where they were raised; they love their lairs and pastures.
No matter how much they are driven away by cruel attacks, due to natural freedom, they often return to their beloved places out of a certain desire for food.
And you, endowed with intellect and equipped with reason, sometimes become so alien to sense that you prefer your own wills or intentions over God's blessings, following your own thoughts.
No matter how much they drag you into hard labors, shipwrecks of salvation, and the ruin of your soul, yet due to excessive indignation of heart, you do not feel it at all.
This is what the divine word says:
At the time of departure, the enemy promises many things.
He convinces himself that where he is going, he will find greater progress, much grace, and an abundance of all things, and that he will be received as an angel.
But after these things, when he is filled with anxiety and stripped of peace, he remembers how he abandoned the pursuit of his progress and the sacred fold.
Then he realizes.
It's as if the storm of his time has calmed, and he sees the evil he has done to himself.
He recognizes the danger he incurred when he departed from the place he once came to with joy, now without peace and with scandal.
He regrets his ruins with late repentance and weeps.
Just like certain birds that are said to weep over those they have killed, all these damages to the soul occur from the evil of disobedience.
However, obedient and humble souls overcome many tribulations and all labors, and send them away quickly.
It must be known that the more humble and obedient we are, the lighter and sweeter we will feel the yoke of the Lord upon us.
The more obedient we are to our superiors and fathers, the more God will obey our prayers.
Let's see how acceptable to the Lord are the works and fasts of those who obey their own wills rather than those of their elders.
They cry out: Why have we fasted, and you have not seen?
We have humbled our souls, and you have not noticed?
And He responds: Because on the days of your fasts, your own desires are found.
(Isaiah 58:3)
We see that through the disobedience of souls, their works are not regarded, their fasts are not heard, and their vows are not accepted.
Therefore, let us more diligently follow the commandments of Him who descended from heaven to us for this purpose, not only to redeem us with the price of death but also to build us up by example of life.
And let us say with Him: I have come not to do my own will, but the will of Him who sent me, the Father.
(John 6:38)
But following one's own desires is so pernicious that the Lord, in His wrath, imposes it as a punishment for sin, saying: And I let them go according to the desires of their hearts.
Therefore, whoever wants their works to be safe or right in the sight of God should prioritize nothing over obedience and should not put anything before it, whether they are older or younger.
The older one is, the more they should strive for edification and perfection.
They should set no limit to their progress or what they can achieve, for it is said to them: "Prepare your work for departure" and again: "Do not fear to be justified until death" Ecclesiasticus 18:22. And again: "Wisdom is praised in the end" Proverbs 1:20.
Therefore, the more we progress, the more we should humble ourselves, because the more we humble ourselves, the more we will progress. No elder should appear so learned that they think obedience, which was appropriate for God, is not suitable for them. Humility and obedience are necessary for the young, but for the elders, they are dignities; the one who progresses well, acts each day as if they are always beginning.
Therefore, the growth of merits should be incentives for progress. Scripture speaks about those who, neglecting their first faults, always fall into others, saying: "The sinner will add to sinning" Ecclesiasticus 3:29. But about progress, it is said: "And the holy one will still be sanctified" Revelation 22:11.
Let's first see what it means, "the sinner will add to sinning." For example, if the passion of any evil or slander begins to attack me, if I am not immediately pricked by repentance, tomorrow such ease and certain (so to speak) sweetness of this vice will come to me that I will not be able to turn away from it and restrain myself.
For it happens that the one who did not want to correct at the beginning will start in the future neither to want nor to be able.
For example, if I began to yield to pride, violated the rule, harmed an elder, and destroyed a younger, if I was not immediately sorry for being so gravely overtaken, the violence of habit and the force of passion will carry me away more and more each day with the utmost delight, so that I no longer understand that I am offending, nor do I feel that I am sinning.
The burden of sin and the habit of sinning can obscure and overwhelm the mind.
Indeed, the heart becomes so hardened by negligence that if it doesn't humble itself, if it doesn't make amends for its intentions, it believes it is causing harm to itself.
Furthermore, it boasts and says:
How steadfastly I resisted them, how well I did not yield, how authoritatively I responded?
He thought I should always humble myself to him.
Anyone who acts this way has clearly given themselves over to the devil, who delights in the vices, passions, and destruction of people.
This kind of soul will face that judgment: The sinner will add to sinning Ecclesiasticus 3:29.
But we, dearest ones, should avoid this and rather hold on to what it says:
And let the holy still be holy Revelation 22:11.
Let us add to our merits daily, and not presume anything about ourselves, because everything we can do is from God.
Therefore, let us be tireless in the work of God, for the sake of eternal reward, and strive for better things every day.
For the very eagerness to grasp, the very habit of making progress will always provoke us to greater things.
When God sees a more fervent devotion of the soul, he will inspire affection.
As much as we add to our effort, so much will he add to our help.
As much as we apply ourselves to diligence, so much will he add to our glory.
Whoever has, more will be given to him, and he will have abundance Matthew 13:12.
In another place it says: I have placed help on the mighty one Psalms 89:20.
Therefore, grace is born from grace, and progress serves progress.
Profits serve profits, and merits make profit from merits.
The more someone starts to acquire, the more they should strive and delight in seeking, so that the profit of acquisition nourishes the appetite for acquiring.
The more eagerly someone drinks from the goods of wisdom, the more they will desire to drink, just as Wisdom itself speaks of itself: Whoever eats me will still hunger.
So let us hasten, dearest ones, our course, so that our life may grow in the end.
Let us seek until the end, where we may deserve to rejoice without end.
Even if we can't perform physical work, let's focus on our desire for spiritual growth, increasing our contrition and charity.
If we set our hearts on ascending every day, no illness or age can wear us out, making us worthy to ascend these spiritual steps to the promises of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Homily Four
Just as the Lord demands us to speak out of necessity, He also requires you, dearest ones, to be willing to listen.
So, I say, it is beneficial for your well-being to obey what we say for your salvation, just as it is our duty not to remain silent.
If we fear the offense of silence, how much more should you fear the offense that comes from contempt?
If it is a great danger for us not to correct others, how much more dangerous is it not to correct ourselves?
The blessed Apostle says: Consider your calling, brothers First Corinthians 1:26.
Therefore, dearest ones, let us also consider our own calling.
It is not enough that we have chosen this place if we are here the same as we could have been in the world.
If we see clearly, not only does this solitude bind us to the necessity of perfection, but the multitude of the congregation itself compels us.
It is precious and important to act well among many and to inspire many to progress by the example of good deeds.
However, it is dangerous and harmful to break the faith of many and corrupt their souls by acting negligently and tepidly.
Just as it is fruitful to live commendably among many, it is dangerous to do anything destructive.
Why do I say this?
Because, unfortunately, we more easily find those who follow what is worse rather than what is better; human frailty tends to imitate evil.
Therefore, let us not believe it is sufficient to see ourselves gathered in this school, unless professed perfection more vehemently condemns our negligence than if it had not been assumed.
For according to the faith of Scripture, to those who promise much, much is required.
Oh, how beneficial the opportunity of this place and the occasion of suitable habitation will be for many, and conversely, how harmful it will be!
It is not to be praised for having lived in this place, but for having acted well in this place.
Because what good is the solitude of this dwelling to the righteous when tyranny and wickedness rule over us?
When anger prevails, and human eyes see greater fears in us than divine ones?
When we, who believe ourselves to be praiseworthy hermits outside the world, actually hold the world within us through various passions?
So, we thought we could help the world through our prayers, but we almost see that we need the world's intercessions more.
It is undoubtedly true that a soul possessed by the desire for worldly pleasures cannot become the kingdom of God.
Therefore, brothers, consider your calling.
Coming to the desert is indeed the highest perfection, but not living perfectly in the desert is the greatest condemnation.
What good is it if we physically occupy a place of peace, but turmoil stirs in our hearts?
What good, I ask, is it if there is silence in our dwelling, but a tumult of vices and a struggle of passions in its inhabitants?
If our external tranquility holds, but our internal is a storm?
We did not come to this place for the world to serve us, to enjoy all things abundantly in complete peace: not indeed for rest, not for security, but we came for battle.
We advanced for the struggle, we hastened to wage wars against vices: to blunt the swords of tongues, not only to avoid harming each other but also not to feel hurt.
Particularly, this pertains to our profession: to seek no consolation in this life, no peace.
To not want to receive good things in one's life but to shun honors, to rejoice in subjection and rejection, to eagerly seek poverty, and to eradicate not only possessions but even desires from our hearts.
For sometimes having nothing is a necessity, but desiring nothing is a virtue.
Therefore, a religious person should impose this way of life upon themselves: to have only as much as necessity requires, not as much as desire covets.
The love of possession, unless completely cut off, is often more intense with small things, causing people to be more tormented by even the smallest matters.
If you are not poor in heart and spirit, poverty itself should be seen not as a virtue but as misery.
Let us understand, therefore, brothers, that it is useless to afflict our flesh with fasting and vigils if we do not correct our minds or care for our inner selves.
What good is physical affliction if we pollute our tongue with wickedness and slander?
Aren't all our efforts reduced to nothing?
Doesn't our work vanish like smoke and shadow, turning to ashes and disappearing like chaff?
Oh, how many long-lasting labors suddenly perish!
How many good things, frequently already acquired and stored up, are snatched from our hands while we neglect to guard what we strive to acquire!
Therefore, we falsely flatter ourselves about the cross and bodily affliction if our exterior is engaged in holy labors but our interior is not cared for from passions.
It's like making a statue golden on the outside but clay on the inside; or like a house magnificently built and beautifully painted on the outside but full of snakes and scorpions on the inside.
What good is it to afflict your body when your heart is not improved?
It's a very hard and grievous condition to devote all effort to the study of labor and not receive the fruit after the labor; to fast and keep vigil, and not correct your manners.
It's like someone who weeds and cultivates the outside of a vineyard but leaves the vineyard itself abandoned and uncultivated, so that it produces thorns and thistles, which, with the cultivator's attention, could have produced the most delightful fruits.
Recognize, therefore, dearest, that to achieve eternal salvation, bodily abstinence alone is not enough unless the fasting of the soul is also fulfilled by abstaining from vices.
For what good is it if someone is chaste in body but polluted in mind?
Whoever is corrupted by malice, driven by the flames of anger, stripped of all God's grace by pride, or stained by lies and curses from their tongue, are they not deceiving themselves?
Are they not mocking themselves if they believe they can be sanctified by fasting and keeping vigil alone?
And therefore, beloved, let us exercise our bodies with fasting in such a way that we cleanse our minds of vices.
Let us constantly think of the coming of that Judge, who will find us prepared, as no one can doubt He will come.
And if you ask how He will come, it will certainly be with the body that was taken for our salvation, condemned for our crimes, damned for our absolution, and pierced with a lance and nails for the healing of our wounds.
For the presence of those venerable scars will be the first unbearable sentence for the guilty.
So what will we do at that time when the marks of our sins and the stains of our lusts are brought forth against the bruises of our crucified Lord?
How do you think our Redeemer will look upon our destruction?
Human sins will be all the graver, the greater the divine benefits have shown themselves to be.
We must fear that He will bring forth in His judgment that voice of resurrection proclaiming the precious marks of the cross, and say to the vessels of iniquity: "Put your finger here, and see My hands; and bring your hand, and put it into My side" (John 20:27), and recognize what I suffered for you and because of you, human impiety.
Those signs of the nails, beneficial to the good and terrifying to the evil, which are kept without pain until the day of judgment, will undoubtedly be presented.
And what follows this but that fearful chasm between the living and the dead, the vast separation of the outer darkness excluded from the nature of the living, the harsh separation from the sweet sight of the saints and the fellowship of the faithful?
And on the other hand, among the tearful moans and wails of the mourners, the miserable assembly of the wretched, and from the blessed homeland, the eternal exile of the most dreadful night?
How sad it will be for a person to see God, to lose Him, and to perish before His presence!
So, dearest ones, while there is still time, let's think about these things and work tirelessly so that what was given to us by the Judge, He may find intact in us when He judges.
Homily Five
We know that the spiritual warfare to which we have committed ourselves has a great reward stored up for the future.
But if we look closely at the work we are doing right now, we can see that we also possess a part of the reward even in the present.
It is truly a great benefit of life to have been able to disdain worldly things and to have begun serving God, to have escaped the miserable dominion of vices, and to have fled the vile slavery of gluttony and lust.
So what then?
Isn't it already a great part of the reward to have nothing in common with the world, not to be tormented by the desires for vain things, not to be mixed up in crimes, to spend the day in innocence, to devote oneself to blessed chastity, and to possess the sufficiency of glorious poverty with the fear of the Lord?
About which Wisdom speaks:
"Better is a little with the fear of the Lord, than great treasures without the fear of the Lord."
Let us understand, therefore, how much the Lord has granted us through His loving call.
Let us count, if we can, from the time we seem to have been preserved here, how much we have gained:
from how many frauds, from how many adulteries, robberies, perjuries, sacrileges we have been freed.
And then we will see how much we owe the Lord even for the benefits we have received in the present.
If we were now in the world, what else would we be doing but wallowing in our evils, staining our souls with daily blemishes, and being wounded daily?
And in such a way that we wouldn't even feel it.
For this is the nature of the unfortunate habit of sinning, that the more one sins, the less one understands their sins, and the more they enjoy sinning.
As the prophet cries out to sinners:
"God is not in their sight, Your judgments are far from them" (Psalms 10:5);
for when the pleasure of sinning creeps in, the memory of the future judgment day is immediately hidden by forgetfulness.
On the contrary, the more one is concerned with themselves, the more they fear, as Scripture says:
"The wise man fears and departs from evil" (Ecclesiastes 1:16).
Therefore, a wise person is always in sorrow and fear.
Just as they sigh over past evils, they tremble with vigilant anxiety over future dangers.
Those who are anxious about past actions think to themselves: maybe they have not wept enough for the past, maybe they have not yet made amends for their countless debts, maybe they have added new wounds to old iniquities, maybe they have imprinted recent crimes over the old stains of their conscience and taken on the name of a changed life only to sin more grievously under the guise of sacred profession.
Some of us think it is enough that we have ascended to this secret place, changed our location and appearance, and lived here for some time, placing all our hope in the number of years.
Thus, deceiving ourselves with a harmful persuasion, we think we have settled all our debts and believe our evils have vanished with the passage of time.
Because we have forgotten them, we believe they have escaped the memory of divine severity.
But it is not so.
All things are collected, stored, and marked with Him.
Let us listen to what he who fought the devil hand to hand in a singular contest, the blessed Job, says: Job "You have sealed up my offenses in a bag" Job 14:17; and again the Lord Himself says: "Are these things not stored up and sealed in my treasuries?" Deuteronomy 32:34.
Let us not think that once-engraved sins can be easily forgiven or that deep wounds impressed in the very depths of the soul can be healed without much effort. Much weeping, groaning, and heartache are needed to heal the pains of the heart. We must apply the entire spirit of contrition, so that old evils, like certain arrows, may be driven out from the conscience.
It is not enough to simply say with our lips: "I have sinned, forgive me, pardon me." Saul said, "I have sinned" First Samuel 26:21, but he did not obtain the pardon that David earned with a single word of repentance. And why is this? Because that confession expressed mere words more than true groans. The joyful humbling of the supplicant did not compensate for the magnitude of the crime.
We must not take lightly the need to address the debts for which eternal death is owed, nor should we dismiss the need for addressing evils destined for eternal fire.
If we want to understand how seriously our judge takes human faults, we should look at the punishments.
As patient as our God is in enduring our sins now, He will be equally severe in examining them; and just as He has prepared immeasurable glory for the righteous, He has also prepared immeasurable punishment for the wicked.
Therefore, we can infer the severity of the punishments from the greatness of the rewards.
Because He who knows how to reward merits also knows how to punish sins.
The remembrance of future judgment and the reflection or lamentation of past sins is very beneficial and much needed.
If someone flatters themselves with the merits of a blameless past life and believes they have served the Lord innocently, thinking they should be secure, they should consider how uncertain and slippery the outcomes of life are.
As it is said: "Do not praise a man during his life" (Ecclesiasticus 11:30).
When they consider this, even if they think they have nothing to mourn from the past, they will find something to fear for the future.
Therefore, no one should feel secure about the past.
So many snares are laid before the feet of our soul, so many enemies watch and guard our path, so many pitfalls and cliffs, so many difficulties lie between us and our end; the path itself, which is narrow and arduous, is beset by so many spiritual robbers.
We must navigate so many rocks and waves before we place our anchor on the desired shore, and yet we think we should be secure about the past and pass our days without daily care, without daily fear and trembling!
Imagine crossing a deep river on a very narrow bridge.
Even if you've safely made it most of the way, a small stumble at the end could still cause you to fall.
In the same way, even if most of our life seems to have gone well, we shouldn't become overconfident, as the final part still holds potential dangers.
Think of a battle: who would lay down their arms before the fight is over or before victory is secured?
No one.
So, we shouldn't consider ourselves safe until we've reached the end successfully.
We also shouldn't think that just being counted among God's servants, by name or by dwelling, is enough for our full salvation.
Our God tells us: Not everyone who says to me, 'Lord, Lord,' will enter the kingdom of heaven.
Why is this?
Because it is not those who merely hear the law who are righteous before God, but those who do the law who will be justified.
Therefore, even if we've lived well so far, we must continue with stability and perseverance, persisting and progressing in our calling.
Truly, I say, even if we've spent twenty or thirty years serving the Lord, to whom we owe everything, if we were to spend just one year straying from this path, it would greatly diminish the joys of eternal life.
All our hopes rest in completion and in the end.
What good are green crops if they promise a harvest but fail at the last moment due to bad weather or floods?
What good is a vineyard that blooms with promise but loses everything to wild animals or hail before the harvest?
Therefore, all prosperity and efforts rest in the end.
When it grieves those who, after many years of hard work and progress, are pulled away by some desires,
what will become of those who believe that four or five years here is a very long time and waste the rest of their lives on worldly vanity?
Even a year in the world can consume our efforts in the desert, just as a great sea can swallow a tiny stream without even leaving its name.
I don't know what gains we wish to live for in that world.
Here, it is considered a great loss not to acquire something every day, but there, it must be considered a great profit just not to lose what has been acquired.
Where it is a serious loss not to progress daily, there it is the utmost virtue not to perish.
Therefore, if we are still poor and needy, let us strive to achieve something here.
If we have achieved something, let us take care to preserve it here.
This alone will be our gain and joy, that we have lived for the Lord here.
Therefore, as long as we remain here, it is within our control to turn to the world whenever we want.
But once you turn away, it will be difficult and almost impossible to look back at this place even in thought.
If anyone thinks they can safely leave this place someday because they have run well and worked hard here, such a person is acting like someone who sets sail with a ship loaded with goods from the port, only to hand it over to storms and drive it onto rocks.
The more we labor, the more cautious we must be.
For those making progress, the enemy lies in wait.
Where he sees any hope or grace, like a roaring lion prowling around to seize prey, he attacks with all his might.
Since he cannot harm those who are here, he wants to lead some of the less cautious away from this place through thoughts and various temptations.
It's as if he's trying to draw them outside the camp, pulling them down from a well-fortified citadel.
Once he has done that, he fights them from a higher position.
Even if he cannot steer the ship, he can at least bring back delightful spoils from the losses and damages that abound in the world.
He will first send various intentions, indignities, and animosities.
While a man strives to fulfill what he has once decided and defined in his fury, he does not think of his own harm nor consider his ruin.
When he has brought him down, then follows a regret that will soon be worth nothing.
Here we are, and yet we are not whole.
We are either agitated by various improper and dishonest thoughts of the heart, or we are wounded by the poisonous swords of the tongue, causing scandal over the smallest and most trivial matters.
Sometimes, even (which is not fitting for a monk) breaking out into quarrels and disputes, and sometimes violating our profession by breaking the rule, not fearing to commit theft against our superiors, indeed not fearing to commit it against our own souls under the eyes of God.
What we fear to do in the presence of our superiors, we do not fear to commit under the eyes of God.
We are not content with necessities.
Through the lukewarmness of the heart, we desire the abundance that we left behind in the world.
Hence, it is not enough that we have excluded external resources from ourselves when desires have settled within us.
From this, it happens that we are sometimes stirred up over the smallest things, and we move the vilest intentions for the desire of worthless things.
Why is this?
Because although we have left behind external goods, we still retain internal evils in our hearts.
And among these, how our adversary exults when he sees that we have despised great things only to be more disgracefully conquered in the smallest matters?
Therefore, getting rid of external things is useless unless we also uproot the things that cling to the innermost parts of the soul.
The Apostle did not say that gold or silver is the root of all evils, but rather the desire for wealth.
First Timothy 6:20 states this clearly.
And not only the rich, but also those who want to become rich fall into a trap and temptation.
This is further emphasized in First Timothy 6:9.
Therefore, the Apostle condemns not only those who have wealth but also the desire to have it.
So, abandoning external possessions means nothing if we hold onto vices within ourselves.
Thus, brothers, we are here, but we are not entirely here; and those within these walls barely resist.
So, what will we do when exposed to the world?
How will those in such danger in the harbor stand in the storm and the onslaught of battling tempests?
Therefore, as much as we can, let us be steadfast.
In this most peaceful bay, even the negligent or lukewarm one has not run in vain if they persevere to reach the prize of completion.
Homily Six
Brothers, we have gathered here to dedicate ourselves to our Lord, not to those things that our enemy delights in.
When we focus on worldly matters or engage in excessive murmuring and backbiting, our enemy rejoices because our time is taken away from God and given to him.
What good is it to exhaust ourselves with precious vigils and labors, yet lack what our God most desires?
God desires a clean heart, free from these minor negligences that, if not addressed, gradually lead us astray and into greater faults.
Therefore, let us first strive to have what our Lord expects from us: gentle and kind speech, a mind free from malice and cursing, dedicated to humility, peace, and charity, avoiding those things that offend the Holy Spirit.
These are the principal sacrifices, the rich offerings, which ascend before the Lord as a pleasing aroma.
Let us also strive to perform these acts in honor of our Lord with a clear mind, the joy of faith, and the affection of good and devoted will.
Whatever we do unwillingly and under compulsion, let us know that we not only gain no benefit from it, but incur the greatest loss.
If we were to provide a service to a powerful man, which higher-ranking persons customarily expect from their clients, wouldn't that man, seeing us perform the duty owed to him with reluctance and disdain, consider it more an injury than an honor, and declare that he is dishonored rather than respected, believing that such negligent and undevoted service deserves offense rather than gratitude?
If the worship and honor of man require devotion, faith, and cheerfulness, it is often better for the one providing the service than for the one being honored, where no benefit is derived from the service itself, but the only benefit is that it may be called worthy of acceptance.
How much more should we honor our God and not come to His service unwillingly and reluctantly, not sad, not ungrateful, and not reluctant, so that God may regard the gifts that are offered with a negligent and vile spirit?
For it is not to a man, but rather to Him to whom our faith promises to serve.
To serve Him, even unto death, even to spend one's life for Him, should seem little; whose services and benefits even the angels confess to be inadequate.
To whom, although everything is owed, nothing is repaid for free, but He repays as though He Himself has become a debtor, in return for the payment of debts, and will restore immense things for small ones.
For this miserable life, full of labors and sorrows, in which both its use is brief and its brevity uncertain, a life which even if the devotion of will pretends to offer to its Creator, the law of death will immediately demand from us, and what is not given by vow, is paid by debt.
For this life, He will give that life which cannot be seen by the eye, nor reached by the silent thought of the mind.
Which indeed is easier to obtain than to describe; whose course will be without end, use without weariness, refreshment without weariness, rest without the leisure of night, age without old age, unfailing brightness under the face of God, and under ancient and perpetual joys always new delight, secure happiness without any danger of loss.
Therefore, let us now try to taste the sweetness of this life daily by contemplating the future ages, even in this body.
And excluding from our senses the bitterness of worldly conversations or desires, let us draw to ourselves the fragrance of that blessedness with all our hearts.
And having dispelled all sluggishness, all laziness, whose mother is infidelity, let us serve the Lord and our God with that cheerfulness, that eagerness, and that joy, by which joy we may come to His gifts at His invitation.
Homily Seven
Those who have chosen to live among many people either yield great fruit or face great danger.
They can be either diligent or negligent.
Blessed is the soul that, while living well in a community, becomes a source of joy for many and helps to uplift and enlighten others.
For indeed, the good it shares with many is increased.
This aligns with the wisdom of the saying:
"My son, if you are wise, you are wise for yourself and your neighbors" Proverbs 9:12.
Therefore, if someone in a community maintains obedience, shows humility, and patience, they build up many and lend to many more.
The good they offer to their neighbors is turned into their own profit.
However, if through disobedience or pride they lead others to sin, they destroy many and incur the danger of damnation.
Whatever harm they caused to others, they also suffer losses from many.
The sin that came from them once, returns to them many times over.
Therefore, just as the one whose life benefits many is greatly admired and praised, so too the one whose life causes the downfall of many is rightly mourned.
So, dear ones, let us strive to do those things that build up others while we are in their midst.
Let our vices not harm others' virtues.
Let our lukewarmness not weaken others' fervor.
Let our anger not violate others' patience.
Let our pride not corrupt others' humility.
Let our weakness not spoil others' health.
Let our ugliness not contaminate others' beauty.
Let us not extinguish others' burning lamps if we cannot light our own.
Indeed, even those foolish virgins, no matter how foolish they were, did not seek to extinguish others' lamps but to light their own.
Therefore, if any of us lack the fullest grace, warmth of humanity, fire of faith, flame of fervor, oil of charity, or light of discernment, let us seek those who are abundant in these qualities.
We should transfer grace to ourselves not by taking it away from others, but by imitating them.
Embrace the good qualities of others without causing harm, but rather with benefit for everyone involved.
You will never run out of anything that benefits another.
A fire lit for many never loses its own light, nor does the multitude of observers diminish the light of the sun.
Instead, the more people look at it, the more it shares its gifts, while always remaining whole.
Blessed is the soul by God, whose humility confounds another's pride, whose patience extinguishes a neighbor's anger, whose obedience silently chastises another's laziness, whose fervor awakens the inertia of another's tepidity.
The one who illuminates the troubled heart of their neighbor, disturbed by anger, with the grace of consolation and edification.
Better is this person than the one who, when their brother is slightly saddened by something, not only fails to lift them up with an outstretched hand, but rather helps push them to ruin with malicious words.
When corrected for the sake of discipline, they incite with bad advice so that others may fall, and arm them in such a way that they may perish.
Therefore, brothers, if our own evils are not enough, let us not act in a way that incurs judgment for the destruction of others.
It is certain, dearest ones, that unless we daily cut back and circumcise our passions, we will become much worse than we were when we lived in the world, making our latter state worse than the former.
Homily Eight
When a farmer prepares his field with seeds, he knows it's not enough to just plow the rough field and break up the hard clods.
He understands that he must also remove unfruitful growth, clear harmful debris, uproot thorny roots, and eliminate weeds, because his land can't be fertile without getting rid of the bad growths.
He takes to heart the words meant for the spiritual farmer:
"Break up your fallow ground, and do not sow among thorns" (Jeremiah 4:3; Hosea 10:12).
Similarly, we who are God's cultivation must remember that our hope is in heaven, not on earth.
It's not enough to merely tame our body with vigils or fasting.
First, we must cleanse our minds by removing vices, pruning our habits, cutting out passions, eradicating pride, planting humility, digging out anger, laying a foundation of patience, cutting off envy, grafting in kindness, and nurturing our hearts with virtues like seeds of good crops.
Otherwise, if our flesh is worn out but our soul does not bear fruit, it's like a field that's endlessly plowed but never yields a harvest.
Therefore, if we are not cleansed inwardly and are afflicted outwardly, we face struggles on both fronts.
We impose so much labor on ourselves for the sake of the soul, yet we invest no effort in the soul itself.
We've given up various worldly pleasures and delights, which brought some joy and sweetness, yet we can't abstain from pride, anger, and the poisonous passions of envy, which bring only bitterness and rancor.
For the love of our Lord, we were strong in leaving behind sweet affections and dear pledges, almost to the point of hating the most delightful faces of our loving parents, so we fled.
We have, in a way, declared war on piety itself.
Now, to avoid negligence, we are weak and lazy in fighting even the smallest faults.
We started by giving up the pleasures of the world in a big way.
But now, we think it's impossible and beyond human strength to overcome things like speaking ill, criticizing, getting upset over petty things, getting angry at people, and being scandalized.
However, what we give in to now in small matters, we do not blame on our own faults.
We teach that our actions are not because it's impossible, but because we are lukewarm.
Therefore, brothers, let's look back at the faith and fervor with which we began.
At least, let's take an example from the start of our way of life to improve our behavior.
If it's dangerous not to add something every day, how much more dangerous is it to have fallen away from our beginnings?
It's necessary, then, that physical labor is followed by spiritual fruit, which means correcting our habits.
The faults attacking both the inner and outer man must be conquered and overcome by each person's effort.
It does little good to break the body if there's no concern for the heart or focus of the mind.
If only the body works and our spirit resists, what good is it to fight passions with a servant found to be at peace with her mistress?
It's easier if sometimes only the flesh is troubled by attacks, like being disturbed by the pricks of gluttony and lust.
It's possible it may not reach every danger if the mind rejects pleasure.
But if the desire for sin takes hold of the mind's fortress, what good is it if the outside seems untainted while the better part is corrupted?
If the inner part is conquered, both parts are already captive.
What good is it to wage war outside the city and suffer destruction within?
Therefore, if the passion of disobedience, the spirit of envy, and the habit of criticizing greet me as I return from my vigils, if secret presumption tempts me to break the rule, and if I mix weeds with the wheat, what seemed to be gathered is scattered, and I have given the hope of the harvest to the birds and wild animals.
In one moment, I wasted the labor of the entire night, and what's worse, I didn't even realize it.
This is the nature of spiritual goods: while they are acquired with great effort, they can be lost so easily that it is hardly noticeable.
This is why we sometimes think people are holy, because we judge them by the gains from their efforts, and we are unable to see the subsequent losses.
Oh, how often we fall into the evil of judgment, the disease of vanity and boasting, without even realizing it!
How often we are burned by the spirit of envy or confused by improper and obscene thoughts, and no sense of pain or remorse follows the awareness of our wound, no contrition or repentance!
But why am I speaking of these hidden things, which penetrate the soul with a serpent-like stealth, striking the unsuspecting and ignorant with a venomous bite?
Sometimes, we openly clash in battles of scandals, stabbing ourselves with our own tongues through slanders and malicious talk.
We are harmed by vices brought against our superiors, and in their injuries, we somehow strike Christ the Lord Himself, who said: "Whoever rejects you, rejects me" Luke 10:16. No pang of conscience, no cure of repentance follows.
But why do I seek the medicine of repentance in us? If only sometimes, after hoped-for forgiveness, there were no regret! If only those who are not ashamed to be humiliated were not regretful to be humbled!
Let that soul answer me, which was so ashamed to acknowledge its sin in a deadly embarrassment before the brothers, as it should have avoided. What will it do when it stands before the divine tribunal, when it is presented before the assembly of the heavenly army? When it begins to be pressed from all sides by the most forceful witnesses, surrounded by the old evils which it refused to cure through the remedy of humility and contrition while it could, which it reserved whole for the eternal judgment and the eternal judge by hiding and concealing them from its superiors.
Therefore, those who grieve and confess their faults and negligences, even those considered small, should know that they have quickly escaped eternal punishment.
So, if we desire not to be deceived by the vanity of the flesh, secret and shameful thoughts, silent pleasures of the mind, and the impiety of an incautious heart, we must first be eager to rid ourselves of the obvious things, such as gluttony, anger, pride, inflated contradictions, and evil criticisms.
For how can we foresee the enemy in secret if we cannot avoid the open battle here?
Therefore, dear ones, our duty requires us to fight not against others, but against ourselves every day, and by constantly pursuing all our enemies within ourselves, we may achieve the spiritual victory granted by the Lord.
Indeed, as long as we belonged to the world, engaging in actions and affairs that now shame us, the adversary did not oppose us; on the contrary, he even agreed with us, because he found nothing to envy in our miserable and lost lives.
Our deeds pleased him, and our crimes were sufficient for him.
Who would wage war against his own soldier?
Who would want to attack his own subject?
Above all, the life of one whom the enemy did not deem worthy to harm was truly unfortunate.
But now, after we have renounced his pleasures, he sees his followers return to the service of their original creator.
He sees, in a way, his idols transformed into temples of God within us.
Gnashing his teeth and roaring like a lion, the ever-watchful adversary explores every possible way to harm us, as mentioned in First Peter Chapter Five.
He directs his attacks through visions, bringing with him seven spirits more wicked than himself, in case he finds our house empty and unoccupied by spiritual goods.
With his hordes, he might be able to take it over, so that he may prepare a dwelling place for himself by sending vices ahead as scouts.
And therefore, dear ones, he devises a thousand ways to harm us.
The younger ones and the foolish, or those with improper behavior, are either tempted by the allure of gluttony or attacked by the urges of untamed flesh.
This aims to corrupt their minds, pollute their thoughts, and gain an unworthy victory over their chastity.
Better and older individuals, on the other hand, are attacked through the evils of pride and boasting, attempting to conquer them through their own progress and merits.
While considering their age and accomplishments, through the most impure vanity, they lose the humility of heart.
What is dangerous is that they convince themselves they are pleasing man in the sight of God.
Moreover, a common and familiar evil is that our tongues become swords against us, inflaming the stings of anger.
It intoxicates the mind with various passions, so when we become angry, criticize, or curse, we believe we are harming others.
But it is not so, dearest ones; for the evil of each vice falls back on its own author.
The slanderer stains their own tongue, the detractor wounds their own heart, the angry one blinds their own mind, and the envious one poisons their own soul with envy.
In this, what Solomon said is fulfilled: "My son, if you are wise, you are wise for yourself, but if you scoff, you alone will bear it" (Proverbs 9:12).
Therefore, beloved ones, as I said, it happens that sometimes we feel worse than we did in the world.
In our struggle, we are our own instigators towards evil because we assist the enemy we have provoked through our own actions in the midst of the battle.
Nor do we persevere with the fervor with which we began, but succumb to weakening tepidity.
Therefore, the great name of our profession must be defended with great strength.
It is a great thing that we have promised to God by coming to the desert, however many things we hope for from God.
Therefore, let us examine all laziness and weariness of mind, and carry out the precious battle with precious affection.
Let us not wait to be compelled to our Lord’s service like hired workers and servants, nor be content for someone else to demand from us whatever we know pertains to our salvation and glory.
Above all, let us be careful that what we must do, we do not do unwillingly.
Let's not resist the task beforehand, nor complain while doing it, nor take false pride in the finished work.
Above all, brothers, let's daily examine our shortcomings with a careful eye.
Let's bring them into view after dispelling the cloud of indifference, saying: "I acknowledge my sin, and my transgression is always before me." Psalm 50.
It's a crime that sometimes habit makes our sins seem trivial and insignificant. Just as we grow from small good deeds, we should be remorseful for small negligences.
It's not a small thing to neglect even the tiniest faults in life. I don't know of any sins that should make us feel secure, not even those committed in ignorance, as we will have to account for idle words and thoughts.
I don't know which sins should be overlooked, especially when even the Lord Himself declared: "Truly, I tell you, whoever says to his brother, 'Fool,' will be liable to the fire of hell." Matthew 5:22.
Who could hope for any leniency in these matters? Just as man is prone to sin, the mercy of our Lord is equally rich in forgiveness.
Therefore, let's consider our calling, brothers, and walk in humility, with all patience and gentleness.
Let's guard our mouths; the fear of future judgment should temper our anger; the thought of the last day should break our pride.
Let's consider the grief that will befall the negligent soul departing from this body— the distress, the darkness, the gloom— when the conscience, surrounded by various crimes, begins to confront it with numerous adversaries.
With all evidence put aside, it will confront our eyes directly, so that both the proof may convict us and the recognition may shame us.
No one will be able to conceal anything or deny it, as the accuser and witness will emerge not from afar, but from within.
Therefore, to understand future confusion from the present one, let's consider this: if someone among us had their sins and secrets exposed just as they are known in their hearts, truly, no one could bear the gaze of everyone else.
What will the unhappy soul do when faced with its shame and filth before the eyes of angels?
But the soul that has lived well, obeyed Christ through its elders, and kept its commitments in all things, will not fear that final hour's inevitability.
Leaving the body, it will feel like being brought into the light after a long prison darkness, like being introduced from a dark cave into a royal hall, or being taken from a pit of misery and filth, dressed in splendid and shining garments, and placed among the sweetness of flowers and spices, refreshed by wonderful fragrances.
Let's remember how pleasant rest is, how delightful relaxation is after laying down a very heavy burden.
How sweet it is to return to a beloved homeland with regained freedom after long captivity.
How precious it is to arrive at the desired land and longed-for harbor after the dangers of a long voyage.
From these, let's gather and understand how pleasant it will be to pass with a good conscience to true and solid joys, to the companionship of angels, and to ascend to that life where there are no labors, no pains, no losses, no inconveniences, and above all, no sins; only eternal innocence, inviolate justice, unshaken security, and everlasting happiness.
Homily Nine
Consider your calling, dearest brothers (1 Corinthians 1:26).
Coming to the desert is the highest form of perfection, but not living perfectly in the desert is the greatest condemnation.
What good is it if you remain calm in a quiet place, but your heart is restless?
If your surroundings are silent, yet your mind is full of turmoil and struggling with desires?
If everything looks peaceful on the outside, but there's a storm inside?
We often count our years and the times we live in.
Don’t be fooled by the number of days you’ve spent here, leaving behind the world physically.
Only count as living the day when you denied your own desires, resisted evil cravings, and lived without breaking any rules.
Count as living the day when you were not stained by malice, envy, or pride; the day you were not tainted by lies or perjury; the day you did not give in to sin and stood against the devil.
Count as living the day filled with equality and holy meditation, the day whose brightness was not turned to darkness by evil company.
Count that day as part of your life, the day whose purpose reached your soul.
We often flatter ourselves with our regular fasting and visible vigils, yet after these vigils, we fall into the evils of gossip, verbosity, and grumbling.
It's much better for someone who sneaks away from the choir of singers to engage in disgraceful feasting and secret drinking—not only with shameful transgression but with abominable vileness—to simply sleep in sobriety.
Who, while fasting, carries around a heart burdened by anger and swelling with rage?
Who abstains from wine but is disturbed by the bitter intoxication of discord?
Who mortifies himself outwardly by avoiding life-giving drinks, but internally spews the deadly poison of hatred from his infected heart?
Does he not understand that the prophetic words are already directed at him, even in this life, as someone pre-condemned:
"Is this the kind of fast I have chosen?" says the Lord (Isaiah chapter 58, verse 5);
or, "Their vine is from the vine of Sodom and from the fields of Gomorrah. Their grapes are filled with poison, and their clusters with bitterness" (Deuteronomy chapter 32, verse 32)?
Sometimes, however, the devil, when he notices a soul empty of faith and stripped of the fear of God, intoxicates the mind with various passions.
When we curse, get angry, or slander, we believe we are harming others.
But it is not so.
For the evil of each vice falls back upon its own perpetrator, as divine scripture says:
"My son, if you are wise, you are wise for your own benefit; if you scoff, you alone will bear it" (Proverbs chapter 9, verse 12);
The slanderer stains his own tongue, the detractor wounds his own heart, the angry man blinds the light of his own mind, and the envious person corrupts his own soul with a sort of pestilential rust.
Just as vipers are born to ulcerated parents, tearing their mothers' insides, human hearts are first torn apart by the very passions they have conceived.
The hearts from which the serpentine generation of vices emerges are first violated by the monstrous fertility of such births.
Concerning such a birth, divine scripture says:
"Behold, he travails with iniquity, conceives trouble, and brings forth falsehood. His trouble shall return upon his own head, and his violent dealing shall come down on his own crown" (Psalms chapter 7).
Therefore, having heard these things, our fervent love for you has long been tormented by pain due to the negligence of some.
And relieved from some of the burdens of the heart, we urge, advise, and even beg you for your own sake (if you are not too proud to listen to the affection of one who commands), to correct our ways from now on, to amend our negligences, so that we do not have to come hereafter with harsh words, but with the necessary measures that hardened hearts demand.
Instead, strive from now on to compete among yourselves with commendable efforts and better emulation.
Let each of you be more dedicated in the work of God, more fervent in prayer, more diligent in reading, purer in chastity, more restrained in sobriety, more generous in shedding tears, more honorable in body, more sincere in heart; milder in anger, more moderate in gentleness, rarer in laughter, more fervent in compunction, more grounded in gravity, more cheerful in love.
Therefore, let us discipline ourselves and hold ourselves accountable for our daily conduct.
Let each soul reflect in the secrecy of the heart and ask: Have I passed this day without sin, without envy, without slander and murmuring?
Have I done anything today that contributed to my improvement, that helped in the edification of others?
I think today I have destroyed that which was beginning; today I have been disobedient to my elder, I have lied, I have perjured myself, I have been overcome by anger or gluttony; today I have laughed more; I have indulged more in food and drink, more in leisure and sleep than was fitting; I have read less, prayed less than I should have.
Who will give me back this day, which I have wasted in vain tales?
So, brothers, let us be moved by compunction for all our negligences in our beds that is, in our hearts: if you do this, we will rejoice in your progress, but you will rejoice in the salvation you have gained, and you will submit to us for the acquisition of your salvation.
May His kindness grant that you advance from our teaching, so that you in turn may help us with your merits, and be an ornament to us in the present and a protection in the future.
Homily Ten
The divine word says in a certain place: On your solemn days, afflict your souls
Leviticus 16:29; 23:27.
Why did He say this?
Because fasting, vigils, and holy afflictions humble and weaken the body, but they purify stained hearts.
They take away strength from the limbs, but add brightness to the conscience; for the sins of pleasures are redeemed through contrition.
Through the exercises of the hard cross, the joys of the deceived flesh are punished.
In this way, the sentence of future death is forestalled by present mortification.
While the author of sin is humbled, the sin is consumed.
While external affliction is inflicted by voluntary strictness, the offense of the terrifying judgment is appeased.
A small amount of labor pays off great debts, which eternal fire would scarcely consume.
Therefore, considering the cause of our salvation, let us do within ourselves what doctors usually do for us.
If some injury or complaint is felt on the surface of the body, a milder remedy is applied.
But if the wound is hidden in the bones or deeply submerged in the innermost parts, the hidden force demands a harsher and more violent medicine.
The greatness of the ulcer is either cured by burning, and pain is driven out by pain.
A similar method should be applied to the illness of the inner man.
If the sins are perhaps slight, for example, if a person has sinned either in speech or in some reprehensible desire, if he has sinned with his eye or his heart; the stains of words and thoughts should be cured by daily prayer and wiped away by private remorse.
If anyone, upon examining their conscience, realizes they have committed a serious crime, betrayed their faith with false testimony, or dishonored the sacred name of truth by perjury, if they have stained the veil of baptism or the garment of pure virginity with shame, if they have killed the new man within themselves, or surrendered themselves to the devil through soothsayers, diviners, and enchanters—these and similar offenses cannot be expiated with ordinary or secret penance.
They require serious and public remedies.
Just as they have destroyed themselves with the ruin of many, they must redeem themselves with the edification of many.
A person deceives themselves if, when they feel the disease burning within their very marrow, they apply a gentle ointment only to the surface of their body.
These principal evils therefore need great wailing, groaning, and a flood of tears.
After weeping, they must say with the prophet:
"I roared because of the groaning of my heart; every night I flood my bed with tears"
(Psalm 6).
And again: "I ate ashes like bread and mingled my drink with weeping"
(Psalm 102).
No one should despise this humility.
It was a great king who said these things; it was a great king who did these things.
Therefore, just as a deceased person is mourned loudly, so too should there be great lamentations over a soul that has perished.
And just as a bereaved mother laments with a broken heart over the loss of her only child, so too should one grieve over their own soul, but with the hope of restoration.
Concerning this only soul, the prophetic message says:
"Deliver my soul from the sword, my precious life from the power of the dog"
(Psalm 22:21).
Why did he say "precious life"? Either because it must be cherished as precious, or because it alone, singular and solitary, will stand before the heavenly tribunal to give account, with all comforts removed.
Thus, it is necessary to pour out the full weight of sorrow over this precious soul pierced by the sword of sins, in hopes it can be revived by the fountains of tears and the warmth of faith.
Our sorrow must be kindled, and our prayers strengthened by remembering the future judgment, supported by works of mercy.
We must heed the words of the prophet with obedient ears, who says:
"Take my advice, O king, and redeem your sins with alms" (Daniel 4:24).
We should also consider the example of the man from the Gospel, as if it were written for our redemption:
"Look, Lord, I give half of my goods to the poor" (Luke 19:8).
About whom we heard in the Gospel, the Lord saying with indescribable dignity and love:
"Whatever you did for one of the least of these brothers and sisters of mine, you did for me" (Matthew 25:40).
These words commend the effects of alms to us with heavenly authority.
But when we speak of alms, noble poverty might become frightened.
Not so, dear ones: let them remember that small coins were preferred to the treasures of the rich.
Because our God is not nourished only by the abundance of giving, but by the goodwill of the giver.
I also believe, dear ones, that our Lord allowed the poor to exist in this world to test the faith of the rich through the poor; or that by showing mercy to the poor, He might show mercy to the rich,
so that those with abundant good works would not lack this opportunity for redemption,
that a benevolent rich person might be enriched even by the poverty of another,
and that everyone who is wealthy might receive great profits from the needy:
and through a marvelous and supreme exchange, while temporary mercy is given to the needy, an eternal treasure is compensated for oneself.
Let us direct our actions, and whatever strength we have, towards exercises of goodwill, and pursuits of justice and mercy.
Let us run while we have the light, before the darkness overtakes us (John 12:35),
for in that world, it will no longer be possible to make amends and seek redemption.
As the divine word says:
"For in death there is no remembrance of you" (Psalm 6:5).
Just as there will be no fear of losing merits there, there will be no forgiveness of sins granted.
There will be no opportunity given to perform good works anymore.
Can anyone feed the hungry there, where there is no need for eating and drinking?
Where neither the wicked in the flames of hell nor the righteous in the delights of paradise will need food and drink?
Can anyone clothe the shivering there, where all concern for covering the body will cease?
Under that cold, of which the prophet says:
Psalm 147:17, "Before his cold, who can stand?"
Where the one who loses the wedding garment here will be naked forever. Where the wicked will be clothed in the darkness of a stained conscience, but the good will be clothed in the robe of immortality and blessedness.
Where garments will be rewards, as it says in Matthew 13:43, "Then the righteous will shine." And again in Psalm 132:9, "May your priests be clothed with righteousness." Or this in Psalm 45:9, "The queen stood at your right hand in gold of Ophir."
Where the eternal light will shine instead of the tunic of the holy bodies, there the clothing, never to be removed through any ages, will be converted into the body. There, the garment will turn into a reward. There, that angelic robe will no longer be an outfit, nor a habit, but a nature.
Can anyone there, being greedy or stingy, do good to another from his abundance? Where even for himself he will not find a single drop in the midst of the boiling lake?
For he will not carry anything with him of what he believed he owned, as the prophet said in Psalm 49:17, "For when he dies, he will take nothing, neither will his glory descend with him." Hearing amidst his weary torments, in Matthew 25:35, "I was hungry, and you gave me no food; I was thirsty, and you gave me no drink."
Let us understand what a condemnation it will be to have robbed the poor, whom it is the greatest crime not to have fed. Therefore, to anyone who now oppresses the poor and needy without any consideration of future judgment, as someone said, "The time will come when he will wish he had left the poor man untouched, and not plundered the one he hated."
And how intolerable the pain will be if anyone incurs the causes of death from where he could have obtained the joys of life?
Do not look down on the poor, because even though they are poor themselves, they can make you rich.
Let us seize from this present age, with fervent devotion, what we can.
Our days pass quickly, may they pass well!
Let us therefore seize what we can from this age, giving thanks to Him who has arranged both lives in such a way that the times of labor and struggles end quickly, but the joys of honors and rewards last forever.
Homily on Saint Blandina of Lyons
Even if we were to pay our respects to martyrs from distant lands, we would still be acting for our own benefit and advantage.
Faith would make them our own, and even though they are far away, we would gain the protection we hope for.
Such help comes from devotion, not from physical locations.
Therefore, you will gain as much intercession from God’s own household as the amount of reverence you show.
Thus, our religious devotion should make outsiders our own, rather than allowing our own to become distant from us through neglect and lack of faith.
Let us recognize, dear friends, the abundant gifts God has given to our church.
People of each city rejoice if they are blessed with the relics of even one martyr; see, we have a multitude of martyrs.
Let our land rejoice, the nurturing mother of heavenly soldiers and the fertile parent of such virtues.
The wicked enemy could not benefit her as much through service as he did through the sword.
For as the holy feasts of this present day clearly show, the more evil rose against her, the more grace and blessing now overflow in her.
We read in Bethlehem that Herod, while trying to kill Christ, destroyed thousands of innocent children, as the prophet says: “Rachel weeping for her children, and she would not be comforted because they are no more” (Jeremiah 31:15; Matthew 2:18).
In the same way, this blessed mother, this renowned homeland of triumphant warriors, rich in the merits of such precious pledges, may have seemed to lose when seen through the eyes of the living, yet she does not need consolation and does not weep for her children; because in the face of grief, by losing, she gained.
Confidently among these things with you, O Bethlehem, land of Judah.
You who endured Herod's savagery through the massacre of the children; you who once deserved to offer to God a pure, innocent people.
Rightly, I say, with you, O Bethlehem, our Lyon would compete and compare the divine favors around each, as if speaking with you, saying:
O Bethlehem, you perhaps surpass us in the number of martyrs.
I, by merit, was in your slaughter, but not in your confession.
In my people, there was the struggle of suffering, in yours there was only the opportunity and chance of happiness.
You were enriched by the blessing of the outcome, I by virtue.
You could see those perishing in the blood of the little ones, but you could not expect those who fought.
You were crowned by the innocence of the dying, I by the glory of the triumphant.
Yours reached the reward of the kingdom without the consciousness of martyrdom, mine, however, afflicted by torments, tested by sufferings, endured the harsh fires of sacrifice.
As many punishments as they received in their bodies, so many crowns they received in their spirits.
And thus, through the wounds of tortures and delays of tormentors, they were consecrated before being killed.
You offered children by age, I also by completed merits.
I offered those who would conquer through their torments, though they could be endangered in their faith.
You offered those who could have the fruit of dying, who could not fear the danger of denying.
You offered a weak people, lest a sacrilegious might find Christ.
I offered a strong number, by whose example even Christ might acquire the sacrilegious in saving the persecutors' servants.
Finally, that blessed death by which Herod, while seeking the holy child alone, sacrificed only the children.
Your triumph was earned by one gender, mine by both.
My fight won the victory over the prince of the world even among women.
My chorus could have your innocent children, your chorus could not have my Blandina.
Divine providence granted among these things that even in such sacrifices of the homeland, a bishop would not be lacking.
He is dragged to a wicked interrogation, the aged and venerable Father Focinus, bishop of this Church.
For his wisdom, as we believe, he remains united with his flock.
After the sacrifice of the Lord's body, he is brought before profane tribunals as a new offering to Christ.
His old age, through the injuries and afflictions inflicted by raging servants, meets such a swift end that you would understand he was preserved for martyrdom alone.
Blessed is he who, at the very threshold of life, finds his end not so much in nature but in glory.
Here, the pious minds of such a great father are strengthened by his example and embrace the punishments they face.
The various kinds of cruelty and new tortures consume the invincible hearts of the saints.
By disregarding the unbearable weight of their sufferings, they conquer.
Fires are applied, but they serve only to consecrate.
Beasts are incited, but their untamed ferocity marvels at its prey.
Torn apart by various torments, their limbs are sanctified by the flames that cannot consume them, honored by beasts that cannot rage against them.
Where are those who say veneration should not be given to the sacred bodies of martyrs?
Behold the bloody savagery that, without understanding religion, still offers veneration.
What ignorance of rational distinction does not accept, the condemnation of evils reveals the honor due to the saints.
Thus, the instrument or ministry of punishment becomes a miraculous testimony of merits.
While it shows reverence to piety, it silently judges impiety.
So then, dearest ones, while our Church is adorned with such trophies of faith, lawlessness seeks to surpass itself in the novelty of its crimes.
Depriving the sacred bodies of the honor of burial, they gave them to the flames.
After the death of men, they fought against humanity itself.
And even when the source of their anger had already perished, they did not stop their cruelty.
Whether they wanted to or not, they witnessed their blessedness, envying them even in death.
How is malice always paired with stupidity?
They turned the venerable bones to ashes, as if the flames could destroy their merits and virtues.
What confusion and madness!
They denied the earth to those who were gaining heaven.
So, you have done nothing new in your cruelty.
You thought you were erasing their memory, but instead, you spread their glory.
You scattered the saints' dust in the flowing Rhone River, thinking they would not rise again.
But resurrection is not destroyed by water, which is celebrated by the grace of regeneration, even through the gift of water.
You entrusted the revered relics to the Rhone.
The force of the river in dissolving the body does what time would do.
So, whatever the bird has snatched from human remains, the beast has devoured, or the wave has swallowed, even if it's not enclosed in a tomb, it is held within the bosom of the world.
For the restoration of man does not depend on the reason of the earth, but on the nature of the law and the power of the restorer.
For He himself testified with a true mouth: I am the resurrection and the life (John 11:25), who lives forever and ever.
Amen.
Homily on the Holy Martyrs Epipodius and Alexander
It's certainly wonderful to offer prayers at public and communal celebrations, but an even greater joy comes from celebrating the virtues of those who have been nurtured.
The veneration and honor of local martyrs and special patrons bring particular joy and require personal affection.
If we are to diligently venerate foreign victories, crowns, and overseas triumphs, making what is foreign our own through our services, and sharing in what is not enclosed in graves through our prayers, how much more fitting it is for us to fervently celebrate and serve those to whom religion owes devotion, the Church honor, and the homeland love?
Just as we are kin to them through the bond of one parent's womb by the right of birth, we claim the privilege of piety and grace towards them.
We approach them with the devotion of faith so that we, who rejoice to be citizens with them on earth, may also deserve to have citizenship with them in heaven.
Thus, the double trophies of Epipodius and Alexander are celebrated by the faith of our Church within a span of two or three days, not with festivals of foreign relics, but with festivals of the unblemished monuments of our native land.
Many of the people's Churches are content with the sanctification they receive by touching the sacred garments or the hard bonds of chains.
Instruments of punishment become testimonies of glory, and materials of pain turn into marks of merit.
However, we possess the whole and complete illustrious gift of the blessed.
What could suffice for the entire world, we hold specially enclosed within the embrace of this city.
We lift up the twin palms of triumph, emulating the apostolic, to the City.
With our own Peter and Paul, we contend with the sublime seat with two intercessors.
And indeed, blessed martyrs, whose precious dust is spread throughout various regions bringing salvation to the people, are honored with full reverence to God.
The more celebrated they are with rich faith, the more acceptable their celebration will be.
But without a doubt, it is much more pleasing and joyful for them if they are especially honored with fervent piety where the fury of their passion occurred; if prayers and sacrifices are offered where they fell as sacrifices to God; if future generations raise vows where cruel savagery spilled innocent blood; if, finally, the enemy of the Christian name sees them consecrated where he thought they were killed.
It is sweeter for them, I say, if they are praised with blessings where they endured great tribulations; if they are invoked for help from where they will first be called to their reward with the sign of resurrection.
Since these things are so, dear ones, to hold onto faith and cultivate religion, we do not need to wait for any evidence from afar.
We are instructed by our ancestors' teachings and reminded by examples from our own household.
Does not the living voice of our relatives' blood cry out to our hearts?
"Learn from us," it says, "to seek and acquire faith, to cultivate it by living, to preserve it by dying; learn to fear sin more than the sword, to love justice more than life for the sake of life, and to fear God. The faith we kept in the midst of war's tribulation, be sure not to lose in peace or the security of peace. Beware not to lose the anchor of hope and religion we guarded in the storm, while you are in the harbor. Beware not to judge a good life as miserable if you see it subjected to afflictions. Beware not to expect any happiness in the world's arena, where we are sent to undergo trials. Blessedness can be prepared here, but it cannot be acquired. Do not seek here what no saint has achieved through labor, no confessor has obtained; do not seek here what even Christ did not find."
If the world had peace, the martyrs would not have glory; if trials did not come first, there would be no opportunity for tribulation.
These, then, are those, dearest brothers, who have gone through great tribulations, who have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb (Revelation 7:14).
They are comrades of those who, according to the Apostle, were stoned, sawed in two, and tested, killed by the sword, were needy, distressed, and afflicted, people of whom the world was not worthy (Hebrews 11:37).
But among these things, dearest ones, when the good and holy suffer so much here, someone might think to themselves and say: Surely the Lord of all things does not care for us, neglects human affairs, and ignores earthly matters.
Oh, whoever you are, how can you look at the labors of the saints and not consider their rewards?
See, throughout the world, in the holy apostles and martyrs, adversity has paved the way to happiness, loss has served salvation, and while it seemed to close the door to life, it opened the door to glory.
By denying the earth to those who trust in God, heaven was prepared.
Therefore, divine providence has set this as an example of patience for humanity.
Given these things, one who is not harmed by virtue is falsely considered miserable.
Let no one call poverty and the hardships of labor and the injustices of tribulation suffered by Christians and faithful people misfortune and misery.
When these things happen to the good, let us understand they are not burdens of hardship but exercises in virtue.
When a servant of God is allowed to struggle with adversity, they are not abandoned but tested; thus, the divine word says: "Blessed is the one who endures temptation; for when they have been proven, they will receive the crown of life, which God has promised to those who love Him" (James 1).
In this world, where evil prevails and injustice dominates, the poor are afflicted, and the rich are multiplied: do you call that person powerful who is strong to their own destruction, who gathers the causes of eternal evil from the deceitful shadow of present gains?
Who would call a hand blessed that is strong against its own throat?
Who would likely praise someone rushing quickly towards steep cliffs?
Who would admire the ascent of someone they foresee will fall from the top?
It's the same as marveling at someone gaining wealth and riches through wicked and unjust means, like watching someone mix poisons in a gold and jewel-encrusted cup.
Would you call happy the one who is unfaithful, lewd, greedy, and bloodthirsty because he scorns the ways of the Lord and is allowed to follow his own paths?
Offended by the narrowness of the right and delighted by the breadth of the left, entangled in crimes, stained by wickedness, contaminated by spoils, and amidst all this, considers himself very blessed, even more unfortunate because he doesn't realize he is unfortunate?
What use is the medicine of heavenly commandments to these people, which can only heal those who are willing?
Thus, lazy for the care of salvation, eager for the service of death and captivity, as it is said, they rejoice in wicked things
Proverbs
2:14,
and they delight in their own destruction; like those who, taking deadly plant juices, are said to perish with laughter.
But amidst all this, someone might think to themselves and say: God of power, God dwelling in the fortress of justice, either He does not condemn sins, which means He is ignorant of them, or He favors sins if He pretends not to condemn them.
It is undoubtedly known that He knows everything, who enters, fills, and exceeds everything, whose eyes see all things laid bare, about whom it is said: For the wisdom of God is manifold, and His strong power sees all continuously.
Therefore, it is undoubted that He knows everything and is close, who commanded you to enter the chamber of conscience when praying; who hears in thought and hears in the heart: that He condemns sins and crimes, the clear warnings of the prophets, the teachings of the apostles, and the oracles of the evangelists testify.
Meanwhile, as He proposes sad punishment, as He threatens eternal fire, He gives the sentence here, but there He reserves it for punishment.
Here He wields the sword, there He will bring destruction.
Why, He asks, does He not immediately punish the sinner?
Who could endure such a mental error?
There's often a complaint about God's patience, saying He shows forgiveness to those who don't deserve it.
But there would be no perfect justice in condemnation unless mercy came first.
Throughout the Scriptures, God kindly shows us His patience.
And what the Lord preaches about the servant—how can the servant criticize the Lord?
Don't we sometimes see even human law administrators, who are praised for their moderation as well as their strictness, prevent judgments through many precedents and edicts?
Guilt is already proven, yet anger is delayed.
They show that in their severity, they still value wisdom and forbearance.
Similarly, our Lord doesn't negligently ignore what happens on earth.
He patiently waits, examining the deeds and wills of people first, then judges, considers merit in their conduct, and tempers judgment with delay.
Gradually, He arranges human affairs through the delays of time, being the dispenser of eternities.
Here, He threatens a blow; there, He fulfills destruction.
But if God didn't understand human affairs, who would help the blessed martyrs in their battles?
Or how would the death of the saints be precious in the sight of God?
As it is written in Psalms chapter one hundred and sixteen, verse fifteen, "Precious in the sight of the Lord is the death of His saints."
Where would the salvation of the righteous from the Lord come from if they did not receive protection in times of tribulation? All these things show the presence of the Lord for those fighting the battles for religion and the justice of faith. He expects and protects. Hence, we should confidently beseech the Son as a helper and protector of martyrs, to strengthen our hands for the spiritual battle against the enemy. If feared, he must be repelled; if ignored, he will enter. However, he loses much strength if he becomes apparent to our consciences, as he only wins by deceit.
Our fathers fought against the harshest pains; we, on the other hand, must fight against the softest pleasures. They conquered the torments of flames; we must conquer the fiery darts of vices. They trampled the devil and brought back spoils from death. Let us beware lest we rob Christ in the poor.
Through the strength of their faith, they were offered as a sacrifice to God.
Let us ensure that none of us, through the wound of sin, becomes a victim of the enemy.
They suffered external punishments in their bodies.
We have what we must kill within ourselves.
As we reflect on the battles of illustrious warriors, let us contemplate our private struggles with our own passions.
Since we know there can be a battle without a persecutor, God can grant martyrdom without bloodshed.