Book One
The Egyptians who arrived wanted to show themselves as students of their province's ancient teachers, namely Jannes and Jambres, who were mentioned by the Apostle Paul in First Timothy three, eight, as having resisted God's servant Moses with certain tricks.
So too did they resist the truth.
When they tried to accuse us by saying that our faith in the Lord's incarnation deviated from the right path, we finally managed to secure from them an agreement.
Setting aside the arguments, individual speakers from each side would debate while the rest sat as observers, allowing only a few to act as judges who could give a verdict based on the merit of the conclusions.
It came to pass that Arnobius was the defender on behalf of the apostolic seat and Serapion was the debater from the Egyptian council.
The judges were Decius Constantius from the Catholic side and Ammonius from the Egyptian side.
II.
The proceedings began in this manner.
Serapion said: Before we come to the point where we accuse you of being Homuncionates, claiming there are two natures and two substances in Christ, I want to know, who are you?
Arnobius said: I am clearly a servant of Christ and a proponent of both the Catholic faith and the truth.
Serapion said: Declare what your faith believes.
Arnobius said: I believe in one almighty God, the creator of all.
Serapion said: How do you know this God, whom you believe to be one, is almighty and the creator of all?
Arnobius said: Because he has deemed it fitting to reveal himself to humanity with great powers.
Serapion said: What powers?
Arnobius said: To skip over earlier events, the land of your province is a testament, as it was struck by ten plagues, losing its king and his army, with almost all elements raging against it because it rebelled against God, the creator of all.
Through his servant Moses, he delivered the people from the sword with a strong hand and an outstretched arm, showing that he is God and there is no other besides him.
If you intend to dispute this, declare it.
Serapion said: Let us move past these points where our faiths agree.
Constantius and Ammonius, the appointed judges, said:
"It is clear that Arnobius has satisfied the matter concerning the one almighty God, and that Serapion has agreed with his assertion. Or, if that is not the case, let Serapion speak."
Serapion said:
"I am eager to know from Arnobius whether his faith does not err in other matters, lest by possibly addressing other issues beyond those in question-which could rightly be refuted-and neglecting the opportunity of this time, we seem to have achieved nothing here."
The investigators said:
"Let Arnobius say whether he permits this man to inquire about other matters besides those about which the contention seems to have arisen."
Arnobius said:
"I do not refuse to be questioned by him on whatever he wishes, lest I seem to cut off the opportunity for me to inquire from him whatever I wish."
The aforementioned judges said:
"Let Serapion say what it is that he wishes to learn from him."
Serapion said:
"Will you say that this one God, the deliverer of the Hebrews, is the only God, or perhaps another?"
Arnobius said:
"The God of the Hebrews is one God. Deuteronomy 6:4. When you hear 'God is one,' do not at all seek another God."
Serapion said:
"Therefore, is the Jewish assertion to be maintained, which declares and believes that the God of the Hebrews is the only and one God?"
Arnobius said:
"The Jews proclaim God as solely such that they deny His Son. They deny that the one who was born of the Holy Spirit from the Virgin Mary is one with Him."
Serapion said:
"The one who was born of the Holy Spirit from the Virgin Mary, is He the same one or another?"
Arnobius said:
"In divinity, He is one. In generation, however, He is another in such a way that the Father and the Son do not cease to be one God."
For God is truly believed to be one, and the complete Divinity is not denied in Him.
Serapion said: And how is the complete Divinity to be believed in Him?
Arnobius said: The complete Divinity is not denied in Him, if the Father, together with the Son and the Holy Spirit, are not entirely denied as one God.
Serapion said: By leading me away from the synagogue's council, you have led me into the madness of Sabellius, who confesses one God as the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit.
Arnobius said: If Sabellius truly spoke of one God, he would not deny His Son and the Holy Spirit.
For he denies the true Father, who does not speak of the true Son, and he denies the Holy Spirit, who does not believe that God is whole in the complete Trinity.
Serapion said: I read to you that Sabellius says anathema to those who dared to deny the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit to affirm the Trinity.
Arnobius said: But he, with the most impious defense, argues that he himself is the Father, he himself is the Son, he himself is the Holy Spirit.
But we say and believe that the Father, who begot the Son, is the Father of His only Son begotten before time.
Serapion said: I don't want you to take me to lofty heights; discuss this now, what was begotten before time.
First, let me exit this, because I understand you to say three gods.
Arnobius said: Your understanding suffers from error.
For you should remember me saying that you truly confess one whole God when you have believed the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit as one God, so that you do not merely say the Father as a concept, but the true Father, who begot the true Son.
Serapion said: So there is another, and another, and another.
Arnobius said: There is another, and another; and yet there is one God.
Serapion said: It cannot stand that the Father, who begot, is another; and the Son, who is begotten, is another, so that the Father is not the Son, and yet there is one God.
Arnobius said: I will show you yourself to have two persons with one substance.
Serapion said: Let the art of dialectic cease.
Arnobius said: The art of dialectic enters into obscure matters, so that what is true may be seen as true.
I promise to show you that two persons have one substance: in you, I mean, because I am discussing this, and you do not simply assert it.
Serapion said: Then simply show me how two persons can have one substance.
Arnobius said: Look, in one of your heads there are two eyes, but they have one sight:
two nostrils, but they have one sense of smell:
two ears, but they have one hearing.
If these pairs in you, being of one substance, contain unity, do you not want to believe that in God the Father and the Son, two persons truly have one substance?
Serapion said: This comparison is recognized as unsuitable, as you use physical body parts as examples for the incorporeal.
The judges said: You are in vain questioning the example taken by Arnobius from the body parts.
For if the physical parts of the eyes, nostrils, and ears, divided in their forms and remaining as if in their own chambers, obtain this unity of substance, enjoying one light, one smell, and one hearing:
how much more should God, who must be acknowledged as incorporeal, having one substance with His Son, also obtain the majesty of omnipotence with Him?
Serapion said: I indeed agree with the reasoning about the physical:
but unless there are incorporeal examples, I cannot relate them to the incorporeal.
Arnobius said: I ask, Judges, that you bear with your dissenting opinion kindly.
For I do not fear seeking those incorporeal examples.
I confess the true Father, the true Son, and the true Holy Spirit, truly three:
truly one, almighty, and I believe it.
Serapion should indeed be compelled to admit silence on this question, as I have given examples of both physical and non-physical things to prove that there are three persons in one substance.
The judges said: Serapion should admit that for the proof of this matter, only examples of non-physical things need to be provided by Arnobius.
Serapion said: I will certainly admit that it is enough when the non-physical examples are as clearly expressed as the physical ones.
Arnobius said: Can we say that perfect wisdom exists in a person who lacks memory, creativity, or intellect?
Serapion replied: How can wisdom be considered perfect if it lacks one of these three things?
Arnobius said: Therefore, if this is the case, and indeed it is; just as in one wisdom these three non-physical persons exist, that is, memory, creativity, and intellect, and though they are three, they do not make three but one perfect wisdom, if all three are perfect: so, in our faith, there will be one perfect deity when we believe that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit hold the omnipotence of one deity.
And just as there is no complete wisdom where something is lacking in creativity, memory, or intelligence, so there is no complete faith in a person who offends in any way against the Father, the Son, or the Holy Spirit, even to the smallest degree.
For faith is the light of the inner eyes; and just as if you prick any part of the eye with a sharp needle, you disturb and weaken the whole light, so too when an error is made in any part of this holy Trinity, even as small as an atom, or moment, or point, it turns the whole clear light of faith into a cloud: and once the mind is wounded, it sees nothing but darkness.
The judges said: Serapion, who did not agree to the physical examples because he thought they could not be applied to non-physical things, must yield to the provided non-physical examples, to reasonably admit that one deity is truly assigned to three persons.
Serapion said: Allow me, Judges, to ask him about what follows.
The Judges said: Just as you are not allowed to repeat what has been rightly concluded, you are not forbidden to present what has not been revealed.
Serapion said: You taught one Divinity in these two, that is, in the Father and the Son, first comparing them bodily, then incorporeally.
Now I want to know what you say the Holy Spirit is, because I sense you believe the Father has two sons.
Arnobius said: Unless I lead you to human reasoning, you cannot reach the divine.
Serapion said: Lead me wherever you wish, as long as you make me understand the reasoning of the Holy Spirit.
Arnobius said: I ask you to tell me, when the king says: Let a forum or a palace or something like this be built, I think that this command from the king made something that was not there come into being.
Serapion replied: It is agreed that this command from the king's mouth makes something that was not there come into being.
Arnobius said: Therefore, the word proceeding from the Father's mouth, full of power, creates all visible creatures.
Serapion said: Again, you have brought me back to the Father and the Son, when I am inquiring about the Holy Spirit proceeding from you.
Arnobius said: You cannot find the Holy Spirit being born, but proceeding.
Serapion said: Show me this procession now.
Arnobius said: I did not tell you this because you listen impatiently to things that could have led you to the investigation of truth.
Serapion said: I will listen patiently, follow wherever you wish, now show me what you mean by the Holy Spirit.
Arnobius said: First, you must admit that the Father said of His Son: My heart overflows with a good word from the Psalms.
Serapion said: Even if I wanted to deny it, everyone present who hears me would refute me.
Arnobius said: When the Word was born from the mouth of the Father, who created all visible and invisible things with His power, the Word could never proceed without the breath of the Holy Spirit.
Serapion said: Therefore, there are two sons that came from the mouth of the Father, namely the Word and the Spirit.
Arnobius said: You are mistaken in your understanding.
You have forgotten that I first led you to the example of a king who commanded markets, palaces, or baths to be made.
And I added: The command of his word had such power that things that never existed came to be.
You confirmed this before people.
Answer now again, is it so?
Serapion said: It is so.
Arnobius said: Therefore, if it is so, indeed because it is so: answer me: Is this Word born from the mouth of the one commanding, confirmed by just reason?
Serapion said: I agree that the Word is born from just reason.
Arnobius said: When the commander's word was born, which went out from the mouth to create what was not, was the breath that proceeded from the one who issued the word born rather than proceeding, able to be shown by any reason?
If this cannot happen for a commanding human, how much more for God?
The Word from the generating mouth cannot fall in such a way that the breath itself, full of the Holy Spirit, is called the Son.
But there is the Father who uttered the Word; and the Holy Spirit, who does not cease to proceed from the Father, having the same power as the Son.
For by the Word of the Lord the heavens were made firm, and by the breath of His mouth all their power.
(Psalms 33:6)
If you remember it is written this way, declare it.
Serapion said: It is written this way in the book of Psalms; there is no one who does not know this.
The judges said: Concerning the Holy Spirit, it is evident to you, the assertion is clear, which your agreement proves: now let us approach those things which have not yet been said.
Serapion said: Behold, just as in one perfect wisdom I agree with memory, intelligence, and understanding; so too I confess that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit exist in one Divinity.
But I ask you: Did the Father truly beget?
Arnobius said: You will find nothing in God that is made, only what is.
That is, the Father is indeed a true Father, a true begetter of the Son: a true Son, truly the only-begotten of the Father.
Serapion said: Before He begot the Son, was He only God and not yet the Father?
Arnobius said: You are mistaken in your question, for He was always both God and Father.
Serapion replied: Then He did not truly beget.
Arnobius said: He truly begot.
Serapion replied: If He truly begot, then before God begot, He was God; but He could not have been both God and Father before He begot.
Arnobius said: You are mistaken because you are comparing human frailty to divine omnipotence.
A man, before having a son, is only a man: but after he begins to have a son, he is still a man, as he was; and he also begins to be a father, which he could not have been before he begot a son.
Do not attribute this limitation to God.
God is unchanging and enduring, He accepts nothing new within Himself: for He has always been both God and Father, and this name of fatherhood was not added to Him: because anything that is incidental can also depart; and what can depart can also fail.
However, the divinity, which remains unchangeable, accepts nothing within itself by accident.
For it is today what it always has been.
Nothing from the past diminishes for Him, nor will anything grow from the future: nor do time periods rule over Him as they do over you, who were once a little child, then a boy, then a young man, then an old man, and after old age, your end comes.
If you think such changes can happen to God, you show yourself to be foolish and are proven to be a blasphemous outcast.
Serapion replied: May God avert this blasphemy, which now, born of foolishness, accuses one of blaspheming in ridicule.
Arnobius said: So, is God unchangeable, or does He change in some way?
Serapion replied: God is unchangeable; yet, by asserting that He begot the Son, He appears to be changeable.
Arnobius said: We have to return to some comparisons to show that birth occurs in such a way that there can be no division of time between the one who begets and the one who is begotten.
Serapion said: I hear something new, that no time can be shown between the one who begets and the one who is begotten.
Arnobius said: That's why we have observers and judges, so that we are cautious about saying we will show something we cannot.
Serapion said: Be careful not to bring me any physical examples again, trying to apply them to the non-physical.
Arnobius said: I'm already afraid of offending your wisdom in this matter.
Serapion said: Not my wisdom, but that of all observers and judges.
Arnobius said: Listen then to the non-physical generation from a physical man.
Serapion said: You're entering into a logical fallacy.
Arnobius said: A logical fallacy can have two sides: to prove what is claimed to be true or to argue that it is not true from some perspective.
But now, what I say, since I will only show the truth without any mark of deception, how can the logic I present be argued against?
Surely, if I say a man's voice is non-physical, am I lying?
Serapion said: Who has ever said a voice is physical at any time?
Arnobius said: No one has said this, yet I want to say that a man's voice is non-physical.
Serapion said: You're saying something that no one is unaware of.
Arnobius said: Is the word born from the voice, or is the voice from the word?
Serapion said: From the voice, the word.
Arnobius said: The word that is born from the non-physical voice, is it physical or non-physical?
Serapion said: Non-physical.
Arnobius said: Behold, from the non-physical voice, a non-physical word is born, the son of the voice.
Can anything later be found?
If you cannot find any time between the word and the voice, how can you find any intervening time between the Father and the Son, the immutable God?
In this investigation, the third person, the Holy Spirit, must also not be overlooked.
Since speech is born from the voice, and breath does not come from being born but from proceeding, through which the completeness of the word is preserved, in the same way, the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father.
Through Him, the complete and perfect Trinity is maintained in Catholic definitions, showing that the Father was never without the Son.
The judges appointed said, "Arnobius's statement likely also clearly explained the Holy Spirit with the Father and the Son. If there are other things that have not yet been said, let them be brought forth."
Serapion said, "If I do not bring forth what concerns me, what has been explained in my mind will be nullified by what has not been brought forward to reach an explanation."
The appointed judges said, "We will seem to tire ourselves with futile labor by listening, and you will work without reason in speaking, if things known to be concluded are repeated. Therefore, you must avoid and be careful in every way not to recall the struggles of words, once explained and concluded, as if you were out of your mind."
Serapion said, "I will not be able to repeat anything that has been explained to reach my agreement; however, it is necessary for me to propose whatever arises from those things that are concluded."
And he added, "Tell me, Catholic, you who do not deny that the Son is begotten from the Father, did the Father beget Him by will or by necessity?"
Arnobius said, "Neither by will nor by necessity."
The judges said, "Explain what you have said, because it is unclear."
Arnobius said, "Every man who wants something or does not want something, if he does not have wisdom beforehand, cannot want or not want something justly. Therefore, it is first necessary for him to have wisdom before virtue, by which he can want or not want something; and thus, he begins to be wise and want, when he has learned through wisdom that he can have it.
So, Serapion asks me, 'Did the Father beget the Son by necessity or by will?' I will briefly respond to one point.
One who suffers necessity should neither be called nor believed to be God."
When the question is settled regarding one absolute matter, the other remaining one must be resolved in this order: I ask the one questioning me, is it more important to understand rationally before wanting rationally?
The appointed judges said: Let Serapion respond to what Arnobius asks.
Serapion said: Who does not know that understanding rationally comes before wanting rationally?
Arnobius said: If wisdom comes before will, then the Son precedes the will, and He was begotten before the Father wanted or did not want anything, because when the will began, the wisdom, which you admitted to, was already earlier.
And although the reasoning I provided is already supported by your agreement, when you said, who does not know that understanding rationally comes before wanting rationally, I will still reinforce this reasoning with the authority of the Apostle Paul, who says about the Son of God that He is the power and wisdom of God in First Corinthians, Chapter One, Verse Twenty-Four.
The appointed judges said: It is clear that Arnobius spoke correctly, that the Father did not beget the Son by will or necessity, because God has no need; he proved with human reason and confirmed with the authority of the Apostle that will cannot be prior to wisdom.
If there are other things to be presented by Serapion, let them be revealed.
Serapion said: I recall you mentioning three persons, the Father as the begetter of the Son, the Son begotten by the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeding from the Father, and you mentioned that these three persons have their own divinity and are completely whole.
Arnobius said: That is so.
Serapion said: Therefore, the Father is not the Son, nor is the Son the Father, nor is the Holy Spirit the Father and the Son; but each one is a perfect God in their own person.
Serapion said: What then do you say now to my question when I ask you; and you tell me the Father is a perfect God, the Son is a perfect God, the Holy Spirit is a perfect God.
Do you say so?
Arnobius said: "Yes, I do."
Serapion said: "And if you do say so, how is it that you don't believe there are three gods?"
Arnobius said: "Even if you forget, not everyone who knows and judges has forgotten.
They know I have one sight with two eyes; one hearing with two ears; one touch with two hands; one step with two feet; and one speech with two lips and one tongue.
And one wisdom from memory, intelligence, and understanding, these three.
One essence of life from all the bodily parts; and one understanding in the five senses.
These understand by seeing through the eyes, hearing through the ears, tasting through the mouth, and smelling through the nose.
So when our discussion has handled all these and concluded about unity, what reason brings us back again to things that are finished both by mutual agreement and by the judgment given between sides?
When I said, just as memory, intelligence, and understanding hold one function of wisdom, so the Father with the Son and the Holy Spirit remain one in their omnipotent kingdom."
Serapion said: "I did not ask about the perfection of each deity, nor did you speak of it.
I say now: the Father is a perfect God, the Son is a perfect God, the Holy Spirit is a perfect God, three make gods.
For either one God has a third part, so that by four ounces only three have one deity; or there are three gods, if each is perfect in his deity."
Arnobius said: "You meet my brevity with a lengthy argument; but as much as you want to go on, I will conclude briefly.
Place three of the most precious and incomparable pearls, all of the same value, in a dark place or in a blind night.
Yet when the light of day and the splendor of the sun comes, the greater the brightness of the light, the greater the splendor of these three precious stones will be to the eyes observing."
I ask now: These three incomparable stones, before they were revealed by the light, remained in their preciousness, and their beauty was within them, yet they were not visible to human eyes?
Serapion said: That is so.
Arnobius said: Is the light that revealed all three stones one, or are there two or three lights of the day?
Serapion said: Who denies that one light can reveal them, even if there are a thousand?
Arnobius said: I indeed spoke of three; you concede to a thousand.
If, therefore, a thousand precious stones show the adornment of their splendor with one day's light, how can the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit not reveal the omnipotence of their singular divinity with one light?
A divinity not seen with bodily eyes, but with the eyes of the heart, if the window of Catholic faith is opened, so that the sun of righteousness may enter through it and radiate with its light?
Therefore truly, let the three precious stones show clearly the same merit, majesty, beauty, diadem, and kingdom, not so that you think one is good, another better; so that you do not magnify one to the injury of another by thinking it more magnificent.
For each stone is so true that it lacks nothing by which another could be considered truer.
May faith alone open the windows of souls, which even God Himself has never opened without our belief.
For no one will be saved unless they subject their belief to the true faith, and it opens the windows of understanding, so that you may see these three most beautiful gems constructed in one kingdom, making one diadem and obtaining one majesty of power.
Serapion said: These three stones, although of the same preciousness and beauty, are nevertheless separated.
Arnobius said: You have seen the division of the three, but you do not see one kingdom of one diadem.
Serapion said: I see one diadem, but in that diadem, the gems are constructed by the art of cataclysm.
Arnobius said: Just as the gems are constructed for you by the art of cataclysm.
Thus, these treasures of omnipotence are naturally placed in one, revealed only to those whose faith allows it.
Complete faith opens the door to this eternal treasure, revealing the perfect unity of the Trinity, and the most complete unity of that unity: the true Father who has always been a Father, and the true Son, of whom He has always been the Father.
For it is not as if He can become the Father of His Son if He was not the Father before.
Nothing changes in Him who is the true God.
He is always the same, unchanging, and He has always been God, truly one and triune.
God cannot be believed to begin to be something that He was not before.
From what He is, that is God, and from this is God, which human language permits to say, but not the very nature of majesty: for from what God is, from that is He the Father, and from that is He the Son, from whom He is both God and Father.
For He did not begin to have within Himself something by substance that He did not have before.
Always with power, which is the Son; always with His breath, which is the Holy Spirit.
Serapion said: I remain silent on all things and confess that the entire Trinity has always existed.
But why should I not believe that the Father is greater, since the Father is not born of the Son, but the Son is born of the Father?
Arnobius said: We have already said that the word is born from the voice, and the voice is not greater because the word is born from it.
At one and the same moment, the voice, word, and breath arise together.
The greatness and diminishment cease because no time intervenes between the voice, word, and breath.
For the Father confirms that the word is the Son, as sacred Scripture testifies: "My heart has uttered a good word" (Psalms 45:1).
And what is as good as the Son, from whom all goodness comes?
However, a word spoken from the heart could not be born without the Spirit and breath of the one speaking.
For it is the breath that proceeds when the word is born.
Hence, I have already said a little before: "By the word of the Lord were the heavens made firm," as the prophets declare, "and by the Spirit of His mouth, all their power" (Psalms 33:6).
The appointed judges said: Let it be stated regarding the abundant and invisible majesty of the Trinity, as Arnobius mentioned, which we learned in full through Serapion's repeated intentions.
If there is anything else that Serapion implies, let him reveal it.
Serapion said: It is not inappropriate that I inquire from the impulse of my mind, for you to express in this holy Trinity, who holds the first place?
Arnobius replied: The Father holds the first place.
Serapion said: What do you say about the Son?
Arnobius said: He also holds the first place.
Serapion said: What about the Holy Spirit?
Serapion said: So, there is no Trinity.
Arnobius said: The Trinity is such that we do not say first, second, third: but one, two, three.
Serapion said: The Father is first, and the Son is first, and the Holy Spirit is first: three firsts, three gods.
Arnobius said: Imagine three emperors in one kingdom, in one harmony, on one throne, in one sweetness, in one bond of love, in one power, and ask among them who holds the first place of power.
Without a doubt, all three who are august are all three first: the second and third place of power will be arranged by the august ones.
Serapion said: So, isn't the first among these emperors the one who first began to have dominion among them?
Arnobius said: Among humans, indeed, the first is the one who began to reign alone; and later appointed the others either by birth or by choice: but in the divine rule, you will never find one of these three ruling without the others.
Serapion said: And why did you bring up the example of three emperors, in which we can say first, second, third, to us?
Arnobius said: To show you that human fragility has such grace in the kingdom, that while it is taught for certain to be first, second, third, this order is excluded through the harmony of the empire, holding only the number; the order, however, is not admitted at all.
For all these three possess one kingdom, one empire, one pinnacle of august dignity.
They have this second, who was not first, just as they themselves are first.
Serapion said:
Do you think it is right for this temporal kingdom to be applied to the divine and heavenly majesty?
Arnobius said:
And if this temporal and mortal empire contains such great harmony of peace within itself, so that one who is older in age by birth and in ruling earlier:
this one is lesser, who took up the empire after many years until today; yet from the hour he became exalted, he cannot be lesser than the one who began earlier by birth.
How much more in this divine harmony of the Holy Trinity, in which one never began to hold the power of the heavenly and eternal throne; there is such unity that, counted as three in number, having the empire of one and the same power, they are called one God and one Lord?
For the divine nature does not differ from itself in any way.
And if the order, which earlier age admits among humans, is excluded by the equality of power; how much more the divine omnipotence where in the Trinity none is before, none is entirely after; so the unity, so the undivided majesty, that while they truly hold the number of three, they truly exist as one God, the origin of peace, calm, and tranquility.
The appointed judges said:
Either let Serapion, if he is able, offer something against these things, or let Arnobius briefly summarize his assertion.
And when Serapion used prolonged silence, Arnobius said:
Our God is one: for since He is the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, no Christian dares to say or believe in three gods; because (as I said) the divine nature does not differ from itself in any way.
For the first and second or third order, which the first or second or third beginning among humans creates through intervals of time, in God, who is an equal beginning before time, does not admit to such an extent, that it cannot even be called a beginning, what existed before time.
Since a step cannot be made from every footstep, which cannot be subdivided, it keeps the number of the Trinity, but assigns the order of one equality.
And so, as I said earlier, because there is no second for the first, nor a third for the second, from the first nothing is born.
Remove the distance, and what you believe in the Trinity, you will find first, so that you may rejoice in having not a second or third, but one God.
Serapion said: I admit that all my objections have been reasonably satisfied.
But I still have many chapters of questions left, especially about the mysteries of the Lord's incarnation.
If you do not have more to say, please allow me to ask.
As I confess that I was satisfied by Arnobius, you know, chosen witnesses, that I have not acted with any legal authority.
For I see in both the Old Testament and the New, this God the Father is unbegotten, thus placed before the begotten, so that he takes the second place after the Father.
Arnobius said: Therefore, bring forth the testimonies of the divine Law, by which you will show the Father to be greater than the Son.
Serapion said: Consider the Son of God himself testifying through the words of Solomon: "The Lord created me at the beginning of His ways, in His works, before the ages He created me" (Proverbs 8:12).
But God the Father Himself speaks about the Son through the prophet Isaiah: "Behold, I lay in Zion a stone of stumbling, and a rock of offense; and whoever believes in Him will not be put to shame" (Isaiah 8:14).
Thus David sings of Him: "The stone which the builders rejected" (Psalm 118:22).
Hence also Isaiah said: "Thus says the Lord to my anointed Lord" (Isaiah 45:1).
Therefore, the Father Himself commands the Son, saying: "The Lord said to my Lord, sit at my right hand" (Psalm 110:1).
Thus also Stephen speaks of the Son: "I see Jesus at the right hand of God" (Acts 7:56), of God the Father, who is, as testified by Paul the apostle, the head of Christ, and Christ is the head of man, and man is the head of woman (First Corinthians 11:3).
This is the Father who says to the Son: "Before the morning star, I have begotten you" (Psalm 110:3).
And thus it is said of Christ: "For He will command His angels concerning you" (Psalm 91:11).
So, the one who commands is greater, and the one who is commanded is lesser.
Hence, the Lord himself says to his apostles:
"If you loved me, you would rejoice because I am going to the Father, for the Father is greater than I" (John 14:28).
And again: "The Father who gave me is greater than I" (John 10:10).
The Son of God himself also says to the Father: "This is eternal life, that they may know you, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom you have sent" (John 17:3).
Therefore, the Son is the second person after the Father because he is the Son, not taking away from the Father the fact that there is one God.
If he had been unbegotten, compared to the one who is unbegotten, the shown equality would make both unbegotten, and therefore would show two gods, if the Son could exist without origin like the Father and be invisible and incomprehensible like the Father.
But now, whatever the Son is, he is not from himself, as he is not unbegotten; he is from the Father and owes his origin to his Father, as he was born from him who has no origin.
There is one God of all without beginning, about whom the Son, who has a beginning, says: "The Father is greater than I" (John 14:28).
To prove this, he added: "The Son can do nothing of himself, but only what he sees the Father doing" (John 5:19).
And he again says: "I have not come of myself, but he who sent me" (John 7:28).
And again, he says: "The works that I do testify of me, that the Father sent me" (John 10:2).
He also says: "He who speaks of himself seeks his own glory; but he who seeks the glory of the one who sent him is true" (John 7:18).
That is why he himself says: "Nothing from himself" (John 8:28), but obeys the commands and precepts of the Father in all things, so that his birth proves him to be the Son, yet his obedient submission asserts him to be subject to the Father's will.
Hence, he says: "I have not spoken on my own; but the Father who sent me gave me a command, what I should say, and what I should speak" (John 12:49).
Here is how he obeys the Father and shows himself to be subordinate:
which demonstrates that he, by his subjection, is a servant;
yet he is approved as the Lord of others, so that rightly God the Father is almighty God, and the Son is God of all others, having every creature subject to him;
to the Father, who subjected all things to him, being subject with all creation, as stated in First Corinthians, chapter fifteen, verse twenty-six.
Because of this, he is established as God to all creatures, saying:
"I have been appointed king by him," etcetera, as it is written in Psalm two, verse six.
Arnobius said:
If your intention truly aimed at either learning or teaching, you wouldn't cut out all these testimonies from divine books, as if throwing a bundle tied with the most twisted knots of your interpretation before the eyes of judges and those familiar with the matter.
Therefore, I address you, judges and those familiar with the matter:
I ask you, please, to insist that the order of the ongoing discussion not be changed, and that the chapters of Scripture I mentioned or others I haven't yet mentioned be presented by Serapion in your presence.
He should not be allowed to bring forward one thing after another simultaneously, unless what was first proposed is explained.
The judges said:
What Arnobius justly requests must be granted.
Hence, Serapion will hasten to resolve these testimonies, which he presented in one bundle with his interpretation, so that Arnobius may be able to respond to each testimony individually.
Serapion said:
The first objection of my testimony is from the book of Proverbs of Solomon, where you recognize the voice of the Son of God:
"The Lord created me at the beginning of his ways," as stated in Proverbs, chapter eight, verse twenty-two.
Thus, it is shown that the Father, who created, is greater than the Son, who was created by the Father.
Arnobius said: So do you truly believe that the Son was born from the Father's substance, not so much born as created?
Serapion said: I do not deny the Son of God.
Arnobius said: If you do not deny that the true Son of God was born from the Father's substance, to which side did you bring forth this testimony?
Serapion said: To show that the Son is lesser than the Father.
Arnobius said: You do not attempt to show that the Son is lesser than the Father, but you try to demonstrate that the Son is a creature of God.
Serapion said: Then establish one of two things: either that this testimony does not have full authority of divine power, or show why it was said.
Arnobius said: Now you have returned to the order so that the explanation of each testimony may be granted to us, with God's help.
Serapion said: Whose voice do you want to understand this as, "The Lord created me at the beginning of His ways"?
Arnobius said: It is the voice of the wisdom of God.
Serapion said: What is His wisdom, if not His Son?
Arnobius said: When it is necessary, it will be said in its place how this wisdom is His Son.
For now, the wisdom of God speaks through the wisest man, Solomon, saying: "The Lord created me at the beginning of His ways."
Serapion said: What is more evident than to say, "He created me"?
Arnobius said: What you are trying to demonstrate by saying "He created me," show this.
Serapion said: How did the Son, having obtained the beginning of creation from the Father, earn the right to hold authority over all creation?
Arnobius said: Surely every creature was not before it was created?
Serapion said: Certainly, it was not.
Arnobius said: Then did wisdom begin when it was created?
Serapion replied: Did it begin when it was created?
Arnobius said: So do you blaspheme the one who created it as being unwise?
Serapion said: May God avert this blasphemy from me.
Arnobius said: So you blaspheme unknowingly.
Serapion said: I do not blaspheme, but rather I praise the creator of wisdom.
Arnobius said: You are forced to conclude one of two things: either you say that he who created this wisdom already had wisdom, or he did not have it when he created it.
Serapion said: The Father was never without wisdom.
Arnobius said: Then he did not create wisdom.
Serapion said: Do not be proud, but be afraid, as it is written in the book of Romans, chapter eleven, verse twenty.
Arnobius said: Who is proud, the one who blasphemes God, or the one who defends blasphemy?
Serapion said: Are you defending God?
Arnobius said: When I hear blasphemy, I rebuke the mouth of the blasphemer, just as I rebuke your mouth and teach you not to call God the Father foolish.
For when you said: Before wisdom was created, it did not exist, and you confirm that wisdom itself, which is created, belongs to God, you show that he who created it did not have wisdom and only began to have it after he created it.
The judges said: This is a place of severe blasphemies.
Why do we delay?
Our ears are dulled, and do your mouths go on?
Therefore, it is fitting that Arnobius, who has revealed the blasphemy, already presents the testimony brought forth by Serapion.
Arnobius said: Wisdom has always been stored within the heart of the Father, just like the art of rhetoric in the heart of the orator, and the art of grammar in the heart of the grammarian.
It is said that the orator created a book of the art of rhetoric, and the grammarian composed a book of arts, not because rhetoric and grammar began from the time they were given to people to read.
For those who wrote it, it has always been in their hearts from the time they were taught.
For us, it was created when our learning began.
That is why I said earlier, appropriately, that the Son of God is wisdom before he came to be.
Therefore, God, who made heaven and earth, and all things in them, created wisdom like the orator creates a book of the art of rhetoric, bringing out from his heart what he has always had since he learned it.
However, he created it for us, so that what was in his heart might also be given a beginning in our hearts through our hearing and seeing.
Thus, God, who learned from no one and possesses eternal wisdom, when He desired to create the heavens and the earth and everything within them, first laid down the power of His wisdom, much like a house He intended to build.
The Father first made the air before He solidified the strongest ground; this means He made the heavens first and then finally solidified the earth with its mountains.
But we should speak about the creatures at the right time; now, let's talk about the Creator.
So Wisdom itself says: "The Lord created me as the beginning of His works" from Proverbs chapter eight, verse twenty-two. A master full of wisdom, indeed the source of wisdom itself, brought forth wisdom from Himself. Listen to what wisdom says: "I, wisdom, founded the earth, prepared the heavens with understanding" from Proverbs chapter three, verse nineteen.
Since time does not arise except from days, and days from light, and light from the heavens, and since the heavens were born from wisdom, time did not exist before the heavens, except from wisdom. Before the heavens, time completely did not exist. Therefore, it is clear that wisdom always existed, and it was created in the manner we described, like creating a book for the wisest speaker. For example, Solomon created the Book of Wisdom, but wasn't wisdom already there before he wrote this book?
You might say: It wasn't there before, but it was in Solomon before he received it from God. Afterward, it was always there. So, if in a human, compared to God, albeit a very small one, once wisdom is placed in the heart, it does not leave. Whatever is believed usefully is believed to be wisdom proclaimed, whether in writings or in crafted buildings and paintings it is seen, and in all arts, it is praised. How much more in God, who is entirely wisdom and who received it from no one?
This wisdom, I say, which He always had, He created when He decided to produce it from His heart through the making of the heavens and the earth. So that the heavens and everything in them, which did not exist, came into being, not so that He would begin to be wise, for He always existed. He created the earth and everything in it, which did not exist, not so that He would begin to have wisdom, which He already had.
But you, Serapion, who did not present the full chapter of this passage, listen to the whole chapter so that you may believe it aligns with my explanation.
The Lord created me at the beginning of His ways, in His works.
He established me before time began, before He made the earth, before He set the depths in place, before He brought forth the springs of water, before He set the mountains in place.
He gave birth to me before the hills.
Therefore, God, knowing that what was said, "He created me," could lead to the danger of blasphemy, added: "Before all the hills, He gave birth to me" (Proverbs 8:25).
By this statement, what He said, "me," was interpreted by wisdom itself as "He created me."
Hence, it follows: When He prepared the heavens, I was there with Him; and when He set apart His throne, when He made the clouds firm above the winds, and when He placed the sure springs under the sky; and when He established the strong foundations of the earth, I was there arranging everything with Him, at which He rejoiced in my presence, as He delighted in the completed world (Proverbs 8:27-36).
And he added: Let the judges now tell the objector of this statement, which was made to teach that the Son of God is not the Son, but his creation.
Let him say if, in the order I followed, I went through the entire text of the sentence, and if what wisdom itself said, "The Lord created me," it also added, "he begot me." Either believe that wisdom was always in the Father or show that God was without wisdom before he created it.
Serapion said: I admit and fully follow, as it is written by Solomon, "before all the hills, he begot me," therefore usefully adding to show that what he said, "He created me, he begot me," was clearly evident.
Arnobius said: You certainly recall saying in the previous conflict why I brought forward incorporeal examples.
So why are you now satisfied with teaching the beginning of God's ways through mountains and hills and visible works, unless you see the mystical sense of divine Scripture only in history?
And searching for the beginning of the ways, you did not look for the ways themselves, but let us teach that God is the creator not only by the judgment of letters but also by the instinct of our own natural consideration.
These are the ways of the Lord:
The first is faith, the second is hope, the third is love, the fourth is perseverance, the fifth is goodness, the sixth is fear of the Lord, the seventh is constancy, the eighth is patience, the ninth is gentleness, the tenth is rest, the eleventh is peace, the twelfth is obedience, the thirteenth is long-suffering, the fourteenth is holy solitude, the fifteenth is contempt for the belly, the sixteenth is study of the mind, the seventeenth is chastity, the eighteenth is kindness, the nineteenth is mercy, the twentieth is justice, the twenty-first is generosity, the twenty-second is the study of the knowledge of God's law, the twenty-third is the love of the best things, the twenty-fourth is contempt for temporal glory, the twenty-fifth is the affection for eternal glory.
These are all the ways of God, in which the Father himself walked daily, as he says through the prophet: "As I live, says the Lord, because I will walk in them, and I will be their Father, and they will be my sons and daughters," says the Almighty Lord.
(Leviticus chapter twenty-six, verse twenty-two; Second Corinthians chapter six).
In all these ways of the Lord, wisdom was created first, so that anyone who begins to have the wisdom of God first will not be able to walk in just one of these ways.
Therefore, these are the twenty-four ways, corresponding to the number of twenty-four elders Revelation 4:4, who assign each book, both of the New and Old Testament, to the one book of the twelve apostles.
These three books are offered to the Creator of the Trinity through three groups of people: those of virginity, widowhood, and marriage.
These three books, walking perfectly through their ways, stand firm in one faith, one hope, one love, and are consecrated in one baptism.
They cannot walk completely through their ways unless the Lord creates wisdom in their minds at the very beginning of the ways.
Thus, the Psalmist says: "Make your ways known to me, Lord" Psalm 25:4, because he knew he could not walk these ways unless the Lord created wisdom in his heart. He prays to God, saying: "Create a clean heart in me, God" Psalm 51:12, because wisdom does not enter into a defiled soul, nor can it dwell in a body subject to sins.
The judges said: Arnobius has more than perfectly satisfied the testimony of wisdom, and that it has always been in God and is created in the minds of those who wish to walk the paths of virtues. If there is anything Serapion would like to ask, let us hear it.
Serapion said: If God first cleanses the heart and does not create wisdom, they are not at fault if they do not walk in the ways of God.
Arnobius said: Let the state of our discussion remain sound: for we began to deal with God the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Spirit, and this testimony was assumed to show that the Son of God is a creation. So far, we have shown that wisdom has always been in God, and it is right that our attention should turn to the deity and our Trinity; however, here we also give a brief response. God is not at all a respecter of persons Romans 2:11; Acts 10:34.
He examines the minds, interests, and thoughts of the children of Adam, and knows very well what he should bring forth from his treasure: and as his fairness requires, so shall he give.
Therefore, as the Apostle says: There is no favoritism with God (Ephesians 6:9; Colossians 3:25), he himself says: Are all apostles?
Are all prophets?
(First Corinthians 12:29; Ephesians 4:11).
Just as you are certain that there is no favoritism, be just as certain that he is not unjust in distribution: whatever he has done concerning the human race cannot be found blameworthy for any reason.
Indeed, David wept and pleaded for a pure heart to be created in him (Psalm 51:12).
Imitate David in repenting and in receiving a share in a pure heart, and you will rejoice in the wisdom of God the Creator in you.
Now, let us return to the testimonies you mentioned.
Serapion said: I recalled the stone which the builders rejected, because it has become the cornerstone (Psalm 118:22; Matthew 21:42); this was done by the Lord, and it is marvelous in our eyes.
Arnobius said: Three things must be sought in this place: who are the builders, what are they building, and who are rejecting the stone.
For the Jews, building upon the foundation of the prophets, not only rejected our Lord Jesus Christ from this building, but also crucified him.
He was rejected by unbelievers (Acts 4:11), but made by God into the cornerstone, to create two in himself (Ephesians 2:15); and the perfect structure, begun by Moses and completed in Christ from the law and the prophets, whose new covenant walls, having their own side walls, were dedicated by this cornerstone into one Church by him who said to Peter: Upon this rock, I will build my Church, and the gates of hell shall not overcome it (Matthew 16:18).
Matthew sixteen eighteen. Serapion said: Tell us, what are the gates of hell?
Arnobius said: There is still an explanation about the rock that must be given.
When that is finished, we will answer about the gates of hell.
Serapion said: The completeness of the sentence requires you to briefly speak about the gates of hell.
Arnobius said: We call those the gates of hell which the rulers of this world have placed as the entrance to eternal death with riches, passions, impieties, and crimes.
Through these gates, idol worshippers enter the temples of demons, fearing the most worthless idols instead of the true God.
They also have other gates through which they enter the synagogues' council, denying Christ the Lord God.
They have other gates through which they enter into the teachings of heretics and schismatic sects.
They have other gates through which adulterers, fornicators, kidnappers, thieves, blasphemers, and all sorts of criminals enter.
To these rulers, at the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Holy Spirit cried out: Lift up your gates, etcetera.
Psalm twenty-four seven, nine.
For they are truly not temporal, in which immortality reigns so that the gates of hell cannot prevail against it; for through them the King of glory entered with all his own.
If you ask who this King of glory is, you will hear the Holy Spirit himself saying: The Lord strong and mighty, the Lord mighty in battle.
There are the gates of justice placed in the ears of people, to which the voice of the Catholic faith calls out, saying: Open to me the gates of righteousness, and having entered them, I will praise the Lord.
Psalm one hundred eighteen nineteen.
However, once the word enters through the ears into the city of the soul, it shows it the gate of eternal life; and it says, This is the Lord's gate, the righteous shall enter through it.
It is shown by our Lord Jesus Christ to have a narrow entrance in this world, but it is affirmed that whoever walks through his very narrow and tight path will reach the wide entrance of eternal life.
It is indeed affirmed by the Lord's own mouth, encouraging and saying: Enter through the narrow gate.
The gate that leads to life is narrow, and only a few find it.
The road that leads to death is wide and spacious, and many enter through it.
(Matthew 7:13)
The judges said:
Arnobius, having been asked about the gates of hell, reveals to us both the realms of the underworld and of heaven.
If anything else is prepared by Serapion, let it be brought forth.
Serapion said:
I will lead you to the promised explanation.
Let us return to the place from which we strayed.
Arnobius said:
Examples of the Lord's incarnation are revealed, sometimes as a stone, sometimes as a mountain, sometimes as a rod, sometimes as an angel, sometimes as a man, sometimes as a priest, and also through testimony.
But there are many other images, which the Catholic understanding, walking along clear paths and shining with the splendor of the Holy Spirit, finds more through prayer than through analysis.
For the rock, by which God's people in the desert were delivered from the danger of thirst, the blessed apostle Paul declared to be Christ, saying:
Our ancestors drank the same spiritual drink; they drank from the spiritual rock that accompanied them, and the rock was Christ.
(First Corinthians 10:4)
And in the Song of Moses, it is said:
Honey flowed for them from the rock, and oil from the solid rock.
(Deuteronomy 32:13)
And in the eightieth Psalm:
He satisfied them with honey from the rock.
(Psalm 81:16)
Also in the seventy-eighth Psalm:
He brought forth water from the rock and made waters flow like rivers.
(Psalm 78:16)
Also in the twenty-sixth Psalm, the Church says of Christ:
You lifted me up on a rock.
(Psalm 27:5)
And in the thirty-ninth, he says:
He set my feet on a rock.
(Psalm 40:2)
And in the sixtieth:
You lifted me up on a rock.
(Psalm 61:2)
And in the one hundred thirteenth:
He turned the solid rock into pools of water, and the rock into fountains of water.
(Psalm 114:8)
And in the one hundred fourth:
He struck the rock, and waters flowed out.
(Psalm 105:41)
And in the Song of Solomon, the Holy Spirit, inviting the Church to Himself, says:
Come to me, my love, my bride, my beautiful one, and in the shelter of the rock, continued as a wall.
(Song of Solomon 2:14)
And in Isaiah, the voice of the Son of God says: "I have set my face like the strongest stone" (Isaiah 50:7).
Also in the prophet Ezekiel, the Lord says: "I have made your face harder than flint and rock" (Ezekiel 3:9).
And in the Gospel, the Lord speaks of the wise man who builds his house on the rock (Matthew 7:24).
But what rock is this, if not the one the Apostle refers to when he says: "No one can lay any foundation other than the one already laid, which is Jesus Christ" (1 Corinthians 3:11)?
There are many other passages as well--too many to list--that teach us the rock stands for the unchanging and absolutely steadfast will of our Lord Jesus Christ.
He showed this will in his flesh: being tempted by the devil, betrayed by a disciple, nailed to the cross, given gall to eat, vinegar to drink, pierced with a spear, and humiliated even to death--the death of the cross (Philippians 2:8).
Even though he endured all these things as a perfect man, he never responded with the impatience or weakness typical of human nature.
Through this, he showed that God, through a man, won victory for humankind--just as the Apostle says in 1 Corinthians: "Thanks be to God, who gives us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ" (1 Corinthians 15:57).
Serapion said: "Your explanation troubles me, because in how you interpret the incarnation of our Lord, you seem to be talking about a man and not about God."
"Since you have explained one of the eight symbolic images referring to the Lord--this one about the rock--so clearly with evidence from divine Scripture, I ask that you complete the remaining seven examples. Once you've done that, I will need only one explanation to understand the Lord's incarnation fully. Because this, I believe, is the whole reason for this debate."
"That's why I don't think you remembered that, at the beginning, I said I would deal with you as if you were one of the Arians, or Eunomians, or Sabellians, or Macedonians--and that I would entertain their claims while staying true to my faith."
"So, as I said, I entered this conflict with you to see whether I would find you caught in some error. If I did, then I would deal with you over that specific issue, the one where you and I disagree."
Nothing remains for me now except for you to explain those eight comparisons you mentioned in Christ, so neatly and blamelessly, that you explain the complete divinity in Christ, revealing so that you do not bring me anything less by not showing the full divine nature.
Show now why you only mentioned eight, when there are many other representations in Christ that could have been mentioned, as you said yourself.
Arnobius said: I considered that many kinds of sacraments are contained in this number.
Firstly, how in the Old Testament, when it was the first day, on which it said, "Let there be light" (Genesis 1:3); also in the New, it was worth being made first and eighth by the resurrection of Christ.
For just as on that day the heavens were opened so that manna was poured out (Exodus 16:14 and 16), David was also the eighth son who became a slayer by defending sheep from wild beasts (First Samuel 16:11), and by defending the people, he became the slayer of the giant (First Samuel 17:49 and 50).
Firstly, when he was still a child, he was made Christ by Almighty God.
And also in the Gospel, eight beatitudes are mentioned by the mouth of our Lord Jesus Christ (Matthew 5), even though there were many other virtues that could have deserved the merit of beatitude.
Therefore, by this example, it seemed to me that while preserving the multitude of comparisons, I should bring forth only these eight allegories, certain that from these that have been brought forth, the others which have not been brought forth can be inquired into, understood when found, and usefully explained by reason of speech.
Serapion said: First through the occasion of my objections, you explained the stone; and when I followed the evangelical chapters, in which the Lord says, "The Father is greater than I" (John 14:28), you brought forth other matters.
So that you don't seem to have brought these examples just to avoid those testimonies, after presenting what you have brought forward, you will give me an answer about them.
Then we will finally approach our specific conflict.
Arnobius said: We should have focused on this one point, on which you truly disagree, that is, on the fact that you do not wish to beneficially believe in the Catholic faith.
That in Christ our God, there are two true and perfect natures, and to confess the true Son of God as well as the true human Son of man.
But how do you foresee being rightfully and lawfully overcome, so that you do not feel defeated alone?
Having taken on the roles of many heretics within yourself, so that when your fellow citizens reproach you for being defeated, you may say you were overcome not by us, but by the victory of Christ, who was able to open through the amazing and most powerful gateway of the Catholic faith the sharpness of many heretics within you.
Serapion said: The wise one conquers deceit when he drives it out from within himself; and he who conquers is twice victorious, because he receives a crown for his faith assertion and gains the reward of the people.
Arnobius said: This all must be attributed to the mercy of God: we can achieve nothing by our own efforts, but we find all through the grace and mercy of God.
I will now address the remaining seven forms of analogy I proposed; then I will explain the two questions you raised from the Gospels, with the Lord's help.
As for you, recalling those same figures with a keen memory, begin to bring them up one by one, so that I can teach from the sacred volumes that I have provided these examples.
Serapion said: First, it is clear that you have explained about the rock; secondly, you promised to show from the Scriptures that the aforementioned mountain is the Lord, so show it.
Arnobius said: In Exodus we read: The Lord said to Moses: This will be a sign for you, that I am sending you to bring my people out of Egypt, and you will serve me on this mountain (Exodus 3:12).
Serapion said: This is about Mount Sinai.
Arnobius said: If you only seek history, enter the Synagogue; but we accept history so that we can explain what is within the history spiritually.
We follow the Apostle Paul, the teacher of the Gentiles, appointed by the Lord, who stirred our minds and hearts to the point that he clearly declared the rock, which truly is a rock from which water was produced, to be Christ.
He said: But the rock was Christ.
First Corinthians 10:4.
The mountain where the glory of God appeared, where there was a fire that gave light but did not burn, where God spoke with man face to face,
Exodus 33:11,
where the Majesty itself wrote the will of its law on two stone tablets with its finger in the Ten Commandments;
where the book of Deuteronomy, that is, the second or repeated law, was written;
the mountain where God made known to man that in the beginning God made heaven and earth,
Genesis 1:1,
and all that is in them, and many other signs of holiness, which would take too long to say;
about which the Psalmist says: The mountain of God, a rich mountain, a mountain in which God is pleased to dwell.
Indeed, the Lord will dwell there forever.
Psalm 68:16-17.
To show what he was talking about in the fifteenth psalm, he said: Who shall rest in your holy mountain?
and added: He who enters without blemish, etc.
Psalm 15:1-2.
And who else is without blemish, except the Lord Jesus Christ alone, who did no sin, nor was deceit found in his mouth.
First Peter 2:22.
For in the twenty-third psalm: Who, he said, shall ascend into the mountain of the Lord?
And replied: The one with clean hands, etc.
Psalm 24:3-4.
And again David sings: Great is the Lord and greatly to be praised, etc.
; and adds: Mount Zion, the sides of the north, etc.
Psalm 48:1-2.
Hence Isaiah also says: In the last days, the mountain of the Lord will be made manifest, and all nations will come to it.
Isaiah 2:2.
David also says in another place: Those who trust in the Lord are like Mount Zion, etc.
Psalm 125:1.
And so, in another psalm it says: "Mount Zion, where you dwell" (Psalm 68:17).
And about that mountain, it also says: "This is the one his right hand has acquired" (Psalm 78:54).
His right hand has acquired a man, one who is perfect, by the power of the Lord's right hand (Psalm 118:16).
The "right hand" of the Father refers to his action and is shown by what he does.
It was the invisible Son himself who, by his omnipotence, accomplished this great work. By taking on human nature, he made himself visible so that he could say: "Whoever has seen me has seen the Father, because I am in the Father and the Father is in me" (John 14:9-10).
Serapion said: "Then the Jews who saw him also saw the Father?"
Arnobius replied: "The Jews saw him, yes, but not in that way. That is why the Holy Spirit says to Isaiah: 'Go and tell this people: You will look, but not truly see; you will hear, but not understand' (Isaiah 6:9; Acts 28:26).
And that is why the Lord says to them: 'You do not know me or my Father' (John 8:19).
But to his disciples he said: 'Blessed are the eyes that see what you see and the ears that hear what you hear' (Matthew 13:16).
"
So then, if the answer seems to be coming from the mountain imagery, remember that this is the third example I gave.
Serapion said: "First you mentioned the stone, second the mountain, and third the tower, using them as symbols."
Arnobius said: "You have remembered well. Just make sure you also accept the truth behind them. He is the one spoken of in Psalm 61: 'You have been my strong tower against the enemy' (Psalm 61:3).
This is the same tower the Holy Spirit speaks of through Isaiah: 'I built a tower in the middle of the vineyard I planted' (Isaiah 5:2).
The Holy Spirit himself explains this vineyard, saying: 'The vineyard of the Lord of Hosts is the house of Israel' (Isaiah 5:7).
And the tower that he says he built in the middle of it, according to Holy Scripture, is the Son of Man, whom he established for himself.
Solomon speaks of him too, saying: 'Wisdom has built herself a house' (Proverbs 9:1).
He, who is the wisdom of the Father, built for himself, in the womb of the Virgin, a perfect man: Jesus, who was predestined to be the Son of God in power, according to the Spirit of holiness (Romans 1:4).
I, 4), not according to the pollution of marriage.
Serapion said: Don't call it the pollution of marriage, because marriage has no pollution, but fornication should be called pollution.
Arnobius said: Marriage has pollution, but no crime; whereas fornication is proven to have both pollution and crime.
But let me prove the indication of the tower.
The Lord Himself says in the Gospel:
A landowner planted a vineyard, put a fence around it, built a tower in it, and rented it to farmers (Matthew 21:33), who did not hesitate to beat the servants sent to them by the landowner; finally, they killed the son sent by the landowner himself.
With this said, they are asked by the Lord, When the owner of the vineyard comes, what will he do to those farmers?
And the Jews answered, He will bring those evil men to a wretched end and lease the vineyard to other farmers.
And the Lord said to them, Truly I say to you, the kingdom of God will be taken away from you and given to a people producing its fruit.
18.
Serapion said: Now, in the fourth place, the speech showing the Lord prefigured by the rod is to be sought, so that your promise may be explained in its order.
Arnobius said: In Exodus, the Lord speaks to Moses: I will stand on the top of the hill, and with this rod, which is in your hand, I will perform all the signs of power.
David also says in the spirit: The rod of equity, the rod of your kingdom.
Your rod and your staff, etc.
(Exodus 4:17).
And David appeals to the Lord, saying: Remember your congregation, etc.
You have redeemed the rod of your inheritance (Psalm 74:2).
He also says: The rod of your power, etc.
(Psalm 45:6-7).
More clearly, it is said about the Lord: A rod will come forth from the root of Jesse, etc.
(Isaiah 11:1).
All of these were fulfilled in Him who was made from the seed of David according to the flesh (Romans 1:3).
Serapion said: Keep the discussion of the flesh, about which there will be a true and open conflict for us: now strive to explain the examples you have proposed.
For you have already mentioned why you set the rod in the fourth place, now, in the fifth place, explain why you mentioned the Angel.
Arnobius said:
Listen to the Lord speaking to Moses:
"Look, I am sending my angel ahead of you, to protect you on your entire journey: heed him and obey him, for my name is in him" (Exodus twenty-three, twenty).
Malachi, however, says:
"The lips of the priest will preserve knowledge, for he is the angel of the Lord" (Malachi two, seven).
Therefore, regarding all the saints who are tested and suffer in this world for the sake of the holy name, it is said:
"This poor man called, and the Lord heard him," meaning the holy people, "and delivered him from all his troubles" (Psalm thirty-four, six to seven).
The Lord sent an angel to encamp around those who fear Him, meaning those who fear the Lord, and He will deliver them, that same righteous people.
Daniel also recalls an angel descending from heaven into the midst of the flames to rescue three youths from the fire, when Nebuchadnezzar had said about him, "The fourth one I see is like the Son of God" (Daniel three, forty-nine); his testimony is not a lie.
David also, in his own psalm, says this about God:
"He sent his angel and took me from my father's sheep, and anointed me with his mercy" (Psalm seventy-eight, seventy).
Serapion said:
Move quickly to the sixth, in the likeness of a man, the Son of God seen before: for what was said about the fifth is sufficient.
Arnobius said:
We read in the book of Joshua that at that time, when Jericho was in a continuous battle, he saw a man standing before him with a sword in his hand.
When he approached him, he said to him:
"Are you one of us, or one of our adversaries?"
The man replied:
"I am the commander of the army of the Lord" (Joshua five, thirteen to fourteen).
Likewise, the prophet Isaiah says:
"The people will cry out to their God in their distress, and the Lord will send them a man who will deliver them" (Isaiah nineteen, twenty).
Daniel also says:
"I saw in the clouds of heaven the Son of Man coming to the Ancient of Days, and he was given authority over the kingdom" (Daniel seven, thirteen).
Daniel himself says:
"A vision like a man stood before me, and he called the archangel Gabriel, and told him to explain the vision I was seeing" (Daniel eight, sixteen).
Similarly, Daniel himself says: "I lifted my eyes and saw, and there was a man dressed in linen, and his waist was wrapped with gold" (Daniel 10:5).
Likewise, Ezekiel says: "I saw a form like a man above the throne" (Ezekiel 1:26).
Also, he says: "I saw someone calling to a man dressed in linen, who was girded with a golden belt around his waist, ascending above the cherubim" (Ezekiel 10:2).
Serapion said: "From abundant testimonies, things that are in doubt should be clarified: but now, seeking brevity, proceed to the seventh similarity of the priesthood you mentioned."
Arnobius said: "In the First Book of Kings, God speaks to Samuel, saying: 'I will raise up a faithful priest for myself, who will act according to my heart in everything'" (First Samuel 2:35).
And David says: "The Lord swore an oath to David and will not regret it, etc." (Psalm 110:4).
Serapion said: "These two testimonies you provided about the seventh similarity are clear: now explain the eighth, that the covenant of God can be understood as the Son of God."
Arnobius said: "The Book of Genesis says that the Lord spoke to Noah and his sons: 'Behold, I establish my covenant with you and your descendants after you, and with every living creature that is with you'" (Genesis 9:10).
Later, after other things, God says to Noah and his sons: "I will remember my covenant between me and you and every living creature" (Genesis 9:15).
Also, the voice of God says to Noah and his sons: "I will place my rainbow in the clouds of the sky, and I will remember my covenant between me and you" (Genesis 9:16).
Also, through Isaiah, the Lord says: "My covenant will be with life and peace, law and truth will be in his mouth, and wickedness will not be found on his lips. Dwelling in peace, he will guide you and turn many away from their iniquity" (Malachi 2:5).
Also, through Isaiah, the Lord says: "I, the Lord, have called you and made you a covenant to the nations, to open the eyes of the blind" (Isaiah 42:7).
Also, through Isaiah, the Lord says: "Listen to me, and you will eat what is good, walk in his ways, and your soul will be saved, and I will make an everlasting covenant with you" (Isaiah 55:3).
Here is what the Lord says through Isaiah: I will make an everlasting covenant with you in peace and faith.
All these things foreshadow the one Son of God.
There are also many other types of figures, which, if necessary to bring forth, I will present with the authority of the Holy Scriptures.
The judges said: With both rational manifestation and legal authority, the defenses presented by Arnobius have been affirmed.
So much so that even Serapion, who is on the opposing side, admitted with his own words, without us having to speak, that everything is as Arnobius defended.
And just as the evening finds the argument begun at dawn, after the silence of the night's rest is over, and God has graciously restored the day to us, the confession of both sides will arise.
Serapion said: I ask that our discussion today ends here, so Arnobius can explain why he wanted to bring forth these foreshadowings of our Lord.
Arnobius said: How is it that among these foreshadowings, even the one for whom they were made, the Son of God, is considered to be accounted for, when the image of truth is in this man, whom the Virgin bore, and is truth itself?
And just as the true Son of God is God, so the true son of man is a man, not mixed in such a way that the nature of each is changed, but remaining in the truth of divinity and in his omnipotence.
The invisible Son of God having his union with man is believed to have presented the true God, the Son of God, for our liberation.
For otherwise, God could not be seen with fleshly eyes.
Whoever denies that God is in Christ, that is, in the man, is the Antichrist, as written in First John, Chapter Two, verses twenty-two and forty-three.
However, anyone who denies something from these likenesses may be found either blameworthy or perhaps not blameworthy.
For they deny the rock, they deny the rod, they deny the mountain, and whatever else can be said to be applicable to Christ.
Whoever denies the perfect man and perfect God cannot be freed from eternal damnation.
Similarly, anyone who dares to think or believe in two sons of God-one born from the Father before time without a mother, and another born of the Holy Spirit from the Virgin Mary-will be struck with eternal condemnation.
However, our confession of faith, from the apostolic seat of Saint Peter, which began with the Apostle himself, is this: Believing in one Son of God from two perfect and complete substances-from the visible and invisible, from the physical and non-physical, from the comprehensible and incomprehensible, from the passible and impassible, from mortal and immortal-we profess the true God and true man.
Declaring and believing that God is in Christ, and Christ Jesus in the glory of the Father, has one divinity.
Just as there is one sight in two eyes, one hearing in two ears, one sense of smell in two nostrils: thus, in these two substances of God and man, there is one Son of God.
Certainly, as I know my attentive listener is careful to remember me referring to the one substance of the Father and the Son, one sight in two eyes, one hearing in two ears, and one sense of smell in two nostrils.
Now to you, it should not seem inappropriate to believe in one person in two substances, not one substance.
Indeed, I have tried to show this, so that just as we believe there is one substance in three persons, so in the two substances of God and man, we believe there is one person of the Son of God.