Little Book on the Praise of the Hermitage
Saint Eucherius, Bishop of Lyons to Hilary Presbyter of Lerins
To the holy lord, most blessed by merits, and most glorious in Christ, HILARY, from EUCHERIUS.
You left your home and family a long time ago with great courage and ventured into the deep, secluded places of the desert that stretch to the great sea; but you returned to the desert with even greater strength than when you first sought it.
When you first entered it as a guest, you had a guide and leader on your journey, whom you later followed as a master of the heavenly army; and leaving your parents, you nonetheless followed a parent.
Now, when you thought it right to pursue the same guide to the pinnacle of the bishopric, love brought you back to the familiar seclusion of the desert.
Therefore, you are now nobler and greater by example.
For earlier, when you sought the desert, you seemed to be accompanied by a brother; now, when you return to the desert, you have even left a father.
And what kind of father, and how much?
One whom you have always respected with a devotion of love; one bound to you by a unique affection, so that you could prefer nothing to his love, except perhaps the love of the desert: which, when you rightly place it above his love, you show that you love not him less, but the desert more.
You also showed how great the love of seclusion was in you, to which even the greatest love would yield.
Indeed, what is this love of the desert in you if not the love of God?
You have thus kept the order of love as prescribed by the law, loving first your God, then your neighbor.
However, I believe (as I infer in my mind) that he did not oppose your journey and purpose solely out of contemplation of your success, but in an unusual manner among those closely bound to each other, he wished to let you go as much as you wished to leave.
For he also loves you greatly in return, but in his love for you, he took care of your well-being; and although his love for you is abundant and supreme, it ultimately aims at your benefit.
3.
Even though you have long since poured out all your wealth on Christ’s poor, making you rich in Christ, and even though you may be young in years but mature in character, and distinguished in talent and eloquence, I admire and love nothing more in you than your desire for the solitude of the hermitage.
Because you often ask me to respond more fully to your extensive and eloquent letters, you must bear with my foolishness for a while, since you are wise, as I recall the manifold grace of the Lord toward this very hermitage beloved by you.
I would rightly call the hermitage the boundless temple of our God.
Indeed, it is believed that He who surely dwells in silence rejoices in secrecy.
He has often revealed Himself there to His saints and, because of the place, has not disdained human companionship.
In the wilderness, Moses saw God with a glorified face Exodus 3; in the wilderness, Elijah, fearing to see God, covered his face First Kings 19:13.
And although He revisits everything as His own and is never absent anywhere, He particularly favors the visitation of the hermitage and the secret of heaven.
They say that when someone asked another where he believed God to be, he answered that he should eagerly follow wherever he was led.
Then, accompanying him, he came to the hidden parts of the vast hermitage.
Showing the secluded place of the vast wilderness, he said, "Here is where God is." And rightly so, for it is more readily believed that He is there, where He is more easily found.
In the beginning of things, when God made everything in wisdom and distinguished each thing suitable for future uses, He did not leave this part of the earth useless and without honor. Creating everything not more for present magnificence than for future foresight, He prepared the wilderness for the saints to come, as I believe.
I believe that the land was made rich in fruits by Him, and instead of relying on a more indulgent nature, it was made fertile by the saints, so that the boundaries of the desert would flourish.
When He watered the mountains from above, the valleys also overflowed with abundant crops, and the barren places were compensated when He enriched them with inhabitants.
The possessor of paradise and transgressor of the commandment, while living in a place of delight, could not keep the law given to him by God.
The more pleasing that place was in its delights, the more prone he was to fall.
Hence, not only did He subject him to His laws, but even death extended its sting to us.
Therefore, let him cultivate the wilderness who desires life, because the inhabitant of the pleasant place brought about death.
But now, let us consider more recent examples of the wilderness always being accepted by God.
When Moses led the flock into the interior of the desert, he saw God shining from afar in a harmless fire, and not only did he see, but he also heard Him speaking.
Indeed, at that time, the Lord, when He advised him to remove the sandals from his feet, declared the ground of the desert holy, saying: "The place where you stand is holy ground" (Exodus, chapter 3, verse 5).
This clearly expressed the merit of hidden honor by judgment.
For the holiness of the place was confirmed by God with the holiness of His testimony; in which (as I believe) He also secretly declared that by approaching the desert, one should free oneself from the previous obligations of life's worries, and, freed from prior bonds, walk without polluting the place.
There, for the first time, Moses became the familiar interpreter of divine conversation; he received the words and in turn reported them; he asked about things to be said or done and was taught, and he conversed with the Lord of heaven in mutual and customary dialogue.
There he took up again the rod powerful in the works of signs, and having entered the desert as a shepherd of sheep, he returned from the desert as a shepherd of people.
What about the people of God then, about to be freed from Egypt and released from earthly works—did they not seek out the wilderness and flee to the solitudes?
(Exodus, chapter 14).
Indeed, they approached God in the desert, from whom they had been freed from slavery.
So they headed towards the desert, a vast, terrifying wilderness, led by Moses.
How great is the abundance of your sweetness, Lord!
When Moses entered the desert, he had seen God.
Behold, he returns again to see Him.
The Lord Himself, clearly the leader of the journey, was guiding His people to the desert, leading them with a column that was sometimes glowing with fire, sometimes shining with a cloud.
He gave a sign from heaven to those who deserved it, a sign that shone with alternating lights and stretched out like a Milky Way.
With focused eyes, Israel followed the ray, glowing from a distance with flashing fire.
For those heading into the secrets of the desert, the Lord, who showed the way, also carried a light ahead.
For these people, who repeatedly headed towards the desert, weren't the barriers of the impassable sea opened up?
(Exodus 14:22) As they made their way through the churning depths, their dusty footprints walked along the Red Sea shores.
Looking up from the deep valley at the towering mountains of water, the guardian of the people led them across the sea's shallows.
Nor did the power of this divine work stop there: for when the sea, which had receded, came back, it covered their path and destroyed their enemies, placing the sea in its place.
I believe this was so that Israel would not return from the desert.
He opened a path through the waters and then covered it with the surrounding waters, so the way into the desert was clear for those who sought it, while the return was closed (Exodus 14:27).
Thus, endowed with this grace, that people, as they headed towards solitude, nonetheless earned more when they possessed it.
For there, the Lord unexpectedly refreshed them with a miracle, providing flowing water from a struck rock to the thirsty, and drawing streams from native springs out of the repellent rocks.
His hidden hand revealed the sudden nature from the hidden veins (Exodus 17:6).
Not only did He pour into the dry rock's insides with the introduced stream there, but He also sweetened the bitter drinks of sad waters with added sweetness (Exodus 15:25).
He drew out one and calmed the other: and with no greater miracle, He returned waters from the rocks than He did other waters from the waters.
The entire crowd was astonished, feeling the help of heavenly aid there, both in the waters that existed and in those that did not yet exist.
In that place, the same people gathered food sent down from heaven on the white ground, when the Lord rained bread from the clouds in a dry shower.
In the tents and around the camps, manna fell from the air like snow, where humans ate the bread of angels.
And because each day has enough trouble of its own, God provided daily food through divine generosity, with the law already given not to worry about the next day.
In the past, when earthly means couldn't provide food in the desert, heaven did.
The same Hebrew people received the law and heavenly commands while living in the wilderness, when they were allowed to see the signs engraved by God's finger on the tablets (Exod. XX).
Brought out from the camps to meet the Lord, they stood at the base of the mountain.
Trembling with fear, they saw the peak of Sinai, where the majestic presence of God rested in great terror.
They saw the mountain burning with fire from afar, covered entirely by a thick cloud.
They were terrified by the lightning flashing from the fire, the thunder resounding with frequent bursts mixed with the sound of trumpets, so the children of Israel, while dwelling in the wilderness, were worthy to see the presence of God and hear His voice.
Such miracles sustained and supported that nation long ago when they lived in the desert, fed by unusual food, sudden drink, and clothing that never wore out.
Even the things surrounding their bodies remained in perfect condition.
Whatever the natural environment couldn't provide, God's manifest greatness supplied.
Only one of the holy ones from this people reached these gifts of heavenly grace, saying about them: "He did not do this for any other nation" (Ps. CXLVII, 20).
God gave them special and unheard-of gifts, replenishing the people with divine offerings in the wilderness.
And although these things are handed down as examples for us, and the appearance of events thrives in hidden mysteries, all who were baptized into Moses, in the cloud and in the sea, ate spiritual food and drank spiritual drink, as stated in First Corinthians 10:2.
Yet, all these things contain the faith of future events, preserving the truth of what was done.
However, the praise of the desert is not diminished, even if those events that occurred there are to be referred to the depth of the sacraments.
Nothing is taken away from grace, even if the state of the body at that time, and the incorruption of garments, presented a glimpse of the life to come.
For the grace of the place is great, if the desert now holds those who will be held by the happiness of the most blessed age.
Consider the fact that the children of Israel did not reach that desirable land without first living in the desert.
The same people, destined to possess that land flowing with milk and honey, first inhabited this dry and uncultivated land.
The whole journey to the true homeland always passes through the dwellings of the desert.
Let him inhabit the uninhabitable land who wants to see the good of the Lord in the land of the living; let him be a guest of this land who strives to be a citizen of that one.
But to move on, David himself escaped the plots of a hostile king only when he sought refuge in the desert, as described in First Samuel 23.
Staying in the dryness of Edom, he thirsted for the Lord with all his heart, so that, thirsting in the desert and in the pathless and waterless place, he might then appear before God in the holy place and see God's power and glory.
Elijah, indeed, the greatest inhabitant of secrets, closed the heavens with rain, opened them with fire, received food from a ministering bird, revoked the fixed laws of death, crossed the Jordan with the river divided, and ascended to heaven in a fiery chariot, as described in First Kings 17 and 18, and Second Kings 2.
And what of Elisha, the follower of this life and virtue?
Didn't he shine brightly through divine miracles?
At times, a split torrent, floating iron, revived people, or an increase in oil marked his work.
And finally, after many other miracles, he showed that he had received a double portion of his master's power by this: while the master, still alive, had raised a dead man, he raised a dead person even after he himself had died (2 Kings 2:14, 6:6).
The sons of the prophets, leaving the cities, sought out the Jordan River with its twin sources and built tents in hidden places near the distant torrent.
The holy group kept watch on the banks of the secluded river, scattered among the tents, and with fitting dwellings, the remarkable group preserved the spirit of their fathers (2 Kings 6).
What about the one who was the greatest among those born of women?
(Matt. 11:11) Didn't he live and preach in the wilderness?
Baptism was handed down by him in the desert, repentance was preached there, and the first mention of the kingdom of heaven was made there.
He was the first to bring these teachings to listeners, where anyone eager to accept them quickly found favor.
It’s fitting that he, destined to be a great inhabitant of the desert, was sent ahead as an angel before the Lord to prepare the way to the heavenly kingdom.
He was both a forerunner and a worthy witness to hear the Father speak from heaven and to touch the Son by baptizing him, witnessing the Holy Spirit descend.
Our Lord and Savior himself was baptized and immediately (as Scripture says) led by the Spirit into the desert.
So who is this Spirit?
There is no doubt—it is the Holy Spirit.
The Holy Spirit led him into the desert, suggesting this and quietly inspiring it, making the desert a fitting place for the Holy Spirit's prompting.
Immersed in the mystical river, he thought of nothing else as more important than heading into the wilderness.
Even though he always sanctified the waters, he was not cleansed of sin because he had not committed sin nor feared it.
Yet he burned with love for the desert and, as the source of all saving examples, desired what was not worthy of us.
If these things are offered to God as a vow by someone free from errors, how much more necessary are they for a person prone to errors?
If they are requested by someone who does not sin, how much more should they be desired by someone who does sin?
There, in the service of the Lord, with the noisy crowds removed, the quiet services of divine strength begin.
And being placed in the desert, as if already taken back to heaven, he is attended by the duties of angels.
As it is written in Matthew chapter 4, verse 11, "Then the devil left him, and angels came and attended him."
There, he refuted the enemy of ancient times who was tempting him with deceitful tricks of his known craft, and the new Adam repelled the deceiver of the old Adam.
Oh, great praise of the desert, that the devil who had conquered in paradise was defeated in the desert!
That place was also a desert where our Savior fed, satisfied, and filled five thousand men with only five loaves of bread and two fish.
As it is written in Mark chapter 8, verses 1 to 9, "During those days another large crowd gathered."
Jesus always feeds his people in the desert with bread.
He had once preferred to give his people the divine gift of manna; now they gathered the fragments.
And with the same miracle, the food fell for the hungry then, just as it now increased for those eating.
The meals were greater than the food brought to the feast.
In deserts, I say, let us now give the reasons for such great signs, nor would power have shown its might if the place had abundance.
And then the Lord Jesus withdrew to the more secluded parts of a high mountain, with only three chosen ones with him.
His face shone with unusual brightness, who, while plainly bearing the assumed human form, believed the indication of declaring majesty to be entrusted to secrets.
There, the greatest of the apostles said, "It is good for us to be here," as recorded in Matthew chapter 17, verse 4.
Clearly cherishing the greatness of the sign, in the remoteness of the desert.
The same Lord Jesus, as it is written, went to a deserted place and prayed there.
As recorded in Luke chapter 5, verse 16, "But Jesus often withdrew to lonely places and prayed."
Therefore, let that place be called a place of prayer, which God the author showed to be suitable by praying there, and taught that the prayer of one humbling himself would more easily penetrate the clouds, aided by the place, because it was honored by secrecy.
And he himself, praying there when he asked, demonstrated where he wanted us to pray.
Why should I now recall John, Macarius, and many others whose lives in the deserts were like they were in heaven?
They came as close to the Lord as a human can get and were admitted into divine matters as much as is allowed for those still in the flesh.
They focused their minds on heavenly secrets and manifested grace through either silent revelations or clear signs.
With the help of these secrets, they advanced to the point where, while their bodies were on earth, their spirits already possessed heaven.
Therefore, I will rightly call this dwelling in the desert a seat of faith, an ark of virtue, a sanctuary of charity, and a treasury of piety.
Just as in a great house, precious things are kept sealed in remote places, so too is the magnificence of those holy ones hidden in the desert, locked away by nature's difficulties, kept within a secluded room of the wilderness, lest it be lost through human interaction.
And fittingly, from the world's Lord, this precious wealth is stored in that part of the worldly house—not only kept safe but also brought forth when needed from its hidden place.
Once, divine Providence had the greatest care for the desert, and even now it is not small.
For even now, unexpected sustenance comes divinely to the inhabitants of the desert, as if it flows down from heaven.
They have their own manna in this bounty, and the Lord no less spreads nourishment for them from His hidden hand.
And when water flows from the rocks, finally responding to divine command as if struck by Moses' rod, what else does it emerge like?
The clothing of those living in the vastness of the desert does not wear out, for it continually comes anew by divine provision, and so it remains.
The Lord once nourished His people in the desert, and He still does now; He sustained them for forty years, and these ones for as many years as there will be.
With good reason, this holy man, driven by divine love, leaves his home and chooses this place.
He rightfully prioritizes it over his relatives, children, and parents, and acquires it with the support of his people.
For those leaving their homeland, this place is aptly named a temporary homeland, from which no fear, longing, joy, or sorrow can call them back.
Clearly, this place alone is worth all the emotions of everyone.
Who can adequately list the benefits of the desert and the advantages for those living there?
Though in the world, they somehow withdraw from it, wandering in deserts, as the Apostle says, in mountains, caves, and holes in the earth.
Hebrews 11:38.
And the Apostle rightly declares that the world is not worthy of such people, who are strangers to the chaos of human society, set apart, quiet, and silent.
They are as distant from the will to sin as they are from the opportunity.
Famous men of the world, worn out by their affairs, used to retreat into philosophy as if it were their home.
How much more beautifully do they turn to these studies of manifest wisdom, retreating magnificently to the freedom of solitary places and the secrets of the deserts?
There, dedicating themselves solely to philosophy, they train in the pathways of the desert as if in their own gymnasiums.
Where, I ask you, can Easter be celebrated more freely than in the dwelling of the desert?
With virtues and continence—continence, I say, which is like another kind of desert of the heart.
For Moses spent forty continuous days in the desert,
Exodus 24:18, and Elijah did the same for the same number of days,
First Kings 19:8, in fasting.
Both extended their fasting beyond human capacity.
And the Lord also spent time in abstinence in the desert,
Matthew 4:2.
We don't read elsewhere of such periods of fasting, so it must be thought that the Lord also granted some strength to those places.
Where, I ask you, can one more freely be idle and see how sweet the Lord is?
Where is the path to perfection more readily opened to those striving for it?
Where is a greater field of virtues available?
Where is the mind's guard more easily maintained, allowing it to look around?
Where is the heart freer to strive to cling to God than in those secluded places where finding God is not only easy but also where one can truly hold onto Him?
And although the desert often presents nothing but fine dust, nowhere are the foundations of that Gospel house more firmly laid (Matt. 7:24).
Even if someone wants to remain in those sands, they certainly do not build their house on sand: nowhere more than there is that building placed on the rock, which, founded on unshakable stability, will last with unmovable strength, so that in times of raging storms, it will not be undermined by winds or torrents.
Therefore, the inhabitants of the desert build such structures within their hearts: those who seek the highest things from the lowest, who pursue lofty things with humility, indifferent and forgetful of earthly matters, in hope and longing for heavenly ones.
They cast aside riches, preferring to be poor, and hurry to be poor while desiring to be rich; day and night, they strive with labor and vigilance to grasp the beginning of that life whose end they will never find.
Thus, the desert holds those who are rightly greedy for eternity in its maternal embrace, well-spending the briefness of life; indifferent to the present time, certain of the future: and thereby they achieve that for those upon whom the end of the ages has come, an age without end will touch them.
There, the laws of the inner man are zealously written, and the rules of the eternal age are understood more subtly.
There, the decrees of human crimes and misdeeds do not assert their power, nor do the laws of severe punishment for grave offenses exercise themselves.
A heart that is not pure is judged by the native laws; and with all diligence, the inner movements of the mind are kept within the bounds of justice: and by the same judge, even the beginnings of slight thoughts are punished.
For others, it is evil to have done wrong, but for these, it is evil not to have done good.
But how can I honor the inward practices of the desert with worthy mention?
Yet now I cannot pass over in silence that strength of virtue in its inhabitants, though hidden from all, is almost as well known.
When they choose to journey into remote places, rejecting the world and human companionship, they find joy in being hidden.
Yet, their merit cannot be concealed.
The more their lives focus inwardly, the more their glory shines outwardly.
I believe God moderates this balance, allowing the desert dwellers to remain hidden from the world but not from their exemplary deeds.
This is the lamp that illuminates the entire world, placed on the lampstand of the desert.
From here, its radiant light spreads through the darkest parts of the world.
This is the city that cannot be hidden, built on the mountain of the desert, offering a glimpse of heavenly Jerusalem to the earth.
So, if anyone is in darkness, let them approach this light to see.
If anyone is in danger, let them head to this city for safety.
Oh, how joyful the deserts are to those thirsting for God, even the most remote paths!
How lovely are those secluded places to those seeking Christ, stretching far and wide with nature standing guard!
All is silent.
Then the happy mind is stirred by the silence towards God.
It is enlivened by indescribable ecstasies.
There is no disturbing noise, no voice except perhaps with God.
Only the pleasant sound of silence fills the secluded station, and the noise sweeter than quiet interrupts the peaceful rest, with the holy tumult of modest conversation.
Then the heights are struck by the sweetly resonating hymns of fervent choirs, reaching heaven as much by their voices as by their prayers.
The surrounding adversary roars in vain, like a wolf around sheep enclosed in pens.
The spacious desert is visited by a joyful chorus of angels, coming and going on Jacob's ladder, illuminating the desert with their frequent hidden visits.
Lest those who guard the city watch in vain, it is specially fortified by Christ the defender.
He drives away His enemies with the enclosure of the desert, as with the barrier of walls, ensuring that God's people are exposed to the spaces of seclusion while being protected from their enemies.
(Genesis 28:12)
That same afternoon, the bridegroom reclines while the inhabitants of the desert, wounded by love, contemplate him, saying:
We have found whom our soul loves; we will hold him and not let him go.
Song of Solomon
3:4
It is not as unproductive as believed; it is not the barren soil of the desert, nor the infertile rocks of the wilderness.
There, a multitude of crops and a hundredfold harvest is stored by the inhabitant.
Seeds do not easily fall by the wayside for birds to consume, nor do they slip into rocky ground to wither under the heat, nor do they flee into thorns to be choked by brambles.
Here, the farmer will reap a bountiful harvest; in these rocks, a crop grows that even nourishes the bones.
Here, the living bread that came down from heaven is found.
In those rocks, refreshing springs burst forth, and living waters, which not only satisfy but also save.
Here is the meadow and delight of the inner man; here, the uncultivated desert is marvelously pleasant, and this same desert of the body is the paradise of the soul.
No land, however fertile, can compare to the desert land.
Is there a land rich in crops?
In this one, the grain grows that satisfies the hungry with its richness.
Is there another land full of lush vineyards?
In this one, the wine is produced that gladdens the heart of man.
Is there another excelling in pastures?
In this one, the sheep are most healthily fed, of which it is said,
Feed my sheep.
John
21:17
Is there another adorned with blooming flowers?
In this one, the true flower of the field and the lily of the valleys shines forth.
Lastly, is there another rejoicing in splendid metals, another gleaming with its gold?
In this one, the varied stones shine with vibrant light.
Thus, this land exceeds each land in its particular qualities and far surpasses all others in all good things.
Rightly, therefore, you are a land to be revered by the Saints, whether they dwell in you, live nearby, once inhabited you, or longed for you.
You are fertile with all good things, where everything is found.
You seek a cultivator who tends his own land, not yours.
You are barren because of the vices of those who inhabit you but abundant in virtues.
Whoever sought the companionship of the Saints in you found God.
Whoever honored you found Christ in you.
He who dwells in you rejoices with the Lord as a resident.
He is both your possessor and a divine possession.
Whoever did not shun your dwelling has himself become a temple of God.
Indeed, I owe reverence to all the places of the desert illuminated by the retreat of the pious, especially embracing Lérins with my honor, which receives those scattered by the shipwrecks of the stormy world in its most pious arms.
From the burning heat of the world, it gently leads them into its shadows, so that there they may regain their spirit under that inner shadow of the Lord.
Abundant with waters, green with herbs, gleaming with vines, delightful to the sights and smells, it presents itself as a paradise to those who possess it.
It is worthy to have been founded by Honoratus, a man of heavenly disciplines, who with such great institutions has gained such a Father, shining with the vigor of an apostolic spirit and the honor of a face.
Worthy to accept him, and to send him forth.
Worthy to nurture the most excellent monks and to produce sought-after priests.
It now holds his successor, Maximus by name; renowned because he deserved to be received after him.
It held Lupus, a name of reverence, who brought back to us that wolf from the tribe of Benjamin.
It had his brother Vincent, a gem clear in internal splendor.
It possesses the venerable Caprasius, equal to the ancient saints in dignity.
Now it has those holy elders who, in divided cells, brought the Egyptian Fathers to our Gauls.
O good Jesus, what gatherings and congregations of saints did I see there!
In these, the alabaster was fragrant with precious, sweet ointment: the scent of life was everywhere.
The face of the inner person is displayed through their outward appearance:
Bound by love, humbled in humility, gentle in piety, firm in hope, modest in their walk, swift in obedience, silent in meeting, serene in countenance.
They show a band of angelic tranquility through contemplation.
They desire nothing, want nothing except Him, the one they long for.
While they seek a blessed life, they live a blessed life;
and while they strive for it, they already achieve it.
Do they wish to be separated from sinners?
They are already separated.
Do they want to possess a chaste life?
They possess it.
They strive to spend all their time praising God?
They do.
Do they desire to rejoice in the company of saints?
They rejoice.
Do they want to enjoy Christ?
They enjoy Christ.
Do they long to attain the life of a hermit?
They attain it in their hearts.
Through the generous grace of Christ, many of the things they hope for in the future, they already merit in the present.
They grasp the matter itself while they follow hope.
They have no small reward even in the labor itself, because almost already in the work is what the reward will be.
My dearest Hilary,
Your return to their fellowship has contributed much to yourself and to them, who now rejoice greatly at your return.
With them, I beg you, do not forget my sins and intercession;
with them, I say, with whom I do not know whether you brought more joy or found greater joy.
You now are a true Israelite, seeing God with your heart, freed from the Egyptian darkness of the world,
having crossed the saving waters with the enemy drowned, following the burning flame of faith in the desert, once bitter, now sweet through the wood of the cross:
You draw waters springing up to eternal life from Christ, you feed the inner person with heavenly bread;
in the Gospel, you receive the divine voice of your throne (Matthew 19:28).
With Israel, you dwell in the desert, with Jesus, you will enter the promised land.
Farewell in Christ Jesus our Lord.