On the Flight from the World
Ambrose of Milan
Chapter One
One cannot escape earthly temptations and desires without divine help.
We face many obstacles from our senses; it is essential to prioritize the sorrowful over the joyful, as joy often leads to vanity.
Ultimately, anyone who wants to be saved must rise above worldly concerns.
We often discuss escaping this world.
Refer to Saint Augustine, Book Two against Julian the Pelagian, Chapter Eight, and Book against the two letters of the Pelagians, Chapter Eleven.
If only our feelings were as cautious and sincere as our words are easy to say.
What's worse, earthly desires often sneak in, filling our minds with vanity.
We end up thinking about and dwelling on what we strive to avoid; it's hard to guard against and even harder to discard.
The Prophet acknowledges this struggle, saying: "Turn my heart toward your testimonies and not toward selfish gain" (Psalm 119:36).
Our hearts and thoughts are not under our control, and when they are suddenly released, they confuse our mind and spirit, leading us away from our intentions, recalling worldly things, introducing mundane matters, and weaving in temptations.
Just when we prepare to lift our minds, empty thoughts cast us down to earthly concerns.
But who is so blessed that they always ascend in their heart?
How can this happen without divine assistance?
Indeed, it cannot.
Scripture says: "Blessed is the man whose help is from you, Lord, whose ascent is in his heart" (Psalm 84:5).
Clearly, blessed is the one whom delight does not distract, whom pleasure does not sway, who does not look to lower things; even Lot's wife could not avoid this.
Inspired by this example, the Apostle, forgetting what is behind and reaching out for what is ahead, hurried toward the prize and deserved to reach it; because he saw Christ before him, who called him to the crown of righteousness.
He achieved this by denying himself to gain Christ.
Ultimately, he did not live, but Christ lived in him.
Amid so many sufferings and temptations, who can keep their path safe and undefiled?
The eye looks and the mind's focus shifts; the ear hears and concentration wavers; the nose inhales and thoughts are disrupted; the mouth tastes and sin is reported; touch ignites desire.
Death enters through the window, says the Prophet Jeremiah 9:21.
Your window is your eye.
If you see someone and feel lust, death has entered.
If you hear seductive words, death has entered.
If luxury captivates your senses, death has penetrated.
Therefore, whoever wants to ascend should not follow the joys, pleasures, or delights of the world, but rather embrace pain and weeping.
It is better to go to a house of mourning than to a house of joy.
Indeed, Adam would not have been driven from paradise if he had not been deceived by pleasure.
Thus, David, who experienced the dangerous glances of man, rightly calls blessed those whose hope is in the name of God Psalm 39:5.
For they do not focus on vanities and false insanities if they always look to Christ with their inner eyes.
Hence, turning to Him again, he says, Turn away my eyes from seeing vanity Psalm 119:37.
Vanity is the circus, for it is useless.
Vanity is the speed of horses, for it is deceitful for salvation.
Vanity is the theater.
Vanity is every game.
All is vanity, says Ecclesiastes 1:2, which is in this world.
Indeed, whoever wants to be saved should rise above the world, seek the Word with God, flee this world, and leave the earth.
For they cannot grasp what truly is unless they first flee from here.
Therefore, the Lord, wanting to draw near to God the Father, said to the apostles, Arise, let us go from here.
Chapter Two
The law about cities of refuge teaches us to flee from the world, with four main points discussed:
First, why these cities were chosen by the lot of the Levites;
Second, why there are six in number;
Third, why three of them are beyond the Jordan, and three in the land of Canaan;
Fourth, why a killer is commanded to wait there for the death of the high priest.
All these points are applied to different virtues.
The law also teaches us to flee from the world and follow God.
For what else does it mean when it says, "You shall designate cities for yourselves as cities of refuge, and they shall be for you a refuge, so that anyone who kills a person unintentionally may flee there" (Numbers 35:11)?
And later: "Six cities of refuge shall be for you, three cities you shall give beyond the Jordan, and three cities you shall give in the land of Canaan" (Numbers 35:13-14)?
Clearly, these cities of refuge are set up for those who commit the crime of manslaughter.
But let us consider this more deeply.
There are four points that remind us that the secrets of this reading must be examined more profoundly.
First, why from these cities, which fell to the Levites by lot, six cities were given for those burdened by the crime of manslaughter, and why not the cities of other tribes were assigned to this duty.
Second, why the number six; this number does not seem to be prescribed without reason, neither more nor fewer cities.
Third, why three cities beyond the Jordan and three in the region of Canaan were set up as refuges for sinners.
Fourth, why the timing and definition of the period are included, during which the killer must stay in the city of refuge until the high priest dies, and after the death of the high priest, the killer may return to their own city of residence (Numbers 35:25).
Therefore, we must discuss each point in the order we proposed and resolve the questions.
It is fitting, therefore, to first explain why the cities of the Levites were given as cities of refuge.
It is clearly appropriate because the Levites are those fleeing from this world to please God.
They leave their homeland, parents, children, and all relatives to adhere to one God.
Finally, it was said to Abraham: "Go out from your land, and from your kindred, and from your father's house" Genesis 12:1.
But you might say: He was not a Levite. However, he had Levi in his body, as we read in Hebrews 7:10.
And the Lord says to the Levites, with His disciples, that is, the apostles: "If anyone wants to come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me" Luke 9:23.
Although it has already been said to all: "But you are a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for His own possession" First Peter 2:9.
The fullness has come, the remnants have ceased. For Christ called everyone; it is open to everyone indeed, so that all may follow. The kingdom is offered to everyone, and eternal life.
Therefore, he to whom God is a portion Cui portio, should care for nothing except God, so that he is not hindered by the service of another necessity. For what is offered to other duties is taken away from the worship of religion and our duty.
For this is the true flight of a priest: the renunciation of domestic things, and a certain alienation from the dearest ones; so that even from his own he denies himself, who desires to serve God.
Therefore, rightly did the eternal law's sanction commend the fugitives to the fugitives; so that those who have forgotten this world may receive those who, condemning their sins and deeds, seek to forget their former life, and wish to abolish the secular things they have done.
Therefore, the minister of the sacred altar is a fugitive from his own. Hence the Lord, as the chief priest, giving an example to the Levites in His Gospel, said: "Who is my mother, or who are my brothers?" Matthew 12:48.
That is, I do not recognize a mother, I do not acknowledge brothers, I am ignorant of relatives. My mother and my brothers are those who hear the word of God and do it Matthew 12:50.
Therefore, the minister only knows the word of God when he knows those in whom the word of God works. And so he is an exile from the world, fleeing the body, fleeing passions, renouncing all things, so that he remains alone, as Elijah said: "And I alone am left" First Kings 19:14.
But he was not alone with whom Christ was.
And the Lord Himself was left alone.
But He says, "I am not alone, because the Father is with me" John 16:32.
The Levites are ministers of God, and their cities are appointed by law as refuges for those who commit murder. They have the authority to carry out divine commands concerning those who have committed mortal sins. The Church does not make its own laws but obeys the command of the Lord's priest. Hear the Levite saying: "I have handed over such a person to Satan for the destruction of the flesh, so that the spirit may be saved on the day of our Lord Jesus Christ" First Corinthians 5:5. Thus, struck by the Levitical sword, the sense of the flesh should die in us so that our soul may live. For if the sense of the flesh does not die, there can be no fruit of eternal life.
There are six cities of refuge. The first city represents the knowledge of the Word and living according to its image. Whoever enters that knowledge is safe from punishment, as the Lord says: "You are already clean because of the word I have spoken to you" John 15:3. And elsewhere: "This is eternal life, that they know you, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom you have sent" John 17:3. This city is like a metropolis, with the other five cities of the Levites adjacent to it. The second city is the consideration of the divine operation by which the world was created. The third city is the contemplation of royal power and eternal majesty. The fourth city is the view of divine propitiation. The fifth city is the contemplation of the divine law, which commands what must be done. The sixth city is also the portion of the law that prescribes what must not be done.
How abundant is divine mercy and how rich is His kindness!
Considering each person's efforts and the frailties of the human condition, which often lead us into fault even unwillingly, and resisting, we often commit unintentional sins, overcome by temptations.
Yet, He provides us with different refuges, namely six cities, so that the remedy against worldly vices and the shipwreck of this age would be provided in the same number with which the world was formed.
Therefore, the first remedy is that if a fault creeps into the life of a well-intentioned person, they should, without delay, if they seek perfect security, hurry to the very pinnacle of all things, where the Word of God resides in the paternal bosom, the secret and recess of God.
This is where the fountain of wisdom lies, from which they may draw the immortal drink for eternal life instead of death.
The second remedy is for those who cannot grasp the knowledge of that good and are slower either in intellect or in the comprehension of faith.
Since the highest knowledge requires swift intellect and sharpness of mind, they should at least consider the works of the Lord.
From these creations, they can contemplate the author of such great works.
From the good things in the constitution of this creation (for they are very good as stated in Genesis 1:31), that supreme and eternal good is understood.
What order of things, what discipline, what grace?
Do not these provoke even a dull mind to love its author?
For if we love our parents because they gave birth to us, how much more should we love the creator of our parents and our author?
Therefore, the operative power of God, even if not seen, is estimated from His works, and His works reveal the worker, so that He who is not comprehended may be understood.
Hence the Lord also said: If you do not believe me, believe the works (John 10:38).
Therefore, this city is also a good refuge, testifying to the grace of its builder and stirring our affection, so that we may desire Him more, who seems to have bestowed upon us such beauty in this structure.
The third order is the contemplation of royal power, so that we submit to the king, even if we do not honor him as we would a parent.
Often, obedience to authority stems from fear of the ruler, who may be ungrateful for the safety provided.
This fear teaches the necessity of sobriety to those who neither desire nor recognize the grace of piety.
Therefore, necessity corrects those whom piety should have guided.
These are the three cities across the Jordan, given for more perfect prudence as a refuge; first, we flee from guilt through the inspiration of the soul, conforming to the image of God.
We were created in this way, with God saying: "Let us make man in our image and likeness" (Genesis 1:26).
This is the law of the first city.
If, due to the frailty of the flesh and the temptations of the world, we cannot shape our minds in this way, let us alleviate sin through the reverence of fatherly generation and the diligence of offspring.
For charity covers a multitude of sins.
Therefore, if one cannot be in the image of God, let him be in the fullness of charity.
The first city excludes guilt, while the second absolves it.
This is the law of the second city: "You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your strength" (Deuteronomy 6:5).
But if there are those of narrow and small spirit who cannot receive the abundance of charity and grace, there is the third city; so that the fear of divine power makes you sober, and fear bends you.
This is the law of the third city: "You shall worship the Lord your God, and him only shall you serve" (Deuteronomy 6:13).
These then are the chief virtues, placed beyond the Jordan for the few, not the many.
Express the archetype as an image, love as a son loves a father, and worship as a subject worships a king.
Those who cross the Jordan, their descent into the Jordan is spoken of: those who descend from higher virtues to these lower ones, where integrity, charity, and humility waver, have refuges closer to humanity that they can seek.
So that those who are burdened with sins and bent by involuntary vices may hope that the Lord can be reconciled to them if they seek forgiveness.
They may hope that they can be corrected if they follow the commandments of the heavenly Testaments, which either guide us to innocence or call us back from guilt.
Therefore, these cities within the Jordan are as follows, so that we may appease God:
let us follow what He commands, and avoid what He prohibits.
Let the ambition of appeasing the divine be obedience to His commandments and caution against prohibited transgressions.
By which we venerate God's propitiatory mercy and His law-giving providence, either through obedience to His institutions or by avoiding the prohibited.
The fourth remains, which speaks about the death of the high priest:
Because until that time, the murderer will be in the city of refuge, until the high priest dies.
Joshua 20:6.
In this, according to the letter, the interpretation falters.
First, the very flight is determined more by chance than by any examination of fairness.
Then, in equal cases, there is an unequal outcome; for it could happen that after the murderer’s refuge, the high priest might die the next day.
But what is the judgment under such uncertainty?
Therefore, because the letter falters, let us seek the spiritual meaning.
Who is this great high priest, if not the Son of God, the Word of God, whose advocacy we have with the Father, who is free from all voluntary and incidental sins, in whom all things in heaven and on earth exist?
For all things are bound by the bond of the Word, held together by His power, and exist in Him.
Because in Him all things were created, and in Him all fullness dwells.
And therefore, all things remain because He does not allow to be dissolved what He has bound, because they exist by His will.
For as long as He wills, He controls and governs them by His command, and binds them with natural harmony.
The Word of God lives, especially within the souls of the faithful.
The fullness of divinity never perishes.
For the eternal divinity and the eternal power of God are everlasting.
However, it feels like it dies for us if it is separated from our soul.
Not because it is tainted by death, but because our mind becomes disconnected.
True death is indeed the separation of the Word and the soul.
When this happens, the soul immediately becomes vulnerable to voluntary sins.
Chapter Three
In the previous chapter, we explored the different kinds of virtues mentioned by the Apostle, not just outlined but clearly expressed, supported by various testimonies from him.
We see these virtues clearly demonstrated in the Apostle when he says:
"So as much as is in me, I am ready to preach the gospel to you who are in Rome."
"For I am not ashamed of the gospel."
"It is the power of God for salvation to everyone who believes, first to the Jew and then to the Greek."
"For in it, the righteousness of God is revealed, that is, in the one who believes" (Romans 1:15 and following).
He then adds:
"From faith to faith, as it is written: ‘The just shall live by faith.’"
So, in whom is the righteousness of God revealed, if not in the one who conforms to the image of the Son of God?
This is the first precept according to the image of God.
The second precept states that the invisible attributes of God, understood through His creations, reveal His eternal power and divinity.
This is His operative power.
The third precept concerns imperial authority, as the Word of God is royal, judicial, and full of priestly justice, rewarding good actions and punishing evil ones in His coming judgment, as the Apostle says:
"We know that the judgment of God is according to truth against those who practice such things" (Romans 2:2).
Therefore, anyone who knows the truth and justice of God should not engage in actions worthy of death.
Next, we consider the propitiatory goodness of God, about which he says:
"Or do you despise the riches of His goodness, forbearance, and long-suffering? Do you not know that the goodness of God leads you to repentance?" (Romans 2:4).
This means it should lead you to repentance.
It calls you because God is good, offering hope for the forgiveness of your sins.
For He does not seek vengeance, but is ready to forgive.
He also mentions legislation, or nomothetics, suggesting that if anyone is softened by contemplating divine goodness and is provoked more to negligence than to repentance, they should follow the law.
As it is said, “For as many as have sinned without the law will also perish without the law; and as many as have sinned in the law will be judged by the law” (Romans 2:12).
The law, however, is twofold: natural and written.
Natural in the heart; written on tablets.
Therefore, everyone is naturally under the law.
But not everyone is their own law.
The one who is a law unto themselves is the one who willingly does what the law requires and shows the work of the law written in their heart.
You know what the good things of the law are; these we should not only know or hear superficially but also do.
For it is not the hearers of the law who are righteous before God, but the doers of the law who will be justified.
You also know what the bad things are.
First, nature itself teaches us good deeds.
You know not to steal, and if your servant steals from you, you punish them; and if someone desires your wife, you think they should be pursued.
So why do you commit what you condemn in others?
Do you who preach against stealing, steal?
Do you who say not to commit adultery, commit adultery?
The law given through Moses also followed.
Through the law comes the knowledge of sin.
You have also learned what to avoid, and yet you do the things you know are forbidden?
What does the law accomplish except to make the whole world subject to God?
For it was not only given to the Hebrew but also called the foreigner and did not exclude the proselyte.
But because the law could silence everyone’s mouth, it could not convert the mind.
Therefore, the ultimate remedy was needed, in which there would be a saving refuge; so that the death of the high priest would free us from every fear of death and strip away our fear.
(See St. Augustine, Book IV, against the two epistles of the Pelagians, chapter 11).
Who is this, but the one of whom it is written: "Behold the Lamb of God, behold him who takes away the sin of the world" (John 1:29).
Whom God set forth as a propitiation through faith in his blood to demonstrate his righteousness (Romans 3:25).
Understand that he is the great high priest.
The Father swore about him, saying: "You are a priest forever" (Psalm 109:4).
Rightly forever, as all others are temporary and under sin, but he holds an unbreakable priesthood: all are under death, but he always lives; for how could he who saves others perish himself?
Such a one, he says, was fitting for us Hebrews 7:2-3. A proper expression.
Indeed, even among those who have chosen their words and expressions carefully, such a phrase is found, as someone says:
A higher place than what was fitting for the victors (Sallust, Book One Histories).
I did not pass over this so that we may know that the Apostle uses words more naturally than commonly or according to art.
So, he says, such a leader was fitting for us: a priest, righteous, holy, innocent, undefiled, separated from sinners, and made higher than the heavens.
This is the Word that, dwelling above the heavens, illuminates all things.
Hence, it is also read that he was anointed by God the Father by nature Acts 4:27;
because he is the true light that illuminates every person coming into this world.
This is the Word of God, in which there is a great priesthood, whose garments Moses describes in the vestments of the high priest in that garment Exodus 29:5 and following,
which by its virtue clothes the world and shines in all things as if clothed by it.
For he clothed himself with the kinship of the human race by taking on this body and poured out his ineffable love to all by his spirit and the fullness of his divinity, from whose fullness we all have received;
so that we may know the love of Christ that surpasses knowledge and be filled with all the fullness of God.
For Christ is the head of all, from whom the whole body is produced and joined together by mutual connection, receiving its growth in the building up of love.
Therefore, this is the Word that surpasses, which he says to Moses in the building of the ark of testimony:
You shall place in the ark the testimony that I shall give you, and you shall make the covering of the mercy seat Exodus 25:16-17.
And later:
You shall put the mercy seat on top of the ark, and inside the ark you shall place the testimony that I shall give you; and I will meet with you there, and I will speak with you from above Exodus 25:22,
that is, from where it is above the heavens, where it is with the Father, from there I will speak to you.
Chapter Four
What it means to flee the world, with an exhortation to do so and to avoid its contamination.
This flight is shown to be glorious with the examples of many Fathers, especially Saint Jacob.
How successfully he fled; and why Laban could find nothing of his among his possessions?
Let us therefore, supported by faith and lifted by its guidance, approach that seat of grace, fleeing this world and its contamination.
To flee means to abstain from sins, to take on virtues in the likeness and image of God, and to extend our efforts to imitate God according to the measure of our ability.
A perfect man is the image and glory of God.
Hence the Lord says: Be perfect as your Father in heaven is perfect.
Matthew 5:48
Therefore, to be like God is to have justice, to have wisdom, and to be perfect in virtue.
For God is without sin.
And so, whoever avoids sin bears the image of God.
There is thus no doubt that one who abstains from sin flees.
Hence the Apostle cries out: Flee from fornication.
First Corinthians 6:18
For the allurements of sins pursue us, lust pursues us: but you must flee from it as from a mad mistress, who, if she catches you, will not let you rest day or night.
She harasses, burns, and inflames you.
Flee greed, so it does not capture you internally.
Flee envy, which not only harms others but even more so the one it possesses.
Flee treachery, lest it ensnare you in its nets.
Hence the Lord says: When they persecute you in this city, flee to another.
If they persecute you in another, flee to yet another.
Truly I tell you, you will not finish going through the towns of Israel before the Son of Man comes.
Matthew 10:23
Even though our flesh may be weak and we may feel advised to flee, it's better to escape from worldly temptations; to not be held by concerns over our riches, the contemplation of our wealth, or the desire for this life.
Instead, with a direct intention of the mind, we should hasten towards the glory of the heavenly kingdom, rush towards the crown, and not be called back by the passions of our body due to earthly things.
Therefore, fleeing can represent either a celebrated or shadowed death.
It might also symbolize those cities of legitimate refuge, so we may seek solace in the heights of virtues, dispensed elsewhere as rewards to the good lender, saying: "Because you have been faithful in little things, you will have authority over ten cities" (Luke 19:17).
The old law recognized these cities, but because he fulfilled the law, who said: "I did not come to destroy the law, but to fulfill it" (Matthew 5:17), he grants a more perfect number of rewards.
So, let us not be ashamed to flee.
This is a glorious flight, to flee from the face of sin.
Thus, Jacob fled at his mother's urging.
For Rebecca said: "Get up, flee to Mesopotamia" (Genesis 27:43).
Moses fled from Pharaoh, the king, to avoid being defiled by the royal court or ensnared by its power.
Ultimately, he considered the reproach of Christ more valuable than the riches of Egypt.
Similarly, David fled from King Saul and from Absalom.
As he fled, he showed piety, sparing his pursuer and praying for the safety of the parricide.
The Hebrew people fled, allowing their faith and life to part the waves for them.
That flight was a path of innocence, a way of virtue, an act of piety.
I dare to say, Jonah fled to Tarshish not physically, but in the ascension of his mind, becoming a type of Christ.
Just as Jonah was in the belly of the whale for three days and three nights, so too, he said, will the Son of Man be in the heart of the earth for three days and three nights (Matthew 12:40).
If Jonah had not fled in this way, he would never have been heard from the belly of the whale.
If you doubt this, let Rebecca show you how blessed the flight that Jacob undertook truly was.
Rebecca advised, "Flee to Mesopotamia" (Genesis 28:2).
Isaac also said, "Get up and go to Mesopotamia, to the house of Bethuel." In hymns or oracles, Bethuel is often said to mean wisdom, but in Latin interpretation, it signifies the daughter of God. Therefore, Jacob is sent to the house of wisdom and is instructed to take a wife from the daughters of Laban, who lived in Haran. Haran means caves, symbolizing the senses like sight, hearing, smell, and taste, which are enclosed within the body.
Those who delight in this world and revel in bodily pleasures are subject to the passions of the senses and are influenced by them. Rebecca advises Jacob to stay with Laban for a few days, not for a long time, so that he does not get tarnished by bodily pleasures and captured by the allurements of the world. She wants him to stay to diligently learn the discipline of virtue and understand the workings of the flesh, so he can know himself and comprehend why and for what purpose he was created.
"Whoever looks at a woman to lust for her" (Matthew 5:28).
The eye falls into sin in this way.
Therefore, let the eye perform its duty without being led by a slippery mind into vice.
A short time is given to understand the senses, or rather to experience them, and this is often the beginning of tender youth.
Immediately, he is called back, lest he stumble further on the slippery path, and the inner footprints of the soul are overwhelmed by the flood of bodily and worldly desires.
When someone has experienced or stood on unstable, uncertain, and damp ground, patience or perseverance, like a mother, calls them back, saying:
"I will send for you and bring you back from there" Genesis 27:45.
So that even in slippery places, you may find a safe harbor of wisdom that prevents you from floundering like in a shipwreck.
And you may return and persist in the worship of God, and be among the gathering of nations, indicating the Church of nations to be assembled by faith.
Thus, trained by the disciplines of patience and perseverance Genesis 29:23 and following, Jacob set out and acquired for himself a union with wisdom, his companion in purpose, richly endowed with prudence.
With this wisdom, he could pass through life's times without any offense.
With the added treasure of wisdom, he established a flock of various sheep for himself. But this flock was rational, shining with the diversity of many virtues.
Hence, he cut away the boastfulness of his flesh Genesis 32:25, which is symbolized by the numbness of the thigh, while preserving the sacred interpretation of the mystery.
Therefore, with these virtues as certain steps, his mind ascended to heaven, and he knew God's secrets. He was strengthened and filled.
So that when Laban searched his house, he found nothing empty, nothing void, no idols, no image of vanity. For there was no image with him, but truth: not a figure of laziness, but a solid form of justice, and an intelligible expression of true virtue.
Thus, Laban searched his spiritual house and found no images. For it was full, not of figures, but of affairs.
He might have found the foundations and peaks of virtues if he had not carried the blindness of heart and the darkness of a deceitful mind.
Indeed, blinded by this wickedness, the minds of the Sodomites could not find the door of holy Lot.
For how could an impious mind see either the exit or entrance of a holy man?
The Lord Himself also says in the Gospel: "The ruler of this world is coming, and he has nothing in me" John 14:30.
How could he find nothing in Him, in whom the fullness of divinity dwells bodily, from whom virtue flows out and heals everyone?
How could he find nothing in the solidity of virtue, the abundance of wisdom, intelligence, and justice?
You yourself said, Lord, Isaiah 1:11: "I am full." You also said: "Put your hand into my side, and do not be unbelieving, but faithful" John 20:27.
He who did not believe put his hand in and found you to be Lord and God. Therefore, it is not you who are empty, but the blind and empty prince of this world, who knows only how to see and find his own things; he does not know how to recognize the things of Christ.
Or if, as many hold: "He will not find nothing in me," meaning he will not find malice in me, because malice is nothing: he will not find the dead, because he is not dead. But how could he find the dead in Him who gives life to the dead and calls things that are not as though they were?
He says he will not find sin in me, who took away the sin of the world. For how can he have nothing, who has everything? And, what is more, he has everything that the Father has, as He himself said: "Everything that the Father has is mine" John 16:15.
Chapter Five
Why we should flee from here and how to cross over with Moses to see God, removing the shoes from our feet: also how to leave behind the shadow of this life, and with holy David, if not like an eagle, at least like a sparrow; if not to heaven, at least to the mountains fly.
Therefore, let us flee from here, where there is nothing, where everything that is thought to be magnificent is empty, where even someone who thinks they are something is nothing and is absolutely nothing.
"I have seen the wicked exalted and lifted up beyond the cedars of Lebanon, and I passed by, and behold, he was not there" (Psalm 37:35).
And you, pass by like David, pass by like a good servant, so it can be said to you: "Pass by, recline" (Luke 17:7).
Pass by like Moses, to see the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and to see the great vision.
This is the great vision, but if you want to see it, remove the shoes from your feet, remove every bond of iniquity, remove the ties of the world, leave behind the shoe that is earthly.
This is why Jesus sent the apostles without shoes, gold, and silver, so they would not carry earthly things with them.
For whoever seeks the good is not praised for their shoes, but for the swiftness and beauty of their feet, as the Scripture says: "How beautiful are the feet of those who bring good news, who proclaim peace, who bring good tidings" (Isaiah 52:7)!
Therefore, remove the shoes from your feet, so they may be beautiful for proclaiming the good news.
He said "Remove" (Exodus 3:5), not "Tie."
Remove, so you can pass by, and find that the wicked one you marveled at on earth is nothing, has no power.
So pass by, that is, flee from the lands where there is malice, where there is greed.
This is why David says to you: "Turn away from evil and do good" (Psalm 34:14).
To turn away is certainly to flee.
However, evil is on earth, good is in heaven.
Hence, he added: "Seek peace and pursue it."
Peace is in heaven.
Finally, coming from heaven, he says: "My peace I give you, my peace I leave with you" (John 14:27).
Therefore, because evil should be avoided and turned away from, and evil exists on earth, iniquities are on earth: let us flee from earthly things so that iniquities do not catch us, as they even caught the holy David, as he himself testifies, saying:
"My iniquities have caught up with me, and I could not see."
Psalm 40:13.
Because the eye of the soul is blinded by the smoke of iniquity, it cannot see what is bright. Similarly, Laban could not see the good in Jacob, nor could the ruler of this world see the glory of Christ.
But you might ask: Why then was Jacob sent to Laban, if Laban is blameworthy? If we consider the name, it means "white" in Latin. Therefore, Jacob is commanded to go out to brighter things. But since he was worldly, we understand it as the brighter things of this life.
As someone not yet perfect, he first goes to him, where he might rejoice for a while in his light. However, he had worse sons, meaning a tolerable name but not deeds. And so, by the advice of his mother, a divine oracle, and Jacob's own will as a lover of discipline, he quickly leaves and abandons him.
Rachel, that is, the Church or wisdom, hides the sacred idols, because the Church does not know the empty ideas and vain figures of idols, but knows the true substance of the Trinity. Finally, the shadow is abolished, the splendor of glory is revealed. Therefore, let us leave the shadow, we who seek the sun; let us abandon the smoke, we who follow the light. Smoke is iniquity; because just as smoke affects the eyes, so iniquities affect those who live that life.
Life is a shadow: our life on earth is a shadow, as Job said.
Job 8:9.
What is there here besides temptations? All time is spent in anxiety, all life in troubles.
"In the midst of snares we walk."
Ecclesiasticus 9:20.
And another complained about snares laid out for him but hidden on the path he walked,
Psalm 142:4,
so that he would not be caught and fall. He wanted to flee like a bird: but the snare was not yet broken.
"Escape has perished from me."
Psalm 142:5.
His wings were weighed down by that dark water in the clouds of the air, and perhaps he could not fly away.
Finally, he sought to receive those wings so that he might fly away and rest, as it is written: "Who will give me wings like a dove, and I will fly and rest" (Psalm 55:7)?
For where there is flight, there is rest.
Indeed, elsewhere it says: "If you sleep among the midst of the folds, the wings of the dove are covered with silver" (Psalm 68:14).
But perhaps you might ask: "How, then, does he say here that he has lost his escape, when he previously said: 'If I take the wings of the morning'" (Psalm 139:9)?
Is this contradictory?
By no means.
For the struggles of the righteous are many.
Does an athlete wrestle only once?
How many times, after winning many crowns, is he defeated in another contest!
How many times does someone who has often won sometimes falter and hesitate in uncertainty!
And it often happens that the strong face strong opponents, and greater contests arise, where greater proofs of strength are shown.
So David, when he was seeking escape to avoid his adversary and could not find his wings, was wavering in a difficult contest.
For when he has his wings in his power, the title of the psalm is "To the End" (Psalm 139), that is, to the perfection and completion of victory.
Indeed, as a victor, he says: "Lord, you have tested me and known me: you have known my sitting down and my rising up" (Psalm 139:1).
Rightly did he have the ability to fly, for he had received the wings of resurrection.
But here he is still in the cave, that is, in the flesh, in a certain cave of this body, with King Saul, son of hardness, and deciding with the power of that intelligible prince, who is not seen but understood.
Hence, the title of the psalm is "Understanding" (Psalm 55), which David, placed in the flesh, concluded: but he deserved to conclude by praying.
Therefore, he began with the voice of prayer.
Add this: The psalm is spoken from the perspective of the Savior, while this one is from the perspective of David.
In the year 430, David did not have victory in his power but hoped for it from Christ.
He raised his hands to God, like the wings of his soul, and fled to the Lord.
He asked for the guidance of the Holy Spirit to know the way to ascend.
Then, he saw the heavens bending down so that Christ might descend, and he asked to be lifted up by His hand.
Or perhaps he no longer sought his own wings because, having become more perfect, he desired the hand of Christ.
Therefore, whoever wants to be lifted by the hand of Christ should first fly up himself and have his own wings.
Whoever flees the world must have wings; and if he does not have his own, lest he alone have his wings who has the power to fly, if, I say, he does not have his own, he should receive them from one who does.
Therefore, whoever flees the world flies: "Behold," he says, "I have fled far away, and I stayed in the wilderness" (Psalm 54:8).
David therefore flew like an owl in a ruin, like a solitary sparrow in a house.
But if you refer this to Christ, He flew in the suffering of His body, so that under the shadow of His wings He might protect the peoples of the nations.
He flew divinely, remained in the body, and dwelt in the desert; so that the children of the desolate would be more numerous than those of her who had a husband.
Let us therefore follow that body, so that we too may rise.
For where the body is, there too are the eagles.
Whoever cannot fly like an eagle, let him fly like a sparrow.
Whoever cannot fly to heaven, let him fly to the mountains, fleeing the lowlands, which are quickly corrupted by moisture, and let him pass to the mountains.
Lot's nephew passed to the mountain of Zoar and was saved; but she who could not ascend, reclining in her feminine affection, lost her salvation.
Approach the eternal mountains, the Lord says through the prophet Micah: "Rise and depart, for this is not your place of rest. Because of uncleanness, you are destroyed and suffer corruption" (Micah 2:9-10).
And the Lord says, "Then those in Judea must flee to the mountains" (Luke 21:21).
Where Mount Zion and the city of peace, Jerusalem, are built not with earthly stones but with living ones.
And ten thousand angels, the church of the firstborn, the spirits of the perfected, the God of the just, who spoke better in His blood than Abel.
For he cried out for vengeance, but He for forgiveness: he accused his brother's sin, but He forgave the sin of the world.
He revealed the crime, but He covered it as it is written:
Blessed are those whose sins are covered
Psalms 31:1.
Chapter Six
How should someone who wishes to flee do so quickly?
Where should they flee, and to what good should we lift our souls?
Let the one who flees, flee quickly, lest they be caught.
They should swiftly plunder this world, as the Hebrews plundered Egypt.
Whoever is in labor, let them give birth, lest, burdened and weighed down by the sins of the mind, they cannot flee.
And let them flee not as one carrying an infant, but as one unencumbered.
Not bearing a child, but presenting one perfect in Christ.
Let them flee not as one resting on the Sabbath, but as diligently as a worker on the job.
Not as a barren one in the cold, but as a fruitful one at harvest.
Therefore, it has been said: Pray that your flight may not be in winter, or on the Sabbath.
(Matthew 24:20).
This flight is rich in virtues, not accomplished by merits.
It knows not the cold of fear, the trembling of death, the contraction of anxiety, the idleness of dissolution, the holidays of indulgence, or the torpor of sloth.
But the heavenly life requires a diligent traveler, a determined competitor for the higher kingdom, a rich farmer who gathers his fruits, and by gathering, plunders them.
For what else is required of you, O man, but to fear the Lord, seek Him, walk after Him, and follow His ways?
(Deuteronomy 10:12).
In what, He says, shall I follow the Lord?
Shall I follow Him in burnt offerings?
Not in ten thousand goats, not in thousands of rams, not in the fruits of wickedness is the Lord reconciled, and sins redeemed.
But in a good life, the grace of the Lord is comprehended.
It has been declared to you, He says, O man, what is good, or what the Lord requires of you.
What else, but to do justice, and love mercy, and be ready to walk with the Lord your God?
Therefore, the Gospel says to you: Rise, let us go from here.
(John 14:31).
The law says to you: Walk after the Lord your God.
(Deuteronomy 13:4).
You have learned how to flee from here, why do you delay?
The Gospel says to you again: Offspring of vipers, who warned you to flee from the wrath to come?
(Matthew 3:7).
And this He says to those who were coming to the baptism of repentance.
Therefore, fleeing through repentance is good: fleeing with the grace of God is good, for it involves the assumption of the one fleeing.
Fleeing to the desert is good, where Elijah, Elisha, and John the Baptist sought refuge.
Elijah fled from Jezebel, symbolizing the outpouring of vanity, and went to Mount Horeb, which signifies dryness.
This was so that the flow of carnal vanity would dry up in him, allowing him to know God more fully.
He was at the brook Cherith, meaning knowledge, where he could drink abundantly from the flowing divine knowledge, avoiding the world to the extent that he did not seek bodily food except what the birds, the servants, brought him.
His sustenance was often not earthly.
In fact, he walked for forty days on the strength of the food he had received.
Such a great prophet was not fleeing just a woman, but the world itself.
Was he afraid of death, he who had offered himself to his pursuer and said to the Lord, "Take my soul" (First Kings 19:4)?
He endured the weariness of this life not out of desire but to escape secular temptation, the contagion of a stained way of life, and the sacrileges of an impious and rebellious nation.
Solomon, too, in the form of that woman, reveals the corruption of this world and teaches us to avoid the arts of prostitutes (Proverbs 7 and elsewhere).
This foreign and adulterous woman is one from whom he urges you to protect yourself.
Do not let your heart turn to the ways of the world, but place it in the hand of the Lord, in which lies the heart of the king.
For he who governs himself, which is more valuable than ruling others, has his heart in the hand of God, and God turns it wherever He wills.
It is no wonder if He turns it to good, for He is of perfect goodness.
Therefore, let us be in the hand of God, so that we may seek the good, that incorruptible and unchangeable good, about which the prophet Amos says: "Seek good and not evil, that you may live; and so the Lord God Almighty will be with you" (Amos 5:14).
How have you said: "We hated evil and loved good"? Where then is the good God, there are the good things, which David desired to see, and believed he would see, as he himself says: "I believe I shall see the goodness of the Lord in the land of the living" (Psalm 27:13).
The good things are the ones that last forever, untouched by time or age.
In those good things is the one who has sought and found God.
Where a person's heart is, there is also their treasure.
The Lord does not usually deny a good thing to those who ask.
Because the Lord is good, and especially good to those who endure for His sake, let us cling to Him with all our soul, heart, and strength.
So that we may be in His light, see His glory, and enjoy the grace of heavenly delight.
Let us lift our spirits to that good, be in it, live in it, and cling to it.
It is beyond all understanding and consideration, bringing perpetual peace and tranquility.
Peace, however, is beyond all understanding and beyond all sense.
This is the good that penetrates everything, and we all live in it and depend on it.
It has nothing above itself, for it is divine; no one is good except God alone.
Therefore, what is good is divine; and what is divine is good.
And so it is said: "When you open your hand, they are filled with good things" Psalm 104:28.
Through the goodness of God, all good things are given to us by merit, untainted by evil. These good things are promised by Scripture to the faithful, saying: "If you are willing and obedient, you will eat the good things of the land" Isaiah 1:19.
Therefore, let us be like that good, so we may obtain those good things. The good that is without iniquity, deceit, or harshness, but with grace, piety, sincerity, benevolence, charity, and justice. All virtues embrace goodness as a fertile mother.
Chapter Seven
The greatest reason why we should flee from here is because this is the very seat of wickedness.
What does it mean to flee?
Wickedness does not perish here, and for what reason?
Regarding the condemnation of the serpent, how does it differ from the judgment passed on man?
To this is added an explanation of the same judgment.
Therefore, there is no small reason why we should flee from here: so that we may go from evil to good, from uncertainty to faithfulness and full of truth, from death to life.
The Lord Himself also said, "I have set before you good and evil, life and death" (Deuteronomy 30:15), showing that good is life, but eternal life.
For if this life is subject to the world and its wickedness, certainly that life is good, which is neither corrupted nor changed, which does not degenerate by any vice, which is acquired by virtue.
Therefore, let us flee the wickedness of this world, in which the days themselves, he says (Ephesians 5:16), are evil; and let us flee diligently.
And so Isaiah cries out, "Strengthen the weak hands, and make firm the feeble knees" (Isaiah 35:3), which means, not the knees of the body, but of the soul; strengthen them, so that the path of the mind may be lifted up to the highest heights of heaven, so that the guide may be firmer, the life more mature, the grace fuller, the prudence more circumspect.
For this is to flee, to know where you are heading, to lift yourself up from the world, to lift yourself up from the body; lest anyone again exalts himself in vain, and inflated by the mind of his flesh does not hold onto the head, and it is said of them: "They fled, and did not see" (Job 9:25).
But this is to flee from here, to die to the elements of this world, to hide your life in God, to avoid corruptions, to not be stained by desires, to be ignorant of the things of this world, which generates various pains for us, empties us when it fills, fills us when it empties.
And all these things are empty and void, in which there is no solid fruit.
The rich man died, and he has nothing; because he is not rich toward God: and therefore foolish, because wisdom is the worship of God, and abstaining from evil is discipline.
Who then would not flee from the place of wickedness, the workshop of depravity, which knows not how to perish?
Finally, the mark placed on Cain was not for nothing; it ensured that no one would kill him, signifying that wickedness should not be entirely extinguished from the earth.
Cain was afraid of being killed because he didn't know how to flee.
Wickedness grows and accumulates with use, knowing no moderation or end, acting through deceit and fraud, as shown by its actions and the blood of the slain, just as Cain was exposed.
Thus, wickedness roams the earth and wanders here; and so we pray for God's will to be done on earth as it is in heaven (Matthew 6:10), so that innocence may also be here.
Since wickedness no longer has a place there, it moves around here, rages here, and spills over, not drowned by the worldly flood, nor burned by the fire of Sodom.
It grew more severely later in the schools, even laying its murderous and sacrilegious hands on the very author of salvation.
The law condemns the act but does not remove wickedness.
The Lord Jesus himself condemned sin, but spared its author, so that the righteous might be tested through him.
For God did not create evil; the devil's malice planted it, and God delayed vengeance so that the devil might be defeated by those he had deceived (Confessions of Saint Augustine, Book IV against the two Pelagian letters, Chapter 11).
Therefore, those deceived are put to the test, to pay the price of their vulnerability and to take up the pursuit of virtue and the diligence of caution.
Hence he says: Be as shrewd as serpents (Matthew 10:16).
Why like serpents?
So that he may be stripped of his own, and he who wanted to strip others may lose what is his, not his venom, but the merits of his nature.
Finally, he is cast down when you ascend.
For it is written: I saw Satan fall like lightning from heaven (Luke 10:18).
It does not say lightning, but like lightning; because he lost his light, which he had before he wanted to take your light.
But perhaps you will say that we also read about the Savior that he will flash like lightning from under the sky.
.
so will be the coming of the Son of Man (Luke 17:24).
Well, here too like lightning, because it is above lightning.
For lightning is from under the sky; but the true light is above the sky.
Therefore, Satan fell like lightning because he lost what he had.
But you have regained what you had lost.
The judgment against him was not lifted as it was for you.
The grace of Christ that freed you, bound him.
The curse remains directly on the serpent because of your deception.
Thus it was said to him: Cursed are you above all livestock on the earth Genesis 3:14.
He is the common enemy of all, who was an enemy of good and is condemned for those he had not yet harmed.
Because he harmed man, to whom all things are subject, he harmed everything.
He broke the common law by which he himself was subject to man along with other creatures.
Therefore, his curse is burdened by the common hatred and execration of all.
The nature of his condemnation is not death but long-lasting punishment: You will crawl on your belly and eat dust all the days of your life Genesis 3:14.
A guilty conscience had to be pressed down, and malice crushed.
The deceitful secret had to be banished as if from the face of God.
At the same time, it shows that earthly malice bends down to the earth.
Finally, it added: You will eat dust all the days of your life Genesis 3:14.
Indeed, the nature of the serpent seems to be described by these words, but more so is every vessel of malice, every serpent of wickedness, that throws itself down to the belly, encloses its venom within, and rolls it inside its chest.
It is slippery in its thoughts, walking over its own frauds, entangling itself in its own deceit, always moving and agitating its venom when it thinks, trampling its belly, that is, the seedbed of its heart.
Hence, David beautifully said: The wicked are estranged from the womb; they go astray from birth, speaking lies.
Their venom is like the venom of a serpent, like a deaf adder that stops its ears, so that it does not hear the voice of charmers, or of the cunning enchanter Psalms 58:3-5.
Because of this, it also seems beautifully said what we read in the prophetic book: My belly, my belly, I writhe in pain Jeremiah 4:19.
Matthew 4:19.
Where there should be innocence, there is wickedness; and what should be peaceful within us is troubled, trampled by traces of wickedness, pricked by claws, and shaken by the spread of evil, where the fertile seedbed of eternal posterity lies.
This seems to refer to the fact that he grieved over losing the children he created and accepted, but even more so because he did not have the seed of the word in his heart.
Therefore, he calls his heart the most precious thing.
Indeed, the heart of the mind is precious, where the fertile crop of plans sprouts from the seed of the word, forming parts of all life, virtues, and disciplines.
Returning to the point, God thought malice should be restrained for the time being, rather than abolished.
He said to the serpent: "And I will put enmity between you and the woman, and between your offspring and hers; she will crush your head, and you will strike her heel" (Genesis 3:15).
Where there is enmity, there is discord and the desire to harm; where there is the desire to harm, there is malice.
Therefore, discord between the serpent and the woman has malice at its root.
Malice was not removed.
The serpent was allowed to observe the heel of the woman and her offspring, to harm them and inject his venom.
Therefore, let us not walk in earthly things, so the serpent cannot harm us.
Let us take up the Gospel footwear, which excludes the serpent's venom and dulls his bite, fitting our feet with the readiness of the Gospel.
Perhaps that is why Moses was ordered to remove his sandals, to take the sandals of the Gospel; or because the preaching of the Gospel was owed not to Moses, that is, not to the prophets, but to the apostles.
This is the sentence we mentioned above, spoken against the serpent.
Let us consider what kind of sentence was directed against man.
Cursed is the author of sin; but he who was deceived by another's fraud is not cursed.
Yet because he did not keep God's command, he is condemned to the toil of his works.
The earth is cursed because of the works of the sinner (Genesis 3:17) and remains cursed until it returns to the ground.
This is why Jesus took on human flesh: to remove the curse of sinful flesh.
He became a curse for us so that blessing could overcome the curse, purity could conquer sin, mercy could replace judgment, and life could defeat death.
He even accepted death to fulfill God's judgment, which was that sinful flesh would be cursed until death.
Therefore, nothing happened against God's judgment because the divine decision was carried out.
The curse lasted until death, but after death, there is grace.
So, since we are dead to the world, why do we still concern ourselves with worldly matters?
We are dead with Christ, so why do we still seek the actions of this life?
We carry the death of Christ in our bodies so that the life of Christ may also be revealed in us.
Therefore, we no longer live our old lives, but instead live the life of Christ—a life of innocence, chastity, simplicity, and all virtues.
Since we have risen with Christ, let us live in Him, ascend with Him, so that the serpent (symbolizing evil) cannot find our heel to strike on earth.
Chapter Eight
Though our bodies are here, we can and should let our spirits flee so we do not vanish with the transient world and its deeds.
To avoid this, let's adhere to God's commandments and strive in any discipline, just as many holy ones have done in the past.
Let us flee from here in spirit, even if our bodies remain.
We can be here physically but present with the Lord if our souls cling to Him, if we follow Him in our thoughts, if we walk by faith and not by sight, and if we seek refuge in Him.
For He is our refuge and strength, as David says: "I took refuge in You, and I was not deceived"
(Psalm 76:3).
Therefore, because God is our refuge, and He is in heaven and above, we must flee from here to there, where there is peace and rest from our labors, celebrating the great Sabbath, as Moses said: "And the Sabbaths of the land will be food for you"
(Leviticus 25:6).
It is a joyous banquet to rest in Christ and experience His delight.
So, will we who flee to God return to the world?
Will we who have died to sin repeat our sins?
Will we who have renounced the world cling to its filth again?
Let us flee from here, for the time is short.
Listen to how you should flee:
"Those who have wives should be as though they have none; those who weep, as though they do not weep; those who rejoice, as though they do not rejoice; those who buy, as though they do not possess; and those who use this world, as though they do not use it. For the form of this world is passing away"
(First Corinthians 7:29 and following).
Therefore, let not our deeds vanish with this fleeting world, lest we also pass away; let us remain in truth.
If we remain in Christ, we stay in truth, we will be with Him and not pass away, and we will say:
"The blessing of the Lord be upon you; we bless you in the name of the Lord"
(Psalm 128:8).
Those who pass away cannot say this because they did not say it while passing by:
"The blessing of the Lord be upon you," as the Prophet said.
So, if we want our works to last, we must not neglect God's commandments, the diligence in seeking Jesus our Lord, nor earning His grace.
That woman did not neglect Him when she entered the Pharisee's house, where Christ was reclining, and poured perfume on His feet.
We must not neglect progress in any discipline, just as young Joseph did not neglect his duty.
He sought his brothers and hurried to the place where they were grazing their sheep.
When he learned they were in Dothan, he went there.
The word "Dothan" signifies a significant decline, meaning a complete and substantial decline of false opinions, which leads to the progress of the soul. For a wise person, when they diminish something, they add to it. Secular opinions, compared to weak women, decline. Thus, it is beautifully shown that Sarah reached maturity to bring forth joy and happiness. She said, "Sarah was past the age of childbearing" Genesis 18:11. Therefore, the decline of desires and vanity is good because it is an addition of truth. Thus, the holy David said, "My soul faints with longing for your salvation" Psalm 119:81. She who had conceded and promised to God was about to give birth to joy and a sober kind of joyful intoxication, giving birth unexpectedly through the swiftness of her mind, the offspring of wisdom. Finally, you also have it written about other Hebrew women that they give birth before the midwives arrive Exodus 1:19, because the souls of the righteous do not wait for arts and disciplines for the sake of inventions, nor do they seek aids for childbirth, but they bring forth their offspring spontaneously, ahead of expectations.
Jacob was no less diligent in finding than in executing. When his mother told him to bring food to his father, we see that he had all the necessary definitions. He quickly found what he needed and testified that God was the author of his discoveries, signifying both the reward of diligence and the abundance of his ingenuity.
The first definition in discovery is this: what is found is sought, and what is sought involves time; what involves time surely requires diligence.
But what surpasses the use of time, God instills, God gives: what God gives pertains to nature, not to diligence.
Therefore, talent is a divine gift.
What is a divine gift pertains to nature.
So, talent is of nature, while discovery is of diligence: the former is without time, the latter needs time.
Consequently, the former is present in time, the latter is investigated in the span of time: the former is above us, the latter relates to us.
To one seeking the food of the word (for man does not live by bread alone, but by every word of God: Isaac was seeking such food, Peter was hungry for such food when he saw the mysteries of the Gentile people who would believe), Esau did not have the food of spiritual and swift talent ready.
While he was hunting and seeking, and preparing to present a very harsh and wild speech, Jacob anticipated with a quick discovery, and with a gentle and almost familiar reply, offering a sweet word to soothe and delight him.
Wherefore the astonished father said: "What is this, that you have found so quickly, my son?" Jacob answered: "Because the Lord your God brought it to me" (Genesis 27:20).
The first definition is in the question, the second in the answer.
Thus finding everything complete, whether of talent or diligence, the father concluded with a definition saying: "See, the smell of my son is like the smell of a field which the Lord has blessed" (Genesis 27:27).
For the field has both the natural talent of fertility and the temporal diligence of cultivation, and rightly in it is fullness, to which nothing is lacking.
When he added: "Which the Lord has blessed," he seems to have preferred the grace of nature to the labor of cultivation. And Esau confirmed it, saying: "Rightly is his name called Jacob. For he has supplanted me these two times, and he has taken my birthright" (Genesis 27:36).
But perhaps you might say: In what did he delay, who was sent by his father to hunt?
But consider that even the father declared he couldn't have it ready because it was asked for spiritually.
Since he lacked the intelligence or means to provide it, he demanded assistance.
He also reminds us of speed, saying: Take the bow and arrow.
Second Kings 13:18.
However, he received the fruit of diligence, recognizing that the gift of intelligence is 438.
And rightly, he brought domestic food, having acquired wisdom from the domestic seed for himself.
Diligence combined with wisdom is beneficial, as is invention with natural talent.
Finally, the holy Isaac, having wisdom in abundance, was walking in the field, or rather, he was being distracted.
We should first join wisdom and then go out into the field with the desire to seek and find.
Many seek poorly without wisdom.
Therefore, Cain, who had not received prudence from God, sought poorly and went out into the field poorly; whereas Abel, who completed the perfect gift of sacrifice, did well.
The sacrifice of wisdom is good, faith is a good offering, and every virtue.
Finally, wisdom killed her victims and mixed her wine in the bowl.
To give the drink of faith to the foolish Gentiles, she called them to her bowl saying: Whoever is foolish, let him turn to me.
Proverbs 9:4.
And to those lacking sense, she said: Come, eat of my bread, and drink the wine I have mixed for you.
Proverbs 9:5.
Plato thought this bowl should be transferred into his books, calling souls to its drink, but he did not know how to fill them, offering not the drink of faith, but of treachery.
Chapter Nine
He urges us to flee from here, just as Jacob fled from his homeland, and like deer to springs; those who long for these springs must pour out their souls over themselves, following Susanna's example.
Just as Paul and Lot fled, we too must flee to the heavenly city until the high priest dies: with whom our old self must also die.
Let us flee from here just as Saint Jacob fled from his homeland.
For he knew that the true homeland was above.
Let us flee like deer to the springs of water, which David thirsted for, and our souls should thirst for too.
What is that spring?
Listen to what is said: "For with You is the fountain of life" Psalm 36:9. To this fountain, let the soul say: "When shall I come and appear before Your presence?" Psalm 42:2. For God is the fountain, but whoever desires this fountain must pour out their soul over themselves; leaving nothing to the desires of the flesh, but letting the soul overflow everywhere.
Susanna beautifully poured out her soul, so that the fires of the body, the fears of death, and the desires of life could not evaporate in her. The soul poured out over her extinguished all carnal desire and worldly ambition. She was even able to extinguish the flames of the wicked elders and shameless priests, except that in them the flood of lust overflowed. When they accused her, if she denied their adulterous demands, Susanna groaned and said: "I am trapped on every side. For if I do this, I will perish eternally: but if I do not, I will not escape your hands" Daniel 13:22. However, she judged it better to flee from the crime rather than the danger. So she wept when the crime was accused of her: she wept when the judgment of an adulteress was vindicated against her, not mourning death, but the slander against her chastity. She wept for the injury to her religion and poured out over herself not her body, but her soul. For she would have poured out her body, if she had yielded to carnal desires. Finally, when she was condemned to death, she cried out like a judge of the guilty, an arbiter of the slanderers; and with the authority of her innocent conscience, she called upon divine judgment to witness, not driven by the fear of death, but by the high power of a rebuking conscience.
Susanna fled from the world and dedicated herself to God, finding refuge in the eternal city that encompasses everything, because all things exist within God.
Paul also escaped by being lowered through a window in a basket, knowing that a triple-braided cord is not easily broken.
He fled to spread the Gospel of the Lord throughout the world, and thus, he was taken up into paradise.
Let us also escape through the window by listening to the Lord's commandments, keeping a clear vision, and preserving the purity of our eyes.
Let us flee like Lot, fearing the sins of Sodom more than its punishments.
A truly pious person avoids the contamination of sins, just as Lot closed his home to the Sodomites.
He did not live with them, did not know their crimes, and shunned their disgrace.
He did not look back at those whose ways of life he did not desire.
Therefore, flee like Lot, who renounces vices, rejects the behaviors of the inhabitants, does not look back, and enters that higher city with the entrance of his thoughts, not leaving it until the High Priest, who took away the sin of the world, dies.
He died once, but he dies for each person who is baptized into the death of Christ; so that we are buried with him, rise with him, and walk in the newness of his life.
You flee well if your heart does not follow the plans and thoughts of sinners.
You flee well if your eyes avoid cups and flasks, so as not to become lustful while lingering over wine.
You flee well if your eyes turn away from what is not yours, so your tongue can keep the truth.
You flee well if you do not respond foolishly to a fool.
You flee well if you avoid the path of the foolish.
It is easy to go astray with bad leaders; but if you want to flee well, keep your ways far from their words.
The High Priest died for you, he was crucified for you, so cling to his nails.
He took on your flesh and your sins: the records of your offenses are nailed to the cross; so you no longer owe anything to the world, which you have renounced once and for all.
And rightly, you owe nothing, for you can say:
For the world is crucified to me, and I to the world
Galatians six fourteen.
So you no longer fear death if you bear Christ, in whom you can say:
Where, death, is your victory?
Where, death, is your sting
First Corinthians fifteen fifty-five?
For when our old self was nailed to the cross, sin was destroyed, the sting was dulled, and guilt was emptied;
so that we may no longer serve wickedness.
For the old self has passed away.
Now, however, it is not the old self in us: but a new creation, having within it the likeness of Christ,
whose death we have been buried with, and we have taken on the likeness of his life, receiving the wings of spiritual grace.
So fly in such a way that it is said of you:
Who are these who fly like clouds, and like doves with their young
Isaiah sixty eight?
Let your clouds rain righteousness, and let the doves bring forth simplicity.
Sail in such a way as to cross the world, not wandering, like the ships of Tarshish;
so that you may direct your course to the intelligent harbors, and bring the wealth of the sea.
Hurry in such a way that it is said of you:
They have become swifter than eagles
Lamentations four nineteen.
For you see that you must flee from the coming wrath, which those who place their hope in repentance and have drawn faith in future reconciliation through our Lord Jesus Christ will be able to avoid,
to whom is the kingdom from ages past, and now, and always, and forever and ever.
Amen.