Book One
Prologue
As Solomon says, it's a person's job to prepare their mind, and the Lord's to guide their tongue, because all human ways are visible to His eyes, and the Lord weighs the spirits.
Proverbs 16.
But that's not the case, my friend, not with those who create scandals.
They use the tools of hatred and envy, or favor and flattery, to craft deceitful scales, weighing one against the other without caring for balance.
They judge wickedly and flatter improperly, being slaves to error, knowingly calling evil good and good evil.
Truly, hatred knows no reason, and envy lacks fairness.
I foolishly noticed this in a close companion who loved some people deeply, thinking they were friends because of their loyalty, only to find out they were enemies through their betrayal.
While he served his brothers with effort, loyalty, and a troubled spirit, as known by the Lord of Hosts, who judges calmly and arranges us with great reverence, this poor man's brothers hated him for no reason, and even friends withdrew from him.
He became a spectacle to many, as he couldn't detect the hidden malice of those who say or do nothing without prompting.
Therefore, it's more reliable to trust in the Lord than in humans.
Indeed, trust is fickle in many, and the friendship of some often suffers a sudden eclipse.
Why do you complain as if these things are unusual, brother?
The hatred and envy of brothers couldn't have been calmed unless Joseph was sold to the Ishmaelites or Potiphar after being thrown into the cistern; nor would the persecution of the envious have ended unless Daniel was thrown into the lions' den.
Malice constantly wages war against innocence.
However, the vices of a senseless mind are wounds.
The more the vice is fulfilled, the greater the trouble grows.
Therefore, the malevolent person harms themselves more than others.
You strongly advised me against attacking those who look down on foolishness.
Instead, you urged me to frequently and urgently offer counsel, so I might recognize and understand the limitations of my own intellect.
So, let our rivals savor their own bitterness, while patience brings its own rewards to us.
It's human to get angry, but it's devilish to hold onto malice.
The things I have written so far-why, when, and with what intention-are things the pen will explore.
Even though this might provoke envy towards me rather than be beneficial to you, it does no harm to anyone with good intentions.
It seems fitting to first acknowledge the valuable writings by the brothers of our Church, especially those skilled in literature, because it's wiser to praise the works of others than our own.
Chapter One
About Lambert, the Second Abbot.
Lambert, our second abbot, was incredibly useful in many respects.
He authored the Life of Saint Heribert, the Archbishop of Cologne, and meticulously documented his miracles.
He also composed music about him, drawing on his remarkable talent for writing verses.
Chapter Two
About Stephen, the First Abbot.
Stephen was the successor who, despite leaving no written records, deserves to be remembered.
He was well-known for his knowledge, but even more so for his exemplary conduct, proving himself to be a worthy leader.
The resources of the young Church were still limited, so he made every effort to acquire land and construct buildings.
By living modestly, he sacrificed his own comforts to benefit others.
He managed his expenses according to the limited resources available.
It was better to have a little with righteousness than an abundance from sinners.
He would sometimes joke with his companions about Vitellius, the most gluttonous Roman emperor, who would feast four or five times a day.
If the Republic hadn't ended his life in time, he would have depleted the air of birds, the sea of fish, the land of animals, the granaries of grain, and the cellars of wine.
Indeed, it's said that at one feast, besides other expenses, he consumed two thousand fish and seven thousand birds, making him as gluttonous as Belshazzar of Babylon.
For that very indulgent guest, each night twelve bushels of fine flour, forty sheep, and six amphorae of wine were provided to satisfy his seemingly endless appetite.
But Stephen, through his actions and teachings, after fighting the good fight, received the crown he had sought by name.
He was a man worthy of divine revelations, especially when an angel of the Lord appeared to him in a vision as he grieved over his brothers' poverty.
The angel, with a radiant face and noble robe, told him that Saints Lawrence and Wolbodo had placed this site under Christ's protection, and its foundations were set in the holy mountains.
Moreover, the inhabitants, if they first sought the kingdom of God, would have all necessary things added to them.
This is a truth he experienced then, and we continue to experience now, thanks to the generosity of Christ, the wisdom of God, with whom there are riches and glory, abundant wealth, and righteousness.
Chapter Three
About Saint Wolbodo, Bishop of Liege.
Since there is no one who lacks glory everywhere, I will briefly share who Wolbodo was.
He came from Flemish origins, and his noble and wealthy parents were made even more distinguished by his remarkable life and knowledge.
He began as a canon and schoolmaster at the church in Utrecht before becoming the bishop of Liege.
Some of our elders have written about his life as a bishop.
It's important to note his deep devotion to Saint Lawrence the martyr, as he dedicated his care and resources to our place during his life and was laid to rest here after his death.
Indeed, he was buried in our crypt of the Holy Mother of God, in a carefully crafted tomb, which includes this epitaph in gilded letters:
Great is the honor of the flesh, but greater is the grace of character,
Placing you in the office and seat of the bishop.
The rich and poor alike felt your presence in all things,
From you comes salvation to some, food to others.
Hence, the same flesh is present to all of us,
And we honor the life-giving tomb.
Thus, the small garden of our Church flourishes with the dual beauty of the rose and lily, as both the martyr with part of his relics and the confessor with his whole body, enhance it with their protection and merits.
Chapter Four
About Everard the Third, Abbot of Saint Laurence.
The third pastor chosen by Stephen was Everard, a monk from the Church of Florennes.
He was a man rich in experience, whose virtues created a peaceful presence.
He tended the Lord's flock with a pure heart and guided it with wisdom.
However, his time was short.
He passed away before even a year had gone by.
Yet, the bright intentions and care he displayed were already taking root and should not be forgotten.
So, let him be remembered as if he had served a full year.
And with the righteous, may he inherit a place where life is long and fulfilling, where there is light and peace.
Chapter Five
Concerning the elder monk and Deacon Louis.
The elder Louis, fondly remembered, had previously documented the journey of Saint Lawrence's relics from Rome to us.
Chapter Six
About Falchalino, a student of Ludovicus.
Falchalinus, who was also a master of schools, had become well-established in his teachings.
He worked with Franconius, the scholar of Saint Lambert, on projects about the squaring of the circle and the fasts of the Four Seasons.
Chapter Seven
About Heribrand, the fifth abbot, a follower of Louis the Second.
Heribrand, our fifth abbot, was a devoted follower of his.
In him, the wisdom of his mind matched the grayness of his hair.
Ecclesiastes chapter nine suggests that his clothes were always white, representing chastity girding his loins, and the lamp in his hands symbolized his love for God and his neighbor burning brightly.
He was highly skilled at composing both prose and poetry, well-versed in divine and human literature.
He wrote the Life of Theodoric the Younger, the abbot of Saint Hubert.
He didn't hide his wealth of knowledge but willingly taught those who were uninformed, always maintaining a calm demeanor in both mind and voice.
What is said gently by the teacher is better understood by the learner.
Minds should be engaged by skill rather than force.
Chapter Eight
About David the Monk
David was a diligent worker who carried the light and easy burden of Christ's yoke into his old age.
He dedicated himself to church duties day and night.
He spent his time praying, reading, and writing the works of learned men for his brothers to read and reflect upon.
These are the defenses of David's tower, adorned with a thousand shields, the complete armor of the mighty.
Despite the fierceness of Phalaris's brazen, fiery bulls, the envy of the Sicilian tyrant found no greater torment than what our Methuselah endured, as he earnestly admonished the negligent and guided the youth to avoid the bread of idleness.
Though bent with age, David remained unwavering in kindness; his tireless efforts bore fruit, and he wrote the Passion of Saint Blaise and the Life of Saint Eucherius of Orleans.
Even if his work wasn't finely crafted, it began with a coarser, hemp-like thread.
Chapter Nine
About the Monk Engelbert.
Engelbert, a diligent examiner and follower of calculations, compiled several useful theorems for mathematicians.
Much like Bootes in the celestial sphere, while constantly engaged in this art, he keeps the chariot of memory continuously revolving without letting it rest.
Through this dedication, he gained significant knowledge.
Thus, I honor him with these verses from Virgil:
He who knows the numbers and paths of the sky, who understands the stars, the various eclipses of the sun, and the phases of the moon.
Why the earth trembles, by what force the deep seas swell when barriers are broken, and then settle back again.
Why the suns in winter rush so eagerly to plunge into the ocean, or what delay causes the long nights.
Chapter Ten
About Berenger, the fourth abbot.
During this time, scholarly pursuits were thriving among the monks and clerics of our city, flourishing just as much as religious devotion, perfectly complementing the state of the churches.
"How beautiful are your tents, Jacob, and your tabernacles, Israel, like wooded valleys, like gardens by the rivers, like tabernacles set up by the Lord, like cedars by the waters" (Numbers 24).
Liege was rich in virtues, disciplines, and wealth.
However, being well-educated was considered more admirable than being wealthy.
And since blessed is the land whose king is noble, our Church at that time aspired to the studies of true happiness, with Berenger, the fourth abbot, who was more noble in spirit than in flesh, presiding.
Although he was of humble birth, as a wise person once said, the eye of God looked upon him favorably; He lifted him from his humility and exalted his head, and many were amazed by him.
Indeed, he was renowned for his wisdom, like a lamp on a candlestick, notable in both the kingdom and the Church.
Nevertheless, the brothers who lived under him could be compared to lilies by the water, as many of them possessed both the purity of religion and the fragrance of a good reputation, enriched with literary knowledge.
Chapter Eleven
This chapter is about Robert, also known as Rupert, who later became the abbot of Tuitium.
Among these individuals, Robert stood out like a golden earring or a shining pearl.
He was a man who paid attention to wisdom, listened to prudence, sought it like money, and dug for it like treasures.
Raised from childhood in our monastery, he grew in virtues as he aged, and as his memory strengthened, so did his intellect, adding knowledge and labor.
Everything he absorbed through reading, he shared through teaching, remaining diligent in prayer and contemplation, especially during morning vigils.
The more privately he engaged in these practices, the more devoted he became.
His heart warmed within him, and during meditation, a fire burned.
Tears were present; he offered them as a sweet fragrance to the Lord, for whom nothing is sweeter than a contrite spirit and a broken, humbled heart.
As a result, he frequently experienced divine illumination, and clear understanding blossomed in him.
As it is written, he who seeks goodness rises well at dawn.
The Wisdom of God opened his mind to understand the Scriptures, allowing him to discuss them with great ability and usefulness.
His works clearly reflect this, untouched by envy or ignorance.
While still young, he wrote a book in verse praising the Holy Spirit, progressing more by inspiration than by any teacher's instruction.
He also wrote another on various Scripture teachings, and a third in heroic verse concerning the Incarnation of the Lord.
Additionally, he discussed the condition of our Church in one book, detailing by whom it was established and what good or evil it received from the Lord, from Euraclus, bishop of the Leodians, to Obertus.
He also crafted another work on the same subject in Sapphic meter.
Finally, he enhanced the lives of Saint Augustine and Saint Odilia the virgin with a radiant style.
He composed songs about the saints Theodard the martyr, and Goar and Severus the confessors.
After becoming a priest, he truly delved into the deepest matters of the heart, focusing all his intention and mind towards the true south.
He wrote twelve booklets about the divine offices or sacraments celebrated in the Church throughout the year.
Then he composed fourteen booklets on the Gospel of John.
He authored forty-two books on the Holy Trinity and its works, where you can find all the fruits of the Scriptures, both new and old, which the Church treasures for its followers.
At the request of Frederick, the Archbishop of Cologne, he thoroughly explained the Apocalypse in twelve books and also covered the twelve Prophets in thirty-one books.
He wrote thirteen books on the victory of the Word of God and thirteen books on the Gospel of Matthew.
In his second-to-last book, he describes how wonderfully and gloriously he received the grace of writing from the Father of lights.
Cuno, the abbot of Siegburg, insisted he document this, having urged him-despite his initial reluctance-by invoking the awe-inspiring name of the Holy Trinity.
He took great joy in this divine gift, which a kind-hearted overseer encouraged him to use eagerly.
He often found delight in his conversations or writings about the Scriptures as if they were treasures.
His devotion to the study of holy readings was matched by excellent morals and piety, leading to his later appointment as the bishop of Regensburg.
Moreover, Robert himself had already become the prelate of the Church, having succeeded the late abbot of Thuit.
Though busy with that ministry and, like Martha, occasionally troubled by many concerns, he diligently focused on the one thing necessary, like Mary.
He sat at the Lord's feet, listening to His word, while engaging in holy meditation and the study of writing.
He maintained such a commendable habit that if he ever felt a lesser grace upon him-since the body's burdens can weigh down the soul, and earthly concerns can press on the mind, especially with external distractions.
As he humbled himself before the crucified Lord, he sought guidance from the holy and true one, who holds the key of David, who opens doors that no one can shut and shuts doors that no one can open (Revelation 3:7), to open what was closed.
To the one who humbly sought and faithfully knocked, the door was soon opened.
Light wondrously illuminated his understanding, allowing him to hear what the Lord God spoke within him.
His tongue was like the pen of a swift writer, and those who came to learn from him received his teachings.
He enriched himself so diligently and filled his heart's treasury so greatly that two or three writers could barely manage to transcribe what he dictated.
This was not surprising, as he had once seen in a night vision the Wisdom of God, the Word of God, kissing him.
His entire body seemed to be made of the purest gold, with numerous pipes pouring forth living waters into him with force.
As the Psalmist says, "The unfolding of your words gives light; it imparts understanding to the simple" (Psalm 119:130), meaning the humble, who are enriched with the knowledge of high secrets, meant only for friends, and are abundantly nourished.
Just as Wisdom itself says: "I poured out rivers, I am like a water channel of immense waters from a river; I am like the river Dorix, and like a water conduit I came out of paradise. I said, I will water my garden of plantations, and I will drench the fruit of my birth, and my channel became abundant, and my river approached the sea, for I illuminate my teaching like the dawn for everyone, and I will proclaim it to distant places" (Sirach 24:30-33).
Thus, Robert also wrote seven books on the Song of Songs, fifteen books on Samuel or David, and nine books on the glorification of the Trinity and the procession of the Holy Spirit.
He also wrote a five-book series titled "Ring," which features a debate on faith between a Christian and a Jew.
Additionally, he published four books on certain chapters of the Rule of Saint Benedict. In the first book, he describes the many attacks from envious people and the troubles he faced from those who falsely accused him of heresy and misinterpreting the Holy Scriptures.
When he was young, he wrote an apologetic book on the will of God addressed to Anselm of Laon, a scholar, and William of Chalons, a renowned bishop in France at the time. In this book, he argued against those who, following the Colitiani heresy, claimed that God willed evil to be done-not the evil of affliction, which is sometimes necessary for correcting sinners, but any evil that contradicts goodness and virtue.
He also published several writings against his accusers or some irreligious people. One was a priest, or rather a concubinary, who claimed with pamphlets that priests could freely use concubines, even when they were menstruating. Another was a cleric who had become a monk, or rather a raven turned from a dove, who defended his error with wicked arguments and preferred to drift and be in danger in the world rather than find rest and salvation in Christ, the true Noah, within the ark of the monastery.
Moreover, a severe fire engulfed and consumed the surrounding workshops of the Abbey of Tuit. Flames raged fiercely, and the abbey itself would have been in danger if divine mercy had not intervened. As some witnessed, a person of celestial brightness stood above, fanning away the rising fireballs with the edge of their garment as if with a fan. The flames retreated, and the house emerged unscathed, undoubtedly fulfilling what the prophet says to the Lord: "In your wrath, you will remember mercy" from the book of Habakkuk, chapter three.
However, the parish church was consumed by the fire. Yet there, too, the right hand of Christ was gloriously magnified.
During a massive fire that was so intense it melted the church bells, the wooden cabinet housing the Lord's body, sealed in a box, remained untouched by the flames.
The Holy of Holies protected His sacred body, whose flesh rested in hope and whose soul was not left in hell, ensuring it would not see decay.
Additionally, the altar cloth, which one of the brothers had extended on a long pole, fell right into the flames.
Yet, when it seemed it would burn, it miraculously sprang back, hovered in the air, moved away from the fire, and landed on the ground intact.
This miracle was akin to when the three young men were in the Babylonian furnace, unharmed by the tyrant, as not a hair on their heads was singed, nor were their clothes altered, and the smell of fire did not pass over them.
Robert recorded these events for perpetual memory in a book filled with gold and deep reflection, titled "On the Fire," which also included a section "On the Meditation of Death."
After completing part of it, that celestial philosopher, oh, that divine partner of eloquence, passed away full of days, just as had been revealed to him earlier, as it is written in the Book of Job: "You will come to the grave in full vigor" (Job 5).
A fruitful olive tree in the house of God, oh, he withered suddenly in the fever's scorching heat.
Robert, equal in knowledge and virtues to the greatest teachers, was placed among the saints, where he may enjoy the ever-flourishing oil of true peace and joy, and the light of the divine, as it is written: "Those who are wise will shine like the brightness of the sky, and those who lead many to righteousness, like the stars forever and ever" (Daniel 12:5).
Chapter Twelve
About Wazelin, or Waselin the Second, the seventh abbot of Saint Laurence.
Our abbot, Wazelin the Seventh, was taught by such an illustrious figure that, having absorbed the seeds of knowledge well, he produced good fruits of virtue.
He was gentle like a dove but wise like a serpent.
As a result, he earned grace and discipline in the eyes of both God and people.
While he adorned his knowledge with the gold of religion, he became renowned, like incense spreading fragrance on warm summer days.
His mastery is evident in the book he wrote, On the Harmony of the Gospels and Their Interpretation, a work both notable and useful, which any diligent reader regrets was left unfinished.
This mastery is also reflected in the paintings or curtains of certain churches, where one can see and understand the clear and unique harmony of allegorical subjects from both the Old and New Testament as arranged by him.
He devoted himself to Saint Nicholas, revising and refining some old writings about his life or miracles.
He composed solemn chants on the Transfiguration of the Lord, the saints of Agaunum, and Saint Apollinaris the martyr.
Moreover, through his efforts, the oratory of Saint George the martyr was built by us with such devotion and care, with such piety and appropriateness, that it deserved to become a place of marvelous worship, transitioning through the patronage of the saints to the house of God.
Placed over the Lord's household, he provided them with a measure of wheat at the right time, for he was endowed with discernment and was eloquent and gentle, making him well-suited to either advise or correct both publicly and privately.
By this time, he had grown old.
His long service to Christ had taken its toll, and illness had worn him down at times.
Yet, with unwavering dedication to reading, prayers, and contemplation, and with his soul's eyes fixed on the true sun, he was, in a remarkable way, rejuvenating with a newness like that of the phoenix.
The story goes that the phoenix, after living more than 500 years, builds a nest of aromatic twigs.
With the flapping of its wings and the fiery ray of the sun, it sets itself on fire.
But after three days, it rises from its own ashes, once again a youthful bird, a unique and singular example.
This is why it is fittingly called phoenice in the language of the Arabs, meaning "unique," because of its rare color or because it is singular in the whole world.
Although these qualities might somewhat apply to Wazelin, they most fittingly apply to you, O Jesus Christ, the unique and singular phoenix. These qualities, I say, are particularly ascribed to you, O Isaac, the only begotten, who are the joy and love of the saints. Anointed with the aromas of all grace, you offered yourself to God on the wood of the cross through the love of the Holy Spirit. Yet, with a unique newness and unparalleled youthfulness, you blossomed again immortally from the tomb after three days, now alive once more.
Chapter Thirteen
Wazelinus the First, abbot of Saint Lawrence by this name.
Another Wazelinus had come before him at the abbey.
Although simple by nature, he diligently performed his church duties from youth to old age with a true zeal for religion.
Sometimes he read, other times he sang psalms, and often he prayed, like a strong ox tirelessly threshing on the Lord's threshing floor.
He was gentle and approachable, much like the holy Moses, in contrast to Nabal the Carmelite, who was as stubborn as a camel, never speaking directly or peacefully.
Let those who are diligent remember Wazelinus.
Wazelinus cared for the diligent like a father.
Free from the bitterness of envy, he would often sweetly say:
"Lord, I have loved the beauty of your house" Psalm 26.
Chapter Fourteen
About the Monk Lambert. Lambert explained the fables of Aesop.
He skillfully used these stories to influence human behavior as the original author intended.
However, our commentator ignored the moral lessons and focused unwisely on allegory, trying to make something sacred out of them, as if one could gather figs from thorns or grapes from brambles.
So, on the first of March, that book was read in the mouse senate, debated, rejected, and received harsh criticism.
Then mice rushed in from the fields and the Palestinian villages, attacked with fierce teeth, gnawed, and scattered the written points.
But what hope did we have of recovery?
We lacked the famous treasures of the Philistines, who could offer golden mice for their vows, and we didn't even have parchment.
Pergamum, the first to give its name to parchments in both use and abundance, was too hard and difficult for us to reach.
Thus, that Aesopian sacrament was lost.
Chapter Fifteen
About Gislebert the Monk.
Gislebert honed his sharp and clear mind through continuous practice, always keeping himself engaged by either thinking or writing.
He crafted the Story of Joseph in heroic verse, compiling it into a single book, and divided the Deeds of David into twelve parts using the same meter.
His writing style is straightforward and easy to understand, yet praiseworthy because, as he said in his own verses, achieving simplicity is often a difficult task:
"I composed poems and completed them with joyful effort, setting a challenging rule for myself: to carefully render word for word. Indeed, it is a task worthy of much praise, an excellent endeavor to move from plain speech, from humble prose to lively verse, and to follow a broad path, so that anyone might aspire to do the same, sweat a lot, and work in vain."
His works possess a unique charm, especially when he embellishes historical narratives with the mystical elements of allegory. Although he excelled in various arts, he was particularly adept at creating sweet melodies in music, as demonstrated in the songs he composed about Saint George the martyr, Saint Ragenufla the virgin, and Saint Begga.
Chapter Sixteen
About John the monk, brother of Gislebert.
John, both spiritually and physically a brother to Gislebert, was a scholar in both learning and duty.
As a boy, I often felt his discipline, much like no one ever wielded the club of Hercules more.
Oh, how many times, while he examined or critiqued our small works, did he look at the tablets in his hooked hands with a sidelong glance!
Oh, how many times I felt as though I had run into him as if he were the one-eyed Polyphemus from Virgil!
When he was once ill, in a rather miraculous way, he seemed to transcend himself and saw many memorable things.
He documented these experiences in writing for the purpose of edification.
He also composed two songs, one about Saint Christopher the martyr, and another about Saint Mary of Egypt.
He went through the story of Tobit and the Martyrdom of Saint Stephen, the first martyr, in heroic meter, and sang parts of the Song of Songs in an antiphonal style.
Chapter Seventeen
About the Monk Nizon.
Let's not forget about Nizon, who became a persistent example of the nature of learning.
Although he had a slow and almost turtle-like mind, he sharpened it through practice, and with constant meditation and reading, he reached the heights of polished advancement, almost as if he had grown wings.
He composed notable melodies about the holy martyrs John and Paul, Saints Nazarius and Celsus, and Lord Frederick, the Bishop of Liege, about whom he also wrote a booklet detailing his deeds, death, or miracles.
He was a simple man who could be deceived but did not know how to deceive others.
As a result, when we were young boys learning from him, we could easily provoke him and avoid his anger, almost as if dodging the strikes of someone who was off balance.
Chapter Eighteen
About Others Not Named Specifically.
We have specifically mentioned those brothers we found to have written something.
There were also many others commendable for both their knowledge and their faith, whose memory is both sweet and useful.
However, we have not written more about them at this time.
We earnestly wish for, and implore you, O Christ, who counts the multitude of stars and calls them all by name, who is the most knowledgeable of the saints, that you may write upon them the name of your God, and the name of the city of New Jerusalem, which descends from heaven from your God, and your new name, so that you may give them, I say, a white stone, and on the stone a new name written, which no one knows except the one who receives it.
Book Two
Chapter One
About Reiner's Early Works.
Just as I've briefly mentioned the studies or works of those who have long since passed, I wanted, dear brother, to recount the talents or writings of our brothers who are still with us.
However, I'm held back by two concerns: that I might be accused of envy if I don't sufficiently praise what deserves praise, or that I might be seen as flattering if I give deserving commendations.
Therefore, they will naturally become better known on their own and shine more brightly through their own merits, as others do not take offense at what rightfully earns appreciation.
For this reason, I'll satisfy your request, or rather your insistence, and reveal to you alone my foolishness.
As a young man, I wrote some laments in verse and rhythm about the troubles of the Church, driven by a desire to learn, and I tried, though I was a modest poet, to imitate the great poets in some way.
From this, I created a small work about the New and Old Testaments and divided it into two books.
I also called this work "Panther" because it was distinguished by a mix of prose and verse.
Moreover, I composed some writings about calculations at that time.
Finally, I wrote a prose booklet about the hanging of a certain thief.
I also wrote about the martyrdom of the seven Maccabean brothers in heroic verse.
Then, I expanded on that chapter about the Apostle: "Do you not know that those who run in a race all run, but only one receives the prize?" from First Corinthians Chapter 9 in a broader Asclepiadean meter.
However, some writings I now recall were secretly taken by a certain acquaintance of ours.
I didn't have copies, and what I feared happened-I was deprived of the first fruits of my labors.
For he went to another region for the sake of his conversion and took these spoils with him as a token of mutual love.
Chapter Two
The same melody about the saints and its fate.
While I was being trained in the art of music, I composed a melody about the saints Sixtus, Felicissimus, and Agapitus to make my study more fruitful.
Truly, talent grows through diligent practice, and the remarkable power of art is evident, as it often brings deep emotion and reflection to those with pious hearts through its sweetness.
However, some people barely noticed this when I was diligently practicing, attributing it to frivolity and mischief.
One of these individuals, who was supported by the authorities of a second priory, seized the tablets where I had inscribed my modest thoughts and examined them for a while.
Meanwhile, I was filled with fear, as the stern face and raised eyebrows of the man hinted at future trouble for me.
Oh, a judge harsher than Minos or Athamas!
He read, fumed, and sang from one part to another: then suddenly, as if deeply offended, he began to destroy the innocent tablets and obliterated what was written with a rival's nail.
What could I do?
Should I resist, shout, or hurl insults?
The birch rods in the chapter house, along with many accusers, reminded me greatly of the uproar of the Pharisees and Sadducees, which once put Paul in peril in the council.
Would a muttered curse help?
A curse clenched between my teeth would be of no use.
So what then?
I lowered my ears like a donkey carrying a heavy load, and with the patience of hypocrites, I became accustomed to disaster.
Should I commit my thoughts to the tablets again?
That fierce nail would threaten.
Should I mend them with parchment?
I pondered the altar and coals of King Jehoiakim and the knife of Judas the scribe, realizing I am neither Jeremiah nor do I have Baruch as my notary.
Thus, I gave up on my endeavor.
After a long time had passed, I began to reconsider if any remnants of the same song remained in my memory.
It was recovered so quickly, as if it had been noted down before my eyes, that I felt God does not disregard sincere prayers.
So, I committed to parchment what had been restored to memory.
I wasn't seeking idleness, which is the enemy of the soul, because staying busy felt much more rewarding.
In fact, I was inspired by that saying of Solomon:
"Do not love sleep, lest you become poor; open your eyes and you will be satisfied with bread"
(Proverbs 20).
I was also moved by this line from Horace:
"You do not wake up to preserve yourself; and yet, if you do not want to be healthy, you will run around like someone with dropsy: unless you ask for a book with light before dawn, if you do not focus your mind on studies and honest matters, you will be tortured by envy or love."
Chapter Three
Other Works of Reinerius.
I've described the conversion of Saint Pelagia in two books, titled: Mirror of Repentance.
Then, I detailed the Passion of the Virgin Mary of Cappadocia in another two books, calling them Virginal Triumph.
After that, I put together the Life of Theobald the Hermit in two books, which I named the Flower of the Desert.
Previously, these works were written in a rough style of dictation, but I refined them as best I could with some knowledge, following the advice of certain friends.
It's important to follow friends who offer pious guidance.
The deeds of the saints are seen as common material, and those engaged in pious studies shouldn't be noted for vanity.
Lastly, I composed a piece titled: A Little Book of Funeral Verses on the Death of a Friend, to which I added a quatrain to be inscribed on the tomb.
Chapter Four
Severe Illness of Reiner and Recovery by Divine Intervention.
Following this, a severe illness struck our community.
The intense fevers from the scorching summer confined many brothers to their beds, and some were even sent to their graves.
Our group was engulfed in mourning as we either fell ill or passed away, overcome by fear or grief.
Yet, to you, O vigilant and holy one, who neither slumbers nor sleeps, who guards Israel, to you, O kind Jesus, we are precious.
You watch over us and our actions every day, from morning to evening.
This was clearly shown to one of the brothers who, while participating in nighttime psalm singing and dozing off, was approached by a figure of heavenly beauty.
The figure gently tapped him and said:
"Why are you sleeping? Watch and pray, as written in the Gospel of Luke, Chapter 22: God has promised a crown to those who are vigilant."
He stayed awake and noticed that the figure, standing in the middle of the choir, indicated with a certain nod those who would soon pass away.
Then the figure ascended the steps of the sanctuary and disappeared.
I, a vessel of misery and weakness, mere clay and lowly mud, felt the rod of God's wrath watching over me, striking me down and reducing me almost to nothing.
Indeed, I fell ill to the point of death, and the Lord turned my entire bed in my sickness, filled me with bitterness, and made me drunk with wormwood.
The hope of living was driven away by signs of impending death.
For a week, without food or sleep, and with my brain nearly dried up by the burning fever, I was in danger, driven by hallucinations and speaking incoherently.
But the compassionate and diligent care of the brothers brought me to the knees of divine mercy and entrusted my lowly mortal remains to the one who holds the keys of death and the underworld, who was dead and did not see decay but now lives forever and ever.
Therefore, I was brought to the crypt of the holy Mother of God at the tomb of Bishop Wolbodon, whom I mentioned earlier.
There I lay down until nearly midnight.
The illness that had overtaken my small body was now reaching into the depths of my soul, locking my senses in a fatal grip.
Suddenly, I saw a holy figure, radiant with pure white hair and dressed in festive priestly attire, standing at the right side of my bed, making the sign of the cross over me three times.
I immediately felt the power of the blessing: sweat broke out across my limbs, and my tired eyes found sweet sleep.
My stomach, which had been rejecting food, now craved it after the fast.
Through the boundless compassion of the blessed Mother of God, with her remarkable grace, she presented the child hanging on the cross to be adored and kissed by the most unworthy; and through the intervention of the holy confessor, who blessed me to live, I was pulled back from the very jaws of death.
But what cries will my soul release, what tears will my eyes shed?
I tremble and fear that the delay of death might mean less correction for my life.
I know, Lord, that a person's path is not their own, nor do they have the strength to walk and direct their steps.
Therefore, correct me, but not in judgment, and not in your anger, lest you reduce me to nothing.
Knowing my frailty, strengthen me as you can, for without you, nothing is strong.
Chapter Five
Grateful Heart of Reiner Towards Heavenly Healers
A Vision of Divine Judgment.
After I regained my strength, I offered what little gifts I could, like a humble prayer to the merciful mother of spirit.
This prayer was rhythmically expressed and elaborated into a divine melody about the confessor himself.
Finally, I don't think it's pointless to share what one brother witnessed about another brother at that time.
One was dying, and the other was lying very ill.
Early one morning, while awake, he clearly saw in the same house a person of judicial authority seated at a tribunal.
Certain worthy men were advocating for the dying man, responding to accusations or objections from demons clamoring outside.
By some divine power, these demons were prevented from breaking in.
Their appearance was nothing short of hideous, and their envy and malice were revealed through their eyes with an almost sulfurous horror.
They surrounded the place like a siege.
As the soul finally departed and the judge withdrew with the blessed spirits, the demons followed with unbearable commotion and chaotic shouting.
It seemed as if the entire air was struggling with terrible storms.
Oh, what a tearful hour!
Oh, what a terrifying trial!
Oh, what a dreadfully compelling necessity!
How blessed is the one whose good conscience keeps him safe at that time!
Chapter Six
Various Works of Reinerius.
For a while, I stopped writing because I either enjoyed reading more or focused my efforts on teaching my brothers as best as I could.
However, when a friend needed something, I wrote a more extensive piece, which I called the Reminder of Piety.
To prevent the tablet from gathering dust and the stylus from rusting away on the wall, I wrote a short work for a friend about the notable features of the islands of Sardinia and Sicily, organized into two small books in verse.
For another person, I wrote two small books: the first about the conflict between two leaders and the remarkable revelation of souls; the second about a captured soldier who was freed by a saving sacrifice.
Indeed, people tend to pursue more eagerly the art they have gained through both knowledge and practice.
So, since I had acquired some skill in writing from my efforts, I took on a project that I knew would exceed my modest abilities, certainly a bold departure from Horace's advice:
Choose a subject equal to your strength, you who write,
and consider carefully what your shoulders can bear, and what they cannot.
If the subject is chosen wisely, neither eloquence nor clear order will abandon you.
Thus, I compiled a history in fourteen small books, detailing how holy Jerusalem and many other cities or regions in the East were reclaimed by Western Christians in our time, titled: The Laurel of the Jerusalem Pilgrims.
Afterwards, a serious illness confined me to bed.
Chapter Seven
The second illness of Reiner, driven away from the heavens.
My skin clung to my bones as my flesh was consumed, for the Lord had aged my skin and flesh, in line with the prophet's words, and crushed my bones.
I lost all appetite for food, and my veins, deprived of nourishment, refused to let me sleep.
So, my soul cried out to God, for His wrath overwhelmed me, and His terrors disturbed me.
Indeed, my soul was drenched in its own tears, broken and filled with an indescribable feeling, stirring the deepest parts of the Spirit of the Comforter, deserving of consolation.
One of the brothers visited and advised me to have the names of the seven sleeping saints written on paper and tied around my head.
This remedy of devout faith sometimes restored sleep to the sick.
I took his advice to heart, did as instructed, and inwardly heard a voice: "Your faith will heal you" (Gospel of Mark, Chapter Ten).
Suddenly, in a mental rapture, I found myself in a palace filled with unimaginable light and incredible fragrance, where the lamp, the glory, the exultation, was the majesty of the true, uniquely desirable, blessed, and adored Trinity.
Yet, it's important to restrain an intemperate and impudent mouth, so as not to burden my unfortunate miseries.
Suffice it to say, in thanksgiving, that among the choirs of those clad in purple and white, I recognized the saints, gloriously marked with golden crowns and scarlet robes.
There, the sweetest new songs resonated, and angelic instruments played the response: "These are the saints who gave up their bodies for the covenant of God and washed their robes in the blood of the Lamb" (Book of Revelation, Chapter Twenty-Two).
But when I returned to myself, I looked around, astonished, almost unaware of where I was.
Meanwhile, a familiar brother sat beside my bed, and as he eagerly asked why I was looking around so intently, trusting in his proven friendship, I recounted the vision, which I soon realized was not frivolous.
My limbs were weakened by illness and bound by pain, as if by chains, so for seven days, I couldn't rise or stand without someone else's help.
However, when I saw that strong and merciful one, who, through the blood of his covenant, released his prisoners from the pit where there is no water, I was freed and strengthened.
I was able to rise without any support when I went with the aforementioned brother to the place of prayer, pouring out thanks with all my heart.
Restored from my weakness, I offered the holy sleepers a gift of praise and thanksgiving, though it was a simple and entirely inadequate melody composed for them.
If anyone is troubled or considers it boastful that I write such things, would they forbid a wretched person from remembering the Lord's mercies?
No well-meaning person accuses a simple and pious intention.
It's good to hide the king's secret, but it's honorable to reveal and confess the works of God.
A reverent mind is not characterized by lofty thoughts, but by agreeing with the humble, as divine revelations to the pious are instruments of virtue, not vice.
But what benefit is there for the wicked, like Balaam or Nebuchadnezzar, to have seen divine things?
The sun dazzles the eyes of those who squint.
It is not a holy vision that merits God, but a holy action.
Chapter Eight
Other works of Reiner.
I also wrote a small book in verse about the arrival of the relics of Saint Lawrence in Liege from Rome.
Additionally, I composed many prayers at the request of the brothers, to be said to the martyr himself and various other saints.
I also published a little book for certain priests about showing reverence for sacred places.
In it, I sharply criticized the practices near cemeteries or around the bodies of the deceased before they were brought to the church.
In particular, girls' choruses and other inappropriate activities were allowed during night vigils.
A sophist, aiming to elevate his own works and diminish ours, challenged me with obscure questions and barbaric expressions compiled from everywhere.
I felt as though I had stumbled into Daedalus's labyrinth and faced the Minotaur.
How would I escape?
What guidance could I find?
I lacked the delicate threads of cleverness.
How would I defend myself?
I had no sword of eloquence.
Nevertheless, I unraveled those complexities, escaped the dreadful beast, and this little book was titled: "He who speaks sophistically is detestable."
Since it's known that variety brings refreshment and change erases weariness, I sometimes varied my study with prose, sometimes with verse, and occasionally with music. For this reason, I began twin songs about the holy confessors Antony and Jerome, as I wished to offer my humble services to such great patrons.
Oh, what a trivial little man I am! Oh, soul focused on earthly things and empty of the heavenly! Yet sometimes I dared to lift the face of my mind, and, lifted by both my heart and tongue like twin wings, I burst into the angelic mysteries.
Indeed, I composed three small books in verse about the victory of the archangel Michael, covering both his triumph over the ancient dragon and his angels with his own angels, and his glorious battle for Christians against pagans, when he established and dedicated a new sanctuary on Mount Gargano.
There are no costs for that structure of metals, marbles, and precious cedar piles, because the rock with its rough hollow expands the arch of its space, offering more reverence than craftsmanship.
For you, O glorious defender, to you, I say, O magnificent one according to your name, admirer of the glorified and admirable Trinity!
Indeed, who is like God?
Human hearts enriched with faith, hope, and love are more pleasing than the rich material of such things.
Additionally, I composed music about Saint Servatius and Saint Begga when some canons requested it.
My brother asked me to create seven hymns about the Holy Spirit, for which I owe love, so that I might fulfill devotion.
Specifically, while he often encouraged me with familiar conversation, he revealed something among other things that is venerable, that is memorable.
Sometimes, when he had devoted himself to vigils and the invocation of the same Holy Spirit, he fell into a trance at dusk and saw himself being carried into a church by someone of complete brightness and admirable sweetness, who was clothed in white, shining brighter than snow, and adorned with flowers.
This person embraced him with the sweetest affection, with both hands placed on his heart, just as a loving mother presses her breasts to a sweet nursing infant, but hid their face as the brother frequently turned to look at them and longed to see them.
He understood that it was the Holy Spirit, yet for a little while, he saw that face, about which it is better to remain silent, for it is safer to be moved by it than to speak of it; it is safer to venerate mysteries than to dispute about them.
Finally, the brother of the most merciful Creator, the most worthy Redeemer, lifted his right hand from his chest.
With his own hands, he made the sign of the cross over his heart, loins, and kidneys as a protective seal three times.
This was to protect and strengthen him against troubling thoughts or fleshly desires.
The choir of the chosen ones present sang in melodious voices:
"Let the hearts of those who seek the Lord rejoice; seek the Lord and be strengthened; seek His face always."
Psalm 104:3-4.
The brother realized that the vision was significant. He affirmed with tearful contrition that he felt infused with a certain light, and the attacks of his mind and carnal impulses were greatly diminished.
Blessed indeed is the one whom You instruct, Lord, and teach from Your law, to give him relief from days of trouble.
Psalm 94:12-13.
Chapter Nine
Other intellectual works left by Reiner.
I wrote five small books about how, in our time, the Church of Liege, with divine help, reclaimed the castle of Bouillon after defeating the invaders.
I titled it: The Bouillon Triumph.
And I also added music to it.
In addition, I composed two songs about the holy martyrs Evermarus and Urbanus at the request of the devoted brothers.
I wrote many epitaphs and letters as well.
With such tasks and similar trivialities, I spent my difficult life, burdened by monastic duties, and in turn, placed these burdens on our little donkey.
However, I did not expect the sharp arrows of some critics, which might pierce my humble writings.
I consider that nothing I have written or will write has any value, but is rather unlearned and even foolish.
Nevertheless, I prefer to create my own work, however poorly, rather than take someone else's, using my own anvil rather than a foreign one, and I do not mend poor Latin with good Latin.
Whoever you are, praiseworthy craftsman, strive to be a new Tubalcain.
Practice admirable skills as an example from old times.
Let your own fire, your own tools, declare your worth.
For it is the sign of a lazy craftsman to always covet others' hammers and bellows, constantly begging at a foreign forge without glory.
A spring is not considered a true source unless it flows from its own vein.
What is poured from outside is foreign.
Therefore, I must be cautious; I must especially heed Horace's advice to a friend: To seek personal wealth and avoid tampering with the writings preserved by Apollo:
Lest, if one day the flock of birds comes to claim their feathers, the crow, stripped of its stolen colors, becomes a laughingstock.
Book Three
Chapter One
This little book introduces a topic of interest.
My own mistakes seem as if they're marked with a black stone.
Sometimes I yearn for little pieces of Parian marble, sometimes for precious pearls with a milky hue, so that these cherished items can clearly reflect the topics that a close group of friends recently suggested for discussion.
These are worthy of exploration and beneficial to understand, as one person rightly seeks what can benefit many.
Specifically, he asked: Why, before the Lord's Birth, are the nine antiphons that start with "O" sung over nine days with the Gospel hymn at the evening church service?
Additionally, why is the passion of Saint Stephen, the first martyr, commemorated on the second day of the Lord's Birth, and the assumption of Saint John the Evangelist on the third, when traditionally one passed on August 3 and the other on June 26, attaining eternal life through death, but being celebrated more promptly?
Why is the fourth day designated for the Innocents, when it's not clearly established that their passion occurred then?
First, I'll discuss these topics and then address the other questions he raised, covering them more extensively as requested, even though I would have preferred to be more concise.
Chapter Two
Why are nine antiphons beginning with the letter "O" sung at vespers for nine days before the Nativity of the Lord?
It is believed in the heart for righteousness and confessed with the mouth for salvation that the Only Begotten of God was incarnated by the Holy Spirit and made man through the Virgin Mary.
Therefore, since wisdom, by the will of the Father, was building a house for itself and carving out the seven columns of grace, that miraculous incarnation took shape and was celebrated within the womb for nine months.
We likewise commemorate it with praise over nine glorious days.
Indeed, we substitute a day for a month.
Since we must attend to other duties of times or solemnities and because other sacraments also need to be celebrated, it would be less appropriate or reasonable to focus on just one thing continuously.
Human nature tires of constancy; what is encountered less often is more appreciated.
The fact that these proclamations are made towards the end of the day, at sunset, mystically signifies that He, who was born of the Father before all ages, God from God, Light from Light, begotten, not made, when the fullness of time came, was made and born of a woman when the rising from on high visited us to give light to those who sat in darkness and the shadow of death.
For He Himself speaks in the Apocalypse: I am the Alpha and the Omega, the first and the last, the beginning and the end (Revelation Twenty-Two), since all things were made through Him and in Him; all things were restored or perfected through Him and by Him.
The earlier letters suggest this: Alpha, the first of the Greek alphabet, and Omega, the last, yet you should notice a clearer mystery beneath.
Indeed, Greek letters not only form words but also represent numbers: and just as each one follows in order, so does its character denote a larger number, Alpha thus signifies one, Omega signifies eight hundred.
Truly, with mercy and grace, the only Son of the Father, in the end times, wished to bring the children of God to Himself-not by nature, but by adoption.
This is symbolized by the number eight hundred, meaning countless, and generously endowed with the eight blessings.
Therefore, the work of compassion and the mystery of mercy, which even amazes the nine orders of angels, is something we marvel at in every way.
Although we cannot match such great blessings with the gratitude in our hearts or words, as the Wise One says:
"Glorify the Lord as much as you can, His magnificence is still greater and more wonderful; bless the Lord and exalt Him as much as you can: for He is greater than praise; by exalting Him, you are filled with strength so that you do not tire, for you will not reach Him."
Yet it would be ungrateful and impious not to give thanks. Therefore, we offer our glorification, blessing, and exaltation of our gratitude to God. Through nine antiphons, we present a manifold prayer, but a harmonious harmony to the eternal Sun, which is about to illuminate the world with the fullness of light.
Indeed, in Christ dwells all the fullness of divinity bodily. He, like a bridegroom emerging from the chamber of a virginal life, presented Himself infused and drenched with the delightful sweetness of all virtues, and the wondrous fragrance of all graces.
Thus, while the antiphons composed in praise of the thrice-holy Trinity are made up of three sets of three blessings, it is desirable for us to discuss the harmony of either of them, if it is granted from above.
Chapter Three
The mystery of the first antiphon is explained:
O wisdom, etc.
The appearance of Wisdom to someone is recounted.
The first of the gifts that the Apostle mentions in his letter to the Ephesians is the message of wisdom.
This corresponds to the first of the antiphons, "O wisdom, who came forth from the mouth of the Most High," even in its literal wording.
God made everything in wisdom, the universe through the Word that came out of His mouth, created by the Most High, because He spoke, and it came to be; He commanded, and it was created.
Psalm thirty-two.
This wisdom reaches from one end of the earth to the other with strength.
Wisdom eight.
While He wishes to have His delights with the children of men, He inclined Himself from divinity, beyond which there is nothing, to humanity, which is the last in created things.
Therefore, Christ, the power of God and the wisdom of God, completed the work given to Him by the Father to do, as beneficially as powerfully, and ascended to where He had descended, since His going forth is from the highest heaven, and His journey to its highest point.
Psalm eighteen.
He had proceeded from God and came adorned with the golden crown of love and mercy and upheld by the fullness of grace, so that even the element that the Church calls upon in its invocation, "O," is shown to signify the complete form of its roundness.
Indeed, I learned that this was revealed from heaven to a certain faithful person.
However, some tend to belittle and mock it, quoting the wise saying: Dreams elevate the foolish, like someone who grasps a shadow and chases the wind; so too is one who pays attention to deceitful visions.
Ecclesiasticus thirty-four.
In response to them, it is said, as the same passage shortly after adds: The dreams of evildoers are vanity, and just as a pregnant woman's heart suffers fantasies, unless a visitation has been sent from the Most High.
Both canonical and other Scriptures provide many examples that not every vision, not every dream is false or erroneous, and sometimes not dreams but revelations are sent from the Most High to devout people, especially those who, like Daniel, are men of great desires.
Indeed, it is also mentioned in the Book of Job:
"In a dream, in a vision of the night, when deep sleep falls on people as they lie on their beds, then He opens the ears of men and instructs them with wisdom" (Job 33).
Aside from a more mysterious meaning, this can quite fittingly be taken literally.
Thus, the Wisdom of God appeared to be seated on a golden throne, with a golden crown on her head, adorned with the fresh grace of jewels.
Her face shone with an unfading whiteness, and her eyes sparkled with a wondrous strength of hidden light.
She was dressed in very bright linen garments and draped in a cloak of gold, much like the Ark of the Covenant, which shone with the purest gold inside and out and had a golden crown above it.
For to the Son of God, as the head, it serves as a diadem or ornament, which He, by grace, desired and by power, was able to assume as a man.
A wonderful fragrance filled the air, like the scent of a field blessed by the Lord.
Men of notable appearance and attire sat around her, blooming like lilies with a kind of youthful freshness, illuminated by rays of wisdom emanating from her everywhere.
They held harps in their hands, made of snowy ivory and intricately inlaid with gold, with which they played the sweetest music, those verses from the Psalms:
"The law of the Lord is perfect, reviving the soul; the testimony of the Lord is sure, making wise the simple; the precepts of the Lord are right, giving joy to the heart; the commandment of the Lord is pure, giving light to the eyes; the fear of the Lord is clean, enduring forever; the judgments of the Lord are true and altogether righteous, more desirable than gold, even much fine gold, and sweeter than honey and the honeycomb" (Psalm 19).
Moreover, an inscription, as if arranged in a sapphire color, read:
"I, Wisdom, dwell in counsel, and I am present in learned thoughts."
On that very night, the faithful man poured out his soul, reflecting on the works of the Lord and His judgments that have existed since ancient times.
He was deeply afflicted and humbled by his own miserable condition, soaking his bed with tears.
Out of abundant compassion, he received this vision for consolation.
Indeed, experiencing heavenly revelations brings comfort and inspires devotion.
So, O wisdom, you who gently arrange all things!
You are truly kind to everyone, and your mercies extend over all your works.
Come, teach us the path of wisdom, as described by the mighty angel that John writes about, who descended from heaven, clothed in a cloud, with a rainbow on his head, a face like the sun, and feet like pillars of fire, holding an open little book in his hand.
Teach us the mysteries of this book, I say, so that your justifications may be our songs on our journey.
Chapter Six
Mysteries of the Second Antiphon - O Adonai.
The second gift of grace is the word of knowledge, to which the second antiphon, O Adonai, clearly corresponds.
For the Lord, interpreted as Adonai, demonstrated how He was a leader in His mercy to the people He redeemed, guiding, teaching, and protecting them as the apple of His eye, as we find in the Scriptures.
It's said that He revealed His name to Moses, which He had not revealed to the fathers:
"I am the Lord who appeared to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob as God Almighty, but by my name Adonai I was not known to them" (Exodus 6).
This suggests He was going to reveal it to you, either by performing signs or by speaking face to face.
He also appeared to Moses earlier in the flame of a bush.
When Moses said, "I will go over and see this strange sight-why the bush does not burn up," He said, "Do not come any closer. Take off your sandals, for the place where you are standing is holy ground" (Exodus 3).
Therefore, as we approach such a revered sight, the footwear of mortal flesh must be removed, so that walking in the spirit of humility, we may be worthy to enjoy the living and life-giving fire.
That bush symbolized blessed Mary, who stands out as remarkable in the purple blush of modest virginity.
The bush was on fire but not consumed, because when the Holy Spirit came upon her and the power of the Most High overshadowed her, the virgin was set ablaze with an indescribable love, yet was not burned.
She conceived God, the Word of God, in her mind and gave birth to Him made flesh, remaining inviolate and entirely free from carnal desire after childbirth.
O fire of sweetness!
O flame of delight!
O unique blaze, where the material not only did not wither in the most chaste flesh but even bloomed like a special rose, by which heaven and earth are tinted in purple!
That fiery splendor marked the zeal and splendid wonders that the Lord was soon to perform in the land of Egypt, in the field of Tanis.
However, it was most especially marked by the humanity of Jesus Christ, burning with charity and shining with miracles.
Here is what John the Baptist said: "Among those born of women, no one has risen greater. He is the one who is coming after me, who was before me, of whom I am not worthy to untie the strap of his sandal." (John, Chapter One).
Indeed, the sandal of Christ is his humanity, with which his divinity is surrounded.
The strap of the sandal is a perplexing mystery to our understanding due to its great subtlety.
Therefore, I refrain, and like Moses, I hide my face.
I do not dare to look upon God, but I fall to the ground because I am dust, and I will return to dust.
With all the longing of my soul, with all the depths of my senses, I proclaim the true praise of the true Virgin: "Blessed are you among women, and blessed is the fruit of your womb." (Luke, Chapter One).
Furthermore, on the fiftieth day after the departure of Israel from Egypt, the law of Moses was given on Sinai.
When the Lord descended upon it in fire, smoke rose from it like from a furnace, and the blast of the trumpet sounded louder.
Thunder was heard, lightning flashed, and a very thick cloud covered the mountain, and the people in the camp were afraid.
All these things happened to them as a symbol.
Indeed, they were a foreshadowing of what occurred on the day of Pentecost.
After the true Moses, that is, Christ, had led his holy people out of the infernal Egypt, and had brought them through the Red Sea of his passion, and had been glorified by his resurrection and ascension from the waters of suffering and mortality, suddenly, there was a sound from heaven like a rushing mighty wind.
It filled the whole house where the apostles were sitting, and tongues as of fire appeared to them and rested on each one of them.
They were all filled with the Holy Spirit and began to speak in different tongues, as the Holy Spirit enabled them to speak.
(Acts, Chapter Two).
Then, as the trumpet of such loud preaching resounded, a multitude gathered and was confused in mind, because each one heard them speaking in their own language about the mighty works of God.
Imagine this: thunder roared and lightning flashed, as miracles shone brightly and divine judgments from the Scriptures were delivered, like this one:
"The Lord your God will raise up for you a prophet from among your brothers, like me. You will listen to him in everything I have spoken to you. And it will be that every soul who does not listen to that prophet will be cut off from the people" (Deuteronomy 18).
Or consider this passage from Joel:
"And indeed on my servants and on my handmaids in those days I will pour out my Spirit, and they shall prophesy. I will show wonders in the sky above and signs on the earth below; blood and fire and vapor of smoke. The sun will be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood before the great and terrible and manifest day of the Lord comes" (Joel 2).
Indeed, when from the pierced side of Jesus of Nazareth, fixed to the cross by the hands of the wicked, after he had already given up his spirit, blood and water flowed out beyond the nature of dead bodies, the Lord gave blood as a sign.
That blood was a sign of death leading to death for some and life leading to life for others, just as the blood of the lamb once was, when signs and wonders were performed in Egypt, against Pharaoh and all his servants.
A bunch of hyssop was dipped in it, and both doorposts and the lintel were sprinkled.
When the Lord passed, striking down the Egyptians, he saw the blood, marked the doors, passed over them, and did not allow the destroyer to enter the houses or harm them.
Similarly, now, those who mark both the doorposts-meaning the soul and body-or the lintel, meaning their reason, with the faith of the cross, so as not to be scandalized by the passion of Christ, which is symbolized by the hyssop-a plant that is humble, bitter, but healing-they believe sincerely, truly confess, and worthily receive the holy Eucharist, will not fall into the hand of the striking devil, because they will be marked with the name of the Holy Trinity, protected by the sacrament.
The fire was given as a sign because of its bright and burning nature.
This signifies that the Holy Spirit would ignite Christ's apostles with zeal and enlighten them with understanding.
Additionally, the forms of divided tongues symbolized the divisions of graces.
The smoke vapor was a sign when many were touched deeply by the apostles' preaching and tearfully sought guidance for their salvation, asking:
"What shall we do, brothers?"
Acts chapter two.
To smoke means to be pierced and to weep over sins.
Indeed, at the first baptism of the Church, three thousand gathered, a miracle in itself, with divine grace foreshadowing that believers from all over the world would come to the faith of the Trinity.
Just as we understand illumination or the fervor of the faithful through fire, the vapor of smoke allows us to understand the blindness of the Jews and the remorse of the penitent, or the obscurity of the unrepentant.
The sun was a sign because, when it darkened during the Lord's Passion, it foreshadowed the blindness of Israel, which began then and continues even now.
Though the moon didn't visibly turn into blood, it became bloodied for them during their Passover celebration, when they ate the lamb on the fourteenth day at evening according to the lunar cycle by the law's command.
By killing Christ, they stained themselves with blood.
The synagogue covered its eyes with a cloth stained by such a monstrous crime.