Book Against the Erroneous Definitions of John Scotus Eriugena
by Florus of Lyon
From the Great Library of the Fathers.
In the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, we begin the little book by FLORI against the nonsense and errors of a very vain man named John, concerning predestination, divine foreknowledge, and the true freedom of human will.
Preface
Some writings have come to the Church of Lyon from a certain conceited and talkative individual.
While discussing divine foreknowledge and predestination using human and, as he boasts, philosophical arguments, he offers no reasoning or authority from the Scriptures or the holy Fathers.
He dares to define these matters as if they should be accepted and followed based solely on his presumption.
These writings are easily judged and rejected by faithful readers well-versed in sacred doctrine because they are extremely vain, full of lies, and contain errors against the faith and truth of God.
With God's help, they are even held in contempt and ridicule.
However, as we have heard, this same man is admired by many as if he were scholarly and learned.
By chattering or writing such things, he leads some into hesitation and others, as if he were saying something profound, into becoming followers of his error.
He occupies all his listeners and admirers with his vain verbosity and windy chatter most perniciously.
As a result, they do not humbly submit to the divine Scriptures or the authorities of the Fathers, but rather follow his fantastical ravings.
Therefore, we deemed it absolutely necessary, with the zeal of charity and the duty of our place and order, to respond to his insolence, with the Lord as our author.
Whoever wishes to read this faithfully, with the fear of God and care for their salvation, may truly recognize how essential it is in these perilous and extreme times to cling firmly to the unchanging truth of the holy Scripture.
They should humbly obey the most established authority of the holy orthodox Fathers, close and block their ears to undisciplined and most vain verbosity, and fear that saying of the Lord with full intention, which we almost see being fulfilled now, where He says: "Do you think, when the Son of Man comes, He will find faith on earth?" (Luke 18:8).
And what the Apostle, in whom the same Lord spoke, sternly warns, saying:
"For there will be a time when they will not endure sound doctrine, but according to their own desires, they will heap up teachers for themselves, having itching ears;
and they will turn their ears away from the truth and be turned aside to fables"
Second Timothy 4:4-5
Therefore, elsewhere, under the persona of the beloved and chosen disciple, he most diligently admonishes every faithful person, and especially the pastoral order, saying:
"O Timothy, guard what has been entrusted to you, avoiding profane and idle babblings and the contradictions of what is falsely called knowledge.
By professing it, some have strayed concerning the faith"
First Timothy 6:20-21
Therefore, with the words set forth, which he arranged in nineteen chapters of his work, as the Lord deigns to grant, we undertake to respond not with our own understanding, but in accordance with the Holy Scriptures and the most blessed Catholic Fathers.
He claimed that all questions of philosophy could be resolved through four fundamental principles.
He argued that there are not two predestinations.
However, the faith of the Church responds by affirming that the truth of God's eternal judgment and ordination-expressed by the term predestination-should be sought not from philosophers, but from God's apostles and prophets.
This truth is not found in the fourfold paths of worldly doctrine but in the one true way, which speaks of itself: "I am the way, the truth, and the life" (John 14:6).
Blessed Jeremiah the prophet urges and invites us to this way, saying: "Stand by the roads and look, and ask for the ancient paths, where the good way is; and walk in it, and find rest for your souls" (Jeremiah 6:16).
Concerning this way, the prophet Isaiah promises the Church, saying: "And a highway will be there; it will be called the Way of Holiness.
The unclean will not journey on it; it will be for those who walk in that Way.
Wicked fools will not go about on it" (Isaiah 35:8).
Therefore, whoever chooses to be foolish in this age for Christ's sake and strives to obey the Apostle, who says: "If anyone among you thinks that he is wise in this age, let him become a fool that he may become wise" (First Corinthians 3:18), should steadfastly and unwaveringly hold to this true way, the good way, the straight way, which is the Lord Christ himself.
They should shun the cunning and deception of human wisdom, about which the same Apostle says: "For it is written: 'He catches the wise in their craftiness'" (First Corinthians 3:19); and again: "The Lord knows the thoughts of the wise, that they are futile" (Psalm 94:11).
Therefore, the question of divine predestination is not resolved through such philosophy and empty deceit but rather confused and entangled, compounded with various lies and errors.
The predestination of God's eternal counsel and judgment, whether in rewarding the just or condemning the wicked, is based on His simple and divine knowledge, where everything is simultaneously and eternally preordained and predetermined.
We truly call this one.
And because of its double effect, by which some are mercifully saved and others justly condemned, we do not hesitate to call it two; faithfully saying with the Psalmist to the judge of all:
"I will sing of mercy and judgment to you, O Lord"
Psalm 101:1.
And faithfully listening to the same judge declaring in the Gospel that this mystery of predestination was eternally arranged with the Father, and wonderfully fulfilled in the blindness of some and the enlightenment of others, when rejoicing in the Holy Spirit, He says:
"I thank you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because you have hidden these things from the wise and prudent, and have revealed them to little children. Yes, Father, for it was pleasing in your sight"
Matthew 11:25, 27.
For what could be said more clearly about both sides than that by His coming He declares that the proud are blinded and the humble are enlightened; this is indeed:
"Because you have hidden these things from the wise and prudent, and have revealed them to little children."
And what could be firmer and stronger about the just and merciful predestination of both things, than what He immediately added in agreement, saying:
"Yes, Father, for it was pleasing in your sight."
And because the Father has given all judgment to the Son: and He, together with the Father, in eternal counsel established and predetermined all these things, which He distinguishes and judges in the world in their own times, He immediately adds about Himself:
"All things have been delivered to me by my Father"
Matthew 11:27.
All things, specifically both to be saved and to be condemned, and justly to be blinded and mercifully to be enlightened, as He says elsewhere:
"For judgment I have come into this world, that those who do not see may see, and those who see may become blind"
John 9:39.
This is the righteous judgment of God, as the Lord and Savior Himself praises and refers to it with thanksgiving to the glory of the Father.
Similarly, all divine Scripture and the entire holy Catholic Church, in psalms, hymns, and spiritual songs that it customarily offers to God, faithfully celebrate by praising and giving thanks, saying with the Psalmist:
The Lord is righteous in all His ways and holy in all His works.
(Psalm 145:17)
And what the lawgiver says in the song of Deuteronomy:
Ascribe greatness to our God.
The works of God are perfect, and all His ways are just: a faithful God who does no wrong; righteous and holy is the Lord.
(Deuteronomy 32:3-4)
Similarly, in the psalm, when it was said generally about the elect being saved and the reprobates being damned:
The Lord is near to all who call on Him in truth.
He fulfills the desires of those who fear Him; He hears their cry and saves them.
The Lord watches over all who love Him, but all the wicked He will destroy.
(Psalm 145:18-20)
The righteous judgment of both parties is commended with abundant and general praise, as it immediately follows:
My mouth will speak in praise of the Lord.
Let every creature praise His holy name forever and ever.
(Psalm 145:21)
Similarly, in another psalm, after setting forth the praise of God, immediately recalling the righteous judgment of God in His praises, he says:
Praise the Lord, my soul.
I will praise the Lord all my life; I will sing praise to my God as long as I live.
(Psalm 146:1)
And shortly after:
He upholds the cause of the oppressed and gives food to the hungry.
The Lord sets prisoners free, the Lord gives sight to the blind, the Lord lifts up those who are bowed down, the Lord loves the righteous.
The Lord watches over the foreigner and sustains the fatherless and the widow, but He frustrates the ways of the wicked.
(Psalm 146:7-9)
In the book of Revelation, after the final judgment and the reward of the righteous and the damnation of the wicked, the saints offer praise and thanksgiving to God for both outcomes.
It is written in the same book:
The twenty-four elders who sit before God on their thrones fell on their faces and worshiped God, saying:
We give thanks to you, Lord God Almighty, who is and who was, because you have taken your great power and reigned.
The nations were angry, but your wrath has come, and the time has come for the dead to be judged: to reward your servants the prophets and the saints, and those who fear your name, both small and great, and to destroy those who have corrupted the earth (Revelation 11:16-18).
Many such things are found in the Holy Scriptures in various ways, so there is nothing better for a faithful person than to recognize and faithfully praise the just judgment of God in both aspects, by saying:
You are just, Lord, and your judgment is right (Psalms 119:137).
The holy Fathers and doctors of the Church also diligently advise that this should be done, as the blessed Pope Leo exhorts in a certain place, saying:
And the blessed Augustine, when he was explaining the words of the psalm to the people, where it is written:
As smoke is driven away, so drive them away; as wax melts before the fire, so let the wicked perish before God (Psalms 68:2):
Who, he says, will boast that he has a pure heart, or who will boast that he is clean from sins?
Therefore, when Scripture says: As wax melts before the fire, so let the wicked perish before God, who does not tremble, who does not leap up in fear?
What then shall we do, and what hope do we have?
For these things are not sung in vain.
Or indeed, when the Prophet says these things, does he wish them for men, and not rather foresee what is to come?
In these words, there appears the figure of one wishing, but it is understood as the foreknowledge of one announcing.
Just as some things in the Scripture of the prophets are narrated as if they happened in the past when they are foretold for the future, some things are said as if by the wish of one desiring: but those who rightly understand what they hear, recognize the vision of the one foretelling.
As in ancient words, future events are signified.
So, in the figure of one wishing or foretelling, the mind must be understood.
Similarly, regarding Judas, the Lord's betrayer, the Prophet seems to wish upon him what he predicted would come.
And about the Jews themselves: "Let their table become a snare and a trap and a stumbling block" (Psalm 69:23); which the Apostle explains as being predicted about them (Romans 11:9); just as Peter recalls what was foretold about Judas under the same figure.
It is not without reason that things to come are spoken of as if they were past: for to God, if they are certain, they are regarded as already done.
The Prophet seems to speak as one wishing what he foresees to be certain to come: indicating nothing else, in my view, except that we should not be displeased with God's known judgment, which He has established as fixed and immovable.
Therefore, in the Acts of the Apostles, when a prophet named Agabus predicted that Paul would suffer many things from the Jews in Jerusalem and even face imprisonment, the brothers tried to stop him from going there.
Paul said, "What are you doing, weeping and breaking my heart? For I am ready not only to be bound but even to die for the name of the Lord Jesus Christ" (Acts 21:10 and following); and when the brothers saw his unwavering determination, they said: "May the will of the Lord be done" (Acts 21:14).
So, because they said, "May the will of the Lord be done," did the apostles wish that he would suffer such things? Or did they rather devoutly submit their minds to the sublime and divine decree?
Similarly, when the Prophet says, "As wax melts before the fire, so let the wicked perish before God," he sees this certainly impending upon sinners; and he is pleased with what God has decreed, lest he himself displease God.
After these words, the most blessed doctor wanted to make sure that the fixed and unchangeable divine judgment of predestination didn't seem to force anyone to act wrongly.
Instead, he wanted to instill a healthy fear, encouraging those who hear it to repent and correct themselves to avoid the coming wrath.
He exhorts by saying:
The most faithful doctor affirmed the unchangeable truth of divine predestination, even in the condemnation of sinners.
Yet, he sincerely taught that if they correct themselves and change for the better, they will escape punishment.
Divine predestination exercises just judgment in punishing sinners but does not take away the remedy of salvation from anyone who converts.
His promise is true and faithful, as He declares through the prophet, not only promising but also swearing:
"As I live, says the Lord God, I do not desire the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way and live" (Ezekiel 33:11).
Chapter Two
In this second chapter, we encounter eight definitions:
1.
Predestination and God's foreknowledge are part of His essence, just like His will, wisdom, and truth.
2.
Foreknowledge and predestination are the same.
3.
One cannot reach God, whom they abandoned by free will, without the gift of cooperating grace and effort.
4.
Predestination exists in God by substance, but relatively, it cannot be done.
5.
Just as it is impious to duplicate, triplicate, or multiply God's essence, wisdom, knowledge, and virtues, anyone asserting two predestinations is guilty of impiety.
6.
There is one divine predestination, just as there is one divine operation, wisdom, and will.
7.
Predestination is not compelled by necessity, just as it is not by will.
8.
Whatever is understood about the divine will should also apply to God's predestination.
Notice how much he has laid out, as if to be followed by everyone and judged by no one, without any testimony from divine Scripture or any attestation from the doctrine of the fathers.
He defined so many things.
But with the Lord's help, we will carefully examine each one and discern what should be believed according to the rule of faith.
He says: Predestination and God's foreknowledge are part of His essence, just like His will, wisdom, and truth.
But we assert that His will is essentially part of the Lord because in His supreme and simple essence, there is no difference between willing and being.
What it is to be is to will, and therefore His will is in Him in such a way that He is His will.
Similarly, regarding wisdom and truth: He possesses wisdom in such a way that He is wisdom; He possesses truth in such a way that He is truth.
In the simple nature of Divinity, there is no difference between having and being; what it is to have is to be, and what it is to be is to have.
Therefore, if we say, as the blessed Augustine says: eternal, immortal, incorruptible, unchangeable, living, wise, powerful, beautiful, just, good, blessed, spirit; out of all these, the last one mentioned, spirit, seems to signify the substance alone.
The others, however, signify the qualities of this substance.
But it is not so in that ineffable and simple nature.
For whatever seems to be said there according to qualities, must be understood according to substance or essence.
However, let it not be that God is called spirit according to substance, and good according to quality.
Instead, both are according to substance; as are all the others we have mentioned.
Therefore, since this is the case, and these three-that is, will, wisdom, and truth-are in God in such a way as to absolutely show the nature of God, who is the highest will, the highest wisdom, and truth, having all power, surpassing all understanding, and remaining unchangeable above all, it is clear that the rule of God is that they are understood to be said of God substantially.
It is also clear that knowledge in God must be understood essentially, because for Him, being is not different from knowing.
What it is for Him to be, this is to know.
Nor is it different for Him to have knowledge than to be knowledge, just as it is the same for Him to have wisdom as to be wisdom.
However, whether God can be said to be foreknowledge substantially, as He is said to be knowledge substantially, let him judge according to reason and the rule of faith who can.
Yet, it seems to us that, just as it is truly said of God: There is no difference for Him between being and knowing, it cannot be said of Him without falsehood or excessive use: There is no difference for Him between being and foreknowing.
For it can rightly and commonly be said: God is knowledge, just as it is rightly and commonly said: God is wisdom, there is no doubt.
But to say: God is foreknowledge, as we have already said, is either not true or too unusual.
A similar or even harsher reasoning applies to what he defined, that God is substantially predestination.
Who has ever heard it said that God's being and His predestining are different things?
It is truly said about Him: His being and His knowing are not different; for Him, to be is the same as to know.
Therefore, we must say that just as God is knowledge, wisdom, and truth, God is also predestination.
However, for us, it seems better and more fitting to true faith and church teachings to view these concepts differently: although knowledge, foreknowledge, and predestination appear different to us, we distinguish them with certain properties.
Knowledge is spoken of absolutely, while foreknowledge and predestination refer to the provision of future events.
Foreknowledge concerns knowing good and evil beforehand, while predestination is about establishing and ordering the good.
This distinction is necessary so that for us, who are temporal and mortal, both God's complete knowledge and His governance of creatures are more distinctly conveyed and understood through such a distinction or distribution.
However, it is more convenient to understand these three in God under one name: knowledge, because whatever we understand and know distinctly in these three is simultaneously present in His supreme, singular, and simple knowledge.
His knowing is perfect and complete; it cannot be diminished or increased, nor can it be altered by any variety of things.
Therefore, what we attempt to distinguish about His knowledge, foreknowledge, and predestination is, in His perfect and unchangeable knowledge, eternally one and the same.
Therefore, we believe it has been correctly observed by ecclesiastical discipline that it is proper and customary to speak of God's foreknowledge and predestination, as the Creator and Judge of all, in relation to His works.
It is also proper and customary to say that foreknowledge and predestination exist in God, that is, in His eternal, perfect, and unchangeable knowledge; but it is neither customary nor proper to say that God is foreknowledge or predestination.
For His knowledge refers to Himself; foreknowledge and predestination, however, refer to creatures.
Hence, in these, His operation, which is performed in or towards these creatures, is demonstrated more than His essence or substance.
Thus, we speak of God's foreknowledge and predestination or of foreknowledge and predestination in God, just as we speak of God's order or arrangement or of order and arrangement in God.
However, we have never heard anyone speak so absurdly or contentiously as to say that, just as we speak of God's order and arrangement, we should say that God Himself is order and arrangement, or should be described and defined as such.
The reason for this new and contentious definition is clear.
There is a fear that if foreknowledge and predestination, like God's governance, are not understood substantially in relation to God, but are referred to the ordering of His creatures, then it cannot be said to be dual or plural.
Therefore, among us, there is no contention about whether predestinations can be spoken of in the plural or not, as long as we faithfully and firmly hold that, by one and the same judgment and council of divine foreknowledge and predestination, two things are certain to be fulfilled: that the just are preordained to eternal glory, and that the wicked, persisting in their impieties until death, are destined for eternal punishment.
For the Scripture clearly says both: about the just, "And as many as were ordained to eternal life believed" (Acts 13:48); and about the wicked justly condemned, "God endured with much patience vessels of wrath prepared for destruction" (Romans 9:22).
This is how both of these things are accomplished in the elect and the reprobate by one and the same effect of divine predestination and judgment: just as by one and the same ray of the sun, healthy eyes are invigorated and weak eyes are irritated; just as also by one and the same fire, mud placed near it hardens, and wax melts.
We should also acknowledge that we must think of God's predestination just as we think of His justice.
Although it is one and remains the same, it clearly receives a double distribution: through it, rewards are given to the worthy, and punishments to the unworthy.
Surely, he asserts that the will of God, as well as wisdom and truth in God, are said essentially, which is truly correct.
For if he were to say that God is substantially justice, he would be speaking very truly.
Why then are these two things, which are said to be substantial in God, or even God substantially, namely His will and His truth, read in the Scriptures in the plural?
As it is held in the Psalms, where the Lord Himself says: "He made all my wills wonderful in them;" and elsewhere: "I have found David, the son of Jesse, a man after my own heart, who will do all my wills."
Likewise, we read in the Psalms: "The Lord is righteous, He loves righteousness." And again: "For truths are diminished among the sons of men." And in another place: "For the Lord requires truths."
Although the light of God and the truth of God are not different, but are simply one and truly believed in God, so that what is the light of God is the truth of God, and what is truth is light. However, when the Psalmist said: "Send out Your light and Your truth," he immediately added in the plural: "They have led me, and brought me to Your holy mountain and to Your tabernacles."
Why this? Because the will, justice, and truth of God, although they are one and simple in His nature, yet in the distribution of His gifts, or in the disposition of His creatures, they become manifold to us. In the same way, the Holy Spirit, who is one and simple in person in the Trinity, is called the manifold grace of God and the seven Spirits because of this same distribution of gifts.
We repeat these points so that readers understand there should be no dispute or contention about the number.
Whether the predestination of God can be referred to in the plural, or for any valid reason cannot be, as long as it is clear that there are two effects: mercifully preordained to life for the elect, or justly preordained to punishment for the reprobate.
Blessed Augustine teaches that just as we can speak of wisdom, we can also speak of prudence or the knowledge of the Lord, with these words: "Your knowledge from me has grown strong, and I will not be able to attain it" (Psalm 139:6).
Observe how the distinguished teacher, thinking and speaking excellently about God, confidently said that God is prudence, and openly declared that God is knowledge.
However, when considering whether God should also be called providence, which certainly belongs to God and is in God, referring to the governance of creation, he refrained from making a rash definition.
Instead, faced with great difficulty and distress, he chose to end the discussion with an exclamation of admiration and prayer to God.
By this example, we should all reflect and speak reverently about God: think moderately and disciplined, and define cautiously and fearfully.
Following these points, the aforementioned disputant, in his usual manner, adds: "And foreknowledge and predestination are one and the same."
But we, rejecting this novel error, should adhere to the most certain and firm rule of faith. With God's help, we should discern that foreknowledge is sometimes spoken of, which cannot be predestination. This is because Almighty God foreknew future good and evil, including the sins of men or angels.
However, He, being just and holy, could not have predestined that they should occur.
However, His predestination pertains either to the creation and governance of creatures, which is certainly good and just, or especially and chiefly to His works or judgments, which He performs or will perform in rational creatures, namely, angels and humans.
Among them, He justifies and blesses some through grace, and abandons and condemns others through justice.
The good things of the saints, including holy humans and holy angels, are His gifts or rewards, while the evils of others, such as eternal punishments, are His just retribution, dispensing all things justly.
Therefore, His predestination is always to be understood in the good things and in His works, which He exercises mercifully or justly.
What He both foreknew by predestining and eternally predestined by foreknowing.
Hence, it is clear that the predestination of God cannot exist without foreknowledge.
Indeed, foreknowledge accompanies predestination in the good and just works of God, but it stands alone in the evil works of wicked humans and angels.
The aforementioned Father, the blessed Augustine, illustrates this most concisely in "On the Predestination of the Saints," chapter 10. Also, in "On the Gift of Perseverance," chapter 14, he states that from all the words of the holy doctor, it is evident that foreknowledge and predestination must be distinctly and properly understood in the holy books. They should not be viewed as one and the same, as some might define them, despite their significant differences. However, sometimes the same doctor shows that predestination, which is never without foreknowledge, is also referred to by the name of foreknowledge, as he mentions in chapter 18: Behold what one must follow, who desires to think sanely, purely, and sincerely about divine foreknowledge and predestination according to the pious understanding of the holy Father. However, the new disputant's definition, which treats these two as one and the same with such great distinction and diligence, should rightly be utterly rejected for its falsity and deceit.
Whether he intended to define this to show that these things-as he previously mentioned-are fundamentally one in God, his assertion is empty and meaningless.
Or if he meant to teach that these things in the Scriptures should be understood without distinction, it is a clear and obvious error.
The same debater adds: A person who abandoned God by free will without effort cannot reach God without the effort of study and the gift of cooperating grace.
In these words, he first says that the person abandoned God by free will.
Certainly, in the one abandoning God and abandoned by God, there was no free will towards good-that blessed freedom commended by the Apostle saying: Where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is freedom.
Second Corinthians chapter three, verse seventeen.
But there was only free will towards evil, captive to dominating sin.
About this miserable freedom and servitude, the Apostle says to converted believers: For when you were slaves of sin, you were free from righteousness.
Romans chapter six, verse twenty.
And again: Do you not know that if you present yourselves to anyone as obedient slaves, you are slaves of the one whom you obey, either of sin, which leads to death, or of obedience, which leads to righteousness?
Romans chapter six, verse sixteen.
Hence the Lord also says: Everyone who commits sin is a slave to sin.
John chapter eight, verse thirty-three.
And the blessed apostle Peter says: For whatever overcomes a person, to that he is enslaved.
Second Peter chapter two, verse nineteen.
The blessed Paul also speaks about the captivity of sin, saying: I see another law at work in my members, waging war against the law of my mind and making me captive to the law of sin that dwells in my members.
Romans chapter seven, verse twenty-three.
Therefore, as it has been said, when man abandoned God and was abandoned by God, he became free from righteousness, which he did not want to serve, and a slave to sin leading to death, because he did not want to be a servant of obedience to righteousness.
And by this, he began to have in his members a law opposing the law of his mind, and capturing him into the law of sin.
Thus, losing the grace of true freedom, by which he could cling to God and say:
"But for me, it is good to cling to God" Psalm seventy-two, twenty-eight. He adhered to sin with the unfortunate freedom of his will and became a slave and captive of sin. From this slavery and captivity, he cannot escape or be freed except through Him who said:
"If the Son sets you free, you will be truly free" John eight, thirty-six.
And so, when man deserted God, he clearly lost the freedom to do good and remained free only to do evil. Hence, we do not understand why such a freedom should be praised in him, rather than being erased and avoided.
Moreover, what is said, that without the effort of work and the gift of cooperating grace, man cannot reach God, the Catholic faith holds otherwise, which most certainly believes, according to the gospel and apostolic truth, that no good work, no preceding merit, but only by the benefit of divine grace, man is saved and comes to God.
As the Lord Himself says:
"No one can come to me unless the Father who sent me draws him" John six, forty-four. And the Apostle diligently emphasizes to the faithful, saying:
"To the one who does not work but believes in Him who justifies the ungodly, his faith is counted as righteousness" Romans four, five.
And again:
"We conclude that a man is justified by faith apart from the works of the law" Romans three, twenty-eight.
And lest they should attribute even that faith to themselves, those who come to God and thus think they are saved by their own merit and not by the free gift of God, he shows elsewhere that even faith itself is a gift of God, when he says:
"You have been saved by grace through faith; and this is not from yourselves, it is the gift of God, not by works, so that no one can boast" Ephesians two, eight through nine.
God, as the Apostle recalls, speaks through the prophet, "I was found by those who did not seek me; I revealed myself to those who did not ask for me" (Isaiah 65:1).
Or as it is read in our edition, "Those who did not ask for me sought me, and those who did not seek me found me." This is clear evidence of grace without works, where people who weren't seeking God not only find Him but also reach Him. This is similar to countless little children who, without performing any good deeds, are brought to God through the faith of the Church and the grace of regeneration. When reborn from water and the Spirit at such a young age, they are absolved from original sin and reach God without a doubt. To think otherwise, believing that one cannot reach God without their own effort, is not Catholic but Pelagian. In a little book titled "Ecclesiastical Dogmas" by Gennadius of Marseilles, chapter 21, there is a definition. However, as we mentioned (and some other things in the same book), it contains errors of Pelagianism.
So, anyone reading it for other useful insights should remember the Apostle's advice: "Test everything; hold fast to what is good" (First Thessalonians 5:21).
He adds that predestination in God is according to substance but cannot be considered relatively.
On this, our better or more suitable interpretation has already been mentioned.
Since he added that predestination cannot be relative to God, it clearly does not refer to predestination to God as it does within the Holy Trinity-the Father to the Son, the Son to the Father, and the Holy Spirit to both.
Nor does it relate to the Word of God, where the Son is referred to the Father, whose Word He is.
Similarly, when the Son is called the image, He is referred to the Father, whose image He is.
And when He is called the brightness of glory, He is referred to the eternal light, from which He is and whose brightness He is.
For the radiance is the eternal light, Wisdom of Solomon 7:26, as Scripture attests.
Unlike the gift of God, when properly understood as the Holy Spirit, it is referred to the Father and the Son, whose gift it is.
In the holy and supreme Trinity, these things are uniquely related to each other, and no one can be said to be of the other.
There is one Father who begets, one Son who is begotten, and one Holy Spirit who proceeds: one Word, one image, and splendor of the Father, which is the only-begotten Son: one gift of God the Father and the Son, which is the Holy Spirit.
Each person is understood in such a way that the property of each cannot be transferred to another.
For example, the Father can never be called the Son, nor can the Son be naturally understood as the Father, nor the Holy Spirit as the Father or the Son.
It is clear, therefore, as we have said, that predestination is not related to God in the same way that the Father is related to the Son, the Son to the Father, and the Holy Spirit to the Father and the Son.
There is no predestination within the Trinity of persons, such that it would naturally refer to another.
However, predestination is entirely related to God, that is, to the whole Trinity, which predestines whatever is predestined.
Without a doubt, predestination is related to the predestiner, just as governance is to the governor, planning to the planner, and ordering to the orderer.
Nor has anyone ever been so absurd and inappropriately contentious as to say that God, who arranges everything, is the arrangement; who governs everything, is the governance; who orders everything, is the ordering.
We believe that no one has ever said that the one who predestines everything to be predestined is the predestination, since all these things, as we have already said-planning, governance, ordering, predestination-are more understood to refer to the works or the operation of the Creator.
But this person, even if he tries to argue that God is essentially predestination, just as He is truth, goodness, and justice-implying that predestination should be spoken of in the singular just like God, truth, goodness, and justice-cannot make it so that the predestination of God can also be substantially called God.
Nor does it have a dual effect and distribution of works, namely either in the preparation of the righteous for life or in the predetermination of the wicked for destruction.
Because even though justice is truly called God, God is not understood substantially with it, and it is rightly pronounced in the plural form.
Yet, the justice of God, which is also God, without a doubt has a dual effect: either in the reward of the good or in the condemnation of the wicked.
Therefore, when predestination is rightly referred to in relation to God who predestines, just as disposition is to the one who arranges, governance to the one who governs, ordination to the one who ordains, operation to the one who works, and creation to the one who creates, even if it can be reasoned that predestination of God should be said substantially, the dual effect declared by the unchanging truth of the Holy Scriptures cannot be nullified.
What does this excessive or even deceitful argumentation mean?
However, he continues and says: Just as it is impious to duplicate, triple, or multiply essences, wisdoms, knowledges, virtues, and all other things that are said about God, so it is impious to assert two predestinations.
To these words, we respond that this is indeed true because essence, wisdom, knowledge, and virtue, when said about God, or God Himself is understood to be essence, wisdom, knowledge, and virtue.
These are not to be spoken of in the plural.
Because the Trinity itself is not three essences, but one essence; not three wisdoms, but one wisdom; not three knowledges, but one knowledge; and not three virtues, but one virtue.
However, when referring to God's different arrangements or actions towards His creatures, it's clear that some of these are described in plural and multiple forms, as in this verse:
"For the Lord is the God of knowledge"
(First Samuel 2:3).
And if He is the Lord of knowledge, it is certainly not of another's knowledge, but His own.
How should this be understood, except that the knowledge, which in Him is naturally one and simple, becomes multiple for us when related to the disposition or ordering of creation, as mentioned before?
Similarly, God is said to be strength, and yet for the same reason we read:
"Recounting the praises of the Lord, and His strength"
(Psalm 148:2).
And just as rightly God is called strength, so rightly the same God is called power, and yet in the psalm we sing:
"Who can declare the powers of the Lord?"
(Psalm 106:2).
Therefore, if God is one knowledge, one strength, one power; yet according to the truth and authority of Scripture, we rightly say of God in the plural and multiple form-the Lord of knowledge, the powers of the Lord, and His strengths-why does this disputant say that it is impious, when it proceeds from the source of truth and piety?
If those things which truly and substantially exist in God are not impiously but piously spoken of in the plural form about God, how is he guilty of impiety who wishes to speak of God's predestination in the same way, because of its double efficiency?
Although we neither reject this because of the truly double efficiency of predestination, nor do we necessarily think it must be said in this way: just as one justice of God, one predestination of God must certainly be understood to have multiple effects.
He adds and says: There is one divine predestination, just as there is one divine operation, wisdom, substance, will.
In these words, he tries to achieve what he did above, namely that just as God is substantially wisdom, substantially will, and He is the highest substance, so it is believed that the same God is predestination and operation.
But regarding predestination, we have already explained our beliefs in various ways.
Now, concerning the single operation of God, which He mentions here, we need to carefully consider what should be thought about this matter according to our faith.
We rightly speak of the operation of God in the creatures He has made, and we can also rightly speak of an operation from God, because, as the Apostle says: "From Him, and through Him, and for Him are all things."
But can we rightly say there is an operation in God, when God does not operate within Himself? All creatures He has made and in which He still operates exist outside of Him, that is, outside of His nature.
However, in another sense, we can say that the creature exists in Him, because it subsists in His power and virtue. Hence, the Apostle says, as already mentioned, that "in Him all things exist"; and in another place: "For in Him we live and move and have our being" (Acts 17:28).
Since God does not operate within His own substance, but His operation is understood to be in creatures, which are not of the same nature or substance as Him, how can it be rightly said that there is an operation in God?
And if it is not rightly said that there is an operation in God, how much less can it be said that God Himself is the operation?
Although the omnipotent God organizes all things within Himself and in Himself, He operates all things within Himself and in Himself.
To perform these actions, He does not go outside Himself nor exceeds Himself, as His willing is doing.
Rather, He calls to Himself the things He operates, so that each may receive being from Him, who supremely is, according to its own mode.
This fulfills what the Apostle says: "Who calls into existence the things that do not exist as though they were" (Romans 4:17).
Therefore, He does not operate anything outside of Himself.
With His sole and eternal will, without any effort, labor, or artifice, He operates all things.
Nor does He operate anything within Himself, as in the perfection and eternity of His substance, He achieves nothing, increases nothing, diminishes nothing, and changes nothing.
However, this does not mean that because His will is done, His will and the act of doing are the same.
This does not signify a unity between Creator and creature, but rather the power of the Creator alone.
So, how can an operation in God, or God Himself, be substantially understood as an operation, as this person asserts?
Unless perhaps it is said that God is an operation, not because someone or something operates in Him, but because He Himself operates everything.
But because this is too unusual, not taken from the authority of sacred Scripture, and very dangerous to faith, lest, when God is said to be an operation, according to the impious error of the Arians, who believed this about the Son and the Holy Spirit, it might be believed that He was made by someone: surely the presumption of such verbosity should be restrained and curbed, and like other novelties of words, as the Apostle very attentively warns, should be avoided.
First Timothy 6:20.
And yet we, who simply understand the divine operation in His works and creatures, read that His operation is placed in plural form in the Scriptures, with the Apostle clearly saying: "There are different kinds of gifts, but the same Spirit; and there are different kinds of service, but the same Lord; and there are different kinds of working, but the same God works all of them in all men." First Corinthians 12:4-6.
Therefore, since the operation of God is so openly said in the plural and is understood in various ways in God's creatures, what utility does such an argument have? It is useless for anything, as the Apostle says, except for the ruin of those who listen. Second Timothy 2:14.
And yet he adds and says: Nothing is compelled by the necessity of predestination, just as neither is the will. Both of these, that is, nothing is compelled by either God's predestination or will, are most clearly false: because by the goodness of God's predestination, the elect are frequently compelled by various scourges, labors, and tribulations, whether to turn to God or to live according to God. Just as the Apostle Paul was compelled when he was still Saul. Acts.
Struck down by the terror of the heavenly voice and blinded by divine intervention, he was restrained from his error and cruelty by such terror, surely to convert him to God.
And yet, already converted, already an apostle, already made a teacher of the nations, he is still chastised, still battered, so that he does not become proud because of the greatness of his revelations.
Second Corinthians 12:7.
By the judgment and fairness of the same divine predestination, the wicked are compelled; and if not to live wickedly and impiously, at least to pay eternal punishment for their wickedness and impiety.
Similarly, by the goodness of God's will, in which there is surely the eternal predestination of God, the chosen are scourged temporarily for correction or testing, and by the severity of the same divine will, the wicked are scourged eternally for punishment.
As the omnipotent God, as the Apostle says, with manifest mercy and hidden judgment, has mercy on whom He wills and hardens whom He wills.
Romans 9:18.
For both are in God's predestination, both are in God's will, namely goodness and severity, about which the same Apostle says: "Behold therefore the goodness and severity of God: on those who fell, severity; but on you, goodness, if you continue in goodness."
Romans 11:22.
Section 8:
He follows and says: And whatever is understood about the divine will should be felt about the predestination of God.
This definition pleases us because it states that the will of God is the predestination of God.
For what else is God's predestination than the eternal and unchangeable will of God for His works?
For God did not predestine by necessity but by will whatever He predestined.
And just as He has done all things that He willed.
Psalm 113:3.
So He has fulfilled all things that He predestined, indeed has already done them: as the prophet says of Him: "Who made the things that are to come."
Isaiah 45:11 according to the Septuagint.
Therefore, it is entirely consistent with what the Apostle says about God, who wills all men to be saved and to come to the knowledge of the truth.
First Timothy 2:4.
As it is in the predestination of God, it should be most accurately understood as the will of God.
That is, those whom God has predestined by His eternal will, chosen from all humankind, He wills all of them to be saved and to come to the knowledge of the truth.
Namely because the predestination of God is certainly the will of God.
Just as it has been truly said about the will of God by the apostle, "He has mercy on whom He wills, and He hardens whom He wills" (Romans 9:18), so it should also be most certainly held about the predestination of God:
Namely that by eternal predestination, just as by His eternal will, He loved Jacob and hated Esau, and from the same lump made one vessel for honor and another for dishonor (Romans 13:21).
But He did this by His goodness for one, and by His just judgment for the other, so that some are vessels of wrath and others are vessels of mercy (Romans 22:23).
Therefore, if this disputant, according to the truth of apostolic doctrine, and as he himself has concluded by his argumentation, holds these things with us faithfully and simply, there will be no need for questioning, no effort required for syllogistic disputation.
Only the tranquility of peace will reign among us.
Chapter Three
In this chapter, he introduces these definitions.
One.
God's predestination, like His essence, forces no one and imposes no necessity.
Two. There are not two predestinations. Three.
Death, sin, and misery are not from God.
Four.
Predestination, like love, is not dual, double, or multiple, and lacks plurality.
We've already discussed these four propositions as allowed by the Lord.
The first states that God's predestination, like His essence, forces no one and imposes no necessity.
The second states that there are not two predestinations.
The fourth states that predestination, like love, is not dual, double, or multiple, and lacks plurality.
However, above, he did not mention love among the examples he wanted to be understood from the substance of God.
And clearly, as the blessed Apostle John teaches: God is love First John 4:16;
so that according to the rule of true faith, we rightly say that there is the love of God, and that there is love in God, and that God is love.
This love, since it is substance in God, like truth, justice, and goodness, when understood about God,
is not said to be dual, because it is substantially one and simple in Him;
and therefore it cannot be called double or triple, because the divine substance is not doubled or tripled; it is the deity itself, the truth itself, the love itself, the Trinity of God.
For it is not less in one than in three; nor greater in two or three than in one.
But as great as deity, truth, and love is in one person of the Holy Trinity, so great it is in two, so great it is in three, that is, perfect in each, perfect in all.
Because the Father is perfect God, and the Son is perfect God, and the Holy Spirit is perfect God, and these three are one perfect God.
In us, however, this love is not substance, but a gift of God, as the Apostle says:
Because the love of God has been poured out into our hearts through the Holy Spirit who has been given to us Romans 5:5.
And so, it can exist within us both twin and double, due to the two commandments of love: love of God and love of neighbor.
This creates in us a dual affection, so we love God with all our heart and our neighbor as ourselves.
(Matthew 22:37, 39).
And because through this gift of love, God works many and countless good deeds in His saints, it is also called manifold in the Scriptures.
For it is the grace of God, about which the blessed apostle Peter says:
"Each of you should use whatever gift you have received to serve others, as faithful stewards of God's grace in its various forms."
(First Peter 4:10).
But who does not know that love lacks plurality and is not found in plural form in either God or us in the Scriptures?
Regarding the statement that predestination does not receive a plural number just like love, it has been sufficiently discussed above and does not need to be repeated constantly.
For even the proposition that compares God's predestination to God's substance, or rather says it is the substance of God, has already been discussed as best we could.
And when he affirms that God's predestination forces no one and imposes no necessity, if he means that by His predestination, the omnipotent God compels no one to do evil, to be evil, and to be nothing else, he is absolutely right.
But if he left this vague and unexplained, to say that predestination forces no one and imposes no necessity, and did not add what it compels or what necessity it imposes, so as to deny that those who persist in their wickedness to the end are to be punished by the just judgment of divine predestination, he clearly accepts divine predestination in part and denies it in part.
By the same predestination of God, He has prepared the righteous for the kingdom but has not preordained the reprobate for punishment.
The third proposition that remains here and is defined is that death, sin, and misery are not from God.
Indeed, regarding sin, as the universal Catholic faith holds, it is rightly said that sin is not from God.
God neither willed, commanded, nor drove man to sin.
In fact, before man sinned, God forbade him from sinning and warned him with the penalty of death to deter him from sinning.
After the sin, God justly punished man as rebellious and contrary to His will.
Therefore, sin is not from God, who created man upright and without sin.
As Ecclesiasticus says, "This only have I found: that God made man upright, but they have sought out many inventions" (Ecclesiasticus 7:30).
The origin of sin is from the one who first sinned in heaven and later deceived man to sin, thereby killing him in paradise.
As the Apostle John testifies, "the devil has sinned from the beginning" (First John 3:8).
The Lord Himself teaches, saying, "He was a murderer from the beginning, and did not abide in the truth, because there is no truth in him" (John 8:44).
In not abiding in the truth, the devil destroyed himself.
By offering sin to man, he killed man.
Just as he was the first sinner, he also became the first murderer, because "the soul that sins shall die" (Ezekiel 18:4).
Thus, the Scriptures say he has the power of death (Hebrews 2:14).
Not by his own power, but because his malicious envy brought death to all mankind.
Hence, the Scripture says, "By the envy of the devil, death entered the world: and they who are of his party imitate him" (Wisdom 2:24).
This impious dominion of his, the Lord destroyed by His own death, as the Apostle says: "That through death He might destroy him who had the power of death, that is, the devil" (Hebrews 2:14).
He is the Lamb of God who takes away the sin of the world (John 1:29).
So, this disputant rightly said that sin is not from God.
However, he unnecessarily mentioned this when defining divine predestination, because no believer says that God has predestined sins.
However, the statement that death and misery are not from God contradicts Scripture, which says: "Good and bad, life and death, poverty and wealth are from God"
Ecclesiasticus 11:14.
But since Scripture also says: "God did not make death, nor does He delight in the destruction of the living"
Wisdom 1:13, we must carefully inquire how both statements can be faithfully understood: namely, that God did not make death, and that both death and life are from God.
Thus, both can be rightly understood in this way: God did not make death, as He created man immortal if he had not sinned.
And again, death is from God, because He justly condemned the sinning man to death; thus, death is not from Him by creation, but it is truly from Him as a punishment.
Just as this physical death, which is primarily understood, is from God because it was justly inflicted by Him on sinning man; so also the second death in hell is justly to be inflicted on man remaining in sin by Him.
Therefore, both this first death, which separates the soul from the body, and the second death, through which both soul and body are lost in hell, because they are just and are inflicted or to be inflicted on man by the just judgment of God, are from God.
Thus, elsewhere the same Scripture speaks of the present physical death: "Do not fear the judgment of death: remember those who were before you and those who are to come after you"
Ecclesiasticus 41:5.
This judgment is from the Lord upon all flesh.
And again: "Fire, hail, famine, and death, all these were created for vengeance"
Ecclesiasticus 39:29.
And how were famine and death created? Not, of course, by any form or formation that they might exist as created things, but they were prepared in the hidden plan of God for His vengeance; so that their coming into the open may seem like a creation of sorts.
And again the same Scripture says: "Death, bloodshed, strife, and the sword, calamities, famine, tribulation, and the scourge: these were all created for the wicked, and for their sake, the flood was made"
Ecclesiasticus 40:9-10.
Since human death, which comes from just and divine retribution, is so clearly stated and truthfully understood in the Scriptures to be from God, it is evident.
Thus, the blessed Elijah, praying for the son of the widow with whom he was staying, said to God: "Lord, have you also afflicted this widow with whom I am barely sustained, to kill her son?" First Kings Seventeen Twenty.
And the Lord openly says in the Gospel: "Fear him who, after he has killed, has the power to cast into hell" Luke Twelve Five.
The clear truth of Scripture should be understood, and vanity should be silenced.
Just as death, which is indeed the punishment for sin, so too all the misery of toil, tribulations, and calamities that have followed humanity after sin, because they were inflicted and are inflicted by divine disposition and judgment, Scripture rightly says they are from God, as the testimonies we have cited clearly show.
Therefore, just as sin, which is contrary to the righteousness of God, is truly not from God, so too the punishment for sin, that is death, and all the calamity and misery that followed, because they are deserved by God's just judgment and are inflicted by His just retribution, are rightly understood to be from God, as Scripture attests.
Even if the devil and other evil angels act in some way, they are ministers of divine retribution and vengeance, not judges or authors, as the history in the books of the blessed Job clearly shows.
It is fully shown there that not only did he dare to wound Job with a grievous sore from the sole of his foot to the top of his head, or kill his children by the collapse of the house, or destroy his abundant family by the sword of invading robbers or by fire from heaven, but he did not even dare to touch his livestock and animals unless the Lord first permitted him, saying: "Behold, all that he has is in your hand; only against him do not stretch out your hand" Job One Twelve.
And again: "Behold, he is in your hand; but spare his life" Job Two Six.
The holy man, filled with divine wisdom, did not attribute his calamities to the devil, even though the devil was the executor.
Instead, he humbly and faithfully referred everything to God and His just judgment, with thanksgiving, saying:
"The Lord gave, and the Lord has taken away; as it has pleased the Lord, so it has been done. Blessed be the name of the Lord."
Job 1:12.
Similarly, in the Gospel, when a legion of demons was cast out from a possessed man, they couldn't enter and destroy the herd of pigs without permission. They said, trembling and sorrowful:
"If you cast us out, send us into the herd of pigs."
And he said to them:
"Go."
Matthew 8:32.
In the psalm recounting the plagues and calamities that befell Egypt for their impiety, with God justly avenging and Moses mediating, Scripture refers everything to God, even if some were inflicted through evil angels. It says:
"He turned their rivers into blood, and their streams, so they could not drink. He sent among them swarms of flies, which devoured them, and frogs, which destroyed them. He gave their crops to the caterpillar, and their labor to the locust. He destroyed their vines with hail, and their sycamore trees with frost. He gave their cattle also to the hail, and their flocks to hot thunderbolts. He sent upon them the fierceness of His anger, wrath, indignation, and trouble, a band of destroying angels."
Psalm 78:44-49.
In another psalm, recounting the onslaught of fire, hail, storms, and tempests, which cause shipwreck, destruction, and devastation, it similarly refers everything to God, saying:
"Fire, hail, snow, frost, stormy wind, fulfilling His word."
Psalm 148:8.
Chapter Four
In this chapter, five definitions are presented in the following order.
1.
Three heresies: The first is from the Pelagians, who promote free will without the need for grace.
The second argues for grace alone.
The third, associated with Gottschalk, introduces the necessity of predestination.
2.
The substance of humanity consists of three things: being, willing, and knowing.
This substance is not lost through sinning.
3.
No nature can perish, nor can free will lose its essence.
4.
Freedom remained in humans after sin, though its vigor and power were lost.
5.
This nature can only begin and complete actions through grace.
Regarding the three heresies mentioned, the first from the Pelagians posits that free will without God's grace is sufficient for human salvation.
This has been well known and condemned by the Church.
The Church follows the voice of the Lord, who commends His grace in all things, and says:
"Whoever remains in me, and I in him, bears much fruit, for without me you can do nothing" (John 15:5).
In saying, "Whoever remains in me, and I in him, bears much fruit," He declares the benefit of grace, which those who remain in Him receive, enabling them to bear fruit for God, just as a branch receives sustenance from the root of the vine. But by adding, "For without me you can do nothing," He clearly shows that human free will, without the help of His grace, can achieve nothing in terms of good works.
The second heresy concerns grace alone: what this is or was in the Church, which preached that only God's grace saves humans to the extent that it denied or destroyed human free will, is unknown to us.
The very ancient and impious heretics Marcion, Valentinus, and Manichaeus introduced two or three principles and therefore asserted two natures for either angels or humans - one good and the other evil.
They claimed that the good nature is so good that it cannot be anything else, and conversely, the evil nature is so evil that it similarly cannot be anything else.
They said nothing at all about the grace of God, but foolishly tried to defend that nature is either good or evil by nature alone.
However, the Catholic Church, instructed and fortified by the faithful teachings of the Law and the Gospel, recognizes and preaches only one principle of all creatures, heavenly and earthly, visible and invisible, namely the Holy Trinity - the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, one God, from whom all things come, through whom all things exist, and in whom all things are.
The Church asserts that no nature exists except from Him, the best Creator, and therefore every nature, insofar as it is nature, is good, and that the evil in nature is not the nature itself but a defect of nature.
This nature in created beings, both angelic and human, has been made mutable and, by its own fault, could fall from the good in which it was created to evil.
From the evil into which it has fallen, as far as it pertains to the human race that is saved by God's mercy, it can rise and be reformed to good.
In the case of the part of the evil angels who are damned by perpetual judgment, they have fallen from God through pride in such a way that they no longer deserve any remedy to be restored, not only having lost the good will in which they were created, but also being deprived of the possibility of that good will by the dreadful judgment of the Creator.
So, since those heretics have either defended nature as being immutably good or accused it of being immutably bad, it's unclear how they could preach about grace or free will.
On the other hand, the Church of God holds, as we briefly mentioned: what is this second heresy, so unknown, so new and unheard of, that denies free will and preaches only grace?
Unless, as it seems to us, this disputant secretly accuses the blessed Augustine of being a heretic, because he clearly shows and teaches according to the truth of the Scriptures that only by the grace of God can a person be saved.
Human will contributes nothing to this eternal salvation unless it has been reformed, healed, enlightened, and restored by that same grace.
Or certainly, he accuses those who, according to Augustine's venerable and catholic doctrine, now feel and teach about the grace of God.
As if they understand his words less, he calls them heretics.
Namely, as if he did not feel the same way about free will, nor do they rightly understand his words.
And so, they err due to the occasion of his words, while they understand them differently than the one who wrote them.
For this reason, it seems to us that he very cunningly and slyly proposed the heresy of grace alone, yet did not reveal its author or followers in any way.
If this is the case, what else does he do but accuse the Church of our time, together with those who provoke him to such things, with the subtlety of a viper?
And therefore, if there are such people in the regions of his kingdom, where this attacker of truth is not only not rebuked or silenced, but is even held in the highest praise and honor, who support him in such matters, especially ecclesiastical men, who could rightly feel sorrow and horror at this evil of contagion and pestilence, that rises so unrestrainedly and shamelessly from those regions against the other parts of the Church of God, which are peaceful, tranquil, and calm among themselves?
Where such a monster and prodigy has long been kept away from the ears of the faithful, it sits, argues, and spreads numerous lies and insults against the faith.
With no vigilance from the shepherds of the Church, it is neither corrected nor expelled.
Finally, to clarify that he did not refer to any older heresy that preached grace, he placed this heresy after the Pelagian, from the times of Saint Augustine until now.
In all this time, no such heresy existed in the Church, except that he accuses either the blessed Augustine, as we have already mentioned, or us who follow him, of this error.
He identifies a third heresy as imposing necessity and force through predestination.
Its author, as he believes, he does not remain silent about, calling it the Gotteschalcanan, after a very unfortunate monk named Gotteschalcus, who was imprisoned for many years.
If Gotteschalcus taught something so dangerous against the Catholic faith that it deserved such severe condemnation by a synodical decree, it would have been standard practice for the Church to communicate this to other Churches to prevent the spread of such an error.
Even if not at the beginning or the end, at least afterward through synodical and ecclesiastical letters, to inform all the brothers and fellow bishops.
If this had been done according to the ecclesiastical custom always observed by the Fathers, as we have said, we would now be better prepared to refute and convince those who propose that he taught necessity and force through predestination.
Therefore, regarding the accusations about predestination being spoken of in the plural, it is clear, as we have demonstrated many times before, that it is not the plural form of the term "predestination" that bothers him, but rather the actual plural nature of predestination itself. This includes its twofold effect: both the preparation of the elect for life and the preordaining of the reprobate for punishment, as we have frequently mentioned and shown from the Holy Scriptures.
To deny this, contrary to the faith of the Church, he has undertaken a great and tedious effort, attempting to persuade us with new arguments that predestination is the essence of God, or even that God Himself is predestination. Therefore, he argues, it should not be understood in the plural sense; that is, predestination should be considered only for the elect and not at all for the reprobate.
From this stance, to nullify the just predestination of the reprobate to eternal punishment, he has ventured into such audacity that he clearly attempts to assert, against the faith and the truth of the Scriptures, that just as sin is not from God, neither is its punishment. In other words, all misery and death that follow a person's sin are not from God.
When, clearly by God's just condemnation and judgment, the misery of labor and toil is inflicted on the sinner, along with the ultimate misery of death itself, as the Lord said about the hardships of a laborious life: "Cursed is the ground because of you; in toil you shall eat of it all the days of your life; thorns and thistles it shall bring forth for you; and you shall eat the plants of the field. By the sweat of your face you shall eat bread" Genesis 3:17-19.
Immediately after, He added the ultimate penalty of death: "Until you return to the ground, for out of it you were taken; you are dust, and to dust you shall return" Genesis 3:19.
And to the woman, who sinned before her husband, He imposed the specific penalty of her sin, in addition to the common penalty shared with her husband, saying: "I will greatly increase your pangs in childbearing; in pain you shall bring forth children" Genesis 3:16.
By denying the just predestination of divine judgment in the case of the condemned, he asserts that all human miseries and even death are not from God.
In other words, they do not pertain to God's judgment.
If asked where death and misery come from, if not from God, what remains but to falsely claim either that they come from nowhere or that they come from the devil.
Saying they come from nowhere is utterly insane.
However, the devil only suggests causes for sinning; the punishment for sin is not inflicted by him, but by the just judge.
Regarding the aforementioned Gottschalk imposing necessity and force with predestination: if he means that the predestination of the condemned forces them to do evil, making them inevitably evil and unable to be anything else, this is entirely contrary to the Catholic faith.
Because it is highly absurd and impious to say that the almighty God (who wants no one to be evil) compels and forces anyone to be evil, and (of whom it is written: The Lord is just and loves just deeds ) forces anyone to be unjust.
Psalm 10:8.
This happens with all the condemned, regarding their sins and ultimate punishment, which was enacted in the first man sinning through the first judgment.
Just as he was not compelled by any impulse or predestination from God to sin, but sinned of his own accord, yet unwillingly and reluctantly accepted the judgment and condemnation of his sin, which was the first punishment of man.
So also the entire multitude of the condemned, descending from that condemnation, is not compelled by God's predestination to sin, since God has predestined no sins.
Nevertheless, by the just and eternal judgment of divine predestination, they are compelled to undergo punishment; receiving from God the force and necessity of just condemnation, which had no force or necessity for perpetrating iniquity.
For those who will stand on the left at the judgment and face eternal fire, they will not willingly accept such punishment.
They will be unwilling, reluctant, and filled with unending sorrow and trembling as they are cast down by the command of divine majesty and the ministry of angels.
As the Lord clearly says in the Gospel:
"So it will be at the end of the age: the angels will come out and separate the evil from the righteous, and throw them into the furnace of fire; there men will weep and gnash their teeth."
Matthew 13:40-42.
To these reapers, that is, the angelic ministers, when the harvest, which is the end of the age, comes, it will be said by the judge himself:
"Gather the weeds first and bind them in bundles to be burned, but gather the wheat into my barn."
Matthew 13:30.
Behold the force and necessity of divine predestination towards the reprobate that the Church of God believes according to the gospel truth. This is the force and necessity of judgment, not the force and necessity of sin. Whoever says that God has imposed or imposes the force and necessity of sinning on man clearly blasphemes horribly against God, asserting that by compelling them to sin, He confirms Himself as the author of sin.
Thus, we, according to God's truth, think about the predestination of the reprobate, faithfully confessing Him not as the author of their sin, but of their just punishment. Therefore, what this person raves about, as if the preaching of this predestination is an imposition of the necessity to sin, we consider slanderous and vain, as is evident from what has been said.
After this, he adds:
The substance of man is threefold: being, willing, and knowing; and this, he has not lost by sinning. But we say that the substance of man is nothing other than what the divine Scripture shows at the beginning of human creation, saying:
"Then the Lord God formed man of dust from the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and man became a living being."
Genesis 2:7.
This is the essence of a human being, through which they live and exist, as both the learned and unlearned know: the soul and the body vitally connected to it.
The body is made from the dust of the earth, and the soul from God's inspiration.
With these, a human being is formed and becomes a living soul.
Since divine authority teaches this and Catholic truth upholds it, what is the purpose of this excess, claiming that the substance of a human being is three things: being, willing, and knowing?
It is clear that the substance of a human being is not three things but two: the soul and the body.
But this person, ignoring the body, which is naturally part of a human being, says that the substance of a human being is being, willing, and knowing, which are attributes of the soul alone, as if the substance of a human being were only the soul.
It seems that he took the opportunity to say these things from the disputations of Saint Augustine in the books on the Trinity; but it is far-fetched to think that such a great teacher would ever speak so absurdly and ignorantly as to define the substance of a human being, which is the soul and body, as being, willing, and knowing.
Therefore, he did not say (as can be clearly understood by anyone who has carefully read and considered his words in those same books) that the substance of a human being is these three things: being, knowing, and willing; but he taught that these things exist within the substance of a human being, not externally but internally, that is, in the rational mind, where a human being was created in the image and likeness of God Genesis 1:26.
He taught that these things are naturally and substantially implanted by God in the rational and intellectual mind itself.
Hence, he rightly says in those disputations that these three things are of one substance with the mind itself and within the mind itself.
Just as the mind substantially has being, it also substantially has willing: that is, it naturally has the ability to know and the ability to will.
This is indeed a great good of nature, wonderfully and excellently created by the best Creator.
But if the human mind only has the ability to exist, to know, and to will, and does not have the gift from its Creator to exist well and happily, to know rightly about its Creator, and to will to be with Him by loving Him, what benefit is it to have existence, knowledge, and will?
When these abilities are to its own detriment without that gift from its Creator, they become meaningless.
For without this gift, it will exist unhappily, know deceitfully, and will destructively and wickedly.
Just like the angelic nature condemned in the devil and his angels, which certainly possesses existence, knowledge, and will in its spiritual substance.
However, its existence is in punishment, and its knowledge and will are entirely turned to error and evil.
So why boast that human nature has not lost these abilities through sinning-existence, knowledge, and will-when it has completely lost the good and happiness of all these?
It has become miserable from being blessed, losing divine knowledge and heavenly will.
Unless it is later assisted and raised by the grace of the Creator, it would not recognize the lost goods, feel sorrow for them, and by feeling sorrow and repenting, implore divine help.
Thus, what it lost by its own fault, it would regain by divine goodness.
Therefore, the ineffable mercy of the Creator did not take away even these natural goods-existence, knowledge, and will-even after sin, so that He would have someone to have mercy on.
For if He had not wanted him to exist after sin, then certainly, along with him and in him, knowledge and will would also perish.
So He wanted him to exist, so that He would have someone to have mercy on; He wanted him to know, so that He would have someone to illuminate with His knowledge; He wanted him to will, so that He would have someone to bless with His love.
Thus, the devil, who wanted to destroy God's creation, remained defeated, and the Creator's goodness and mercy remained undefeated.
But why he proposed this will become clearer from his subsequent propositions.
For he immediately added after these two connected propositions and said: No nature can perish, nor did he lose free will, that is, his own nature.
In these words, it was stated that no nature can perish; this was said generally about the nature of all things.
Where did he learn this, or how did he show it to be true?
Clearly, the entire nature of things could exist from nothing by the will of the Creator, so that it was something that did not exist before; likewise, if He wishes, it can perish and return to nothing, so that it no longer exists.
Scripture shows this by speaking of the greatness and power of the Creator: "He is higher than the heavens, so what can you do? He is deeper than hell, so how will you know? His measure is longer than the earth and wider than the sea. If He overturns everything or confines it to one point, who can resist Him? Or who can say to Him: Why do you do this?" Job 11:8-10.
Certainly, the omnipotent Creator, when preparing to destroy the world with a flood because of the extreme wickedness and impiety of humans, said through the testimony of Scripture: "I will destroy man whom I have created from the face of the earth, from man to animal, from creeping things to the birds of the sky." Genesis 6:7. And again: "The earth is filled with violence because of them, and I will destroy them with the earth." Genesis 6:13.
Therefore, just as with that great and dreadful flood, a large part of the world's nature was destroyed and changed for the worse, as it had been said: "And I will destroy them with the earth." Almost the entire nature of animals, that is, both humans and livestock, was destroyed by water: even the souls of the wicked, who deserved to perish by such a dreadful punishment, were reserved and passed on to greater, that is, infernal punishment; only those who were saved in the ark by the mercy of God, in such a small number, were delivered.
Could He not (if He wished) destroy the entire nature of the world and all worldly or heavenly things with the astonishing power of the Creator, as is clearly shown in the books of the Maccabees?
Certain holy men, preparing to fight against their adversaries, are recorded to have said: "But we trust in the omnipotent God who can destroy both these enemies coming against us and the entire world with one gesture." Second Maccabees 8:18.
You should ask him about that final conflagration of the world, which the blessed Apostle Peter talks about:
In which the heavens will pass away with a great noise, and the elements will melt with fervent heat
Second Peter 3:10.
What does he think will happen then to the nature of the four elements of the world?
If they remain as they are now, how is that apostolic statement true?
But if they are mostly changed or destroyed, how is this definition true, that no nature can perish?
Certainly, the four seasons-spring, summer, autumn, and winter-each have their own distinct qualities.
But when there is a new heaven and a new earth, and the course of the sun, moon, and stars, which now continuously succeed each other for the refreshment and rest of mortals, ceases,
and thus those four seasons, conducted by the sun's course, cannot exist as they do now, how will their nature not perish?
And he should also be asked what he believes will happen when the heaven and earth are renewed by fire and transformed into a different quality that suits the immortal bodies of the saints.
What, I ask, does he believe will happen to the entire nature of birds, quadrupeds, reptiles, and aquatic creatures?
If it is believed that they will be completely consumed in that immense conflagration because the renewed world will no longer accept anything mortal,
how will it be true that no nature can perish?
Especially since it is written about the sea of such vastness in that miraculous change of things:
And the sea is no more.
If he had said that human nature cannot perish, he might be heard to some extent,
not because God cannot dissolve it if He wishes, but because the promise of our Lord cannot be nullified,
as He Himself promised, saying:
But the very hairs of your head are all numbered
Matthew 10:30.
And in another place:
Not a hair of your head will perish
Luke 21:18.
When he says that no nature can perish, let him consider what has also happened to rational beings like the devil and his angels.
By divine and terrible judgment, they not only lost the will to do good but also the ability to desire that good.
After stating that no nature can perish, he immediately includes free will by adding: Man did not lose his free will, that is, his nature.
It's as if, by his false and deceptive argument, he has proven to us that man did not lose his free will by sinning; because, according to him, free will is man's nature.
However, we say, according to the truth of the Catholic faith, that the nature of the first man was created entirely good and endowed with a good will by the good Creator.
As Scripture says in the book of Ecclesiastes, chapter seven, verse twenty-nine, God created man upright, so he not only had a naturally good and free will but also could remain in the state in which he was created, needing and being helped by divine grace.
Hence, from his perspective, the psalm saying is understood: "In my prosperity I said, 'I shall never be moved.'" He immediately adds about his fall and sorrowfully says to God: "You hid your face, and I was troubled." The abundance of good will and blessed freedom before sin was from God; to whom he says: "Lord, by your favor you have made my mountain stand strong." But when God turned his face away, not illuminating him with his countenance, he became troubled, which was both the merit and punishment of sin.
This one, however, who, without the aid of divine grace, praises the good of nature alone so much that he argues free will was not lost by sinning, saying that free will is part of human nature, is clearly involved in the Pelagian error.
He claims that humans had free will solely by nature both before and after sinning and did not lose it, and that free will is part of their nature.
However, it was not truly free except when it remained piously subjected to God and good.
But when it sinned by disobeying God and arrogantly breaking His command, it immediately became enslaved to sin.
Because, as the Lord Himself says:
"Everyone who commits sin is a slave to sin" (John 8:34, 36).
And so, what was once free to do good, after that miserable fall, could not be free except to do evil.
From this deep pit of damnation, it cannot rise to the freedom of good will without being freed by Him who said:
"If the Son makes you free, you will be truly free."
This one, who thinks that free will was not lost by sinning because it was created with a good and free will, and therefore naturally had the affection of good will, should know that almighty God created every rational creature, both humans and angels, endowed with good and upright will.
As long as they maintained their order, piously subjected to God and aided by His grace, their dignity remained in them, that is, both the good of nature and the gift of grace.
But if, by pride against the Creator and presuming on their own strength, they abandoned the order of their subjection and obedience, they would immediately, by the just judgment of their Creator, be deprived of the gift of grace, and their nature would turn for the worse.
Hence it is written in the psalm:
"Man, when he was in honor, did not understand; he was compared to the foolish beasts and became like them" (Psalm 84:13, 21).
Before sin, human nature, created by God, was honored by the grace given to it.
But Adam did not understand the source of this divine goodness and grace.
When he abandoned the Creator, relied on himself, and, with the serpent's suggestion, desired to be like God without any master, he was deservedly abandoned by the Creator.
As a result, he was completely corrupted, both in soul and body.
The soul, having lost the freedom of justice and good will, was oppressed by sin, ceased to seek higher things, and desired lower things like a brute or a beast.
The body, condemned to the condition of death, was destined to return to the earth and dust from which it was taken, accepting the sentence of just judgment.
Behold the great evil to which human nature has fallen, wholly corrupted by sin, having lost the freedom for good, and free only to desire evil, unless it is healed and restored by the grace of Him who came to seek and save what was lost Luke 19:10.
As for the angelic nature, it has been depraved and horrifically corrupted in the devil and his angels, having lost free will for good.
They not only cannot rise to it but cannot even desire it, and have turned to unchangeable malice for only evil.
Who can rightfully dread, let alone explain in words, the extent of this corruption?
For the nature of the body itself is both healthy and sick: what thrives and flourishes in good health, when lost, is turned into worse, weighed down, and afflicted by the disease of sickness.
But anyone who does not believe that free will and free choice for good are beneficial for the human mind, but that the mind itself is good, seems to misunderstand, as we have already said, some words of Saint Augustine in his books on the Trinity.
Chapter 10, verses 11 and 12, truthfully and completely state that both the mind and its knowledge, by which it understands itself, and the will of the mind, by which it desires and loves itself, are naturally one substance.
This substance exists as it is, knows itself through understanding, and desires itself through love.
Indeed, the mind, its knowledge, and its love are all one substance.
However, it is not claimed that the knowledge and will of the mind, by which it understands and loves itself, are the mind of a person, but rather they reside in the mind of a person.
Thus, the flaw in this argument is evident.
When discussing free will, which allows a person to desire either good or evil, it is not about the will by which the mind loves itself.
Instead, it refers to the will by which it loves the highest good-God-when righteous, or the lowest good-the world-when corrupt.
This will, though of the same nature as the will by which the mind loves itself, differs greatly in affection-as much as the love of oneself differs from the love of God or from the love of the world.
By this will, the mind loves itself; by that will, it either loves God above itself or the world below itself.
As we have said, it is of one nature but varies in affection.
It is singular in the love of oneself and diverse in the love of good or bad things, by which it is either attracted or distracted.
Therefore, since the will of nature, which Blessed Augustine discusses, by which the mind loves itself, has nothing to do with the free will by which good or bad things are desired, but pertains only to the mind and refers to itself, it is less clever-or too foolish-to call it free will.
Blessed Augustine never says this, and it is unthinkable that he would.
After all, who does not know that this will of the mind, by which it desires and loves itself, is naturally common to all people and always operates freely?
What human mind, except for those who are insane or mad, does not naturally desire to exist, to live, and to remain unharmed?
To this end, the will of all minds is free.
What could be freer than a will that loves its own mind, loves to exist, loves to live, and loves not to perish?
And what could be more redundant than calling such a will free, when it can never be anything else but a love for itself or its mind?
Or calling it free choice when it cannot be considered a choice unless it involves different matters that need to be discerned, judged, chosen, or rejected?
The will of the mind finds no diversity within itself but always loves itself equally and clings to itself in natural peace and unity.
Therefore, let us refrain from saying, when discussing human free will-which chooses either good for salvation or evil for destruction-that the will of the mind is simply nature.
While it is true that the mind's will loves both itself and other things, it loves itself with an unchanging, natural affection, and it loves other things with a variable affection that can change, turning to either good or evil.
If the mind's will, which loves other things, either good or evil, were the nature of humans, as some suggest, it would be only good or evil and could not change from one to the other.
Therefore, this will-such an affection of human will according to the truth of the Scriptures-was implanted in humans by the good Creator as good and upright when they were created.
This will remained good and upright with the cooperation of God's grace as long as it piously obeyed the Creator.
But because human nature itself was created mutable by the unchangeable Creator, and the affection of the human mind is similarly mutable, it stood in good with God's grace and fell to evil by God's hidden judgment when that grace was abandoned.
And, as has often been said, what was once free for good, having lost that happy freedom, fell under the miserable slavery of sin.
He adds, as if defining, that freedom remained for man after sin, but its vigor and power were lost.
We need not dwell longer on these words because, as we have frequently mentioned, the one who had free will, good nature, and the gift of grace aimed at the highest and eternal good-created to love, desire, seek, find, and contemplate-fell from such a great good by sinning and became a slave of sin.
As the Lord Himself testifies, saying:
"Everyone who commits sin is a slave to sin"
(John 8:34)
And the blessed Apostle Peter says:
"For by whom a person is overcome, by him also he is brought into bondage"
(Second Peter 2:19)
Thus, having lost the gift of grace and being corrupted and depraved in the good of nature, he fell so miserably from such great happiness that he cannot return to that good, to love and enjoy it, to which he ought to have adhered, unless through the help of the most merciful reconciler and mediator, and the price of His blood, by which we are redeemed from such captivity, so that we can regain our former freedom and be made friends from enemies.
Of this mediator, it is written:
"For there is one God and one mediator between God and mankind, the man Christ Jesus, who gave Himself as a ransom for all"
(First Timothy 2:5)
And again:
"For if while we were enemies, we were reconciled to God through the death of His Son"
(Romans 5:10)
Therefore, whoever says that after the most unfortunate fall of transgression, by which, having lost original freedom, he became a slave of sin, became a slave to the one by whom he was also overcome, became an enemy of God, and needs one mediator and reconciler, through whom he may receive redemption from slavery and reconciliation to God.
After such a great and miserable fall, anyone who claims they have the freedom to seek, love, and earn true good without being redeemed, justified, reconciled, and reformed by the grace of the true mediator, is completely going against the faith of the Church.
They teach against the truth of the Gospel and apostolic doctrine, and nullify the cross and death of Christ.
If a person could recover true freedom of mind after sin without the redemption of the cross and death of Christ, as the Apostle says to some who thought they could be justified otherwise: "Then Christ died for nothing" Galatians 2:21.
This is the wisdom of words that nullifies the cross of Christ First Corinthians 1:17.
If a person could have true freedom after another sin, then redemption and a redeemer are unnecessary, making the coming and death of Christ superfluous.
The claim that a sinful man loses only the vigor and power of freedom but not freedom itself is incorrect. He did not partially retain and partially lose the good of freedom; he lost both the vigor and power of freedom, as well as freedom itself. Now, he cannot, by himself, attain the true good from which he fell.
He remained free to do evil; just as he deserted the good with free will, he adhered to evil with free will.
After that condemnation, man has free will to incline towards and be inclined by his own will to evil; he has free will to rise to the good. But rising to the good is not due to his own strength, but to the grace of God who has mercy.
He has free will to wish well, live well, and adhere to God; but these abilities are not due to his own strength, but to the grace of God who has mercy.
Even one who is gravely ill can be said to be able to receive health, but to receive health, he needs medicine.
And the one who is dead could be said to rise again, to live again, but not by their own power, but by God's.
Similarly, human free will, once wounded, once dead, can be healed, but not by its own power, but by the grace of a merciful God.
Therefore, it is right to admonish everyone, it is right to preach the word of God to everyone, because they have the ability to believe, they have the ability to turn to God, so that by the word admonishing from outside, and God awakening them from within, those who hear may come back to life.
It can be rightly said about such a person: Because he was dead, and came back to life; he was lost, and was found.
Concerning this possibility of human nature, which is nevertheless worthless without the generosity of divine grace, blessed Augustine teaches thus, saying (On the Predestination of the Saints, chapter 5): The ability to have faith, like the ability to have love, is a natural trait of humans: but to actually have faith, like to actually have love, is the grace of the faithful.
But since the will to believe is prepared for some by the Lord and not for others, we must distinguish what comes from His mercy and what comes from His judgment.
For all the ways of the Lord are mercy and truth (Psalm 25:10).
Yet His ways are unsearchable (Romans 11:33).
Therefore, both the mercy by which He freely saves and the truth by which He justly judges are unsearchable.
After this person said in vain and deceitfully that freedom remained for humans after sin, he added another conclusion, and said: Nature can always begin, but can only be perfected by grace.
If he says it like this, as if human nature through its own free will can always begin good, but can only be perfected by the grace of God, so that the beginning of all good is always attributed to humans, but its perfection only to God: so that humans claim the first part of doing good for themselves, and God the second part: such a sense is entirely Pelagian, and contrary to the truth of the Gospel and the Apostles.
For the Lord Himself, to show that the beginning of our good is not from us, but from Him, says: You did not choose me, but I chose you (John 15:16).
And the Apostle says to the faithful:
The one who began a good work in you will carry it on to completion until the day of Christ Jesus.
(Philippians 1:6)
And again:
It has been granted to you on behalf of Christ not only to believe in him, but also to suffer for him.
(Philippians 1:29)
And the blessed Apostle John says:
Not that we loved God, but that he loved us first and sent his Son as an atoning sacrifice for our sins.
(First John 4:10)
And again, the blessed Apostle Paul says:
Let us run with perseverance the race marked out for us, fixing our eyes on Jesus, the pioneer and perfecter of faith.
(Hebrews 12:1-2)
Therefore, if we truly wish to be Catholics, we must faithfully attribute everything to divine grace, both the beginning of our good work and the end.
As the aforementioned testimonies of Holy Scripture clearly demonstrate, the Lord chooses his saints, not the other way around.
God begins and completes the good work in his faithful:
it is from him that believers receive the ability to suffer for him, the beginning of faith, and the end of martyrdom.
He loved his saints first, so that they could also love him.
And our faith has the Lord Jesus as its author, starting it in us; and it has him as its perfecter, completing it.
Therefore, let us hold firmly to these truths, so that being grounded in true faith, we may be safe from heretical error.
Or if these words have another correct and acceptable meaning, let the one who wrote them show it.
Chapter Five
In the fifth chapter, he presents the following propositions:
1. No one is compelled by God's foreknowledge and predestination. 2.
God knows even those things that He would not make happen, but predestines only those things He would make happen.
3.
Just as God's foreknowledge and predestination are not the cause of sin, neither are they the cause of punishment or death.
4.
God does not compel anyone to sin, nor to live righteously.
5.
If any cause precedes the will, that is, nature, to think or do good or evil, it is not nature.
Out of these five propositions, three have already been sufficiently discussed above, and do not need to be repeated: the first, second, and fourth.
Therefore, two remain, which are now first presented.
In the third proposition, he says: Just as God's foreknowledge and predestination are not the cause of sin, neither are they the cause of punishment or death.
To these words, we respond: if God's foreknowledge and predestination are not a cause of sin to anyone, which is entirely true, then the same divine foreknowledge and predestination are not unjust, nor blameworthy in any way, by which He foreknew and predestined the wicked, who persist in their wickedness, to be condemned to eternal punishments.
By His foreknowledge and predestination, Almighty God is not the cause of their sin, but the just avenger of sin, and He does not drive them to sin, but justly delivers them to suffer punishment.
Thus, as the true and truthful God, He foreknows the future sins of men; hence the Scripture says: "Eternal God, who is the knower of secrets, who knows all things before they happen" (Daniel 13:42).
Not that by His foreknowledge He compels anyone to sin, but that by His eternal providence He justly orders or condemns those who sin.
By His predestination, by which He has decreed to punish the wicked, as already stated, He did not make them wicked, but justly ordained that those who persist in their wickedness should not go unpunished.
What this person explains is that, just as God, through His foreknowledge and predestination, is not the cause of anyone's sin, He is also not the cause of the punishment and death that result from sin.
We must faithfully understand this: by sinning, man himself becomes the cause of his own punishment and death.
Yet, because Almighty God is a just judge, even though the cause of punishments and death lies in human actions and not in His foreknowledge and predestination, there is eternal justice in the same foreknowledge and predestination, through which those who remain in their impiety are subjected to punishment and death.
Therefore, according to this reasoning, the predestination of God, by which He imposes eternal punishments on the impious, is not negated.
For, even if His predestination does not cause the punishments, there is still justice and the judgment of justly inflicting them.
The fifth proposition is as follows: If any cause precedes the will, that is, nature, to think or do good or evil, it is not nature.
Here, he clearly speaks against the truth.
For if no cause precedes the will of man to think or do good, where does a good will, that is, pious affection, come from in man, so that he can think or do something good?
For man does not have a good will from himself, about which it is said: "Peace on earth to people of good will (Luke 2:14).
" Nor does he have the ability to perform good works from himself, about which it is said: "Glory, honor, and peace for everyone who does good (Romans 2:10).
" But he has these from Him, about whom the Apostle says to the faithful: "For it is God who works in you to will and to act according to His good purpose (Philippians 2:13).
"
He precedes the will of man with His mercy, as the Psalmist says: "My God, His mercy will go before me (Psalm 59:10).
" He inspires in man the grace to think rightly, as the Apostle says: "Not that we are competent in ourselves to claim anything for ourselves, but our competence comes from God (Second Corinthians 3:5).
"
He Himself is the reason for our good will, desires, and accomplishments.
He is the source of our mercy and grace, enabling us not only to wish well, act well, and achieve well but also to think well.
He does this not only in the present for His chosen ones, but also, before the foundation of the world, He predestined them by His grace to be holy and blameless before Him.
As the Apostle testifies, saying: "He chose us in Him before the foundation of the world, to be holy and blameless in His sight in love" (Ephesians 1:4).
With such a significant cause, which is undoubtedly the cause of all good things in both creation and reward, being our best and eternal source of good will, preceding us with His grace so that we can wish well and act well, how can anyone claim that no cause precedes our good will and deeds?
Or, if there is a preceding cause for these good things, how can it be said it is not nature, when Almighty God, the cause of our good will, is Himself the highest and best nature above all?
Therefore, anyone who does not believe that this highest and most effective cause, which is also the highest and best nature, precedes our will so that we can wish and act rightly, clearly opposes the truth and is proven to be in error like the Pelagians.
For if this blessed cause did not precede human wills, there would be no predestination of the good, no redemption of the miserable, and no reward for good deeds.
But thinking or doing evil is not preceded by this highest and best cause.
Instead, it is preceded by a defective cause-the abandonment of the highest good and the desire for something lower, when the soul turns away from the love of God and longs for lesser things.
Therefore, the will of fallen human nature becomes bad, having no cause for its badness other than, as mentioned, the abandonment of the highest good.
Such a lack of willpower made both the angels who abandoned God and humans who similarly disobeyed Him evil.
However, this deficiency is clearly not a part of their nature.
Instead, it is the nature of either humans or angels abandoning their Creator and turning to themselves or even to the lowest creatures.
This is the origin of all evil will, corrupt desires, and actions.
Although God is not the cause of our evil wills, nor any existing nature, but rather the failing affection of a rational creature from the love of the Creator, He is still the judge and avenger of our thoughts.
He is the eternal predestinator of His just revenge and judgment, something which this person tries to invalidate with many convoluted arguments.
Regarding the claim that will itself is a nature, we have already warned that this error stems from a misinterpretation of the words of Saint Augustine.
When he discusses the will of the human mind that loves itself, which is always good in loving its nature and cannot be otherwise, this person contentiously applies it entirely to the will discussed in the context of free will.
As we said, the same will of the mind is different when it naturally loves itself, when aided by grace it loves God, or when corrupted by its own fault it loves the world.
The difference is not one of nature but of affection.
Therefore, it can be both good and bad, depending on what it loves either rightly or wrongly.
Chapter Six
In this sixth chapter he defines:
1.
No sin and no punishment for it can arise from anywhere else except from a person's own will, using free will wrongly.
2.
And it is extremely foolish to doubt that human will is according to nature.
3.
Nor can it be doubted that this very rational substance exists.
Why he established these three definitions and what he wanted to achieve with them is not entirely clear.
Perhaps his main intention in all these arguments is either to defend free will according to nature, which is certainly Pelagian, or to undermine the predestination of God's just judgment as much as possible, which is Ciceronian.
For Cicero, as the blessed Augustine mentions in his books "The City of God" (Book 5, Chapter 9) and shows from Cicero's own words, tried so hard to nullify the arrangement of divine providence that he not only denied predestination but also entirely denied God's foreknowledge, wanting to defend human free will with this reasoning:
And thus he made his listeners sacrilegious while trying to make them free, causing them to think they were so free in their own will that they were in no way subject to God's providential arrangement or predestination; denying God what is supremely and properly God's, that is, foreknowledge of all future events and the predestination of His arrangements.
What else is this but to say that God is not God?
For how is He truly God who has no foreknowledge of future events?
This is something that must be greatly feared and avoided now as well.
Lest through such contentions and disputes, while we accept and deny a part of God's predestination, intending to make men free, we make them sacrilegious.
Because it certainly pertains to our faith to believe that God's predestination, which is just, is full and perfect in both directions.
It is sacrilegious to deny this, as it is against faith.
Since the main aim here is either to defend free will according to nature or to deny the predestination of God's justice halfway, he could use these three arguments in defense of free will.
When he says that no sin and its punishment come from anywhere else but the person's own will misusing free will, it is true because the sin was committed by the person's own will, and the punishment for sin, which is death, misery, and suffering, followed as a consequence.
However, there is a big difference between sin and its punishment.
The person alone committed the sin, but both the person deserved the punishment, and God justly inflicted it.
This argument does not conclude or show what he wants, namely that no punishment for sin, no misery, no suffering imposed on sinners, comes from God.
Therefore, eternal punishments for the wicked could not have been predestined by God because they are not from Him, just as sin is not, nor is the punishment.
As we have already shown, Scripture clearly cries out against this error.
Sirach 11:14 says, "Good and evil; life and death; poverty and wealth are from God." Certainly not the evils that people commit by sinning and acting unjustly, for which God is not at all the author, but those justly imposed on people by God's judgment because of sins, such as famine, killings, hostilities, devastations, and other calamities and disasters.
The prophet Amos also says, "If there is calamity in a city, will not the Lord have done it?" (Amos 3:6).
And the Lord Himself, through the prophet Isaiah, says, "I am the Lord, making peace and creating calamity" (Isaiah 45:7).
Hence, He also threatens with certain evils, saying, "And I will bring calamity upon them, the year of their visitation" (Jeremiah 11:23).
And again, "I will heap calamities upon them and spend My arrows against them" (Deuteronomy 32:23).
All these things God is said to create, not as if He is creating some nature, but by decreeing, instituting, and inflicting them with His just judgment.
How should we correctly distinguish and understand, according to this sense, that God did not create death, as stated in Wisdom 1:13?
Yet, death comes from God, as mentioned in Ecclesiasticus 11:14.
Blessed Augustine clearly explains this by saying:
He adds that it is most foolish to doubt that human will is according to nature.
It is true that the will of a rational soul is in accordance with its nature.
However, this natural will is understood differently when it loves and refers to itself, which is always naturally good, versus when it loves the Lord piously or the world perversely, referring to things it loves either above or below itself.
Therefore, such a will is no longer in its own mind when naturally present.
It relates to various things outside its substance and can be good or bad, not by nature, but by affection.
This means it is blessed by rightly loving higher things or corrupted by wrongly desiring lower things.
In this matter, it is not just nature, but either the virtue or vice of nature-virtue from divine grace or vice from the corruption of its own will.
This is the free will of the human mind: the inclination to desire one thing or another.
This inclination is not outside of nature, because it moves spontaneously in either direction.
However, to move towards good, it is stirred by divine grace, and to move towards evil, it is corrupted by its own desire.
We thought it necessary to briefly and diligently demonstrate this, so it can be understood how absurd and deceitful it is to assert the natural freedom of choice everywhere, solely because of the will of the human mind, which naturally loves itself.
He neither notices nor admits, or at least pretends not to notice, that the issue of free will is not about the will itself but rather about how that will, influenced either by divine grace or corrupted by its own faults, inclines towards good or evil.
Therefore, it is evident that his stubborn attempt to defend free will naturally is futile and pointless.
Although free will exists in human nature and the human mind has a natural ability to desire good, live rightly, and be happy, the ability to actually want good, live rightly, and achieve happiness comes not from human strength but solely from divine grace.
He tries to force us into a position where we either partially deny divine predestination or, by fully asserting predestination, seem to eliminate free will-similar to Cicero's argument that divine foreknowledge negates free will.
Cicero claimed that if God's foreknowledge were true, human free will couldn't exist, or vice versa.
Consequently, that blasphemer chose to defend human free will by completely denying God's foreknowledge.
Anyone who examines this closely can see how much this person follows and imitates that argument.
Denying God's foreknowledge also denies God's predestination, as predestination without foreknowledge is meaningless.
To clearly understand how both free will and divine predestination can truly coexist without one destroying the other, we find it necessary and beneficial to include the words of Saint Augustine, who, in opposition to Cicero's impious argument, defends both concepts and teaches that both must be upheld.
(Augustine, The City of God, Book 5, Chapter 9).
Item after some: And after some:
Item after a few:
These things are for our instruction and confirmation against the errors of human presumption and argumentation.
The most blessed doctor has very clearly discussed this, who also, in another place about this same matter, thus says:
Item about the immutable reason of mutable things in God, and about His eternal and general predestination and foreknowledge, in another place thus says:
Chapter Seven
In the seventh chapter, he provides the following definition.
1. Free will should be considered among the intermediate gifts of God.
Therefore, it could have been used to sin.
Here, a brief explanation is needed: although he says that free will is a gift from God, he asserts it only naturally, in the manner of the Pelagians.
The faith of the Church clearly distinguishes between the gifts of nature and the gifts of grace.
For instance, God Almighty naturally gave humans a rational and intellectual mind, and in that mind, memory, understanding, and will.
He also naturally gave the human body substance, form, appearance, health, and the senses of seeing, hearing, smelling, tasting, and touching, all of which are enlivened and animated by the soul.
These are clearly natural gifts that God implanted in humans during the first creation.
However, when God gives humans faith, hope, charity, piety, good will, the ability to do good works, and other similar gifts of His grace, these are gifts of the Holy Spirit, about which the Apostle says:
"But all these things are produced by one and the same Spirit, distributing them to each one individually as He wills"
First Corinthians
12:11.
He also explains that it is said in the psalm:
"When He ascended on high, He led captivity captive and gave gifts to men"
Ephesians
4:8;
Psalm
68:18.
Therefore, the Catholic faith, the true faith, also considers free will among the gifts of grace. Although God naturally implanted it in humans when He created them as good and endowed with good will, it still needed the grace of the Creator to remain in the good state in which it was created. Once it lost its freedom due to the first sin, it became weakened, corrupted, and deteriorated. Like a fallen ruin, it cannot rise at all to that eternal and supreme good for which humans were created unless it is healed, restored, enlightened, and liberated by God's grace. It cannot become truly free in any other way unless it is made free by God's grace through Him who says:
"If the Son sets you free, you will be free indeed"
John
8:36.
So that what the Apostle said might come true in us:
"Where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is freedom"
Second Corinthians 3:17.
Therefore, as we have said, it is a foolish and Pelagian error to think that free will, which was lost by Adam's sin, can be restored without the grace of Christ.
The idea that free will, created in the first man, was good, right, and inclined towards higher and divine things, allowing him to be sinless if he chose, is far from the truth. Such a belief misrepresents the greatness of free will as one of the highest gifts from God, rather than a mediocre one.
As we have said, the good of free will in that first man was so great that none of the saints in this present life possess it. Although their free will is liberated and healed by the grace of Christ, they cannot live without sin. Despite their strong desire not to sin, they still find themselves unable to avoid it.
Hence, they need to pray daily and truthfully say to the Heavenly Father:
"Forgive us our debts, as we forgive our debtors."
Therefore, the gift of free will in paradise was not mediocre but the highest, allowing man to live without sin as long as he remained obedient to God. Had he continued to subject himself to God's rule and help, he would have been further perfected and given the strength to no longer sin.
However, the free will of the first man could lead to sin due to the abandonment of God and his own presumption. By neglecting to remain under God's guidance and wanting to be self-sufficient, he lost the gift of divine grace, the good of nature, and found himself condemned to misery.
Chapter Eight
In the eighth chapter, he presents these definitions:
One, the substantial trinity of the inner human is contained in essence, will, and knowledge.
Two, there is no difference for him between being and willing, nor between willing and knowing; rather, these three are one nature, and the entire nature of the soul is will.
Three, free will is the nature of humans, and their free movement and power to move is what free will is, which is a gift from the Creator.
Four, just as the physical body could die because it was not yet perfect, that is, spiritual, so free will, still belonging to the physical body because it is mortal, could sin because it was not yet perfect.
This perfection of freedom would be fulfilled after keeping the commandment, when the will to sin would be entirely taken away from it.
Five, this movement is granted to no animal except humans.
Six, there is such a difference between human free will and its substance that nature is in rational will, while free will is in its freedom, whether in the naturally free movement of will or in the gift of intelligence.
Seven, these three, that is, freedom, movement, and intelligence, compose free will among themselves: so that, just as the substance in which it exists is threefold - it exists, it wills, and it knows - so it is threefold: free, moving, intelligent.
Therefore, he says that the substantial trinity of the inner human is contained in essence, will, and knowledge, partly taken from the discussions of Saint Augustine in the books "On the Trinity," and partly thought out by himself.
For the blessed Augustine, disputing about the holy and supreme Trinity, in Book Nine, Chapter Two, and Book Fifteen, Chapter Seven, and about the mind of humans where they were created in the image and likeness of God, draws a likeness to God, so that through that image of the trinity which is in the human mind, he might elevate us to contemplate in some way the Trinity which is God.
He insists that these three aspects-being, knowing, and willing-are present in the human mind in a way that they are distinctly three, yet one in substance.
Specifically, when the mind, which naturally exists, naturally knows itself and naturally wills, that is, loves itself, its knowledge and will are then directed towards itself.
At that time, although these three-being, knowing itself, and willing itself-are distinctly understood to be in the mind, the being itself is the essence of the mind.
It naturally knows itself and naturally wills itself; it is whole, and just as it entirely has being, it also entirely knows and loves itself.
Therefore, the scope of its essence is the same as the scope of its knowledge and will.
From this comparison, the blessed doctor encourages us to rise from the likeness of our mind to contemplate the true Trinity, which is God.
Just as these three aspects-being, knowing itself, and willing itself-are found in the human mind, each can be distinctly discerned, yet they are substantially and naturally one.
As great as the mind is, so is its knowledge of itself and its love of itself, because it entirely knows and loves itself.
Thus, from this image and likeness of God, let us elevate our understanding to the Trinity of the Lord.
Recognize in the blessed and supreme Trinity, distinctly and properly three things-Father, Son, and Holy Spirit-these three are essentially and naturally one and equal, so that just as great as the Father is, so is the Son, and so is the Holy Spirit.
In this way, as if through a mirror and a reflection of our mind, let us learn to understand the holy Trinity, distinct in persons, united in substance, equal in nature and power.
This man, after reading these enlightening words aimed at strengthening our faith, was not content with the moderation and piety of the holy doctor.
He disregarded the boundaries set by him and added his own ideas, claiming that these three things, contemplated in the mind of man, form a substantial Trinity.
However, a substantial Trinity, meaning one that exists substantially in persons, can only be found in the one true God.
Therefore, the same doctor, to prevent anyone from making mistakes on this matter, clearly warns and teaches in his books that these three things are not the man himself but are of the man or in the man.
In contrast, within the holy Trinity, those three distinct aspects should not and cannot be said to exist in one God, but rather that God truly is one.
We do not say that the Trinity is in God; instead, the Trinity itself is God.
As the holy doctor states in book fifteen on the Trinity, chapter six: "These three are in the mind, or the mind itself: and thus these three are not the man, but are of the man, or in the man. Even when the body is removed, if we consider the soul alone, its mind is like its head, or eye, or face, but these are not to be thought of as bodies. Therefore, it is not the soul, but what excels in the soul, that is called the mind."
But can we say that the Trinity is in God in such a way that some part of God is not God Himself? This man, after wrongly stating that a substantial Trinity is contained in the essence, will, and knowledge of the mind, added something even worse. He claimed that in the mind of man, its being and willing are not distinct, nor are its willing and knowing different, and that the entire nature of the soul is will; but these three are one nature.
Conversely, our faith firmly holds that no creature, whether angelic or human, exists with such a simple nature or essence that its being is also its understanding, because it can exist without understanding. Nor is its being the same as its willing, because it can exist without willing. Nor is its being the same as its knowing, because it can exist without knowing.
This is not the same as loving for him, because he can exist without loving.
Only the divine nature has that supreme and ineffable simplicity, where to exist is the same as to have whatever can truly be said to exist.
For example, for God, to exist is the same as to understand, because in Him, essence and understanding are not different: essence is understanding, and understanding is essence.
Similarly, for Him, to exist is not different from being wise, because in Him, essence and wisdom are not different: essence is wisdom, and wisdom is essence.
On this topic, the same blessed doctor speaks as follows:
And after some things:
Again, when he spoke only about the Son, he said this about Him:
Therefore, since these things are so, how did he dare to say about the human mind's creation: "And it is not different for it to exist and to will, nor is it different to will and to know, but these three make up one nature and the whole nature of the soul is will"? When, on the contrary, the holy doctor, whom he seems to follow, and whose caution and moderation he presumptuously surpasses with his own levity and vanity, shows so much distance between those three things found in the human mind as a certain likeness of the Trinity, that is, being, knowing, and loving.
He shows this distance so clearly, saying (On the Trinity, Book 10, Chapter 11, 12):
Behold, according to the truth taught by the holy man, how great is the distance and diversity in the human mind itself among these three things, which are naturally in it and belong to it: the memory of itself, the understanding of itself, and the love of itself.
While through memory alone it remembers itself, through understanding alone it understands itself, and through love alone it loves itself.
Therefore, memory can do one thing, understanding another, and love another: what memory can do, understanding cannot, and what understanding can do, memory cannot: and what memory and understanding can do, will cannot.
And if the essence of the mind is considered distinctly, what it can do essentially in these three, it surely cannot do without them.
This person argues that for the mind, being and wanting are not different, nor are wanting and knowing different.
If we accept this, what is this new, unheard-of claim suggesting?
It's saying that just as God has a simple nature, the human mind should also be believed to have a simple nature.
If for the human mind, existing is the same as wanting, then its essence and will are clearly not different; rather, the essence itself is will, and the will itself is essence.
Similarly, if for the human mind, wanting and knowing are not different, then will and essence are not different; rather, will itself is knowledge, and knowledge itself is will.
From this incredible reasoning, it follows that, as this person says, the entire mind is essence, the entire mind is will, and the entire mind is knowledge.
Just as it is truly believed about God, and can only be rightly said of Him, that what He has, He is: He has justice, but He is justice; He has wisdom, but He is wisdom; He has goodness, but He is goodness.
Therefore, it follows that the same should be said of the human mind: what it has, it is.
That is, it has will, but it is will; it has knowledge, but it is knowledge; so that, just as we believe about God, there is no difference for Him between being and having.
Behold, therefore, this author, or rather deceiver, against all the truth of faith, against the authority of Holy Scripture, against the sincerity of the teachings of the Fathers, indeed against all divine and human reason, has invented a creature, that is, the human mind, which is of a simple nature, and thus unchangeable, just as God is of a simple and unchangeable nature.
While, on the contrary, the truth cries out, and Saint Augustine himself, as we have shown above, clearly affirms that every creature is complex and in no way truly simple; and he also says: nothing changeable is simple, but every creature is changeable.
Therefore, let this man choose one of two options: if the nature of the mind, as he tries to assert, is simple, it is not changeable, because, as the teacher himself says, and very truly says, nothing changeable is simple.
However, if the nature of the mind itself, like all creation, is truly changeable, it is not simple.
So, let it be far from us to think that the blessed Augustine, who affirms that all creation is changeable and complex, and in no way simple, thought or wrote such things about the nature of the human mind that he would assert it to be not only similar but also equal to God if he had said that it is of an unchangeable and simple nature!
Let anyone who is willing and able read diligently and investigate very carefully what he said about this matter in the books about the Trinity, and they will find him saying that the three things found in the human mind, which have often been mentioned because of the unity of the substance of the mind in which they reside, are one, and one mind, and one substance.
They will find him saying that these things are substantially within the mind, and that the mind is substance, and self-knowledge is substance, and self-will is substance.
Likewise, they will find him saying that the whole mind knows itself, the whole mind wills or loves itself; yet nowhere will they find him saying that the mind itself is knowledge, that the mind itself is will.
Since it has already been shown from his own words above that knowledge is one thing there, through which the mind alone knows itself, and will is another thing, through which the mind alone loves itself.
Why, then, when the whole mind knows itself, did he not say that the mind itself is knowledge?
And when the whole mind wills itself, did he not say that the mind itself is will?
Unless because the mind itself is a creation and is not simple; and its being is one thing, its knowing is another, its willing is another.
But if anyone, or this man who said this, objects: how then are these three one, one mind, one substance, if there is this and that?
He should recognize that these three can be said to be substantially one because they are one, and in one substance.
And potentially this and that, because, as the teacher himself shows, memory in the mind can be one thing, intelligence another, and will another.
In the divine Trinity, we can say one person and another and another; but we cannot say one thing and another thing and another thing, because of the supreme unity of its simple nature.
Therefore, there is supreme simplicity where one thing and another thing can never be found.
An ancient debater, discussing the incorporeal nature of the soul, once said: "And when the soul wills, if it wills entirely, it is entirely will."
He carefully asserted that the soul can sometimes be called entirely will when it entirely wills, because it wills not outside itself, but in itself and with itself.
He did not define it absolutely as will, but conditionally said, "if it wills entirely, it is entirely will."
This means that if it does not will entirely, it is not entirely will, something naturally understood by everyone.
The soul can will one thing in part and not will the same thing in part; what it entirely wills, it can entirely not will.
Therefore, due to this changeable and variable movement of will, the nature of the soul should not be said to be entirely will.
It is not entirely will when it wills in part, nor when it entirely does not will what it had willed, even though it always has the ability to will.
Yet, with its nature and substance always remaining, it wills the same thing according to its desires or rejections, either remaining the same, changing, or perishing.
Therefore, let us stop saying that the entire nature of the soul is will, that is, that the soul itself is will.
The soul is not of a simple nature like God, where to be is the same as to will, nor is it different for the soul to be and to have will.
Given these points, let such an impious and profane notion be driven away from the ears of the faithful.
Those who admire and willingly listen to such a teacher should remember that they are Christians.
They must keep the Catholic faith-the true understanding of God-whole and unviolated.
They should faithfully guard the father's teachings and avoid the impious presumptions of words with all piety.
As the Apostle vehemently recommends, saying: "O Timothy, guard the deposit, avoiding profane novelties of words and oppositions of falsely named knowledge; which some have professed and have fallen away from the faith, or have shipwrecked concerning the faith" First Timothy 6:20-21."
Let us learn not to have itching ears-that is, being eager and desiring empty and old wives' tales. Regarding this evil, the Apostle says: "For there will be a time when they will not endure sound doctrine, but according to their own desires, they will heap up for themselves teachers, having itching ears. And they will turn away their ears from the truth and will be turned aside to myths" Second Timothy 4:3-4."
What remains for those who say or receive such things-that is, to equate the human mind with God, suggesting it is also of a simple nature-except that, as the worst ancient heretics said, they blaspheme that God and the soul are of the same nature.
He further says: "Free will is the nature of man, and its free movement, and the power of moving; that free will is a gift of the Creator." However, as we have already stated, and as the truth of the matter evidently shows, we do not say that man is will, but that man has will; because obviously, to be is one thing, and to will is another. Therefore, it is not man who is will, but it is man's will.
Nevertheless, he shows that, with Pelagian error, he believes free will to be according to the nature of man alone, and to be a gift of nature, not a gift of grace-that is, human will, as he says, free movement, and the power of moving.
This clearly shows that human will not only has a natural tendency to desire good or evil but also the freedom to choose and act on that desire.
However, the Catholic faith asserts, against all such errors, that free will, although originally upright and whole in humans before sin, has been corrupted by sin, even lost, and has no desire for good nor the ability to do good, except through hidden grace given and inspired by Him of whom the Apostle very truly says:
"For it is God who works in you both to will and to act in order to fulfill His good purpose"
(Philippians 2:13).
As we have already mentioned, it is naturally instilled by the Creator that one can will and even be able to do good; but to will and do this does not come from oneself, but only from Him who works in the hearts of the faithful to will and act for His good purpose.
Hence, there is that most ecclesiastical and faithful definition, which the blessed Pope Celestine sets forth in his decrees saying,
(Celestine, Letter to the Bishops of Gaul 819):
And again, from this apostolic and ecclesiastical definition, it is most certainly shown that free will in humans can do nothing to desire or achieve good unless it has been freed by the grace of Christ.
However, it is free to do evil, because when one sins, one is not compelled by any necessity, but is corrupted by one's own will.
Then he adds: Just as the physical body could die because it was not yet perfect, meaning it was not yet spiritual, so the free will, still animal in nature and mortal, could sin because it was not yet perfect.
This perfection of freedom would be fulfilled after keeping the commandment, while the will to sin would be taken away.
Where else should we talk about the physical and spiritual body, except what the Apostle teaches, saying: If there is a physical body, there is also a spiritual body, as it is written: the first man Adam became a living being; the last Adam became a life-giving spirit.
First Corinthians 15:44-45.
And earlier, when talking about the resurrection of the dead, he said: It is sown a physical body, it will rise a spiritual body.
First Corinthians 15:44.
In these words, how else can we distinguish between a physical and a spiritual body, except that the physical body is only given life mortally and corruptibly through the soul?
This was the nature of Adam's body even before the sin; because although it was not yet destined for death and decay, it could still be corrupted and die due to sin, just as it happened to him and happens to all his descendants, by the just judgment and punishment of Him who said: Until you return to the ground from which you were taken, for you are dust, and to dust you will return.
But the spiritual body is called such, not because it ceases to be a body and becomes a spirit, because even though it is spiritual, the Apostle still calls it a body.
But then it will be a spiritual body when it is given life immortally and incorruptibly through the spirit.
The kind of body the last Adam, that is, the Lord Jesus Christ, showed in His resurrection, through which He transformed the mortal body He had taken into immortality and incorruption, and will show in His holy ones on the last day through the same grace of incorruption.
Even as, according to the same Apostle:
This corruptible body must put on incorruption, and this mortal body must put on immortality, so that what is mortal may be swallowed up by life; and thus the saying that is written will be fulfilled: Death is swallowed up in victory.
First Corinthians 15:53-54.
The body, which is now sown as a natural body in death, will be raised as a spiritual body.
First Corinthians 15:44.
It will no longer need sustenance, it will no longer be subject to corruption or death, but will instead be brought to life by the spirit with eternal immortality.
This is how Adam's body would have been if there had been no intervening death, as a reward from God for his obedience, had he not sinned.
Therefore, it is true that Adam's body was still natural and had not yet been transformed into that immortality, which would have been given to him if he had remained obedient to God.
So, even if he had not sinned, he could not die, and if he had sinned, he could die; it is clear that he could die because he had not yet been granted immortality.
In this man, there was still a natural will, according to the desire of the human soul, not according to the spirit of God.
He was not yet in the inner man, that is, in the spirit of his mind, spiritually, but was still natural, sensing in a natural, not spiritual, manner.
About whom the Apostle says:
The natural man does not accept the things of the Spirit of God.
First Corinthians 2:14.
The Apostle shows that the great mystery which was to come in Christ and in the Church was prophesied by him, when, filled with the divine Spirit, he says:
For this reason, a man will leave his father and mother and be united to his wife, and the two will become one flesh.
Ephesians 5:31.
With these words, the Apostle explained:
This is a great mystery: but I speak concerning Christ and the Church.
Ephesians 5:32.
How then was his will not spiritual, aided by the spirit, and enlightened, even elevated by the grace of prophecy?
Yet even the spiritual will could sin if it fell into worse circumstances.
As the same Apostle shows, even the spiritual can be tempted, that is, overcome by some temptation of sin, where he says:
Brothers, if someone is caught in any wrongdoing, you who are spiritual should restore such a person in a spirit of gentleness, considering yourself, lest you also be tempted.
Galatians 6:1.
So then, the will of that man, even if spiritual, could be tempted and overcome by temptation.
And if it had reached that fullness of happiness by obedience where it could no longer sin, the will to sin would not be taken away from him.
As this person says, it was not in him at all, but the good will that was in him would be so perfected by such happiness that it could not be changed to evil.
For the human will can be faithfully understood in three states:
Firstly, that the first man was created with a good will such that, if he wished, he could avoid sinning.
Now, however, even holy people, because they are born from his corrupted lineage, cannot avoid sinning even if they wish to.
Hence, they truthfully say to God every day:
Forgive us our debts.
Matthew 6:12.
But in the happiness that will be given to them, they will be so strengthened in virtue that they will no longer be able to sin, just as they will be clothed with such grace of incorruption that they will never be able to die.
It is strange, however, why he wanted to add and say:
This motion, that is, free will, is granted to no animals except humans, when it is clear to everyone that where there is no rational nature, as in all brute and irrational animals, there can be no rational will to seek good or evil.
But they are led to everything they do by mere natural, brute, and senseless appetite.
From this, whatever actions they perform cannot be called good or bad, nor vices nor virtues, as far as they are concerned.
It might be thought that human free will is somewhat like the desire of irrational beasts, driven solely by natural impulse.
Similarly, human free will is led by its own natural instinct to whatever it wishes.
How contrary this is to the truth has already been demonstrated many times.
This disputant has taken such liberties with the senses and ears of his audience that he dared, like a fabricator and potter of lies, to create a new definition of free will, as if it were clay and muddy, and to present it as something significant to the observers.
He further added: Let there be such a difference between human free will and its substance, that its nature lies in rational will.
Free will indeed in its freedom, or in the movement of naturally free will, or in the gift of intelligence.
Behold what kind of free will he teaches: surely Pelagian, not Christian!
Its nature is rational will, but its effect lies in the natural freedom of the will; and from or in the natural will alone, it has freedom, movement, and the gift of intelligence.
We, however, according to the truth of faith, recognize free will in man in this way: although it is naturally implanted by God in the rational mind and given as good and right in the first condition, by the merit of sin, it is depraved and stripped of natural virtue.
It can have no freedom towards true good, no movement of good will, and no light of intelligence unless restored by the grace of Him who said: If the Son makes you free, you shall be free indeed John 8:36; and who, by His inspiration, moves the hearts of whom He wills to faith, as the prophet says: I will shake all nations, and the Desired of all nations shall come Haggai 2:7; and to whom we daily pray, saying: Give me understanding, that I may learn Your commandments Psalm 119:73.
And again: "Give me understanding, and I shall live" (Psalm 119:144).
Regarding this understanding, we give thanks to the Giver, saying: "I will bless the Lord, who has given me understanding" (Psalm 16:7).
True free will is not a gift of nature, as some proponents of the Pelagian heresy claim, but a gift of grace.
It is free because it is liberated by the grace of Christ.
This proponent argues that freedom of choice, movement, and intelligence all rest solely in the power of nature.
He presents free will as a new entity composed of these three parts.
He says: These three-freedom, movement, and intelligence-together form free will.
Just as the substance in which it resides is threefold-being, willing, and knowing-so too it becomes threefold: free, moving, and intelligent.
He argues that free will rests solely in nature itself and in those things inherent to nature.
He contends that, just as three things are naturally inherent to the human mind-being, willing, and knowing-so too free will proceeds from the mind itself and resides within it, having freedom, movement, and intelligence from it alone.
Thus, man is naturally free, moving, and intelligent through this kind of free will.
He does not say that the human mind possesses these three things within itself, but rather that it is threefold by simple nature.
And in the same way, he claims that free will is threefold.
Who has ever heard of such contentious impiety of error?
He strives so hard to confine and seemingly fortify free will within the boundaries of human nature alone, completely excluding God's grace from it.
So what response should be given to him, to whom so many responses have already been given on this matter?
Unless someone wants to be or appear as a Christian, they should reject this insane and deadly error.
The more subtly they seem to follow and assert it, the more unfortunately they are trapped and blinded by the devil.
They should humbly submit themselves entirely to the truth of Holy Scripture, the authority of the Church Fathers, and the simplicity of faith, casting aside the false and deceptive arguments of human inventions.
Otherwise, while they believe they are securing their own freedom and separating themselves from Christ, they truly deserve to be alienated from Him.
For cursed is the man who trusts in man and makes flesh his strength, and whose heart turns away from the Lord.
Jeremiah 17:5.
But blessed is the man who trusts in the Lord, and whose trust is the Lord.
Jeremiah 17:7.
Chapter Nine
In this chapter, he presents these definitions:
First, foreknowledge and predestination are attributed to God by analogy with temporal things.
Second, all predestination is foreknowledge.
Considering the use of temporal things, which vary by the past, present, and future, it pertains more to temporal things where many future events are expected:
Because clearly foreknowledge and predestination properly concern future things.
However, with God, just as nothing is past, nothing is future either, since in His eternal knowledge all things are eternally present.
Therefore, these concepts are more metaphorically attributed to God than properly.
So, how did this person frequently define foreknowledge and predestination not only as being of God and in God (which we also acknowledge) but as the very substance and essence of God?
If he contradicts his own argument, affirming one thing and later negating it, why do we need to refute his vanity when he so effectively refutes himself?
If any rule of sophistical disputation, which he solely follows, allows secular wisdom to affirm in one place and subvert in another, who cannot see how contemptible and utterly rejectable it is, where there is no firmness of truth, and so impudent, so brazen, so insolent is the freedom of falsehood.
As for his statement that all predestination is foreknowledge, it is partly true:
Because all predestination of future things is not without foreknowledge, through which those future things are foreseen.
But if this means that predestination does nothing more than foreknowledge, it is most manifestly false:
Because by foreknowledge, future things are only foreseen;
But by predestination, they are also established, defined, and decreed.
Therefore, the predestination of the wicked to eternal punishment not only foresaw but also established and defined by a just and eternal judgment what they would suffer.
Chapter Ten
In the tenth chapter, he presents four definitions as follows:
One, that God foreknows or predestines sins, or the death or punishments of humans or angels, should be understood in the opposite way.
Two, that all evil is sin and its punishment; and these are nothing.
Three, that sin and its consequences in death and misery are nothing other than the corruption of a complete and blessed life, so that each one is opposed to the other.
Indeed, sin opposes integrity, death opposes life, misery opposes blessedness.
These are absolutely nothing.
Four, that every defect or deprivation or sin of a perverse will and its end in death and eternal misery of punishments are absolutely nothing; and therefore cannot be foreknown or predestined.
Behold to what extent this diabolic debate has led: a man who wants to appear Christian, with pagan and diabolic arguments, subverts and destroys all faith in divine foreknowledge and predestination.
He argues that God foreknew and predestined the wicked to be damned, nullifying the just judgment of God and His eternal and unchangeable counsel in their damnation.
He contends that sin and every punishment and damnation which follows sin are nothing.
And therefore, because they are nothing, they could neither be foreknown nor predestined by God.
So wherever in the Holy Scriptures or in the doctrines of the Fathers it is read that such things were foreknown and predestined, it should be understood in the opposite way, that is, that they were neither foreknown nor predestined at all.
What is this but to openly declare insanity?
For who among the faithful ever presumed to think or say that what truth declared is not truth; what faith taught is false; what all the faithful believe is nothing?
This person argues that sin, punishment, misery, and calamity-whether temporary or eternal-are nothing because they lack an essence for existing or subsisting, unlike the earth, waters, fires, plants, and trees, which have a substance for existing or subsisting.
We know and believe that human souls and the spirits of good or evil angels have the substance for existing and subsisting.
Therefore, he boldly asserts with diabolical presumption that God could only know, foresee, and predestine the substances of things.
He claims that things contrary and punitive to these substances, because they lack the substance of existing, cannot be foreseen or predestined by God, and thus could not be known by Him.
He argues that God did not foresee the sin of the first man, because sin lacks the substance for existing.
Nor did He foresee the punishment for sin-death, misery, and eternal suffering-because these similarly lack substantial existence.
But where is the faith that firmly holds that Almighty God is truly prescient of all future events?
Where is it that through His prophets, in the holy Scriptures, He foretells so many sins of men, and so many punishments, calamities, and miseries of sinners with His spirit?
Where is it also that His only begotten Son, who is Eternal Truth, foretells so many persecutions of His Church, so many wars, pressures, labors, terrors, earthquakes, plagues, and famines, advising His followers to endure them with utmost patience?
Why has this impious person dared to utter such an obvious lie, or rather such unheard-of and wicked blasphemy, against the faith of the entire holy Church, against the truth of the heavenly Scriptures, and against the majesty of Almighty God with sacrilegious mouth and impious words?
What tries so hard to imitate and assist the devil's plan and deception by claiming that the eternal punishments, which God truthfully predicts and threatens for the wicked, are nothing?
Just as the serpent in the beginning tried to remove the fear of death that God had warned about from the heart of man and entice him to delight in sin, saying: "You will not surely die" (Genesis 3:4); so too does this one, an imitator of the serpent, by saying that the eternal torments, which God warns sinners about, are nothing, remove the healthy fear from the hearts of listeners and make them reckless and eager to sin.
Therefore, it must be firmly and unshakably believed that the all-powerful God knows all future events, both good and bad.
Not only did He foresee the nature of all things before He created them, but He also foresaw whatever could be contrary and harmful to those natures.
Not because these things exist in substance, but because they can harm the substances created by Him in a penal way.
For Scripture confirms this faith, saying: "Eternal God, who knows the hidden things, who knows all things before they happen" (Daniel 13:42).
And the Lord Himself warns His faithful about these things in the Gospel, saying: "I will show you whom you should fear: Fear Him who, after He has killed, has the power to cast into hell; yes, I tell you, fear Him" (Luke 12:5).
But this one, on the contrary, says that the eternal torments, for both humans and evil angels, which are threatened and prepared for them, are absolutely nothing.
If the eternal punishments for evil angels and the worst of humans are not predestined, then why did the just judge and condemner of them say in that judgment: "Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels" (Matthew 25:41)?
If he is indeed prepared and predestined, is he predestined for the condemned among the angels?
But for the wicked, who are to be punished with the same eternal fire, is he neither prepared nor predestined?
However, the blessed Enoch, the very ancient patriarch who walked with God and was taken by the Lord, prophesied about the eternal punishments and penalties for the wicked even before the flood.
The blessed Apostle Jude, speaking of the most wicked heretics who began attacking the Church of God in the times of the apostles, bears witness, saying:
Enoch, the seventh from Adam, also prophesied about these men, saying:
"Behold, the Lord is coming with thousands upon thousands of his holy ones to execute judgment on everyone, and to convict all the ungodly of all their ungodly acts they have committed in their ungodliness, and of all the harsh words ungodly sinners have spoken against him"
(Jude 14-15).
This judgment of condemnation for the wicked, unrighteous, and blasphemous people, foretold so marvelously from the beginning of the world and to be truly fulfilled at the end of the world, is also declared by the blessed Apostle Peter in these words:
"But there were also false prophets among the people, just as there will be false teachers among you. They will secretly introduce destructive heresies, even denying the sovereign Lord who bought them-bringing swift destruction on themselves"
(Second Peter 2:1).
And a little later he adds:
"Their condemnation has long been hanging over them, and their destruction has not been sleeping"
(Second Peter 2:3).
Therefore, if we seek the eternal predestination of this judgment from God, let us carefully hear what he says:
"Their condemnation has long been hanging over them," that is, they are not judged for the first time now; nor for the first time when they depart from the body to eternal punishment.
But this judgment of their condemnation has long been decreed, long predestined from eternity; and it has long been prepared for them without ceasing.
If we seek to understand the punishment that will befall them through such judgment, it says their destruction does not slumber.
Likewise, regarding these wicked and blasphemous people, the same apostle says:
"These are waterless springs and mists driven by a storm, for whom the gloom of darkness has been reserved"
(Second Peter 2:17).
How has it been reserved for them, except that it was prepared for them from the beginning and will be given to them in the end?
Blessed Jude the apostle testifies to this with nearly the same words, saying:
"These are clouds without water, blown by winds; autumn trees without fruit, twice dead, uprooted; wild waves of the sea, casting up the foam of their own shame; wandering stars, for whom the storm of darkness is reserved forever"
(Jude 12, 13).
Against these horrendous and terrible threats that Almighty God warns the wicked and sinners through His prophets and apostles, he says:
All evil, sin, and its punishment do not exist.
And he asserts again:
The integrity of nature, life, and happiness exist.
But on the contrary, sin, death, and misery do not exist at all.
He further added:
Any defect or deprivation of perverse will, sin, and its end-death and the misery of eternal punishments-do not exist at all: and therefore, they are neither foreseen by God nor predestined.
If we must discuss any of these things individually, faith clearly knows that evil, which is contrary to good, just as vice is to virtue, darkness is to light, and sickness is to health, does not exist substantially.
Because, as has been said above, it does not have the substance of existing and subsisting by itself, like heaven, earth, water, air, fire, and other corporeal or spiritual creatures.
Rather, the desertion of the highest good, to which a rational creature, whether angelic or human, must adhere to be blessed, has received this name to be called evil.
Therefore, by deserting the highest good, rational creatures-whether angels or humans-sin and fall away from that good, are deprived of good, and this is their greatest evil.
Whether we say that evil is the abandonment of good, a deficiency of good, or the absence of good, we are correct.
Just as a vice is the abandonment of virtue, darkness is the absence of light, and weakness is simply a deficiency of health.
Similarly, sin has no substance of its own.
Instead, the abandonment and deficiency of justice are what we call sin.
Likewise, death has no substance of its own.
It is merely the loss of life.
In the same way, punishment has no substance, but pain and suffering from pain are called punishment.
This is just the disturbance or loss of tranquility and natural peace, as punishment disrupts the tranquility and peace of nature through pain and suffering.
All of these things-evil, sin, punishment, death, and misery, which is simply the loss of happiness-though they have no substance of their own, must necessarily occur within or from some substance.
The abandonment of good, called evil, and the abandonment of justice, called sin, clearly happen in either an angelic or human mind.
Similarly, the loss of life, called death, and the loss of tranquility or natural peace, called punishment, and the loss of happiness, called misery, are found in both the soul and the body.
The soul dies by abandoning its life, which is God, and the body dies by losing its life, which is the soul.
These two deaths-the death of the soul and the death of the body-are nothing but the loss of either happiness or tranquility in both.
But the punishment felt in torment and pain is clearly experienced either in the soul or in the body; and when it happens in the body, it is mostly inflicted by another body: like when someone is whipped, wounded with swords, or tortured.
This will also happen in eternal punishments, where the bodies of the damned will be tormented by fire and sulfur.
However, all these pains and torments inflicted on the body by other bodies also affect the soul through the body.
For the soul can feel pain and be tormented without the body; just like the soul of the rich man in hell, who said, "for I am tormented in this flame" (Luke 16:24); but the body cannot feel pain without the soul.
Therefore, the Almighty God, about whom it is written: "For before they were created, all things were known to the Lord God: so also after they were completed, He looks upon all things" (Sirach 23:29).
And again: "He looks from eternity to eternity, and nothing is new in His sight" (Sirach 39:21).
And again, when Scripture speaks about humans, it says: "And all their works are as the sun in the sight of God: every thought is known to Him, and no word is hidden from Him" (Sirach 17:26).
To this, I say, almighty and ineffable Creator, who, before they were created, knew all things in His eternal knowledge, who, even after He completed all things, sees them not differently, but just as He saw them to be done, sees everything not outside Himself, but in Himself.
And so, in His sight, nothing is new, not even when it was first created, because it has always been eternal in His knowledge.
All human deeds are as clear as day to Him; no human thought escapes Him, and no word of theirs is hidden from Him.
This wondrous Creator and governor, who always knew in His eternal foreknowledge the nature, form, and order of all things that were to be, likewise eternally foresaw their state, whether they would progress towards betterment or decline towards worse.
He, the most just ordainer of His work, both foresaw and predestined the rewards for those who would advance towards Him and the punishments for those who would stray from Him, and foretold that He would fulfill these.
So, whether it is evil and sin, which are a departure from good; or death and punishment, which are justly due to that departure, they have always been in the foreknowledge of the Creator, who alone truly knows the measure of advancement and decline in His creatures, and alone is the just judge of their progress and decline.
Thus, death and sin and all punishment and misery that follow from sin, because they have no substance of their own existence, are nothing.
And because they harm the rational creature, whose defect and corruption are signified by these names, they are truly felt in its substance, whether bodily or spiritual.
And what has no substance by existing is utterly harmful by causing harm.
Let such blasphemy cease, and let the omnipotent God be acknowledged as the creator of all natures, the truest knower of their state, and the most just ordainer.
Chapter Eleven
In the eleventh chapter, the following occurs and says.
1.
There is no predestination by God except for those who are prepared for eternal happiness.
2.
It is incorrect to say that God foresees and predestines everything: He foresaw what He would do and what He would not, as if He did not know.
Similarly, He predestined those He prepared for grace.
Conversely, He did not predestine the wicked for destruction or eternal punishment: if they are predestined, they will inevitably perish and suffer penalties.
If this is true, how can the world be justly judged if predestination forces it to perish?
3.
The Holy Scriptures often place foreknowledge and predestination together, or mention only absolute predestination, for those whom God has chosen for eternal happiness.
4.
The Apostle referred to foreknowledge and predestination only in the saints, while Augustine sometimes applied them to the reprobates.
Primarily, he says that there is no predestination by God except for those who are prepared for eternal happiness.
Whether he said this from his own understanding or heard it from others, we know that this is a modern error among many, who do not believe that God's predestination is found in the Scriptures except in part of the elect.
Nor did the blessed Apostle Paul place predestination in his Letters except only in the elect, as he also says in the following.
We must humbly submit and obey the truth; not contentiously defend what we once believed, but diligently scrutinize the Holy Scriptures, not only the apostolic but also the prophetic, from which all apostolic authority descends.
As the blessed Paul clearly declares at the beginning of the Epistle to the Romans, saying that he was set apart for the Gospel of God, which He had promised beforehand through His prophets in the Holy Scriptures.
Romans 1:1
At the end of the same letter, he confirms that the mystery of the gospel's preaching, including the deepest mystery of God's foreknowledge and predestination, has been revealed through the prophetic Scriptures.
He says:
"Now to him who is able to strengthen you, according to my gospel and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the mystery that was kept secret for long ages but has now been disclosed through the prophetic Scriptures, etc."
Romans 16:25-26.
Likewise, in the Acts of the Apostles, he speaks of himself, saying:
"To this day I stand testifying both to small and great, saying nothing but what the prophets and Moses said would come to pass"
Acts 26:22.
Therefore, when the Apostle shows and confirms that he has been set apart for the gospel of God, which was promised beforehand through the prophets in the holy Scriptures, and that all the mysteries he preaches are revealed through the Scriptures, and that he says nothing beyond what is written in the law and the prophets, it becomes clear. The depth of divine foreknowledge and predestination must be diligently investigated not only in the Apostle's teachings but also in the writings of the prophets themselves.
What is found in both with clear truth should be faithfully followed without any debate or controversy. So, let's first hear what the Apostle, who testifies that he says nothing beyond what is written in the law and the prophets, says about this matter.
Let's not be absurd or contentious by denying something about predestination just because the word "predestination" is not explicitly mentioned. Whether the term "predestination" is used or the truth of predestination is evident, it should be accepted with equal faith.
He first talks about the predestination of the elect in this way:
"For those whom He foreknew, He also predestined to be conformed to the image of His Son, so that He might be the firstborn among many brothers. And those whom He predestined, He also called; and those whom He called, He also justified; and those whom He justified, He also glorified"
(Romans 8:29-30).
After saying this, even if he had not mentioned the reprobates, we would still need to understand by contrast what should be thought about them.
Specifically, from the predestination of the elect to glory, we also recognize the predestination of the reprobates to punishment.
Just as in the creed we seem to only confess eternal life, which is the reward of the saints, by contrast, we must similarly and undoubtedly believe and understand eternal death, which is the damnation of the wicked.
The Apostle himself teaches us this rule of understanding in the Scriptures.
When he spoke about the resurrection, he said:
"It is sown a natural body, it is raised a spiritual body"
(First Corinthians 15:44).
To ensure he wasn't speaking about a "spiritual body" without Scriptural authority, he immediately added what must be understood by contrast, saying:
"If there is a natural body, there is also a spiritual body"
(First Corinthians 15:44).
Then, confirming both, he provides the testimony of Scripture and says:
"As it is written, 'The first man Adam became a living being'; the last Adam became a life-giving spirit"
(First Corinthians 15:45).
Similarly, when God said to the first man:
"Of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil you shall not eat; for in the day that you eat of it, you shall surely die"
(Genesis 2:17).
He certainly threatened death to the disobedient.
But doesn't faith recognize what should be understood by contrast, that He prepared life for the obedient?
Again, when God speaks to Abraham:
"Any male who is not circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin on the eighth day shall be cut off from his people; he has broken my covenant"
(Genesis 17:14).
It is clear that this man, who was not circumcised on the eighth day, will be cut off from his people because he has broken God's covenant.
This doesn't refer to the time in his mother's womb or his very early infancy when he could neither do good nor evil, but rather to the time in paradise with Adam's transgression, in which, as the Apostle says, all have sinned.
Those who descend from that condemned origin.
Therefore, just as this man, not circumcised on the eighth day, is clearly declared to be perishing due to the guilt of the first transgression, so it is to be faithfully understood that he who is properly and lawfully circumcised is absolved from that guilt.
We say this to make it clear that, even if the Apostle had remained silent about the fate of the reprobate in his discussion of predestination, our faith should nonetheless notice and understand what should be thought about them by the opposite implication.
However, he does not remain silent.
Right after presenting a similarity of both the elect and the reprobate, he adds this about the twins Isaac and Rebecca:
"Though they were not yet born and had done nothing either good or bad (so that God's purpose of election might continue), not because of works but because of his call, it was said to her, 'The older will serve the younger.
' As it is written, 'Jacob I loved, but Esau I hated.
'" (Romans 9:11-13; Malachi 1:1-2).
Therefore, it is clear in this example, and in Jacob, who was loved and chosen without any merits and yet was similarly subject to original sin, that the predestination of the elect to life is declared.
In Esau, who was hated solely due to the guilt of original sin, the predestination of the reprobate to destruction is declared.
This is further supported by what is stated shortly after about both sides:
"So then he has mercy on whomever he wills, and he hardens whomever he wills." (Romans 9:18).
And then he adds: Doesn't the potter have the power to make from the same lump of clay one vessel for honor and another for dishonor?
Romans chapter nine, verse twenty-one.
Regarding these vessels of honor and dishonor, he immediately adds: What if God, wanting to show His wrath and make His power known, endured with much patience the vessels of wrath prepared for destruction, and to make known the riches of His glory on the vessels of mercy, which He prepared beforehand for glory?
Romans chapter nine, verses twenty-two to twenty-three.
From all this, it is clear that the Apostle is speaking not only about the predestination of the elect, which he mentioned first, but in the broader context of his argument, he is addressing the predestination of both groups, whether to life or to death.
He has illustrated this with examples and prophetic testimonies, presenting Jacob as the example of the elect, and Esau as the example of the reprobate.
In these two groups, certainly, God shows mercy to whom He wills and hardens whom He wills.
But He shows mercy by mercifully helping, and hardens justly by abandoning.
Just like a potter from the same lump of clay, all of which was condemned, He makes one vessel for honor by mercifully delivering it, and another for dishonor by justly condemning it.
So there are two orders: some being vessels of wrath, and others vessels of mercy.
The former are prepared for destruction, the latter prepared for glory.
But those prepared for destruction are so by their own merit and by God's just judgment.
Those prepared for glory are so by no merit of their own, but by the benefit of divine grace alone.
Since the Apostle speaks so clearly: "And vessels of wrath made for destruction, and vessels of mercy prepared for glory, and from the same lump one vessel for honor, another for dishonor," who does not understand that in these words, the divine predestination of both parties is most clearly shown? The elect are predestined to life not by any merit of their own, but solely by God's goodness, while the reprobate are predestined to destruction not by any prejudice of God, but solely by their own merit, whether original or actual.
Divine predestination does not impose the necessity of perishing on them, just as it does not impose the necessity of sinning. It only imposes the necessity of suffering just punishments. So, those who remain in sins by their own will are tormented by necessity in punishments.
If we carefully and faithfully consider the Apostle's discussion from this passage to the end, where he says: "For God has imprisoned all in disobedience, so that he may have mercy on all" (Romans 11:32), we see that it is about the predestination of both parties.
This applies whether it is within the one people of the Jews, in those who were blinded, and in those who deserved to be saved according to the election of grace, or in both Jews and Gentiles.
While some were broken off like natural branches, and others were grafted into a good olive tree like a wild olive tree (Romans 11:17), without a doubt, he discusses this with his words and especially with prophetic testimonies.
In these prophetic testimonies, which the blessed Apostle proposed with such authority, he intended to teach us about the depth and obscurity of this matter-that is, divine predestination for either side-based on their firmness and evident attestation.
We must particularly consider with full dedication that, even though the word "predestination" isn't directly mentioned in these texts, the concepts themselves clearly relate to both types of predestination. They are evident and well-explained, which is why the Apostle confidently used them to confirm and teach this significant matter. He conveyed them to the Church to be understood and upheld, guiding us with his authority and example.
This way, we avoid contentious or unnecessary debates about the word "predestination" in the sayings of the holy prophets among ourselves, and certainly do not quarrel (God forbid).
Instead, with peaceful and pious understanding, wherever the matter is clearly declared, we must undoubtedly recognize and affirm divine predestination.
The first prophetic testimony he referenced is from Genesis, where he says: "For this is the word of promise: At this time I will come, and Sarah shall have a son" Romans 9:9. Although it may not seem to mention predestination directly, it clearly speaks of a promise. This promise can only be rightly understood if it is faithfully taken as the predestination of Abraham's chosen descendants, meaning those who are considered children of God, distinguished from the children of the flesh by divine grace.
As the Apostle himself explains in the same passage, saying: "It is not the children of the flesh who are the children of God; but the children of the promise are counted as offspring" Romans 9:8.
In the second place, he referenced a passage from Genesis about the twins, Isaac and Rebekah, where it was said, "The older will serve the younger" (Genesis 25:23).
Although predestination may not seem explicitly mentioned there, the matter is so deeply demonstrated that the Apostle urges us to pay careful attention to the entire oracle given to Rebekah about the twins.
We must consider that they were neither condemned from their mother's womb nor had they done anything good or bad in their lives.
They were conceived from the same union, yet Almighty God made a great distinction between them.
Without any preceding merits of good or evil, by His goodness and judgment alone, He preferred one and subjected the other to servitude.
And lest we think this is a minor issue, as if it were only about temporal circumstances where one descendant would dominate over the other, the Apostle elevates our understanding by adding a testimony from the prophet Malachi.
Here, God speaks about the same twins, not just temporally but eternally distinguished and separated by a great distance in both temporal and eternal matters.
God says, "I have loved Jacob, but Esau I have hated" (Malachi 1:2).
This prophetic testimony is rightly understood only when joined with the one from Genesis.
Just as it was said, "The older will serve the younger," so also, "I have loved Jacob, but Esau I have hated," is understood to have preceded before they were born and before they had done anything good or bad. It must be accepted that in the just divine judgment, both God's love for Jacob and His hatred for Esau preceded.
And with these two things-God's love towards one and hatred towards the other, and their birth, and all the merit of their lives having been predetermined according to the true and apostolic understanding-since neither could be blamed for any bad things they had not yet done, nor credited for any good things they had not yet performed, it is understood that these actions are justly done.
The almighty God, who had eternally determined in his judgment both the election of one and the rejection of the other, had predefined the original guilt in them coming from Adam's transgression, to which both were equally bound.
Foreseeing the future, he would mercifully love one and liberate him, and justly hate and reject the other and condemn him.
From this, we may faithfully understand the deeper and more hidden arrangement of divine judgment.
We may perceive more profoundly, with the enlightening apostolic understanding, the general condemnation of the entire human race in Adam: from which the almighty God liberates those he wishes by his grace alone and condemns those he does not wish by his eternal justice.
Although in this prophetic testimony, where God says, "I have loved Jacob, but Esau I have hated," (Malachi 1:2-3), the word predestination does not appear, the truth of the matter is so evident in the election or rejection of both parties that nothing stronger or more explicit could be said.
From the form of these twins, almighty God is shown by his testimony to have loved some with his eternal mercy and hated others with his eternal judgment.
This prophetic testimony and apostolic understanding show that both the love and the hatred of God towards the two twins, still in their mother's womb, are understood from God's mercy and judgment.
The words of the prophet Isaiah wonderfully resonate and agree with this, where the almighty God is shown as the helper of the chosen people from the womb, and conversely, the condemner of the reprobate people as if from the womb of a transgressor.
The same prophet says first to the chosen people: "This is what the Lord says, the one who made and formed you, your helper from the womb" (Isaiah 44:2).
Then, after addressing the people, adding in the voice of God:
"And I called you a transgressor from the womb" (Isaiah 68:8).
The Apostle clearly explains that what was shown in the form of the twins must be understood as referring to the two types of people, namely the chosen and the rejected.
While some are accused by divine judgment as transgressors from the womb, God similarly shows Himself as a helper from the womb to others, so that from the same originally condemned mass in the maternal womb, some vessels become for honor, and others for dishonor (Romans 9:21,15).
Similarly, in the third prophetic testimony, which is stated as:
"For He says to Moses: I will have mercy on whom I have mercy, and I will have compassion on whom I have compassion" (Exodus 33:19).
The word of predestination is clearly implied.
The matter is so clear that it cannot be doubted at all.
Since Almighty God, to all equally condemned from that first transgression, not for any preceding good merits, but by His grace alone, shows mercy to whom He shows mercy, and becomes compassionate to whom He grants compassion; it is evident that to the others, to whom He chooses not to grant this grace, He justly and eternally judges them with hatred and condemnation.
After this, he added the fourth prophetic testimony, just as the third from Exodus, saying:
"For the Scripture says to Pharaoh: For this very purpose I have raised you up, that I might show my power in you, and that my name might be proclaimed in all the earth" (Romans 9:17).
Although the term "predestination" isn't explicitly mentioned here, the concept of the wicked being destined for eternal destruction because of their own wickedness is made so clear that anyone who hears and understands it faithfully cannot doubt it. The impious, hard, and unyielding king of the Egyptians, by divine judgment, whether due to his damned origin or the power of his royal honor, was raised up solely for this purpose: that he, being deserving of eternal destruction by his own merit, with God adding iniquity upon iniquity, would increase his contempt for the Lord.
By such great and various plagues, through God's admirable power, he deserved to be scourged and ultimately, along with all his similarly impious people, to be destroyed by eternal submersion and perdition. They would justly receive what they deserved, and God's omnipotent power, whether in their scourging or their destruction, would become more magnificently known to all. From the punishment of one, many would advance to the knowledge of God and their own salvation.
As blessed Ambrose clearly discusses this matter: Thus says blessed Ambrose. The apostle, after presenting two testimonies-one pertaining to the mercy granted to the elect, the other to the judgment inflicted on the reprobate-and as if concluding both, teaching that both occur by the merciful and just will of God, adds: Therefore, He has mercy on whom He wills, and He hardens whom He wills. (Romans 9:18)
Then, against the audacity and presumption of men who, not recognizing their own fragility nor considering their own merits, dare to criticize divine judgments they do not understand, he presents a fifth testimony from the prophet Isaiah, saying: O man, who are you to answer back to God?
Does the molded object say to its maker: Why did you make me like this?
(Isaiah 45; Romans 9)
Although the word "predestination" is not mentioned, the concept is so clearly and perfectly defended that it compels the faithful listener to truly understand that the omnipotent Creator is a true potter. All humans, made from the clay of the earth by Him, are His creation. Therefore, for the most just reason, the creation cannot judge its potter; rather, the potter judges his creation. He alone knows with His eternal counsel how to kindly shape each vessel of His great creation, and to ordain and arrange them for the uses that please Him, which are indeed just and proper.
To make this even clearer, he adds a sixth testimony from the prophet Jeremiah, saying: "Does not the potter have the power to make from the same lump of clay one vessel for honor, and another for dishonor?" (Romans 9:21).
In the book of Jeremiah, we read that the Lord said to him, "Arise, and go down to the potter's house, and there you will hear my words." (Jeremiah 18:2 ff.) When the prophet entered, the potter was working a piece of clay with his hands.
Suddenly, the work he was making was spoiled, and immediately he turned and made it into another vessel, as it seemed good to him.
Then the prophet was commanded to go and proclaim to the people from the person of God: "Can I not do to you as this potter does, O house of Israel?" says the Lord: "Behold, like clay in the hand of the potter, so are you in my hand," etc. (Jeremiah 18:6).
With this prophetic reading, God clearly shows that He is the potter, and all of humanity is like clay in His hands.
He can shape different vessels from it as He pleases.
From one single lump, all equally condemned in Adam, He makes vessels distinct and different by His judgment.
Some are made for honor, and others for dishonor.
Even a vessel destined for destruction, if through the potter's repentance, is broken in His hands and is no longer fit for destruction, it is reshaped through His wisdom and goodness into a vessel for honor, pleasing the Creator's eyes.
In all these words, although predestination is not explicitly stated, the power and truth of predestination are shown on both sides: the elect and the reprobate, the vessels of honor and the vessels of dishonor.
It is revealed with such clarity and distinction that nothing could be found more certain or clearer.
We have presented all these things with careful and diligent consideration to the readers, so that according to this form of apostolic understanding in all prophetic Scriptures, we do not struggle much with the word predestination.
The truth of divine predestination matters is so clearly and abundantly presented that human frailty can scarcely grasp it all.
We have included some examples here, especially those that are clearer and more evident, so that the peaceful and faithful listeners may be more easily instructed, and the contentious, if they do not refuse to accept the truth, may be corrected sooner.
We do not discuss the predestination of the elect now, since understanding and faithfully believing it is clearly presented by the Apostle through prophetic testimonies.
None of us should doubt, with the Lord's guidance, the just judgment of predestination by which He has preordained and destined the wicked for destruction.
This is a topic that many hesitate over.
We will share a few clear examples from many.
In the book of Genesis, we read that Almighty God foretold the destruction of the entire human race, except for those saved by His mercy in the ark, because of their excessive iniquities and impieties.
They would perish in the present and face eternal damnation in the future.
He spoke to the holy patriarch Noah, saying:
"The end of all flesh has come before me. The earth is filled with iniquity because of them, and I will destroy them with the earth"
Genesis 6:13.
Regarding this general destruction, earlier in the same Scripture, it says:
"And God said: My spirit shall not remain in man forever, because he is flesh. And his days shall be one hundred and twenty years"
Genesis 6:3.
And a little later:
"But God saw that the wickedness of man was great on the earth, and every intention of the thoughts of his heart was only evil continually. And it repented the Lord that he had made man on the earth"
Genesis 6:5-6.
Where it is also added:
"I will destroy man whom I have created from the face of the earth, both man and beast, and creeping thing, and the birds of the heavens. For it repents me that I have made them"
Genesis 6:7.
What could be clearer than such a prediction and predestination of the destruction of all the wicked, with whom the world was then filled? This is what God wanted to announce long before to the holy and chosen patriarch. He decided and predetermined this in His eternal counsel, showing that He had established and predetermined these things not through an angel or any prophet of that time, but by Himself.
And yet, the most kind judge and creator did not abandon even those whom he had justly predestined to such dreadful destruction and death because of their iniquities and impieties.
He still showed them the goodness and pity of his mercy.
He granted them time and space to repent, giving them 120 years to either satisfy God by repenting worthily or, if they accumulated wrath for themselves due to their hard and unrepentant hearts, to perish inexcusably on the day of wrath.
In this way, he predestined them to destruction because of their wickedness, but he did not compel them to sin by predestination.
He waited for them to repent for so many years.
The book of Ecclesiasticus speaks lamentably about the unfortunate stubbornness and terrible damnation of these people, mentioning their destruction, saying:
"The ancient giants did not plead for their sins, who were destroyed, trusting in their own strength: and he did not spare their journey and cursed them because of their pride. He did not have mercy on them, destroying the whole nation that exalted itself in its sins. And like the 600,000 foot soldiers who gathered in the hardness of their hearts: and if one had been stiff-necked, it would be a wonder if he had been spared. For mercy and wrath are with him. He is powerful in supplication and pours out wrath. According to his mercy, so does his correction judge a man according to his works."
(Ecclesiasticus 16:8-13).
Such is the prediction and predestination of God speaking to Abraham about the future oppression, affliction, and deliverance of his descendants, and conversely, the damnation and destruction of their oppressors, when he said to him:
"Know for certain that your descendants will be strangers in a land that is not theirs, and they will be enslaved and afflicted for 400 years. But I will judge the nation that they serve, and afterward, they shall come out with great possessions."
But you will go to your ancestors in peace, buried at a good old age.
However, in the fourth generation, they will return here, for the iniquities of the Amorites are not yet complete up to the present time.
Genesis 15:13-16.
What could be clearer than this predestination?
It predicts that the descendants of Abraham will live as strangers in a foreign land for many years and that they will be subjected to servitude and affliction.
From this very affliction, they will be gloriously liberated, and at the appointed time-in the fourth generation-they will return to the land promised to their ancestors.
The blessed patriarch himself will be united with his ancestors in peace and good old age.
Conversely, the nation and the king of the Egyptians, who will oppress them, are destined for eternal destruction by the eternal judgment of God.
A similar, or even more evident, prophecy and predestination is about the destruction of the Amorites, or rather the seven most wicked nations.
Due to their impiety, the almighty God determined long beforehand that He would destroy and wipe them out, as He clearly declared to Abraham when He said, "For the iniquities of the Amorites are not yet complete up to the present time."
He had promised the same holy patriarch that, once they were destroyed, He would hand over their kingdoms and lands to his descendants as a possession. Yet this just and merciful judge did not wish to do this out of favoritism. According to His goodness, patience, and long-suffering, He waited and delayed for many ages, giving them a space for repentance. If those nations persisted in their impieties and fulfilled the measure of their sins, they would be justly punished in the fullness of their iniquities. In their place, the descendants of Abraham, who were to serve God, would succeed-not because of favoritism or their own righteousness, but solely by divine goodness.
When the time came for the destruction of these nations due to their iniquities, and for the introduction of the seed of Abraham into their lands through God's mercy, God spoke about their sins and the imminent, just destruction to the seed of Abraham, that is, to the people of Israel, saying:
"Do not defile yourselves with any of these things with which all the nations that I am driving out before you have been defiled, and with which the land has become polluted. I will punish its sins so that it will vomit out its inhabitants" (Leviticus 18:24-25).
Shortly after, He said:
"For all these abominations have the inhabitants of the land done, who were before you, and have polluted it. Therefore, be careful that the land does not vomit you out as it vomited out the nation that was before you when you do the same things" (Leviticus 18:27-28).
Concerning the ultimate destruction of these nations, both in the present and in the future, Scripture generally says:
"For it was the Lord's decision to harden their hearts so that they would fight against Israel, fall, and not deserve any mercy, but perish, as the Lord had commanded Moses" (Joshua 11:20).
What could be clearer about the predestination of the wicked to eternal destruction than this: Almighty God, who had decreed this in His secret judgment, had foretold these things to Abraham long before, had frequently threatened them in the intervening times, and finally, Scripture confirms that it was His decision, that is, His counsel and judgment, that they should not deserve any mercy but should utterly and eternally perish in their wickedness and contempt.
Regarding these divine judgments, the Book of Wisdom also speaks to God, saying:
"For who will say to you, 'What have you done?' or who will stand against your judgment? Or who will come before you as an avenger of wicked people? Or who will blame you if the nations perish that you have made?"
For there is no other God but you, who cares for everyone.
You judge justly, and neither king nor tyrant will question those you have destroyed in your presence.
Since you are just, you arrange everything justly.
Wisdom of Solomon 12:12-15.
Similarly, when the same Scripture distinguishes between divine goodness towards His people and righteous severity towards their enemies, specifically the Egyptians, destined for eternal ruin, it says:
Showing how you exalted your own people and killed their adversaries.
When they were tested, they received discipline with mercy and learned how the wicked, judged in anger, suffered torment.
You tested these people like a father admonishing them; but you condemned those others like a stern king interrogating them.
Wisdom of Solomon 11:9-11.
And again:
It was fitting that destruction without excuse should come upon those exercising tyranny, but to show how their enemies were exterminated.
Wisdom of Solomon 16:4.
And again:
Even the righteous were touched by the trial of death, and there was a disturbance in the wilderness among the multitude, but your anger did not last long.
A brief trial of wrath was sufficient; but upon the wicked, wrath came without mercy until the end.
Wisdom of Solomon 18:20, 25 and 19:1.
And shortly after, regarding the eternal destruction of the Egyptians in the Red Sea, it says:
While still mourning and lamenting at the graves of the dead, they took up another thought of ignorance.
Those whom they had begged to leave, they pursued as fugitives.
A fitting necessity led them to this end, and they lost the memory of what had happened, so that the punishment might complete the torments that were lacking.
Your people crossed over miraculously, while they found a new death.
Wisdom of Solomon 19:3-5.
Similarly, in the book of the prophet Daniel,
Daniel
The four great cardinal kingdoms of the future, their order, their times, and their eternal nature and destruction, as determined by divine predestination, are revealed through God's admirable foreknowledge and arrangement.
These kingdoms are depicted either as four metals in the statue seen by the king in his dreams or as four beasts rising from the sea.
They are also foretold through prophecies of kings and wars up to the end times, including the downfall of the Antichrist and the coming of Christ for judgment.
These kingdoms, along with the kingdom of the Antichrist, have brought great and horrendous evils to the world and have greatly oppressed and attacked the Church of God.
Who can fully comprehend this?
Yet, all these events, whether past or future, are understood to have happened or will happen according to the eternal judgment of divine foreknowledge and predestination.
They have been wonderfully foretold in their order, marked by their times, and set to end at their appointed limits, as recognized and described long ago through prophetic revelation.
If we look for the term "predestination," which is the decree and pre-definition of divine judgment in prophetic words, we find a remarkable and memorable example in the prophet Isaiah. He speaks historically about the destruction of the Babylonian and Assyrian kingdoms, but mystically about the destruction of the entire city of the devil at the end of the world. He introduces Almighty God swearing-confirming His words with His unchanging truth-and says in Isaiah 14:24, 26, 27:
"The Lord of hosts has sworn, saying: Surely, as I have thought, so it shall be: and as I have purposed, so shall it come to pass." And a little later: "This is the plan determined for the whole earth: and this is the hand stretched out over all nations. For the Lord of hosts has decreed it: and who can annul it? His hand is stretched out, and who can turn it back?"
Clearly observe the predestination of the destruction of the reprobate-those nations opposing the people of God and His enemies.
This happens through the divine mind's discussion and counsel, its decree, and the extension of God's hand, signifying the fulfillment and perfection of all works under an oath.
This oath declares the immovable firmness of divine counsel.
In the vision of the great tree, which extended to the ends of the earth and was seen by the king in a dream, God ordered it to be cut down.
This tree represented the height of worldly power, often overthrown by divine judgment due to arrogance.
This vision shows that such events occur by the predestination, decree, and judgment of divine counsel, through the ministries of holy angels.
The king himself recounts this dream: I was looking in the vision of my head on my bed: and behold, a watcher, and a holy one descended from heaven.
He cried aloud and said: Cut down the tree, and cut off its branches, shake off its leaves, and scatter its fruit, etc.
(Daniel 4:10-11).
And later: In the decree of the watchers, it is determined, and by the word of the holy ones, until the living know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men, and gives it to whomever he will (Daniel 4:17).
These things were not done just for Nebuchadnezzar, but to instill fear and humility in all worldly powers who read or hear these words.
It serves to remind everyone that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men, giving and taking away power according to His judgment.
Since this is orchestrated through angelic ministries, it is said that the decree of the watchers and the word of the holy ones will be fulfilled in these matters.
The prophet further clarifies that the watchers' sentence is the sentence of the Most High, saying: This is the interpretation of the sentence of the Most High, which has come upon my lord the king (Daniel 4:24).
Therefore, the decree of divine judgment, by which events are determined and established by God, belongs to the Most High and the holy angels.
The Most High judges and commands, while the holy angels, who judge all lower things under His authority, obey and execute these commands.
They are granted authority so that their words in such matters carry the weight of command.
However, a petition is added, so that whatever is to be carried out in the world by them may be obtained through prayer to God.
This predestination and determination of divine judgment is briefly shown by the prophet Ezekiel.
In reference to the kingdom and priesthood of Judah, due to their impiety in the last times when Christ the Lord is coming, it is said to the condemned king: "But you, profane and wicked prince of Israel, whose day has come in the time of iniquity appointed," thus says the Lord: "Remove the turban, take off the crown" (Ezekiel 21:25).
The crown represents the kingdom and the turban represents the priests.
Both were taken away from that people when Christ the Lord came, as their day of appointed iniquity arrived.
The Lord also speaks of the sharpened and polished sword for the slaughter and destruction of the wicked: "To be placed on the necks of the slain wicked, whose day has come in the time of appointed iniquity" (Ezekiel 21:29).
These predestinations are clearly shown by the Apostle in his letters and by the prophets in the ancient Scriptures.
Through these, we see that nothing is unjust or disorderly; everything is arranged with justice and reason.
Blessed Augustine, faithfully following this apostolic and prophetic authority, spoke truly of predestination in the just judgments and dispositions of God.
Contrary to what some may falsely claim, Augustine did not pretend, but spoke against the deceitful and false rules that attempt to destroy what is affirmed as true by one, using similarity and opposition.
He wants everything stated simply and truthfully in the Holy Scriptures or in the teachings of the Fathers about predestination, particularly regarding the reprobate, to be understood in the opposite way.
So, what was done should be seen as not done, and what was said should be seen as not said.
Who has ever heard such madness?
Shouldn't anyone who dares to think or write such blatant lies against the truth of the Scriptures and the purity of the Fathers' teachings be kept far away from everyone's ears?
After presenting so many deceitful arguments, he suddenly remembers the Holy Scriptures, the Apostle, and Augustine, almost as if in a dream.
However, his conclusion from the Holy Scriptures and the Apostle, that nothing about the predestination of the wicked to eternal punishment is mentioned, is clearly shown above to be a blatant lie.
He claims about God, according to his ridiculous and contemptible rule: "He foreknew what He would not do, instead of He didn't know."
Who has ever heard such a thing?
That where we read that God foreknew something, we understand that He didn't know.
Both are certainly false, that either "He foreknew" is understood as "He didn't know," or that what God would not do is said because He didn't know:
Who truly, with His eternal knowledge, as He foreknew whatever He was going to do, so also He foreknew whatever He was not going to do.
For example, He foreknew that He would raise Lazarus and did so; He foreknew that He would not raise Judas and did not do so.
But this man says: "He predestined the wicked to destruction or eternal punishment, instead of not predestined";
that is, where we read "He predestined," we understand with unheard-of madness "He did not predestine."
He also raises the question: "How will the world be justly judged, which is forced to perish by the necessity of predestination?"
Let none of us say such a thing.
Because it is the most obvious blasphemy to say that God, by the prejudice of His predestination, forces someone to sin and perish by sinning.
By the just judgment of His predestination, those whom He has decided to punish for persisting in sins, He calls back from sin and instills a healthy fear in those who listen.
This fear corrects them, and through correction, they avoid condemnation.
Chapter Twelve
In this chapter, he introduces definitions like these:
1.
All of God's foreknowledge is predestination, and all predestination is foreknowledge.
2.
All of God's predestination is entirely the preparation of grace, and all grace is a gift.
Therefore, all divine predestination is the preparation of His gifts.
3.
Punishment tortures the wicked justly, which is not a gift; otherwise, if it were a gift, it would not torture but surely liberate.
Therefore, punishment is not predestination.
If it were, it would not be punishment but grace.
However, it is punishment, so it is not predestination.
4.
Hence, predestination should always be understood in terms of the gifts of divine generosity.
Those predestined for punishment are always understood in opposition, like the elect for the non-elect: the children of God for the non-children.
Anyone who has diligently read and faithfully understood what we have previously said according to the rule of faith, with the Lord's help, can easily judge and refute these four very long and meaningless propositions, seemingly crafted with the artifice of syllogisms.
For who does not understand how blasphemous and impious it is to say, as he does here in the first statement, that all of God's foreknowledge is predestination?
When faith clearly holds that the omnipotent God foresees all things, both good and evil: what He Himself will do and what He will not do; but predestines only the good, which He will do either by mercifully liberating and rewarding the elect or justly condemning the reprobate, because what is just is certainly good.
Therefore, if according to his definition, all of God's foreknowledge is predestination, then everything He foreknew, including evil, He predestined Himself to do, which is absurd!
Because He only foreknew evil, but in no way predestined it, as He was not going to do it Himself, unlike everything He predestined.
Neither did He decide or ordain that it should happen.
Similarly, the premise of the second proposition begins with falsehood and therefore also ends with falsehood.
For it is said:
All predestination by God is entirely a preparation of grace.
This has been clearly shown with apostolic and prophetic testimonies, where we found and demonstrated that God's predestination must be understood in two ways: either for the merciful reward of the good or for the just damnation of the wicked.
Therefore, as the words of the blessed Augustine, which we cited earlier, clearly teach, God's predestination, when understood in a positive sense, is a preparation of grace.
In the third proposition, it is very false to assert that there is no predestination to punishment.
For if the punishment for the devil, his angels, and all the reprobates who are to be punished with them was not predestined, Truth would never say: "Go into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels" (Matthew 25:41).
And what he states at the end of this third proposition-that predestination must always be understood in terms of the gifts of divine generosity-is also false.
Predestination is truly understood not only in the gifts of divine generosity but also in the judgments of just damnation.
His fourth proposition, which is as follows: The predestined to punishment should always be understood in the opposite way, belongs to that insanity discussed earlier, where he wants us to understand predestined as non-predestined.
But what he added, by way of example: Just as elect means non-elect; children of God means non-children, will be better discussed in the following chapter, where he explains more broadly what he thinks about these things.
It must be remembered and recognized, however, that the blessed Augustine, as his words cited above demonstrate, sometimes said that in Scriptures the foreknowledge of God signifies predestination (On the Gift of Perseverance, chapter 18).
From these words, he, as if taking the opportunity for his argument, goes against this very true statement, which Augustine sometimes taught should be understood in this way, adding the word "all" and removing "sometimes."
And so, he gave a very incorrect definition, saying:
All foreknowledge of God is predestination.
Similarly, because the blessed Augustine, as we mentioned earlier, defined predestination as the preparation of grace by God
(On the Predestination of the Saints, chapter 10),
which applies only to the elect, he added the word "all," and made a very incorrect definition, saying:
All predestination by God is entirely the preparation of grace.
Chapter Thirteen
In the thirteenth chapter, it says this:
1.
To consider Judas as chosen instead of not chosen, and the children of God instead of not the children, is to take it in the opposite sense: just like the same friend who was never not an enemy.
2.
It is pointless to seek the children of God outside of His chosen ones: it is pointless to think that His chosen ones are not predestined by Him.
3.
Likewise, it is impious to think that those predestined by God are not among His chosen ones, or to consider the chosen ones of God as different from His children, nor to be predestined if they are not children of God.
4.
Those predestined for punishment, destruction, or suffering should be understood as nothing other than not predestined; but from the mass condemned by the merit of original and personal sin, they are not separated: therefore, they are allowed to live impiously and will be punished with eternal fire.
In these words, it is understood that Judas was counted among the chosen apostles by the Lord, where it says: "Did I not choose the twelve of you?" (John 6:71).
So the others are understood to be truly chosen, but he in a contrary sense, that is, ironically, is called so; it is better if it is taken this way so that Truth is recognized to have spoken truly.
So all twelve are understood to have been chosen by the Lord: but the others in one way, Judas in another, that is, the others eternally to the kingdom, this one temporally to ministry.
For he was chosen for a time among the others to the apostolic ministry, sent to the office of preaching: he also perhaps received the grace of miracles; hence blessed Peter in the Acts of the Apostles speaks of him this way: "For he was numbered among us and received his share in this ministry" (Acts 1:17).
And when they had set up two, and prayed that God would show which of them should be appointed to the place that he had lost by transgressing, they prayed saying: "You, God, who knows the hearts of all, show which of these two you have chosen to take the place in this ministry and apostleship from which Judas turned aside to go to his own place" (Acts 1:24-25).
Thus, he was chosen by the Lord to be temporarily associated with the apostles and to share in their ministry and apostleship.
It is said that he fell from the apostolic rank.
However, the Lord, who always knew in his eternal foreknowledge the unwavering faith of the other apostles and his fall and future ruin, did not do this out of ignorance of the future.
As the blessed John the Evangelist testifies, "For Jesus knew from the beginning who they were that did not believe, and who it was that would betray him" (John 6:64).
Therefore, the Lord himself, after saying what was previously mentioned, "Did I not choose you, the twelve?" (John 6:70), immediately added, as one truly knowing the future, "And one of you is a devil." The Evangelist, explaining who he was talking about, immediately added, "He was speaking of Judas son of Simon Iscariot, for he, one of the twelve, was going to betray him" (John 6:71).
He also knew the place of his damnation in eternal punishment, which was deservedly assigned and predestined for his impiety.
Thus, the apostles said, "To go to his own place" (Acts 1:25).
And the Lord himself said, "Woe to that man by whom the Son of Man is betrayed; it would have been better for that man if he had not been born" (Matthew 26:24).
And yet, he wanted him to take on the ministry and position of apostleship for a time.
This way, when he misused the Lord's great goodness, the Lord would, in contrast, use his great evil for our great good.
By teaching through such an example, he showed that in his Church, there would be bad people mixed in, just as this man was among the apostles for a time.
He shared with the Church not only the sacraments and divine ministries but also the place of governance.
He demonstrated patience to his followers, showing how he tolerated the bad, knowing this man well and enduring him with amazing patience.
This taught true believers that they were not defiled by such company and that their God-given ministries should not be rejected.
The blessed apostles were not defiled by his false companionship, nor was his ministry, as long as it was done according to God, disapproved of.
When his wretchedness reached the point of betrayal, the great evil of one man was turned into the good of the whole world.
Through this, the true Lamb who takes away the sin of the world was sacrificed.
The good Lord chose him for good, granting him good things and turning his evil into our good.
His transgressions and perdition were due to his own wickedness, but being chosen among the good was due to the Lord's goodness.
If he had remained in goodness, as the Apostle says:
"Consider therefore the goodness and severity of God: severity to those who have fallen, but goodness to you, provided you continue in his goodness" (Romans 11:22).
Regarding the temporary ministry of apostleship, about which the Lord said:
"Did I not choose you, the Twelve?" (John 6:71),
it can be well said that he was chosen among the others.
But concerning the eternal election to beatitude, only those were chosen of whom he said, when distinguishing between him and them:
"I do not speak of all of you; I know whom I have chosen" (John 13:18).
Therefore, it can be well and truly understood that it was said, with Judas included:
"Did I not choose you, the Twelve?"
And when that one was separated as a reprobate: I know whom I have chosen.
It's not necessary to interpret it any other way.
Both are clearly shown to be true by evident reasoning.
For it is also written about Saul when he was chosen for the kingdom, for which he was to be useful in many ways.
He indeed received this as chosen, as Scripture says:
There was a man from the tribe of Benjamin named Saul, chosen and good, and there was no one among the children of Israel better than him (First Samuel 9:2).
However, he was later very unhappily rejected, cast off, and perished.
Yet, for a time, he is said to have been chosen for a certain temporal usefulness of the kingdom.
He was preferred to the people of God by the mystical anointing and by the choice of lot through the holy prophet.
But where the evangelical Scripture specifically names Judas as a son, we do not read.
For when the Lord said of the apostles: The wedding guests cannot fast while the bridegroom is with them (Luke 5:34), there is no necessity that this should not also be rightly understood as said of the others, excluding Judas.
For it exclusively pertains to those, with him already lost, what the Lord adds, saying:
The days will come when the bridegroom will be taken away from them, and then they will fast in those days (Luke 5:35).
But if anyone wishes to understand that Judas himself is among the sons in these words of the Lord, it can clearly be so because of some faith he had in the Lord and the fellowship of the sacraments, by which he was joined to the holy apostles.
Not contrary but rightly and consequently he could be called so.
Thus, even when the Lord said to the one who was about to betray Him and mark Him with a kiss:
Friend, why have you come?
(Matthew 26:50), it can be well understood.
Not what was happening at that moment, but what had been reproached to him before: that when he had once been, in a certain way, a disciple and friend, he suddenly turned into such a cruel and impious enemy.
But even if this was said ironically, as some have interpreted, it does not lend any validity to the rule of this new and foolish debater.
It's one thing to sarcastically state something true, like when we indignantly or reproachfully say to a bad man, "You are a good man," or to someone acting poorly, "You are doing well," or to an enemy, "Friend," and many similar things. It's quite another thing, according to this diabolical rule, to openly deny the truth with falsehood. For instance, when someone, justly condemned by divine judgment for their impiety, is truthfully said to be predestined for punishment, and this person, in new madness, falsely teaches that "predestined" means "not predestined."
With this most perverse and false understanding, neither Scripture, which must never be misinterpreted in matters of faith, nor any ecclesiastical teacher, nor any truthful person has ever spoken. But if no one is predestined by the just judgment of God to suffer punishment for sins, as some claim, what did the Apostles mean when they prayed to the Lord about Judas, saying, "Judas turned aside to go to his own place"? Acts 1:25. What did Solomon mean when he said, "The Lord has made everything for its purpose, even the wicked for the day of trouble"? Proverbs 16:4.
What is meant in the book of Job, where it is written, "The wicked are reserved for the day of doom; they shall be brought forth to the day of wrath"? Job 21:30. Why does Scripture say about the Egyptians in the Red Sea, who were destined to be eternally destroyed, "For a deserved necessity led them to this end"? Wisdom 19:4. This clearly shows that they were led to destruction by the necessity of divine judgment, and yet deservedly so for their impiety and contempt.
What also is meant by what is written elsewhere: "He who turns from righteousness to sin, God has prepared him for the sword"? Ecclesiasticus 26:27. And the angel said to Blessed John in the Revelation about the Antichrist, who is yet to be revealed and destroyed at the end of the world: "The beast that you saw was, and is not, and is about to rise from the abyss and go to destruction" Revelation 17:8.
If this is not predestined by God, how does the angel say,
"These words are the most faithful and true words of God"?
(Revelation 21:5)
If the same Antichrist, the man of sin, the son of perdition
(Second Thessalonians 2:3) ,
along with all his followers, is not predestined for the judgment of eternal damnation, how does the Apostle clearly say about him,
"Whom the Lord Jesus will kill with the spirit of his mouth, and will destroy with the brightness of his coming"?
(Second Thessalonians 2:8)
And about all who are to be deceived by him, and who will perish with him forever, he adds shortly after,
"Because they did not receive the love of the truth so that they might be saved, God will send them a powerful delusion so that they will believe the lie, and all will be judged who did not believe the truth but consented to unrighteousness"
(Second Thessalonians 2:10-11)
How is it said in the prophet Ezekiel, regarding the sharpened and polished sword for the slaughter and destruction of the wicked,
"That it may be upon the necks of the wicked who are to be slain, whose day has come, in the time of iniquity that is predetermined"?
(Ezekiel 21:29)
Why does the same prophet also say about the Jews who will lose both kingdom and priesthood, and will perish in their infidelity under the persona of the wicked king,
"And you, profane, wicked prince of Israel, whose day has come, in the time of iniquity that is predetermined, this is what the Lord says: Remove the turban, take off the crown"?
(Ezekiel 21:25-26)
The crown being the kingdom, and the turban being the priesthood, as we have already stated, is clear.
If anyone objects that these two prophetic examples do not indicate predestination but predetermination, let them understand that predestination is nothing else but the predetermination of a future event.
This is clearly shown by the Apostle, saying,
"According to the predetermination of the ages, which he made in Christ Jesus our Lord"
(Ephesians 3:11)
For where we read "predetermination" in Latin, in Greek it has Prothesin, which is properly translated into Latin as "purpose."
Which message is also placed in the Letter to the Romans, where the same Apostle says:
"And we know that in all things God works for the good of those who love Him, who have been called according to His purpose" (Romans 8:28).
But the purpose of God is nothing other than the predestination of God, as the same Apostle explains, for after saying "those who have been called according to His purpose," he immediately adds, "For those God foreknew He also predestined to be conformed to the image of His Son" (Ephesians 3:29).
From all these things, we can most rightly understand that the purpose of God, the predestination of God, and the foreordination of God are one and the same.
This foreordination, that is, predestination, is most clearly placed in the Apostle's words in a good sense and in the Prophet's words, which we mentioned earlier, in a bad sense, as it designates those ordained to life here, but there those ordained to destruction.
Such are the vessels of wrath, as the same Apostle says (Romans 9:22), "prepared for destruction," or, as others have translated it, "perfected for destruction," both by their own merit and by the just divine judgment.
About whom he says:
"Because they are left in the mass of the damned due to the merit of original sin, allowed to live wickedly, and ultimately to be punished with eternal fire," and even unwilling and contradicting, he says nothing other than that they are predestined by divine judgment to eternal fire.
For if that mass is wholly damned, it is undoubtedly condemned by the just judgment of God and condemned to eternal perdition and punishment.
What else is this than to say that this same mass is condemned by divine judgment to eternal destruction?
Thus, while trying to resist the truth, he is compelled, even unwilling and unaware, to confess the truth with invincible reason.
Chapter Fourteen
In this chapter, it states:
From the words of Augustine, it is shown that only the just are considered predestined, as he says:
We do not know who belongs to the number of the predestined and who does not.
And again: We cannot distinguish the predestined from the non-predestined.
Also: Those who fall and perish were not among the predestined.
The punishment predestined for sinners: those who are foreknown only, not predestined.
This is also inferred from human laws, which do not define a person as sinful, but by defining the punishments for those who will sin, aim to deter those prone to sinning by the severity of the punishments; and through this, they bring about no less mercy than retribution for the transgressors.
To these words, we respond, indeed from the words of the blessed Augustine
(On the Predestination of the Saints, chapter 10, 16)
it is shown that the predestined can also come from the unjust.
When he defined what predestination is, he said: The predestination of God, which is in good, is the preparation of grace.
Without a doubt, he would not have added "in good" unless he knew that predestination also exists in evil, as he clearly demonstrates from the book of Acts of the Apostles, citing the passage:
For truly in this city, they were gathered together against your holy servant Jesus, whom you anointed, Herod and Pilate, along with the people of Israel, to do whatever your hand and your plan had predestined to take place
(Acts 4:27-28)
He also added: Indeed, the hand and the plan of God predestined to be done by the Jewish enemies as much as was necessary for the Gospel because of us.
Therefore, it is clearly shown both from the words of the divine book and from the words of Saint Augustine that the predestination mentioned here was not for good for those who committed such great and terrible deeds against the Lord at the time of his passion, but for great and deadly evil; although God turned it into good for us.
If anyone thinks that the blessed Augustine quoted this testimony incorrectly from the book mentioned earlier, because we read: "What your hand and counsel decreed to happen," let them know that he quoted it accurately, as it is in the Greek.
The word itself, proorisen, is also found here in Greek, where it says: "What your hand and counsel predestined to happen."
This same term is also found in the Letter to the Romans in Greek, where the Apostle says: "And those he predestined, he also called" (Romans 8:30).
From this, it is clear that the same Greek term is properly translated into Latin as "predestined."
But it can also be translated as "decreed" or "predefined," so we can understand that predestined means nothing other than decreed and defined.
This is clearly demonstrated in the words of the prophet Isaiah, where he says: "For the Lord God of hosts has decreed" (Isaiah 14:27); and in the book of Daniel: "In the decision of the watchers, the decree is" (Daniel 4:14).
So what good does it do to lie with such intent and contention, saying that the blessed Augustine defined all predestination of grace as preparation?
He never said "all," but defined predestination only in respect to what is good, implying that only the righteous should be called predestined.
He is not found anywhere to have said otherwise, but applied the term only to the predestination of the righteous, by which some are predestined, and others are not.
He insisted less stubbornly and shamelessly, as if that holy doctor always had to speak of both kinds of predestination, both good and bad, together.
It doesn't follow that when he discusses only the predestination of the good, he denies the predestination of the bad.
He clearly mentions and demonstrates this in many places (On the Perfection of Righteousness, chapter 13).
About which
we will place one testimony here as an example, where it says: That Psalm blames a certain people, among whom there was not a single one who did good (Psalm 13:3).
These people wish to remain children of men and not become children of God, by whose grace a person becomes good and is able to do good.
We should understand the good mentioned here to mean what it says there: God looked down from heaven upon the children of men, to see if there were any who understood and sought God (Psalm 14:2).
Therefore, this good, which is seeking God, was not done by anyone, not even one, among those destined for destruction, as God's foreknowledge had passed judgment upon them.
But what use is this example of God's predestination of the wicked, against this one, when he is ready, with his usual madness, to tell his listeners: when they hear in the words of this holy teacher that a kind of people is predestined for destruction, they should understand the opposite, not predestined, and thus they are deceived, who seek truth not in the Scripture of truth, but in the fabricators of lies.
He further adds and says: Punishment is predestined for sinners, but they are only foreknown, not predestined.
We have spoken enough about this matter both here and in the previous chapter, showing clearly with many testimonies that sinners who remain in their sins are justly predestined by God's judgment for punishment.
It is surprising by what sense or reason it can be understood that God has predestined punishments for sinners, and yet has not predestined the sinners for punishments; for when He predestined and prepared those punishments for them, He certainly did not ignore who would be punished and tortured by them.
Even this one admits that they are foreknown.
Therefore, if He most certainly foreknew who would be justly punished and tortured by those punishments, what else did He do when He prepared the most certain punishments for the most certain people, except that He most certainly predestined them for punishments?
For indeed, only those will suffer them, whom He foreknew would suffer them.
So, what does it mean for unchanging foreknowledge to have foreseen punishment, other than to have unchangeably predestined it?
There was no fear that what it most certainly foresaw would justly happen, it would not predestine itself to justly do.
However, the nature of human laws is different.
They set certain punishments for those who sin, without knowing exactly who will sin in such a way that they would justly deserve those punishments.
Therefore, they can prepare and predestine punishments for sinners, which they know to be just.
Yet, they cannot predestine the sinners themselves to those punishments, as they are completely unknown to them.
But if they were to know for certain the individuals who would be worthy of those punishments, they could indeed very justly, just as they set punishments for sinners, predestine those sinners to certain and just punishments.
Just as in the examination of judgment, when they have most certainly proven individuals guilty of a capital crime, they proclaim the death penalty decreed by the laws for them and pronounce a clear sentence condemning them to death.
This certain knowledge of judgment gives them the authority to predestine not only the punishments for sinners but also the sinners themselves to those punishments.
Therefore, if both of these can rightly and justly be done in human judgment, informed and guided by certain knowledge, so that punishments are justly and irreproachably decreed for sinners and sinners for punishments; and yet none of these criminals are compelled to sin by the laws or judges, but only justly punished because they have sinned: how much more incomparably and ineffably must we believe it is done in divine judgment, since eternal knowledge knows both the punishments justly due to sinners and the sinners to whom they are due?
While He is the author or cause of no sin, He most justly predestines both the punishments He knows to be most just for sinners and the sinners, never unknown to Him but eternally well-known, to eternal punishments.
None of us claim, as is often argued, that God's predestination forces anyone to sin.
Rather, we state that for the sins they have committed, they must bear the punishment.
Just as laws, by decreeing punishment, do not compel sin but ensure that voluntary and willing sins are justly punished.
Chapter Fifteen
In the fifteenth chapter, he provides the following definitions.
1. Sins and their punishments are nothing. 2.
God foreknew and predestined sins or punishments; as if He did not foreknow, did not predestine, and did not prepare them: using the example of Judas, who was chosen as if he were not chosen, a friend as if he were not a friend, a son as if he were not a son.
3.
Punishments are evil and therefore not from God, from whom nothing evil comes, and God does not punish what He Himself does, nor take away their natural gifts.
4.
Pain is the absence of health, darkness the absence of light, silence the absence of noise, sadness the absence of joy, labor the absence of rest.
Thus, sins or punishments are foreknown or predestined.
5.
By feeling pain, we do not come to know pain itself, but rather health, which we would not know if we did not have some notion of it.
6.
The memory of health remains in the senses; but health itself resides in that substance which God created.
In these six propositions, the first point he made, that sins and punishments are nothing, has already been discussed above, as much as we could.
For even if sins can be said to be nothing, in that they have no substance in themselves to exist or subsist, still the abandonment of justice, which is to sin, cannot happen except in and through some substance, whether spiritual or physical;
spiritual when truth, justice, and goodness are abandoned in the soul itself, and their opposites, lies, injustice, and malice, enter in.
Although these have no natural substance for subsisting, they are still great vices or illnesses of nature, that is, of the soul itself, which they dominate and whose health and integrity they violate;
so that the soul itself, bent and depressed by these, becomes servile from being free and sick from being healthy, as the Lord says in the Gospel: "Everyone who commits sin is a slave to sin" John 8:34.
And the Psalmist, pleading sorrowfully and miserably: "I said, Lord, have mercy on me, heal my soul, for I have sinned against you" Psalm 41:4.
But because these evils begin in the mind, although they are mostly carried out through the body, the spiritual evil of the mind moves into the physical evil of the body.
Thus, like a plague, it stains and corrupts the whole being, so that the soul, serving the dominant sin, brings its own body into the same servitude.
The members of the body become instruments of unrighteousness to sin, which makes the unrighteousness and sin dominate even more strongly and violently in both.
Hence the Apostle says to the faithful: "Do not offer your members to sin as instruments of unrighteousness, but rather offer yourselves to God as those who have been brought from death to life, and offer the members of your body to God as instruments of righteousness" Romans 6:13.
To this great and deadly illness that claims and wounds the whole person, only the one true doctor can apply a remedy and bring health, who said about himself: "It is not the healthy who need a doctor, but the sick" Matthew 9:12, and about whom it is written: "He will save his people from their sins" Matthew 1:21.
About whom also the Apostle says: "This is a faithful saying and worthy of all acceptance, that Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners" First Timothy 1:15.
Therefore, the one who persistently says and repeats that sins are nothing, what else does he seek to do, instigated by the devil, but to make them seem insignificant in the hearts of listeners, so that they do not grieve, do not recognize how great the evil that holds them is, nor care to say with the Psalmist: "Have mercy on me, O God, according to your great mercy, and according to the multitude of your tender mercies, blot out my transgressions. Wash me thoroughly from my iniquity and cleanse me from my sin. For I acknowledge my transgressions, and my sin is always before me" Psalm 51:1-3.
Let this deceiver be cast out from the ears and hearts of the faithful.
In the face of such great misery, let us sorrowfully and simply implore the great mercy of God.
Against the multitude of so many miseries, let us seek a multitude of mercies, so that iniquity may be erased, the person may be washed from that iniquity, and cleansed from the sin by which they had become filthy and unclean.
Let them recognize their iniquity, not think their sin is nothing, nor put it behind their back, but always keep it before their eyes and implore Him who said:
"I have blotted out your iniquities like a cloud, and your sins like a mist"
(Isaiah 44:22).
Similarly, he tries to diminish, lighten, and nullify the punishments due to sins, always asserting that they are nothing.
Although they have no substance in themselves, through physical natures-eternal fire, the lake of sulfur, and the worms that never die-they are inflicted on the bodies and souls of the damned, tormenting both together.
Therefore, although they are not substantial, they are always penal and miserable in the souls and bodies of those they torture without end.
Therefore, let us not be deceived into thinking that the punishments of sinners are nothing; but rather let us hear what Truth most truly says:
"The rich man also died and was buried in hell. Lifting up his eyes, being in torment, he saw Abraham afar off, and Lazarus in his bosom; and he cried out and said: 'Father Abraham, have mercy on me, and send Lazarus, that he may dip the tip of his finger in water and cool my tongue, for I am tormented in this flame.'"
(Luke 16:22-24).
A little later, when he was pleading for his brothers, he said:
"That he may testify to them, lest they also come into this place of torment"
(Luke 16:28).
Behold the unfortunate and most miserable condemned rich man.
As soon as he died physically, his soul was buried in hell, where it was held in torment.
He was tortured even more in the place where he had sinned the most, which was with his tongue.
He was tormented in the flame that burned and scorched everywhere.
Just as he had not given the crumbs from his table to Lazarus, the poor man full of sores lying at his door, he did not deserve to obtain a drop of water from Lazarus' finger to cool himself a little.
He even begged for his brothers so that they would not come to that place of torment.
Therefore, according to the voice of Truth, hell is a place of torment, and the souls of the wretched, stripped of their bodies, are buried there and are in torment.
They are tortured by the same means by which they sinned, so their judgment is without mercy because they did not show mercy.
As it is written in the book of James, chapter 2, verse 13: "Because judgment without mercy will be shown to anyone who has not been merciful. Mercy triumphs over judgment." Let every faithful person hear this and be afraid, and while there is still time, flee from the coming wrath about which blessed John the Baptist said: "Who warned you to flee from the coming wrath? Produce fruits worthy of repentance." Luke chapter 3, verses 7 to 8. The Lord Himself often calls this place of torment the outer darkness, the furnace of fire, and the eternal fire prepared for the devil and all the wicked, where there will be endless pain, eternal weeping of the eyes, and gnashing of teeth. Book of Matthew, chapter 25, verse 41. Regarding such punishment of the unfortunate condemned, the prophet Isaiah says: "Their worm will not die, and their fire will not be quenched, and they will be loathsome to all mankind." Book of Isaiah, chapter 66, verse 24. Also, blessed Job tearfully implores God, saying: "Are not my few days almost over? Leave me alone, so that I may have a moment of joy, before I go to the place of no return, to the land of gloom and utter darkness, to the land of deepest night, of utter darkness and disorder, where even the light is like darkness." Book of Job, chapter 10, verses 20 to 22.
And blessed John in the Apocalypse says: "They were thrown," he says, "into the lake burning with fire and sulfur, which is the second death, and they will be tormented day and night forever and ever" (Revelation 20:14).
And as he says elsewhere: "The smoke of their torment goes up forever and ever" (Revelation 14:11).
Let us faithfully believe these things, truly fear them, and completely reject this babbler and deceiver from our ears:
For, as the Apostle says, "Bad company corrupts good morals" (First Corinthians 15:33).
Hence another Scripture also advises saying: "Fence your ears with thorns, and do not hear a wicked tongue" (Sirach 28:28).
Immediately after these things, he adds his impious and furious rule, where he tries to persuade us that when we hear something is done, we should understand it as not done; when something is said, we should understand it as not said.
He also claims that God foreknew and predestined sins or punishments as if He did not foreknow, did not predestine, did not prepare them.
This is clearly contrary to faith and truth.
For if God did not foreknow all future sins of angels or humans, He is not all-knowing of the future.
And what else is this but for this foolish person to say in his heart, "There is no God" (Psalms 14:1), if He did not foreknow the punishments justly owed to sinners, how can He threaten them so frequently, so gravely, and so terrifyingly in the Gospels and other Scriptures?
But he says: Since sins or punishments are nothing, because they do not have the substance of existing on their own.
And therefore, God could neither know nor foreknow what is nothing.
As if it were unknown to God whatever does not exist, and what He Himself did not make to exist essentially and naturally:
since with His omnipotent knowledge and foreknowledge, just as He knows all that He made, He also knows what He did not make:
and, as He knows what He would make, so He always knew what He would not make.
So indeed, both what He wanted to exist and what He did not want to exist, He could not at all be ignorant of.
And what He did not want to have the nature or substance of existence, He undoubtedly knew to be a great evil for the subsisting nature of angels or humans, when it is changed for the worse with sin and eternally punished without end.
Now, it's true that God does not predestine sins.
He did not predestine them, except for what He Himself was going to do, which are certainly good and just.
However, it's utterly false to say that He did not predestine punishments, but also prepared them.
As the Lord Himself says in the Gospel: "Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels" (Matthew 25:41).
He adds the example of Judas quite absurdly and incongruously, as shown above.
And immediately he adds, saying: Punishments are evil and therefore not from God, from whom no evil comes.
Against this, God Himself testifies through the prophet, saying: "I am the Lord, making peace and creating evil" (Isaiah 45:7).
And elsewhere it is written: "If there is evil in the city, has not the Lord done it?" (Amos 3:6).
And again: "Good and evil, life and death, poverty and riches, are from God" (Sirach 11:14).
And therefore it must be faithfully discerned that there is one kind of evil, that is, vice, contrary to good, which certainly is not from God, but either invented by the devil or committed by man.
And another kind of evil, which signifies some affliction either temporary or eternal: such as famine, pestilence, hostilities, devastations, death, and those that are called eternal punishments; all of which are indeed from God, because they are prepared or inflicted only by His just arrangement and His just judgment.
But the one who confirms that those eternal punishments are not from God must be compelled to say from whom he thinks they are, whether from the devil, for whom they are prepared; or from humans, who are equally to be punished there; or from no one, so that they exist co-eternally with God without any author.
He continues by saying: God does not punish what He created, nor does He take away their natural gifts.
To consider this more carefully, it is clear that what God made in rational creatures, either angelic or human, exists as spirit in angels without a body, and as soul and body in humans.
The natural gifts that God gave to these rational creatures, which He wants us to understand, are those that He spoke about extensively earlier.
That is, the human or angelic mind naturally possesses memory, intelligence, will, being, knowing, and willing.
It naturally remembers itself, understands itself, loves itself, exists, recognizes itself, and loves itself.
Free will is also considered a natural gift from the Creator, as He has clearly shown in His words above.
Thus, He says that God does not punish what He created; that is, neither the angelic spirit in evil angels, nor the spirit and body in humans who are to be condemned.
And how does He say that the eternal fire is prepared for the devil and his angels, if those angelic spirits are not to be punished by that fire?
How also does He say elsewhere about humans and to humans: "But rather fear Him who can destroy both soul and body in hell" (Matthew 10:28), if neither soul nor body, both created by God, are to be punished by that torment of hell?
But indeed, both spirits and bodies will be punished in hell, as true faith believes, and as Truth itself testifies: not because God created them, but because they did what God did not make, and what God hates and does not allow to go unpunished, that is, sins.
These cannot exist or be punished without their authors: for they do not subsist by themselves to be punished in themselves, but they are within depraved minds, whether angelic or human, committed by them, adhering to them, and to be condemned with them and in them.
Thus, it is also true what Scripture says in praise of God: "For you love all that exists, and hate nothing of what you have made" (Wisdom 11:25).
And what the Lord says: "Who can destroy both soul and body in hell" (Matthew 10:28).
For He loves His creature, as it is in its pure nature, created by Him.
And He hates it insofar as it is corrupted.
Hence it is written: "You hate all who do iniquity, You destroy all who speak falsehood: The Lord abhors the bloodthirsty and deceitful man" Psalm 5:7-8. Therefore the prophet also says about certain people: "They have become as detestable as that which they loved" (Hosea 9:10); and again: "Likewise, both the ungodly and his ungodliness are hateful to God" (Wisdom 14:9).
Thus, He loves everything that exists and hates nothing that He has made; yet, in the rational creature corrupted, depraved, and spoiled, He does not allow these things to go unpunished and disordered.
It is justly ordered and punished in pain the nature that did not want to be blessed under God and from God but desired to be free in itself and by itself: so that what did not want to be subjected willingly, should be subjected unwillingly; and what could have been always blessed there, here becomes endlessly miserable.
Because it is impossible to escape the hand of God, as Scripture itself says, (Tobit 13:2), to whom it is necessary that what did not want to be subjected willingly, be subjected out of necessity.
But what benefit will it be to the rational natures themselves, if in that eternal damnation the natural gifts, as he says, are not taken away?
Since it is clearly understood that they are to be left only to increase the heap of torments, not to any fruit of happiness, so that they remember themselves, to the eternal sorrow of a guilty conscience: they understand themselves to be always miserable, always damned; they love themselves, so that they grieve more for perishing endlessly what they love.
But what kind of free will will there be in those, whose will can neither abandon its own iniquity nor perform any good further?
As Scripture says: "Whatever your hand finds to do, do it with all your might, for in the grave, where you are going, there is neither working nor planning nor knowledge nor wisdom" (Ecclesiastes 9:10).
What benefit will it be to them to always be unhappily, to know their damnation, to wish but not be able to escape their punishment?
All things given here to do good and obtain the Lord's grace, if any trace remains, will serve as punishment, not comfort.
However, if the memory, intellect, and will of a rational creature are directed not towards themselves but towards their Creator, what will these faculties do in those who are completely abandoned by God and separated from that eternal and true light?
What, I ask, will memory do, where no one can say, "I remembered God, and I was delighted"? Psalm seventy-seven verse three, and where what is written will be fulfilled: "For in death there is no remembrance of you" Psalm six verse five. There will be no enlightenment of intellect by which God is known, sought, and found. There will be no devout affection by which God is loved, desired, and enjoyed. For they will be in outer darkness, away from that light, and will not enjoy any of its illumination.
And that dreadful night, about which our true light, the Lord, says: "As long as I am in the world, I am the light of the world. The night is coming, when no one can work" John nine verse five, four. Therefore, as long as He is in the world through His illuminating grace, He is the light of the world, liberating it from its darkness. But when He withdraws this grace of His illumination from those condemned to eternal blindness, what else will remain for them except a dreadful, perpetual night in which no one can work?
If we also consider the bodily senses, which are natural gifts from the Creator, what will sight avail there, where there will be no view of light? Or if there is sight for a moment, it will not be for comfort, but for greater pain: so that they may see something good, which they can no longer have or earn. Just as that rich man, condemned to the same infernal punishments, could see Abraham and Lazarus for a moment Luke sixteen verse twenty-three, but it increased his pain, not provided him any relief. Although this is believed to happen before that final judgment according to the hidden disposition of the Creator, nothing like this is read to happen afterward. What will hearing do there, where a dreadful noise and sad, countless groans will always be heard?
What will happen to our sense of smell when, as God warns through the prophet, "Instead of a sweet smell, there will be a stench"?
(Isaiah 3:24)
And what about taste, when eternal hunger and thirst are upon us?
As it is clearly written about the city of the devil, meaning the entire multitude of the damned, in Revelation: "In one day her plagues will come, death and mourning and famine; for mighty is the Lord God who judges her" (Revelation 18:8).
The Gospel speaks clearly about the condemnation of the rich man, highlighting his eternal thirst and burning tongue.
What about the sense of touch when the whole body experiences no pleasure or sweetness, but faces eternal pain, burning, and torment?
What, then, is the point of saying, as if to console fools, that God does not punish what He has created, nor takes away their natural gifts?
Since He punishes corrupted nature eternally for its wrong acts, and if He allows any natural gifts to remain in that damnation, it will only increase the punishment, not bring comfort.
What does it mean to say: Pain is the absence of health, darkness is the absence of light, silence is the absence of noise, sadness is the absence of joy, and labor is the absence of rest?
Thus, sins and punishments are foreseen or predestined.
If, by these words, he wanted to persuade us that just as we know pain through the absence of health, darkness through the absence of light, silence through the absence of sound, sadness through the absence of joy, and labor through the absence of rest, so God foresees sins or predestines punishments, then what could be more horrible than such a thought?
It equates divine virtue with human weakness.
The power of God, always constant and unchanging, knows everything within itself.
It doesn't need to know anything outside of itself.
It doesn't distinguish between things that happen one way or another, because it perceives everything equally with its eternal and unchanging knowledge.
It sees what it has willed to be and what it hasn't willed to be.
It doesn't recognize sins due to the absence of justice.
Being the highest form of justice, it sees within itself whatever deviates from it.
Similarly, it doesn't recognize punishments due to the absence of blessedness.
As the highest blessedness, it perceives the depth of punishment for those who stray from its tranquility.
Thus, it understands deviations from justice within justice itself, and recognizes punishments within blessedness, seeing the pain and labor of those who separate from its tranquility.
He further explains: By feeling pain, one doesn't truly know the pain but rather knows health, which they wouldn't understand without some notion of it.
This implies that the pain of eternal punishment cannot be fully recognized by the suffering soul, as pain itself lacks substance.
Therefore, since pain is insubstantial, it isn't recognized by the sufferer; instead, health is recognized by comparison.
Health, which is naturally present in the body and contrary to pain, would not be known unless it remained in memory.
To support this idea, he adds: The memory of health remains in the senses, but health itself resides in the substance created by God.
Perhaps he wants to convey that within the sense of eternal suffering, there is always a reminder of health.
Through the senses, whether the body or the soul feels the pain, the memory of health is created from the very experience of pain.
True health in that damnation might be understood because the substance of a human, which God created, is not consumed or destroyed in the perpetuity of both soul and body, but rather lasts eternally in a kind of wholeness of its own.
All these points illustrate that through eternal pain, neither the knowledge of health, nor the memory of it, nor health itself in those who are to be tormented, is lost.
On the contrary, all of these-knowledge and memory of health in a perpetually suffering soul, and the preservation of an indestructible nature-add not to any grace or joy of salvation but rather to the accumulation of pain.
Thus, the damned suffer not only in body and soul, but also, while remembering and recognizing the good health they have utterly lost, they are punished in that very memory and recognition.
Therefore, it is insane to consider there being health in eternal and all-encompassing pain, while what is thought to remain there as a sign of health is nothing but a source of pain.
As the one who is tormented never ends, so do the torments themselves never end.
Chapter Sixteen
In the sixteenth chapter, he proposes twelve definitions, saying:
1. No nature punishes another nature. 2.
The punishments of sins are nothing other than the sins themselves. 3.
In eternal fire, the punishment is nothing other than the absence of blessed happiness.
4.
In it, everyone has an inherent notion of absent happiness and its desire: the miserable will have a notion and knowledge of happiness and truth, and therefore they are not miserable, nor are they punished.
5.
In the devil and wicked men, only the perversity of their own will is punished; neither nature sinned, but the will did.
6.
Nor did the general nature sin in the first man, but the individual will of each person.
7.
If that nature were to sin, since it is one, it would certainly perish completely.
8.
Therefore, in no one is nature punished, because it is from God, and it does not sin, but the voluntary lustful motion is punished.
9.
Thus, in the wicked, the punishments are not endured for what God made, but for what pride has viciously invented.
10.
The lust of a perverse will is tormented, while it is not allowed to have what it wrongly or unworthily desires.
11.
No evil comes from any good.
12.
He who, here, with the free choice of will, which is the gift of natural intelligence, that is, the sharpness of mind, turns it to the uses of disgrace, there, by the most just decree, does not enjoy the dignity of truth at all, and does not avoid the darkness of eternal ignorance.
In these words, when he first stated that no nature punishes another nature, he seems to mean that every nature created by the good author, God, is good inasmuch as it is nature: for example, the nature of the soul or body is good; and the nature of fire, inasmuch as it is nature, is also good.
Therefore, since both are naturally good, he rightly seems to say and define that no nature punishes another nature; because, evidently, two goods, according to his understanding, cannot be contrary to each other, lest one good nature could be a punishment for another good nature.
The clear fallacy of this argument seeks to undermine the firmest truth of faith in the hearts of listeners.
This truth is one that all the faithful undoubtedly believe and confess: that both the nature of evil spirits and the nature of lost humans, including their souls and bodies, will be damned, punished, and tormented without end by His just and eternal judgment:
He who can destroy both soul and body in hell, and who, after killing, has the power to throw into hell (Matthew 10:28).
Our faith is certain not only about these eternal punishments, by which both angels and human nature will be tormented by eternal fire, but also that it is most certain in the common sense of humans that nature is never punished except by nature.
Just as the body can be punished by itself-when it fails from health and succumbs to weakness and disease, diminishing the good of health and suffering the evil of disease-or by the withdrawal of another nature that supports or comforts it.
For instance, when food, drink, light, clothing, or anything of that kind is taken away as a punishment, the body wastes away, fails from hunger and thirst, and is afflicted by darkness or tortured by cold.
Additionally, the human body can be punished by the nature of another thing, such as when robbers' bodies are punished by whips, swords, and multiple torments inflicted upon their bodies by other natures as a punishment.
Given that these scenarios are true and that nature is never punished except by itself, by the withdrawal of another nature's benefit, or by inflicted violence, how then can one say that no nature is punished by nature?
So, as far as it depends on itself, it destroys the truth of eternal punishments.
Both the nature of spirits and bodies are in accordance with the gospel and apostolic truth: the nature of eternal fire will torment day and night forever and ever.
But if he says this because natures do not harm each other except by their qualities-like fire and water, where water is naturally wet, and fire is naturally dry-then fire can be extinguished by water's moisture, and water's moisture can be dried out by fire's dryness.
These things don't oppose each other because of their natures, but because their qualities are contrary to each other.
If he says this, let him know that in our faith, it doesn't matter whether natures are punished by natures or if natures penalize each other by their natural qualities.
Both were created by one Creator, meaning both the nature and the qualities inherent in the nature.
Therefore, both together are rightly called one nature, distinguished from each other by their proper qualities by the wisest Creator.
Furthermore, since the nature of the angelic or human spirit is immortal, by the power of the Creator and just avenger God, it will be bound to that corporeal and eternal fire, both penally and eternally.
Just as here, by the same power of the supreme Creator, the human spirit is bound to the earthly body and cannot be released except by the will and judgment of the one who bound it.
Likewise, the nature of the human body in that eternal fire of the damned will be so penally immortal that it will never be dissolved by death, enduring eternal punishments.
It will be passible and incorruptible, afflicted by every kind of pain, torment, and punishment without end.
For Scripture warns us to avoid this punishment with all intent, saying: Humble your spirit greatly, because the vengeance on the flesh of the impious is fire and worms.
Sirach 7:19
.
And again: For the Lord Almighty will take vengeance on them; on the day of judgment, He will visit them.
He will put fire and worms in their flesh, so they will burn and feel it forever.
Judith 16:20-21.
Someone in ancient times posed a similar question about the conflict of natures.
We find it necessary to briefly insert here how this question was posed and how it was thoroughly refuted by Saint Augustine, for the instruction and confirmation of the readers, especially since the one who posed it was either Pelagius himself or a follower of Pelagius, as is this person.
Therefore, Saint Augustine recalls the same question, saying:
After this, Saint Augustine adds his contrary response, saying:
The holy doctor goes on to convince and destroy the madness of the wicked man.
Since the terror and truth of eternal punishments are so clearly and abundantly recommended by our faith to instill a healthy fear and prompt continuous improvement, how could this person dare to add and say that the punishments of sins are nothing but their sins themselves?
Since our faith most certainly holds that there are other punishments for sins that souls suffer in the present due to their own merits, being deserted by God, deserted from the light of justice, from the contemplation of truth, from the illumination of charity; and sometimes even handed over to a reprobate mind.
For divine Scripture very clearly testifies that these punishments are inflicted on sinners and lovers of carnal pleasures in the present, when it says about certain people: "My spirit will not remain in these men forever, because they are flesh" Genesis 6:3; when the wicked, lamenting and groaning at the end, will say: "The light of righteousness did not shine upon us, and the sun did not rise upon us" Wisdom 5:6; when Scripture says about the same wicked people: "For their own wickedness has blinded them" Wisdom.
And generally about those who hate their brothers:
Everyone who hates his brother is in darkness and walks in darkness and does not know where he is going because the darkness has blinded his eyes.
(First John 2:11).
And about some people, it is written:
Since they did not see fit to acknowledge God, God gave them up to a debased mind to do what ought not to be done.
(Romans 1:28).
The punishments of sinning souls are their own sins because the health of their souls is corrupted and violated, and their conscience becomes miserable, disturbed, and full of anxieties.
Thus, the punishments of sinners are their own sins by the just and terrible judgment of God.
And yet for the same sins, other very severe punishments are immediately inflicted in the present, as shown above.
Moses testifies very clearly about all these present punishments, with which the souls of sinners are continually struck and punished, saying about the almighty God:
Showing mercy to thousands who love Him;
(Deuteronomy 5:10);
and repaying those who hate Him immediately, to destroy them, without delay, repaying them what they deserve.
(Deuteronomy 7:10).
Therefore, even in the present, the gravest punishments of souls are their own sins.
The gravest punishments of souls are the abandonment and damnation by God, which sinners are continually repaid for their merits.
But those punishments of eternal torment remain for the future, about which it is written, the Lord saying:
The rich man also died and was buried in hell.
(Luke 16:22).
And again:
Lest your adversary hand you over to the judge, and the judge to the guard, and you be thrown into prison.
Truly I tell you, you will never get out until you have paid the last penny.
(Matthew 5:25-26).
And in another place, when speaking about the wicked servant who refused to forgive his fellow servant as he had been forgiven, he said:
Then his master, angry, handed him over to the torturers until he would pay his entire debt.
(Matthew 18:34).
These punishments for sinners, whether due to their own sins or because of being abandoned by God, are deserved.
They are inflicted immediately in the present or through various afflictions that are divinely imposed on sinners now.
Additionally, there are eternal punishments that await at the end.
Since Scripture clearly testifies to this and the Church's faith holds it undoubtedly, let those deceived by such fallacies hear what the Apostle warns all the faithful:
"Let no one deceive you with empty words, for because of these things the wrath of God comes upon the sons of disobedience" (Ephesians 5:6).
Blessed Jerome adds to these words of the Apostle, explaining:
This holy doctor, refuting the error of ancient heretics on this matter, overturns the fraudulent lies and fabrications with apostolic truth.
Yet, this man dares to add even greater and more detestable things, saying:
"In eternal fire, there is no other punishment than the absence of blessed happiness."
Rightly, he is asked why both evil angels and wicked humans are to be cast into eternal fire if they will suffer no punishments or torments from that fire? Is it only so that those who now dwell either in the air or on the earth will begin to have a new dwelling in the fire? Consider how it is written about the three holy youths condemned in the Babylonian furnace: the fire had no power over their bodies, their hair was not singed, and the smell of fire did not pass over them. As the Scripture says about them:
"The angel of the Lord went down into the furnace with Azariah and his companions, drove the flame of the fire out of the furnace, and made the middle of the furnace like a moist whistling wind, so that the fire did not touch them at all, nor hurt them, nor cause them any pain" (Daniel 3:49-50).
He contends with astonishing madness to affirm this about others as well.
Imagine if it were possible for an incredible miracle to occur: a vast multitude of fallen angels and lost humans standing amidst immense and raging flames, yet the fire doesn't touch them at all.
The fire would forget its strength, leaving the devil and his angels unharmed.
Who could ever believe such a thing or tolerate the madness of such great impiety?
If there is no punishment in the eternal fire for the damned, then there can't be any glory in the eternal reward for the righteous.
For the same one who promised this glory by saying, "Come, blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world" (Matthew 25:34), also truly threatened that punishment by saying, "Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels" (Matthew 25:41).
He also added with unchanging truth about both: "Then they will go away to eternal punishment, but the righteous to eternal life" (Matthew 25:46).
So, if we seek to understand what that kingdom prepared for the righteous from the foundation of the world is, we should faithfully see it as eternal life.
If we want to understand what to believe about the fire into which wicked humans and angels are cast, we should likewise see it as eternal punishment.
There can be no greater glory than eternal life; nor any greater punishment than eternal suffering: the former for those in the kingdom, the latter for those damned in the eternal fire.
Blessed John clearly testifies about this punishment of eternal fire in Revelation, saying, "They were thrown into the lake of fire and sulfur, and will be tormented day and night forever and ever" (Revelation 20:9-10).
And in another place: "And the smoke of their torment goes up forever and ever" (Revelation 19:3).
Therefore, neither the angels nor the damned humans in eternal fire will ever be at rest or free from punishment.
As the Truth says:
"They will be tormented day and night forever and ever; and the smoke of their torment will rise forever and ever." Revelation 14:11
This punishment even now follows those like the rich man clothed in purple and condemned.
About whom, Scripture says: "They spend their days in prosperity, and in a moment go down to Sheol" Job 21:13.
Just like the rich man, they immediately begin to be in torment, suffer in the flame, and are assigned to the place of eternal torments.
As we have heard, this man often says when someone tries to oppose him with the truth of the faith: "What do you want? Reason defeats you."
So, what is this reason, empty of all reason, alien to all truth, and driven by the spirit of the most impious error, and fanatical?
He wants people to abandon the truth of Christ and follow his fantastic and demonic shadows.
When he said that the condemned in eternal fire feel no other punishment than the absence of blessed happiness, he adds, as if it were a kind of their happiness, "In this (that is, in the absence of blessed happiness) there is no one who does not naturally have within them the concept of the absent happiness and its desire.
"
He also adds that the miserable will have the concept and knowledge of happiness and truth, and thus are not miserable nor punished.
With these words, he clearly tries to affirm that all those who will be in that damnation, which he thinks is nothing other than the absence of the happiness that the saints enjoy, will naturally have an innate understanding and desire for that happiness, of which they will not be partakers.
Repeating and emphasizing this, he says they will have the knowledge and understanding of truth and happiness; and thus, being miserable, they are not miserable, nor punished.
So, through this understanding, those who seek knowledge, awareness, and desire for happiness and truth-without which they would be damned-are not truly miserable, and those punished are not truly punished.
Because being absent from happiness and bliss, they can be called both miserable and damned.
However, having knowledge, awareness, and desire for happiness and truth, which will be absent from them, means they are not truly miserable or damned.
Yet, the faith of the Church understands that the greatest damnation for a rational creature is to be separated from God; to be deprived of His illumination, grace, liberation, and the joy of His vision and contemplation.
Therefore, angels and men damned with such great unhappiness and completely excluded from happiness and truth, even if they felt no external punishment or torment, gain nothing from the knowledge, awareness, and desire for happiness and truth promised to them.
This is because it only leads to greater torment to have some knowledge of truth but never experience its foresight; to desire eternal happiness but never rejoice in its possession.
It is unthinkable to believe they are not the most miserable, completely separated from God, or to say they are not punished when excluded from eternal happiness.
Therefore, they will truly be miserable and eternally damned, always exiled from truth and happiness, without any light of truth or joy of happiness.
In addition to this utmost misery, they will also face endless external punishment, tormented inside by the unhappiness of their conscience and outside by the fire of hell.
The Psalmist briefly shows both of these when he speaks to the Judge of the living and the dead: "May Your hand find all Your enemies; Your right hand will find those who hate You" (Psalms 21:8-9).
You will make them like a fiery furnace in the time of Your presence.
The Lord, in His anger, will disturb them, and fire will devour them.
Psalm twenty-one, verses nine to ten.
Blessed Augustine explains this succinctly:
Given this, we must diligently ask ourselves, according to the rule of true faith, what to think about those who will be punished with eternal damnation.
By understanding the state of those eternally damned, we grasp how much the Lord deems it worthy to grant.
We learn why there can be no correction or liberation from there.
Therefore, the Catholic faith firmly holds that no person, upon departing from the body through death, can gain any merit to abandon the wickedness in which they died or be changed for the better.
Even if some, as the piety of the faith knows, receive forgiveness of sins after death through the prayers, offerings, and alms of the Church, and are cleansed by certain purgatorial punishments, deserving to be associated with eternal happiness, this does not grant them any new merit after death.
Instead, it is merit they acquired before death.
Indeed, their life's merit in the body is such that they deserve to be helped by these remedies even after death.
The Apostle clearly states:
For we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ, so that each one may receive what is due for what he has done in the body, whether good or evil.
Second Corinthians, chapter five, verse ten.
Indeed, the deeds of the body, whether good or evil, are what the soul did while it was in the body.
Just as the soul could not do any good or evil before the body existed, neither can it do any good or evil after the body is laid down, for the time for doing and acting ended with the death of the body.
Even those bound only by the guilt of original sin and leave the body without a saving remedy are damned due to their own bodily evils.
They contracted that original debt in the body and with the body, which leads to their eternal damnation.
Therefore, everything must be revealed, as the Apostle says, before the judgment seat of Christ, so each may receive according to what they have done in the body.
Second Corinthians 5:10, explains that it's about what they did or contracted in the body.
Indeed, they could neither do anything before having a body nor can they do anything after leaving the body.
There's no longer time for action, only for receiving according to their deeds.
Our faith must be certain that none of those to be punished with eternal damnation on the day of judgment carried any merit from this life that could free them from eternal destruction.
If any had prepared such merit in this life, they would not be handed over to eternal damnation by the just judge.
Whoever is to be punished with that damnation, without a doubt, carried such merit from here, ensuring by just judgment that they will never be absolved or freed.
To ensure that such damnation is both just and eternal, the reason is that there will be no further opportunity to correct the past, and no merit for future improvement.
There will be repentance for past evils and a desire for liberation and deliverance, but it will have no effect.
Where then is the mercy of God, who will neither be moved to forgive by such great and long repentance nor by the desires of the damned, or even by the groans of those asking for release?
How can He be just if He disregards these things?
How can He not look upon such pain of conscience and the affliction of His creature?
What, I ask, will be the reason that nothing healthy or acceptable can be done there?
If it could, it would never be rejected by such great mercy and justice.
Why is it not possible?
It's because, with God completely withdrawn from them, they lack the special grace through which the virtues of faith, hope, and charity are granted.
Without this grace, they cannot repent of the past with true piety or desire the future with genuine piety.
This means they cannot believe, hope, or love piously.
As mentioned, they are fundamentally separated from God and are preserved for eternal punishment solely by His omnipotent power.
Thus, they will never be able to partake in the Holy Spirit.
Even if they have some form of faith-whether from memories of things they heard or learned here, or from the terror and manifestation of present things-they cannot truly connect with the Holy Spirit.
This includes the revealed power and authority of God and Christ that will be evident to all.
It will be seen in the majesty of His judgment, the eternal reward of the righteous, and the eternal damnation of the wicked.
These truths will be undeniable, and while they will be known and acknowledged by all, they will only be worshipped out of sheer terror.
At that time, all creation will be perfectly subject to the Creator-either out of piety, as in holy angels and holy humans, or out of necessity, as in evil angels and impious humans.
This will fulfill what the Apostle recalls from the prophet: "As I live, says the Lord God, every knee will bow to me, and every tongue will confess to God" (Romans 14:11).
In the same judgment, it will become clear what Scripture predicted about the wicked: "They will say among themselves, repenting and grieving with anguish of spirit: These are the ones we once held in derision and as a likeness of reproach.
We fools considered their lives madness, and their end without honor; how then are they counted among the children of God, and their lot is among the saints? Therefore, we strayed from the path of truth, and the light of righteousness did not shine for us, and the sun did not rise for us" (Wisdom 5:3-6).
They will say these and other sorrowful things on that day.
So, if from such immense divine power and the manifestation of Christ the Lord, combined with the fear of such a profound and evident eternal judge, there is any faith-whether from those who once believed or even from unbelievers compelled by such present majesty and terror-
then, in their lamentation, as we have already mentioned, they say:
"We have strayed from the path of truth, and the light of justice did not shine for us, and the sun did not rise for us"
(Wisdom of Solomon 5:6).
Yet, such faith in those who, as often said, are utterly abandoned by God and illuminated by none of His grace, will certainly not come from pious love but from the necessity of terror:
as the blessed Apostle James testifies is in demons, saying:
"Even the demons believe-and shudder"
(James 2:19).
Such faith, therefore, will not avail them for salvation but for confusion, as it is written in the psalm:
"Let them be ashamed and terrified forever; let them be disgraced and perish"
(Psalm 83:17).
There will be no hope left for them, condemned by the eternal sentence and completely despairing of their deliverance:
likewise, no love by which they might piously love God and their neighbor according to God, or in God, or for God, will be in them, since God Himself, who is love, will have abandoned them.
The grace of the Spirit, of which the Apostle says:
"God's love has been poured into our hearts through the Holy Spirit who has been given to us"
(Romans 5:5), will not be present with them, and the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, the love of God, and the fellowship of the Holy Spirit will have departed from them.
For even if that rich man, already condemned in hell, seemed to love his brothers, whom he had left in the flesh, according to God, for whom he was anxiously striving and pleading that they might not come to that place of torment
(Luke 16:27), it was not truly according to God, since it was extorted from him not by divine love but either by the terror of present damnation or by human affection.
Without faith and charity, and lacking the hope that comes from God's illumination and the Holy Spirit's gift, there will be no true repentance for past actions, nor any desire for a better future.
This is because their actions won't stem from genuine piety and love for divine grace, but from the necessity brought by tribulation and distress.
Thus, with the light of divine illumination completely withdrawn, and excluded from the promised joy to the faithful servant, as the Lord says: "Enter into the joy of your Lord" (Matthew 25:21), they will remain alienated from God's light.
They will be sent into outer darkness, into that terrible night about which the Lord says: "Night is coming, when no one can work" (John 9:4).
And in another place, He mercifully warns: "Walk while you have the light, lest darkness overtake you" (John 12:35).
In such darkness and night, they will no longer be able to do anything pious and fruitful that the just judge can accept, nor can they earn anything to escape eternal damnation.
Without pious repentance, there will be no forgiveness of sin; consequently, the punishment will never end.
Any memory of truth or happiness they have will be barely grasped by human sense, not as usually inspired by God's grace.
Then, indeed, the terrifying Scripture will be fulfilled: "Only distress will give understanding to the hearing" (Isaiah 28:19); and "Because neither work, nor reason, nor wisdom, nor knowledge will be in the grave, where you are heading" (Ecclesiastes 9:10).
There will be no good work to earn merit, no reason to justly excuse or satisfy, no wisdom from the illumination of truth, no knowledge from the exercise of any virtue.
How then will they have knowledge and awareness of the truth, from which they will be eternally deprived of both illumination and contemplation?
How can they desire the same truth and happiness without the love of piety, which allows the truth to be truly loved and true happiness to be truly desired?
They might have some knowledge of the truth because they recognize themselves as deserving of such punishments, condemned by a just judgment, never to be freed from eternal judgment.
But all this serves them only as torment, not for the comfort of consolation.
Thus, they may desire a certain happiness, to be delivered from those torments, and to be refreshed by some peace or rest.
However, knowing and desiring the very truth of God, the very happiness of God, is a gift for the pious and those illuminated by God's spirit, not for the impious condemned by perpetual blindness and unhappiness.
Even if there were some who once believed and knew, and somewhat remembered the truth or happiness, it would only cause them more grief, more repentance, and a just recognition of their condemnation.
Indeed, they may desire time to amend their ways to escape punishment, but without the piety needed to merit God's favor.
Therefore, let those who are not illuminated by God and are alienated from the life of God stop claiming they are not miserable or damned by any sweetness of truth and happiness.
True and eternal misery is to be alienated from a blessed life.
No greater damnation exists than to be utterly excluded and repelled from God, with no hope or recourse to God anymore.
Hence, let every faithful person consider how vain and insane it is to claim that those who can never be blessed by God can be blessed by themselves, not by any grace of God, but by some supposed goods of nature.
Even if Almighty God leaves them in that state, it will be a testament to His goodness and a witness to their just condemnation.
This will help them realize the fairness of the judgment carried out on them and thus be condemned by their own judgment.
This unspeakably horrible damnation of the wicked and impious, without any consolation of divine mercy or illumination of truth, is briefly emphasized by Blessed Augustine, who warns us to avoid it at all costs, saying:
Moreover, when he explained the words of the psalm where it is said, "In hell, who will give you praise?" (Psalm 6:6), he acknowledged that in hell, the rich man, of whom the Lord says that he saw Lazarus at rest while he himself was in torment (Luke 16:23), confessed so much that he even wanted to warn his family to refrain from sins because of the punishments they do not believe exist in hell.
Even though his confession was in vain, those torments happened to him justly, since he also desired to teach his family to avoid falling into them.
What then does it mean: "In hell, who will give you praise?" (Psalm 6:6).
Does it mean that in hell, where the wicked will be thrown after judgment, they will see no light of God to confess anything to Him, due to the deeper darkness?
For this man, while still lifting his eyes, although through a huge chasm, could still see Lazarus at rest, from whose comparison he was compelled to acknowledge his own situation.
In these words of the holy doctor, it is perhaps not necessary to understand two hells, one where the souls of the damned are now cast down, and another where those same souls will be thrown after judgment along with their bodies.
But one and the same hell can be understood, now sometimes milder in the torments of souls; after judgment, however, more atrocious and horrible in the torments of both souls and bodies.
For our Lord seems to refer to both punishments of hell-the present age and the future-under the single name of Gehenna in the Gospels.
He speaks of the present punishment when He says:
"Fear him who, after he has killed, has the power to cast into Gehenna" Luke 12:5.
And of the future punishment when He says:
"But rather, fear him who can destroy both soul and body in Gehenna" Matthew 10:28.
The holy Fathers of the Church frequently understood the same eternal fire to be inflicted upon the wicked both before and after judgment. But the aforementioned doctor signifies such a great difference between the two punishments that now, through certain visions and divinely arranged manifestations, the light of God can somewhat be felt there, by which the damned are at least driven to confess their crimes.
When they see some of the divine light, they have, from the respect of this granted vision, someone to whom they can confess. However, then, oppressed by greater and irreparable darkness, they will not deserve to see anything like that, by which they could be driven to any confession, so that it can be truly understood about them:
"For in death there is no remembrance of you; in hell who will confess to you?" Psalm 6:5.
Hence, the prophet Isaiah, foreseeing this irreparable damnation and warning most attentively that it should be foreseen and avoided, where there will be no place to find God, no grace to call upon Him:
"Seek the Lord while He may be found, call upon Him while He is near" Isaiah 55:6.
He clearly shows that He cannot be found in that damnation anymore, nor can He be appeased by any invocation or supplication from the wretched damned, as if He were far off and completely alienated from them.
This one also adds and says: In the devil and wicked men, only the perversity of their own will is punished, not the nature, but the will that has sinned. Behold again something new and unheard of.
This person argues that in the devil and wicked people condemned to eternal destruction, it is not their nature that God punishes, but their perverse will.
According to this person, it is not their nature that sins, but their will.
However, the faith of the Church firmly holds that rational nature, whether in angels or humans, has both natural reason and a natural will inherent from God.
Nature, with its reason and will, is one entity.
This rational nature cannot exist without will, nor will without nature.
Therefore, whatever this nature wills, it is inseparable from its nature.
When this nature wills something, it does so entirely, not partially.
So, whether it is moved to do good, it acts with its entire will.
Conversely, if moved to do evil, it acts with its entire will as well.
Therefore, whether moved to good or evil, it is moved entirely.
When it is moved to good, it is virtue.
When it is moved to evil, it is vice.
Thus, by virtue, the whole nature becomes better when moved to good; by vice, the whole nature becomes worse when moved to evil.
It is not only the will that is improved by virtue, but the whole nature.
Nor is it only the will that is worsened by vice, but the whole nature.
By virtue, not only the will, but the whole nature becomes good.
Conversely, by vice, not only the will, but the whole nature becomes bad, not by losing the goodness of its substance, but by being corrupted and depraved by the vice of its will.
When this nature acts rightly, it acts entirely because it wills it entirely.
Similarly, when it acts wrongly, it acts entirely because it wills it entirely.
Therefore, it is just before God that the whole nature is glorified for good deeds, and conversely, the whole nature is condemned for evil deeds.
For if in wicked angels and wicked people it is not the nature that sins, but the will.
Therefore, in both holy angels and pious humans, it is not their nature that has done anything right or earned any good, but only their will.
And if, in the case of evil angels and wicked humans, it is not the whole nature but only the will that will be condemned, then likewise, in the case of holy angels and humans, it is not the whole nature but only the will that will be glorified.
But it is absolutely certain, and faith holds without doubt, that the entire nature of the holy angels is already blessed and glorified; similarly, the entire nature of holy humans will be blessed and glorified.
Therefore, conversely, it must be held without any doubt that in evil angels and wicked humans, it is not only their will but their entire nature that will be condemned, because the whole nature has sinned.
However, this person, against all faith and the truth of God, introduced such an argument to claim that angels and wicked humans are to be condemned only in their will so that his insane deception may have a place.
He says, as he already stated above, that in the eternal fire there will be no other punishment except the absence of blessedness.
Thus, according to this person's view, there will be no punishment inflicted externally on angelic or human nature because it did not sin; only the will will be punished internally in the conscience.
He asserts that only the will sinned, and it will be punished not by any torment of external punishment, but only by the absence of blessedness and the prohibition of its depraved desire, which it will not be allowed to fulfill.
All these ideas are contrary to faith and truth.
They favor the will of the devil by flattering humans so that they neither truly recognize that they have sinned, since their nature is defended as not having sinned, nor truly recognize that they are to be punished, since it is claimed that not their nature but only their will is to be condemned.
This is evident to all who care for their own salvation, who reject heretical fabrications and delusions far from themselves, and who faithfully follow the evangelical and apostolic truth.
To ensure that those who read our argument against this insane and impious definition are more reliably and firmly informed, we include the words of the blessed Augustine, who teaches about this matter very clearly and thoroughly, saying:
Shortly after, he says: We must be careful not to fall into that prophetic judgment where it is written: Woe to those who call what is good, evil, and what is evil, good; who put darkness for light, and light for darkness; who put bitter for sweet, and sweet for bitter (Isaiah 5:20).
And yet the Lord says: An evil man brings evil things out of the evil treasure of his heart (Matthew 12:35).
But what is an evil man, if not an evil nature, since man is by nature?
Furthermore, if man is something good because he is by nature, what is an evil man, if not a bad good?
However, when we distinguish these two things, we find that a man is not evil because he is a man, nor is he good because he is wicked.
Rather, he is good because he is a man, and evil because he is wicked.
Therefore, whoever says it is bad to be a man or good to be wicked, falls into that prophetic judgment: Woe to those who call what is good, evil, and what is evil, good (Isaiah 5:20).
For such a person criticizes God's work, which is man, and praises man's fault, which is wickedness.
So every nature, even if it is flawed, is good as far as it is nature; as far as it is flawed, it is evil.
Behold, the venerable doctor does not say only the corrupted or flawed will of man is evil, but the flawed nature of man is evil: and he confirms that what is evil is nature; and he says that an evil man is an evil nature.
Thus, he says: He did not say that an evil man is only an evil will, but an evil nature.
Clearly, because when a man is evil, he is evil not only by will but by his whole nature.
Yet he faithfully teaches that we must distinguish, when we say an evil man, between God's work and the fault of the man himself; because evidently, to be a man is God's work, to be wicked is man's fault.
And thus nature, even if it is flawed, is good as far as it is nature; as far as it is flawed, it is evil.
In all these matters, he asserts that not only the will, but the very nature itself is good, insofar as it is nature; however, he also says that the very nature itself is bad, insofar as it is flawed.
This must be faithfully followed, understood in a Catholic manner, and firmly held, so that we know for certain that neither the will of the evil angel nor that of the evil man alone is bad when they sin; rather, their whole nature is bad and will suffer eternal punishment when they are damned.
He further adds: Neither did the general nature sin in the first man, but the individual will of each person.
If that nature had sinned, since it is one, the whole of it would certainly perish.
With these words, he tries to assert clearly that in other men, nature does not sin, only the will does; similarly, in the first man, nature did not sin, only the will.
Therefore, the nature of the human race in general did not sin in him because his nature did not sin; only the specific and individual will of each person sinned in him, meaning he sinned by will alone.
He asserts that if the whole nature of man had sinned, the whole would have perished.
But now, because only the will sinned, only the will is corrupted; nature remains unharmed.
What then shall we say to these elaborate and unheard-of fantasies?
Except that we oppose them with the testimonies of the Scriptures of God, by which we truly understand and faithfully hold that the whole nature in that man sinned, the whole perished, and the whole was transmitted to his descendants subject to sin and perdition:
As the Apostle clearly teaches, saying: "Through one man sin entered into the world, and through sin, death, and so death passed upon all men, in whom all have sinned" (Romans 5:12).
He does not say: "Through the will of one man sin entered into the world," but "through one man"; nor does he say: "and so it passed into the wills of all," but "so it passed into all men"; nor does he add: "in whom the wills of all sinned," but "in whom all have sinned."
Through one man, sin entered the world, affecting the entire nature of humanity.
Just as it was completely corrupted by sin in that man, it passed into all humans, completely corrupted by sin, so that from that origin, the entire sinful nature of all humans was derived; because in that one sinning man, the whole nature of all sinned.
Hence, as the Apostle says, all became, not by will, but by nature, children of wrath.
For he says:
"We were by nature children of wrath, like the rest" Ephesians 2:3.
Truly, all who are born from that corrupted root become by nature children of wrath, not as that nature was created by God, but as it was made through sinning.
From this perspective, the Psalmist says:
"Behold, I was conceived in iniquities, and in sins did my mother conceive me" Psalm 51:5.
Behold, a sinful nature conceived in iniquities, born in sins. This nature, entirely lost in Adam and passed on lost to his descendants, our Lord Jesus Christ came to seek and save-not partially, that is, only in will, but completely.
As he says:
"For the Son of Man came to seek and to save what was lost" Luke 19:10.
And because it was entirely lost, he came to save it entirely.
Therefore, he took on the whole of it, both the soul and the body of man, so that he might save it completely through his death and resurrection: justifying the soul from sins, and raising the body from the dead.
As the Apostle says:
"He was delivered up for our trespasses and raised for our justification" Romans 4:25.
Therefore, whoever says that human nature was not entirely lost strives to nullify, as much as they can, the sacrament of the divine incarnation. For the Lord would have taken on the whole of it in vain through his incarnation, if the whole did not need salvation, if the whole did not need a savior.
It's amazing how he says that in the first man, each of our own wills committed sins that did not yet exist at all; and that the nature of all of us did not sin, which was indeed in him.
But he argues: if the entire nature of that man had sinned, the entire nature would indeed perish.
Therefore, according to his reasoning, if only the will in him sinned, then only the will perished; and if it perished, then it certainly needs to be liberated, saved, and reformed, so that it can be healthy and free through Him who says: "If the Son sets you free, you will be truly free" (John 8:36).
And how does he defend free will from the virtue of nature, and not from the gift of grace, in this entire, very vain dispute of his?
And if, according to him, only the will perished and the nature remained safe, then the Truth, God forbid, did not speak the truth when He said about Himself: "He made the whole man well on the Sabbath" (John 7:27).
He adds and says: Therefore, nature is punished in no way because it is from God and does not sin, but the voluntary lustful movement is punished.
And so, in the wicked, the punishments are not endured for what God made, but for what pride found wickedly.
The lust of a perverse will is tormented when it is not allowed to have what it wrongly or unworthily desires.
Therefore, what he says: Nature is not punished in any way because it is from God and does not sin, is doubly contrary to faith and truth.
Because both angelic and human nature, as shown above in many ways, is punished by the just judgment of God and eternal damnation.
Since evil cannot and should not go unpunished, it must be punished where it is found and by whom it is perpetrated, that is, in the very natures in which sins are committed and which are corrupted and depraved by sinning; and therefore, they are justly condemned for these.
And the angelic or human nature itself, although it is from God not by generation but by creation, not by birth but by origin, can indeed sin and does sin.
Both aspects are affirmed by the Catholic faith because it knows both to be true: nature is truly punished because of sin, and conversely, this person denies both, claiming neither that nature is punished nor that nature sins.
According to his assertion, no nature created by God is found that does not sin, just as the one nature begotten by God alone does not sin.
However, true faith firmly holds that every rational nature, both angelic and human, has the potential to sin.
This is evident in the rebellious angels and in humans who fell by transgressing the commandment.
But the same nature in the elect angels does not sin due to divine grace and goodness, making them good by nature and sustained by grace.
Only that nature, which is from God in such a way that it is what God is, cannot sin.
It is not created from nothing but begotten or proceeding from Him, which is undoubtedly the only begotten Son of God and the Holy Spirit.
Hence, this person who says no other nature does not sin attempts to equate the creature with the Creator, which is a clear blasphemy.
What else remains for him but to claim that the angelic or human spirit is of the same nature as God, as the impious ancient heretics did?
While they introduced two natures separately opposed to each other, one good which cannot be evil and the other evil which cannot be good, this person, in a new and unheard-of type of error, says in the same angelic or human spirit that nature does not sin, meaning it cannot be evil; and that the will sins, meaning it can be evil.
Therefore, when he said that nature neither sins nor is punished, to confirm that only the human will sins, he immediately added: but the voluntary lustful impulse is punished.
Repeating and emphasizing this, he added: In the wicked, punishment is not endured for what God has made, but for what pride has wickedly invented.
With these words, as mentioned earlier, he confirms that the nature of angels or wicked humans will never suffer punishment.
Rather, what a proud will has wrongfully committed should be punished in the will itself.
And as if we were to ask him what the future punishment of this corrupt will would be, he added, as if explaining: The desire of a perverse will is tormented when it is not allowed to have what it wrongly or undeservedly desires.
Behold, this is the kind of torment he predicts for the wicked will in angels and wicked humans.
That is, not eternal fire or any external punishment, but the torment of being oppressed and restrained from fulfilling their wrongful desires.
Thus, it is established that not only will the nature of wicked angels or humans never sin and never be punished, but also the will itself, which sins in them, will feel no punishment or suffering, except what all wicked people suffer in this life when they are not permitted to fulfill their wrongful desires, either due to divine judgment or some other necessity compelling them.
From this, it is clear that every punishment, every torment, every suffering of future damnation, which Almighty God so frequently and so terribly threatens, he utterly denies.
Therefore, as something contrary to our faith and an enemy of the truth, it should be repelled far from the ears and hearts of the faithful.
To these great and important matters, he adds a very brief definition and says: Evil comes from no good.
To understand this vigilantly, it must first be considered that something good can become evil.
Just as the nature of angels or humans is certainly good in its own way and in its own kind, this good nature can become evil through vice.
Therefore, insofar as it is nature, it remains good, and insofar as it is corrupted, it begins to be evil.
Thus, it is not doubted that good can become evil, but for this to happen, that is, for good to begin to be evil, there is no preceding cause from which this could consequently occur.
For example, if we ask what makes something in nature good, we find that the highest good is God, and all good comes from this highest good.
If we ask why someone is wise and just, we similarly find that the highest wisdom and the highest justice is God.
Therefore, He is the highest and most certain cause of why anyone who is truly wise is wise, and why anyone who is truly just is just.
So, for someone to be good, wise, and just, the preceding and efficient cause is the highest wisdom and highest justice itself.
But can we say in the same way, if asked why evil begins in something good, that there is a highest evil beyond all angelic or human nature, and that from this highest evil comes everything evil in these creatures, such that a bad angel and a bad man have a preceding and efficient cause of their wickedness, by which they become evil from good?
Even an angel, like a man, was indeed good and began to be evil.
So where did he get the preceding cause that made him evil?
Could a good God be the cause by which an angel became evil?
Absolutely not, because the supremely good could not be the cause of evil.
Similarly, it is absurd to say there is a highest evil, and that it is the preceding cause by which a good angel became evil.
If we say this, we clearly introduce two principles contrary to the truth of faith: that just as there is a principle of good, there is also a principle of evil.
But this is absurd because there is no nature of evil at all, nor does it exist substantially, so that it could be the principle of anything.
Rather, evil is called a deficiency of good, just as darkness is a deficiency of light, and illness is a deficiency of health.
Therefore, this deficiency of good, which is called evil, how did it come to be in the devil, who was the first to sin?
It did not come from God, because God is not the author of evil; it did not come from any substance of evil, because there is no substance of evil.
If someone says that this change from good to evil was done by his own will, we must ask whether that will was good or evil.
If it was good, how could a good will cause an evil will?
But if an evil will caused this change, who created that evil will?
Since it's impossible to find an answer, we must admit that there was no preceding cause that created the evil will by which a good angel became evil.
Instead, the cause is a deficiency because a deficiency of good is called evil.
Similarly, in a sinning human, just as a good person became evil, neither God's will nor the nature of evil-which clearly does not exist-could be the cause.
Nor could the person's own good will be the cause of evil, nor could his evil will have a creator.
If it is said that the devil's evil will made the human's will evil, just as he could have given in to the evil suggestion, he could have also resisted.
Since both options were in his power, no one pushed him, no one forced him, and no one could prevail by persuasion, except because he fell by his own voluntary deficiency and became evil from good.
This also applies to other people; hence, it is clear that the good itself, that is, the good nature, is from God.
However, when this good nature is corrupted by vice and becomes evil, it comes from nothing, because it has no efficient cause but a deficient one.
Therefore, this whole matter is rightly understood and said about rational angelic or human nature, so that in them, it is understood that the good nature itself becomes or is evil from no creator.
As frequently said, the evil in rational creatures neither comes from God nor from any evil creator but started from their own deficiency from good.
This person claims that neither angelic nor human nature commits sin, but only the will of that nature.
It seems they've made this distinction to show that the will's goodness can turn evil while defending the nature itself as free from evil.
Since the nature couldn't be the author of evil to its own will, which changed from good to evil, it suggests that for good to become evil, it comes from nothing.
Evil doesn't have an efficient cause from any author; rather, it is a deficiency of good.
This implies that evil originates from no good, because the good of angelic or human will, when turning evil, wasn't produced by their nature, thus it remains blameless.
Essentially, for the good of its will to become evil, it was made from nothing, not from itself.
However, he misinterpreted this argument from the words of Saint Augustine in "The City of God."
What Augustine argued for the edification of faith and against heretics, especially the Manichaeans, this person has twisted against the faith itself.
In everything, he uses Augustine's subtle arguments meant to confirm piety and repurposes them to support his error.
He also states that one who, with the free will of choice-a gift of natural intelligence-turns it to disgrace, justly loses the honor of truth and cannot avoid the darkness of eternal ignorance.
Here, he is not talking about angelic or human nature itself, nor its will, but rather its intelligence.
In the rational mind, three things are considered: being, knowing, and willing.
And now, it seems we have sufficiently discussed two things: being and willing, both in their own natures.
Now let us also consider knowing, that is, intelligence itself.
With nature preserved and free from all punishments, according to his understanding, not only the will of this nature but also the intelligence in future damnation is understood to be punished, not with any external torment, but only with an inner loss.
He explains that whoever, by free will, has misused the gift of natural intelligence-which should have been used for seeking, finding, and contemplating the truth-by focusing on vain, useless, or harmful things, will face punishment in future damnation.
The free will of man, which has misused intelligence here, will be punished by not enjoying the light of truth.
It will justly lose the good of intelligence and fall into the darkness of eternal ignorance.
If this is the case, it is indeed a great punishment for human will: that which has misused intelligence in this life, in future damnation, will lose the good of intelligence, will not enjoy any light of truth, and will be condemned to eternal ignorance.
This punishment of the perverse human will, losing the light of intelligence, will be so severe that it justly seems to be lost, and in its place, the darkness of eternal ignorance will prevail.
This punishment of the human mind in future damnation is not rejected by us, because, as we read in the Gospel of Matthew.
.
When the useless servant is condemned for not using the single talent of intelligence he received effectively, and by using it, doubling it:
but instead, tied it in a napkin or hid it in the ground, meaning he lived delicately and immersed himself in earthly cares, rendering it unfruitful:
when, I say, that useless servant is condemned, as the Gospel truth reveals.
First, it will be said: Take the talent away from him (Matthew 25:28);
and then it will be added: And throw the useless servant into outer darkness: there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth (Matthew 25:30).
Hence, no punishment should be feared by a faithful person more than this: being stripped of the light of God's intelligence and thrown into outer darkness, where for those damned with eternal blindness, there will be no illumination or contemplation of truth.
Since these things are so, how could he promise the knowledge and wisdom of that same happiness and truth to those who are to face such severe damnation of eternal blindness, always suffering the absence of truth and happiness?
Because of this knowledge, he asserted that the miserable would not be miserable and the damned would not be damned;
therefore, let him hold on to what he said truthfully here, and discard what he placed there unnecessarily and vainly.
Chapter Seventeen
In the seventeenth chapter, he provides seven definitions in this way:
1. God is not the author, maker, or predestinator of punishments. 2.
God's predestination is only for things that are good, but His foreknowledge applies to both good and bad.
This difference is not by nature, but by the use of language.
3.
Just as it is said that God is present everywhere by the power of His presence, but not everywhere by the grace of His dwelling, it can be said that He is everywhere by foreknowledge, but not everywhere by predestination.
As the truth clearly proclaims about God: wherever God is by presence, He will certainly be by dwelling; similarly, wherever He is by foreknowledge, He will necessarily be by predestination.
4.
And, just as God's presence and dwelling are only in those things which are made by Him, so His foreknowledge and predestination are only of those things which He would make.
Just as His presence and dwelling are not in those things which are neither made by Him nor created by Him, so His foreknowledge and predestination are not in those things which He neither made nor gave, because they are nothing.
5.
The eternal fire was made to burn the devil and his angels, not humans.
After he was cast down from the ether, where in his ethereal body he could not feel punishment, an aerial body was added to him, in which he would feel the fire.
6.
That fire is not a punishment, nor was it prepared or predestined for this purpose.
But it was predestined to exist in the universe of all good things.
It was made the seat of the impious, where without a doubt both the blessed and the wretched will dwell.
7.
There is no misery except eternal death; eternal death is the ignorance of truth.
And there is no misery except the ignorance of truth.
Where the truth is unknown, there is no life.
Therefore, what he first stated, that God is not the author, maker, or predestinator of punishments, is clearly against the faith, as we have frequently shown above.
For those punished with eternal damnation-whether the devil, his angels, or wicked people-it's not unjust.
Each one is tormented according to their own deeds and the extent of their wickedness.
This fulfills what is written in the psalm about the just and eternal judge: "He will repay each one according to their deeds" (Psalm 62:12).
The fire of hell is one, but it torments each person differently, just as the sun's heat is one but is felt differently by each person depending on their constitution.
The punishments never end because it is just in God's sight that those who never wanted to end their sins should never have an end to their torments.
Those who did not want to submit to God in piety will be subjected to Him out of necessity, ensuring no creature remains contrary to its Creator.
Those who rejected the truth and believed in iniquity will be coerced by iniquity and unable to deny the clear truth of divine judgment, divine majesty, and the power of God and His Christ.
Even the wicked, who have always been strangers to the worship of God, will be forced to confess the truth.
They will lament and repent too late, saying: "So we have strayed from the way of truth, and the light of righteousness did not shine on us, and the sun did not rise upon us" (Wisdom 5:6).
Thus, when God threatens dreadful and eternal punishments through His prophets, He often adds at the end of His threats: "And they shall know that I am the Lord" (Exodus 29:46).
This means they will admit, out of necessity and to their shame, what they never wanted to acknowledge out of piety and devotion for their salvation.
Even the devil, the author and instigator of all wickedness, along with his unclean and damned angels, will come to the end of his tyranny, which he has continuously exercised against God and the salvation of the human race from the beginning.
As it is written: "He will be thrown down before the eyes of all" (Job 40:28).
Because of all these things, and other secrets known only to God, the holy Scriptures also refer to hell as useful.
Just as the punishment by human laws serves to maintain peace by deterring the guilty, hell has a similar purpose.
For the Scripture says, when speaking of a bad tongue: "And hell is more useful than it" (Ecclesiasticus 28:25).
Since the eternal punishments of angels and damned humans are so just and orderly, why shouldn't God be the author of them?
Not that He causes such evils, but He is the just organizer and judge of these torments.
How is He not the author of these punishments, considering it is clearly stated in the Gospel: "Who can destroy both soul and body in hell" (Luke 12:5); and: "Who, after He has killed, has the power to cast into hell" (Matthew 10:28); and who will say in the judgment itself: "Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire" (Matthew 25:41).
If those punishments and the place of torments exist somewhere in creation, who else could be their maker but God?
Scripture clearly states: "He who lives forever created all things at once" (Ecclesiasticus 18:1).
Indeed, that eternal fire is a created thing and is not co-eternal with God; it was created for just and proper uses.
Anyone who claims that this or any other creation is not from God, the sole author of all, but from some other unknown source, is clearly engaging in heretical impiety, whether of the Manichaeans or other wicked heretics.
Therefore, since that eternal fire is truly a part of creation, it undoubtedly has the same author as all other creatures; about whom it is also written: "For in six days the Lord made the heavens, the earth, the sea, and all that is in them, and rested on the seventh day" (Exodus 20:11).
Let this person say where he thinks hell is located, the place of eternal torment-whether in the sky, on the earth, in the sea, or among other things in them.
Wherever he thinks it is, it must have been made by Him.
He who made the sky, the earth, the sea, and everything in them.
Given these points, why shouldn't the omnipotent God, who is the author and creator of all things, be rightly and truly understood, or even believed to be the predestinator of both the righteous and the ordained punishments?
Although to those suffering and enduring those punishments they may seem bad, to that eternal judge they are not bad because they are just, and nothing just can be called bad.
Therefore, He both predestined and prepared that eternal fire, of which Truth itself says:
Which is prepared for the devil and his angels (Matthew 25:41);
and of which Solomon says:
Judgments are prepared for scoffers, and blows for the backs of fools (Proverbs 19:29).
If these punishments for the impious and unjust were not predestined by the just God as judge, how is it said about them, still future and yet to come, through blessed John in the Apocalypse:
And they will be tormented day and night forever and ever (Revelation 20:10);
and again:
And the smoke of their torment will rise forever and ever (Revelation 14:11).
How does blessed Peter also say about certain evil people:
For whom the gloom of utter darkness has been reserved (Second Peter 2:17).
And blessed Jude the apostle similarly says about them:
For whom the storm of darkness has been reserved forever (Jude 13).
Surely, we all unanimously confess that God predestined all things that He would make, and undoubtedly no one but Him could make such great, just, and eternal judgments.
Therefore, if they pertain to His works and cannot be made by anyone else, it is certain and should not be doubted at all that they have Him as their predestinator, who is their author and creator.
If someone says that God is not the author or creator of punishments because punishment, like evil, sin, or death, does not have substance or nature to exist on its own, and therefore could not have been predestined by God, we must firmly contradict them with the evident truth.
Clearly, the word "punishment" does not represent any subsistent thing or nature, unlike words such as Heaven, earth, or sea.
These words immediately denote specific natures of things.
Although the word "punishment" does not signify something that exists by itself, it does represent a significant evil acted upon by existing natures.
So, even though it has no substance of its own, it signifies something brought about through existing things and substances, just as the word "death" signifies no substance of its own because it cannot exist by itself.
Yet, "death" signifies and is understood as a severe evil known in the separation of soul and body.
Thus, almighty God did not predestine punishment to exist in its own nature, but He did predestine it in the natures and substances that truly exist, to which such a great evil, signified and understood by that name, is truly and substantially exhibited.
After this, he says: God's predestination is only for things that are good, but His foreknowledge is for both good and evil.
This difference does not arise from the nature of things, but from the manner of speaking.
We hold and embrace this difference between God's foreknowledge and predestination, because, as the holy Fathers have handed it down and the truth itself demonstrates, it is true.
God, who knows all future events, has eternally foreseen everything that is to come, both good and bad.
However, He predestined only the good things that He Himself would bring about, through either His free mercy or His just judgment.
Therefore, it is most accurate to understand God's foreknowledge in both good and bad things, but predestination only in the good and just things, which He not only foresaw but also determined, defined, and decreed to come to pass.
This person mentions this difference to argue that God could foresee bad things but could not predestine them, not understanding the distinction of evil that we have already pointed out; namely, that one kind of evil is contrary to good, which is indeed a vice and does not have God as its author, and another kind of evil is contrary to peace, rest, or health, which never happens except by God's will and judgment.
As He speaks through the prophet:
I am the Lord, who makes peace and creates evil" Isaiah forty-five, verse seven.
Hence, it is also said by another prophet:
"Shall there be evil in a city, and the Lord has not done it?" Amos three, verse six.
And again:
"Good and bad, life and death, poverty and wealth, are from God" Ecclesiasticus eleven, verse fourteen.
Therefore, regarding the evil that is understood as vice or sin, God is not the predestinator, because He is not its author;
but regarding the evil that is understood as affliction, torment, and punishment, whether temporal or eternal, since these, as Scripture teaches, are from Him and arranged and inflicted by His judgment, He is clearly both the author and the predestinator, because He both foresaw them as future and justly predestined them to be done.
Given these things, bringing up this difference did nothing but deny the truth and demonstrate ignorance.
As for what he said: that this difference in divine foreknowledge and predestination is not from nature but from the use of expressions, it seems better and more true to us that it is from nature and according to nature; because even in God's nature:
"There is no variation or shadow due to change" James one, verse seventeen.
So, for Him, knowing is one thing, foreknowing is another, and predestining is yet another.
His one, simple, and eternal knowledge contains everything at once and equally, which in temporal matters is acted upon and exhibited in different ways.
However, since God's foreknowledge and predestination truly relate to the state and disposition of His creatures, they do not differ in God's eternal and unchangeable knowledge.
Everything there is one and simple knowledge, neither varied by times nor changed by the diversity of things.
Yet, there is a difference in temporally passing things.
Some things are present or past, where human understanding properly recognizes knowledge, and other things are future, to which it properly understands foreknowledge or predestination to apply.
And because in those future things there occurs another diversity, so that some are good, and others are evil, another difference occurs.
Predestination is recognized in good things only, while foreknowledge is understood in both good and evil things.
Thus, this difference between foreknowledge and predestination, although it does not arise from the nature or according to the nature of the unchangeable deity, is nevertheless recognized from the nature and according to the nature of administering and disposing of the changeable creature.
We have also spoken more fully about this matter above, in the second chapter of this discussion.
Therefore, we in no way allow these things, which are so rightly and truly distinguished by their properties and handed down to us by the Fathers, to be disturbed and confused by anyone's new presumption.
So, when someone indiscriminately and confusedly presumes to say, as this person does, that all foreknowledge is predestination, it is most clearly blasphemous.
While God can foreknow even evil things, it would be said, God forbid, that He predestined them.
Although predestination, because it is not without foreknowledge, cannot absurdly be said to include foreknowledge.
However, he argues that this distinction comes not from the truth and nature of things, but only from the usage of our language, and he provides an example that contradicts his own statement.
He says: Just as it is said that God can be present everywhere by the power of His presence, but not everywhere by the grace of His habitation, so it can be said that He is everywhere by foreknowledge, but not everywhere by predestination.
Yet, the truth clearly states about God: wherever He is present, He is indeed present by habitation.
Similarly, wherever there is foreknowledge, there must necessarily be predestination.
He asserts that this religious phrasing of ecclesiastical discipline, which helps us distinguish and say that God is everywhere by the presence of His majesty, but not everywhere by the presence of His habitation, is not from the nature of things, but only from the usage of human language.
This undermines the most beneficial sense of the entire Holy Scripture, where the almighty God is presented to us as being generally everywhere by the presence of His majesty, but specifically by the grace of His habitation.
Regarding His general presence of majesty, He Himself says: "I fill heaven and earth."
And the Prophet says to Him: "If I ascend to heaven, You are there; if I descend to hell, You are present: if I take the wings of the dawn and dwell in the uttermost parts of the sea, even there Your hand will lead me, and Your right hand will hold me"
Psalm 139:8-10.
But regarding the grace of His habitation, which is not everywhere but in His temple, that is, in the holy and rational creature, angelic or human, which alone is capable of His knowledge and intelligence, illumination, and grace; sometimes signified by the heavens, through which the heavenly life of angels or holy humans is understood; sometimes by the specific mention of His temple.
Scripture speaks in this way: "He who sits in the heavens shall laugh"
Psalm 2:4.
And: "To You, I lift up my eyes, You who sit in the heavens"
Psalm 123:1.
And: "Look down from Your holy habitation, from heaven"
Deuteronomy 26:15.
Our Father, who is in heaven. Matthew 6:9.
And what the Apostle said:
Do you not know that you are the temple of God, and that the Holy Spirit dwells in you?
First Corinthians 3:16.
And again:
For you are the temple of the living God, as God says,
because I will dwell in them and walk among them, and I will be their God, and they will be my people.
Second Corinthians 6:16; Leviticus 26:12.
Since there is such a great distance and difference between the presence of divine majesty, which is generally and potentially shown to all creation,
and the grace of habitation, which is specially and mercifully granted only to rational and chosen creatures who can comprehend its influence, understanding, and sweetness:
Why does he try so recklessly to nullify this divine sense, so necessary for our faith and salvation, to the extent that he says the very truth cries out?
That wherever God is present, He is also in habitation?
On the contrary, this truth of God's Scripture always carefully discerns and distinguishes that the habitation of God is only in His temple, either heavenly or still placed on earth, commended through the goodness of His grace.
It is indeed said that He sometimes inhabits a temple made by hands and consecrated with religious devotion to His name,
because of the grace of that consecration, and the more familiar worship of His majesty, and the more renowned effect of supplication and hearing:
As the Lord Himself shows in the Gospel, saying:
And whoever swears by the temple, swears by it, and by Him who dwells in it.
Matthew 23:21.
And yet the Scripture clearly says:
Because the Most High does not dwell in temples made by hands.
Acts 7:48.
Hence Solomon also says in his prayer about the temple which he built and consecrated for Him:
If heaven, and the heaven of heavens cannot contain You, how much less this house which I have built?
Second Chronicles 2:6.
Thus, we understand that in a temple built by human hands, dedicated and consecrated to His name, God can be said to dwell by a certain grace of favor and through the sanctification of heavenly sacraments.
However, He does not dwell there by the immensity of majesty and the abundance of grace that He bestows only on the chosen and rational creatures.
A certain holy and glorious martyr said about Him: "The whole world is His temple." If by this he meant the entire world, consisting of heaven and earth, it is understood correctly. This is because God can be worshiped everywhere in the world, adored everywhere. True worshipers no longer worship in Jerusalem with the Jews, nor on that mountain with the Samaritans, but worship the Father everywhere in spirit and in truth. (John 4:3)
However, if he meant that the whole world is His temple in the sense that Scripture often refers to the entire human race, it is clear that the whole world is the temple of God.
Specifically, those who, from the entire human race, are converted and gathered to God become His temple.
Hence, the same blessed martyr, after saying "The whole world is His temple," added, "He must be dedicated in our mind, consecrated in our heart."
Therefore, from the truth and nature of things, Almighty God is said to be everywhere by the presence of majesty, but not everywhere by the grace of inhabitation. He exhibits the presence of majesty to all creation generally and grants the grace of His inhabitation only to the chosen rational creatures.
But what does it mean to say: Of God, there is foreknowledge everywhere, but not predestination everywhere; and wherever there is foreknowledge, there will necessarily be predestination? Who has ever spoken in such a way as to say that God is everywhere by foreknowledge? Since His foreknowledge is known only to Him.
Why say that He is everywhere by predestination, when His predestination is only known to Himself?
Similarly, it is foolish to claim: Wherever there is foreknowledge, there must necessarily be predestination.
No one says this; as some of the ancient Fathers have noted, it is merely a novelty of speech.
We say that God is everywhere in majesty, power, and virtue because all of this-majesty, power, virtue-is He, who is everywhere.
However, it is unnecessary to say that He is everywhere by foreknowledge or predestination.
Nowhere is it written that God is foreknowledge or predestination.
Therefore, the statement that God's foreknowledge and predestination apply only to the things He would do is clearly false, because His foreknowledge can also apply to evil things, which He was not going to do.
Moreover, the claim that His foreknowledge and habitation are in things neither from Him nor made by Him is similarly foolish.
Where has he ever read this?
Where has he heard from the faithful that God is said to have presence and habitation in things neither from Him nor made by Him?
What are these things which, as he writes, are neither from Him nor made by Him?
If such things exist, then there is some creature which is neither from God nor made by God.
This is not Christian but Manichaean because the Gospel cannot lie, where it is written: All things were made through Him, and without Him nothing was made.
John 1:3.
It is also similar to what he immediately added: The foreknowledge and predestination of God are pronounced in opposition to those things which He neither made nor gave.
He says it is pronounced in opposition, so according to his own new and insane rule, what is pronounced is not truly pronounced.
Therefore, it is a lie to claim that eternal punishment is nothing and has not happened; such a claim contradicts the truth on both counts.
These future events were truly foreseen by God and will truly be inflicted by God on those who deserve it.
Since these things are so clearly found in the Scriptures as having been done, foreseen, and predestined, let such a rule be crushed and perish, which insanely affirms that deeds should be understood as not having happened.
He further added, saying: The eternal fire was made for burning the devil and his angels, not humans.
This is what this person and others perhaps seeking or affirming seem to say; that is, that this eternal fire was not prepared for human punishment but only for the punishment of evil angels.
The Lord did not say in that judgment to those who will be on his left: Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire prepared for you, but rather, prepared for the devil and his angels.
So from this, it appears to be prepared only for evil spirits, that is, the devil and his angels (Matthew 25:41).
Hence, it is understood that some have held the opinion that one fire now tortures the souls of the damned in the underworld, and another eternal fire will be entered by humans only then, when, resurrected with their bodies, they will be compelled to go into the same eternal fire along with the devil and his angels.
Whether it is one fire in which now only souls, and then also bodies, will be tormented, or whether it is one fire or another; let us believe the true Scripture.
Both the punishment of eternal fire and the outer darkness, which will undoubtedly be there, are prepared and reserved not only for the angels who did not keep their principality but abandoned their dwelling, whom God also delivered into judgment to be tormented as they fell from heaven, but also for wicked humans.
As we have already mentioned, blessed Peter the apostle speaks about certain wicked individuals who will be condemned to final destruction: "For whom the gloom of darkness is reserved forever" (Second Peter 2:17).
Similarly, blessed Jude the apostle says about the same individuals: "For whom the storm of darkness is reserved forever" (Jude 12).
Just as that gloom and storm of eternal darkness are prepared and reserved for wicked and very evil people, so too is the eternal fire, which must be understood as the same.
Therefore, what the Lord says about the same eternal fire: "Which is prepared for the devil and his angels" Matthew 25:41, we should faithfully understand that what is said primarily about the devil should consequently also be understood about his followers, about whom Scripture says: "But they imitate him, who are on his side" (Wisdom 2:25).
So, the punishment primarily prepared for the devil is also accepted as prepared and reserved for his followers, as the above-mentioned apostolic words clearly demonstrate.
He adds and says: After he was cast down from the ether, where he could not feel pain in an ethereal body, a body of air was added to him, in which he could feel fire.
Regarding this matter, let us not listen to this man's hasty and inconsiderate definition, but rather let us heed the pious, moderate, and very cautious words of blessed Augustine, who was more searching than defining.
He says, the higher part of the air, because of its pure tranquility, is joined in common peace to the sky, to which it is adjacent, and is named by the same name.
In this part, perhaps, if the transgressing angels were with their prince before their transgression, now the devil, then the archangel (for some do not believe them to have been heavenly or super-heavenly angels), it is not surprising if after sin they were cast into this gloom, where there is still air, and it is woven with thin moisture.
If those transgressors, before they sinned, possessed heavenly bodies, it's not surprising that they were transformed as a punishment into an airy quality.
This way, they can now suffer from fire, an element of a higher nature.
They were not allowed to occupy the higher and purer spaces of the air.
Instead, they were confined to these murky regions, which serve as a kind of prison until the time of judgment.
If we need to inquire more diligently about these transgressing angels, we can look to the teacher of piety, who presumes nothing rashly but treats each matter cautiously and humbly.
He says that the transgressing angels, with their leader now called the devil - formerly an archangel - were either in the higher part of the air, the ethereal heaven, before they sinned, or perhaps they existed in the heavenly realms among the other celestial or super-celestial angels.
If they were only in the ethereal heaven, they were cast out from that pure and serene tranquility into this lower and murky part of the air after their sin.
Similarly, if before their transgression, like the other angels, they had heavenly bodies, those bodies could have been transformed or were transformed as a punishment into an airy quality.
This way, they can now suffer the punishment due to them from the fire.
Therefore, this holy teacher did not define whether they existed in the ethereal heaven or even in the starry heaven before their sin, but he does not deny either possibility.
Wherever they fell from after their transgression, whether from the higher or lower heaven, even if they had heavenly bodies before, they were transformed as a punishment into an airy quality.
He does not consider it inappropriate that no other bodies were added to them from the air itself, that is, airy bodies.
Unlike him, it is not concluded that the devil was cast down from the ether to the air, because he could have fallen from the heavens.
Nor is it concluded that he had an etheric or heavenly body.
But if he did, it was transformed into something worse as punishment.
Nor was an airy body added to him, as if he were clothed with two bodies, one heavenly or etheric, and the other airy.
Instead, his heavenly body itself, if it existed, was changed as punishment into an airy quality, so that it would no longer be a heavenly or etheric body, but an airy body, where he could feel the punishment and torment of fire.
Again, considering the same matter elsewhere, and deliberating very cautiously and hesitantly, he says: Therefore, with this caution that the blessed doctor shows in his inquiries, such matters should be considered and discussed, and nothing should be believed lightly or falsely.
He continues, and says: That fire is not a punishment, nor was it prepared or predestined for that: but it was predestined to be in the universe of all good things, and has become the place of the impious, in which without a doubt the blessed will dwell no less than the wretched.
In these words, when he says that the eternal fire is not a punishment, he clearly contradicts the Truth itself, that is, the judge of the living and the dead, who foretold that he would say in that judgment: Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire (Matthew 25:41).
And so that we understand that the eternal fire itself is punishment and everlasting torment, immediately after a few words about the wretched who are to be eternally damned and tormented there, he adds, saying: Then they will go away into eternal punishment (Matthew 25:46).
He also contradicts the blessed apostle Paul, who says: In the revelation of our Lord Jesus Christ from heaven with his mighty angels: inflicting vengeance in flaming fire on those who do not know God and who do not obey the gospel of our Lord Jesus Christ.
They will suffer the punishment of eternal destruction from the face of the Lord and from the glory of his might (Second Thessalonians 1:7-9).
It contradicts the blessed apostle John regarding the same lake of fire and sulfur in the Apocalypse, where he says:
"And they will be tormented day and night forever and ever"
(Revelation 20:10);
and again:
"And the smoke of their torment will rise forever and ever"
(Revelation 14:10).
And the Scriptures, which say:
"He will give fire and worms into their flesh, so that they may be burned and feel it forever"
(Judith 16:21).
And again:
"Humble your spirit greatly, because the revenge of the wicked is fire and worms"
(Sirach 7:19).
Since these things are so, and must be faithfully held for constant fear and correction,
how does this person dare, or why is he allowed such impious and harmful freedom, to say in the Church, to the subversion of the listeners and the nurturing of a deadly security, that there is not that eternal fire of punishment?
When the Lord testifies that it is eternal punishment, and the truth of apostolic teaching clearly declares it as the fire and flame of vengeance, eternal punishment in destruction, torment day and night, and the smoke of their torment rising forever and ever.
And therefore, we must undoubtedly and truly believe these things, so that such fear may restrain and mortify in us the delight of sinning, and may arouse and strengthen the diligence of doing good and pleasing God.
For the Lord himself shows us this as especially necessary, saying:
"I will show you whom to fear: fear him who, after he has killed, has the power to cast into hell"
(Luke 12:5);
and again:
"But rather fear him who can destroy both soul and body in hell"
(Matthew 10:28).
Wherefore, elsewhere the Scripture, showing the benefit of this fear, and the harm of security, says:
"The fear of the Lord drives out sin"
(Sirach 1:27):
for the one who is without fear cannot be justified.
What this person is saying is that the eternal fire wasn't initially created for punishment, but simply to exist within the universe created by a good Creator.
However, according to our faith, this is not to be accepted.
Instead, we believe that the omnipotent God, who created everything from the beginning, did so with specific reasons and necessary uses in mind, creating nothing in vain or superfluously.
He intended each creation to have its own purpose or utility: like light for day, darkness for night, the firmament of heaven as the seat of the luminaries, the separation of waters above the heavens to temper the stars, herbs and trees for the sustenance of living beings, the greater light to rule the day, and the lesser light and stars to rule the night.
Just as these things were created and ordained from the beginning, God immediately assigned them to their proper duties and uses.
Similarly, the eternal fire, created from the beginning, is believed to have been predestined by His just providence and justice for the purpose He indicated when He said to the wicked and condemned: "Go into the eternal fire," adding, "which is prepared for the devil and his angels" (Matthew 25:41).
This means it is for the eternal punishment of both angels and humans.
From His words, "Come, blessed of my Father, receive the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world" (Matthew 25:34), we can understand that, conversely, the eternal fire for the punishment of the wicked was also prepared from the foundation of the world.
However, there is no injustice with God in preparing and predestining the fire of eternal punishment for such a great multitude of the wicked, long before they even existed.
For example, in the construction of a new city, if a dreadful and terrifying prison is built at the same time as the city itself, it cannot be considered an injustice, but rather a provision of mercy and justice.
This way, those who live in the city, seeing the penal and grim prison of condemnation, are either mercifully deterred from sinning, or, if they do not avoid sins, are justly and inexcusably punished.
Thus, the fire created for eternal punishment should be believed to be both merciful and just, as it either corrects people through fear or justly punishes those who refuse to be corrected.
Regarding the creation of this eternal fire, which we must understand to be among those works of God, when He made the heavens and the earth, the sea, and all that is in them in six days, and rested on the seventh day from all His work which He had done Exodus 20:11, so says the holy Pope Gregory, explaining the words of the book of blessed Job, where it is written about the wicked: "A fire not fanned will devour him" Job 20:26, he says this:
Still explaining the same blessed doctor's words following which it is said of the same wicked person: "The heavens will reveal his iniquity, and the earth will rise up against him" Job 20:27, he adds what should be faithfully thought about the punishments of that eternal fire:
Also, when he explained the words of the same book, in which it is written about the same wicked person: "He will repay what he has labored for and will not swallow it down; according to the measure of his iniquity, so shall he suffer" Job 20:18, he says:
This holy doctor speaks these terrifying truths in a terrifying and true manner, to arouse the minds of the listeners to fear, stimulate them to correction, and compel them to awaken from deadly security to the care of their own salvation.
However, this one, still speaking vainly about vain things and falsely about false things, says that the eternal fire, which was created for this purpose alone, as he wishes, to be in the universe of all good things, has become the seat of the wicked.
He did not say torment, punishment, or suffering was made for the wicked.
Instead, he said a seat was made for the wicked.
According to his understanding, just as each person's seat is their home, where they peacefully reside, so also for the wicked, that fire is not a torment of damnation but a peaceful seat of dwelling.
He further adds about the same fire, saying: "In which undoubtedly the blessed will dwell no less than the wretched." Here he said they will dwell in that fire, not be tortured or punished, completely denying, as usual, the true punishments of eternal torments, which all of Scripture announces with such terror and commends with such attention.
But when he says: "In which undoubtedly the blessed will dwell no less than the wretched," he clearly strives to affirm that both the blessed and the wretched will dwell in one eternal fire after the resurrection. This follows the foolish and vain persuasion of secular philosophers, who think that the souls of the pious, after the dissolution of the body, will dwell either in the ethereal heaven, in that circle called the Milky Way, or in the spheres of the stars.
He calls all these, including the ethereal heaven itself, the firmament of heaven where the Milky Way appears, and the stars themselves, eternal fire, just like the fire of Gehenna. He thinks all these, which are established above the three elements of the world-earth, water, and air-exist from the fourth element, fire. Thus, the same fourth element of the world, and in the underworld, is eternal fire, which is prepared for the devil and his angels, as stated in Matthew 25:41, and for all wicked humans; and in the heavenly spaces is eternal fire where the dwelling of the blessed will be after the resurrection.
Behold the kind of happiness promised to the saints and the chosen ones of God: those who lived on earth as mortals will now live immortally in the highest element of the world, as He says, in eternal fire.
Their reward will be to dwell in any element, no matter how bright or peaceful, and yet pure.
However, the Lord promises eternal happiness not in the elements of the world but in heavenly and super-heavenly realms, where Christ is seated at the right hand of God Colossians 3:1, exalted above the heavens, and interceding for us Romans 8:34.
Regarding the height of this happiness, the Apostle says: "Jesus did not enter a sanctuary made with hands, which are copies of the true one, but into heaven itself, to appear now in the presence of God for us" Hebrews 9:24.
To this dwelling, so that His saints may reach it, He prays to the Father in the Gospel, saying: "Father, I want those you have given me to be with me where I am, and to see my glory, the glory you have given me" John 17:24.
About this blessed and angelic dwelling of the saints, the Apostle says: "We know that if the earthly tent we live in is destroyed, we have a building from God, an eternal house in heaven, not built by human hands" Second Corinthians 5:1. He also said: "I desire to depart and be with Christ" Philippians 1:23.
To all the chosen ones after the resurrection, He promises: "We will be caught up together with them in the clouds to meet the Lord in the air. And so we will be with the Lord forever" First Thessalonians 4:16.
About this glorious and blessed dwelling of the righteous, the Psalmist says: "The upright will dwell in your presence" Psalm 139:14.
Therefore, let this dwelling be sought and desired, not in the elements of the world, but in the presence of God, in the vision of Christ's glory, in the company of the blessed and super-heavenly angels. When the saints will be, as the Truth itself promises, equal to the angels of God in heaven Luke 20:36.
Therefore, the habitation, or rather the confinement, of the blessed will not be in one fiery element of the world, nor will they be enclosed there like the wicked in eternal fire.
Instead, they will have all the elements of the world under their control, so subjected to them with such happiness and ease, and so suited to their immortal state, that wherever they want to be, and just as they want, they can be there immediately.
They will see and possess all these things not so much as a reward of blessedness, but as a culmination of happiness, and for the praise and glory of the Creator.
For prophetic Scripture promises this power and glory to them, saying:
"But the kingdom and the power and the greatness of the kingdoms under the whole heaven shall be given to the people of the saints of the Most High: whose kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and all kings shall serve and obey him"
Daniel 7:27.
After these things, he adds and says: There is no misery except eternal death. Eternal death is ignorance of the truth, and there is no misery except ignorance of the truth; and where truth is unknown, there is no life.
Indeed, what is said in these words could be good if the good itself were not said with a bad, that is, a wrong meaning. For it is true that for a just and wise man, all labor, all adversity, all misery that can happen in this mortal life, if it does not break him and change him for the worse but rather exercises him tirelessly, cannot be misery to him, because it does not make him miserable. Instead, it purifies and tests him, and like gold in a furnace makes him purer. Such a man considers no misery to be his except ignorance of the truth, as he is still delayed from its contemplation, and in a way is repelled by his own weakness.
He does not fear this external death of the body, but that internal death of the soul, which is truly the ignorance of the highest truth, by which all unbelievers are dead, who neither believe nor acknowledge God's truth. About them, the Lord also says:
"Let the dead bury their own dead"
Matthew 8:22; and the Apostle: "Alienated from the life of God through the ignorance that is in them"
Ephesians 4:18.
The life of the faithful is truly the knowledge of the truth itself.
They know it here through faith, and in the future, they will know it through vision.
Here, they receive life through faith in the truth, as it is written: "The righteous will live by faith" (Romans 1:17).
There, they will have eternal life through the knowledge and vision of the same truth, as the Lord says: "This is eternal life, that they know you, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom you have sent" (John 17:3).
Therefore, anyone who attains this knowledge through true faith and eternal contemplation will undoubtedly have eternal life through the eternal vision of Truth.
But for those who are separated from it, either through unbelief or ultimate damnation, what will such separation and ignorance of the truth be for them if not eternal death?
According to this understanding, this is what is read in the teachings of the doctors.
However, what they read well, he twists into something depraved and perverse to fit his own error and lies:
He says all this with no other intention than to use such an argument violently and wickedly, misusing it from good to bad, to seemingly show and confirm that there will be no other misery for the damned in eternal fire, whether they are evil angels or lost humans, except for ignorance and, as he said before, the absence of the truth itself;
And that this ignorance and absence of the truth alone will be their eternal misery, their eternal death:
So that in this way, he contends they will be free from all the misery of punishments and torments applied externally, and from all death of penal damnation.
But no matter how much he contends and tries to argue otherwise, besides that death which they incur internally from ignorance and absence of the truth, they will also suffer externally, as the Apocalypse says: "The lake of fire and sulfur, which is the second death" (Revelation 20:10, 14).
They will truly suffer eternal misery when God, the just and powerful judge, inflicts fire and worms upon their bodies.
They will burn and endure pain forever.
As stated in the Book of Judith, Chapter 16, Verse 21:
"For they will always be in death, compelled to die by the severity of their punishments, and the strictness of divine judgment will never allow them to be extinguished."
Chapter Eighteen
In the eighteenth chapter it says:
1.
The error of predestination comes from ignorance of the disciplines that wisdom intended as companions and investigators, and from ignorance of Greek literature.
2.
The word oro means "I see," "I define," and "I determine."
Similarly, the compound  means "I foresee," "I predefine," "I predestine"; thus, predestination and predefinition are essentially foreseeing.
3. God neither foresaw nor predestined death and punishment because they are nothing.
4. Sinners are left in the mass of original sin; left behind, they are deprived of light; deprived of light, they are tormented by darkness; deprived of life, they are destroyed by death.
5. God does not abandon or forsake what He created in them (otherwise their nature would return to nothing if the highest essence were not in them); but He has rejected what He did not create in them, that is, pride.
6.
God always dwells in the nature that He created towards Himself.
7.
God's wisdom has predestined, through its laws, the limits beyond which the malice of the wicked cannot go, and does not allow anyone's malice to extend infinitely, imposing limits based on divine laws.
8.
The wicked and the devil desire nothing more than to withdraw from Him who is the highest essence.
If the divine law allowed, their nature would return to nothing.
However, eternal laws prevent them from falling as much as they would like, causing them to suffer, be tormented, punished, and tortured, making them miserable in the poverty of empty pleasures.
This difficulty, which stops them from achieving what they lustfully desire, leads to their penal destruction and the just torment of their wretched desire.
9.
The number of each party is predestined.
10.
The wicked serve God unwillingly: not the nature He created in them, which He does not punish, but the evil will, which He did not create in them and which He punishes; and in serving Him unwillingly, they are punished by their own punishment.
For those He does not justly free, He somewhat prepares them by allowing them to prepare themselves for it.
When he says:
The error of predestination arises from ignorance of the disciplines, which wisdom itself wanted to be its companions and investigators, and from the lack of knowledge of Greek literature;
he certainly reminds his listeners to learn the knowledge of the liberal disciplines from him, as he is a very learned and philosophical man, perhaps also to learn the expertise of Greek literature from him similarly:
for he affirms that wisdom itself has those same doctrines of the liberal arts joined to it as companions and associates, so that whoever wishes to attain its understanding must absolutely have those liberal disciplines to investigate what is true through them.
Therefore, if ignorance of secular literature has caused error regarding the truth of divine predestination among others, what has this man, who boasts of being skilled in them, investigated about this matter through them?
What truth has he found?
What has he discussed in his lengthy speech that is supported by the firmest reason and worthy of all acceptance?
Where nothing else is found except the superfluous labor of vanity, the entanglement of infinite error, and the most open opposition to the truth, while he despises the Scriptures of truth, and also remains ignorant of the histories of divine words, not meditating on them day and night, nor striving to correct, direct, and inform his faith according to their rule:
but he spends days and nights reading human vanities and wishes to fill his belly with the husks that the pigs eat
Luke 15:16, yet he does not find any nourishment from it: but he wastes away and perishes with the most wretched hunger under the rule of the most wicked master, who sent him into his field to feed pigs
Luke 15.
Let him return to himself, get up, and go to his father so that he may find bread inside when he was dying of hunger outside; there he will be fed with the feast of the fattened calf, sacrificed for the salvation of the world; there he will hear the music and chorus (Luke 15:25), which is the admirable harmony of the heavenly Scriptures and the sweet concord of the faithful, who all, being of the same mind, are united in the same sense and judgment, unanimously honoring God with one voice and the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.
In this house, therefore, placed by God's mercy and the grace of faith, let us hear and faithfully hold on to what the steward of the eternal bread, that is, the divine word, conveys to us, saying: If anyone among you seems to be wise in this age, let him become a fool so that he may become wise.
For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God.
For it is written: He catches the wise in their craftiness.
And: The Lord knows the thoughts of the wise, that they are vain (First Corinthians 3:18, 20).
Let's also hear that most wise man, who says: I am the most foolish of men, and human wisdom is not with me; I have not learned wisdom, nor do I know the knowledge of the holy ones (Proverbs 30:2, 3).
We do not say this as if there is no truth to be found in those human writings, or that those disciplines do not have some usefulness in seeking the truth; but because every faithful person must first diligently learn the truth of faith from the authority of the Scriptures of God: so that whatever might later need to be read or known from those human writings, it should all be judged from that divine authority and truth of faith; so that whatever does not disagree with its rule may be accepted without danger, but whatever is found to be in discord with it should be rejected as deadly.
Whoever thinks they can discover the truth of God and the integrity of faith without true knowledge, without the trustworthy authority of Holy Scripture, and without the diligent teaching of the Fathers, using only human writings and disciplines, undoubtedly deceives and misleads themselves.
While trying to appear as an inventor of truth, they become a teacher of error.
The order of piety must be so attentively observed that even the sacred writings in the books of the law and the prophets cannot be useful and beneficial to readers unless the faith of Christ either precedes in the heart of the reader, through which they are truly understood, or is faithfully sought in them and found with God's illumination.
Thus, the Apostle, advising and instructing his faithful and beloved disciple, says: "And from childhood you have known the sacred writings, which are able to instruct you for salvation through the faith that is in Christ Jesus" (Second Timothy 3:15).
This means that the sacred writings can instruct a person for salvation through the faith that is in Christ Jesus, because without this faith no saving instruction can be found there.
Therefore, this person erred greatly, perceiving and writing much that was false and fallacious, because they ignored the Holy Scriptures, did not seek the truth of faith in them humbly and faithfully, but arrogantly believed they could find it through human and inept arguments.
Consequently, they did not find it but rather attacked it faithlessly and unhappily.
Therefore, whoever wishes to escape human error concerning the truth of divine predestination and find what they should hold according to the truth should carefully and faithfully read the prophetic, evangelical, and apostolic writings, as we have already said, and should not dare to defend their own understanding against them, but humbly submit to their authority and truth, lest they try to kick against the goad to their own ruin.
From these sacred writings, since we have already discussed this matter at length above, to avoid boring the readers, we will briefly mention just one point here, from the letter of the blessed Jude the apostle.
Speaking about the most ungodly heretics who have attacked and will attack the Church of the Lord from the time of the apostles until the end of the world, he shows that they have been given over to a depraved mind by the eternal and just judgment of God.
This causes them to dare to speak such great and terrible things against God, and they are ultimately condemned to eternal destruction by the same divine judgment.
He says: "For certain men have secretly slipped in among you (who long ago were marked out for this condemnation), ungodly people, who change the grace of our God into a license for immorality and deny Jesus Christ our only Sovereign and Lord" (Jude 4).
Showing how long ago and how many ages before this was predicted and prophesied about them, he adds after many things: "Enoch, the seventh from Adam, also prophesied about them: 'See, the Lord is coming with thousands upon thousands of his holy ones to judge everyone, and to convict all the ungodly of all the ungodly acts they have done in an ungodly way, and of all the harsh words ungodly sinners have spoken against him'" (Jude 14, 15).
Regarding their eternal damnation and the horrible punishment prepared and reserved for them, he explicitly adds, saying: "They are wandering stars, for whom blackest darkness has been reserved forever" (Jude 13).
What could be clearer about the predestination of the ungodly to the condemnation of eternal judgment than that these ungodly people were marked out for this judgment so long ago and so many ages before, by both divine judgment and prophetic prediction?
(Jude 4).
We shouldn't be so unreasonable as to think that because the blessed patriarch and prophet Enoch, the seventh generation from Adam, prophesied this, that God Almighty decided or predestined something then that wasn't already in His eternal judgment and counsel.
In God's unchangeable eternity, there can be no new will or recent arrangement; but what was eternally determined by Him, He wanted to be prophesied and fulfilled in the most fitting order over time.
This was for the judgment and condemnation of those who would dare and do such things, and for the testing and strengthening of His Church, which He also intended to be more diligently taught and more gloriously arranged through such contradictions and attacks.
As the Apostle says: "For there must be heresies among you, that those who are approved may be made manifest among you" (First Corinthians 11:19).
If we seek the just and eternal predestination of God in the condemnation of the wicked, let's hear that certain men are marked out for this impious judgment; and they are marked not just temporally by prophetic speech, but eternally by divine judgment.
For what was eternally fixed by God was foretold and marked temporally through the prophet.
If we ask whether punishment and torment are prepared for them by God's eternal judgment, let's hear what is said about them: "For whom the storm of darkness is reserved forever"; and thus, faithfully accepting the divine truth, neither the wicked nor the punishments divinely prepared for the wicked. But you, beloved, building yourselves up on your most holy faith, praying in the Holy Spirit, keep yourselves in the love of God; and rebuke some who are judged, save others by snatching them out of the fire, and have mercy on others with fear (Jude 1:20-23).
He does not say, "Rebuke those to be judged," but rather, "Rebuke those already judged." This means that what is destined to come to those persisting in their impiety, now appears to them by the terrifying predestination of divine and eternal judgment, as has been said. This applies to those who are to be punished in the future and already condemned by divine sentence in the present.
Moving on, we need to consider what this man adds to appear knowledgeable in Greek: "Behold the Greek word oro, which means 'I see,' 'I define,' and 'I determine.' Similarly, the compound prooro means 'I foresee,' 'I predefine,' 'I predestine.' Thus, predestination and predefinition are nothing other than foreseeing."
In these words, he correctly states that oro can be translated into Latin as video. But how should this video be understood? Is it simply seeing many things passively and presenting themselves to our sight, or is it with a certain fixed gaze, by which we come to know something with certainty? Or do we direct our gaze with such intention that our sight follows like an arrow toward a target? Just as Scripture says of the ironworker or any other metalworker, that the eye of the craftsman is upon the object being made, with such intense focus that nothing in it is allowed to be different from what he has intended.
Therefore, the term oro, meaning "I see," should be understood in such a way that this vision is directed with certainty, so that the gaze, or the aim, or the crafting, or other such actions are directed straight and unwaveringly toward it.
From the word oro comes the term oro, which in Latin is visio. This vision, for example, of a dream or some revelation, was defined by the ancients as seeing something that will happen in the same way it appeared.
Therefore, especially in the Scriptures, any vision of divine revelation, seen in the spirit in such a way that it cannot happen otherwise, is read in Greek as appearing or being seen in oro.
According to this clear reasoning, when it is said "I see" in this context, it is understood as "I define" or "I determine." When the sentence is composed with the added preposition, and it is said prooro, it is understood as "I predetermine" or "I predestine," which both have the same meaning and can also be interpreted as "I foresee." This foresight, when related to God, is completely certain, and it will happen as He has foreseen. From this word oro, it seems that the Greek word , which means determination, is derived, and with the added preposition , it means predestination. No one has ever dared to interpret these two words as vision or prevision, but as determination and predestination. Similarly, from the same word oro, it seems that orisen, which means "he determined," is derived, and with the added preposition proorisen, it means "he predestined." However, prooro, as mentioned above, can also be interpreted as "I foresee." For example, in the psalm where we say in Latin: "I foresaw the Lord always before me" (Psalm 15:8); in Greek, it is read as prooro  , indicating certain foresight and determination.
Blessed Jerome, in his edition, put it this way: "I have set the Lord always before me," which more clearly pertains to determination. What is determined is directed towards a specific intention or plan, as shown in Scripture, which says: "Or like an arrow shot at a designated target" (Wisdom 5:12).
And the Apostle, where he says about himself: "I press on toward the goal for the prize of the heavenly calling of God" (Philippians 3:14).
The blessed Jerome, explaining this, said:
"Therefore, let this person not mock our ignorance by changing some Greek words with a new interpretation and diminishing their force as much as he can. For what all the ancient interpreters in the Holy Scriptures have understood as either predestination, predefinition, providence, or purpose, this person now wants to call 'foreknowledge' with an unusual and absurd name.
And although foreknowledge in God, like prescience, is most certain, we do not allow the sense of predestination to be diminished or destroyed by the novelty of this term. This is because God can foresee and know in advance even those things which He is not going to do. However, only those things which He will do, either out of His mercy or His judgment, are understood to be predestined by Him.
Therefore, let us completely reject the notion that predestination and predefinition by God are nothing but foreknowledge, as this person has said and seemingly defined. This interpretation is clearly impious, as if God merely foresaw what each person would do and what they would suffer for their actions, and did not predestine or predefine in His eternal judgment anything about the person who would act well or poorly.
Furthermore, this person adds and says that God neither foresaw nor predestined death and punishments because they are nothing. This is so vain and contrary to the truth that it has already been shown sufficiently and often.
Then this person, speaking of God, adds: 'He left sinners in the mass of original sin; those left behind He abandoned; the abandoned are tortured by darkness, deprived of light, and killed by death. God does not leave or abandon what He has made in them; otherwise, their nature would return to nothing if the supreme essence were not in them. But He scorned what He did not make in them, which is pride.'"
Therefore, what he says about God leaving sinners in the mass of original sin-if he had said the reprobate, or those who are to be punished or damned, it would certainly be true.
For indeed, the reprobate, those to be punished and damned, remain in that mass condemned generally from Adam, because the omnipotent potter did not distinguish them from it, as he makes one vessel for honor and another for dishonor from the same lump.
Romans 9:21
Now, what he says, that God left sinners in the mass of original sin, cannot be entirely true, because surely he distinguished and liberated sinners.
As it is written: "I came not to call the righteous, but sinners." Matthew 9:13 And of whom the Apostle says: "This is a faithful saying, and worthy of all acceptance, that Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners." First Timothy 1:15
However, because he did not say, "He left all sinners in that mass," which would certainly be blatantly false, but said indefinitely, "He left sinners in that mass," this can be understood as partial, so what is said may stand in some way.
But what he adds about those left in the mass of sin: "Left them, deserted them to be tormented by the darkness, deserted by life to be killed by death," he wants them to be understood as left by God, and by leaving, deserted. Therefore, because they are deserted by the true light, they are tormented by the darkness of their blindness in mind, and because they are deserted by the true life, they are killed by a special death in the soul. This is to be their punishment and penalty in that eternal damnation, so that with no external torment applied, they are punished solely by the blindness of mind and the death of the soul, as he has tried to assert repeatedly above.
And to show that some great good remains for them in that damnation, he still says of them: "Nor does God leave or desert what he made in them, otherwise their nature would revert to nothing if the supreme essence were not in them, but he despised what he did not make in them, that is, pride."
Behold the goodness that God proclaims to remain for them, the very goodness He deems fit to bestow even upon the insensible elements.
By His almighty power, He grants them existence and ensures their continuation.
Their nature is not reduced to nothingness; through that same power, He sustains and preserves them.
However, these elements of the world, as they exist, are preserved in their natural state, continuing to praise the Creator and serving the use or honor of rational beings.
But the nature of the damned and lost is preserved by God's almighty power so that it does not perish.
By God's just judgment, it serves only to their punishment, ensuring their agony never ends.
It is fitting to praise the Creator, who did not wish the goodness of nature, which He created, to be entirely destroyed.
What He says is true: Otherwise, their nature would return to nothingness if the supreme essence were not in them.
If He had said their nature would return to nothingness if the supreme essence did not grant them existence or preserve their existence, it would be true.
For everything that exists received its existence from that supreme and divine essence.
However, since He said, unless the supreme essence were in them, it seems He attributes so much to those who will be damned in perdition that they might even seem to be the temple of God.
For if the supreme essence is in them, and since the supreme essence is God, who says of Himself: I am who I am (Exodus 3:14), then God will be in them, and they can be called the temple of God.
So that God may say of them: And I will dwell in them.
Indeed, they would be more than a temple if the supreme essence were in them.
They would seem to be united with God by a certain essential union-something that is uniquely to be believed about the one and only Mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus, whom the Word of God and God the Word united to Himself by an essential and natural conjunction, that is, He assumed Him into the unity of His person.
If he claims that the highest substance exists within them by its own action, meaning their substance isn't destroyed or lost through any grace of inhabitation that allows them to enjoy some good in it and from it, he should reconsider this unusual and bold way of speaking.
Instead of saying the highest essence is in wicked people doomed to eternal damnation, he should state that the highest essence is present to them through the power of the one acting, not through the dignity of the one inhabiting.
There's a significant question that should be explored with faithful piety as far as divine grace allows: how the omnipotent God is believed to always be present everywhere in the universe of creation and sometimes even within it.
However, we propose this topic for more investigation rather than explanation here, so that the truth of this matter may be sought piously and faithfully by the devout, and with God's help, truly found.
This individual, lacking experience in ecclesiastical speech and Christian piety, further asserts regarding the same wicked, damned people, that God always dwells in the nature He created for Himself.
By these words, he clearly refers to human nature, which God made in a rational mind to His image and likeness.
He claims that God always dwells in this rational mind nature, both in the present age and in the future, in believers who are faithful to Him, in unbelievers and pagans who are estranged from Him by their own disbelief, in the elect whom He made His temple, and in the reprobates whom He condemned to eternal damnation.
This is certainly contrary to faith and truth.
If this were true, it would mean that God the Father, Christ, and the Holy Spirit dwell even in the most unfaithful Jews and pagans, who, as far as the good nature created by God is concerned, are made in the image and likeness of God.
Likewise, it would imply that God the Father, Christ, and the Holy Spirit dwell in those condemned to eternal damnation.
In what impious and detestable sense could anything more horrible be said or thought?
For this absurdity also follows: if angels, who are certainly rational creatures, are rightly believed to be made in the image and likeness of God, they did not receive anything less in their nature than humans.
Even in the devil and his angels, who exist of the same nature as the holy angels, God the Father, heaven forbid, and Christ, and the Holy Spirit would be said to dwell.
Whereas this gift of blessed and gracious dwelling is believed to be granted only to the chosen and faithful rational creatures, as we have shown from the Scriptures above.
For the Lord promises to the pious and faithful, saying: "My Father and I will come to him and make our home with him" (John 14:23).
Similarly, He promises the dwelling of the Holy Spirit, saying: "And I will ask the Father, and he will give you another Helper, to be with you forever" (John 14:16-17).
He also adds shortly after: "You will know him, because he will dwell with you and will be in you."
About such people, God Himself says: "I will dwell in them and walk among them" (Second Corinthians 6:16).
And the Psalmist says: "They will rejoice forever, and He will dwell in them" (Psalm 5:12).
He also says elsewhere: "If the Lord had not been on our side, let Israel now say, if the Lord had not been on our side" (Psalm 124:1).
Hence, the blessed apostle John, distinguishing between the indwelling God of the pious and the indwelling devil of the impious, says to the faithful: "You are from God, little children, and have overcome them, for He who is in you is greater than he who is in the world" (First John 4:4).
If this person desires correction, let him learn faithfully from the Scriptures, and not argue against the truth of God with human and vain arguments, but let him submit to it with gentle piety.
But since everything he says about those who remain in the state of original sin is repeated only to assert that they are bound by the chain of original sin and not predestined by God to punishment, we must ask him and others who think this way whether it was by any judgment of God that such a large number of the human race became subject to that original sin and thus deserving of eternal death, or not?
If it was not by God's judgment but only by the natural course of corrupted origin that this happened, then sin was transferred to them naturally from that first man in such a way that none of its condemnation was transferred to them, and only the origin of sin, not its just punishment, came to them from Adam.
Clearly, the Apostle says that through one man sin entered the world, and through sin, death, and so death spread to all men.
Romans chapter 5, verse 12.
Therefore, through one man, not only sin but also the punishment of sin, death, entered the world.
By whose judgment, if not by Him who had foretold to man: "On the day you eat from it, you will surely die"?
Genesis chapter 2, verse 17.
Eating from that forbidden tree was indeed sin, and the punishment of sin was consequently added: you will surely die.
God certainly threatened him with not only this first physical death but also the death that happens in the soul through sin, because the soul that sins shall die.
Ezekiel chapter 18, verse 4.
This also includes the second death, which is eternal damnation, to which the guilt of that first sin drags every man unless freed by the grace of Christ.
When God said these things, He did not only want to instill terror in the listener, but He revealed by that threat what He justly decreed in His eternal judgment: that by His just and eternal judgment, if man committed that sin, first, death would be inflicted on the soul, second, the body would also be dissolved by death, and third, he would also be condemned by the second death.
This entire damnation, both in the soul and the body, would be passed on to all descendants along with the sin itself over time.
Thus, the judgment of His eternal counsel and justice, which He decided to begin with the first individual man, was extended to all his offspring:
so that by His just judgment, anyone from that condemned mass in Adam who was not separated by Christ's grace would be bound by the first sentence of divine judgment to eternal damnation.
He did not merely leave the reprobates in the mass of original sin without making any decision or judgment about them;
rather, He judged that His eternal and just judgment, which began with the root, would follow in the offspring;
and what began in the parent would necessarily be fulfilled in the descendants.
Among the faithful, there is no doubt whatsoever that Almighty God, before man sinned, knew he would sin:
and just as He foresaw the sin, He also predestined what man would suffer by His just judgment:
and what He began in judging justly, He completed in the entire progeny with the same foreknowledge, the same predestination of judgment, and the same justice of damnation.
However, the claim that God left the reprobates in that mass of damnation without predestining anything about their damnation
seems to be taken from the book which the Greeks call Hypognosticon,
which many mistakenly believe to be by Saint Augustine due to a false title.
The style and sense of that book itself show that it is not by Saint Augustine and not only contrary to his writings but also contrary to the faith.
The testimonies taken from this new edition we use, which he continuously refuted when disputing against heretics and dealing with matters of faith using the old edition,
convince the contradictors and instruct the faithful.
He further adds: God's wisdom has predestined, in His laws, the limits beyond which the wickedness of the impious cannot progress, etc.
, up to where he says, the most just torment of desire.
In these words, some truths are mentioned as a basis to draw a false conclusion.
It is true that God's wisdom, within the hidden laws of His plan, has predestined and set limits on the extent and measure of the wickedness of evildoers, whether they be angels or humans, so that their malice cannot proceed as far as they would desire.
If their malice is restrained by certain measures and limits under God's hidden laws, it is clearly true because both the devil and wicked humans always have the will to do evil or harm, but they do not always have the power, except when and as much as God allows them.
For instance, when the devil maliciously wished to harm the blessed Job, he was given a limit.
He could only harm as much as he was permitted, not as much as he wanted.
And regarding wicked humans who attempt evil and crooked deeds but cannot accomplish them because God imposes limits, Scripture clearly states:
"They devised plans that they could not fulfill."
Psalms 20:12.
And again:
"He thwarts the plans of the crafty, so that their hands achieve no success."
Job 5:12.
What this person adds, saying that the devil and all evildoers desire nothing but to sin and act wickedly, thereby distancing themselves from God, who is the supreme essence, is clearly true. By sinning and acting wickedly, they distance themselves from God and perish. As it is written:
"Those who are far from you will perish."
Psalms 73:27.
And what this person further adds, saying that the wicked desire of both the devil and wicked humans is so inclined and eager towards evil that if divine power permitted them, they would immerse themselves in sins to such an extent that even their very nature could be destroyed, is indeed exaggerated but perhaps not entirely false.
Similarly, he adds that because of the difficulty and impossibility imposed on them by divine power and providence, they do not fall into as deep an abyss of wickedness as they desire.
In their minds - both in the minds of evil spirits and very wicked people - there is an effort to try and a torment of repeatedly thinking about what they cannot achieve.
This effort indeed becomes a torment, a punishment, a torture for their minds, so that they are tortured and punished by their very own evil will.
He further adds that from this internal torment and punishment of the mind, while they cannot fulfill their desires because God opposes them, the soul becomes miserable, enduring the lack of their empty pleasures.
It is true that this perverse desire of the mind, whether fulfilled or not, makes the mind miserable.
But the mind is much more miserable when it is permitted to do such things than when it is prevented from them by divine power.
It is more unfortunate to be able to do evil than just to want to and not be able to.
Hence, the saying of the secular philosopher about someone is true: "O miserable one, who was allowed to sin!" Indeed, he who said this spoke the truth, because if the one about whom this was said were prevented from sinning, he would certainly be less miserable with just the will to sin. But when he was allowed to sin, with the most unfortunate permission, he was much more miserable both in the desire for evil and in the affection.
The reason why this person explains and reiterates everything he has mentioned is clarified at the end.
He says that the difficulty and impossibility faced by wicked angels or humans, due to God's opposition, will only occur in the eternal damnation of punitive destruction and the torment of their unjust desires.
They will suffer this torment in their minds because they will no longer be able to fulfill their perverse desires, nor will any external punishment from eternal fire be applied to them.
This, he says, is a manifest lie, contrary to faith and truth, as has been frequently shown before.
He then adds that the wicked serve God unwillingly: not the nature that God created in them, which He does not punish, but the evil will, which He did not create in them and which He does punish.
Therefore, they are punished by their own evil will, from which He justly does not free them, and in a way, He allows them to prepare for this punishment themselves.
His intention is similar in these words.
He says that all the wicked, both evil angels and humans, in their subjection to God's power and judgment, will unwillingly serve the divine disposition.
According to his understanding, they will be unwillingly subjected to God not by the nature that God created in them, which He never punishes, but by the evil will, which He did not create in them and which He alone punishes.
From the fact that they serve divine judgment unwillingly, they are punished not by external torment, but internally in their own will.
Their will becomes their punishment as it desires to be wickedly free but is restrained from that perverse freedom by divine power.
Therefore, he says, the only punishment of wicked angels and humans is that in desiring but failing to obtain the freedom of wickedness, they are tormented by their own will alone.
The nature by which they exist in spirit or body is created by God, and therefore, it never sins, is never punished, and never suffers any torment.
Regarding all these matters, as the Lord has provided, we have already responded sufficiently above.
Here, we raise only one point for everyone to consider, indeed even to condemn: how he claims, against human understanding and apostolic truth, that nature does not sin, but only the will of nature.
For who among humans has ever said that when someone commits adultery, gluttony, or drunkenness, only the will sins in that person, and neither the soul nor the body sins?
On the contrary, according to the truth of the Catholic faith, all souls with their bodies must be brought to the judgment of Almighty God, so that just as they have sinned in both and through both, they may be judged and punished in both.
For if the nature of the bodies of the wicked is entirely free from sins, what need is there for it to rise again, since it deserves no condemnation?
Or how will it justly be condemned with its soul, if it had no partnership in sinning, and incurred no merit of sin?
If this were so, it would be sufficient for only the soul to be presented at judgment, and for the evil will, since it inhabits it, which he says alone sins, to be punished in it.
Thus, such an assertion of impiety not only attacks the faith of the truth but also the faith of the resurrection.
The Apostle says: Therefore do not let sin reign in your mortal body, so that you obey its desires.
Neither present your members to sin as instruments of unrighteousness; but present yourselves to God as those alive from the dead, and your members as instruments of righteousness to God.
Romans 6:12, 13.
So, according to the Apostle of Christ, if sin reigns in our mortal body, and it holds its power there when we obey its desires, causing our actions to become tools of wickedness for sin, which then overpowers and harms our soul, how does the body not sin, nor the sin pertain to it, in which the kingdom of sin dwells and the army of sin operates?
Chapter Nineteen
In the nineteenth, and final, chapter, it says:
This eternal fire is the fourth element of the world, where the bodies of the saints will be transformed into an ethereal state, and the bodies of the wicked into an airy state.
In this transformation, there will be great joy for the natures themselves, but unspeakable torment for evil wills.
The bodies of all the wicked angels and humans will suffer the punishments of eternal fire.
Their substance will not perish, their beauty will not fade, and their natural health will remain.
All the good qualities of nature will shine forth in a marvelous order for the adornment of the universe, except for the blessedness which they will be deprived of.
With the higher corporeal fire contending with the bodies of the lower air, the natural force preserved, the unhappy souls will suffer eternal hardships from their own bodies.
This same fire will be glory for all bodies, but for the damned souls, it will be filled with punishment both internally by their own wickedness and externally by the fire.
In these fantastical words, full of every madness and delirium, the simplicity of faith and apostolic confession is omitted.
The whole Church believes and confesses that our Lord Jesus Christ rose from the dead on the third day, ascended to heaven, sits at the right hand of the Father, and will come from there to judge the living and the dead.
At his coming, there will be the resurrection of the flesh and the granting of eternal life to the saints.
This simplest and purest confession of piety is omitted, never mentioning Christ's coming from heaven, never recalling the resurrection from the dead.
Everything is confused and obscured with certain inventions, making it hard to recognize any truth of the resurrection, divine judgment, eternal punishment, or the future life of the saints in his writings.
He says that in the eternal fire, which he considers to be the fourth element of the world, located naturally above the earth, waters, and air, the bodies of the saints will be transformed into an ethereal quality.
Even the bodies of the wicked will transition to an airy quality.
This view clearly contradicts the apostolic doctrine, which states that the resurrection and transformation of the saints will not occur in the fourth element of the world, nor in some fiery furnace, but in this earthly dwelling place, where both the just and the unjust lived and died.
This miraculous and ineffable transformation will happen with incredible speed, as the Apostle himself says, in a moment, in the blink of an eye, which is indeed the fastest of all bodily movements.
He states: "We will all rise, but not all of us will be transformed. In a moment, in the blink of an eye, at the last trumpet: for the trumpet will sound, and the dead will rise incorruptible, and we will be transformed" First Corinthians 15:51-52. These words clearly describe the general resurrection of all.
However, he specifies this general resurrection when he says that we will all rise, but not all of us will be transformed. When he adds: "And the dead will rise incorruptible, and we will be transformed," he shows that all will rise with their bodies, but not all will be transformed with the glorification of the just. The wicked will rise incorruptible in the sense that they will no longer be able to die; however, they will be entirely capable of feeling and enduring eternal punishments and tortures. As the Scripture says, fire and worms will be given into their flesh to burn and torment them forever Judith 16:21.
The righteous, on whose behalf the Apostle speaks, will be changed and rise incorruptible, no longer subject to death.
They will have the special privilege of their bodies being transformed for the better, as the Apostle explains:
"For this perishable body must put on imperishability, and this mortal body must put on immortality"
First Corinthians 15:53.
This means that the same body, now perishable and mortal in the saints, will become imperishable and immortal by the power of the resurrection. It will be clothed with incorruption and immortality.
The incorruptibility of the saints will be so great that they will no longer experience pain, labor, trouble, or need.
Through the immortality granted to them, death will be swallowed up in their bodies. Not only will death be eradicated, but the cause of death, the sting of sin, will be utterly destroyed.
However, the sting of sin will never be eliminated in the bodies of the damned, so they will never truly be free from death.
Regarding this blessed transformation of the righteous, the Apostle says:
"When this perishable body puts on imperishability, and this mortal body puts on immortality, then the saying that is written will be fulfilled: 'Death has been swallowed up in victory. Where, O death, is your victory? Where, O death, is your sting?'"
First Corinthians 15:54-55.
Regarding the transformation of the wicked and the eternal punishments of the damned, whose bodies, according to this person, will be changed into an airy quality in a new and unheard-of kind of error, the Apostle says nothing at all.
Therefore, we should rather disdain such a fantasy than listen to it, lest we become itching ears and turn away from the truth to myths.
How, according to him, will they change into an airy quality?
For if they become airy from earthly, it will not be a true resurrection, because the same bodies will not arise that fell through death; those were earthly, these will be airy.
But if the nature of earthly bodies remains, and yet they take on the quality of air, being changed by the subtlety of the air and winds, the faith of the Church does not accept this novelty.
As already mentioned, the Apostle says nothing about the transformation of the wicked.
But what he says about the bodies of the saints being changed into an ethereal quality, if he believes this change will occur while their nature remains, so that the same bodies that fell in death and were raised in resurrection will be glorified with heavenly brightness and become luminous from being obscure, it is enough for us to hold to this wondrous clarification of theirs.
As the Lord says about them: "Then the righteous will shine like the sun in the kingdom of their Father" (Matthew 13:43).
But if he says the same bodies will be changed into an ethereal quality so that they lose their nature and become heavenly instead of earthly, he clearly contradicts the truth of the resurrection and is therefore not to be listened to at all.
Anyone who desires to simply, purely, and truly understand the resurrection of the saints and the nature of spiritual bodies should listen to and faithfully hold what the blessed Augustine sincerely teaches about these matters, saying:
He adds and says: "And in this wonderful joy of natures within themselves will be perfected, but the ineffable torment of evil wills; that is, to speak according to his sense, the wonderful joy of natures will be perfected there only, which according to him have not sinned at all."
The joy of nature lies in the belief that the earthly body will change: for the wicked, it will take on an airy quality, while for the holy, it will ascend to an even higher glory, an ethereal quality.
The wicked will face indescribable torment from their own bad conscience.
This idea has already been proven to be vain and false.
He further adds:
The bodies of all the wicked, both angels and humans, will suffer the punishment of eternal fire.
Their substance will not perish, their beauty will not diminish, and their natural integrity will remain intact, showcasing the good qualities of nature for the adornment of the universe, except for the happiness they will be deprived of.
It is surprising that he says: The bodies of all the wicked, both angels and humans, will undergo the punishment of eternal fire, which he previously denied repeatedly.
In this instance, he either falsely confessed this, being deceitful to God by lying about his faith while presenting truth with his mouth, as it is written:
"You will destroy all who speak falsehood: the Lord abhors the bloodthirsty and deceitful man" (Psalms 5:6-7).
Or if he confessed this truthfully out of fear of offending the Church to avoid being judged as faithless, the confession is empty and worthless due to his prior multiple denials.
For us, it is not permissible to say one thing now and another later in matters of faith:
What the Church received from the Lord and his apostles must be believed and confessed;
so that we may hold it with unchangeable truth, as the Lord commanded, saying:
"Let your statement be, 'Yes, yes; No, no'" (Matthew 5:37);
so that our truth may be confirmed by unchanging truth and falsehood rejected by our confession.
And yet, he reveals how strongly he believes in the torments of eternal fire in what follows.
After stating that the bodies of impious angels and humans will endure the torments of eternal fire, to clarify his belief, he immediately added:
This will happen in such a way that their substance, that is, the substance of the angels and wicked humans, will in no way perish, so that beauty will by no means be lacking to them, and their natural intactness will remain in them.
Behold what good he attributes to them in the torments of eternal fire, namely the integrity of nature, beauty, and intactness: so that they have the integrity of their nature, because their whole nature in soul and body will remain perpetually.
But let each faithful person consider where or how they might have beauty, for beauty is either of the soul or the body.
But which of the faithful would believe that there could be any beauty of souls there, where there will be the loss of all virtues and the filth of all vices?
For a soul is either beautiful by virtue or deformed by vice.
But what beauty of bodies could there be, where it will be obscured and darkened by the eternal horror of sadness, the eternal burning of fire, and the eternal tearing of worms?
What natural intactness could there be in those damned angels and humans, as he says, since their nature is preserved intact for them only for this purpose, and never separated from its natural frame, so that it may be fully tormented without end.
But he, not content with such foolishness and absurdity of his corrupted mind, adds at the end a most blatant error of heretical impiety, so that what he harbored in his heart against the truth and for the subversion of listeners, he also spewed out with his mouth.
He immediately adds about the similar natures of demons and condemned humans that afterwards that is, after those eternal fire punishments they will shine with all the good things of nature in a marvelous order.
They will be endowed and illuminated in their souls with the natural gifts of memory, intelligence, and free will; and in their bodies, they will shine and excel with the liveliness of the five natural senses and the beauty of perfect form.
He also says that they will be exempt from punishments and adorned with all natural goods so that they may enhance the adornment of the universe, shining with great beauty.
Among other earthly and heavenly creatures, they will remain as ornaments of the world, who were once in damnation.
And after this, lest it should seem entirely against the faith of the Church and the evangelical and apostolic truth, he added, except for the blessedness from which they will be deprived.
That is, they will shine with all the natural goods, demons and humans freed from punishments, except for the blessedness of the vision of God, which alone will be denied to them, so it may seem nothing good is lacking for them.
Behold what a man dares to think, to say, and even to write, who wants to appear Christian and strives for nothing else but to oppose Christian truth and to introduce the doctrines of heretics, with whom he is unfortunately united, into the purity of the Church.
For the Church of Christ denies and detests both, because both are heretical and entirely contrary to the truth.
That is, both the liberation of demons and humans from those eternal punishments and the existence of some intermediate place where those same demons and humans are in rest and abundance of all goods and clarity, neither in the damnation of eternal fire with the devil, nor in blessedness with God.
And it firmly holds that after that universal judgment, no one can be except either in eternal blessedness or, conversely, in perpetual misery.
For those who have been sent to either punishment or the joy of eternal life in that judgment, they will never be able to be elsewhere or different.
As the Lord clearly shows about both sides: the condemned, who will be on the left, and the blessed, who will be on the right, delivering an irreversible sentence when he says, "Then these will go away into eternal punishment, but the righteous into eternal life" (Matthew 25:46).
If there will ever be an end to that eternal punishment, there will also (God forbid) be an end to eternal life.
But if eternal life will never end, without a doubt, that punishment, that is, eternal torment, can never end either.
Therefore, there will not be some, as this person imagines, placed in the middle so that they are neither blessed nor miserable, and yet have some rest outside the Father's house.
For the Lord clearly says, "In my Father's house are many mansions" (John 14:2), showing that outside his Father's house, that is, outside the community of holy angels and chosen humans, which he inhabits forever, there is no place, no mansions of rest.
For all that multitude and diversity of mansions is only in the Father's house, where just as in one heaven one star differs from another in brightness, so in one and the same house there will be a diversity of mansions according to the diversity of merits.
After this, he adds and says, "With the quality of the higher fiery bodies contending with the bodies of the lower air, the intention of the unhappy souls to endure eternal sufferings from their bodies is naturally preserved."
Here is how he believes, if indeed he believes, that the eternal fire will be executed: He thinks this fire, which is the higher element, will affect the bodies of demons, which he believes are airy, and the bodies of wicked people, which he previously said would turn airy as well.
Now he explicitly states they are airy, just like the demons' bodies.
The nature of both elements-fire (which he believes to be the eternal fire in the punishment of the damned) and air (which he believes to be in the bodies of demons and lost people)-will clash in that prison of damnation.
This causes the unfortunate souls of both humans and demons to suffer eternal punishments from their airy bodies.
This is because these two elements, fire and air, will retain their natural force even in that furnace of eternal fire.
Just as in this world, the higher fire's heat, through the sun's warmth, makes the lower air vaporize and boil, affecting our bodies with its vapor and heat; so, in that furnace of eternal punishment, the fire naturally inflames the airy bodies of demons and humans, causing the souls within them to endure eternal afflictions from the heat and burning of their own bodies.
Now, let him who feels and writes this explain how the unfortunate souls of both angelic and human creatures will ever be rescued from those punishments and, as he says, shine with all the goods of nature if their airy bodies will suffer eternal punishments from the fire's force.
For if they are freed from those punishments, they will certainly be free from afflictions; but if they are in eternal afflictions, they will never deserve liberation.
However, this person, explaining further how he thinks this punishment, so fictional and painstakingly crafted, will be, adds: Thus, evidently, this same fire will become glory for all bodies, while for the damned souls it will be filled with punishment from within by their own wickedness and from without by the fire.
These words seem to assert that the same eternal fire torments the souls of the damned both internally through their guilty conscience and externally by inflaming and heating their bodies, thereby increasing their punishment.
This means they are tortured not only internally by their conscience but also externally by fiery punishment.
However, the same fire imparts a certain glory to their bodies made of air.
We believe that just as this fire, which shines in the stars, illuminates the dark nature of this air with its glow-naturally dark unless lit by the rays of the sun by day or the moon and stars by night-so this person thinks that the bodies of demons and humans made of air will be enlightened and glorified by the radiance of that eternal fire, just as the blackness of iron is turned into brightness by the heat of the furnace.
So how could he have said earlier that the airy bodies of angels and humans will undergo the punishment of eternal fire?
If that eternal fire is punishment for them, it certainly will not be glory; if it is glory for them, it will not be punishment.
Therefore, rejecting and pushing away such tortuous and serpentine twists and laborious and pernicious windings, let us hold onto the simplicity of faith: believing that the true bodies of the damned humans, that is, earthly bodies, will endure true and eternal punishments for those who will suffer that damnation.
Because the truest Word of Truth says in the Gospel, "For the hour is coming when all who are in the graves will hear the voice of the Son of God: and those who have done good will come forth to the resurrection of life; and those who have done evil, to the resurrection of judgment" (John 5:28-29).
At the voice of the Son of God, all who are in the graves will come forth: they will receive the same bodies that were placed in the graves, and they will rise in those same bodies, having either the resurrection of life or the resurrection of judgment; so that they will either possess eternal life in those bodies or suffer eternal death in them.
It's essential for us, and absolutely necessary for our salvation, to be grounded in the truth and simplicity of faith.
We should fear and, with the Lord's help, avoid the evil that the Apostle warns the Church, betrothed to Christ and endowed with the virginity of pure faith, to fear.
He says: "For I betrothed you to one man to present you as a pure virgin to Christ. But I fear that just as the serpent deceived Eve with his cunning, your minds may be corrupted and fall away from the simplicity that is in Christ." (Second Corinthians 11:23).
Therefore, he also warns elsewhere, saying: "Avoid foolish and old wives' tales." (First Timothy 4:7).
And again: "Avoid profane and idle chatter, for it will lead to more ungodliness, and their talk will spread like gangrene." (Second Timothy 2:17).
In the same spirit and concern, the blessed Apostle Peter also admonishes the faithful, saying: "Therefore, dear friends, since you have been forewarned, be on your guard so that you may not be carried away by the error of lawless men and fall from your secure position. But grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ." (Second Peter 3:17-18).
Let these not become for us like jokes and play, because even the Apostle calls Ishmael's play with Isaac persecution.
And so, wherever we recognize such things, we should be stirred by zeal for the faith against them, being guided and helped by the one who says in the psalm: "Zeal for your house consumes me." (Psalm 69:10); and who also, making a whip out of cords, drove out the violators of God's house with their wares, because they had made the same house of his Father a den of thieves.
(John 2:15).
Truly, they turn the house of the Lord, which is the Church of the living God, the pillar and foundation of the truth (First Timothy 3:15) into a den of thieves, and truly, they are thieves who, under the pretense of the Christian name, try to hide their infidelity and with deceitful and malicious arguments lay traps for the lives of the faithful.
And because this man, whose words we have responded to with the Lord's help using philosophical rules and syllogistic arguments, boasts, let us listen faithfully and obediently to the most blessed bishop and confessor of Christ, Hilary, as he reproves such men and says:
Likewise, the same glorious confessor, when he was explaining the words of the Apostle, who says:
"See to it that no one takes you captive through philosophy and empty deceit, according to human tradition, according to the elemental spirits of the world, and not according to Christ."
These are the words of the blessed Hilary.
But let us hear our Lord Himself, both terrifyingly and sweetly threatening and promising in the Apocalypse, about how much punishment and damnation await not only the authors but also the supporters of lies, and with what pious intention one should withdraw from such people, so that each of the faithful, cleansed and pure in faith, may deserve to have a share in the tree of life:
"The one who conquers will inherit these things, and I will be his God and he will be my son. But for the cowardly and the faithless, the detestable, and all liars, their portion will be in the lake that burns with fire and sulfur, which is the second death" Revelation 21:7-8.
And again:
"Its gates will never be shut by day-and there will be no night there. They will bring into it the glory and the honor of the nations. But nothing unclean will ever enter it, nor anyone who does what is detestable or false, but only those who are written in the Lamb's book of life" Revelation 21:25-27.
"Blessed are those who wash their robes, so that they may have the right to the tree of life and may enter the city by the gates. Outside are the dogs and sorcerers and the sexually immoral and murderers and idolaters, and everyone who loves and practices falsehood. I, Jesus, have sent my angel to testify to you about these things for the churches" Revelation 22:14-16.