Four Epistles
by Remigius of Reims
Epistle One
Letter to Chlovis, King of the Franks: A Consolation on the Death of His Sister Albofledis, Who Departed This Life Not Long After Receiving Baptism.
To the illustrious Lord Chlovis, King, from Remigius, the bishop.
It deeply troubles me to hear of your sorrow regarding the death of your sister Albofledis, of blessed memory.
But we can find solace in knowing she left this world in a manner that calls for remembrance rather than mourning.
Her life was such that we believe she was chosen by God and taken to heaven.
She continues to live in your faith, even though she is no longer with you physically.
Christ fulfilled His promise, and she received the blessing of virginity.
She should not be mourned, for she has been consecrated and now shines before the Lord with the purity of virginity.
Indeed, she is crowned with the reward of her virtue.
Let the faithful not mourn her, for she has earned the sweet fragrance of Christ.
Through Him, who is pleased with her, she can offer help to those who seek it.
My Lord, remove sadness from your heart: with a well-composed mind, govern the kingdom more wisely, and take up higher counsels with a serene spirit.
Strengthen your body with a joyful heart: by dispelling the numbness of grief, you will be more vigilant over your safety.
You have a kingdom to administer, and it must be governed under God's guidance.
As the head of the people, you bear the responsibility of leadership.
Do not let those who have come to see happiness through you find you overwhelmed by grief.
Be your own soul's comforter, maintaining the vigor of your wisdom, so that sadness does not cloud your mind.
Regarding her departure, I believe she is now joined with the choirs of virgins and the King rejoices in heaven.
Greeting your glory, I commend to you my close friend, the priest Maccolus, whom I have sent.
I ask you to forgive me for sending these words of encouragement instead of coming in person, as I should.
However, if you command, despite the harshness of winter, I will strive to come to you with the Lord's help, ignoring the cold and overcoming the toil of the journey.
We have received great news that you have undertaken another military campaign.
It is not surprising that you are becoming like your ancestors always were.
First and foremost, ensure that the Lord's judgment remains with you.
Your humble diligence has earned you the highest merit.
As the saying goes, a man's deeds are judged by their outcome.
Seek advisors who can enhance your reputation.
Your kindness should be pure and honorable, and you must show respect to your priests and always seek their counsel.
Working well with them will help stabilize your province.
Uplift your citizens, help the afflicted, support widows, and nurture orphans.
Educate them so that everyone loves and respects you.
Justice should come from your mouth: do not take advantage of the poor or foreigners, nor desire gifts or anything from them.
Your court should be open to all, so that no one leaves saddened.
Use the wealth you have inherited from your father to free captives and release them from servitude.
If someone comes before you, they should not feel like a stranger.
Play with the young, converse with the old, if you want to reign nobly and be judged favorably.
Epistle Three
TO THREE BISHOPS.
About the priest Claudius, in whose case he complains that he has been disregarded by them.
To my truly holy and most blessed brothers in Christ, Heraclius, Leo, and Theodosius, from Bishop Remigius.
Paul the Apostle says in his letter: "Love never fails" (First Corinthians 13:8).
This did not seem to settle in your minds, as shown by the letters you sent me.
I offered a simple prayer for Claudius, whom you claim is not a priest, to express your indignation towards me.
While I do not deny that he has seriously erred, it would have been fitting for you to respect my age, if not my merits.
By the grace of God, I have presided over the episcopal seat for 53 years, and no one has ever addressed me so boldly.
You say it would have been better if you had not been born.
This would have been convenient for me, to avoid hearing the reproach of a transgressor.
I made Claudius a priest, not corrupted by a bribe, but by the testimony of an excellent king, who was not only a preacher of the Catholic faith but also a defender.
You write that what he commanded was not canonical.
You hold the highest priesthood.
A leader of regions, a guardian of the homeland, a conqueror of nations imposed it.
You have shown such bile towards me that you did not even show respect to the author of your episcopacy.
I asked that Claudius, the perpetrator of sacrilege, be kept in repentance.
We read in Jonah 3:5-10 that the Ninevites, through repentance, escaped the destruction foretold by a heavenly warning.
John, the precursor of the Lord, preached in the Gospel (Matthew 3:2) that as the kingdom of heaven approached, the people should repent lest they perish.
In the Apocalypse (Revelation 2:5 and following), it is written to the angels of the churches by the command of the Lord and Savior, that they should correct what they had done less worthily through the satisfaction of repentance.
From the angry words of your holiness, I understand that you do not pity a fallen man after his ruin.
But I see you rather wish that he not be converted and live, when the Lord has said: "I do not desire the death of the dying, but that he turn and live" (Ezekiel 33:11).
This is what we should follow.
This is the Lord's will that we should not ignore, but hold on to:
He has placed us not for wrath, but for the care of people, to serve kindness rather than anger.
In your letter, you mention that a certain Celsus, who believed in Claudius, was taken away.
You do not know whether he is alive or dead, and you ask me to investigate this.
You are unsure if he should be searched for in this world or in the underworld.
You want me to return his belongings, which I do not know were taken away.
You order the impossible, so that you may commit impiety.
You write that I am fifty years old, mocking rather than rejoicing out of love.
You insincerely neither spare me nor show respect after breaking the bond of charity.
Epistle Four
TO FALCO, BISHOP OF TONGEREN
He accuses him of usurping jurisdiction in the Church of Mosomagum against the rights of the Church of Reims.
To my truly holy and most blessed brother in Christ, Bishop Falco, from Bishop Remigius.
From what I have learned and confirmed by events, it seems that you found it more important to insult me than to offer a greeting.
What a fitting beginning you gave-wounding me as a bishop before I even saw you as one!
You flew too quickly with tender wings and a lighthearted spirit, not with mature counsel.
At the very start of your episcopate, you attempted to enter a foreign jurisdiction when you should have entered your own with modesty.
Was it right for you to believe that the Church of Mosomagum, which the metropolitan of the city of Reims has always governed with Christ's help, could be taken over by your illicit ordinations?
I still think you do not know your own place, yet you invade others'.
With such lightness, you have consecrated priests, appointed archdeacons, and established the head of the esteemed school and the militia of readers;
I do not complain that you did not seek my counsel in these matters, but I wish you had at least consulted yourself!
If your holiness was ignorant of the canons, it was quite premature to transgress before learning them.
But if you knew the statutes of the churches, it is even more serious and perilous that your folly trampled on the decrees of the ancient and great bishops.
Beware, lest by presuming on others' rights, you lose what you seem to have.
Since the ordinations you performed are not valid, with what counsel will you defend the beginnings of the priestly office, if you mix the offense of rash transgression with stubbornness or impotence?
It will be a greater danger to have violated ancient sanctions than to be praised for standing against the canons you created.
But why should I speak of the orders of those promoted by your blessedness?
More importantly, if we examine it according to the statutes and severity of the elders, your episcopate will come into question no less than their status.
The Lord says in the Gospel to Peter: "Simon, son of John, do you love me?" and Peter replies: "Yes, Lord, you know that I love you" John 21:15. To which the Lord commands again and again: "Feed my sheep."
Because I am not skilled in feeding Christ's sheep, I cannot provide them with abundant heavenly nourishment. I, who have been instructed by holy teachings, remind you to feed those entrusted to me by Christ's command, and to refrain from overstepping. Always act in a way that is worthy of you. Serve the Church, which you have been deemed worthy to oversee by divine dispensation, and as a concerned shepherd, watch over the safety of the Lord's flock.
If only my modest abilities could provide what I wish you to have in the name of the Lord! But because I lack these abilities, or because the services entrusted to me are the Savior's, I do not seek to be saved as a hireling.
In the Revelation of John (Chapters 2 and 3), he addresses his seven angels and writes to each Church.
Therefore, he corrects and chastises the deeds and merits of the leaders.
Since the form of pontifical action is conveyed under the title of angel, I grieve over the audacity of your presumption to change old laws as a new one, being reckless with caution, and treating earthly matters as divine.
Let those whom you have chosen as priests listen to us.
Let your priests themselves listen to us.
I trust the Creator's judgment will be pronounced not for you, but against you, by the judges.
For who, with integrity, would not disapprove of someone who has broken the rule of the Church, who ought to have preserved it?
You command, as I hear, that the tributes of the tenants be brought to you, and you order that the revenues of the fields be delivered.
It is understood that you coveted the property of the Church, not the Church itself, when as a diligent seeker, you demand what I have remitted to those to whom it rightfully belonged.
I do not want it to be hidden from you that the levity and priests you have appointed against the order are now removed from the order.
For I considered it inappropriate to admit those whom you had no right to ordain.
Alas, how much you have repelled me from the purpose of your worship, while you prefer to act wrongly than to keep fraternal bonds!
I had hoped you would stay a cleric, since you became one through the duty of a priest.
But even if this concern doesn't affect you, I sincerely declare that it pains my heart just as much that you've gone astray as it does that I have been disdained.