Adventius' book about Waldrada aims to prove that Waldrada, the mistress of Lothair, was married to him at a young age by his father, Emperor Lothair.
However, Theutberga, the legitimate wife, was later forced upon the unwilling king through threats.
(According to Baronius, in the year 862, number 29.)
The late Emperor Lothair, of blessed memory, was elected by the people of the Roman kingdom as emperor.
While governing the kingdom of the Franks, he decided to give his son, Lord Lothair, a noble virgin named Waldrada under the name of divine faith, so that he would keep and protect her in the faith of God in the future.
To make this union appear just, he gave one hundred estates to the young boy as a dowry, who was not yet of his own liberty, although he was to be the heir to his father.
But he remained under guardians and managers, as the Apostle speaks of such cases, saying:
Galatians 4:1-2,
"As long as the heir is a child, he is no different from a servant, though he is lord of all; but he is under guardians and managers until the time set by his father."
As long as the aforementioned emperor held the supremacy of the Frankish kingdom, the young boy adhered to the girl given to him by his father as a gift. This was done publicly, not secretly, because truth has no corners, in the presence of bishops and nobles, as his tutors and his uncle Leutfrid testify.
When Lord Emperor Lothair passed away, during the days of mourning, Hubert of Acefala and his accomplices brought his sister Theutberga to the young King Lothair and fraudulently united her with him, threatening the king's safety and the stability of his kingdom if he did not comply with their demands.
The king reluctantly agreed, as he himself testified.
A bad reputation of disgrace follows Theutberga, and she is accused of incestuous relations with her brother Hubert.
A written confession is brought forth, where her voluntary confession is read.
She is condemned by the judgment of the consuls, saved by the mercy of the bishops, and takes flight.
The pious King Lothar sent a message to Rome through distinguished men to inform them about this event and explain the reasons behind it.
The blessed Pope Nicholas, after understanding the situation, sent the esteemed Rodoald of Porto and John of Fidenza as envoys to France.
He decided to hold a general council in the city of Metz.
There, the glorious King Lothar attended with all his noble advisors and sat in the holy synod.
He presented the reasons for his actions in front of the envoys from Rome, explaining how his father, the highly esteemed and perpetual Augustus, Lord Lothar, had personally given a noble virgin and the other matters we mentioned earlier.
Theutberga publicly confessed her guilt in the council held in Metz, and all the senators of the Frankish kingdom agreed to proceed.
Their wisdom, both temporal and spiritual, shone through, following the tradition of their ancestors who guided the Roman Empire with counsel.
This lineage, during the times of the emperors Lord Louis and the magnificent Lothar, adorned with the title of consul, I have seen.
The entire populace acclaimed that their special advisory privilege should not be discarded, as they were not accused of any crimes but praised for their honesty and virtues.
Therefore, because many people have various opinions on these matters and propose different definitions, I will strive to clarify my thoughts and feelings on these matters for the reverence of the faithful.
When the pious emperor gave his son a noble girl, I was not yet burdened with the responsibilities of a bishop and did not participate in these events.
When Theutberga was introduced and the marriage was consummated, I was completely unaware except by hearsay.
With these matters discussed, sought by the clergy and elected by the people, I was canonically consecrated as bishop.
I understood it this way: The most Christian Emperor, in the faith of Christ and his own, gave a virgin to his son.
The faith of God does not give a harlot but rejects it, saying: "You shall not commit adultery" (Exodus 20).
And the Psalmist says: "You will destroy all who are unfaithful to you" (Psalm 73).
Paul, who was girded with the faith of God, exclaims, saying: "Understand this, that no fornicator, impure person, or covetous man, which is idolatry, has any inheritance in the kingdom of Christ and of God" (Ephesians 5).
He who bears the mark of Jesus in his body, which is the banner of faith, does not support adulterers but pierces them with the spear of sacred zeal, saying: "Neither shall adulterers inherit the kingdom of God" (First Corinthians 6).
The Lord, who is faithful and gives the holy promises of David and to the orthodox Emperor Lothair, did not take away the power to marry his son to any girl he had decided upon, says in the Gospel: "Whoever divorces his wife and marries another commits adultery" (Matthew 19).
Therefore, it is necessary for those who hear this to listen to and keep the paternal canons with pious and devoted zeal, because one should never transgress the boundaries of the Fathers.
For the sacred canons proclaim by paternal gift that a woman given is free from blame.
The Emperor, who was devoted to divine worship, did not permit his son, King Lothair, to engage in the detestable crime of fornication.
The profession of all the senators was such regarding the union with Waldrada, that his father had given her to him in the faith of God.
Regarding Theutberga, who confessed and was proven guilty of the evil of her crime due to the horrendous embrace of her shameless brother, they similarly protested entirely.
She was neither terrified by our fearful threats nor comforted by pleasant flattery.
He himself, according to the Apostle, did as he says: "If possible, as far as it depends on you, live at peace with everyone" (Romans 12).
When we listen to the voices of noble consuls, as we've noted through various examples over time, and hear the advice of the senators, which has been approved, we have decided on our subscriptions and definitions in this way:
If Theutperga had confessed to the aforementioned crime, I would judge her unworthy of royal society.
And if Waldrada had been joined to the king by the faith of God's gift through her father, I would not dare to blaspheme the faith of God, lest the Scripture pierce me with the spear of the word, saying: "Do not allow blasphemers to live" (Leviticus 24).
The Apostle gives permission so that each may abound in his own sense (Romans 14).