Against Greed Book Threeby Salvianus of Marseilles
In the previous two books, we discussed two distinct groups among your children: those who love the world and those who represent the image of religion, my lady, the Church of God.
In this book, if God wills it, we aim to address both groups as needed, sometimes speaking to each separately and other times addressing them together.
It is up to each group to recognize their parts as they read, and to receive what is said with the love of God.
Given that we have already emphasized the special virtues of all Christians—mercy and generosity—and proven with many suitable witnesses that these are the main merits of the saints and remedies for sinners, I believe no one expects more.
Especially since anyone seeking more should consult the books of God, which are filled with so many and great testimonies that the testimony of all heavenly scriptures is nearly unanimous.
Now, we need to address the reasons behind unfaithful responses, which some people use as a deadly excuse.
The Savior, speaking in the Gospel, says that wealth and money are given to people by the Lord so that they may be returned with multiple interests.
He tells the most greedy debtor: "Wicked and lazy servant, you knew that I reap where I have not sown, and gather where I have not scattered: you should have therefore put my money with the bankers, and at my coming, I should have received what was mine with interest. Take therefore the talent from him, and give it to him who has ten talents" (Matthew 25:26-27).
And a little later: "And cast the unprofitable servant into outer darkness: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth." Although this can refer to other things, it is appropriately adapted to this context and cause.
Since the moneylenders of the Savior are rightly understood to be the poor and needy, because the money given to such people increases; without a doubt, whatever is given to the needy is repaid to God with interest.
Hence, elsewhere the Lord himself more clearly commands the rich to distribute their wealth and make for themselves purses that do not wear out.
Luke twelve, thirty-three.
And in his chosen vessel, he indicates that riches are given by the Lord to the wealthy so that they may become rich in good works.
First Timothy six, eighteen to nineteen.
Therefore, even I, the least and most unworthy of God's servants, say that the foremost and most beneficial duty of religion is for a Christian rich person, while in this life, to spend the riches of this world for the name and honor of God; but secondly, if somehow prevented by fear, weakness, or some necessity, to at least distribute everything when dying.
But perhaps he says: I have children.
Indeed, the main page of the booklet and its contents, as I think, have already mentioned not a little about this, and the Lord's word is sufficient, saying: Whoever loves son or daughter more than me is not worthy of me.
Matthew ten, thirty-seven.
But also the prophetic saying that neither fathers for the children, nor the children for the parents should be judged, but each person will be saved by their own righteousness or perish by their own iniquity.
Ezekiel eighteen, twenty.
And therefore, whatever riches a person heaps up for their children, it will not benefit them in judgment that they left a rich heir.
But let it be, parents can be forgiven if they leave some hereditary assets to their children, as long as it is to good, as long as it is to holy.
Let it also be, they can be forgiven if they leave something even to the bad and wicked.
They seem to have some appearance of an excuse saying: Piety conquered, the force of blood compelled, nature itself as if by the hand of love drew to its right: we knew what God's justice required, what sacred truth demanded; but we confess, we were subdued by the yoke of incarnate kinship, and we gave captive hands to the bonds of love: faith yielded to blood, and the laws of piety overcame the devotion of religion.
Something can be said, even though it cannot be said beneficially: it is the shadow of an excuse that does not excuse, giving the appearance of a plea to the accused, but not the security of innocence.
For I do not promise anyone that anything can provide firm support for any matter if they have loved anything more than God, according to what is written, John 3:19: "This is the verdict: Light has come into the world, but people loved darkness instead of light."
There is no doubt that whatever is placed before divine love will be darkness for that person. So, this is how it is.
But let it be, as I said, that parents can be indulged even if they indulge unhealthily. What about those who do not have children, but still completely turn away from the prospect of their own salvation and the remedy for their sins? And although they lack their own biological offspring, they still seek others to whom they can dedicate their wealth, that is, to whom they can assign some shadowy name of kinship, making them their imaginary adopted children, and thus, through deceit, replace the pledges they lack.
The most miserable and impious, though not bound by the ties of children, create for themselves bonds that bind the unhappy necks of their souls. Although there is no domestic strife, they seek conflict outside; and although there are no grounds for danger, they still rush into voluntary destruction. These most unfortunate errors, whether they should be received with anger or sorrow, can seem almost uncertain to some.
For error is worthy of sorrow, impiety of detestation. We are drawn to tears by misfortune, and to anger by faithlessness.
In one way, we mourn for human foolishness; in another, we are moved by the love of God.
There is no doubt that no person, standing on the brink of death and facing the tribunal of God, would think of anything other than their own end, their own exit, and their own danger.
Yet, instead of focusing on their own hope and soul, which they ought to nurture with all effort and resources, they only think about how lavishly their heir will consume their possessions!
Most miserable of all, why are you anxious, why do you fret, why do you concern yourself with things that will perish?
Are you afraid that no one will be there to devour what you leave behind after your death?
Do not fear, do not worry.
If only saving your soul were as easy as your possessions perishing!
Oh disbelief, oh perversity!
It is often said that everyone wishes better for themselves than for others.
But this is a new kind of monstrosity: to wish well for anyone else but not for oneself.
Behold, most unfortunate of all, you are heading to the sacred examination, to that dreadful and intolerable judgment, where for the wandering and anxious soul, there can be no comfort except a good conscience and an innocent life, or at least mercy.
For the guilty person, there is no help except a generous mind, fruitful repentance, and abundant alms as if strong hands.
Finally, depending on the diversity of merits, you will find either the highest good or the highest evil, either an immortal reward or endless torment.
And yet, you think about enriching your heirs, sigh over the wealth of your relatives, whom you will make richer with your inheritance, to whom you will transfer your possessions, and whose storerooms you will fill.
Most unfortunate of all, you think about how well others will live after you, not about how badly you will die!
Tell me, please, you miserable, faithless person, when you divide your wealth among many, when you enrich many with your resources, have you treated yourself so badly that you don’t even secure a place for yourself among strangers as an heir?
Look, the duty of the sacred tribunal awaits you as you leave this life.
The torturing angels and the terrible ministers of immortal torments are waiting.
And you ponder the future pleasures of your worldly heirs.
You dwell on the delights of others, thinking about how your heir will dine well after you, with what abundance he will fill his stomach, and how he will gorge until he is sick!
Most unfortunate of all, what do you have to do with these trifles, these delusions, this foolishness, this ruinous vanity?
Can this help you at all in the midst of the greatest punishments?
If the one who lavishly consumed your possessions burps well after a fine meal, or if, after you gave everything to be devoured, he provides more relief to you with his overflowing indigestion if he vomits well?
But about these matters we are discussing now, if the situation and reason require, we will add more later.
In the meantime, I say this particularly and remind you with a special admonition, that no one at all, no matter how dear, should be preferred over their own soul.
For it is not unfair that any Christian gathers less in this world even for legitimate heirs, as long as they help themselves in eternity in many ways.
Because it is easier for children to lack something here than for parents in the future, and present scarcity is much lighter than eternal poverty.
Especially because, in that place, not only poverty but also death and punishment are feared.
It is certainly easier for heirs to lack something from the inheritance here than for testators to lack salvation there.
And those to whom the inheritance is left, if they have any piety in them, should especially want those who leave it to them not to perish.
If they truly do not want it, they are much less worthy of receiving anything because a wise testator does not unjustly leave what an unworthy heir does not deserve.
Therefore, it is best for each person to look out for themselves and leave everything to their soul and salvation.
Although, sometimes it may not only be children to whom more is naturally owed, but also other dependents, whether by merit or condition, so that justice and the worship of God support them in sharing and giving.
It is right to leave something to them piously, but not to leave something impiously.
If the parents are in distress, the siblings are faithful, the spouses are holy, or, to extend the duty of piety further, if the relatives are poor, the in-laws are needy, or finally, any needy person, especially those who are dedicated to God.
This is the most important and outstanding thing: if someone acts out of a duty of piety with a feeling of religion.
Blessed is the one who loves their family with the spirit of divine love, whose charity is the worship of Christ, who considers God the father of all natures, and by turning the gifts of love into sacrifices, prepares for themselves so much immortal profit and blessed fruits, that by lending to their Lord what they provide to their dependents, they secure an eternal reward through temporary generosity to their family.
But now, very differently and impiously, less is left to their own family to whom more is due out of reverence for God, and piety considers less those whom religion especially commends.
Finally, if children are offered to God by their parents, those offered are postponed by all children; they are judged unworthy of inheritance because they were worthy of consecration; and because of this, they become of little value to their parents in only one thing: because they have begun to be precious to God.
From this, it can be understood that almost no one is considered more worthless among humans than God; whose neglect causes parents to especially despise those children who have begun to belong to God.
But indeed, those who do these things offer a compelling rationale for their plan, saying: Why is it necessary to leave an equal portion of the inheritance to children who are already religious?
Nothing is more just, nothing is more fitting, than since they have embraced a religious life, they should beg: not because this will oppress them with poverty, but because they have renounced earthly possessions and hold the hope of heaven, which they will soon possess in reality, with God leading and protecting them, rewarding them with sufficient temporal blessings and the immortal hope of eternal things.
Yet, as far as the inhumanity of parents is concerned, these children are left in need, having been made destitute by their parents.
Even if some are not entirely expelled from the home and are not completely cast out as if banned from water and fire, they are left with little or only as usufructuaries; they are left so far inferior to their brothers that even if they do not suffer from poverty, they seem needy by comparison.
You ask: Why do religious children need to receive an equal portion of the inheritance with their brothers?
I respond: So that they can perform their religious duties, so that religion can be enriched by their resources, so that they can give generously, so that everyone may benefit through them, even those who have nothing; indeed, if their faith and perfection are so great that they soon will have nothing, they will be more blessed after giving everything away.
Why, I ask, most inhumane parents, do you impose the necessity of such unworthy poverty on them?
Allow this decision to religion itself, to which you have entrusted your children: it is more fitting that they become poor by their own will.
If you so desire them to be destitute, grant this to their own devotion.
Allow them, we pray, the right to choose poverty: they ought to choose it willingly, not endure it unwillingly.
Finally, even if they endure it, let them bear it out of devotion, not suffer it as a condemnation.
Why do you cast them out as if from nature and renounce them as if from the right of blood?
I too wish them to be poor; but so that poverty itself may have its reward, and by a splendid exchange, they may choose poverty out of abundance, so that from the choice of poverty they may obtain abundance.
Why do I strive to draw you to humanity and piety through the duty of reason, when that often hinders, and this matter makes parents impious when it ought to make them more pious?
You should leave more of your inheritance to your religious children so that something from your wealth might reach God through them.
But instead, you do not leave it to your children, ensuring they have nothing to give to God.
Indeed, you seem to think that by not acknowledging your children, they will not recognize themselves as God's children; repaying sacred benefits with this exchange, while you ensure that nothing you have honors God, even though you have everything through His gift.
Why do you act so unfaithfully, so impiously?
We do not ask you to give your own to the Lord: return something to God from His own.
Why do you act so greedily, so impiously?
It is not yours that you are denying.
Do you think it unfair to make religious children equal in inheritance to secular children?
Do you act in a way that makes them regret the religion they chose, seeing them as worthless because of their faith?
Thus, the pious and good Lord, who maintains His purpose and profession in them.
However, as far as it depends on you, you act to make them worshippers of the world, favoring secular children over religious ones.
What else is it but to forbid religion, to hold it in contempt?
But perhaps it might seem unjust to accuse all parents equally in this matter, as not all act with the same injustice towards their children.
Indeed, someone might say, there are many parents who make equal portions for their children, except they distinguish them by one condition: for the parts assigned to religious children, they order the use to pertain to them, but the ownership to others.
This is much worse and more unfaithful.
It seems more tolerable to leave less with ownership to some children than to entirely take away ownership from them.
This situation might be somewhat tolerable if something under this rule were left to friends, in-laws, or relatives.
But when it comes to children, who are denied ownership, it leaves them with nothing.
The most egregious betrayal by parents has found a way to completely exclude God from their inheritance by denying property ownership to their religious children.
They allowed them to use the property to live by, but took away ownership so they would have nothing to leave to God.
Oh, the cunning of an irreligious mind!
It found a way to appear concerned for its children while showing even greater impiety toward God.
It allowed the religious offspring to use things without owning them, so they lived as if they were wealthy, but died as if they were beggars.
Thus, the most unfaithful parent could leave this world feeling secure, knowing that nothing of theirs would reach God.
Although, as I mentioned earlier, through the use of things, religious children might seem to have some semblance of wealth, it is not so.
For even if the use of something seems to hold value, the conscience does not.
No one can consider themselves wealthy, even briefly, who knows they own nothing of their own.
What are you doing, most miserable unfaithfulness and error of pagan irreligiosity, if I may say so?
Do you hate God so much that you cannot even love your children just because they belong to God?
Indeed, some leave their freedmen in a better condition than you leave your children.
In daily practice, it is customary for slaves, even if not highly regarded, to be granted Roman freedom by their masters.
This freedom allows them to own their savings and the right to make a will, so they can give their property to whomever they wish while alive and transfer it upon death.
Not only that, but the things they acquired while in servitude are not forbidden to be taken from the master's house.
Sometimes, the mistress's generosity even extends to retracting her own rights to grant ownership to the freedmen.
How much better, oh most unfaithful father, do those masters treat their freedmen compared to how you treat your children!
The things they give, they give forever; you give temporarily.
They grant their freedmen the privilege to make a will; you take it away from your children.
They ultimately grant freedom to their slaves, while you seem to bind your children to servitude.
For what else is it but binding them to servitude when you do not allow them to possess anything as if they were freeborn?
Therefore, you follow the custom of those who subject their undeserving slaves to the yoke of Latin liberty because they judge them unworthy of Roman citizenship.
They order these slaves to live under the title of freedmen, but they do not allow them to have anything when they die.
By denying them the right to make a final will, they cannot give away their possessions even after death.
In this way, you command your devout children to be like these Latin freedmen; they live seemingly free but die as slaves, bound by the law of their siblings.
Even if they appear to have their own will while alive, they die as if under their control.
What great crime do you think lies in the title of religion, so much so that you do not believe your religious children to be yours because they have become children of God?
In what way have they become guilty of a crime of good will, so that you think they should be considered worse for wanting to be better?
But you say you do this not with that intention: which is like someone saying they do evil things with good intentions and commit acts of impiety with a pious mind.
What good does it do, oh most inhumane parents, that you assert you dishonor your religious children with good intentions?
The matter itself rejects this; your actions contradict you.
Is it not enough that you say these things with bare assertions?
You are witnesses against yourselves by your actions.
Do you think it unworthy that your holy and God-pleasing children are compared to those serving the world?
It is true, and you judge well: However, if you were to use this judgment justly and differently; that is, not comparing bad children to good ones, sinners to saints, and recognizing those who excel in life and merits before God, they would also surpass in your grace and honor.
For what is more correct, what is more just than honoring those who are better; those who win in judgment should also win in reward; and those who stand out in the holy Gospel should also be recognized in human testament.
At the very least, the piety and will of parents should align with the will of Christ, that those whom God has chosen should also be honored by parents.
But not only is this not done, everything is done in the opposite way.
The defiled are preferred over the pure, the impious over the faithful, darkness over light, earth over heaven, the world over God: and do such parents think they will escape God's judgment, who trample on His worship and the dignity of their judgment?
But evidently, parents say they do these things not out of contempt for God, but with cause and reason.
To whom, they ask, would they leave their substance, having no children?
I will tell you to whom: And I will not name those I mentioned above, the poor of God, not strangers, or far-off people, lest it seem harsh or inhumane.
I speak of those dear and close ones, whom even you, who have many offspring, rightly prefer to your children.
I am speaking of yourselves, O most unfaithful parents, I am speaking of yourselves.
Can anything be closer to anyone than themselves, can anything dearer be found?
We commend each of you to your soul, your salvation, your hope.
And you say you are pious because you love your children?
Nothing can be said more harsh, nothing more inhumane, nothing so savage, nothing so impious than you, from whom it cannot be obtained that you love yourselves.
The devil says in the holy Scriptures, skin for skin, and all that a man has he will give for his life Job 2:4.
The devil himself did not deny that a man's soul is his most beloved possession.
Even though he strives to turn everyone away from caring about their souls, he still admits that souls should be cherished by everyone.
So what madness is it to consider your souls worthless when even the devil thinks they are precious?
What madness is it to consider them worthless when even the one who tries to make them worthless says they should be dear to you?
Therefore, whoever neglects their souls loves themselves even less than the devil does.
Given these points, consider this: you who think religious people have no one to whom they can leave their possessions.
Consider, even according to the devil's opinion, if they do not have possessions, they have themselves.
Suffice it to say, I believe what we've discussed so far adequately covers the matter at hand.
That is, you ought to prioritize your life, hope, and salvation above all other things and feelings.
But perhaps you want this shown not only through the virtues of things but also through authoritative examples.
I could indeed say that God's commands are greater than all examples, proclaiming daily throughout the world:
"Do not store up for yourselves treasures on earth, but store up for yourselves treasures in heaven"
(Matthew 6:19-20).
And elsewhere: "Whatever a man sows, that he will also reap"
(Galatians 6:7).
These apply equally to worldly people and to God's people, to those who have children and to those who do not, since everyone desires to possess eternal life.
There is no doubt that where there is a common desire to have something, there should be a common effort to achieve it.
It does not matter if people fulfill God's words or not, as their authority does not depend on human obedience but on the certainty of the Lord's presence.
Nothing can be added or taken away from them by us, as their honor remains constant through their divine Author.
But if human weakness seeks encouragement from the examples of others, to more easily do now what others have done before, we show in the first book that these deeds, done by some followers of Christ, are performed not sparingly, but abundantly; not by a few, but by many; not in ancient times, but quite recently.
What do the Acts of the Apostles, which are almost before our eyes, say?
All those who believed had everything in common.
(Acts 2:44)
And again: Great grace was upon them all, for there was no needy person among them.
For all who owned fields or houses sold them, brought the proceeds, and laid it at the apostles' feet.
(Acts 4:33-35)
Elsewhere too: And no one claimed that any of their possessions was their own.
(Acts 4:32)
And this involved no small number of believers, so that no one may be less moved by the authority of the scriptures, thinking these examples were of a few.
For the multitude of the early Church can be recognized from this alone: at the very beginning, eight thousand people were reported to have joined the Church in two days.
(Acts 2:41 and Acts 4:4)
And it is clear to estimate what a multitude of people of all kinds grew in the following days, when just two days, apart from different ages and sexes, produced such a great number of men.
Therefore, when there was already such an innumerable and perfect people, I ask you, all parents, among those many thousands of believers living in such perfection of faith, were they all with children or all without children?
Neither, I think.
For no Church congregation is not mixed with both.
Therefore, those Christians who do not have children can understand to whom they should leave their possessions, as did those who did not have children then.
But if they have it, let them learn what they should do when they see parents preferring the love of God's children over their own.
Every age and condition has something to follow.
Whoever shares in faith should also share in blessed examples.
If those people gave up all their possessions for God, even disinheriting themselves while alive, learn to at least inherit your own goods when dying.
As I said, even you, most unfaithful parents, should consider this carefully for your own sake.
You must, believe me, not forget about the salvation of your souls, even among your children.
It is certain that your close ties are your closest bonds.
But, believe me, no one is closer to you, no one more connected, than you yourselves.
So love your children, but in the second rank after yourselves: love them in such a way that you do not seem to hate yourself.
For unwise and foolish love is mindful of another and forgetful of oneself.
Sacred Scripture says, "The son will not bear the iniquity of the father" (Ezekiel 18:20).
And the Apostle says, "Each one shall bear his own load" (Galatians 6:5).
Therefore, the wealth left to children does not free parents from poverty: rather, excessive wealth left to children is the parents' eternal poverty.
Through this, no one is more harmful to parents than children who are loved too much.
While children are overflowing with their father's goods, parents are tormented in eternity.
Even if a son is so pious that he wishes to share the goods left to him with his father to cool his father's suffering, he will not be able to.
After death, a son's piety cannot repay what each person's lack of devotion and faithlessness has denied.
Therefore, according to the Apostle, each one should consider his own burdens, because each man will carry his own loads.
The flames of the unfortunate dead are not cooled by the wealth of their heirs.
The rich man in the Gospel who was clothed in purple and fine linen (Luke 16:19 and following).
Without a doubt, the man who had been wealthy for 265 years left his heirs enriched by his death.
But this did not benefit him at all.
His brothers, wealthy with his riches and talents, lived in abundance while he couldn't even get a drop of refreshment.
They had plenty, but he was in need.
They rejoiced, but he was in pain.
They enjoyed wealth, but he was tormented.
They perhaps lived in luxury, but he was always in flames.
Oh, what an unhappy and pitiable condition!
With his wealth, he prepared happiness for others but affliction for himself; joy for others but tears for himself; brief pleasure for others but eternal fire for himself.
Where were his relatives then?
Where were his kin?
Where were even his children, if he had any, or the brothers he remembered and loved so much that he did not forget them even in punishment?
What did they profit him?
What support did they offer?
The wretched man was tormented; and while others enjoyed his riches, he, burning, begged for a drop of refreshment but could not obtain it.
And, if anything could add to his punishment, he had to ask for it from the one he had once despised, the one who had rotted in filth and pus, the one whose stench and filth he had long fled from, who had fed dogs with the ulcers of his body, whom swarming masses of worms had even carved through the interior recesses of his decayed body.
Oh, what a grievous and lamentable condition!
The poor man bought happiness with his begging, the rich man punishment with his wealth.
The poor man, although he had nothing at all, bought eternal riches with his poverty.
Oh, how much more easily the rich man could have obtained these with his many possessions!
Burning amid torments and crying out amid punishments: "Father Abraham, have pity on me, and send Lazarus to dip the tip of his finger in water and cool my tongue, for I am in agony in this fire" (Luke 16:24).
Then, indeed, the rich man no longer shunned the hand of the once poor Lazarus, nor did he disdain his help.
He begged for that fetid and filthy hand to be placed in his mouth and for the intolerable flames of his throat to be soothed by the touch of that hand.
Oh, what a great change had happened!
He now desired to be touched by the one he had previously despised even seeing.
So, let the rich consider this: those who are unwilling to use their wealth to avoid such suffering.
The man we are speaking of was rich, and so are those we are addressing now.
They share the same name.
Let them beware not to share the same fate.
Rich children will not free their guilty parents, nor will an affluent heir extinguish the flames of a miserable testator with his abundant luxuries.
It’s hard to leave little to one’s children and relatives, but it’s much harder to be tormented for eternity.
I believe that rich man, when he was tormented, was not as pleased by his heir’s wealth as he was anguished by his own bodily torment.
He was not as pleased that his heir dined well as he was anguished that he himself was suffering terribly.
He was not as pleased that his heir lived in exquisite luxury as he was anguished that he was melting in unbearable fires.
He was not as pleased that his heir entertained parasites and gluttons with his wealth as he was anguished that he himself fed the flames with his own marrow.
And I think if someone had given him the choice then, whether he would rather his heirs be rich or he not be in misery and torment, he would have surely wished them to be deprived of all good things, provided he could be freed from all evil.
He would have wished to offer everything he possessed, provided he could escape what he endured.
He would have wished to give all the wealth he had and the temporary treasures of silver and gold to quench the eternal tortures and that perpetual fire, if somehow he could extinguish it with the mass of his riches, and stop the overflowing globes of fire with the immense wealth he had amassed.
And what do I say he wished, to redeem that endless evil with his wealth?
I say more.
He would have wished to give all his substance to gain for himself, in the flames, at least one hour of rest.
To soothe the flames in his throat, he would have gladly dipped even a poor man's finger in water.
How could he not have preferred to buy rest at any price when he asked for a small drop of refreshment with such great effort?
But what good were such things then?
How did they help the miserable man, who wanted to offer everything for himself at that point but had not wanted to do so when he was well?
Or what good was it then that he wished to give everything he had already lost, when he had given nothing for himself when he possessed everything?
Indeed, as the Holy Spirit says in the Scriptures, the repentance of the dead is too late.
How is this?
The divine word says to God the Father, "In death, there is no one who remembers you; in the grave, who will give you praise?" Psalm 6:6. It declares that a dead sinner is completely excluded from the confession of sin and that no one can be mindful of God afterward who had forgotten Him in this life.
Thus, all hope is entirely cut off from him, and every path to life is blocked. Since the only way for the guilty to find salvation is to pour out prayers to God and incessantly seek heavenly mercy, even this way is denied to the sinner by the deadly judgment of oblivion. He is not even left with the memory of God, from whom he should hope.
Therefore, let those who wish to have rich children after death think about this, as they do not remember the future punishments even in death. Let those who wish to have wealthy heirs in this fleeting and short life think about this, for they condemn themselves to eternal death. In doing so, they do not truly benefit their heirs but harm themselves; they do not love them as much as they hate themselves. For the love that considers only the short term is not as beneficial as the severe hatred that will torment in eternity.
And so, our God, as we mentioned in the first part of this book, commands parents to accumulate discipline for their children, not money; to bestow what is everlasting, not what will perish. This kind of matter and holy work benefits both children and parents alike: children through the instruction of discipline, and parents through the generosity of their giving.
Indeed, this discipline benefits the children by offering them eternal salvation, while generosity benefits the parents by helping them escape eternal death.
But to whom are we saying this, and why are we saying it?
Where can we find open ears or seeing eyes?
As we read about the wicked, it's evident that almost everyone has turned away; they have together become useless: there is no one who does good, almost no one.
Psalm 13:3.
A new madness has overtaken both secular people and even some who profess religion.
As we mentioned earlier, now not only for their children or grandchildren, which can be borne out of natural necessity, but also for their kin and relatives; and not only directly, as they say, but also indirectly and sideways, or rather perversely, they give their own property, the price of their redemption, as it is written:
Psalm 49:8-9: "He has not given God his atonement, and the price of the redemption of his soul."
And a little later: "Together," he says, "the foolish and the senseless will perish: and they will leave their wealth to strangers, and their graves will be their homes forever."
Psalm 49:11-12.
Now is not the time to discuss the difference between the foolish and the senseless, nor does it really matter what the difference in their merits is, as their destruction is the same. Therefore, that is sufficient cause, when he said that both the foolish and the senseless will perish together; let us see what he has added either for the cause or for the extent of their destruction. "They will leave," he says, "their wealth to strangers." It is true.
For what could be so foolish or so lost as for someone not to take care of his own, especially when God says that it profits a man nothing if he gains the whole world but loses his own soul? Or what, he says, will a man give in exchange for his soul?
Matthew 16:26.
Therefore, if people ought to despise the whole world to avoid the loss of their souls, and for the sake of their salvation someone should even despise his own gains; how unfaithful, how senseless is it for someone to condemn his own soul to make another person rich?
Especially since the one who receives the use of temporary things does not gain much, and the one who loses the reward of eternal happiness suffers immeasurable losses.
As the psalm follows:
Their graves are their homes forever.
How miserable, then, is the fate of those who, as if consigned to everlasting tombs, prefer that the condition of their bodies after death is somehow the same as that of their souls!
Indeed, it would be less miserable if it were the same, or if they were like unthinking animals, feeling neither the sense of good nor the pain of evil.
But what is bitter and intolerable is that they perish alike, but are not punished alike: for their death is eternal without feeling, while theirs is with all pain.
Thus, the destruction of sinful men makes their condition indeed similar to that of beasts, but their punishment is still more severe.
Let them consider all these things we are saying, or rather, let them consider all those things that God says, those who do not take care of themselves at all before death, nor help themselves in death, and for whom there is complete forgetfulness of their own souls.
It hardly matters anymore among men, as long as they do not take care of themselves at all.
For if any of those we speak of do not have children as death approaches, they unfaithfully seek out whom they may call either relatives or kin; or if that is lacking, they at least seek some fictitious names of new relationships.
It does not matter, as I said, who they remember, as long as they forget themselves; it does not matter whom they say they love, as long as they hate their own souls; it does not matter whom they make rich, as long as they consume themselves in eternal poverty.
Oh, wretchedness, oh, madness!
What have the most miserable of all done so badly to themselves that while they serve the pleasures of others, they perpetually persecute themselves!
For you may see some with the most unfortunate vanity investigating some new and noble relatives, you may see the shameful names of unknown kinships and the ridiculous inventions of recent and powerful relationships, when someone says of some adopted and sudden relative:
I make him my heir and parent.
Or any widow or girl of holy profession: I name him my nearest heir.
Some, who were considered almost strangers and outsiders all their life, suddenly in their final moments become regarded as close ones; and those who were always strangers to the living, start being considered relatives of the deceased.
They suddenly include in their will those they never included in their affection; and this especially happens with the wealthy, the noble, or the honored, who, unless they were powerful, perhaps would not have been considered relatives.
Ridiculous ambition of the miserable testator, giving the value of his property to buy the lie of kinship, purchasing for the price of inheritance the name of heir, and with all the strength of his patrimony, working so hard that the one named as heir does not deny being a relative.
The most unfortunate testator, in his most foolish and miserable vanity, makes a nobleman his heir to seem more honorable in death because he appeared humble in his life.
O blindness, O insanity!
With what effort, most unfortunate people, do you ensure that you will be miserable for eternity?
With much less care and effort, you could have ensured that you would always be happy.
Indeed, I can find no other cause for this than sheer unbelief and treachery; either people do not think they will be judged by God, or they do not believe they will be resurrected at all.
For no one who is certain they will be resurrected and judged by God for their good and bad deeds would fail to strive for the hope and happiness of receiving eternal good for good deeds, or fear and danger of suffering eternal bad for bad deeds.
But this seems to be at odds with the Christian name, to say that one does not believe in the future.
What, then, is the cause, that if one believes what God has said, they do not fear what God threatens?
If they do not believe the words that God has spoken, let them not believe the rewards that God promises!
For he does not prove that he believes in God's promises, who does not act in such a way as to be able to receive the rewards promised by God.
In this life, when people realize they must face judgment by human authorities and go to court, they seek out lawyers, hire advocates, and try to gain the favor of officials.
They do all this out of fear of the coming judgment, even though they can't guarantee the outcome.
Even if they can't buy victory itself, they still pay a lot for the hope of winning.
Tell me, those of you who claim to believe in God's judgment, if you truly believed, like the people mentioned earlier, that you would be judged by God, wouldn't you secure your hope and salvation at any cost?
But you don't believe.
You say you do with your words, but your actions show otherwise.
As the Apostle says, you profess with words but deny with actions.
Titus 1:16.
To prove your disbelief through your own actions, tell me, why do you leave your wealth to a rich relative, an in-law, or even a stranger if they are absent?
Why didn't you give it away while you were healthy and unharmed?
Why didn't you hand it over to your heirs while you were sound and vigorous?
But in your will, you cautiously and diligently write: When I depart from this life, then you, my dearest heir, shall have it.
Tell me, why do you give nothing of yours to this dearest and most beloved person while you're alive, but only when you see yourself dying?
And what do I mean by "seeing yourself dying"? You ensure that neither while you are alive nor while you are dying they have anything of yours, but only when you are gone. It's strange that you allow them to have anything of yours only after you are completely gone, unless you have also ensured that it is only after you are buried. Even in saying, "When I depart from this life," you seem to have taken precautions. This means completely leaving human affairs, with the whole person no longer present among human matters.
Tell me, why are you so meticulous in your will?
Why include such detailed and careful provisions?
Without a doubt, it's because you consider your property essential while you're alive.
You don't want to be deprived of your resources, and you think it's very unfair that while you're alive and well, someone else becomes rich from your wealth, while you are reduced to poverty.
This is true, and I understand your concern.
I agree with everything you say in this regard.
But there's one thing I'd like you to explain.
Why is it that you, who find the use of your possessions so necessary for yourself, don't consider the fruits and returns of your property necessary after your death?
You say, without a doubt, because nothing is needed by the dead, and there's no need to reserve anything for that time.
Because being deceased and feeling nothing, you can neither take pleasure in the possession of your things nor be troubled by their loss.
The reason is clear.
Therefore, you assign your wealth to someone else when you die because you can't enjoy its benefits after death.
But what about the fact that the most excellent vessel of God, the apostle Paul, testifies and proclaims that "Whatever a man sows in this life, that he shall also reap after death" (Galatians 6:8); and "Whoever sows sparingly will also reap sparingly, and whoever sows bountifully will also reap bountifully" (Second Corinthians 9:6)?
From this, it's clearly understood that those who sow sparingly cannot reap a blessing.
By saying, "Whoever sows sparingly will also reap sparingly, and whoever sows bountifully will also reap bountifully," he emphasizes that the blessing is found in generosity, showing that those who sow sparingly will reap poverty, and those who sow generously will reap blessings.
But perhaps these things, whoever you are, O unbeliever, seem either not strong enough or not clear enough to you. What about the fact that the Lord himself in the Gospel clearly teaches that no Christian loses out on good works, saying: "Whoever gives even a cup of cold water to one of these little ones, solely in the name of a disciple, truly I tell you, he will not lose his reward" (Matthew 10:42)?
What could be said more clearly?
He said that this matter would have a reward in the future, even if it had no value in the present.
He granted such honor to his worship that something done through faith would be worth much more here, even if it seemed worthless now.
But lest anyone flatter themselves, thinking they could buy great things with little, he cleverly pointed out that even for a cup of cold water, the reward would not be lost.
This clearly shows that something great would not be given in return for something small, but that any work of faith would not be wasted.
So you have an undeniable assurance of a future reward, a completely reliable guarantee of receiving good for your works.
He is not only faithful but also merciful and compassionate.
He not only pays what he has promised but also shows his willingness to be indebted.
He who promised a reward for a cup of cold water not only wants to repay what he received but also demonstrates his generosity.
Clearly merciful and full of compassion, he considers not only the generosity of the rich but also the service of the poor, showing that God would be indebted to even those who have nothing to lend.
But perhaps you, whoever you are, a rich person, may find this work of the poor unworthy of your wealth, and you might want to hear some specific promise of sacred rewards for yourself.
You have first what God says to the rich man in the Gospel: "Go, sell all your possessions, and you will have treasure in heaven" (Matthew 19:21).
Then there is the general command: "Do not store up for yourselves treasures on earth; but store up for yourselves treasures in heaven" (Matthew 6:19-20).
Lastly, those who are given all worldly possessions are invited to the work of generous giving with the promise of infinite reward.
It is said that anyone who, for the sake of honor and love for Him, gives a house, a field, or any other asset to charity, will receive a hundredfold in the future.
Moreover, He says, they will also possess eternal life.
What greater promise could He make to believers than to promise to repay His great lenders a hundredfold?
And not only this, but He says, they will possess eternal life.
This is much more than the reward of a hundredfold because what one receives a hundredfold, one will possess forever.
Therefore, the possession will not be fragile and fleeting, nor will it perish like earthly riches, a passing shadow, or a vanishing dream.
Whatever is given by God will be immortal; whatever is received will last without end.
And because of this, as I said, whoever receives in this way receives more than a hundredfold because the eternal nature of the hundredfold surpasses its value.
Since this is the case, and without a doubt, whoever believes in God will receive so much, how can you think that you will not use the things you give to God after death, when the Lord promises you not only their use but also an increase and a superabundant reward?
Or perhaps you do not want to receive such great things?
But reason does not allow you to be unwilling.
For there is no person among humans who, when able to be happy, would choose to be miserable; no one who, when able to have the delights of the highest good, would choose to suffer the punishment of the greatest evil.
No one, indeed no one; and therefore, neither would you: unless perhaps there is some monstrous and discordant nature in you differing from the human race, that you alone would choose not to be well, you alone would flee happiness, you alone would delight in suffering.
If that's not the case, then why, even in your final moments, don't you at least perform the ultimate offering and manage your affairs so that, if you can earn merit from God, you might be wealthy and blessed?
But if not, at least you might avoid being miserable, burned, tormented, cast into outer darkness, or boiled in eternal flames.
Given this, as I've mentioned, why don't you avoid evil in every way or strive to achieve good?
Why don't you do these things?
Why don't you seek eternal good?
Why don't you fear eternal evil?
Is it not because you either don't believe you'll be judged by God or don't believe you'll be resurrected at all?
If you did believe, how could you not avoid the immense evil of future judgment and escape the torments of immortal punishment?
But you don't believe; indeed, you don't believe.
Although you may assert otherwise in speech and profession, you don't believe: your speech and profession boast of faith, but your life and death reveal unbelief.
Otherwise, prove me wrong; I want to be proven wrong.
I don't ask you to prove your belief through the deeds of your former life; I'm satisfied with just one testimony from your final moments.
Behold now, behold, you are about to die, departing from your body, not knowing where you will go, where you will be taken, to what punishments and horrors you will be dragged, with only one refuge remaining in your final moments, one opportunity to escape the darts of eternal fire, to offer for yourself at least what you have in substance, since you have nothing else to offer to God.
And yet, you, forgetful of yourself and oblivious to your salvation, think about new legatees and sigh about enriching an heir?
And doing these things, you say you believe in the judgment of God, yet, when you are to be judged, you don't even consider it in your last moments!
And you claim to believe in the salvation of your soul, yet your soul is of no value to you.
It hardly matters to you whom you benefit, as long as you harm yourself!
You say you believe you will be the future judge, before whom no one is considered lesser or more despised than the judge himself!
You hold him in such contempt, you despise him so much, that you do not even think of yourself as long as you can disregard his commands.
Either refute me and prove me wrong if I am lying.
Behold, your judge is calling out to you, telling you not to love anyone else more than yourself when it comes to extending your possessions and resources, not to think more of anyone else than yourself when you are dying, not to consider anyone closer to your soul, not to judge anyone dearer.
For what will it benefit, says the Savior, if a person gains the whole world but loses their soul?
Or what will a person give in exchange for their soul?
This means: What will it profit you, oh most unfortunate person, if you possess the whole world or leave it to your relatives, but lose your salvation and soul?
The loss of the soul takes everything away entirely; and a person has absolutely nothing if they lose themselves to the loss of the soul.
Or what, he says, will a person give in exchange for their soul?
This means: Do not regard money or possessions, oh person; do not hesitate, at least when dying, to offer as much as you can from your resources and possessions for your hope.
Whatever you give for yourself is cheap; whatever you offer for yourself is of little value: because your soul is more precious compared to all things.
Therefore, do not hesitate to give for yourself: because if you lose yourself, you lose everything in yourself; but if you gain yourself, you will possess everything with yourself and in yourself.
Therefore, when your Lord is calling out these things to you as you are dying, whoever you are, you harden your mind, you block your ears; and asserting faith with bare words, you think it is enough to have words instead of actions, and you consider yourself firm enough to have the support of belief if you seem to honor God, whom you despise with your actions and deeds, with false words.
Son, says the Holy Scripture, if you have, do good to yourself, and offer good offerings to God.
And elsewhere: Have mercy, it says, on your soul.
See the compassion of our Lord towards you.
See how merciful our Lord God is, who asks for mercy for us on our behalf.
"Have mercy," he says, "on your soul." This means: Have mercy on that which you see me breaking with compassion; have mercy at last on the one I always pity; at least have mercy on your own soul, since you see me showing mercy to someone else.
And what after this, oh most miserable man? When God deals with you in this way, you do not comply! He asks you to have mercy on yourself, and you refuse! He pleads your case with you, and you do not accept it! He deigns to ask on your behalf, and he cannot obtain it from you! And how, whoever you are, oh most miserable man, how will he hear you later pleading in his judgment, when here you refused to hear him pleading for you?
But evidently, there is a great reason why you cannot listen to God. Your relatives and kin surround you as you are sick; wealthy matrons surround you; noblemen surround you; your sickbed is crowded with people dressed in silk and gold garments. Oh, what a great reward in eternity it is to give your own goods to such beggars! It is evidently a worthy and just cause that you take away from your soul what you leave to such needy people.
But surely you are broken by compassion, and you are overcome by the piety of lamenting relatives. There is a certain reason. You see, indeed, the most opulent and splendidly dressed people, anxious for you, weeping for you, showing you sad faces with festive attire, displaying faces composed to sadness, buying your inheritance with their imagined concern. Who is not moved by such compassion, who is not moved by such grief; or how, when you see such things, can you not forget yourself?
For you see forced tears, feigned sighs, fake anxiety, not hoping for your recovery, but waiting for your death. You see all their faces fixed on you, as if accusing you of delaying your death. Oh, unfortunate and most miserable you, whose final end so many relatives desire and pray for!
I am certain that the prayers of such people have no influence at all with God.
I might be surprised that you are alive, given how many wish for your death.
For these people, whoever they are, you abandon your soul, and you say you believe in God's judgment while disregarding His commands to leave your inheritance to such individuals?
The prophet says of one who believes in God, "He has scattered, he has given to the poor; his righteousness endures forever" (Psalm One Hundred Eleven: Nine).
And the Savior Himself said to all the rich, "Sell what you possess, and give alms" (Luke Twelve: Thirty-Three).
And elsewhere, "Sell what you have, and give to the poor" (Matthew Nineteen: Twenty-One).
Does He say, give to your relatives, give to your in-laws?
Certainly not; but to the poor, to the needy.
Does He say to a rich relative, to any powerful person at all?
Certainly not; but to the needy, the poor, the destitute.
And rightly so.
For if you give your wealth to your wealthy relatives, does your righteousness endure forever?
Or if you increase their riches with your wealth, will you have a treasure in heaven?
Woe, says the prophet, to those who call evil good, and good evil (Isaiah Five: Twenty).
God even forbids you to praise such people, and yet you do not fear to enrich them!
He does not want these people to hear preaching words, and you bestow wealth on them!
He forbids honoring their lives with false words, and from you, their treasures and riches are accumulated!
But you evidently fear the faces of surrounding relatives, and you are afraid to offend those present and besieging your bed.
Do not fear them, says the Lord through the prophet, nor be afraid of their faces, for they are a rebellious house (Ezekiel Two: Six).
And therefore you too, be fearless and steadfast.
Do not fear their faces, nor be broken by their flattery.
Despise those who covet your inheritance and are already dividing your wealth among themselves; who do not love you, but your inheritance, indeed who curse you out of greed for your possessions.
While they impatiently thirst for you, they hate you.
They see your presence as a rival and an adversary, and they believe your existence is a barrier to their desires.
Therefore, despise such people and see them as worthless.
Don't be swayed by their flattery: it's poison to you.
Ignore their praises: they are like murderers' swords, more dreadful than any weapon.
Everyone sees those who openly rage, but the unsuspecting do not see these ones who lie in wait.
Those who rage are avoided; these secretive ones kill.
They are more dangerous in their new way of harming because no one wants to be hurt by iron swords, but with these flatteries, many even want to be killed.
A new and immeasurable lure of deadly evil.
Whoever is struck by those swords is tormented by fear and pain; whoever is killed by these flatteries is delighted.
Therefore, flee from this evil, flee from the flattering snares set for you, flee from the harmful attentions and deceivers seeking your favor.
These are the actions that cut your throat and drag you to death.
Therefore, flee from such flatteries and their diligence.
They are your executioners and torturers, who surround you now but will kill you in the future.
With joined hands and as if conspiring by mutual agreement, they try to hurl you into the eternal fires of hell.
So, do not fear them, do not dread them.
Lift your spirit and assume the strength of holy authority.
If they strive so hard for you to perish, why shouldn't you strive even harder to live?
Therefore, be strong and take counsel with a steadfast mind.
It is quite unfaithful and foolish to prefer making others miserable rather than being happy yourself; and to make others luxuriate in temporary pleasures, while delivering yourself to be burned by eternal fires.