Fragment One (Alias Part One)
The Excellence of Faith, Hope, and Love.
The Apostle Paul, inspired by the Holy Spirit, addresses the Corinthians with these words:
"Now faith, hope, and love remain" First Corinthians 13:13.
He captures the profound mystery of complete truth through this trio of human affections.
He explains that the roles or gifts of other things, in which we are currently partly engaged, will come to an end First Corinthians 13:8 and following, when the perfection of the heavenly council is revealed with the arrival of our Lord Jesus Christ.
When our mortal condition is transformed into eternal glory, what is now perceived as temporary will cease to be; when what is given is eternal, it will always remain so.
The value of faith, hope, and love is such that, even when our bodies succumb to death, they persist and never fade away; and while everything else in a person is partial, these alone are perfect.
Whether prophecies are abolished, tongues cease, or knowledge is destroyed, these three superior qualities reach unchanging perfection: they neither change externally nor gain more than they already possess.
As absolute truth dispels prophecies, tongues, and knowledge, it will also embrace faith, hope, and love as guides and advocates for attaining eternity, just as eternity itself will hold them.
The blessed Apostle indeed distinguished the significance of these qualities with a slight degree of honor, making it clear that while the rest will be done away with as heavenly growth progresses, these three alone remain.
The Merit of Faith. The Nature of Hope. The Affection of Love.
Thus, God is perceived as the forerunner of righteousness, believed by those unaware that He is God.
For this reason, the faith of Abraham is credited as righteousness first Hebrews 11:6 and Romans 4:9, and the faith of the Canaanite woman, who silently tested the Lord, saves her daughter Matthew 15:28, and to those who believe in His name, power is given in John, that they might be born of God John 1:12.
The merit of faith is immense, and perfect happiness belongs to those who believe in God.
Through faith, those born into sin and sickness find justice, health, and a birth from God.
Hope, on the other hand, surpasses the pleasures of worldly life and the goods of this age, trusting in what is arranged by God.
It stands to gain future rewards in exchange for present losses.
The Lord rewards such hope with the promise:
"Everyone who has left houses, or brothers, or sisters, or mother, or children, or fields for my name's sake will receive a hundred times as much and will inherit eternal life" (Matthew 19:29).
This confidence in God's virtues is an outstanding testimony, as it disregards present things as uncertain and holds onto the future as eternal and present!
However, while the Apostle assigns equal glory to enduring faith, hope, and charity, indicating they are equally inviolable, he suggests that charity surpasses the others.
Through charity, we are bonded to God by a certain love.
Our will becomes inseparably united with His, infused with the love of devotion, from which neither sword, nor hunger, nor nakedness will separate us (Romans 8:35).
Through it, anger, jealousy, ambition, injustice, indulgence, and greed are restrained.
Therefore, while faith, hope, and charity remain, the greatest of these is charity (First Corinthians 13:13).
Through this bond of inseparable affection in the name of God, no worldly disturbances can dissolve or divide us.
Love compels Hilarius not to remain silent about the wickedness of heretics.
In line with this great and solemn apostolic authority, I, too, among others, bear witness through this love instilled in us before time began, for the hope of heaven.
I stand firmly with the name of God and the Lord Jesus Christ, rejecting the company of the wicked and the fellowship of unbelievers.
With Him, we thrive, enjoy the comforts of this world, overflow with blessings, take pride in our royal closeness, and falsely hold the title of bishop, becoming a burden to everyone, both publicly and privately, in the governance of the Church.
Such power was granted, as to others, if only I would corrupt the truth of the Gospel with falsehood, ease the guilt of conscience with ignorance, and defend corrupt judgment with excuses.
Not to be accountable for the sin of heresy by my faith, which would indeed be subject to it, but by the simplicity of the ignorant, and to lie about integrity under the difficulty of public understanding.
For this love, remaining in the simplicity of heart through faith and hope in Christ, did not endure these compromises.
Having received from the Apostle, "For God has not given us a spirit of fear" to Timothy 1:7, and having learned from the Lord's words, "Whoever acknowledges me before others, I will also acknowledge before my Father in heaven" Matthew 10:32;
And as it was said by the same, "Blessed are those who are persecuted because of righteousness, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven: blessed are you when people insult you, persecute you, and falsely say all kinds of evil against you because of me; rejoice and be glad, because great is your reward in heaven" Matthew 5:10 and following:
I could not choose a guilty conscience in the silence of ambition over enduring hardship for the confession of God.
What Kind of Work is Being Undertaken.
I'm trying to bring to public awareness a work that is serious and complex, tangled in deceit, subtly manipulated by heretics, and prejudged by the dissimulation and fear of many.
This work is foreign due to the despair in the places where it unfolded and where we act-ancient in time, yet new in silence.
It has long been overlooked under the pretense of peace, recently revived by the cunning of deceitful people.
In this situation, even as peace is sought in the affairs of the Roman Empire, the king is troubled, the palace is buzzing, bishops are rushing about, and officials and leaders are hurriedly moving, all disturbed by the urgency against apostolic men.
Everywhere there is action, anxiety, and urgency.
The effort and care needed to maintain this claim clearly reveal its injustice.
I recall many conversations where some of God's priests are exiled because they didn't side with Athanasius.
This error has occupied nearly everyone's minds, so under his name, they don't see a worthy cause for each of them to undertake exile.
What is Omitted.
I omit, although the greatest respect should be given to the king, for every kingdom is from God, that his judgment should not be equitably admitted to episcopal decisions.
Because things of Caesar should be rendered to Caesar, and things of God to God.
Luke chapter 20, verse 25.
I remain silent about the emperor's removed judgment of the case.
I don't complain about a sentence being extracted from someone absent.
Although, as the Apostle says, where there is faith, there is also freedom.
Second Corinthians chapter 3, verse 17.
Priestly simplicity should not endure this.
But I pass over these matters, not because they should be despised, but because more serious issues lie beneath them.
Although from these events that occurred in various lands, it could have been understood that something entirely different was happening than what was believed.
Nonetheless, we decided to set forth the whole matter with more careful attention in this volume.
For at that time, these issues were thrust upon us hastily: the corruption of the Gospels, the distortion of faith, and the feigned blasphemous confession of Christ's name.
In that discussion, everything was rushed, disorganized, and confused because the more we tried to be heard, the more stubbornly they resisted listening.
Where to begin.
I'll start with the recent events, specifically when my brother and fellow servant Paulinus, the bishop of the church of Trier, in 353, did not get involved in their downfall and deception at the town of Arelatensi.
I'll explain the nature of that judgment, which led to him being considered unworthy of the church by the bishops and worthy of exile by the king when he reported his decision.
This isn't shown by the order of events but through reasoning based on present circumstances, so that from these things, his faith might be understood rather than the fear, from which he suffered injury because he did not agree with them.
How it should be read.
I advise that careful attention should be given to this entire volume.
Everything must be separated by time, distinguished by judgments, and by people; the strength of words must be judged so that the frequent letters and synods introduced then do not become tedious before the end.
It concerns what understanding of God should be sought, what hope of eternity exists, and where the perfect truth should be established.
And since such a serious matter is being discussed, each person must take care to understand these things in a way that, standing firm in their own judgment, they do not follow someone else's opinion.
The end.
Fragment Two (Alias One of Part One): Here Begins an Example of a Letter
The Council of Sardica to all Churches. (Written in the year 347.)
Purpose of the Council.
The Arian heretics have often and boldly opposed the servants of God who uphold the true Catholic faith.
They have attempted to introduce false doctrines and persecute the orthodox believers.
Their opposition has become so apparent that even the devout emperors couldn't ignore it.
Therefore, with God's grace, these merciful emperors convened a holy council from various provinces and cities, allowing it to take place in the city of Sardica.
The goal was to eliminate all discord, completely expel false teachings, and ensure that everyone upheld the piety found in Christ.
Bishops from the East were encouraged by the devout emperors to attend, mainly because of the frequent complaints regarding our beloved brothers and fellow bishops, Athanasius of Alexandria and Marcellus of Ancyra in Galatia.
We believe their slanders have also reached you and have attempted to sway your judgments.
They want you to believe their accusations against the innocent while hiding their own wicked heresy.
But they have not been allowed to continue this for long.
The Lord, who guides the Churches and suffered death for the Churches and for all of us, has enabled us to ascend to the heavens.
The Eusebians hesitate to attend the Council.
Previously, when Eusebius, Marius, Theodorus, Diognetus, Ursacius, and Valens wrote to Julius, our fellow priest and bishop of the Roman Church, against the aforementioned fellow bishops-Athanasius and Marcellus-they claimed that our bishops were involved.
However, what Eusebius did was nothing but full of falsehood and lies.
Even though it was clear from the letters that exposed their lies, they didn't want to come when they were invited by our beloved brother Bishop Julius in 623.
If they had confidence in their actions against our fellow bishops, they would have attended.
Their falsehoods were further exposed by their actions at this holy and great council.
They arrived at the city of the Sardicans, but when they saw Athanasius, Marcellus, Asclepas, and others, they were too afraid to face judgment.
Not just once or twice, but repeatedly, they ignored the invitation from our synod of bishops, especially from the most venerable elder Hosius.
Despite his age, confession, and long-proven faith, he made such an effort for the Church's benefit and is worthy of all reverence.
While everyone waited and encouraged them to come to judgment to personally refute everything they said or wrote about our absent fellow priests, they didn't show up, just as we predicted.
This demonstrates their falsehood, not only through deceitful fraud or cunning excuses.
Those who have confidence to prove their claims in others' absence are ready to do so in their presence.
But since they didn't dare to come, we believe no one can overlook this, even if they wish to continue their malice.
They prove nothing against our fellow priests whom they accuse in absence but avoid when present.
They flee; how many and how great are their crimes.
They fled, dearest brothers, not only because of those they falsely accused but also because of those who came from different places to accuse them of many crimes.
For the men returning from exile brought forth chains and shackles.
Once again, from those still held in exile, relatives and close friends sent messages, bringing complaints from both the survivors and those who perished in exile.
They pursued this injustice relentlessly.
Most notably, bishops were present, including one who showed the iron and chains he had carried around his neck because of them.
Others testified that they had been threatened with death due to their accusations.
They were so desperate that they would have even killed bishops if they hadn't escaped their deadly grasp.
Our blessed fellow bishop, Theodulus, died while fleeing from their harassment.
He was condemned to die because of their accusations.
Some displayed sword wounds and scars.
Others complained of being starved by them.
These testimonies came from men of high standing, chosen from all the churches, gathered here to explain the events: armed soldiers, people with clubs, threats from judges, and falsified letters.
Forged letters by Theognitus against our fellow bishops Athanasius and Marcellus were read, intending to provoke the emperor against them.
Those who were deacons under Theognitus at the time confirmed these facts.
Additionally, there were reports of virgins being stripped, churches burned, and ministers of God imprisoned-all due to the wicked and detestable heresy of the Arians.
Those who renounced their communion were forced to endure these sufferings.
Upon entering Sardica, they feared facing their opponents.
Considering their situation, they realized they were in a difficult position.
Ashamed to admit their wrongdoings, which could no longer be concealed, they finally arrived in the city of Sardica, hoping their presence would dispel any suspicion of misconduct.
Seeing those who were falsely accused by them, and those they had fiercely opposed, the accusers, plagued by their own conscience and even betraying their own misdeeds, could not come when called.
In Greek, they were unwilling, especially disturbed by the conscience of our fellow priests Athanasius, Marcellus, and Asclepius, who not only appealed for judgment but also challenged their accusers.
They aimed not only to prove the falsehoods fabricated against them but also to expose the impious and wicked acts committed against the Churches.
However, seized with such terror, they fled, and through their flight, they revealed and exposed their own falsehoods.
The innocence of Athanasius is proven.
Even though their malice and deceit were evident not only from past events but also from these, making it impossible for them to scheme any further evil, we demonstrated, according to truth and reason, the necessity to investigate their actions.
We found that they were also false in these matters and did nothing but attack our fellow priests.
The man they claimed Athanasius had killed, named Arsenius, is actually alive.
This made it clear that all other claims they boasted about were full of lies and deceit.
Regarding the allegation about a cup supposedly broken by Macarius, a priest of Athanasius, those present from Alexandria testified that nothing of the sort happened.
Furthermore, the bishops writing from Egypt to our fellow priest Julius assured that no such suspicion existed there.
This letter is documented in the works of Athanasius, volume one, page seven hundred twenty-two.
They also claimed to have records against him; however, these records were made without the presence of the other party.
When questioned about their actions, both the pagan and the catechumen claimed they were inside when Macarius arrived.
They mentioned that the well-known Scyrus, who was unwell, was lying in the church, in the cell.
It became clear that the entire ritual hadn't been properly conducted, as catechumens were present, and those who were ill were lying down.
Scyrus, who plotted all sorts of wickedness, claimed he had burned a book of divine Scriptures by Athanasius.
When confronted, he confessed he was unwell when Macarius was there, revealing himself as a false witness.
Ultimately, they rewarded Scyrus for his deceit with the honor of the episcopate, even though he wasn't a presbyter.
Two presbyters, who have now joined the council and were previously with Meletius, received by Alexander, the blessed bishop of Alexandria, and now with Athanasius, testified that Scyrus was never Meletius's presbyter, nor was he present at Mareotis as a church or minister.
Yet, they presented him as a bishop, despite him never having been a presbyter, to disguise their falsehood with the title of episcopate in front of their audience.
Marcellus and Asclepas are blameless.
The book written by our brother and fellow bishop Marcellus was read, revealing the wickedness of Eusebius and his associates.
They pretended to approve what Marcellus proposed as if it had already been proven.
What followed, along with the preliminary statements, was read, confirming his true faith.
He did not claim the Word of God began with the Holy Virgin Mary, as falsely accused, nor did he say His kingdom has an end.
Instead, he wrote that His kingdom is without beginning and without end.
But Asclepius, our fellow bishop, presented the records completed in Antioch in front of the adversaries and Eusebius from Caesarea.
The judgments showed the bishop to be blameless.
The crimes, names, and skills of the Eusebians.
They were rightly summoned often, but they didn't dare to come.
They fled, driven by their own guilty conscience.
By fleeing, they confirmed their falsehoods and made the accusations against them believable.
What then?
Above all else, they even accepted and promoted those who had long been deposed and expelled by the Church because of Arius's heresy.
They advanced deacons to the priesthood, and priests to the bishopric, solely to spread their impious doctrine and corrupt the pious faith.
After Eusebius, there are two leaders among them:
Theodore from Heraclea, Narcissus from Neronias in Cilicia, Stephen from Antioch, and George from Laodicea, although he was afraid and did not attend from the East, Acacius from Caesarea in Palestine, Menophantus from Ephesus in Asia, Ursacius from Singidunum in Moesia, and Valens from Mursa in Pannonia.
Indeed, those mentioned, along with others from the East, did not allow the holy Council to enter, nor did they permit access to the holy Church of God at all.
Upon arriving in Sardica, they held synods among themselves at each location and made agreements with threats to ensure those coming to Sardica for judgment would not attend or meet with the holy and great synod.
They came solely to have a meeting with their presence, which they immediately fled from.
We learned this from our fellow priests, Arius from Palestine and Stephen from Arabia, who indeed came with them but withdrew from their treachery.
These individuals came to the holy council, voicing their grievances about the violence they had endured.
However, they claimed that nothing was being done properly on their behalf.
They also mentioned that many of true faith were being prevented by threats from joining us.
Because of this, they insisted on staying in one place, without being allowed any time or freedom.
The decision of the council.
Therefore, it was not right to remain silent or leave unpunished the falsehoods, imprisonments, murders, fights, forged letters, assaults, abuses of virgins, exiles, destruction of churches, arson, and transfers from one church to another.
Above all, the doctrines of the Arian heresy that rise against true faith.
For this reason, we declare our dearest brothers and fellow bishops, Athanasius of Alexandria, Marcellus of Ancyra in Galatia, and Asclepius of Gaza, and those who were ministering to God with them, to be innocent and pure.
We write to each of their provinces so that the congregations of each church may recognize the integrity of their priest and know that they have their bishop.
As for those who have intruded into their churches like wolves, namely, Gregory in Alexandria, Basil in Ancyra, and Quintianus in Gaza, we declare that they neither hold the title of bishop nor have any share in their communion, nor should anyone accept letters from them or write to them.
Additionally, Theodore, Narcissus, Acacius, Stephen, Ursacius, Valens, Menophantus, and George (even though he did not attend due to fear, as mentioned, but because he was once expelled by the blessed memory of Alexander, bishop of Alexandria), and because both he and the others associated with Arian madness were accused of crimes, the holy council deposed them all equally from the rank of bishop.
We have judged that not only are they not bishops, but they should not even have communion with the faithful.
For separating the Son and alienating the Word from the Father, they must be cut off from the Catholic Church and become strangers to the Christian name.
Therefore, let them be cursed for daring to corrupt the word of truth.
As the Apostle commands: If anyone preaches to you a gospel other than what you have received, let him be cursed.
(Galatians chapter 1, verse 9).
Announce that no one should communicate with them, for there is no fellowship between light and darkness.
Keep them all far away, as there is no partnership between Christ and Belial.
Be cautious, dear ones, not to write to them or accept their letters.
Also, make sure, beloved brothers and fellow priests, to confirm all that we have established through your letters, as if you were present in spirit at this council.
This will make it clear from the agreement of the letters that all bishops share the same sentiment and that there is unity in will among all.
We wish you well in the Lord, Brothers.
It ends.
Here begins the example of the letter made in the year 347 to Bishop Julius of Rome, directed to Julius by the council.
Why Julius was not present at the council: The prerogative of the See of Peter.
What we have always believed, we continue to feel now, for experience proves and confirms what each has heard.
It is true, as the most blessed teacher of the nations, the Apostle Paul, spoke about himself: Do you seek proof of Christ speaking in me?
(Second Corinthians chapter 13).
Since the Lord Christ dwelled in him, it is certain that the Holy Spirit spoke through his soul and resonated through his body.
And so you, dearest brother, though separated in body, were present with us in mind and will.
The reason for your absence was both honorable and necessary, so that neither the schismatic wolves would deceive and snatch, nor the heretical dogs, driven by rabid rage, would bark madly, nor indeed would the serpent devil pour out the poison of blasphemies.
It seems most appropriate for the priests from each province to report to the head, which is the seat of the Apostle Peter.
The legates of Julius.
Given that everything that has been done, decided, and established-along with the documents and personal testimonies of our beloved brothers and fellow priests Archidamus and Philoxenus, and our dear son Leo the deacon-can be truthfully and faithfully explained, it seems almost unnecessary to repeat these things in these letters.
It was clear to all who came from the eastern regions, calling themselves bishops, although some of them are certain authorities mentioned in the previous letter number seven, whose sacrilegious minds have been tainted by the poisonous Arian heresy, that they hesitated for a long time due to distrust and did not want to come to judgment, criticizing your and our blameless communion.
This was because we believed not only in the testimony of eighty bishops about the innocence of Athanasius, in the Council of Alexandria, whose letter is mentioned in number five, but also because when they were summoned by your priests and by letter, they refused to come to the synod that was to be held in the city of Rome.
It was quite unjust for them to deny communion to Marcellus and Athanasius when so many priests bore witness.
Three matters to be discussed at the synod.
There were three matters that needed to be discussed.
Even the most religious emperors agreed that everything should be thoroughly examined and discussed again, especially concerning the holy faith and the integrity of the truth, which they violated.
Secondly, regarding the persons they claimed were deposed; about the unjust judgment, or if they could prove it, the confirmation would be just.
The third question, which truly deserves to be addressed, concerns the severe and bitter injuries, even intolerable and wicked insults, inflicted on the churches.
They kidnapped bishops, priests, and deacons, exiling all the clergy, dragging them to desolate places, and killing them through hunger, thirst, exposure, and all kinds of deprivation.
Some were imprisoned and suffered in filth and stench, while others were bound in iron chains so tight that they were strangled by the narrowest bands.
Indeed, some of these unjustly imprisoned people died from such punishment, and there is no doubt that their deaths were glorious martyrdoms.
They even dare to still hold some people without any criminal cause, except that they resisted and declared their condemnation of the Arian and Eusebian heresy, refusing communion with such people, while those who preferred to agree with them benefited.
Those who had previously been cast out were not only received back but were also promoted to clerical positions and rewarded for their falsehoods.
The perversity of Ursacius and Valens.
Regarding the actions of the wicked and unskilled young men, Ursacius and Valens, understand, most blessed brother.
It was clear that they did not cease to spread the deadly seeds of their corrupt doctrine, and that Valens, having left the church, attempted to invade another church.
During this disturbance, one of our brothers, Viator, who could not escape, was attacked and trampled in the city of Aquileia and died on the third day.
Valens was undoubtedly the cause of his death, as he was the one who disturbed and incited.
But as you read the letters we sent to the most blessed emperors, you will easily see that we left nothing out, as much as reason allowed.
To avoid a long and tedious account, we briefly indicated who did what and what they committed.
The decisions from the synods of Sicily, Sardinia, and Italy should be communicated through Julius.
Your great wisdom ensures that, through your writings, our brothers in Sicily, Sardinia, and Italy understand what has been decided.
They should not unknowingly accept letters of communion, known as 'little letters,' from those who have been justly demoted.
However, Marcellus, Athanasius, and Asclepius should remain in our communion because unfair judgments, their flight, and the evasion by those who refused to attend the bishops' council cannot harm them.
As mentioned earlier, the full report from the brothers sent by your sincere love will inform your unanimity thoroughly.
We have listed the names of those expelled for their crimes so that your distinguished authority is aware of who has been deprived of communion.
As we previously stated, please kindly remind all our brothers and fellow bishops through your letters not to accept their letters of communion, or 'little letters.
'
List of Heretics
Ursacius from Singidunum, Valens from Mursa, Narcissus from Hierapolis, Stephanus from Antioch, Acacius from Caesarea, Menophantus from Ephesus, Georgius from Laodicea.
Names of the Bishops Below, Who Were Present at and Subscribed to the Council of Sardica
Ossius from Cordoba, Spain. Annianus from Castolona, Spain.
Florentinus from Emerita, Spain. Dominianus from Asturica, Spain.
Castus from Zaragoza, Spain.
Praetextatus from Barcelona, Spain.
Maximus from Lucca, Tuscany.
Bassus from Diocletianopolis, Macedonia.
Porphyrius from Philippi, Macedonia.
Marcellus from Ancyra of Galatia, Macedonia.
Euterius from Caindo, Phrygia.
Asclepius from Gaza, Palestine.
Moysius from Thebes, Thessaly.
Vincentius from Capua, Campania.
Januarius from Benevento, Campania.
Prothogenes from Serdica, Dacia.
Dioscorus from Thrace.
Hymenius from Peraea, Thessaly.
Lucius from Caynopoli (or Hadrianopoli?), Thrace.
Lucius from Verona, Italy.
Evagrius from Heraclea, Macedonia.
Dionysius from Lignedon, Achaia.
Julius from Thebes with seven gates, Achaia.
Athenodorus from Blatea, Achaia (or from Dacia, Blacena).
Diodorus from Tenedos, Asia.
Alexander from Larissa, Thessaly.
Aethius from Thessalonica, Macedonia.
Vitalis from Aquae, Dacia Ripensis.
Paragorius from Scupi, Dardania.
Trifon from Marciarce, Achaia.
Athanasius from Alexandria.
Gaudentius from Naissus, Achaia (or Dacia).
Jonam from Particopolis (or Parthenopolis, or Paroecopolis), Macedonia.
Alypius from Magari, Achaia.
Macedonius from Ulpianis, Ardania (or Dardania).
Calvus from Castra Martis, Achaia Ripensis.
Fortunatianus from Aquileia, Italy.
Plotarcus from Patras, Achaia.
Eliodorus from Nicopolis.
Eutarius from Pannonia.
Arius from Palestine.
Asturus from Arabia.
Cocras from Asapofebiis, Achaia.
Stercorius from Canusio, Apulia.
Calepodius from Campania.
Lerenius (or Irenaeus) from Secoro, Achaia.
Martyrius from Naples, Achaia.
Dionysius from Elis, Arcadia.
Severus from Ravenna, Italy.
Ursacius from Brescia, Italy.
Portasius (or Protasius) from Milan, Italy.
Marcus from Fissia, Asia.
Verissimus from Gaul, from Lyon; Valens from Achaia, from Dacia; Ripense from Scio; Palladius from Macedonia, from Dui; Gerontius from Macedonia, from Brevi; Alexander from Achaia, from Morenis; Euthitius from Achaia; Titius from Asia, from Montonis.
Altogether, there are 61 bishops.
The innocence of Athanasius is evident.
The duty of sacrifice is solely the priest's responsibility.
As Hilary suggests, the matter requires no further explanation.
Everything has been stated and demonstrated so clearly that it's obvious to all: witnesses from Egypt were assembled, Athanasius himself was present, and the false judges disgracefully fled under the cover of night, exposing their guilt.
Let's consider the origin of the case that led to the accusation against Athanasius.
He is accused by his own priest of disrupting the altar during the sacrifice, with the priest Scyrus present.
However, Scyrus denies this, and the false accusation, along with its author, is condemned.
Moreover, the act of sacrifice could not have been performed without a priest.
When questioning a person's actions, there's no room for such a grave accusation, especially since there is no church in Mareotis.
Could it be that religion itself faltered?
Or did the place where the sacrifice was violated somehow fall apart?
Scyrus is said to have been ordained as a bishop from a deacon, supposedly to give more authority to the false claim of the deceitful bishop.
But if there was a church, and if it exists: if it doesn't exist, then it never did.
The uncertainty is whether these false accusations were proven true, or if those who later pointed them out were not established, which, if it was, it cannot not have been?
The accusations against Athanasius remain unproven.
If someone is educated through human institutions and seeks to use common sense, and if they are dedicated to pursuing truth through wisdom, let them focus and consider what they truly believe in these matters of judgment.
Let them reason about the sources of evidence.
We have two key indicators:
One affirms the crime but doesn't provide evidence and simply points to someone experiencing harm; the other denies the crime, the location, and the person involved.
So, which opinion do you think is fair to accept?
Surely, anyone who examines both sides carefully would say:
If there's a crime, it needs proof; if there's a location, it must be shown; if there's a person involved, they should be identified.
But truly, when there's no evidence of the act, the place, or any person involved, it would be irrational to judge things that don't exist.
There's no reason to condemn Athanasius.
Priests, look to heaven and the stars, and to the Creator who made them from nothing, with the faith and hope you have received.
Remember that the form of judgment you use will be used to judge you.
(Matthew, Chapter Seven, Verse Two)
Answer me, as I ask: by what judgment did you condemn Athanasius?
You might say, by the Bishops: and this would be the basis of your confession.
You claim they followed the sacred respect of judgments within episcopal communion.
But will you deny knowing that Athanasius, whose condemnation Valens, Ursacius, and Saturninus demanded, was reinstated to communion by Hosius, Maximinus, and Julius?
I'm not comparing; I'm asking, what was your opinion on Athanasius's alleged crime?
His presbyter Macarius is said to have stormed into the Mareotic church, disrupted presbyter Scyrus, and desecrated the sacraments of our salvation.
The witnesses in this case were a catechumen and a pagan.
But later, wasn't it decided by the saints gathered at Sardica that there was no church in Mareotis and that Scyrus wasn't a priest?
What path have you followed?
You give authority to false bishops and deny it to others?
Do you make decisions as if things don't exist, yet judge those that do not exist?
To believe in this suggestion, I think prison demanded it, the guard insisted, the torturer pressed on, the sword loomed, and the fire burned.
Where things do not exist, wickedness has gained episcopal authority among you, while in seeking truth, holiness has lost faith.
Oh, true disciples of Christ!
Oh, worthy successors of Peter and Paul!
Oh, pious fathers of the Church!
Oh, ambitious envoys between God and the people, you have traded the truth of Christ for the falsehood of men!
We have therefore addressed the first proposition, which promised that Athanasius could not be found guilty of the crimes you accused him of.
Now, let's say a few words about what happened with Marcellus and Photinus.
The condemnation of Photinus, and the repentance of Ursacius and Valens.
Photinus, the Bishop of Sirmium, was influenced by Marcellus, as he was also a deacon under him for some time.
He continued to disrupt the truth of the Gospel with new teachings after corrupting the morals and teachings of innocence.
This often happens, as the growth of vices leads to a loss in the love of God, and the insane pursuit of corrupted knowledge increases.
Therefore, to remove Photinus from the bishopric, who had already been condemned as heretical two years earlier at the synod of Milan in 347, priests gathered from many provinces in 349, concerned and anxious about the disturbances and mix-ups.
It had long been necessary to separate several bishops guilty of either false judgments against Athanasius or communion with the Arian heresy from the Church.
Taking this opportunity, Ursacius and Valens approached the bishop of the Roman people in 349, begging to be received back into the Church and asking to be admitted into communion through forgiveness.
Julius, upon their request, granted pardon.
This not only benefited the Catholic Church but also weakened the Arians by welcoming those who had previously disrupted unity back into Catholic communion through reconciliation and peace.
Since confession deals with truth, repentance with fault, and pardon with wrongdoing, Valens and Ursacius sought to join the communion.
They confessed in letters about Athanasius's innocence, the falsity of the judgment against him, and the sin of the Arian heresy.
Here's an example of a letter that Valens wrote by hand in Rome in the year 349, after renouncing the Easterners, declaring Athanasius not guilty, which Ursacius signed.
To our Most Blessed Lord Pope Julius, Valens and Ursacius send greetings.
It's clear that we previously made serious accusations against Bishop Athanasius in our letters.
When summoned by your Holiness, we failed to provide an explanation for our reports.
We confess before your Holiness, in the presence of all our presbyter brothers, that everything you heard from us about him was falsely presented and lacks all merit.
Therefore, we are eager to embrace communion with Athanasius, especially since your Holiness, in your innate kindness, has deemed our error worthy of pardon.
We also confess that if the Easterners or Athanasius ever summon us with bad intent, we will not attend without your knowledge.
As for the heretic Arius and his followers, who say, "There was a time when the Son was not," and who claim the Son is from nothing, denying-here add God-that the Son of God existed before the ages, as we declared in our previous document presented at Milan, we now and always anathematize with our own hand, with which we write. We confess: and again we say, we have condemned the Arian heresy and its authors forever, as stated above.
Signed by the hand of Ursacius: I, Ursacius the Bishop, have affirmed this profession of ours.
Hilary mentions that this letter was sent two years after the Romans condemned the heresy of Photinus.
Similarly, there is another letter from 349 AD, written by Valens and Ursacius, which they sent to Athanasius and the bishops sometime after sending the previous one from Rome, originating from Aquileia.
To our brother Athanasius from Ursacius and Valens.
The arrival of our brother and fellow priest Moses to your esteemed self, dear brother, gives us the opportunity to send our warmest greetings from the city of Aquileia.
We hope this letter finds you in good health.
You will encourage us if you also reply in writing.
Rest assured, through these letters, that we share a place with you in church communion.
May divine mercy protect you, Brother.
With the previous letters, pardon is granted to those who pray, allowing a return to the Catholic faith along with communion.
This is especially true since the letters of those seeking pardon contained the truth of the Sardican synod.
Athanasius separates Marcellus from his communion.
Meanwhile, a council is held at Sirmium.
Photinus, a heretic previously condemned and cut off from the unity of communion long ago, still could not be removed due to the support of the people.
Yet, Athanasius separated Marcellus, who, after his book was read (a book which we also possess), had been reinstated to his bishopric by the Sardican synod's decision.
When he saw that new and ambiguous teachings were being mixed in, Marcellus sought the path to the doctrine that Photinus had embraced, leading Athanasius to separate him from his communion before Photinus was accused.
This showed a pre-emptive judgment of a corrupted will, not based on the book's publication.
However, because good can easily turn to evil, he did not give authority to the actions against Marcellus before but focused on the actions to be taken against Photinus.
Supporting Athanasius, the Council of Sardica aimed to overturn the Eastern decisions.
It's important to note that after the council dissolved at Sardica, no other council against Marcellus was ever convened.
Similarly, when the Westerners made their decision about Photinus and informed the Easterners, no judgment was made against him.
Instead, some clever and cunning individuals, persistent in their malice, sought the chance to revisit the judgment that was overturned by Athanasius' acquittal at Sardica in six hundred and forty.
While writing about Photinus, they brought up Marcellus as if he were the originator of such teachings.
This was meant to revive the already settled and truthfully buried issue about Athanasius by bringing the matter back into public memory and to use Photinus' condemnation to subtly implicate Marcellus.
The earlier letter shows that Marcellus was condemned by the Arians, using his book on the subjection of the Lord Christ as an opportunity, along with Athanasius.
However, the reading of the same book shows he was found innocent.
The falsehood of the Arian judgment at the Council of Constantinople in three hundred and thirty-six is proven by this still-existing book.
Regarding Photinus, letters were sent to the Easterners as was customary, not to force unjust agreement as is done now, but to educate everyone.
But why does the Sirmium Council of the Easterners accuse Athanasius of denying communion to Marcellus?
Was it because of a flaw in his book that Marcellus was excluded?
They themselves acknowledge that Photinus took his ideas from Marcellus' teachings.
When Athanasius denied him communion, Marcellus refrained from entering the church.
Thus, communion with him in this faith, meaning the true faith about the subjection and tradition of the kingdom, teaches that denying it again reveals the errors in another's doctrine.
Both judgments of this man are without fault because he adhered to the agreement made at the synod of Sardica.
But in the case of the rejected one, Marcellus renounced it alone, without any backing from the synod.
However, that's a matter for another time.
Even though his longstanding hatred towards Athanasius has been satisfied, this scheme has progressed to an even greater level of wickedness.
The Sirmian Rescript, while claiming to represent true faith, is actually filled with deceit and poison.
The third point gives me the chance to show that the faith laid out at the beginning of the letter is fraudulent, heretical, and hides poison beneath its flattering words.
We profess this: There is one unbegotten God the Father, and His only Son, God from God, light from light, the firstborn of all creation, along with the Holy Spirit, the comforter.
This gentle beginning is meant to intercept the security of the readers and the simplicity of the unlearned, leading them to agree with the same subscription and then transition to judgments against Photinus and accusations against Athanasius, ultimately condemning the Catholic faith.
I hope the synod of Sardica has shed light on this, particularly Athanasius's innocence, by revealing the crimes fabricated against him by the Arians and how they pressured the people of God into a deadly doctrine.
However, as the matter requires, I will state it briefly.
Apostolic men have always worked to defend the faith of the Trinity.
In doing so, they have stirred up hatred from the Church's enemies.
The duty of apostolic men has always been to proclaim perfect faith constantly and publicly, to suppress heretical efforts, and to extinguish false doctrines by exposing the truth of the Gospels.
This is to prevent the spread of vice from contaminating and infecting the minds of listeners.
They took great care to discuss in detail, through various letters, what the perspective of God the Father should be, what the knowledge of God the Son should entail, and what sanctification through the Holy Spirit means.
This suggests that the Son of God is acknowledged as God through God the Father, and that the Father is in God the Son, with the Son being God within God the Father.
According to the statement, "I and the Father are one," John 10:30, and again: "As you, Father, are in me, and I in you," John 17:21, our faith is centered in the names and persons of the Father and the Son as one God.
The reason we've faced opposition from the Jews, the hatred from pagans, and the anger from heretics is simply because we profess the eternal power and the name of the Son within the Father. The heretics' opposition always stems from a misguided faith.
While they are preoccupied with vices and stray from innocence, they get caught up in the complexities of pointless questions. Having become unacceptable in life, will, and judgment, they turn to novel doctrines to gain favor, having lost the truth's essence.
The Occasion of the Council of Nicaea. The Doctrine of the Arians. When our predecessors learned that Arius and others were spreading a most irreverent faith, and it escalated beyond mere opinion to a formal condemnation, representatives from all over the world gathered and converged on Nicaea.
By clarifying the faith to the people and illuminating the path of divine knowledge, they aimed to eradicate the seeds of this emerging evil at its source.
Arius taught that God the Father, to create the world, begot the Son and, by His power, made Him from nothing into a new substance and another God, distinct and new. This was disrespectful to the Father, suggesting something similar to Him could be created from nothing, and blasphemous to Christ, as it stripped Him of the Father's infinite nobility.
So, when they learned from the Father: "There is no other God besides me," Isaiah 45:18; and from the Son: "I am in the Father and the Father in me," John 14:11; and: "I and the Father are one," John 10:30.
They broke the sacred bond of unity, giving God's Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, a beginning in time, an origin from nothing, not from another.
To address this issue, more than 300 bishops gathered at Nicaea.
By unanimous agreement, a heretical condemnation was decreed against all Arians.
After examining the Gospel and apostolic teachings, the perfect light of Catholic unity was brought forth.
What was expressed is supported by the faith itself, as it is presented.
This faith, written at Nicaea in the year 325 by 318 bishops, stands against all heresies.
We believe in one God, the Father Almighty, maker of all things visible and invisible.
And in one Lord Jesus Christ, the only-begotten Son of God, born of the Father, that is, from the substance of the Father, God from God, light from light, true God from true God, begotten, not made, of one substance with the Father, which the Greeks call
homoousion,
through whom all things were made, whether in heaven or on earth, who for us men and for our salvation came down, was incarnate, became man, suffered, rose again on the third day, ascended into heaven, and will come to judge the living and the dead.
And in the Holy Spirit.
However, those who say, "There was a time when he was not," and "Before he was born, he was not," and that he was made from non-existent things, which the Greeks call
ex ouk onton,
or those who say the Son of God is of a different substance or essence, changeable and mutable; these the Catholic and Apostolic Church condemns.
By comparing sincere faith with adulterated falsity, the falsehood is exposed.
Faith compared to faith reveals the mentioned falsehood.
The one arranged at Nicaea is complete and perfect, and with all entrances by which heretics usually creep in completely closed, it is connected with the inviolable solidity of eternal unity between the Father and the Son.
This one, however, flatters with simplicity, first asserting that we believe in such a way that it is absent from anyone.
However, the faith of the Westerners, rooted in the teachings of the Gospel, recognizes the Father in the Son, and the Son in the Father; the Father is unbegotten, and the Son is eternal in substance.
This means that just as the Father always is, so too the Son is always in the Father, born of God to be God, not conceived, and always existing in that from which He originates.
On the other hand, the faith of the Easterners, as expressed from Sirmium, does not align with this belief.
It speaks of God from God and praises the firstborn, while establishing the name of the Trinity.
It disguises its harmful intent under the guise of religious moderation, saying God from God, light from light, suggesting that from this confession, God and light, made by God, not begotten from God, might exist.
This implies that they do not stem from the substance of the Father's eternity.
Consequently, this diminishes the Father and implies that the Son, if God is born from nothing, is merely part of creation's order, rather than its source.
Thus, although Christ existed before the world, He is considered from time, not from eternity, placing Him within the created order.
Through this belief, something preceding Him is implied, as He began to exist from time.
Furthermore, everything that God is, is dissolved in Christ, since His birth from Mary, who did not exist at one time, is considered from time.
In what sense is Christ the firstborn of all creation?
Even those lacking good hope seek apostolic authority to justify such a significant claim, since it is said of Him, the firstborn of all creation.
However, by removing the surrounding context, they falsely adapt it to suit their doctrines, using the Apostle's name.
The order of the words is as follows: He is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of all creation, because by Him all things were created in heaven and on earth, visible and invisible, whether Thrones, or Dominions, or Principalities, or Powers.
All things were created through Him and in Him, and He is before all things.
Colossians chapter one, verses fifteen and sixteen.
The image of the invisible God is an order from nothing, and it began at a certain time.
He is the firstborn of all creation, where the order of the unknown creation is expressed through him.
But does he not follow the firstborn of all creation?
Because in him, all things in heaven and on earth were established.
This means that the material of all visible and invisible elements of the universe was created and established through him.
Therefore, all things exist through him and in him.
Hence, he is the firstborn of all creation because, from the beginning, all the beginnings of what he would create were established in him.
However, he is not first in number in the order of creatures.
He is the image of the invisible God, always existing with the power of creation within himself.
He became the firstborn of those things that would be created through him, visible and invisible, in heaven and on earth.
The Trinity is presented in a confusing way.
Indeed, the narrative of the Trinity is similarly misleading.
They have separated the Son from the Father with impious and malicious words, attributing authority to two separate entities.
A third is counted in the Spirit.
When the Father is in the Son and the Son is in the Father, the Holy Spirit receives from both.
In this expression of the Spirit, the unity of this sacred and inviolable Trinity is proclaimed.
However, heresy gives birth to division when pronouncing the Trinity.
The Nicene Creed is very precise.
The diligent and perfect discourse of the Nicene Creed, with its strict truth, has concluded all heretical ideas.
It states: We believe in one God the Father, and in one Son, his Jesus Christ.
Both are one, and each is one, in the personal name of the Father.
In the Son, he is one because he is one from both.
True God from true God teaches both power and naming with equal truth in both.
Neither should anything different be considered in either, since both are one, God from God, and true from true.
Since there is one in both.
The phrase "born, not made" emphasizes the difference between being born and being made. Being made suggests coming from nothing, while being born indicates coming from a father.
Those who are born share the nature of their origin, while what is made is created.
So, creation doesn't start from nothing, but birth originates from a parent.
The term "of" one substance with the Father," known as homoousion in Greek, means that only eternity is like itself, and what always exists is in God.
This clarifies the essence of the Lord Jesus Christ to protect against any heretical distortions.
Essence refers to what always exists, needing no external support, and is called substance because it contains and maintains its eternal power.
When He says, "I" and the Father are one" (John 10:30); and "Whoever has seen me has seen the Father" (John 14:9); and again: "I am in the Father, and the Father is in me" (John 14:11); and "I came from the Father" (John 16:28): it signifies equality, both in God who is unbegotten and in God who is begotten.
The same eternal substance is present in both.
What descended, became incarnate, was made man, rose on the third day, ascended into heaven, and is coming to judge the living and the dead, are the sacraments of our salvation.
Therefore, the Son of God is constant and unchanging, bringing glory to corruption rather than tarnishing eternity by assuming human form.
Anathema to those who claim He was made from nothing, which the Greeks call ex ouk onton, and who say: "There was a time when He was not," or "Before He was born, He was not," as these beliefs curse the eternal nature of Christ's divine origin.
To spread this faith to everyone, Athanasius, who was a deacon at the Council of Nicaea and later became the bishop of Alexandria, was a strong supporter and fought against the Arian plague throughout Egypt by steadfastly holding to the truth.
Because of this, false accusations were made against him, with testimonies sworn against him.
The matter was later judged by the faithful in court decisions.
It will be very informative to understand what the speech to Emperor Constantius by the Council of Sardica in the year 647 said after Athanasius was cleared.
Fragment Three (Alias Two of Part Two)
The Beginning of the Decree of the Synod of Eastern Bishops at Serdica, from the Arian Side, Sent to Africa (Published in Three Hundred Forty-Seven)
To Gregory, bishop of Alexandria; the bishop of Nicomedia; the bishop of Carthage; the bishop of Campania; the bishop of Naples in Campania; the bishop of Rimini in Campania; the bishop of Salona in Dalmatia; Amphion, Donatus, Desiderius, Fortunatus, Euthicius, Maximus, Sinferuntius, and all our fellow priests, presbyters, and deacons throughout the world; and all who are under heaven in the holy Catholic Church.
The bishops who have gathered from various provinces of the East: namely, the province of Thebaid, the province of Palestine, Arabia, Phoenicia, Syria, Mesopotamia, Cilicia, Isauria, Cappadocia, Galatia, Pontus, Bithynia, Pamphylia, Paphlagonia, Caria, Phrygia, Pisidia, and from the islands of the Cyclades, Lydia, Asia, Europe, Hellespont, Thrace, and Emimontu, have convened in the city of Serdica, offering eternal salvation in the Lord.
A false love for unity and traditions to be observed.
Indeed, we all have an unwavering prayer, beloved brothers, that the holy and Catholic Church of the Lord, free from all dissension and schism, may preserve the unity of the spirit and the bond of charity everywhere through true faith.
But also to hold, embrace, guard, and maintain an unblemished life is indeed right for all who call upon the Lord, especially for bishops who preside over the most holy churches.
Secondly, it is vital that the rule of the Church and the sacred tradition of our forefathers and judgments remain firm and solid forever.
They should not be disturbed by us or by new sects emerging, or by twisted traditions, especially when appointing or expounding bishops.
This is to ensure that we uphold the evangelical and sacred precepts commanded to the holy and most blessed Apostles and to our ancestors, which have been kept by us until this day and are still being maintained.
The Teachings of Marcellus.
In recent times, a certain Marcellus of Galatia emerged, considered more dangerous than all heretics.
With a sacrilegious mindset and profane speech, he tries to limit the eternal and timeless kingdom of Christ the Lord.
He claims that the Lord began His reign 400 years ago and that it will end with the world's demise.
He also boldly asserts that during the conception of the body, Christ became the image of the invisible God and then became bread, the door, and life.
Marcellus doesn't just rely on words or eloquence; everything conceived with his sacrilegious mind and uttered with a blasphemous mouth is compiled in a book filled with blasphemies and curses.
He adds many worse things, slandering the divine Scriptures with his interpretations and wicked mind, showing openly and clearly that he is a heretic.
He mixes his claims with certain impurities, sometimes blending with the falsehoods of Sabellius, the malice of Paul of Samosata, and the blasphemies of Montanus, the leader of all heretics.
He combines them into one confusion, turning to another gospel, which is not another, as the blessed Paul condemns:
"But even if an angel from heaven should preach a gospel other than the one you accepted, let them be under God's curse."
(Galatians 1:8).
The first condemnation of the same.
The Church's archive preserves the critique of his doctrine.
There was significant concern among our parents and ancestors about this sacrilegious preaching.
In the city of Constantinople, during the revered reign of Emperor Constantine, a council of bishops from many eastern provinces gathered with the aim of reforming a man deeply entrenched in wrongdoing through wise guidance.
They hoped that, after being corrected with utmost holiness, he would turn away from his sacrilegious preaching.
However, despite their persistent efforts to reprimand and lovingly urge him for a long time, they made no progress.
After numerous corrections, they could achieve nothing because he continued to contradict the true faith and opposed the Catholic Church with malicious defiance.
Consequently, everyone began to shun and avoid him, recognizing that he was led astray by sin and was self-condemned.
They condemned him through ecclesiastical actions to prevent him from contaminating the flock of Christ with his harmful influence.
At that time, they also documented some of his most perverse thoughts against the true faith and the holy Church for future generations' memory and caution, placing these records in the Church's archives.
These were the initial acts of the heretic Marcellus according to his impiety, but worse followed.
For which of the faithful could believe or tolerate what he did and wrote, deeds that were justly anathematized?
There is a book of judgments written by the bishops against him, in which even those currently allied with him, like Marcellus, and supporters such as Protogenes, bishop of the city of Serdica, and the one from Syracuse, signed their names within the judgment.
Their signatures affirm the most holy faith that should remain unaltered, and that the holy Church should not be undermined by false preaching, to prevent a plague and the gravest harm to souls from affecting everyone.
As Paul says: Galatians Chapter One, Verse Eight, if we or an angel from heaven preach to you any other gospel than what you have received, let them be accursed.
Marcellus, who was condemned by several bishops, has been accepted back into communion.
We are truly amazed that some, who claim to be church leaders, have welcomed him back, even though he dares to preach a different Gospel than what is true.
They don't investigate the blasphemies recorded in his book, nor do they align with those who have thoroughly examined everything and rightly condemned him.
Marcellus, considered a heretic by his own people, sought help from elsewhere to deceive those unaware of him and his harmful writings.
Whatever he does among them, he hides his impious writings and profane ideas, presenting lies as truth, and taking advantage of the simple and innocent.
Under the guise of church authority, he has led many church leaders astray, bringing them under his control, and introduced the heretical sect of Sabellius.
He deceives them with clever tricks, reviving the schemes and deceptions of Paul of Samosata.
Marcellus' foreign tradition is mixed with all the heretical sects mentioned earlier.
Therefore, all the holy leaders of the Church gathered, remembering the words of the Lord Christ, who said:
"Beware of false prophets, who come to you in sheep's clothing, but inwardly are ravenous wolves. You will recognize them by their fruits" (Matthew 7:15-16).
To avoid and shun such people, to not easily communicate with them, to recognize them by their actions, and to pre-condemn them based on their sacrilegious writings.
We now greatly fear that in our times it will be fulfilled what is written:
"While men slept, his enemy came and sowed weeds among the wheat" (Matthew 13:25).
For when those who should be vigilant in guarding the Church are not watchful, false words that mimic the truth completely overturn what is right.
Marcello is denied communion.
Therefore, having fully understood Marcello's sect and crimes from his book, we have written to you, beloved brothers, advising that you neither admit Marcello nor those who join him to the communion of the holy Church.
Remember the prophet David, who says:
"I said to those who commit crimes, do not commit crimes; and to sinners, do not lift your horn.
Do not lift your horn on high, do not speak wickedly against the Lord" (Psalm 74:5-6).
And heed Solomon, who says:
"Do not move the ancient boundaries that your fathers have set" (Proverbs 22:28).
Given these things, do not follow the wicked errors of Marcello, and reject the unjust teachings against the Lord Christ that he has spread, so that you do not become participants in blasphemies and crimes.
But for the sake of brevity, let us discuss Marcello only to this extent.
Crimes fabricated against Athanasius.
Regarding Athanasius, the former bishop of Alexandria, consider what has been done.
He was gravely accused of sacrilege against God and profanation of the holy Church's mysteries.
He broke the cup dedicated to God and Christ with his own hands, shattered the revered altar, overturned the priest's seat, and even demolished the basilica, the house of God, the Church of Christ, down to the ground.
He also handed over a presbyter, a serious and just man named Narchen (Ischyram), to military custody.
Furthermore, he was accused of insults, violence, murder, and even the killing of bishops.
During the most sacred days of Easter, he acted tyrannically, allied with leaders and counts.
Because of him, some were imprisoned, others were tortured with whips and scourges, and 652 others were forced by various torments to join his sacrilegious communion.
Nor were these acts committed by the innocent, hoping that, through the leaders and judges and even through the prisons, he and his faction could prevail.
He forced unwilling people to join his communion through beatings and various tortures.
He compelled those who resisted and instilled fear in them in a tyrannical manner.
These accusations made by his accusers were indeed serious and bitter.
Events at Tyre concerning Athanasius.
Because of these issues, it seemed necessary to first call a council at Caesarea in Palestine in the year 334, but it was not held.
Since neither he nor his followers attended that council, it was convened again the following year, in 335, at Tyre because of his alleged crimes.
Bishops from Macedonia, Pannonia, Bithynia, and all parts of the East came, compelled by the emperor's command.
Upon learning of Athanasius's alleged misdeeds, they did not blindly believe the accusers.
Instead, they selected distinguished and respected bishops from their council and sent them to investigate the events for which Athanasius was accused.
These bishops, after witnessing everything firsthand and uncovering the truth, returned to the council and confirmed with their testimony that the crimes attributed to him were true.
Therefore, they passed a fitting sentence on Athanasius for his crimes.
As a result, he fled from Tyre and appealed to the emperor.
The emperor listened, and after conducting an inquiry and recognizing all his misdeeds, sentenced him to exile in Trier.
With these events unfolding, while Athanasius was justly condemned to exile for his criminal actions-being sacrilegious against God, profane in sacred mysteries, violent in the destruction of basilicas, and a dreadful persecutor of innocent bishops and brothers-the bishops upheld the authority of the law, the canon of the Church, and the holy tradition of the apostles in rejecting such evils.
Athanasius's return from exile.
After arranging his return from exile following his condemnation, he arrived in Alexandria from Gaul after a long time, in the year 338.
Disregarding past actions, he engaged even more aggressively in wickedness.
Compared to what came next, his initial wrongdoings were minor.
On his journey back, he undermined the church by restoring some excommunicated bishops, promising others a return to their positions, and appointing bishops from among non-believers, all while the priests remained safe and unharmed.
Through battles and killings by pagans, he completely disregarded the laws and succumbed to despair.
Consequently, through force, murder, and war, he plundered the basilicas of the Alexandrians.
A holy and virtuous priest, Gregory, was appointed in his place by the council's judgment, specifically the Antiochene Council in 341.
Yet, like a barbarian enemy and sacrilegious plague, he brought in pagan people, burned the temple of God, destroyed the altar, and secretly fled the city.
Crimes were falsely attributed to other bishops who returned from exile.
The consecrated Body of the Lord and the completed sacrifice were involved.
But if anyone hears about Paul, once the bishop of the city of Constantinople, after his return from exile, they will shudder.
Indeed, in Ancyra of the province of Galatia, after the return of the heretic Marcellus, there were incidents of house burnings and various kinds of wars.
Priests were dragged naked to the forum, and, with tears and sorrow, it must be said, the consecrated Body of the Lord was shamelessly hung around the priests' necks.
He publicly stripped the holiest virgins dedicated to God and Christ in the forum, in the middle of the city, exposing them with horrendous disgrace as the crowds gathered.
In the city of Gaza in the province of Palestine, after his return, Asclepas destroyed the altar and incited many seditions.
Furthermore, in Hadrianopolis, after his return, Lucius ordered the sacrifice prepared by holy and virtuous priests to be, if it can be said, thrown to the dogs.
Given these circumstances, do we still believe that the sheep of Christ are entrusted to such great wolves?
Shall we make the members of Christ members of fornication?
God forbid.
The crimes of Athanasius.
He was accepted by Julius and the bishops of Italy.
Athanasius traveled through various parts of the world, deceitfully leading some people astray with his flattery, deceiving innocent bishops who were unaware of his actions or Egyptians who didn't know of his deeds.
By begging for letters from others, he disturbed peaceful churches or invented new ones as he pleased.
However, this had no power against the judgment already established by the most holy and illustrious bishops.
The commendation of those who were neither judges in the council nor familiar with the council's judgment, nor present when Athanasius was heard, could neither be valid nor helpful to him.
Finally, when he realized these efforts were futile, he went to Julius in Rome and to some bishops of Italy.
Deceiving them with false letters, he was easily received into communion by them.
Then they began to work, not so much for him, but for their own actions, which they had rashly communicated, believing in him.
If those letters were from some people, they were not from those who were either judges or had sat in the council.
And even if they were from some people, they should never have hastily believed those who spoke for themselves.
But the judges, who had sentenced him, chose not to believe.
He was deposed by the Arians who defend themselves.
Therefore, because others were also exposed for their crimes in court, they are now joined with Marcellus and Athanasius.
However, Asclepas was stripped of his bishopric honor seventeen years ago, in the year three hundred and thirty.
Then Paul, Lucius, and all those associated with such individuals traveled through foreign regions, persuading the judges not to believe those who had rightly passed judgment against them, so that through this kind of exchange they might arrange a return to the bishopric.
They didn't defend themselves in the very places where they had sinned, nor in nearby areas where they had accusers.
Instead, they tried to overturn a fair judgment by going to foreigners who were far from their own regions and unaware of the facts.
They cleverly did this, knowing that many judges, accusers, and witnesses had passed away after so many judgments.
They thought they could restart the trial, wanting to present their case to us, who neither excused nor judged them.
Those who judged them have already gone to the Lord.
They are accused of wanting to submit Easterners to Westerners.
They even wanted to have Eastern bishops act as judges and came as defenders when their defense was not valid, especially since they couldn't be defended when their accusers confronted them face to face.
They thought they could introduce a new law where Eastern bishops would be judged by Westerners.
They wanted the Church's judgment to be established by those who were not so much concerned about them as about their own actions.
Since ecclesiastical discipline never accepted such wrongdoing, we ask you, beloved Brothers, to also condemn with us the wicked destruction and deadly attempts of the lost.
They seemed to agree with those they had condemned.
For even when Athanasius was still a bishop, he himself condemned Asclepas by his own judgment.
And Marcellus similarly never communicated with them.
Paul indeed participated in Athanasius's explanation, and writing the judgment with his own hand, he also condemned him along with the others.
And as long as each of them was a bishop, they confirmed their own judgments.
But when each of them was worthily expelled from the Church for their own merits for different reasons and at different times, they made a greater agreement through a single conspiracy, forgiving each other the offenses which, when they were bishops, they condemned with divine authority.
The Beginnings of the Sardica Council.
Athanasius, traveling to Italy and Gaul, sought a trial for himself.
After some of his accusers, witnesses, and judges had passed away, he believed he would eventually be heard again, thinking the passage of time would obscure his alleged crimes.
Julius, the bishop of Rome, along with Maximus, Hosius, and many others in their group, arranged for a council to be held at Sardica, with the emperor's support.
We arrived at Sardica upon the emperor's summons.
Once there, we discovered that Athanasius, Marcellus, and others who had been expelled and condemned for their crimes were meeting and discussing with Hosius and Protogenes, and even participating in the celebration of the divine mysteries.
Protogenes, the bishop of Sardica, was not ashamed to associate with the heretic Marcellus, despite having denounced Marcellus's sect and beliefs at the council, subscribing to the judgments of the bishops multiple times.
Thus, it became clear that by associating with Marcellus, Protogenes essentially condemned himself by his own actions.
The Efforts of the Easterners to Expel Athanasius and Others from the Synod.
Adhering to ecclesiastical discipline and wanting to offer a chance for redemption, we instructed those with Protogenes and Hosius to exclude the condemned from their assembly and not associate with sinners.
Then, they were to listen with us to the judgments previously made against them, as Marcellus's writings were self-evidently heretical and required no further accusation.
We urged them not to let their episcopal position obscure their corrupt intentions.
However, they resisted these instructions for reasons unknown to us.
They refused to separate themselves from Marcellus's sect, placing the crimes of Athanasius and others above the faith and peace of the church.
We, 80 bishops, who traveled from distant provinces to Serdica with great effort to establish peace for the Church, witnessed these events with tears.
It was significant that they outright refused to dismiss those whom our predecessors had rightfully condemned for their crimes.
Therefore, we found it wrong to associate with them, nor did we wish to mix the holy sacraments of the Lord with the profane, adhering to the principles of ecclesiastical discipline.
Since they did not dismiss Ossius and Protogenes from among them, possibly due to a guilty conscience, they greatly feared this becoming public; none dared to judge them, lest they also condemn themselves for associating with those they should not.
We urged them repeatedly not to shake the foundations, overturn the law, disturb divine rights, or confuse matters, and not to disrupt even a small part of the Church's tradition for peace.
They should not introduce a new sect or favor those from the West over the Eastern bishops and their holy councils.
Yet, they ignored our pleas, threatened us, and promised to vindicate Athanasius and others deemed wicked, as if they could say or do anything else, having accepted all the wicked into their company.
They proposed arrogantly, driven more by audacity and recklessness than by legitimate reason.
Seeing that those who accept the condemned fall into offense and crime as violators of heavenly laws, they tried to establish a judgment with such authority that they wanted to call themselves judges of judges and, if possible, reopen the verdicts of those already with God.
We, however, pleaded with them for many days to reject the condemned from among them and join the holy Church, agreeing with the fathers who speak the truth.
However, they completely refused to agree to this.
Instead, they suggested sending delegates from both sides to Mareotis.
During our discussions, five bishops from our side, who were among the six initially sent to Mareotis, stepped forward.
They suggested that bishops from both councils be sent to the locations where Athanasius had allegedly committed his crimes and scandals.
This way, under God's witness, everything could be accurately documented.
If our reports to the council were proven false, we would accept the blame and would not raise any complaints to the emperors, the council, or any bishop.
However, if what we previously stated was confirmed to be true, then those from your group who communicated with Athanasius after his condemnation, as well as his supporters and defenders, including Marcellus, should be presented.
No one from your group should then complain to the emperors, the council, or any bishop.
This proposal from our side was something that Ossius, Protogenes, and all their associates feared accepting.
The people gathered at Sardica are facing criticism.
A large crowd, including various criminals and outcasts, came to Sardica from Constantinople and Alexandria: individuals guilty of murder, bloodshed, robbery, looting, and numerous unspeakable acts.
Among them were those who desecrated altars, burned churches, and plundered homes; they profaned God's mysteries and betrayed Christ's sacraments.
These individuals, while promoting the wicked doctrines of heretics against the Church's faith, brutally murdered wise presbyters, deacons, and priests of God.
Ossius and Protogenes gathered these people in their assembly, honoring them while despising us, the deacons and priests of God, because we refused to associate with such individuals.
They spread falsehoods among the common people and nations, claiming that our discord was due to human presumption, not God's cause.
By mixing divine and human matters and tying private issues to ecclesiastical affairs, they created chaos and discord, accusing us of causing a severe schism unless we communicated with them, which we considered sinful.
They frequently shouted these accusations.
We steadfastly refused to communicate with them unless they rejected those we condemned and properly honored the Council of the East.
They complain about the wicked being granted communion.
You can learn about what they did or what kind of council they held from this.
For instance, Protogenes, as previously mentioned, anathematized Marcellus and Paul but later accepted them into communion.
They also included Dionysius from Elica in the province of Achaia, whom they had previously exposed.
Together, both accusers and accused, judges and defendants, they handled the divine mysteries.
Bassus, originally from the city of Diocletian, was found guilty of various crimes and immoral acts, leading to his rightful deportation from Syria.
He was made a bishop, but his behavior became even more corrupt, resulting in his exposure and condemnation.
Yet today, he seems to be aligned with those very people.
Protogonus of Thessalonica frequently accused him of disgraceful deeds and crimes, claiming he had mistresses both in the past and present, and refused to associate with him.
However, he has now been accepted into friendship, seemingly cleansed by being with worse individuals, and is considered righteous among them.
Asclepas, upon arriving in Constantinople due to Paul, stirred up events in the church after a series of horrifying incidents.
Despite the murders that stained the altars with blood and the destruction of pagans, he continues to associate with Paul, the cause of these events.
Those who connect with Paul through Asclepas receive writings from him and send them back.
From this gathering of the lost, what kind of council could be formed, where instead of punishing their crimes, they acknowledge them?
They refuse to be associated with these acts.
Unlike us, who lead the most holy churches and guide the people, forgiving what should not be forgiven: they even forgave the crimes and blasphemies of Marcellus, Athanasius, and others, which were forbidden to be forgiven.
For it is written, "If a man sins against another, they will pray for him to the Lord; but if a man sins against God, who will pray for him?" (First Samuel 2:25).
But we do not have such a custom, nor does the Church of God (First Corinthians 11:16).
We do not allow anyone to teach these things or introduce new traditions, lest we be called traitors of the faith and betrayers of the divine Scriptures, which is forbidden, and be condemned by the Lord and by people.
They blame the Westerners for the schism.
But those mentioned earlier were also plotting against us.
Knowing we couldn't join them with the help of the wicked, they tried to intimidate us with writings from the Emperors, hoping to force us into their communion unwillingly.
They aimed to disrupt the deep and lasting peace of the Church worldwide because of Athanasius and Marcellus, through whom the Lord's name is blasphemed among the nations.
If they had any fear of God, they should have abandoned their wicked presumption to prevent this storm, which they started, from continuing, lest their actions cause the Church to divide against itself.
And if those fighting on their behalf had any fear of God, even if nothing condemnable was found among them, they should still loathe and dread that their actions are tearing apart the Church's unity, overthrowing profound peace with insane rage and a desire for honors.
The Church denies the power to restore those who have been deposed.
Seeing how things were unfolding, each of us decided to return to our homeland.
We chose to write from Serdica, report what happened, and declare our judgment.
We cannot receive Athanasius and Marcellus, who lived wickedly and blasphemed the Lord, back into the honor of the episcopate, as they have long been exposed and condemned.
Those who are crucifying the true Son of God and publicly declaring him again have pierced him with bitter blows, as stated in Hebrews chapter six verse six.
One of them, by blaspheming the Son of God and his kingdom, has died an eternal death once.
The other, sinning against the body of the Lord and his mysteries in a profane manner and committing other outrageous acts, was expelled and condemned by the judgment of the bishops.
Therefore, since we cannot depart from the tradition of our ancestors, as the Church has not taken such authority, nor received such power from God, we do not restore those mentioned to the honor and dignity of the Church, and we rightly condemn those who do.
However, we do not welcome into the Church those who have been justly condemned, whether in the past or more recently, in accordance with the laws of God, the traditions of our ancestors, and Church disciplines.
We believe in the prophet who says, "Do not move the ancient boundary stones set by your ancestors" Proverbs 22:28. Therefore, we never disturb what is fixed and solid; instead, we preserve what has been established by our forefathers.
Those they decide should be denied communion. Therefore, after much consideration, beloved brothers, we openly instruct you that none of you should be misled into communing with, that is, Ossius, Protogenes, Athanasius, Marcellus, Asclepas, Paul, Julius; nor with any of those condemned and rejected from the holy Church, nor with their associates, who commune with them either directly or through writings. Consequently, you should never write to them, nor receive writings from them.
Now, regarding what remains, we pray, beloved Brothers, that you ensure the unity of the Church and everlasting peace; choose holy bishops in whom there is both complete faith and a holy life. Shun those who have been stripped of the honor of the episcopate for their crimes and wish to reclaim the position they rightfully lost for their deeds. Instead, denounce those whom you see committing worse crimes after their wrongdoing. They do not heed the Lord saying, "You have sinned, cease" Sirach 21:1.
They do not know how to stop and become stronger in their wickedness; the deeper they sink into the abyss of vices, the more they overturn the world. Indulging in seditions, they bring the fiercest wars and persecutions upon the holy Churches and strive, in a tyrannical manner, to captivate the people of the Lord under their dominion.
They are unjustly demanding the convening of such a council.
Recognize their worst intentions from these actions, as they've caused such a storm in the world that nearly the entire East and West are troubled.
Everyone is leaving their church duties, abandoning the people of God, and neglecting the very teachings of the Gospel.
We, elderly and frail in body, unwell and sick, have been forced to travel from afar, abandoning our sick on the journey because of a few wicked individuals who were rightly condemned long ago for wrongfully seeking the leadership of the Church.
The empire, religious emperors, tribunes, and leaders are concerned about the dire state of the republic and the life and status of the bishops.
The people are not silent either.
All the brotherhood in every province anxiously awaits the outcome of this storm of troubles.
The public service itself is worn down to nothing.
And what more?
The rise and fall of the world are completely overturned and disturbed by a harsh and fierce storm because of one, two, or a few wicked people who think impiously and live shamefully, in whom no seeds of religion have taken root.
If they had, they would imitate the prophet who said, Jonah "Pick me up and throw me into the sea, and it will calm down for you, for this storm has come upon you because of me."
But they do not imitate this because they do not follow the righteous.
Thus, the leaders of all the wicked are seeking the leadership of the Church as if it were some kind of tyrannical kingdom.
Judgments of councils should not be reconsidered.
Neither do they seek this for the sake of justice.
They do not serve the Church, those who attempt to dissolve divine laws and rights, and the decrees of others.
Therefore, they were trying to introduce this novelty, which the ancient custom of the Church abhors, that whatever Eastern bishops might have decided in a council would be reopened by Western bishops; similarly, whatever Western bishops decided would be undone by Eastern bishops.
But they were pursuing this from their own most depraved mindset.
The decrees of all councils that were justly and lawfully enacted are affirmed by the actions of our ancestors.
A council held in the city of Rome under the heretics Novatus, Sabellius, and Valentinus was confirmed by the Easterners.
Similarly, what was decreed in the East under Paul of Samosata was agreed upon by everyone.
Therefore, we urge you, beloved brothers, to consider the order of church discipline and strive for the peace of the whole world by rebuking those who associate with the wicked and completely removing the evil from the churches.
This way, as the storm rages because of them, Christ the Lord may command all winds and maritime storms to cease, granting the holy Church perpetual and tranquil peace.
They condemn the prominent figures from the West.
We, however, intend no harm to anyone, but we uphold the precepts of the law.
For we have been gravely wronged and poorly treated by those who sought to disturb the rule of the Catholic Church with their depravity.
Yet, with the fear of God in our hearts and considering the true and just judgment of Christ, we have shown no favoritism, nor have we spared anyone, to maintain church discipline.
Hence, the whole council condemned Julius of Rome, Hosius, Protogenes, Gaudentius, and Maximinus from Trier according to the most ancient law.
They were supporters of the communion of Marcellus and Athanasius and others involved in the murders of Paul of Constantinople and his bloody acts.
Protogenes was anathematized along with Marcellus, having frequently signed the sentence against him or his book, and those who judged Paul of Constantinople but later communicated with him.
Gaudentius, disregarding his predecessor Cyriacus who justly signed the sentences imposed on the wicked, got involved with the crimes of Paul, whom he shamelessly defended.
Julius, bishop of the city of Rome, was regarded as a chief and leader of wickedness because he was the first to open the door of communion to those who were guilty and condemned, thereby allowing others to disregard divine laws.
He presumptuously and boldly defended Athanasius, a man whose accusers and witnesses he did not even know.
He also supported Ossius due to the aforementioned reasons, particularly for his mistreatment of the blessedly remembered Marcus, to whom he had always inflicted severe injuries.
Furthermore, he defended all evil individuals who had been rightfully condemned for their crimes with all his strength.
Ossius lived in the East among the wicked and the lost, notably forming a disgraceful friendship with Paulinus, a former bishop of Dacia.
Paulinus had been accused of sorcery, expelled from the Church, and to this day remains in apostasy, living publicly with concubines and engaging in fornication with prostitutes.
Macedonius, a bishop and confessor from Mopsuestia, burned the Paulinus books of crimes.
Ossius also aligned himself with Eustasius and Quimatios, infamous for their shameful lives, though nothing further needs to be said about their disgrace, as their downfall was self-evident to all.
From the very beginning, Ossius supported these and other such individuals, always favoring the wicked and acting against the Church by aiding the enemies of God.
Maximinus of Trier refused to accept our fellow bishops sent to Gaul.
He also became the first to communicate with Paul of Constantinople, a wicked and utterly depraved man.
Maximinus caused the great disaster of Paul being recalled to the city of Constantinople, which led to numerous murders.
Therefore, he is responsible for the bloodshed that occurred when Paul, a condemned man, was brought back to the city.
Because of these reasons, the council rightly decided to depose and condemn Julius of Rome, Ossius, and the others previously mentioned.
Therefore, beloved brothers, you must guard yourselves against them and avoid them entirely.
Do not allow them into communion with you, nor accept their letters or send them any letters of fellowship.
Because those who were with Ossius tried to undermine the Catholic and Apostolic faith by introducing a new sect derived from the teachings of Marcellus, mixed with Sabellius and Paul, creating confusion, we found it necessary to affirm the faith of the Catholic Church, which Ossius and the heretics aligned with Marcellus, denied.
Consequently, upon receiving our letters, each of you must agree to this decision and sign our decrees with your own subscription.
Our faith is as follows: We believe in one God, the Father Almighty, creator and maker of all, from whom every family in heaven and on earth is named.
And in His only-begotten Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, who was begotten from the Father before all ages, God from God, Light from Light, through whom all things were made, both in heaven and on earth, visible and invisible.
The Word who is wisdom and power, and life, and true light, who, in the last times, became incarnate for us, born of the holy Virgin Mary, crucified, died, and was buried; on the third day, He rose from the dead, ascended into heaven, and sits at the right hand of the Father, and will come at the end of the world to judge the living and the dead, rewarding each according to their works; His kingdom will continue unceasingly for all eternity.
He is seated at the right hand of the Father, not only in this age but also in the age to come.
We believe in the Holy Spirit, the Comforter, whom He sent to the Apostles after His ascension into heaven, teaching and instructing them about everything, through whom souls that faithfully believe in Him are sanctified.
The holy and Catholic Church condemns as heretics those who claim that the Son of God came from what did not exist, or from another substance and not from God; or who say there was a time or age when the Son did not exist.
In the same way, the holy and catholic Church condemns and opposes those who claim there are three gods, or that Christ is not God, or that Christ did not exist before time began, nor was He the Son of God.
It also condemns those who assert that the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit are the same person, or that the Son was not begotten, or that the Father did not beget the Son through His wisdom and will.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Stephen, Bishop of Antioch in the province of Syria, also known as Sprecila.
Olimpius, Bishop of Doliche.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Gerontius, Bishop of Lampania.
Menophantus, Bishop of Ephesus.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Paul, Bishop.
In 665, Eulalius, Bishop of Amantia.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Macedonius, Bishop of Amaraquetias, also known as Mopsuestia.
Thelaphius, Bishop of Chalcedon.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Acacius, Bishop of Caesarea.
Theodore, Bishop of Heraclea.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Quintianus, Bishop of Taxia.
Marcus, Bishop of Arethusa.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Cyrotus, Bishop of Roeum.
Eugeus, Bishop of Lisicia.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Antony, Bishop of Zeuma.
Antony, Bishop of Docimum.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Dion, Bishop of Caesarea.
Vitalis, Bishop of Tyre.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Eudoxius, Bishop of Germanicia.
Dionysius, Bishop of Alexandria province.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Macedonius, Bishop of Virita.
Eusebius, Bishop of Dorlana.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Basil, Bishop of Ancyra.
Proheresius, Bishop of Sinope.
I wish you well in the Lord.
Bishop Eustacius from Epiphania sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Pancratius from Parnassus sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Eusebius from Pergamum sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Sabinianus from Cathimera sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Bitinicus from Zelon sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Dominius from Palladiano sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Pison from Troas sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Cartherius from Aspona sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Filetus from Juliopolis sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Quirius from Mareota sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Thimasarcus sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Eusebius from Mignenia, also known as Magnienia, sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Quirius from Philadelphia sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Timotheus sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Euthemon from Thaneos sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Callenicus from Pelosio sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Leucadas from Ilium sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Noconius from Troas sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Adamantius from Cius sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Eddesius from Cos sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Theodolus from Neocaesarea sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Sion sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Theogenes from Lycia sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Florentius from Ancyra sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Isaac from Lueto sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Eudemon has signed on his behalf and sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Agapius from Theriaco, according to another source, Therinco, sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Bassus from Car sends his blessings in the Lord.
Bishop Narcissus from Anapolis sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Embracius from Miletus also sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Lucius from Babtinus extends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Nonnius from Laodicea sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Pantagatus from Gaul, possibly Galatia, sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Flaccus from Hierapolis sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Sysimius from Perga extends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Diogenes sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Cresconius sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Nestorius sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Emmonius extends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Eugenius sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Antonius from Gusia extends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Demophilus from Beroea sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Euticius from Philippopolis sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Severus from Cabula sends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Timotheus from Anchialus extends his greetings in the Lord.
Bishop Valens from Mursa sends his greetings in the Lord.
The decree of the Synod of the Eastern Bishops at Sardica, from the Arian side, which was sent to Africa, is now concluded.
Fragment Four (Alias One of Part One)
Example of a Letter from Bishop Liberius of the City of Rome to the Eastern Bishops
To our most beloved brothers and fellow bishops throughout the East, Liberius, bishop of Rome, wishes you eternal health.
1.
Liberius extends his communion to the Easterners but denies it to Athanasius.
In my efforts to maintain peace and unity within the Churches, after receiving your letters of goodwill regarding Athanasius and others addressed to the late Bishop Julius, I followed the tradition of our elders.
I sent the priests of Rome-Lucius, Paul, and Helianus-to Alexandria, to meet Athanasius, asking him to come to Rome so we could determine the necessary Church discipline regarding him.
I also sent letters through these priests, stating that if he did not come, he would be considered outside the communion of the Roman Church.
The priests returned and reported that he refused to come.
Therefore, in response to your letters of goodwill about Athanasius, which you sent to us, know that with these letters I have established peace with all of you and with all bishops of the Catholic Church.
However, Athanasius remains outside my communion and that of the Roman Church, and is excluded from ecclesiastical correspondence.
2.
This letter was fabricated in vain.
Why?
What in these letters is not holy?
What does not come from the fear of God?
But Potamius and Epictetus, while enjoying condemning the bishop of Rome, as stated in the Council of Ariminum, refused to acknowledge these things-or dared to ignore them.
Even Fortunatianus, the bishop, sent the same letter again to various bishops, achieving nothing.
However, by denying communion to Athanasius, they ended up creating more trouble for themselves.
This turned the whole situation into a risk for them, as long as they didn't undermine the Council of Sardica.
At this council, Athanasius was acquitted, and the Arians were condemned.
Letters from all over Egypt and Alexandria reminded them that just as letters had been sent to Julius to restore communion to the exiled Athanasius, similar letters were now sent to Liberius.
These letters focused on defending him to ensure the matter was understood in context.
Fragment Six Hundred Seventy-One, Fragment Five (Also Part Two).
Letter of the Envoys Sent to Emperor Constantius by Liberius, Bishop of the City of Rome, Through Lucifer, Bishop (circa Year Three Hundred Fifty-Four)
Glorious Constantius Augustus, from Liberius the Bishop:
Liberius requests a council because he is being targeted by slanderous speeches spread among the people by Constantius.
I humbly ask you, most peaceful emperor, to lend me attentive ears, so that the intentions of my heart may become clear to your gentle spirit.
As a Christian emperor and son of the late, revered Constantine, I believe I deserve to obtain this without delay.
However, I realize my challenge lies in not being able to win back your favor, despite my repeated attempts at reconciliation.
The speech you sent to the people, which I must endure patiently, has deeply hurt me.
It astonishes me that your spirit, usually inclined towards mercy and, as it's written, never holds onto anger until the day's end, still holds indignation towards me.
Most devout emperor, I seek true peace with you-one not made up of deceptive words, but one reasonably confirmed by the teachings of the Gospels.
This is not only about the matter of Athanasius but many other issues that have arisen, for which I had asked your gentleness to convene a council.
Your sincere devotion to God desires that the cause of faith, where our first hope in God lies, be diligently examined, to ensure that those who should admire our devotion to God find no fault.
It would have been fitting for a worshiper of God, and worthy of your empire, governed and enhanced by Christ's piety, to grant us your kindness for the sake of reverence to the holy religion you prudently uphold.
He is falsely accused of suppressing the letters of the Eastern bishops and explains why he did not trust them.
Many hasten to tear apart the Church's members, falsely claiming that I suppressed the letters to hide the crimes of the one they were said to have condemned from being known to all.
What about those letters?
The ones from the Eastern and Egyptian bishops, all accusing Athanasius of the same things?
It's clear to everyone, and no one denies it, that we shared the letters from the Eastern bishops, read them to the Church, presented them to the council, and even responded to the Eastern bishops.
We didn't align our beliefs with theirs because, at the same time, a verdict from eighty Egyptian bishops opposed them, which we also reported and explained to the Italian bishops.
Therefore, it seemed against divine law to side with anyone when more bishops supported Athanasius.
Eusebius, who had been sent and rushed to Africa, left us these writings, if he owed faith to God: nevertheless, all these writings were later brought to Arles by Vincent, who had been sent with the others, so they wouldn't be missing to secure a council.
He clears himself of the charges fabricated by Constantius.
Your wisdom sees, therefore, that nothing unworthy of those serving God has entered my mind.
God is my witness, and the whole Church with its members is a witness, that I have rejected all worldly things by faith and fear in my God, as the evangelical and apostolic teachings instruct.
Not with reckless fury, but according to established and observed divine law, and living in another ecclesiastical ministry, I have fulfilled nothing out of boasting or a desire for glory that pertained to the law.
And to this office, God is my witness, I came reluctantly; in which I wish to remain, as long as I am in the world, without offending God.
And I have never completed my statutes, but the apostolic ones, so that they were always firm and kept.
Following the custom and order of the elders, I allowed nothing to be added to or taken away from the bishopric of the city of Rome: and keeping that faith, which ran through the succession of so many bishops, among whom many were martyrs, I always wish it to be preserved unblemished.
Since he can't communicate with the Easterners, the concern for the church and your own devotion finally persuade me to reveal the reason to your piety.
The Easterners seem to want to join in our peace.
But what kind of peace is it, most merciful emperor, when there are four bishops from their side-Demophilus, Macedonius, Eudoxius, and Martyrius-who, eight years ago, refused to condemn the heretical views of Arius at the council in Milan and left in anger?
If it is right to agree with their opinions, what danger might it pose?
Your fairness and mercy can judge.
It's not new what is now being subtly attempted under the guise of Athanasius's name.
There are letters from Bishop Alexander, sent long ago to Sylvester of holy memory, indicating that before Athanasius's ordination, he expelled eleven presbyters and deacons from the church because they followed Arius's heresy.
Now, some of them are said to have formed gatherings outside the Catholic Church, with which George in Alexandria is also claimed to communicate through letters.
So, what peace can there be, most tranquil emperor, if bishops are forced to follow the opinions of such people, as has now happened throughout Italy?
Here is another point, since your tranquility accepts it patiently.
There are letters from legates who had been sent to your mercy, which have recently arrived.
They indicate that due to the disturbance of all churches, they were willing to submit to the opinions of the Easterners, but proposed a condition: if those same people condemned Arius's heresy, they would be inclined to obey their opinions.
The agreement, as they indicate, is confirmed by written testimony, and a council is convened.
They receive responses with deliberation, stating that they cannot condemn Arius's doctrine, and that Athanasius should be deprived of communion, which was their only demand.
Hence, may your mercy also consider this, whether it should be carefully and thoroughly examined, while rightly preserving the law of the Catholic religion, whether the matter concerning the man should be diligently and thoroughly handled.
The council earnestly prays.
We repeatedly ask for your kindness and dedication to God, through His power, who has shown everyone His greatness in your defense against Magnentius back in the year 353, when he was defeated.
Keeping in mind the benefits from Him who governs your empire, we ask that these matters be thoroughly discussed in the assembly of bishops with careful consideration.
With God's favor and your peaceful times, and with your tranquility in agreement, we hope everything can be examined.
So, once it's confirmed by the judgment of the priests of God, and when all are in agreement on the declaration of faith, as confirmed by many bishops at Nicaea in the presence of your father of blessed memory, it can be preserved as an example for the future.
We hope that the Savior Himself, who sees the intentions of your mind, may rejoice in such a great undertaking, having rightly prioritized the cause of faith and peace even over the needs of the state.
Therefore, to appeal to your kindness, and hoping you will listen to our representations with a benevolent mind, it has been decided that my brother and fellow bishop, the holy man Lucifer, along with Pancratius the presbyter and Hilarius the deacon, should proceed.
We believe they can easily secure the council from your clemency for the peace of all the Catholic churches.
May the mercy of Almighty God protect you for us, most merciful and religious Augustus.
It ends.
Fragment Six (Alias Part One)
Liberius Before Going into Exile, Wrote This Uniform Letter to the Confessors, That Is, to Eusebius, Dionysius, and Lucifer Established in Exile (Year Three Hundred Fifty-Five)
Liberius congratulates the exiles.
Although, under the guise of peace, the enemy of humanity seems to have fiercely attacked the Church's members, you, most beloved priests in the Lord, have demonstrated through your outstanding and unique faith that you are pleasing to God here and have already been marked as martyrs for future glory.
So, how can I possibly express the merits of your virtue with praise and words of joy?
Torn between the sorrow of your absence and the joy of your glory, I truly cannot find the words, except that I know I can offer you more reassuring comfort if you believe that I have been cast into exile with you.
Indeed, I am quite saddened that a harsh necessity temporarily separates me from your company while I am still waiting in expectation.
I had wished, most devoted brothers, to be offered up for all of you first, so that your love might more greatly follow the example of glory through me.
But this shall be the reward of your merits, that you have first come to the illustrious glory of confession through the perseverance of faith.
Therefore, I ask your love to believe that I am with you in spirit and not to feel my absence, understanding that I am sufficiently grieved by being temporarily separated from your company.
You can know how much glory you have attained, particularly because those crowned during persecution could only feel the bloody swords of the persecutor.
Whereas you, devoted soldiers of God in every way, have even experienced false brothers as enemies and have borne victory over the treacherous.
The more their violence could grow in the world, the more rewards of praise are found to be conferred upon the holy priests.
Therefore, be secure in the heavenly promise.
He asks them to pray for him.
The deeds of Milan are something they want to learn from.
And since you have been brought closer to God, please lift me, your fellow priest and servant of God, to the Lord with your prayers.
Help me endure the attacks that come every day, so I can withstand these more serious challenges with greater tolerance.
May my faith remain strong and the status of the Catholic Church be preserved, so the Lord may find me worthy to stand equal to you.
Since I wish to know more faithfully what happened in that encounter, I ask your holiness to kindly share everything in writing.
This way, the mind tormented by various rumors, or the body's strength already weakened, can find relief through your encouragement.
And may God keep you safe, Brothers in the Lord.
TOn Vincentius of Capua, Written by Liberius to Caecilianus, Bishop of Spoleto (circa the Beginning of the Year Three Hundred Fifty-Four)
He laments the downfall of Vincentius.
I urge you, dearest Brother, not to let Vincentius's actions distract you from your good work.
Regarding Vincentius's downfall, he tells Hosius:
Since I cannot ignore your conscience, many bishops from Italy gathered, and together with me, appealed to the devout Emperor Constantius, requesting him to order, as previously agreed, that a council be held at Aquileia.
I inform Your Holiness that Vincentius of Capua, along with Marcellus, another bishop from Campania, undertook our mission.
I had great hope in him, believing he would uphold the cause well and often deliberate on the same matter with Your Holiness.
I believed his mission would preserve the pure Gospel of God.
However, not only did he achieve nothing, but he was also led into falsehood.
After this, overwhelmed by double sorrow, I resolved that I must devote myself more to God, lest I be seen as a recent informer or agree to judgments against the Gospel.
Liberius condemns Athanasius.
Despite everything Liberius had done or promised, he was exiled, rendering all efforts void.
He wrote to the heretical Arian transgressors who unjustly judged the holy orthodox bishop Athanasius.
To the most beloved brothers, priests, and fellow bishops in the East, Liberius writes around the end of the year 357.
For your holy faith, known to God and to people of goodwill, because of divine fear.
As the law states, "Judge rightly, sons of men," from Psalm 57 verse 2, I do not defend Athanasius.
But since the bishop of blessed memory, Julius, my predecessor, had accepted him, I feared being judged as a transgressor by someone.
When I realized, at the time God intended, that you had rightly condemned him, I immediately supported your decision.
I sent a letter about his condemnation through our brother Fortunatianus to be delivered to Emperor Constantius.
With Athanasius removed from communion with us, and with his letters not being accepted by me, I declare that I am in peace and unity with all of you, as well as the Eastern bishops and throughout the provinces.
He subscribes to the faith of Sirmium.
To assure you of my true faith through this letter, my lord and common brother Demophilus kindly explained your faith and the Catholic faith, which was discussed, explained, and accepted at Sirmium by many of our brothers and fellow bishops.
This is the Arian perfidy I noted, not apostasy.
Liberius follows: by all those who were present; I received this with a willing heart, did not contradict it, and agreed to it.
I follow it and hold it.
Again, anathema to you and a third time, traitor Liberius.
I believed I should request your holiness, since I am in agreement with you in all things, to kindly work with common counsel and effort, so that I may be released from exile and return to the seat entrusted to me.
Authors of his faith.
The perfidy described at Sirmium, which Liberius calls Catholic and was explained to him by Demophilus, was written by:
Narcissus, Theodorus, Basilius, Eudoxius, Demophilus, Cecropius, Silvanus, Ursacius, Valens, Evagrius, Hyrenius, Exuperantius, Terentianus, Bassus, Gaudentius, Macedonius, Marthus, Acticus, Julius, Surinus, Simplicius, and Junior, all heretics.
Likewise, Liberius from exile, Ursacius, Valens, and Germinius.
Liberius separated from communion with Athanasius.
Because I know you are children of peace, and you love the harmony and unity of the Catholic Church; therefore, not compelled by any necessity, with God as my witness, I say for the good of peace and harmony, which is preferred over martyrdom, I write to you, my beloved brothers.
Let your wisdom know that Athanasius, who was the bishop of the church in Alexandria, was condemned by me before I sent letters from the Eastern bishops to the court of the holy emperor, and he was separated from the communion of the Roman church, as all the priests of the Roman church can testify.
This was the only reason for my delay in sending letters about his name to our brothers and fellow bishops in the East, so that my envoys, whom I sent from the city of Rome to the court, and the bishops who were deported, could be recalled from exile if possible.
He earnestly requests to be sent back to Rome.
And I also want you to know that I asked brother Fortunatianus to go with my letters to the most merciful Emperor Constantius Augustus, asking that for the good of peace and harmony, in which his piety always rejoices, he orders me to return to the church entrusted to me by divine will: so that during his reign, the Roman church may not suffer any tribulation.
And you should know with a fair and simple mind, my beloved brothers, through these letters of mine, that I have peace with all of you bishops of the Catholic Church.
For you will gain great comfort on the day of retribution if peace is restored to the Roman church through you.
Moreover, I want you to inform our brothers and fellow bishops Epictetus and Auxentius that I have peace and ecclesiastical communion with them: I believe they will receive this gladly.
Whoever disagrees with our peace and harmony, which, by the will of God, is established throughout the world, should know that they are separated from our communion.
Anathema is declared by me against the traitor together with the Arians.
Also concerning the exile of Liberius to Vincentius (year three hundred and fifty-eight).
He's upset that Urbicus was taken from him.
I'm not teaching, but I'm reminding your holy spirit, dearest brother, that bad company corrupts good morals.
First Corinthians 15:33.
You're well aware of the plots of evil men, which is how I came to this struggle.
And pray 683 times that the Lord grants tolerance.
My beloved son Urbicus the deacon, whom I thought was my comfort, was taken from me by Venerius, the official in charge.
In his name, he seeks a return from exile.
I thought it was important to inform your Holiness that I've withdrawn from the dispute regarding Athanasius' name and have written to our brothers and fellow bishops in the East about his name.
Therefore, since, God willing, there is peace with you everywhere, please meet with all the bishops of Campania, inform them of this, and, with their collective support and your letter, write to the most gracious emperor about our unity and peace, so I may also be freed from great sadness.
And in his own hand: May God keep you safe, brother.
Also written in his own hand on the page: We have peace with all the Eastern bishops, and with you.
I'm resolved to God, you shall see: if you wish me to perish in exile, God will be the judge between me and you.
Fragment Seven (Also Second of the Part)
Title: Here Begins the Example of the Letter of Emperor Constantius to the Italian Bishops Who Convened at the Council of Ariminum (dated May Twenty-Seventh, Year Three Hundred Fifty-Nine)
Victor Constantius, the ever-triumphant Augustus, addresses the bishops.
Only matters of faith should be discussed at the Council.
Previous decrees, esteemed ones, uphold the sanctity of the law in church matters.
We have understood from the letters you sent that the same diligence should be applied:
since it aligns with the bishops' duty, and the safety of all people is strengthened by this foundation.
However, circumstances have led to the reestablishment of these decrees.
For no one would find it unnecessary to repeat established definitions, as frequent reminders are known to increase diligence.
Given these circumstances, you should acknowledge that matters of faith and unity need discussion, and ensure proper order is maintained in church matters.
For the prosperity of all people will flourish, and faithful harmony will be maintained when such questions are fully resolved, without stirring up concerns.
Regarding the Eastern bishops:
This matter should not extend your focus too far:
because your council is not authorized to define anything regarding the Eastern bishops.
Therefore, you should only discuss matters relevant to you:
and after swiftly completing everything, send ten delegates to my court with unanimous agreement, as indicated in previous letters.
These delegates could respond to any proposals from the Easterners or discuss matters of faith, ensuring every question is resolved suitably and ambiguity is laid to rest.
Thus, do not decide anything against the Easterners:
if you wish to make any decisions against them in their absence, whatever is undertaken will have no effect.
For such a decision cannot have strength, as our statutes already deny it power and authority.
Since these things are so, you should faithfully adhere to what aligns with the moderation of religion as agreed upon by the esteemed bishops.
Ensure that what religion demands is fulfilled, and avoid what it prohibits.
May divinity keep you safe for many years, Parents.
Written on May twenty-seventh, three fifty-nine, during the consulship of Eusebius and Hypatius.
The Catholic definition begins here, held by all Catholic bishops before they were influenced by earthly power to join the heretics at the Council of Ariminum in three fifty-nine.
Nothing should be added to or taken away from the Nicene Creed.
We believe this pleases all Catholics, and that we should not stray from the creed we received, which we recognized as complete in discussions with everyone.
Nor will we depart from the faith taught by God the Father through our Lord Christ, guided by the Holy Spirit, as revealed by the prophets.
This faith was received in the Gospels and all the apostles, through the tradition of the fathers, according to the succession of the apostles, up to the council held at Nicaea against the heresy that arose at that time, and it remains established to this day.
It is clear that nothing should be added or removed from these teachings.
Therefore, it is agreed that nothing new should be created: the name and essence should remain firm, as suggested by many holy Scriptures in our minds.
This is something the Catholic Church, along with divine teaching, has always confessed and professed.
All the Catholics, united in agreement, signed this definition.
At the same council, after it was established that the paternal tradition should not be diminished, even those who opposed it were condemned with the unified spiritual voice of all in agreement.
This is an example of that discussion.
Title: Eusebius and Hypatius, Consuls, Twelve Days Before the Kalends of August (July Twenty-First, Year Three Hundred Fifty-Nine)
After deliberating on the course of action, Grecianus, the bishop of Calle, spoke:
"Dear brothers, the Catholic council has shown the patience it should, demonstrating the pious Church time and again, along with Ursacius, Valens, Germinius, and Gaius, who have repeatedly changed their beliefs and caused turmoil in all churches.
Now, they attempt to impose their heretical views on Christian souls.
They want to overturn the decree made at Nicaea, which was established against the Arian heresy and others.
Moreover, they presented us with a creed they had written, which we could not accept.
They have already been declared heretics to us in the past and proven so over many days.
We have not admitted them into our communion, condemning them with our own voices while they were present.
Now again, what do you all think?
Please voice your opinions so that it can be confirmed with each person's signature."
All the bishops said: "We agree that the heretics should be condemned, so that the Church, truly Catholic, may remain in perpetual peace with unwavering faith."
Appendix Six Hundred Eighty-Six: Fragment of the Superior
This is a condemnation of the heresy of Arius and a comprehensive declaration of faith that the Catholics affirmed at the Council of Ariminum, signing it with their own hands.
Although Arius's blasphemies had been condemned before, they remained concealed because it wasn't known that he had blasphemed.
Thankfully, with God's help, when we gathered at Ariminum, his harmful heresy was revealed.
Therefore, along with his blasphemies, we also condemn all heresies that have previously arisen against the Catholic and Apostolic tradition, just as they have been condemned by past councils in various places.
We declare anathema on those who claim the Son of God comes from nothing and from a different substance, not born from God the Father, true God from true God.
If anyone says the Father and the Son are two gods, meaning two separate origins, and does not profess the one deity of the Father and the Son, let them be anathema.
If anyone claims the Son of God is a creature or a creation, let them be anathema.
If anyone says God the Father himself was born of the Virgin Mary, claiming the Father and Son are the same, let them be anathema.
If anyone claims the Son of God began from Mary, or there was a time when he was not the Son, let them be anathema.
If anyone says the Son of God is not truly ineffably born of God the Father, but is an adopted son, let them be anathema.
If anyone professes the Son of God as temporal or merely human and not born of God the Father before all ages, let them be anathema.
If anyone says the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are one person or three divided substances and does not profess the one deity of the perfect Trinity, let them be anathema.
If anyone says the Son of God existed before all ages but not absolutely before all time, assigning him a beginning in time, let them be anathema.
If anyone claims all creation was not made through the Word but without or before him, let them be anathema.
We similarly anathematize any other blasphemies of Arius or anyone else that may be found.
Fragment Six Hundred Eighty-Seven, Eight (Also Two of Part Two)
Letter of the Council of Ariminum to Emperor Constantius, Where the Bishops Deviated from the True Faith (written in Three Hundred Fifty-Nine)
To the most blessed and glorious Augustus Constantius, from the synod of Rimini.
The synod of Rimini does not decide anything new.
By God's command and your pious order, we believe it was arranged for bishops from different provinces of the West to gather at Rimini, so that the faith might be clarified to all the Catholic Churches and heretics could be identified.
During our discussions, we agreed to uphold the faith that has endured from ancient times, through the prophets, the gospels, and the apostles, through God Himself and our Lord Jesus Christ, the savior of your empire and the giver of your salvation, which we have always upheld.
We deemed it wrong to change anything from the saints or from those who sat in the Nicene council with Constantine, your pious father, of glorious memory.
That council was made known and impressed upon the people's minds and was established against the Arian heresy, to drive out heresies.
If anything is taken away from it, it opens the door to the heretics' poison.
We condemn those eager for change.
For this reason, Ursacius and Valens once fell under suspicion of the same Arian heresy and were suspended from communion.
They sought forgiveness, as their writings show, which they received from the council of Milan, with representatives of the Roman church also present.
In this, with Constantine present, it was written with great care that he who held it, baptized, departed to the peace of God.
We consider it wrong to alter anything from it and to remove in any way the many saints, confessors, and successors of martyrs, the authors of that council.
Even they preserved everything from past Catholics according to the scriptures, and it has remained to these times, in which your piety has received from God the Father through God and our Lord Jesus Christ the power to rule the world.
At that time, they also attempted to overturn what had been reasonably established.
Your letters have guided us to discuss faith, and the disturbers of the Churches, Germinius and Gaius, have introduced something new that contains much false teaching.
When their proposal was publicly rejected at the council, they decided it should be rewritten.
It's evident they frequently changed their position in a short period.
To avoid ongoing disturbances in the Church, we resolved to uphold the established and reasonable traditions.
To inform your grace, we instructed our envoys to do nothing but firmly maintain the ancient decrees.
Your wisdom should understand that the promises made by Valens, Ursacius, Germinius, and Gaius would not bring peace if removed.
Instead, they caused more disturbances in all regions and the Roman Church.
He asks Constantius to accept their decrees and release the bishops from Ariminum.
For this reason, we ask your grace to kindly and calmly receive and listen to all our envoys.
Do not allow any injustice to overthrow the ancient ways; let what we received from our wise ancestors, who acted with the Holy Spirit, remain.
This newness has not only disturbed the faithful but also prevents non-believers from approaching faith.
We also pray that you instruct the many bishops detained at Ariminum, many of whom are aged and poor, to return to their provinces so that their congregations are not deprived of guidance.
We repeatedly ask that nothing be changed or diminished; let everything remain intact as it was in the time of your holy father Constantine and continues into your religious era.
Let your holy wisdom ensure that we remain steadfast and not be displaced from our positions.
Allow bishops to be devoted to their prayers for your health, your kingdom, and the peace that divinity grants you deeply and eternally for your merits.
Our messengers will deliver the subscriptions and names of the bishops or envoys, as another document guides your holy and religious wisdom.
Acts of the envoys.
With this letter, bishops of unwavering faith sent ten envoys to the emperor.
However, the heretical group also sent ten envoys from their side.
Upon their arrival at the emperor's court, they were received.
Sadly, the envoys of the Catholics were not welcomed.
Exhausted by long delays and frightened by the emperor's threats, they renounced the complete faith they had once defended and accepted the betrayal they had previously denounced.
You will find this to be true from the following details.
Six Hundred Ninety: The Deeds, Where the Bishop Delegates Betrayed the True Faith, Begin.
(Year Three Hundred Fifty-Nine, Tenth Day of October) (In the Consulship of Eusebius and Hypatius, Six Days Before the Ides of October)
The decrees at Rimini are annulled.
When the bishops gathered at the residence of Nicaea, formerly called Ustodizo, in the province of Thrace, Restitutus, Gregory, Honoratus, Athenius, Iginus, Justinus, Priscus, Primus, Taurinus, Lucius, Mustacius, Urbanus, Honoratus, and Solutor were present.
Restitutus, bishop of Carthage, said:
Your wisdom knows, most holy fellow priests, that when the discussion of faith was held at Rimini, the dispute caused such division that, through the devil's instigation, discord arose among the priests of God.
This led to a situation where I, Restitutus, along with a group of bishops, judged Ursacius, Valens, Germinius, and Gaius as if they were the authors of evil understanding, deciding that they should be separated from our communion.
But since we have addressed and examined everything closely, and found that nothing should displease anyone, that is, the Catholic faith according to its profession, to which we have all subscribed, and that they were never heretics:
Therefore, because harmony and peace with God is of utmost importance, it was decided by our common agreement that everything discussed at Rimini should be nullified, and that their communion should be fully restored, with God's favor, so that no one remains in division, which could or should stain them.
And therefore, as I said, since we are present, each one should state whether what I have pursued is correct, and sign with their own hand.
All the bishops said, It is agreeable, and they signed.
However, what the confession of faith is, to which they later subscribed, which Valens also brought with him to Rimini, you will recognize from what is written below.
It is concluded.
Fragment Sixty-Nine, Fragment Nine (Also Second Part)
The Beginning of the Example of Faith in the Letter Sent to Emperor Constantius by Treacherous Bishops (At the End of Three Hundred Fifty-Nine)
To our most glorious and victorious Lord Augustus Constantius, the council of Ariminum agrees with the Easterners-that is, Migdonius, Megasius, Valens, Epitectus, and others who accepted the heresy.
They reject the term "substance."
Enlightened by your pious writings, we have given and continue to give the greatest thanks to God for blessing us by informing us of the actions we should take under your guidance. We greatly rejoiced because we recognized what we held, so that no one may ever use the terms "ousia" or "homoousios," which are unknown to the Church of God and often cause division among brothers.
Oh, how fortunate we are to have such happiness, that through your pious understanding, others who tend to adopt these names for God and the Son of God have been corrected!
Therefore, we offer our obedience to your clemency, for the truth has shone forth, unconquerable and victorious, ensuring that the name, unworthy of God and not found in the holy laws, is now spoken by no one.
They ask to be released from Ariminum.
Therefore, we pray for your piety, as we are still detained in the place where the synod was held, from which we gave our response through our delegates. We ask that you command us, who retain the complete doctrine among the Easterners, to be released to our congregations. This way, those who love the truth and do not change the name of God may be revealed, and we who uphold the Catholic truth may no longer be detained with those infected by perverse doctrine.
Therefore, we sincerely pray, Lord, for your compassion before God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ, God and Son of God.
We ask that you guide us, who have committed to sound doctrine, to step away from the term "ousia" at your command, and allow us to return to our congregations.
So that the Church may rejoice, as it does not allow the alteration of the names of God and His Son entirely, through the power and glory of your authority.
To whom divinity has granted so much that it becomes clear that the sacrilegious terms "ousia" and "homoousia" should now be set aside, as these are not found in the divine Scriptures regarding God and the Son of God.
Help us, merciful emperor, who worship the supreme God:
help those who pray to God the Father Almighty through Christ, the Son of God:
help those who listen devoutly to your judgment, who know no worship except through God the Father, through our Lord Jesus Christ, His glorious Son.
And especially, lord emperor, command us to return to our congregations by sending letters to the most distinguished Prefect of the Praetorium, Taurus:
because we have fully obeyed in proclaiming the name of God, to the Easterners and in accordance with your arrangement.
In this matter, which we have always upheld, we must now return to our congregations.
Regarding this matter, we have sent letters to our Eastern bishops, so they may know we have always upheld this, and to remain with them in the Catholic faith.
May divine compassion make you, most glorious and in all things, the vindicator, most pious emperor.
The End.
Fragment Ten (Also Part One)
Example of the Letter from the Eastern Bishops, Given to the Returning Delegates from Ariminum (Written at the End of the Year Three Hundred Fifty-Nine)
To the beloved brothers Ursacius, Valens, Magdonius, Megasius, Gaius, Justus, Optatus, Martial, and the other delegates of the Ariminum synod: Sylvanus, Sophronius, Neo, Herodianus, Patricius, Helpidius, Theophilus, Theodorus, Eumacius, Didimion, Ecdicius, Arsenius, Passinicus, Valentinus, Eucarpius, Leontius, Eortasius, and Macarius send greetings in the Lord.
The delegates of the Seleucia synod are informing the Ariminenses about their actions towards the supporters of Aetius.
In our efforts to achieve unity and true peace while resisting heresy as mandated by the synod, we felt it was essential to inform you about the current happenings in the Church, to prevent ignorance from making you allies of such great impiety.
We believe you have continued, not without the delegates of the entire synod-comprising more than one hundred bishops-to refrain from entering this church until now.
Therefore, we also want you to be informed so that the heresy already present in the Church does not completely take over.
This heresy dared to deny our Lord Jesus Christ as truly the only begotten Son of God, God from God, similar to the Father, so we need you to know that these blasphemous proclamations about the only begotten God are being considered and preached by these people.
We have also presented this to the most pious Emperor Constantius, who, moved by religious conviction, wanted all these things to be anathematized.
However, there is now a scheme being prepared to have Aetius, the author of this heresy, condemned, focusing more on the man than on the doctrine itself.
Therefore, we urge you, Brothers, to carefully reconsider these matters and strive to uphold the Catholic faith.
Additionally, your Charity should not doubt that everything that occurs must be communicated to the Western churches.
We wish you, Brothers, to fare well in the Lord.
Those who receive these letters are poorly regarded among their people.
The delegates from Rimini were accused of treachery.
With these issues at hand, along with the aforementioned blasphemies, an accusation was made against the one who took on the responsibility.
The hypocrisy, once revealed in their deceit, drove them to risk being deposed.
The pain of a guilty conscience is so intense that no one is deterred by the truth!
If the book of Valens and Ursacius doesn't reflect your faith, why not agree to its condemnation?
Isn't it universally acknowledged that poison is evil, killing the innocent is a crime, and disrespecting the Lord is horrifying?
Anyone who doesn't condemn these actions essentially declares support for them, because no one fails to denounce what they hate, and what they don't denounce, they approve.
After the Synod of Seleucia, when you arrived in Constantinople, why did you immediately align with the heretics you had condemned?
You didn't hesitate in your visit, nor did you take time for careful consideration.
Then, the Eastern delegates, who did not share communion with the bishops of the synod, approached you to explain their actions and show the heresy they condemned.
Shouldn't you at least have paused and reserved judgment on all discussions?
Yet, for some unknown reason, you didn't accept what was right in your conscience.
Instead, you immediately joined your group and engaged in the fellowship of your blasphemies.
You didn't even consider allowing the Rimini synod to be honored if some were misled by shame.
You quickly exposed your deceit by not anathematizing your own.
Those who betrayed their treachery.
Those who don't want the Son to be like other creations.
Those who wish him to be from God.
Who is eternal?
Why do you say, according to the Scriptures, that He is like others?
In the gathering of many who accuse you, why do you not call the Son of God a creature?
You answered that the holy people of Ariminum did not deny Christ as a creature, but as different from other creatures.
This is because it is said He is not created like other things, not due to the absence of creation, but because He is set apart from others.
So, although He is not different from others, He is still not something else.
As if any creature is like another, such as an angel to a human, a human to a bird, a bird to a beast.
If I am lying, those who heard are witnesses.
And if they remain silent, your book, defended most impiously by you, speaks with me.
In it, like glass to sapphire, the Son is alien to the Father and Christ to God.
Then, where you deceived listeners, it is not from non-existent things, but from God.
Would it not be clear deception because you said this?
Since it is not from non-existent things, but from God, according to your profession, because the will to what exists was the beginning.
Am I truly lying?
If you did not condemn those in Eastern gatherings by the agreement of your booklet, who said it was not from substance that He was born, but from will.
You also profess that He is eternal with the Father.
You truly have said this, if it had not been shouted against me.
Why, before eternal times, did you preach that from the true Father God, the true only begotten God was born?
So that eternity with the Father is not already of previous angels and human souls, but of future ones.
You also said He is like according to the Scriptures.
As if not according to the Scriptures, man is like God, and the mustard seed, leaven, and net are like the kingdom of heaven.
But to go through the lies of your hypocrisy is idle.
For the works of your impiety cry out against you.
What kind of crime is theirs?
A servant, perhaps not the best but certainly adequate, unwillingly endures the insult from his master and, if given the chance, seeks revenge.
A soldier protects his king from danger, even at the risk of his own body, disregarding his own life.
Even dogs, kept to guard the house, instinctively bark when they sense something, and when they pick up the scent of approaching people, they leap around in suspicion.
You have heard of Christ, the true Son of God and the only God.
It's believed that you deny Him, and yet you remain silent.
Why do I say remain silent?
You resist those who shout against you and join those who make noise.
That's not all.
Even from your library, weapons are taken up to preach impiety, and war against God is waged with your support.
So where is your declaration at Nicaea in Thrace, where you claimed all heresies were condemned?
Your falsehood has been exposed: the night of your declaration has been illuminated by the Sun of righteousness to His preachers.
You approve of these things, you condemn them, and then you join the heretics.
Thus, what you previously hid to deceive people, you now reveal, openly professing hatred against God and Christ.
Fragment Eleven (Alias of the Second Part)
The Beginning of the Catholic Faith Presented at the Pharisaic City by the Gallican Bishops to the Eastern Bishops
To our most beloved and blessed fellow priests, all the Eastern bishops residing in various provinces in Christ, the Gallican bishops send their greetings.
The Deception of Heretics.
With every sense of our life and faith, we give thanks to God the Father through our Lord Jesus Christ, because He has brought us into the light of the knowledge of His confession, through teachings, prophecies, and apostolic works.
This ensures we are not left in the darkness of worldly ignorance, bound by worldly judgment.
Since the only hope for complete salvation is to confess God the Father almighty through His only begotten Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, in the Holy Spirit.
Furthermore, our reason for daily gratitude increases, as He not only frees us from worldly error but also keeps us from being entangled with the unforgivable company of heretics.
From your letters sent to our beloved brother and fellow priest Hilary, we understand the devil's deceit and the cunning of heretics against the Church of the Lord, attempting to deceive us with differing opinions in the Eastern and Western regions.
Many, who were present either at Ariminum or Nicaea, were forced into silence regarding the term usia under your authority: a term you originally created against the heresy of the Ariomantarians, which we have always faithfully and devoutly accepted.
In what sense the synod embraces "homoousion."
It does not reject "homoiousion."
We have embraced the term "homoousion" to affirm the true and legitimate birth of the only begotten God from God the Father, rejecting the blasphemies of Sabellius concerning the union, and understanding that the Son is not a part of the Father.
Instead, the whole and perfect only begotten God was born from the whole and perfect unbegotten God, thus we confess Him to be of one usia or substance with God the Father, to avoid the implication of a creation, adoption, or mere title.
He is from Him, just as a son is from a father, as God is from God, as power is from power, as spirit is from spirit, as light is from light.
He willingly listens to his likeness to God the Father, since he is the image of the invisible God, as it says in Colossians chapter one, verse thirteen.
This likeness is worthy of the Father, from the true God to the true God.
It's not the union of divinity that we understand, but unity; because while union is singular, unity in the truth of birth is the fullness of the one being born.
Especially since the Lord Jesus Christ himself told his disciples, "I and the Father are one," as recorded in John chapter ten, verse thirty. This signifies not only the love he has for the Father but also the divinity that is God from God.
According to, "Whoever has seen me has seen the Father," in John chapter fourteen, verse nine; and, "If you do not want to believe me, then believe in my works, because the Father is in me, and I am in the Father," from John chapter ten, verse thirty-eight.
The Son existed before time, yet became lesser than the Father by taking on the form of a servant.
Therefore, we hold this faith and will continue to do so, rejecting the notion that "He was not before he was born." We do not claim the only-begotten God to be unbegotten, but it is impious to place any time before the God of times, since saying "he was not before he was born" involves time.
We also acknowledge that the Son was obedient to the Father, even to the point of death on the cross, due to the human weakness he took on. As he mentioned regarding his ascension to heaven, "If you loved me, you would rejoice because I am going to the Father; for the Father is greater than I," found in John chapter fourteen, verse twenty-eight.
Through his acceptance of flesh, he deigned to call us brothers, as stated in John chapter twenty, verse seventeen, while remaining in the form of God, he chose to be in the form of a servant.
Those who have fallen should reconsider their actions and condemn the authors of error.
Therefore, dear friends, from your letters, we have come to understand that our straightforwardness has been misled by silence.
Even the devout individuals who returned from Ariminum to Constantinople, as your letter indicates, could not be forced to denounce such blasphemies, as our brother Hilarius, a faithful preacher of the Lord's name, has proclaimed.
We also refer back to all those actions that were mistakenly conducted out of ignorance.
We regard Auxentius, Ursacius, Valens, Gaius, Megasius, and Justin as excommunicated according to your letters.
Certainly, as we mentioned, following our brother Hilarius' declaration, who refused to be at peace with those who embraced these errors, we condemn all the blasphemies you mentioned in your letters, particularly rejecting the apostate priests who have unjustly replaced our exiled brothers, whether through ignorance or impiety.
We pledge this before God and also affirm that anyone who dares to oppose what we have established in Gaul should be removed from communion and the priesthood.
For neither, as in other cases, do we permit the opportunity to preach without condemnation, nor oppose God and the majesty of Christ, the only-begotten of God, in a manner different from our understanding of homoousios, will be considered worthy of the holiness associated with the priesthood.
This is why even Saturninus, who impiously opposes these beneficial decrees, has been excommunicated by all Gallican bishops, as Your Charity is aware from the letters of our brothers.
Their long-hidden old crimes and the irreligiousness of their new rashness, as revealed in their letters, have rendered them unworthy of the bishop's name.
The Catholic faith, as explained by Gallican bishops to the Eastern bishops, has been concluded at the city of Pharisaea.
Preface of Eusebius to Gregory, Bishop of Spanense (Written around the year Three Hundred Sixty)
To the most holy brother in the Lord, Bishop Gregory, Eusebius sends greetings in the Lord.
I received your sincere letter, in which I learned, as befits a bishop and priest of God, that you stood against the transgressor Hosius.
Unlike many who fell at Ariminum and joined in communion with Valens, Ursacius, and others whom they later condemned after realizing their blasphemy, you refused to give your assent, faithfully adhering to the creed written by the Nicene fathers.
We rejoice with you in this, and we also celebrate for ourselves because, having this resolution and faith, you deemed us worthy of remembrance.
To you who remain steadfast in the same confession and hold no association with hypocrites, we promise our communion.
With whatever arguments you can muster, and with as much effort as you are capable of, rebuke the transgressors, reproach the unfaithful, fearing nothing from secular power, as you have done.
For greater is he who is in us than he who is in the world.
We, your fellow priests, suffering our third exile, share what we have come to realize: that all the hope of the Arians does not rest in their or any limited agreement, but on the protection of secular power, ignoring the writings that say, cursed are they who trust in man.
But our help is in the name of the Lord, who made heaven and earth.
We wish to endure in sufferings so that, as it is said, we may be glorified in the kingdom.
Please write to us about the progress you have made in correcting the wicked or how many brothers you have found standing firm, or have corrected through your own admonition.
All those with me greet you, especially the Deacon, and they ask that you kindly extend our greetings to all those faithfully adhering to your side.
Here ends the letter of Eusebius to Bishop Gregory of Spain.
Fragment Twelve (Other of Part One)
Here Begins the Example of the Letter of Liberius, Bishop of the City of Rome, Made to the Catholic Bishops of Italy
Liberius sends his greetings to the Catholic bishops across Italy, wishing them eternal salvation in the Lord.
Some are reluctant to forgive those who faltered at Rimini, but Liberius holds a different view.
He believes that the fault of ignorance can be erased through repentance, as shown in the holy Scriptures.
We learn that piety is beneficial in every way, even surpassing the benefits of physical exercise.
The current time urges us to pursue it.
For if some, in their endeavor, harshly attempt to undo what is wisely provided, they aim to reinforce what is already established by apostolic authority.
It was noted that those who acted ignorantly at Rimini, despite being forbidden from ignorance, fell into error, and thus the truth must be restored.
But I, who must take a balanced approach, especially since the judgment criticized by many has been accepted by all Egyptians and Greeks, indeed must show mercy to those we discussed earlier.
However, the authors who misled the innocent with deceitful and malicious tactics should be condemned, as they obscured the truth by presenting darkness as light, and light as darkness.
Therefore, if anyone caught in ignorance repents, our brief advocacy should restore them.
If they encountered the deceptive and dark poison of the Arian doctrine, they should denounce it and oppose its authors even more fiercely, having experienced their aggression.
They should fully commit themselves to the apostolic and Catholic faith upheld until the Council of Nicaea.
Through this profession, even if it seems mild to some, they should regain what they lost through deceit away from righteousness.
However, if there is someone foolish enough-which I doubt-who not only refuses to accept the cure but actually believes that the harmful poison and virus will justify themselves, they will be proven wrong by reason.
Recklessly aligning with the author of deceit, they will face consequences from the spiritual authority of the Catholic Church.
Example of the Letter of the Bishops of Italy
To our dearest brothers across Illyricum who hold onto the faith of our ancestors, the bishops of Italy wish you eternal salvation in the Lord.
As the Apostle says, by the grace of divine gift, we have begun to think and confess as one.
Regarding Italy, after recognizing the deception it suffered at Ariminum, it has returned to the faith of our fathers, the one established at Nicaea.
We are also glad that God has kindly regarded Illyricum, and, having shed the burden of infidelity, it has started to embrace the correct judgment.
Therefore, dearest brothers, please accept our firm and unanimous decision.
We uphold the decrees of the Nicene council against Arius and Sabellius, with which Photinus is condemned by shared inheritance.
We rightfully annul the decrees of the council of Ariminum, which were compromised by certain individuals, with the agreement of all provinces.
We have also decided to send copies so that there might be no disagreement in maintaining the faith or in refuting the council of Ariminum.
Therefore, whoever wishes to share in our unity, and whoever desires to have undivided peace with us, should hasten to approve our judgment and send their agreement to the faith we have mentioned and to the annulment of the council of Ariminum without hesitation.
We sincerely ask for this, which we offer with the consent of many of these provinces.
It is clear that the authors of the Arian or Aetian heresy, Valens and Ursacius, and their other companions, were not only recently exposed in Illyricum but had long been condemned there.
Fragment Thirteen (Alias Second Part)
Epistle of Germinius the Bishop Against the Arians Who Had Already Signed at the Council of Ariminum, Knowing That They Had Done Wrong (Circa Year Three Hundred Sixty-Five)
I, Bishop Germinius, believe and declare that there is one true God, the Father, eternal and almighty.
And that Christ, His only Son and our Lord, is God, born of the true God the Father, true Son of God, begotten before all things.
He is similar to the Father in all things: divinity, love, majesty, power, glory, life, wisdom, and knowledge, as He is perfect, born from the perfect.
I also acknowledge that He took on human form from the Virgin Mary, as the prophets foretold, and as the teachings of the gospels and apostles show was fulfilled.
We accept, believe, and declare His sufferings, death, resurrection, and ascension into heaven.
And that at the end of the world, He will come down from heaven to judge the living and the dead and to repay each according to their deeds.
And in the Holy Spirit, that is, the Comforter, who is given to us by God the Father through the Son.
The end.
Fragment Fourteen (Alias Part One)
Example of the Letter of Valens, Ursacius, and Others to Germinius (Written in the Year Three Hundred Sixty-Six)
To the most religious brother Germinius, Valens, Ursacius, Gaius, and Paulus send their greetings.
Germinius is accused of defending the homoousion.
When the concern for hope and salvation arises, those who are involved should be praised more than criticized.
Salvation and hope primarily rely on the Catholic faith.
Therefore, although our lordly brothers and fellow bishops, Valens and Paulus, asked you to respond to the rumors about you, most religious lord, you chose not to, because you have testified in your letters that you continue in the same love and are ready to show unblemished affection towards us.
For this reason, we gathered in Singidunum and once again urge your holiness with these words to eliminate any cause of doubt and kindly write back to us.
If you have not departed from the Catholic faith, which was presented and confirmed at the holy council in Ariminum, to which all the bishops of the East agreed, as you have already declared, please state this more clearly.
Here is what is outlined: We say the Son is like the Father according to the Scriptures, not according to substance or in all things, but absolutely.
If this definition is changed, the once treacherous assertion of Basil, for which a synod was held and rightly condemned, will be revived.
A retraction is demanded.
Therefore, kindly declare clearly in your letters that you have not said, do not say, nor will say, that the Son is like the Father in all things except in being uncreated.
Lest what the bearers of the letters, Deacon Jovianus and Subdeacon Martyrius, asserted by word of their request before my aforementioned lords, our brothers and fellow bishops Valens and Paulus, may seem more believable-that you profess the Son to be like the Father in all things.
If you can show through your writings that you understand our concerns, the complaint about the misconduct by some of your clerics, Palladius and Gaius, who are our brothers and fellow bishops, falls under your responsibility to investigate, even though you initially did not want to, as advised in the first meeting.
They should naturally provide an explanation for their rash actions.
We have sent this message through Secundianus the priest, Pullentius the reader, and Candidianus the exorcist to your Charity on December 18, 366, during the consulship of the most noble Gratian and Dagalaifus, and we've kept a copy with us.
Fragment Fifteen (Alias One of Part One)
Begins the Letter of Germinius to Rufianus, Palladius, and Others (Year Three Hundred Sixty-Seven)
To the most religious Lords and Brothers Rufianus, Palladius, Severinus, Nichaeus, Heliodorus, Romulus, Mucianus, and Stercorius, Germinius sends his greetings in the Lord.
The Son is shown to be entirely like the Father through tradition and Scriptures.
Vitalis, a distinguished man serving in the esteemed Prefecture, informed us through his report that your Holiness wishes to be clearly informed about what displeases Valens, Ursacius, Gaius, and Paul regarding our faith.
I felt it necessary to clarify this to your Holiness through this letter and to affirm what I trust has been within you from the beginning.
We hold fast to what we have received from the fathers and what we have learned once from the divine Scriptures and teach daily:
that Christ, the Son of God, our Lord, is entirely like the Father, except for being unbegotten; God from God, light from light, power from power, whole from whole, perfect from perfect, begotten before ages and before all that can be understood or spoken, whose birth no one knows except the Father alone, as the Son himself asserts:
"Because no one knows the Son except the Father, nor does anyone know the Father except the Son, and those to whom the Son chooses to reveal him" (Matthew chapter eleven, verse twenty-seven);
through whom all things were made, without whom nothing was made, according to the divine words of our Savior, the Son, saying:
"My Father is working until now, and I am working" (John chapter five, verse eighteen);
and again, "Whatever the Father does, the Son does likewise" (John chapter five, verse nineteen);
and again, "I and the Father are one" (John chapter ten, verse thirty);
and yet again, "Whoever has seen me has seen the Father" (John chapter fourteen, verse nine);
and again, "Just as the Father has life in himself, so he has granted the Son also to have life in himself" (John chapter five, verse twenty-six);
and again, "Just as the Father raises the dead and gives them life, so also the Son gives life to whom he will" (John chapter five, verse twenty-one);
and again, "Believe in God, believe also in me" (John chapter fourteen, verse one);
and finally, "For the Father judges no one, but has given all judgment to the Son, so that all may honor the Son as they honor the Father" (John chapter five, verse twenty-two).
And again, to whom did the Father say, "Let us make man in our image and likeness"? (Genesis 1:26).
He did not say, "in your image," or "in my image," to avoid suggesting any difference in the divinity of His Son.
For this reason, He said, "in our image and likeness," to reveal His Son, God, as being similar to Himself in all things.
The Evangelist said, "We have seen His glory, the glory as of the only begotten from the Father, full of grace and truth." (John 1:14).
And the Apostle to the Corinthians declared, "In whom the god of this world has blinded the minds of the unbelievers, so that they might not see the light of the gospel of the glory of Christ, who is the image of God" (Second Corinthians 4:4).
The same Apostle also wrote, "He has transferred us to the kingdom of His beloved Son, in whom we have redemption and forgiveness of sins, who is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of all creation" (Colossians 1:13 and following).
And again, the same Apostle said, "Have this mind in you, which was also in Christ Jesus, who, though He was in the form of God, did not consider equality with God something to be grasped, but emptied Himself, taking the form of a servant, being made in the likeness of men" (Philippians 2:5 and following).
Who does not understand that just as in the form of a servant our true flesh was in Christ, so also, in the form of God, the true divinity of the Father is in the Son?
And again, "See to it that no one takes you captive through philosophy and empty deceit according to human tradition, according to the elemental spirits of the world, and not according to Christ; for in Him the whole fullness of deity dwells bodily" (Colossians 2:8).
If, therefore, the whole fullness of divinity dwells in Christ, He is no longer partly similar and partly dissimilar, as those now assert, who, going backward due to the contention of their desires, have turned themselves away from us.
What is presented in opposition needs to be clarified.
Some claim they can use the divine Scriptures to argue that Christ is a creation and a creature:
However, we assert, according to the Scriptures, that He is the way, the gate, the stone of offense, the rock of scandal, the foundation, the arm, the hand, the wisdom, the word, the lamb, the sheep, the shepherd, the priest, the vine, the day, and more.
We understand and express all these things to reflect the powers and operations of the Son of God, not to equate His divine birth from the Father with these names;
because everything was created from nothing through the Son, but the Son was not created from nothing; He was begotten from God the Father.
Regarding the inconsistency of Valens, and the cause of the faith declared by Marcus of Arethusa.
I am amazed that Valens either forgot or is deceitfully ignoring what was decided and accomplished in the past.
Under the Emperor Constantius of blessed memory, when disagreements about faith began, in the presence of the emperor, with George the bishop of Alexandria, Pancratius of Pelusium, Basil the bishop of Ancyra, Valens himself, Ursacius, and myself present, a discussion about the faith continued until nightfall and reached a conclusion.
Marcus was chosen by all of us to dictate the faith, in which it was written:
The Son is similar to the Father in all things, as the holy Scriptures say and teach: to which we all agreed and signed with our own hands.
But if something is now being suggested by the spirit of this world, we cannot yet openly know.
As we professed from the Scriptures that the Son is similar to the Father in all things, except for being unbegotten; let them also explain from the Scriptures how He is partly similar and partly dissimilar.
Dear Brothers, I confidently and without delay bring this matter to your attention through Cyriacus the official.
The opportunity arose after Carinus the deacon, whom I sent to you, delivered the statement numbered 710.
Through your vigilant devotion to God, I hope it will be shared with the entire brotherhood, ensuring that no one is unknowingly caught in the deceitful traps of the devil.
Now, it is up to your unity to write back to me with what the Holy Spirit suggests to you.
I must inform you that I couldn't sign this letter due to the pain in my hand.
However, I have instructed our brothers and fellow priests Innocent, Octavius, and Catulus to sign it.