On the Prophet Malachi
by Haymo Bishop of Halberstadt
In Malachiam Prohetam.
The Hebrews believe that Malachi, the last of the twelve prophets, was Ezra, who was both a prophet and a priest.
He prophesied at the same time as Haggai and Zechariah, which is why no specific time is given in the title.
His name means "angel of the Lord" or "my angel," because he was so authoritative that whatever he said was believed as if it had been spoken by an angel of the Lord.
Some even thought he was naturally an angel who had descended from heaven in human form to remind the people, who had recently returned from captivity.
Chapter One
The burden of the word of the Lord to Israel through Malachi the prophet.
As mentioned before, when a burden is placed on the prophets, it signifies a message of threat or adversity towards sinners.
Therefore, the burden of the word of the Lord here is heavy for those it is directed at.
Yet, it also offers some consolation because it is spoken to Israel, not against them, meaning the forthcoming words are meant for their understanding, not their destruction.
Here, Israel refers to the two tribes of Judah and Benjamin.
Since the ten tribes, formerly known as Israel, were taken into captivity, the remaining two tribes began to be collectively called Israel.
The phrase "In the hand of Malachi" implies that Malachi was chosen due to his righteousness. Prophecy is granted to those who purify themselves and reject corruption. Conversely, for those with blood on their hands, the word of the Lord is not given.
"I have loved you," says the Lord. But you ask, "How have you loved us?" Was not Esau Jacob's brother? Yet, I loved Jacob, but I hated Esau. I turned his mountains into a wasteland and his heritage into a desert for dragons.
If Edom says, "We have been destroyed, but we will return and rebuild," thus says the Lord of hosts: They may build, but I will tear down. They will be known as the border of wickedness, the people with whom the Lord is angry forever.
Your eyes will see, and you will say, "The Lord is magnified beyond the border of Israel."
Having mentioned the burden of punishments they bear, the Lord explains why they deserve these: "I have loved you," he says, but you have not reciprocated. As the proverb goes, failing to return love to the lover is a waste of their efforts. Because they did not love the Lord who loved them, he threatens them with punishment, so they might experience through suffering what they refused to feel through his blessings.
Indeed, when he says in the past tense, "I loved you," he denies loving in the present while confessing past love. Therefore, when the Lord said, "I loved you," they, in their recklessness, replied: "How have you loved us?" as if they had forgotten the countless benefits granted to them.
To this, the Lord responded: "Was not Esau Jacob's brother? To remain silent about other things, like how I recently freed you from Babylonian captivity, I will go back further and show from the very beginning of your existence how I have loved you. Before Rebecca gave birth to Jacob and Esau, I loved you in Jacob, but I hated the Edomites in Esau. I made his mountains, the region of Seir, a desolation, and his cities deserted by humans, to be occupied by dragons and beasts.
But if Edom, who is Esau, says: 'We have been destroyed, but we will return and rebuild our cities,' they indeed will build, but I will tear down."
The love and hatred of God should not be thought of in a human, carnal way. For just as God created all, so He loves: He has mercy on humans and hates nothing He has made. Therefore, God's hatred either arises from foreknowledge of the future or from deeds. For God loves those whom He sees resisting vices and obeying divine commands. But those He sees serving sins and wanting to rebuild vices already destroyed are said to be hated.
These things are said according to history by the Hebrews, who also interpret the Edomites as representing the Romans, cruel and bloodthirsty. Edom is interpreted as red or bloody, and their empire will be destroyed at the end of the world, with the power of the whole world passing from them.
In an allegorical sense, Esau and Jacob, brothers born from one lineage, represent the figures of vices and virtues. Although these two are contrary, they come from one source of the heart. Since we are free in will, according to our choice, we either turn to vices or virtues. Esau was born first, because vices come first through infancy, adolescence, and youth.
Afterward, Jacob was born, known as the "supplanter," because the stronger age follows, corrects, and replaces the errors of a more fragile age. Hence, it is rightly said that the older brother, hairy and wild, was accustomed to hunting and the woods, while the younger, gentle and simple, is reported to have lived at home.
Therefore, under the name Esau, God asserts that He hates vices, not the nature which He made good. He places his borders in desolation so that all evil may be eradicated and vices may not grow. If brazen malice tries to rebuild what has been destroyed, the Lord declares that He will destroy it again. This happens in two ways: either when sinners are corrected or when those who persist in sin are condemned by just vengeance.
A son honors his father, and a servant his master. So if I am a Father, where is my honor? And if I am a Master, where is my fear, says the Lord of hosts? It's as if He were saying: Although before you were reborn, I loved you as children in Jacob, yet choose by what name you wish to call me, that is, either Father or Master. So if I am a Father, why do you not give the due honor to the Father? If a Master, why do you despise me? Why do you not fear me as a Master?
He says this to those who, having recently returned from captivity, remained in their former sins, not venerating God with either fear or love, even though the temple and city were not yet rebuilt. Spiritually, God wants us first to be His children, obeying Him willingly, and serving Him not out of fear but out of love. But if we do not want to be this, He at least wants us to be servants, avoiding evil out of fear of punishment and doing good.
Therefore, the Lord seeks honor from sons and demands fear from servants. For the beginning of wisdom is the fear of the Lord, so that starting with fear, we may transition to the love of children.
To you, O priests, who despise my name, and say: In what have we despised your name? You offer polluted bread upon my altar and say, In what have we polluted you? In that you say, the table of the Lord is despised.
To you, O priests, my message is specifically directed.
You who despise my name and diminish my sacrifices.
When you returned from Babylon, you should have turned completely away from past crimes, yet you add contempt for my sacrifices.
But they, as if unaware of these things, still inquire of Him who knows everything, "In what way do we despise you?" The Lord answered:
You offer polluted bread on my altar, namely the bread of the presence which, according to the traditions of the Hebrews, the priests themselves should sow, reap, grind, and bake. Disregarding this, they took any bread and placed it on the Lord's table on the Sabbath, where it was kept until the next Sabbath, and it was called holy bread, which no one was allowed to eat except the priests.
Thus, He said: You offer polluted bread on my altar, and while you mistreat my sacrifices, you violate me, whose sacraments they are. In that you say: The table of the Lord is despised, can be explained by the fact that the altar they made after returning from captivity did not have the glory of the old one. So, they said the table of the Lord was despised, as if religion lacked sanctity, which lacked ambition, when, on the contrary, God does not require the altar's decoration, but the devotion of the one offering.
But in a higher sense, the divine message reproaches the priests and ministers of the Church for treating the divine mysteries negligently and offering polluted bread on the Lord's altar. When unworthy people approach the altar and with a polluted conscience drink the pure blood and receive the most holy bread with a defiled mouth, thus, the table of the Lord is despised, which is holy in itself, because of the vileness of the ministers.
But in another sense, when a preacher, who should distribute spiritual bread—that is, teaching—to the people, flatters the powerful and the rich, speaks things that please them, and does not rebuke sinners with just severity, he pollutes the bread of teaching and insults the Lord Himself.
He thinks that the table of divine Scriptures is similar to the table of secular teachings, which is the table of idols.
"If you offer a blind animal for sacrifice, isn't that wrong?
And if you offer a lame or sick animal, isn't that wrong?
Offer it to your governor; would he be pleased with you or accept you?" says the Lord of hosts.
"And now, plead for God's favor so that He may have mercy on you.
This has been done by your hand.
Will He accept you?" says the Lord of hosts.
After returning from Babylon, the priests and other ministers of the Lord’s temple were offering illicit sacrifices—blind, lame, and variously afflicted animals—complaining that they offered these due to scarcity and necessity.
Therefore, He says: If you were to offer such gifts to your governor, would he not reject them?
He would surely say that an insult had been made to him.
So why do you offer to the Lord what you do not dare to give to men?
Allegorically, the victim of God is a good work, a prayer, alms, and other sacrifices pleasing to God.
But if the victim is blind, if the mind of the one offering is not enlightened by the light of truth—that is, if the intention of the one offering is not pure—the victim of prayer is lame, approaching God with a double mind, and weak, not having Christ, who is strength and wisdom.
Such victims, if offered, can in no way please God and rather make the offerer guilty.
And now, plead for the Lord’s favor, so that He may have mercy on you, as mentioned above.
Who among you is there who would shut the doors and light my altar for nothing?
The meaning is this: There is none among you who serves me freely—that is, without payment—not the high priest, not the priest, nor even the doorkeeper, and the one who lights the fire on the altar to burn the holocausts.
You receive from the people a tenth of all crops and other items decreed by law from the sacrifices of the offerings.
Because you offend God by offering weak sacrifices, repent and seek the Lord's face, so He may have mercy on you.
This passage shows that service to God without immediate reward is more pleasing to Him.
The Apostle preached the Gospel freely, working day and night with his hands to provide for himself, so as not to burden anyone.
"I have no pleasure in you," says the Lord of hosts, "and I will not accept an offering from your hand." This prophecy is clear and doesn't need deep explanation: it addresses priests offering unlawful sacrifices, angering God. It teaches that spiritual sacrifices will replace carnal ones. Not just in one Jewish province, but everywhere, a pure offering will be made to God, now frequent in the Church.
"For from the rising of the sun to its setting, my name is great among the nations, and in every place incense is offered to my name, and a pure offering; for my name is great among the nations," says the Lord of hosts. But you have profaned it by saying, "The table of the Lord is defiled, and its food is contemptible."
As mentioned earlier, the people who returned from captivity had only built an altar with random, unpolished stones. Missing the temple's ornaments, they thought its worship was lesser. So, the Lord speaks through the prophet: "You consider the altar and the offerings on it to be defiled, not realizing that the Lord seeks neither gold nor silver decorations, nor a multitude of sacrifices, but pure intentions from the offerers."
Indeed, we should not think of the table here as the one for the showbread, but the altar where sacrifices were burned, as indicated by "with the fire that consumes it."
Those loaves were not consumed by fire but were eaten by the priests.
Or certainly, it can be understood in this way: "The table of the Lord is defiled, and what is placed upon it is contemptible, with fire that consumes it; what good," they say, "does it do if we offer the best? For whatever they are, they must be consumed by fire."
And you said: "Behold, it is from our labor, and you blew it away," says the Lord of hosts. You brought from the spoils the lame and the sick as an offering. "Should I accept this from your hand," says the Lord of hosts?
The people who returned from Babylon, when offering sacrifices to the Lord, were compelled and sorrowful, saying: "Behold, we offer this from our labor. We are the prey of enemies, and whatever we could have, we consumed on the long journey. Whatever we have, we offer." Saying these things, they blew away their sacrifices, making them worthy of being blown away.
Some manuscripts say, "you blew me away," meaning: Not with the sacrifice, but with me, whom you were sacrificing to, you did harm. For this reason, I will not accept it. "Cursed is the deceiver, who has a male in his flock, and when making a vow, sacrifices a weak one to the Lord, because I am a great King," says the Lord of hosts, "and my name is feared among the nations."
He openly mocks those who said: "Behold, it is from our labor," and shows them deceitfully pretending poverty when they had the best, and making vows, they offer worthless things. These very things are not from their flock but from the spoils and weeping of the poor.
Chapter Two
And now, this command is for you, priests.
If you do not listen and take it to heart to give glory to my name, says the Lord of Hosts, I will send poverty upon you.
You have done wicked things, he says, but because I prefer repentance over the death of a sinner, if you do not listen to me and give glory to my name, which is both dreadful and awesome among the nations, I will send true poverty upon you, so that no longer lying, but compelled by need, you will say: Behold, from labor.
And I will curse your blessings, and I will curse them because you did not take it to heart.
The good things you now possess through my blessing will be cursed because you did not take it to heart, that is, you did not want to listen and act on what was told to you.
We can interpret the deceitful curse as the Jewish people, who, although they had the excellent and spotless Lamb, the Lord Savior, and were forewarned by the voices of all the prophets to receive and sacrifice him, believing that he came as the Son of God for the salvation of all, they did not want to do this.
Instead, they rejected Christ and chose the weak and sickly Barabbas, who prefigured the type of Antichrist.
But even though they did this, the name of Christ is dreadful and revered among the nations.
Behold, I will throw dung on your faces, the dung of your feasts, and it will take you away with it.
This threat is directed at the priests who misused the legal ceremonies.
He contemptuously calls the most sacred things the dung of the feasts, which they received as a gift according to the law, namely the right arm, the breast, the tongue, the stomach, and the other things which in Leviticus the priests are commanded to receive from the people's sacrifices.
He now declares he will reject these and throw them in their faces, to show that they are as vile as those things they offer.
And it will take you away with it, meaning the dung of your feasts, so that your faces will be disfigured by the foul mixture of dung.
And you will know that I sent this command to you so that my covenant with Levi might stand, says the Lord of hosts.
My covenant with him was one of life and peace.
Therefore, he says, I will do this so that you may know that I am the one who once chose Levi, your father, and in Levi, Aaron, so that my covenant with Levi and his descendants would be for an eternal priesthood to serve me.
Symbolically, God wanted all people, but especially priests, to be holy and without blemish.
He commanded them to have the arm, or the right arm, adorned with good works, the breastplate of a good and innocent conscience, and the tongue of holy confession.
They are also commanded to have the stomach, so that they contain nothing deadly or poisonous within.
For the stomach digests food, and the body is nourished by its juice.
Therefore, through the stomach, the bond of charity is signified, by which all members support one another, not seeking their own interests, but those of others.
If, therefore, the priests act against this, God threatens that all these things will be turned into dung, and that dung will take them and disfigure the face of their soul, so that it cannot lift its face and say: Your face, Lord, I will seek, etc.
And I gave him fear, and he feared me, and was afraid before my name.
The law of truth was in his mouth, and no injustice was found on his lips.
He walked with me in peace and uprightness and turned many away from iniquity.
From the person of Levi, praised by divine mouth, the duty of the priest and what kind he should be is described.
For the covenant of God was with Levi the patriarch, from Levi it passed to Aaron and his descendants.
The covenant of life, however, is not a right that is common to you and all living beings, but of the one who says: I am the way, the truth, and the life, and of whom the Apostle says: Our life is hidden with Christ in God.
He is also our peace, according to the Apostle, who made both one.
I gave him, he said, the fear of the Lord, which is the beginning of wisdom.
He was in awe of My name, showing a state of mind agitated by the trembling of his body, as it is written: "Upon whom shall My Spirit rest, but upon the humble and quiet, and who trembles at My words?"
The law of truth was in his mouth, meaning simple teaching, and it was not tainted by any stain of falsehood.
No injustice was found in him because he imitated that one high priest of whom it is truly said: "He did no sin," etc.
He walked with Me in peace and righteousness, so that he would not only have peace himself but also bring peace to others and show no partiality in judgment, turning many away from iniquity.
For a priest who does not correct wrongdoers loses the office of a priest.
For the lips of a priest should keep knowledge, and people should seek the law from his mouth, for he is the angel of the Lord of hosts.
It doesn't say they will speak or utter, but they will keep, to fulfill it in action, and thus propose to others what they should do by word and example.
They should seek the law from his mouth, that is, the priest.
We also read this in Haggai: "Ask the priests about the law."
Discipline pertains to priests, so that when asked about the law, they can answer.
Hence Paul, describing the form of a priest to Titus, so that he may be able, he said, to exhort in sound doctrine and refute those who contradict.
Malachi is interpreted as the angel of the Lord, and every priest is an angel of the Lord, a mediator between God and humans, and announces God's will to the people.
But you have turned aside from the way, and you have caused many to stumble in the law.
You have made the covenant of Levi void, says the Lord of hosts.
Therefore, I have made you contemptible and low before all the people, because you have not kept My ways and have shown partiality in the law.
As if to say openly: I wanted you to be as I described your ancestor Levi to be; but you have instead turned away or deviated from the way I showed you, of which it is said elsewhere: "This is the way, walk in it, neither to the right nor to the left."
Many are offended by the law, especially those who, while instructing others with their words, lead them astray by their bad behavior.
You have nullified my covenant with Levi by negligently performing the duties of a priest.
Therefore, I have made you contemptible, so that instead of the honor and reverence due to you, you are trampled upon and despised.
As the blessed Gregory says, when someone's life is despised, their preaching is also disregarded.
He considers it a grave matter that they show favoritism, despising the righteous poor and favoring the proud rich.
Isn't there one father for all of us?
Didn't one God create us?
Why then does each of you despise your brother, violating the covenant of your fathers?
As it is written in the book of Ezra, when they returned from Babylonian captivity, both the leaders and many priests and Levites rejected their Israelite wives, who were aged, poor, worn out by the long journey, and weakened by the fragility of their sex.
They took young women, flourishing in beauty, nobility, and wealth.
The prophet rebukes them, urging them to reject those they had illicitly married and to take back those they had wrongly cast aside.
He says: Isn't there one father for all of us?
Judah has transgressed, and an abomination has been committed in Israel and Jerusalem because Judah has profaned the sanctuary of the Lord, which he loves, and has married the daughter of a foreign god.
Judah and Israel or Jerusalem here refer to the two tribes of Judah and Benjamin, along with the priestly, that is, Levitical tribe.
These were the only tribes that returned from captivity.
The ten tribes were still held captive by the Assyrians.
Judah has profaned the sanctuary, the chosen seed of God, by mixing with foreigners and taking the daughters of the wicked in marriage.
This follows: He had a daughter of a foreign god, meaning he took a wife who worshiped idols, against God's command, which says: You shall not take a daughter from the stock of Canaan as a wife for your son.
The Lord will destroy the man who does this, whether master or disciple, from the tents of Jacob, and the one offering a gift to the Lord of hosts.
Note that it does not say: Who did, but of future time: Who will do.
It does not take away forgiveness of a past crime, but threatens a curse for the future.
It calls those who had fallen to repentance, making no exceptions.
Whether teacher, disciple, commoner, or one offering a gift, that is, a priest, they are all struck with the same curse, as there is no difference among them if the guilt is equal.
And you did this again: You covered the altar of the Lord with tears, weeping and groaning, so I will no longer look at the sacrifice, nor accept anything pleasing from your hand;
and you said: The wives of the Israelites, abandoned by their husbands and seeing foreign wives in their husbands' beds, fled to God alone, prostrate with tears and groaning before His altar, as if complaining that God allowed such things to happen, when all things are governed by His providence.
Therefore, it says that the sacrifice of the priests who committed these acts cannot be looked at, nor accepted from their hand, hindered and overwhelmed by the tears of the wretched.
Yet they arrogantly, as if they had done nothing wrong, ask why their sacrifice could not be accepted; to whom it is answered: Because the Lord has testified between you and the wife of your youth, whom you have despised.
She is your companion and the wife of your covenant.
Did not one make them, and the rest of His spirit remains?
And what does one seek, except the seed of God?
For this reason, a man will leave his father and mother and be joined to his wife.
In this way, she is your partner and the wife of your covenant, formed from the rib of the man.
The remaining spirit of him, that is, the man, signifies the profound union between a man and a woman, almost as if one soul inhabits two bodies.
And what does the one, you understand, God, seek but godly offspring?
God, who joined them with such affection and closeness, desires godly offspring so that children of Israelite descent are born from them.
Therefore, since marriages were instituted for the creation of children, and you have fertile wives who can bring you the joy of children, why do you seek beautiful wives and abandon your legitimate ones?
He then urges us to repentance, saying: Guard your spirit, and do not despise the wife of your youth.
She was first joined to you in virginal marriage; let her stay with you until old age.
If you hate her, let her go, says the Lord God of Israel.
Yet injustice will cover his garment, says the Lord of Hosts.
This should be understood from the perspective of the priests and Levites and others who did not want to break illegal marriages.
When they were reprimanded by the prophet for this, they responded: God commanded it in the law.
If you hate your wife, let her go.
But why the Lord permitted this, the Savior explains in the Gospel to the apostles who asked: Is it lawful for a man to divorce his wife?
When the good teacher clearly showed that she should not be divorced, they asked again: Why then did Moses command to give a certificate of divorce?
The Lord replied: Because of the hardness of your hearts this commandment was given, or the lesser evil was permitted, so that a greater sin, that is, murder, would not occur.
If anyone, he says, divorces his legitimate wife and marries another, except for reasons of fornication, he commits adultery.
And injustice will cover his garment, that is, the flesh, with which the soul is clothed like the body with a garment, so that he is punished in the way he sinned.
Guard your spirit, and do not despise.
Because, he says, you cannot divorce your wives without committing a great sin.
Guard your souls, and do not despise your wives if they are poor or disfigured by some deformity.
You have made the Lord weary with your words, and you ask: How have we made Him weary?
By saying: Everyone who does evil is good in the sight of the Lord, and such people please Him.
Or certainly, where is the God of judgment?
The people, having returned from captivity, saw all the surrounding nations that served idols.
Their own enemies and plunderers, the Chaldeans, were rejoicing in wealth and prosperous successes, possessing all the things considered good in the world.
Meanwhile, they themselves, who were worshippers of the true God, were oppressed by poverty and servitude.
They were scandalized, saying there was no providence of God, but that everything happened by chance.
What is worse, they said that the evil pleased God and the good displeased Him.
This is more fully explained by the prophet David, who says he almost doubted and slipped when he saw the peace of sinners.
Finally, he added: Therefore, I have justified my heart in vain and washed my hands among the innocent.
This is a disease the human race suffers from, and this is the complaint they lament.
Chapter Three
Look, I am sending my messenger, and he will prepare the way before me.
The Lord Himself explains in the Gospel that this prophecy refers to John the Baptist, saying, "This is the one about whom it is written: Look, I am sending my messenger before you, and he will prepare your way before you."
In the Gospel, the voice of God the Father is speaking to the Son. Here, however, Christ speaks about John: "Look," He says, "I will send my messenger, who will prepare the way before me."
The Savior sent John ahead of Him into the wilderness to preach the baptism of repentance.
And then it follows: "And suddenly the Lord you are seeking will come to His temple, and the messenger of the covenant whom you desire."
Thus, Christ the Lord begins to speak about Himself as if He were someone else, as is customary in Scripture.
He is the ruler who dominates all creation, He is the messenger of the New Covenant, He is the one to be sought and desired by all, who was always expected by the ancient fathers.
Therefore, with John preparing the way for the Lord in the hearts of people, the Lord, the ruler, immediately comes to His temple, that is, to His Church, or to the hearts of individual believers, to whom the Apostle speaks, "You are the holy temple of God."
The Hebrews refer this statement: "I am sending my messenger," to Elijah.
But what follows: "The ruler will suddenly come to his temple," they apply to the Antichrist, whom they will accept instead of Christ at the end of the world.
Look, He is coming, says the Lord of hosts, and who can think of the day of His coming?
And who can stand to see Him?
He is the one of whom it was said above: "The ruler will suddenly come to His temple, and the messenger of the covenant."
Look, He is coming, and He will not delay, and who can think of how much glory and majesty He will come with?
If no one can think of it, who can bear it?
For He is like a refining fire, burning sinners.
Fire will burn before Him, etc.
This fire will consume wood, hay, and straw.
He will not only be like fire, but also like the soap of fullers, which in Hebrew is called borith, used to wash garments that are excessively soiled.
For those who have committed serious sins, there will be a refining and burning fire; but for those who have committed minor sins, there will be the fuller's soap.
Hence, it is said through Isaiah:
"When the Lord washes away the filth of the daughters of Zion and cleanses the bloodstains from Jerusalem by a spirit of judgment and a spirit of burning" (Isaiah 4:4).
Those who have the filth of minor sins will be purified by the spirit of judgment; but those who are stained with blood, that is, burdened with serious crimes, will be burned by the spirit of burning to be purified.
"And he will sit as a refiner and purifier of silver" (Malachi 3:3), meaning, understanding, and speech, so that whatever is mixed with tin or lead will be burned away in the Lord's furnace, and pure gold and silver will remain.
"He will purify the sons of Levi and refine them like gold and silver, and they will bring offerings in righteousness to the Lord" (Malachi 3:3).
By the sons of Levi, we understand all the priestly order, from whom judgment will begin, because it is written: "For it is time for judgment to begin with God's household" (First Peter 4:17); and elsewhere: "Begin at my sanctuary" (Ezekiel 9:6).
If the sacred order is to be purified and refined by flames, what should be said of the others, whom no privilege of holiness commends?
"And the offerings of Judah and Jerusalem will be acceptable to the Lord, as in days gone by, as in former years" (Malachi 3:4).
When, he says, the sons of Levi have been purified, then the sacrifice offered for Judah and Jerusalem will be pleasing to the Lord, that is, for those who confess the Lord in deeds and words, and who contemplate his peace in their minds.
The following phrase: "As in days gone by, as in former years," signifies that just as they pleased the Lord in the beginning, so after sin, being purified by repentance, they will start to please him again.
"So I will come to put you on trial. I will be quick to testify against sorcerers, adulterers, and perjurers, against those who defraud laborers of their wages, who oppress the widows and the fatherless, and deprive the foreigners among you of justice, but do not fear me," says the Lord Almighty (Malachi 3:5).
It is very terrifying: "I will come to put you on trial, and I will be quick to testify."
He who is the judge will also be the witness because he will judge the outward actions of works; he himself will be the witness of the hidden conscience of sorcerers, adulterers, and perjurers.
These secretly committed crimes will be brought to light.
And then there are those who openly slander the wages of workers, even though the Lord says:
The wages of a worker should not remain with you overnight.
They also slander widows and orphans, even though the prophet says:
The Lord will not ignore the cry of the orphan and the widow when she pours out her groan.
They oppress the foreigner, even though the Lord specifically commands:
Do not mistreat or oppress a foreigner.
In a deeper sense, a foreigner means a catechumen, who is not yet made a citizen of the heavenly Jerusalem through baptism.
Therefore, no one should think that perjury or fraud, slandering a widow and an orphan, and oppressing a foreigner are minor sins, since the Lord equates them with evil deeds and adultery and says He will judge them similarly.
For I am the Lord, and I do not change.
We should not think that His nature changes when He judges, or that He takes on any passion of anger or fury, since He said:
I will come to judgment,
and added:
And I do not change.
It is truly said of Him:
But you, Lord of hosts, judge with tranquility.
And you, sons of Jacob, are not consumed.
For from the days of your ancestors, you have turned away from my laws and have not kept them.
The Lord says:
You, sons of Levi, often change through evil deeds and adultery and other sins.
But I, who am a just judge and judge everything with tranquility, am not changed by any diversity of persons.
Although I acknowledge myself as a severe and just judge, you, sons of Levi, are not consumed, even though you are refined by the fire of tribulations, nor are you purified from your sins by scourges.
This is also what is said through Jeremiah:
I have struck your children in vain; they did not receive discipline.
This is neither new nor something you have done only once, to deserve any pardon.
You have inherited impiety from the days of your ancestors by turning away from my laws and not keeping what I commanded.
This can also be said about those placed in the Church: they are the sons of Jacob who overcome vices.
They are the disciples of the Church's teachers and instructors, who are in the Church in name only.
Yet, they do not turn away from vices nor keep God's commandments, falsely claiming the name of the Christian religion for themselves.
"Return to me, and I will return to you," says the Lord of hosts. In His great mercy, God encourages those who ignore Him to return to Him, and He promises to return to them. But they, not understanding that they have turned away from the Lord by sinning, impudently ask: "How shall we return? We have never turned away from you." To which the Lord responds: "Will a man rob God? Yet you are robbing me and you ask: 'How are we robbing you?' In tithes and offerings. You are cursed with a curse, for you are robbing me, the whole nation of you. Bring the full tithe into the storehouse, so that there may be food in my house, and thereby put me to the test," says the Lord of hosts, "if I will not open the windows of heaven for you and pour down for you a blessing until there is no more need. I will rebuke the devourer for you, so that it will not destroy the fruits of your soil, and your vine in the field shall not fail to bear," says the Lord of hosts. "Then all nations will call you blessed, for you will be a land of delight," says the Lord of hosts.
During the times of Malachi (who is also believed to be Ezra) and Nehemiah, there was a severe famine, forcing the poor among the people to sell their sons and daughters, as well as their possessions and all their property.
As it is written in the book of Ezra: "We have many sons and daughters, let us sell them for grain, so we may eat and live." Others said: "Let us mortgage our fields and vineyards and houses, and take grain in the famine." Those who had grain in their storehouses did not want to give tithes to the Levites, who had no inheritance, but the first fruits and tithes were their inheritance. "Can a man rob God, that is, defraud Him? You are defrauding me, because you do not give tithes and first fruits to my ministers."
I am enduring deception, as the Levites, who are my servants, were forced to abandon the temple due to poverty.
This means He feels cheated by those who serve Him, just as He feels visited in those who are in prison, and receives food and drink in the hungry, as mentioned in the six works of mercy.
As it is said: If a man betrays his God, even though it can simply be taken as defrauding or cheating, it can also be understood in a deeper sense to refer to the Lord's passion.
Meaning: It is no surprise if you now betray me in my servants, and as much as it depends on you, you suspend me, because one day you will nail me to the cross.
Therefore, because you are not giving the tithes that I commanded through Moses to be given to the priests and Levites, you are cursed with hunger and poverty.
This famine has come upon you because of it.
For you are betraying me, not just my servants, but the whole nation.
To show you that this has happened because I am angry with you, I urge and remind you to bring tithes into the storehouses of my temple, so that my servants may have food.
And test me on this, if I do not open the floodgates of heaven for you—that is, if I do not pour out so much rain on you that it seems the windows of heaven are open—and I will pour out blessings on you until there is abundance.
The word "pour" shows great generosity, and I will rebuke the devourer for you. That is, locusts, worms, or rust, and other things harmful to human labor. By rebuking them, that is, by the command of my majesty, I will prevent them from harming you, and they will not destroy the fruits of your land.
Your happiness will be so great that all the surrounding nations will marvel at the fertility of your land, and you will be a desirable land because everyone will want to live there. What is said about their tithes, we can say about the people of the Church, who are commanded not only to give tithes but also to give all they have to the poor and to the ministers of the Church.
But if they are unwilling to do this, at least let them, like the Jews, give some portion to the priests and the poor, so they do not feel God's anger, but rather experience His most gracious generosity.
"Your words have been strong against me," says the Lord, and you say, "What have we spoken against you?" You have said, "It is useless to serve the Lord, and what profit is there because we have kept His commandments?"
As previously mentioned, the people who returned from captivity and were knowledgeable of God's law, and seemed to observe the law, paying tithes, and fulfilling other commands of the law, saw all the surrounding nations prospering in everything while they themselves languished in poverty and want. They said: "What good is it to worship the true God and keep His commandments?"
Therefore, the Lord says through the prophet: "Your words have been strong against me," meaning your words have weighed heavily against me. But they, not understanding that they were sinning gravely in their words of blasphemy spoken against the Lord, ask: "What have we spoken against you?" To which the Lord responds: "You have said, 'It is useless to serve God, and what profit, that is, what use, what reward, is there because we keep His commandments?'"
They spoke this way because they wanted immediate rewards for serving God, and therefore they did not deserve to find it in the future. Unlike them, holy Tobias said: "We are the children of the saints, and we expect another life."
They further add: "And because we walked mournfully before the Lord of hosts?" There is indeed a sorrow in religion when someone walks simply and humbly, as there is praiseworthy shame, of which it is said: "There is a shame that brings glory." Of such sorrow, the Psalmist says: "All day long I walked in sorrow."
Therefore, now we call the arrogant blessed, that is the proud, who do not fear to hurl such blasphemies against God. Why he calls them blessed, he shows by adding: "Indeed, those who do wickedness are built up, that is, in worldly glory, and after their crimes, they enjoy all prosperity."
They tested or resisted God by doing things contrary to His commandments.
They were saved, believing their safety was just the happiness of this present age.
These things, literally said about the Jews, can also be understood, not inappropriately, about heretics and all those who boast about the prosperity of this present life.
These people advance in their impiety and lead many others into their wickedness.
Then those who feared the Lord spoke, each to their neighbor.
The sense is this: When blasphemers and those who criticize God's judgments, which are sometimes hidden but always just, speak, then those who feared God spoke to each other.
They understood that the reward for good and evil does not always come in this present age but is reserved for the future.
Humans cannot know the unfathomable judgments of God, nor should they dispute His fairness and justice.
It is fitting for the holy ones to speak of such things.
It does not say what those who fear God spoke, so we might understand that they spoke of things contained in the words of the Scriptures.
But if we read according to the Septuagint interpreters: "These things were spoken by those who fear," it should be taken ironically and announced in a subdued voice, "These things we have said were spoken by those who fear," meaning those who do not fear God, who should not even think such things, much less speak them.
The Lord paid attention and listened, and a book of remembrance was written before Him for those who fear the Lord and think on His name. The Lord paid attention and listened to the just and those who feared the Lord discussing among themselves, whose hearing is eternal knowledge. For to Him, hearing is the same as seeing. He is entirely an ear and entirely an eye, and from His entirety, He sees and hears. Therefore He heard, meaning He foreknew, and predestined before all ages.
A book of remembrance was written before Him. This book is eternal memory, in which all the saints are inscribed and predestined before God. This book is referred to in the Revelation: "The books were opened, and another book was opened, which is the book of life."
The two open books are the Testaments, by which each person will be judged.
The truly open book is the memory of what each individual has done.
Hence, it is well stated in some manuscripts: “It is the book of each person's life.
” This book is written as a monument for those who fear God, so they know that when the day of judgment comes, punishments will be given to the blasphemous and wicked, and rewards to those who fear God.
About this book, the Lord says in the Gospel: “Rejoice because your names are written in heaven.
” The Psalmist, as if explaining, says: “The righteous will be remembered forever.
”
And they will be mine, says the Lord of hosts, on the day when I make them my special possession, and I will spare them as a man spares his son who serves him.
Then you will return and see the difference between the righteous and the wicked, between one who serves God and one who does not serve him.
They will be my special possession, because I will choose them not only with a general call, by which all Christians are called, but also with a particular and unique call, by which only the chosen are called.
Of this, the Apostle says: “Those he called, he also justified.
” He also asserts that he was called in this way, saying: “Paul, a servant of Christ Jesus, called to be an apostle.
”
And I will spare them as a father spares his son who serves him, in whom there is a dual affection: piety towards the son and servitude towards the servant.
Then you who now blaspheme and say: “What profit is there in keeping his commandments?
” will recognize, by their election and your rejection, what is the difference between the righteous and the wicked, between one who serves God and one who does not serve him.
Chapter Four
Behold, the day is coming, burning like a furnace, and all the arrogant and evildoers will be stubble.
The day that is coming will set them on fire, says the Lord of Hosts.
This day is the time of universal judgment, which will be light for the saints but darkness for sinners.
It will be a day burning like a furnace, turning all the wicked into stubble and burning them with the eternal fires of that day.
When it sets them on fire and burns them up, it will leave them neither root nor branch.
This is what the wicked will suffer on the day of judgment.
Then it follows, saying what will come for those who fear the name of the Lord.
The sun of righteousness will rise for you who fear my name, with healing in its wings, and you will go out and leap like calves from the stall.
You will trample the wicked, for they will be ashes under the soles of your feet on the day when I act, says the Lord of Hosts.
The sun of righteousness is Christ, to whom God the Father has given judgment, and who will judge everything justly, allowing neither vices nor virtues to be hidden.
He will rise for those who fear God, but will set and be darkened for those who scorn and blaspheme him; hence the damned will say, as it is written in the Book of Wisdom: "The light of righteousness did not shine on us, and the sun did not rise upon us."
In the wings of this sun is healing, to protect those healed through repentance and bring them back to the folds of his flock, as it is written in Deuteronomy: "He spread his wings, etc."
Then those who were held captive in the prison of this world will go out and leap like calves from the stall, pleasing to God as sacrifices, renewed and shining, having cast off the squalor of mortality.
Or, as another version says, like calves freed from chains, from which the Apostle wished to be liberated, saying: "I desire to depart and be with Christ."
Not content with such joy, they will trample the wicked, for they will be ashes under the soles of their feet, as the Apostle prays: "God will soon crush Satan under your feet."
They will trample not by gloating over their destruction but by agreeing with God's just judgment, and with no compassion in their hearts toward them.
Compared to the divine majesty, the saints see themselves as mere ashes.
That's why Abraham said, "I will speak to my Lord, even though I am dust and ashes." But the proud, like their leader who said, "I will ascend above the heights of the clouds, I will be like the Most High," will be brought down to the pit of hell and will truly be ashes under the feet of the saints.
Remember the law of my servant Moses, which I commanded him in Horeb for all Israel, with statutes and judgments. Horeb is a mountain in Sinai where Moses received the law written by the finger of God on stone tablets. Since you know that the day of judgment is coming, when the root and branch of the proud will be burned by fire, but for those who fear, the sun of righteousness will rise, you must remember the law I gave you through Moses and act upon its teachings.
Moreover, we are commanded to remember the spiritual and divine law, and to fulfill it not carnally, but spiritually. For the Apostle says that the law is spiritual. The Psalmist also shows that the law is spiritual, saying: "Open my eyes, that I may see the wonderful things in your law." This spiritual law was given by the Lord in Horeb, which means dryness, because the law, understood spiritually, dries up all the moisture of vice. He spoke to Israel of statutes and judgments because the mysteries of the Scriptures are meant for those worthy of seeing God with a pure heart.
"Behold, I will send you Elijah the prophet before the great and terrible day of the Lord comes, and he will turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the hearts of the children to their fathers, lest I come and strike the land with a curse." After reminding us to remember the law of Moses, he says he will send Elijah, because Moses represents the law and Elijah symbolizes prophecy. This is why, when the Lord was transfigured on the mountain, Moses and Elijah appeared with him, speaking, as both the law and the prophets foretold the coming of Christ.
Therefore, before the day of judgment comes, the Lord will send Elijah, whose name means "My God is the Lord," and he is the Tishbite from the town of Tishbe, which means conversion.
The prophets encourage us daily to convert and repent, so that the heart of the fathers may turn to the children.
This means that the faith of Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, and the other patriarchs can inspire and teach the children through prophetic readings.
In this way, what they believed about Christ being fulfilled, we may also believe has been fulfilled.
Alternatively, the heart of the fathers—that is, the mind of God that was in the fathers—may be transferred to the children of adoption, and the heart of the children may turn to the fathers.
This ensures that believers from both Gentiles and Jews can agree in faith and religion with the Father in Christ.
If the spiritual understanding of prophecy does not turn the heart of the fathers to the children, and the heart of the children to the fathers, the coming Lord will strike the earth with a curse.
This curse represents the alienation of eternal damnation, where He will say to those on His left: "Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire."
He mentions striking not only the heavens—those who live a heavenly way of life—but also the earth—those who are wise in earthly matters and eager for earthly deeds.
We have discussed Elijah, following the teachings, although many of us also believe he will literally come and restore all things and pay the debt of death. However, when the apostles asked the Lord about Elijah's coming, He replied: "Elijah has already come, and they did not recognize him, but did to him whatever they wished," implying that John was to be understood as Elijah. He added: "If you are willing to accept it, John himself is Elijah who is to come."