Chapter One: On the Three Dwellings - The Kingdom of God, the World, and Hell; The Good of the Kingdom of God and the Evils of Hell
Under the hand of Almighty God, there are three dwellings: the highest, the lowest, and the middle.
The highest is known as the Kingdom of God or the Kingdom of Heaven; the lowest is called hell; and the middle is referred to as the present world or the earth.
The extremes are completely opposed to each other and have no connection.
For what fellowship can light have with darkness, and Christ with Belial?
Second Corinthians 6:14, 15.
The middle, however, bears some resemblance to both extremes.
It contains light and darkness, cold and heat, pain and health, joy and sorrow, hate and love, good and evil, just and unjust, masters and servants, rule and subjection, hunger and satisfaction, death and life, and countless other things.
Among all these, one part reflects the image of the Kingdom of God, while the other mirrors hell.
This world is a mix of good and evil; but in the Kingdom of God, there are only good people, and in hell, only evil ones.
Each place draws from the middle.
Some people from this world are lifted to heaven, while others are pulled into hell.
For like is joined to like, meaning good people are with good people, and evil people with evil people; just humans with just angels, and transgressing humans with transgressing angels; servants of God with God, and servants of the devil with the devil.
The blessed are called to the Kingdom prepared for them from the foundation of the world, while the cursed are cast into eternal fire, prepared for the devil and his angels.
Matthew 25:34, 41.
However, to speak, think, or truly understand the goods of the heavenly Kingdom as they are, is beyond anyone clothed in flesh; for they are much greater and better than can be imagined or understood.
Hence it is written: "What no eye has seen, nor ear heard, nor the heart of man imagined, what God has prepared for those who love him."
First Corinthians 2:9.
The Kingdom of God surpasses all fame, exceeds all praise, is beyond all knowledge, and is more excellent than any imagined glory.
Even to speak or think about the evils of hell as they truly are is impossible; they are far worse than we can imagine.
The kingdom of God, on the other hand, is filled with light, peace, love, wisdom, glory, honor, sweetness, affection, music, joy, everlasting happiness, and every indescribable good beyond words or thoughts.
Hell, however, is a place of darkness, discord, hatred, foolishness, misery, disgrace, bitterness, offense, pain, burning, thirst, hunger, unquenchable fire, sadness, everlasting vengeance, and every unspeakable evil beyond imagination.
In heaven, the inhabitants are righteous people and angels, with Almighty God as their king.
In stark contrast, the inhabitants of hell are wicked people and demons, led by the devil.
For the just, the vision of holy people and angels, and above all, of God Himself, brings satisfaction.
Meanwhile, the wicked and sinners are tormented by the sight of condemned people and demons, and above all, the devil himself.
Nothing is desired in the kingdom of God that isn't already there.
But in hell, nothing desired is ever found.
In God's kingdom, everything that pleases, delights, and satisfies is present.
In contrast, in the pit of everlasting misery, only what displeases, offends, and torments is found.
In the eternal kingdom, there is life without death, truth without error, and happiness without disturbance.
Every good abounds in the kingdom of God, with no evil present.
Conversely, every evil is abundant in the prison of the devil, with no good present.
No unworthy person is accepted into the kingdom of God; likewise, no worthy or just person is dragged to hell.
Chapter Two: On Infernal Punishments
There are two main torments in hell: unbearable cold and the heat of unquenchable fire.
As it is mentioned in the Gospel: "There will be weeping and gnashing of teeth" Matthew thirteen:fifty-one; twenty-two:thirteen; and twenty-five:thirty.
Weeping and the melting of eyes arise from heat, while the gnashing of teeth comes from the cold.
This is also reflected in the words of the blessed Job: "They pass from the waters of snow to excessive heat" Job twenty-four:nineteen.
From these two sources stem countless types of punishments: unbearable thirst, the agony of hunger, the torment of stench, the horror, the fear, the anguish, the darkness, the severity of torturers, the presence of demons, the ferocity of beasts, the cruelty of attendants, the tearing by immortal worms, the worm of conscience, fiery tears, sighs, miseries, pain without remedy, chains without release, eternal death, punishment without end, and the absence of Christ after having seen Him, which alone surpasses all the aforementioned and is more intolerable than all punishments.
Chapter Three: On Those Whom the Eternity of Punishment Does Not Deter from Worldly Pleasure.
The Double Punishment of Hell.
One Hundred Years Is No Portion of Eternity.
Woe to those who are destined to endure all these everlasting evils for the brief pleasure of an hour.
The glory of this entire world, though vast, pales in comparison to eternal glory.
It would have been better for them, as was said about the unfortunate Judas in Matthew 26:24, not to have been born, than to suffer the torments of hell for their wicked deeds.
What could be more foolish or insane than being deceived by mere shadows and images of true glory, delight, beauty, and honor, like children, instead of seeking the real thing?
Who would choose a reflection of gold in water, ignoring the real gold, and not be seen as foolish by everyone?
Who would prefer a reflection of the sun in a mirror over the sun itself without being ridiculed?
In the same way, we should pity, not mock, those who pursue the fleeting pleasures of this world and the flesh, ignoring eternal glory and the indescribable joys of heaven.
This is the sad and foolish choice of those whose minds are not sound, even if the unspeakable torments of hell weren't the consequence.
The dual punishment is indeed being excluded from the kingdom of God and being eternally in hell, condemned with the devil, losing the presence of angels, and enduring the terrifying presence of demons.
The extent to which this should be avoided, shunned, and feared cannot be overstated.
Who in their right mind would choose a hundred years of punishment for just one day of pleasure?
Yet, the miserable and utterly unwisely follow the pleasures of the flesh, failing to avoid intolerable punishments, not for a hundred years, not for a thousand times a thousand, but for eternity, for the fleeting delights of forty or sixty years, or any corruptible pleasure.
How much difference is there between one day and one hundred years?
It's not just that; there's an even greater difference between forty, sixty, or one hundred years and eternity, whether it involves future good or bad.
One day is a small part of a hundred-year span, although a very small part; but a hundred-year span is no part at all in eternity.
If, for example, a hundredth or a thousandth part were a portion of eternity, then multiplying that portion by a hundred or a thousand times would mean eternity would cease to exist, which contradicts the concept of eternity.
If eternity were to end in any way or at any time, it wouldn't be eternity at all.
Chapter Four: From the Broad Way to the Narrow.
The Happiness of the Blessed, Knowledge, and the Love of Their Own Fate.
On the Unspeakable Sweetness of the Vision of God.
Therefore, we must strongly resist earthly pleasures, firmly fight against the deceptive allurements of this world, and be vigilant against the various suggestions of Satan.
We must diligently avoid the broad way of the world that leads to death Matthew 7:13;
But with all the desire of the heart, we must approach and seek after the narrow way that leads to life.
This narrow way is the path of abstinence, chastity, humility, and all religious devotion, which Christ has walked before us on His journey to His kingdom.
Let us follow in His footsteps until we reach the royal city where He reigns.
Whatever we can say about this city is like a drop from the sea or a spark from a fire.
In this city, the righteous will shine like the sun as the Lord says in Matthew 13:43.
There will be perfect peace, perfect rest, no labor, no pain, no poverty, no old age, no death, no night, and no desire for food or thirst;
The food and drink of all will be the vision of Christ and the Holy Trinity, and the contemplation with the pure eye of the heart of the Divine itself.
And the continual reading, so to speak, of the book of life, that is, eternal truth and supreme wisdom, and the vision of the Word of God, which is Jesus Christ;
Where whatever is hidden from us now will be more clearly revealed;
Where it will be clear why one is chosen and another rejected;
Why one is taken into the kingdom and another reduced to servitude;
Why one dies in the womb, another in infancy, another in youth, and another in old age;
Why one is poor and another rich;
Why the son of an adulteress is baptized and sometimes the son of a legitimate wife dies before baptism;
Why one who begins to live well sometimes ends poorly, and one who begins poorly often ends well.
All these things and many such matters will be plain and open in the book of life.
In the same city, the reward of each will be the reward of all, and the good of all will be evident to everyone through the love of each person.
There, the good of all will be open to everyone.
In that place, everyone will understand each other's thoughts.
No one will be arrogant or envious.
How could someone who loves everyone as themselves feel envy, when no one envies themselves?
No one will wish to be better or higher than they are, because being different from what they deserve wouldn't be right.
Nor will they want to be different from what they are, because being as they will be is beautiful, not just for themselves but for the entire body of the heavenly Church.
Just as a body would look deformed and unattractive if any part were placed higher or lower than nature intended, so too would someone be out of place in God's kingdom if they were positioned higher than the skill and will of the Almighty Creator intended.
This would bring disgrace, not only to themselves but to the whole assembly.
Even the least among them will have greater glory than owning the entire world, even if it were eternal.
It's truly insignificant to enjoy the elements compared to enjoying and rejoicing in God Himself, or to take pleasure in visible and physical things.
The beauty of justice and the joy of eternal light, which is unchanging truth and wisdom, is so profound that even if one could experience it for just a single day, innumerable years of this life filled with material pleasures would rightfully be considered worthless.
It wasn't said in vain or without deep feeling:
"For one day in your courts is better than a thousand elsewhere" Psalm 84:10.
Nothing compares to the delight and joy that come from the invisible and incorporeal, from the company of angels and all the righteous, from the certain knowledge and understanding of the divine nature itself, and from seeing God face to face.
The angels marvel at His beauty, the dead are raised by His command, and His wisdom is beyond measure Psalm 147:5.
Psalm one hundred forty-six, verse five:
Whose kingdom knows no end and whose glory is beyond description;
whose light is so bright that it outshines the sun, making the sun seem dim;
whose sweetness is so great that, in comparison, honey tastes as bitter as wormwood;
whose face, if seen by those in hell, would take away their pain, sorrow, and sadness;
whose presence, if it appeared in hell alongside the holy, would turn it into a paradise;
by whose will not even a leaf falls from a tree;
whose fiery eyes reach the deepest parts of hell;
whose ear hears the silent voice of the heart, which is thought;
whose eye hears as well as it sees;
whose ear sees as well as it hears, for they are not of the body, but of the highest wisdom and certain knowledge.
Whose delights satisfy without causing weariness: once found by the blessed, they are always desired, quenching hunger and thirst without pain, and always bringing joy with a burning desire.
Whose wondrous secrets remain forever new and astonishing to those who see them, causing as much wonder after a thousand and a thousand thousand years as they did at first sight.
And although angels have seen them since the beginning of the world, they admire them today just as much as on the first day; otherwise, they would have long since lost their value from constant viewing by the angels.
Whose knowledge of the past and future is not past and future, but present.
Chapter Five: All Things Are Present to God, Without Prejudice to Human Freedom
We discuss God's speech and praise, His existence before time, and how true evil is worse than false evil.
The vision God grants to the blessed, along with His eternity and knowledge, is profound.
He doesn't see the Day of Judgment or the first day of the world in the way we do, but He perceives both.
His foreknowledge doesn't compel anyone to sin, a misconception many hold.
They argue that if God foresaw Adam's sin, Adam couldn't have avoided it.
This mistake leads to the blasphemous idea that God causes sin, yet they are trapped by their own logic.
If God's foreknowledge makes things inevitable, then man sins by his own will, not out of necessity, because God foresaw him sinning by choice, not compulsion.
Therefore, if God's foreknowledge can't be avoided, man sinned by choice, without any other force compelling him, because God foresaw him sinning this way.
Thus, if he sinned voluntarily, he wasn't forced.
If he wasn't forced to sin, he could have chosen not to; thus, he deserved punishment because he sinned willingly.
Otherwise, he wouldn't face God's penalty of death.
God's speech is a hidden inspiration, revealing His will and love invisibly to minds, leading Angels to obey Him in all things.
His praise for the chosen ones is the way He will showcase their good deeds to all, and the ongoing praise from the chosen is their eternal admiration of Him.
In a wondrous way, He did not precede the world and time by time itself; He always existed without a beginning.
Time didn't exist before the world; it was created with it.
If time began with the world, it wasn't made before it.
So, as we've said, God didn't precede the times and the world, which are simultaneous with them, but slightly prior, as by His motion, they began.
Whatever moves precedes its own motion.
God existed before the world, beyond time itself.
There was no time before the world began.
His light dispels the darkness of ignorance, and we understand that part of this light reveals everything we've said to be true and certain.
Through this same light, we recognize that truth is better than falsehood.
However, true evil or true sin is worse than false evil or false sin-not because it is true, but because it is evil or sin.
Otherwise, it couldn't be considered evil or sin unless it was truly evil or sin; a false evil is not evil, just as false silver is not silver.
Someone might truthfully claim that evil or sin has arisen or been created, implying it's a work of truth, which is entirely false.
Everything true comes from truth, and everything true, inasmuch as it is true, is good.
Therefore, truth gives true existence to evil or sin, but not the evil or sin itself; one thing is the evil itself, another is its true existence.
Although the evil itself is not good, it is good that it exists as truth.
Otherwise, if it were not good for evil to exist, God wouldn't allow it to happen.
Indeed, the Almighty creates many good things from evil, like forming and making good people from human adultery.
If even a small part of that light, shining through narrow gaps, has helped us understand these truths and all other things we know, imagine the kind and amount of light of knowledge and wisdom we'll experience there, where we will see the sun of truth face to face, and truly know wisdom.
His presence makes those who are with Him similar to Him.
Whoever adheres to true wisdom, true beauty, and true eternity will indeed become wise, beautiful, and eternal.
Thus, His absence makes us unlike Him in every way.
His eternity is without beginning and without end.
If there were a time when He did not exist, who would have created Him?
Because He alone is God, and before Him, there was no other God, nor is there now, nor will there be.
Surely, He did not create Himself, since nothing creates itself; by what power would one who did not exist at all make himself?
This means that God was not created at all.
Since God was never created, He existed before everything else without having a beginning.
Anything that was created has a beginning, and anything with a beginning was undoubtedly made by God, who was not made but created everything.
His knowledge, without any change in understanding and without shifting back and forth, comprehends and grasps the infinite truth of all creatures-
angels, humans, stars, grains of sand, hairs, words, thoughts, every moment-together and all at once.
Therefore, God is the source and origin of all knowledge: the more someone drinks from it, the more they will thirst.
Chapter Six: The Knowledge of the Blessed.
On the Threefold Vision: Bodily, Spiritual, Intellectual.
As we've mentioned before, the kingdom of the whole world, even if it were eternal, is far surpassed by the company of angels and saints, and by the vision of God Himself.
In this vision, a threefold knowledge emerges: the person who sees, God who is seen, and all others who will see and understand everything.
Just as through a glass mirror we experience a threefold vision-seeing ourselves, the mirror itself, and whatever is present-so through the mirror of divine clarity, we will see God Himself as much as it is possible for a creature.
We will know ourselves and others with true and certain knowledge.
Then, by seeing God, we will perceive the hidden things of creation and even hell itself.
It will be clear to the righteous how God is invisible, incomparable, without beginning and without end, before all things and after all things.
We will understand the difference between being born, which pertains to the Son, and proceeding, which pertains to the Holy Spirit.
One is born from one; the other proceeds from two.
The Father did not precede the Son in time, but in origin, nor the Holy Spirit.
All things of God are one in God, except in relation.
The wisdom of God, truth, and eternity are not different from each other, but are one, like all other things.
The wisdom of God is not more wisdom than truth, nor more truth than wisdom, nor more than eternity, nor all other things of God.
They are one in God, and not only are these the same in God, but they are not other than God Himself.
The world was in God before it existed in itself, not as the world, but as God.
He is entirely everywhere without place, great without size, good without quality.
He penetrates all things, clean and unclean, without being polluted.
If visible light can illuminate every place, even penetrating refuse heaps without absorbing their stench or being polluted, how much more does God, who is invisible and unchanging light, penetrate, govern, sustain, surround, and illuminate all things without any change or pollution?
This applies not only in the heavens and on earth but also in hell.
Then, God's chosen ones will experience a threefold vision:
First, a physical vision, where they will see bodies shining like the sun, the moon, or the stars.
Second, a spiritual vision, where they will perceive the likenesses of bodies in spirit, not through deceptive imagination; this vision is also enjoyed today by the spirits of the righteous beyond the confines of the body.
And third, an intellectual vision, where with the pure eye of the mind in spirit, they will see God, their own souls, their inner virtues, and angelic spirits.
Then they will give thanks to God twice:
First, for their deliverance from eternal damnation,
and second, for the indescribable reward of blessings.
At that time, the common adversary and enemy of all, the devil, will be condemned in the presence of God's chosen ones.
His condemnation and unbearable punishment will provide a delightful spectacle for the elect.
Then, with the most ardent love, they will love their liberator and giver of all good things.
With endless and unfailing heartfelt praise, they will glorify the almighty, kind, and merciful God, to whom honor and glory belong now and forever and ever.
Amen.