Chapter One: On the Blessing of Reuben, the Firstborn of the Sons of Jacob
Jacob the patriarch, foreseeing the Church's future in the Holy Spirit, describes this state as he blesses his sons, saying:
"Reuben, my firstborn, you are my strength and the beginning of my sorrow, foremost in gifts, greater in authority, you have been unstable as water" (Genesis 49).
He starts his prophecy with Reuben, the firstborn, and continues down to Benjamin, the youngest, reaching the conclusion.
Since the Church's structure includes leaders and followers, Reuben symbolizes the leaders, while Benjamin represents all good and perfect followers.
Indeed, any good leader can be called Reuben, meaning "seeing a son," when he diligently cares for both himself and his followers with wisdom and vigilance.
He is rightly called God's firstborn, because just as the kingdom and priesthood were once hereditary rights of the firstborn, now, in spiritual terms, all good leaders are kings and priests.
These kings are truly powerful, knowing how to lead themselves by living virtuously and advising their followers wisely.
They are also priests because they offer gifts and sacrifices daily for themselves and their people.
Such kings and priests are affectionately addressed by God Almighty, our true Jacob, who says: "You are my strength."
They deserve to be called the strength of the Lord when, empowered in the Lord, they boldly resist carnal desires and continually support their weaker subjects, not just through preaching but also through diligent prayer.
How this admirable strength is achieved is mystically suggested by the words: "And the beginning of my sorrow."
There is a kind of pain that separates a person from God, and another that the merciful Lord embraces as His own.
This good pain is highly valued when someone groans and grieves, continually praying to God for their own sins and the sins of others.
One feels this good pain when troubled and saddened by the struggles of this mortal life, causing them to feel distant from the Lord.
By lamenting in this way before the Lord, it marks the beginning of God's pain, leading to repentance and atonement, as they humbly inspire others with words and examples to seek eternal life.
This pain of leaders and followers is aptly called the pain of God the Father because He approves of it, viewing the pain of His people as His own.
Hence, He says, "You, my firstborn, are my strength and the beginning of my pain."
It's as if He's saying: "You are to govern yourself and your followers according to my will.
You should support those who are weak.
You must inspire my pain- the pain that pleases me- into the hearts of my people, because you are first in gifts, and greater in command.
You are first in gifts because I've given you greater prudence, wisdom, understanding, and other virtues above others.
You are greater in command because I've appointed you as a leader, master, and teacher over others.
But you've only partially responded to my gifts.
You've been poured out like water.
Water symbolizes the grace of preaching and spiritual teaching, as the Lord mentions in the Gospel: 'Whoever drinks the water I give them will become a spring of water welling up to eternal life' (John chapter 4, verse 14).
Just as water extinguishes, washes, and refreshes, so does good preaching cleanse the hearts of followers, drawing out the water of contrition from deep within, accomplishing the cleansing of sins.
It quenches thirst, refreshes, and even awakens the hunger and thirst for heavenly joys.
When a good leader achieves this grace, it's fittingly highlighted in the word that follows, emphasizing the humility they must maintain: 'Do not grow.
'
There's a type of growth that is beneficial and another that is harmful.
A person grows well when they develop virtues, but they grow poorly when they become arrogant because of these virtues.
So, don't grow in pride or arrogance by claiming what is mine as your own, or you might seem ungrateful to me.
Everything you have, you've received from me; I'm the one who gave it, and I can take it away whenever I choose.
For I will show mercy to whomever I choose, and I will be compassionate to whomever I please.
Exodus Thirty Three Nineteen.
So, the higher you are elevated by my gift, the more humble you should be in your own eyes, and you must attribute everything you have to me alone.
You've ascended your father's bed.
By this, we mean the innocent, pure, clean, and spotless souls of your subjects, which can rightly be called the bed of God the Father because they provide a pleasant and desirable resting place for Him, whom even the heavens cannot contain.
You've ascended, he says, your father's bed because you've received power and authority over the bodies and souls of my humble ones in my place and on my behalf.
Therefore, if you've grown inwardly from such a great gift of mine, meaning if you haven't maintained true humility, you've stained my bed.
The bed of God signifies the heart of any good leader.
It must always be humble before God, yet it becomes stained when it's tainted by the harmful dust of pride and arrogance.
Since we've said that through Reuben, Jacob's firstborn, we should understand the order, life, and conduct of leaders, we must also consider how, in the last of the same sons, Benjamin, we can observe the order of the perfected among the subjects.
Chapter Two: On the Blessing of Benjamin
Benjamin, he says, is a ravenous wolf.
In the morning, he will devour the prey, and in the evening, he will divide the spoils.
(Genesis 49)
Benjamin is interpreted as the son of the right hand.
So, anyone who wishes to become and be recognized as the sons of the right hand of God must strive to imitate the nature of a wolf.
A wolf's nature is to seize what belongs to others, always yearning to devour what is not his.
Similarly, a person who seeks salvation, and to be counted among the sons of the right hand of God, must always desire what belongs to others.
This means constantly striving to satisfy his hungry soul with things that are not his own.
By things that are not ours, we can appropriately understand spiritual and heavenly matters.
While a person, being earthly and carnal, can claim things of earth and flesh as his own, anything related to spiritual or heavenly matters is not his own.
Therefore, Benjamin becomes like a ravenous wolf when a good follower, with all his heart's desire, begins to yearn for those heavenly and spiritual things that are not his own.
He is described as ravenous, suggesting boldness in seizing; bold is he who dares what should and should not be dared.
From the desire for heavenly and spiritual goods, a healthy and praiseworthy boldness is born within a person because, with the confidence he has in the Lord, he strives to seize, that is, to obtain from God, the grace of heavenly sweetness.
This grace is reserved for the chosen and beloved sons of God, through a certain constant effort of daily labor.
This good boldness, this commendable seizing, is not displeasing to God, as the following words mystically suggest:
In the morning, he says, he will devour the prey, and in the evening, he will divide the spoils.
By morning, the divine illumination or knowledge of God is appropriately received; by evening, the knowledge of oneself is understood.
When a person is illuminated inwardly by the grace of heavenly visitation, this is a sweet and desirable morning, whose radiance leads him to the desired knowledge of God.
On this bright morning, he enjoys his reward, feeling refreshed by the long-awaited blessing of heavenly sweetness.
After this lovely morning comes the evening, when he begins to truly and perfectly understand himself, with humility and insight.
In this evening of perfect self-awareness, he redirects his efforts, striving to turn all parts of his body, once under the influence of evil, towards serving Christ.
He aims to use his eyes, ears, and hands only in ways that he believes will honor and praise God's name.
Chapter Three: On the Blessing of Simeon and Levi, Brothers
We see the order of leaders and followers, represented by Reuben and Benjamin, as encompassing both the penitent and the innocent, as well as the active and the contemplative.
This dual nature is reflected in the ten remaining sons of Jacob, positioned between Reuben and Benjamin.
In Simeon, Levi, Judah, Zebulun, and Issachar, we find the active life, while Dan, Gad, Asher, Naphtali, and Joseph represent the contemplative life.
The active life is well illustrated by Simeon, Levi, Judah, Zebulun, and Issachar.
Simeon means "hearing," Levi "added," Judah "confessing," Zebulun "dwelling of strength," and Issachar "reward."
The active life, being challenging and demanding, is fittingly seen in Simeon as the penitent, Levi as the convert, Judah as the confessor, Zebulun as those battling against evil, and Issachar as those who worthily satisfy God.
A person who truly repents can be seen as both Simeon and Levi, when, through genuine repentance, they are heard by the Lord and added to the community of the righteous, united with Christ through holy actions and righteous desires.
It is rightly said of such a person: "Simeon and Levi are brothers, instruments of violence are their swords" (Genesis chapter 49).
The blessed patriarch, inspired by the Holy Spirit, foresaw in his sons that the true sons of Jacob, all destined for eternal life, although once instruments of wickedness due to sin, would, through repentance and conversion, become instruments fighting strongly against that same wickedness.
Simeon and Levi, representing the penitent and the converts, are rightly called brothers, since neither repentance without conversion, nor conversion without repentance is sufficient for salvation.
However, such repentance and conversion must be adorned with the virtue of discretion to please almighty God.
Therefore, it's fittingly added:
"May my soul not enter their counsel, and may my glory not be in their assembly, because in their anger they killed a man, and by their will, they demolished a wall."
Some penitents, when they begin their spiritual journey, tend to overburden themselves with excessive labor. However, the Almighty doesn't approve of this kind of fervor, which is why it is said, "May my soul not enter their counsel."
It's as if to say: My soul doesn't find joy in their counsel, because in their indiscriminate and imprudent self-affliction, they become useless to me and themselves, bringing no joy to my heart.
When someone starts something without seeking God's counsel, or the counsel of those who represent God, they often attribute their actions to their own strength rather than to God. The Lord therefore adds:
"And may my glory not be in their assembly," meaning: In the assembly, or in their multitude of labors, my glory won't be present, because in what they do without discretion, they seek their own praise and glory, not mine.
I won't take pride in them, because in their anger they killed a man, and by their will, they demolished a wall.
The "man" represents strength and bodily vigor; the "wall" symbolizes hardness of heart. They kill a man in their anger when, driven by indiscreet fervor, they mortify their flesh excessively. They demolish the wall by their own will when they soften the hardness of their heart through voluntary labors, eventually achieving enlightenment and peace of mind.
But cursed is their anger, because it is persistent, and their indignation, because it is harsh.
The fervor of those penitents and converts, who, at the start of their journey, unjustly weaken their bodies through excessive labor, making themselves unfit for good works, can rightly be called cursed anger. This is because it persists without the obedience to God and their spiritual guides, lacking God's blessing.
Their anger is rightly called harsh, meaning unyielding, because they can't be turned back by any command or warning from their teachers due to their reckless severity.
But will those who are meant to be saved perish through such stubborn rage and harsh anger?
Not at all.
"I will divide them," says the Lord, "in Jacob, and scatter them in Israel."
By Jacob, meaning "supplanter," the overcoming of vices and the commendable actions of an active life are fittingly described.
By Israel, meaning "man seeing God," the contemplation of the heart and the good actions of a contemplative life are suitably expressed.
God Almighty divides a person in Jacob when He inwardly teaches them through His mercy how, by overcoming vices with the success of virtues, they should separate and cast away harmful and useless things from the good deeds they performed in active life.
This beneficial division happens when they try to act with cautious discernment, carefully and for God's sake.
After this praiseworthy division, they are scattered in Israel, that is, into the contemplation of the mind.
And note what is said: "I will scatter."
That which is scattered into tiny divided parts gradually diminishes and is reduced to nothing.
Thus, when a person reaches the sweet contemplation of the mind through God's mercy, whatever has clung to their body through less discerning actions, or to their heart through wicked thoughts or feelings up to that point, is gradually dispersed and cast away with the help and grace of God.
They also suitably receive the noble name of Judah when, having been somewhat exercised in active and contemplative life, they turn to humble, true, and perfect confession.
And after true confession of sins, they receive the sweetest blessing from God the Father, which follows.
Chapter Four: On the Blessing of Judah
Judah, your brothers will praise you.
Who, I ask, can more fittingly represent these brothers than the angelic hosts of the heavenly army, who stand by Judah-the one who sincerely and humbly confesses-even at the very moment of his confession?
They embrace the true humility of the penitent, the humble repentance of the confessor, and lift him up with great praises before the eyes of the Supreme Majesty as a brother and chosen son of the beloved Father.
The spiritual growth of a person, still journeying on earth, brings joy and happiness to the angelic virtues in heaven.
The Lord says, "Judah, your brothers will praise you." It is as if He is saying: Because you have truly humbled yourself before me, you have rightly earned praise from your brothers, the angelic spirits. When you were small in your own eyes, I made you the leader over the tribes of Israel. Is it any wonder we call the holy angels brothers of the chosen people when the Creator and Lord of angels Himself has deemed to call them brothers? As He says through the Prophet: "I will proclaim your name to my brothers, in the midst of the congregation I will praise you." And again, after His resurrection, He says: "Go, tell my brothers" (Matthew 28:10).
Confessors, who receive the confession of the one confessing in the place of God, are called His brothers.
They praise the marvelous mercy of Almighty God in him and for him, rejoicing in his progress in every way.
Whoever has deserved to be lifted up before God by such praises from angels and people who witness the perfection of his life, the merciful and compassionate Lord, with the following words, suggests how he ought to watch over himself with a providential eye of caution, lest, through praise or vanity, the gift of God within him be lost.
"Your hand will be on the necks of your enemies, and the sons of your father will bow down to you." By "hand," we can understand good action; by "on the necks of your enemies," the hidden temptation of evil spirits, suggesting pride in the mind.
Pride is reflected in one's demeanor, as highlighted in the psalm by the Prophet:
The Lord, who is just, brings down the proud.
(Psalm 128:14)
The spirit of rebellion, always envious of human salvation, becomes even more aggressive towards those it sees advancing spiritually in God.
When it cannot succeed through external actions, it tries to undermine them with proud thoughts in their hearts.
Thus, the Lord says, your hand will be on the necks of your enemies; meaning, when you act well and worthily, do not become arrogant in your heart; always remember to stay humble.
If you do this, the children of your father will honor you.
Here, the father can be seen as either the devil or the present world, and the children as the works of the world, which are the works of sin.
Regarding this father, it was told to Abraham: Leave your country, your relatives, and your father's house.
(Genesis 12:1)
And again, the Lord advises every blessed soul through the Prophet, saying: Forget your people and your father's house.
(Psalm 45:11)
It is correctly stated, your father's house.
For once, we were children of the devil, and we were also children of the world.
We became children of the devil through the sin of the first man, but through baptism, we were reborn and became children of God by grace.
After this, by our own choices, we became children of the world when we succumbed more to worldly desires than to heavenly ones.
However, anyone who turns away from worldly vanity and returns fully to God through true repentance and confession, if they maintain true humility, will be honored by the children of their father because, having received the forgiveness of sins through God's mercy, they will be cleansed from dead works, contracted through devilish suggestions and love of the world.
And it is rightly said, the children of your father will honor you, because just as someone who wants to worship another person bows down, so all iniquity falls away and disappears from the soul of one who truly confesses and remains humble after confession, as God purifies them inwardly.
Our true Jacob, with a noble plan of piety and consolation, gives us an example of learning humility when he says:
The cub of the lion, Judah.
The lion is naturally the strongest of beasts.
It also sleeps with its eyes open, and when it roars, the other animals tremble at its voice.
Through the lion, we can understand any good and just teacher and instructor, who must be strong in holy work and in suppressing vices and carnal desires.
It sleeps with its eyes open when it stays free from the world's disturbances, yet remains vigilant to the spiritual and physical needs of its followers.
When such a person preaches, all who recognize they've sometimes lived in a beastly way begin to tremble with a healthy fear at the joy of eternal life and the dangers of eternal damnation upon hearing his voice.
Therefore, Almighty God wants everyone who desires to be His child to always strive for humility.
Thus, he says, The cub of the lion, Judah;
as if to say: Be a cub of the lion, be a humble follower of the teacher and instructor I have appointed for you.
Be an imitator of his strength, a prudent follower of his teaching.
Remember why you came and where you decided to go.
To the prey, my son, you have ascended.
From the valley of this world, you have ascended to the heights of this holy conversion, so that you may seize what is not yours, that is, to be filled with spiritual sweetness and the gift of heavenly virtues.
You have ascended to take prey from the devil, recognizing that you were once his willing servant, you may snatch yourself from his power, and by living holy, justly, and soberly, restore yourself to me, your Creator and liberator, both in body and soul.
You have not been deprived of your desire due to the help of my preceding and subsequent grace.
You lay down to rest like a lion and a lioness.
Resting from troubles, you find peace in good things, like a lion-representing a good leader or teacher I provided; and like a lioness-the holy congregation that embraced you.
Blessed is the person who, by resting from sins and embracing good things, is worthy of praise from the Lord!
The next part of the text hints at the greater grace that will come to him.
"Who will rouse him?"
It's as if to say: Only the one to whom this name "who" truly applies, whose name is unknown, can bring him back from the death of sins, from the spiritual death now, so that after physical death, he may be restored to eternal salvation, resurrected both in body and soul.
This person will certainly be able to please God in life, as the text immediately adds:
"The scepter shall not depart from Judah, nor the ruler's staff from between his feet, until he comes who is to be sent."
The scepter, usually held by kings, symbolizes the royal authority through which a person revived from spiritual death governs himself in goodness and wards off evil.
The ruler's staff from between his feet can be understood as the sense and understanding of the heart.
Notice it says, "from between his feet."
It's as if one foot is the heart and the other is the body.
A person performs good deeds in the flesh, lifting himself to God; he possesses understanding in the heart, continually rising from the constraints of mortality to God and the freedom of the heavenly homeland.
A blessed person should be supported by these two feet until the one who is to be sent arrives, until the sweet love of God, which is the Holy Spirit, sent from above into human hearts, dispels the mind's darkness with the brilliance of his wondrous visitation and pours himself into the desiring heart with the grace of eternal sweetness.
And he will be the expectation of nations.
In him and through him, the forgiveness of all sins is accomplished.
When he arrives, he ignites the human heart with the invisible fire of his love, boosting spiritual steadfastness and fervor.
Thus, it is fittingly added: Binding his colt to the vine and his donkey to the choice vine, O my son.
The colt can symbolize a small and humble human spirit; the vine, a spiritual dwelling of conversation.
The Holy Spirit binds his colt to the vine when he strengthens a person's small and humble spirit with the sweetness of his love, confirming them in spiritual conversation.
This happens so that anything once seen as hard or difficult in the austere spiritual life, or any doubt or inconsistency they faced, completely disappears.
They begin to embrace and love both the bitter and the sweet, as much as humanly possible, for the sake of God.
He also binds his donkey to the choice vine when he aims to direct the body, represented by the donkey, and all bodily senses to the service, praise, and honor of our Lord Jesus Christ.
He is the vine from which the wine of eternal sweetness flows, as he declares in the Gospel: I am the true vine, and my Father is the gardener.
John, Chapter 15, Verse 1.
Therefore, anyone grafted into this vine, who delights in frequently engaging all senses and every part of the outer body in the service, praise, and honor of God, deserves to hear inwardly the sweetest voice of the Lord speaking invisibly: O my son!
For he is a son of God because he continually deserves to be intoxicated by the paternal sweetness.
Hence, it follows: He will wash his robe in wine, and his garment in the blood of grapes.
In the wine, the abundant grace of the Holy Spirit; in the robe, the soul adorned with humility and other virtues can be rightly understood.
The robe is washed in wine when a humble soul, cleansed and purified by compunction from the invisible source of eternal sweetness, strives to die completely to sins and vices, so it may be worthy to be clothed in Christ, its heavenly bridegroom.
He also washes his garment in the blood of grapes when, in line with the passion of Christ, he cleanses and renews his body daily.
The garment symbolizes this renewal from the oldness of sins.
As a person strengthens outwardly in virtues and virtuous actions, their spiritual sense and understanding grow inwardly.
Thus, it is rightly said: His eyes are more beautiful than wine, and his teeth are whiter than milk.
Here, wine represents either the strictness of the law or the joy of the present world; eyes symbolize understanding, and teeth symbolize spiritual senses.
When one begins to understand the strictness of the law on a spiritual level and shifts their senses from the straightforward meaning of the text to uncover the hidden sweetness of spiritual grace, their eyes are rightly seen as more beautiful than wine.
This is because the spiritual understanding that emerges from sacred Scripture is more beautiful, purer, and more joyful than all worldly pleasures.
He also has teeth whiter than milk when, strengthened by spiritual sense, and setting aside the basic letter, he begins to break down not only lighter but also deeper secrets of sacred Scripture with the strong teeth of constant meditation.
Chapter Five: On the Blessing of Zebulun
After Judah comes Zebulun, which means "dwelling of strength," fittingly following in order. Simply confessing sins isn't enough if, after confessing, one doesn't strive to resist sins and enemies with firm resolve. Therefore, it says:
"Zebulun will dwell on the seashore and be a haven for ships, reaching as far as Sidon" Genesis 49.
We can interpret dwelling on the seashore as the steadfastness of a heart made bitter through repentance. Those who fight effectively against the devil are said to dwell on the seashore because, through the unwavering bitterness of a penitent heart, demons are defeated, and vices are eradicated. So, anyone who wants to be stronger than their enemy in this intense battle should quickly seek refuge in the haven for ships.
A haven is a port where ships are safe after facing dangerous waves. This haven aptly represents the most peaceful port of eternal rest, where, after the trials and hardships of this life, the chosen are gathered. However, no one can reach this haven unless they are aboard the ships crafted by the Almighty for the salvation of people.
The term "ships" symbolizes the various orders within the holy Church that provide salvation and lift a person from the depths of vice to the port of eternal salvation.
There's also another haven of ships in this life, which is the stable love of God and love of neighbors. When someone finds stability in holy living through this love, it's rightly said that Zebulun dwells, or rests, in the haven for ships. For if the heart is truly aflame with love for God and neighbor inwardly, and outward challenges arise, there is true rest. Even if not fully realized yet, in hope, it's as though one rests happily with the Lord in the harbor of eternal salvation.
The shore pulls them back so they don't succumb to evil; the haven keeps them, allowing them to rejoice in doing good. Therefore, it immediately follows:
"Reaching as far as Sidon."
The pursuit of Sidon is often seen as futile.
Someone who reaches Sidon diligently seeks out everything insignificant or less commendable in their body or soul,
as if engaging in a meticulous hunt, aiming to reduce it to nothing.
Chapter Six: On the Blessing of Issachar
After this hunt with Zebulun, Issachar finds success by willingly embracing any work or difficulty for the sake of God.
This leads to the following:
Issachar is described as a strong donkey lying down between boundaries; he sees that rest is good and the land is excellent.
He bows his shoulder to bear burdens and becomes a servant of tribute.
(Genesis Chapter Forty-Nine)
Issachar, whose name means reward, offers a means to receive worthy satisfaction from God for sins, as we discussed earlier.
However, to make such satisfaction for past wrongs in a way that pleases Almighty God, one must strive to be a strong donkey.
A donkey is known for bearing burdens, patiently carrying everything placed on it.
Similarly, Issachar represents a person who strives to repay God with the reward of pious labor for what he unjustly took, thus embodying the qualities of a burden-bearing animal.
He must present himself as humble, strong, and gentle to endure whatever arises from his body's frailty, the malice of the old enemy, or even from those around him.
He should be strong in body to endure and strong in heart for patience.
The path to such great strength is mystically suggested by the following words:
Lying down, he says, between boundaries.
It's important to note that he mentions two boundaries here.
One boundary represents the eternal life we hope for; the other, eternal death, which we wish to escape.
To lie down is to rest in the humility of the heart.
When he considers the joy of eternal life on one side and reflects on the dangers and miseries of eternal death on the other, he becomes like a strong donkey lying between boundaries.
Motivated by the prospect of eternal happiness and the fear of eternal damnation, he is driven to endure physically and be patient in heart.
Through true humility, he advances to genuine peace of heart.
But where does this come from?
He understood that it was good, and that the land was the best, so he committed himself to it.
He saw how beneficial, pleasant, and delightful it is to rest in true humility in this life.
True humility brings true peace to both heart and body.
It's rightly called good because through it, one earns the way to the best land, the land of the living.
Good in hope, but best in eternal reward, as the Psalmist confirms, saying:
I believe that I shall see the goodness of the Lord in the land of the living
(Psalm 27:13).
Therefore, out of love and desire for this best land, he dedicates himself, courageously restraining himself, and devoutly preparing for patience and endurance.
And he became a servant to tribute.
He serves through tributes by devoutly accepting the labor and pain required from both body and heart.
In this way, the prophet David perfectly paid tributes when he said:
For you alone consider labor and pain
(Psalm 10:14).
We must constantly offer these tributes to God, serving Him with our bodies as much as we can, and with our hearts, always striving for heavenly desires.
This is the active life, aptly represented by Simeon, Levi, Judah, Zebulun, and Issachar, engaging in active labor while enjoying contemplative sweetness.
Chapter Seven: On the Blessing of Dan
Once the tasks of an active life are complete, the contemplative life begins.
This transition is well represented by the five brothers: Dan, Gad, Asher, Naphtali, and Joseph.
The contemplative life shines with the beauty of deep reflection, yet it still involves the efforts of active life.
Neither life can be perfectly or effectively practiced without the other, which is why it's aptly said:
Dan will judge his people, as one of the tribes of Israel.
Genesis 49.
Dan, meaning judgment, symbolizes the spiritual person who, through reflection and delight in the heavenly homeland, rises as much as possible above earthly actions.
This person carefully considers and judges not only their deeds and words but even the smallest thoughts, which are like their people, in line with the Scripture that says:
The spiritual person judges all things, but is judged by no one.
First Corinthians 2:15.
But since it's necessary for a person, in both active and contemplative life, to wisely provide for themselves, the following blessing or prophecy of the patriarch Jacob suggests this in a mystical way:
Let Dan be a serpent on the road, a horned snake on the path, biting the horse's heels so that its rider falls backward.
The serpent, or snake, moves so smoothly that it can often be seen before its movement is felt.
However, the horned snake is not found in these regions.
The serpent represents prudence, as the Wisdom of the eternal Father in the Gospel tells us:
Be wise as serpents and innocent as doves.
Matthew 10:16.
In the horns of the horned snake, we understand power.
The spiritual person must imitate the serpent on the road, meaning that all actions in the active life, which is symbolized by the road, should be done not with sudden or hasty actions, but with pleasant, prudent, and careful thought.
Let them also be a horned snake on the path, meaning powerful and wise in the contemplative life.
Be wise in prayer and strong in contemplation.
A wise person is someone who, during prayer, can effectively drive away distracting thoughts with a heartfelt desire, and has learned what and how to pray.
Through such wise prayer, one is elevated to a powerful state of contemplation, where they become so focused that, by ignoring fleeting things, they are inspired to seek and desire only what truly lasts.
This allows them to achieve the following:
Biting the horse's hooves so that its rider falls backward.
Our flesh, on which our spirit resides, can be likened to the horse; the hoof, which represents lifeless flesh, symbolizes any dead actions found in the flesh.
To bite the horse's hoof means to strive to overcome and shed anything mortal within oneself with the strong discipline of penance, so that the ancient enemy, seen as the rider, falls backward and cannot find a place to sit.
It's important to note why it says "so that it falls backward." What is behind someone cannot be seen by them. One makes the rider fall backward by understanding that the devil, who incites all evils, is ready to take control through tempting sins. By not yielding to these impulses and biting the horse's hoof as described, they defeat him before sins become evident, before they are known by God or others, before the heart's secrets are revealed to God, or before any disgraceful actions reach others.
Finally, having defeated the enemy in this way, they can confidently declare to the Lord:
I will wait for your salvation, Lord.
It's as if to say: Compared to your eternal vision, I seem far from all the joys of this world.
Because I'm focused solely on you, who are all I need, I long with my heart and soul, yearning and waiting for your salvation.
Not just, Lord, for the salvation you reserve as a reward for your chosen ones in eternal life, but also for the salvation you prepare daily in this life for those who love you, through the grace of your inspiring presence and the blessings of your sweetness.
Chapter Eight: On the Blessing of Gad
As a person strives to elevate themselves by contemplating heavenly matters, they become more subtly targeted by the enemy's temptations.
The patriarch, filled with the Holy Spirit, aptly added, saying:
"Gad, equipped, will fight before him, and he will be equipped in return" from the Book of Genesis, Chapter Forty-Nine.
The name Gad, meaning "temptation" or "raider," suitably represents the hidden and secret temptations through which the evil enemy tries to overthrow even the most perfect individuals.
A hidden temptation is one that occurs inwardly, so subtly that even the person experiencing it cannot discern or recognize it.
As it quietly and secretly infiltrates the human heart, it can suddenly shake and confuse even the mind that seemed steadfast.
It can be so overwhelming that, as if enveloped in a cloud of anxiety, the person doesn't know what they're experiencing, mistaking good for evil and evil for good, and finding everything that once seemed sweet and desirable to be sad and bitter.
Against this kind of harmful temptation, which primarily attacks the spiritual, a person should strengthen themselves with mental fortitude, always returning to the comfort of internal reflection.
They should diligently guard themselves with the shield of constant prayer, allowing nothing to enter their mind that might divert their focus from the love of internal light.
In this way, when they are prepared for the battle of the Lord, it can be said of them:
"Gad, equipped, will fight before him," because the highest examiner of hearts sees and approves their struggle and conflict, and not only allows them to triumph with Him, but also mercifully rewards them both now and in the future.
This is mystically shown in the following words:
"And he will be equipped in return."
What does it mean to be equipped in return?
What can we gather from these words?
Essentially, they convey that God Almighty mercifully strengthens and protects those who earnestly guard their hearts from harmful thoughts and actions, both internally and externally.
As a person becomes more detached from earthly concerns through a love for heavenly aspirations, they become more worthy of experiencing the rich sweetness of heavenly joy.
This aligns with what the blessing or prophecy seems to suggest in a mystical way.
Chapter Nine: On the Blessing of Asher and Naphtali
"Asher," he says, "his bread will be rich, and he will provide delights to kings" (Genesis 49).
Asher means "blessed," and this name is fitting for someone who, by judging himself as strictly as Dan and resisting temptations as strongly as Gad, deserves to be called blessed.
His blessedness becomes clearer when it is said, "his bread will be rich."
Bread can be understood as heavenly nourishment, which deeply touches the heart; the richness of the bread implies an abundance of compunction, arising from heavenly sweetness.
The prophet David longed to be satisfied with this richness when he said: "My soul will be satisfied as with fat and richness, and my mouth will praise with joyful lips" (Psalms 63:5).
Therefore, it is rightly said that his bread is rich, for he is often nourished by this heavenly sweetness within himself, and if necessary, he can also sweetly and effectively nourish others.
This is why it is suitably added: "And he will provide delights for kings."
In the Holy Scriptures, kings are those who, holding the scepter of justice in their hearts, correct everything within themselves and know how to govern their habits, words, actions, and thoughts according to God's will.
For such kings, the administration of heavenly doctrine is like a sweet and abundant preparation of delights.
However, those who are not kings, who lack this power of governance, regard the word of God not as delights or sweetness, but as bitterness.
It is rightly said, "Asher, his bread will be rich, and he will provide delights to kings," because filled with the richness of internal sweetness, he is well-suited to praise with joyful lips and to proclaim heavenly instruction to kings, those who rule themselves.
After receiving such a great grace of divine favor, Nephthalim, meaning "expansion," emerges. Though limited in worldly matters, he grows deeper in heart and soul towards the one he envisions with his mind.
Consequently, Nephthalim is like a deer set free, expressing words of beauty. He becomes like a deer when he begins the leaps of prayer and contemplation, which are both lovely and desirable.
For without the leap of prayer first, the leap of contemplation becomes quite weak. Therefore, once he transitions from the leap of pure prayer to the most powerful leap-namely, the leap of contemplation-he is not only rightly called a deer but also, with a sweet addition, a deer set free. This is because he cannot be restrained by flesh, the world, or even the devil himself. Instead, he is continually sent forth, rising above all earthly things, towards the one he worships and loves above all, whom he alone hungers and thirsts for.
If ever he is called back for the benefit of others, he can offer words of beauty, bringing forth teachings that beautify the human heart. Thus, he ultimately becomes like Joseph, meaning "increaser," and can rightly be considered as such.
In this way, a truly spiritual person mystically embodies the names of five brothers within himself: when Dan judges his people wisely; Gad arms himself strongly against hidden temptations; Asher, meaning blessed, in his life; Nephthalim expanded in the love of God; Joseph increased in the love or edification of others, advancing to the point where he is called the true son of the true Jacob and, according to the rightful meaning of the text, deserves to be blessed by his father's blessing.
Chapter Ten: On the Blessing of Joseph and its Allegorical Significance
Joseph is a growing son, a growing and attractive son.
These words can be especially and most worthily referred to the special and only-begotten Son of the eternal Father, who is rightly called Joseph, because He is our Creator and Recreator.
He is the author and increaser of our entire salvation, who, being both God and man, was rightfully called a growing son by prophetic foresight by the blessed patriarch.
He is indeed the growing Son of God the Father in heaven according to divinity; He is also the growing son of the Virgin mother on earth according to humanity.
However, how God the Father, always and without beginning unbegotten, can have God the Son always and without beginning begotten from the same Father grow, is not something anyone should or can discuss.
For He, from whom He was begotten, stands equal in all things, co-omnipotent and co-eternal.
But He, who according to the nature of divinity could neither become greater nor lesser, deemed it worthy to grow for humanity by assuming the form of humanity.
However, that growth was so pure, so clean, and so holy, that it could never be stained by any blemish.
Hence, it is appropriately added, and attractive in appearance.
For in the very weakness of humanity He assumed, He remained entirely chaste, entirely clean, entirely whole, and therefore always lovable, delightful, and desirable to God the Father and the angelic host.
He is beautiful in form, whose appearance and beauty the distinguished prophet David, foreseeing in the Holy Spirit, extolled with due praises, saying:
"You are the most handsome of the sons of men" (Psalm Forty-five, verse two).
He was indeed handsome, because He alone was conceived and born without sin, alone lived without sin among sinners, and remained in the beauty of His own purity.
For He did not come to be contaminated by our sins, but to cleanse the contaminated, and to recall those wrapped in the shadow of eternal death to the light and glory of everlasting life.
Therefore, it is fittingly added soon after:
The daughters ran over the wall.
But they provoked and argued, and those with arrows envied Him.
The wall is understood as the divinity of Christ, who truly is the wall of His Church, protecting it with the shield of His mercy, as the prophet testifies, saying:
"Our strong city, Zion, the Savior has set a wall and a rampart in it" Isaiah 26:1.
By the daughters, a term indicating weakness, we rightly understand human infirmities, which He took upon Himself not out of necessity, but solely out of love.
The running of the daughters signifies human emotions, which made Him, who was stable, unchangeable, and impassible in His divinity, mutable and passible, moving from insult to insult, from place to place in the humanity He assumed for our sake.
In this kind of running, they provoked and argued, and those with arrows envied Him.
In those who, having arrows, provoked the Lord, we can understand the perverse hosts of evil spirits, which abound with the arrows of various temptations, attacking both the good and the bad, the just and unjust, at all times.
They did not withhold these arrows from Him, their Creator and Master of all; according to this prophecy, they first provoked Him, then argued against Him, and finally envied Him.
They provoked Him when, at the very beginning of His birth, they stirred up the fury of the wicked Herod against Him; because of Herod's cruelty, He, so young and tender, was warned by an angel to flee into Egypt, where He stayed hidden until Herod's death.
But whom they could not extinguish in infancy with these and other such provocations, they later dared to challenge with arguments, saying:
"If you are the Son of God, command these stones to become loaves of bread" (Matthew 4:3); and again: "If you are the Son of God, throw yourself down" and again: "All these I will give you, if you fall down and worship me" (Matthew 4:9).
But when they still couldn't succeed and realized that the venom of their malice ultimately turned against them, they became even more wicked and envied him until they executed him by crucifixion.
However, in another sense, we interpret the darts as representing the Jews, who had the Law and the Prophets, which they should have used to fend off and defeat the ancient enemy, like powerful arrows.
They did not accept the Lord who came in the flesh for their salvation.
With their disbelief and corrupt lives, they provoked him; then they argued against him to deepen their wickedness, blaspheming his name, and maliciously opposing all his words and deeds.
In the end, they envied him.
It was difficult for them to witness his presence, and they didn't relent in their envy and hatred until they condemned him to the humiliating death of being hung between two thieves.
Yet, in what seemed like defeat, he was victorious, because through the glorious triumph of his death, he nullified the power of death.
Hence it follows: His bow remained steady, and his hands and arms were released by the hands of the mighty Jacob.
The bow, made of wood and string, or horn and string, nobly represents our Lord and Redeemer.
The string can be seen as his most holy flesh, remarkably stretched and drawn by various trials and tribulations.
The wood or horn symbolizes his almighty divinity, which remained steadfast and unyielding to human suffering until this noble string, namely the most sacred flesh of Christ, began to be tormented by insults and stretched by the afflictions of the cross for our salvation.
The string, drawn by the suffering of humanity, soon led to divine compassion because the harsher the only begotten Son of God suffered in the flesh, the more graciously God the Father inclined toward the reconciliation of the human race.
Here is the bow that the Father promised long ago in 754, saying,
"I will set my bow in the clouds of the sky" (Genesis nine thirteen).
This bow was strong, drawn with great power and weight.
After fulfilling all that he came to do,
he was finally lifted up on the cross, given gall and vinegar to drink, and declared,
"It is finished" (John nineteen thirty).
Then, in a miraculous way, he released his noble and chosen arrow, his most holy soul, with such might
and strength that it powerfully reached the depths of hell, disrupting the dominion of death and binding
the strong ruler of death.
Without delay, the chains on his arms and hands were loosed by the powerful hand of Jacob.
In his arms and hands, the patriarchs, prophets, and other chosen ones were represented, who, bound by original sin,
were held captive in darkness and the shadow of death for many thousands of years.
Their chains were finally loosed
by the powerful hand of Jacob when, suddenly illuminated by the splendor of his divinity, they were recalled to their
former freedom, with the handwriting of their sins erased.
Then it was fulfilled what the patriarchs had long foreshadowed with the words:
"From there, he said, the shepherd, the stone of Israel, came forth."
By Israel, which means a man seeing God,
we understand the holy and chosen angelic spirits, who have seen the desirable face of their Creator without interruption
since the day of their creation. No inconsistency or change has ever separated them from gazing upon the brightness of
his divinity.
Their stone has been and is the same omnipotent God, who supports them so they do not fall, and with his strength and power,
he establishes and strengthens them so they cannot fall further.
So, the one who serves as the cornerstone for the angels in heaven emerged from the depths of hell.
He is the Shepherd of humanity and the Redeemer who, after discovering people lost in the winding paths of the infernal city and struggling with the long wait for his arrival, while trapped in the jaws of the wolf-the ancient enemy-triumphed and mercifully guided them back to the serene pastures of heavenly life.
This fulfilled the prophecy given to the patriarch, which said: "The God of your father will be your helper, and the Almighty will bless you with blessings from the heavens above, blessings of the depths below, blessings of the breasts and womb."
The God of the Father of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ is the divinity of Almighty God, who consistently supported him and carried out all his deeds in and with him. Just as he was always truly human after taking on humanity, he never ceased to be truly God.
And the Almighty, that is, the Holy Spirit, blessed him by filling the hearts of his disciples with an extraordinary and indescribable gift, making them strong, fearless, and unwavering in glorifying, blessing, and magnifying his name.
Therefore, God the Father and God the Holy Spirit blessed God the Son with blessings from the heavens above and blessings of the depths below, because, as the Apostle says, "It pleased God for all fullness to dwell in him, and through him to reconcile all things to himself, making peace through the blood of his cross, whether things on earth or things in heaven" (Colossians 1:19-20).
He made peace with things in heaven and on earth because he began to restore and renew the number of holy angels, which had decreased, with those he redeemed, at the glorious price of his blood.
And so, with the wall of enmity that existed not only between God and humans but also between angels and humans being broken down in his flesh, humanity rejoices in being restored to a joyful communion, destined to join the happy company of angels.
The Almighty also blessed him with gifts from above, as the heavenly choirs of angels, dressed in new praise, sang joyfully:
"Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace to people of good will" (Luke 2:14).
He blessed him with the depths below, when after his glorious triumph over death, he descended to the underworld.
The holy people, who were captive in death, joyfully exclaimed:
"You have come, O desired one, whom we awaited in darkness, to lead forth those bound in chains on this night. Our sighs called for you; our abundant lamentations sought you. You have become hope for the desperate, a great comfort in torments."
He blessed him with the blessings of the Church, as the first Church, starting with the apostles, was filled with the heavenly milk of faith and divinely arranged teaching. It began to overflow with a new abundance of heavenly gifts with the miraculous coming of the Holy Spirit.
He blessed him with the blessings of the nations, as those who had not yet embraced his faith were gathered into the holy mother Church. Gradually nurtured by spiritual grace, they were deemed worthy to conceive and bring forth our Lord and Redeemer in their hearts through faith.
These blessings of the growing Son, the Son of Almighty God, did not end with his death, resurrection, and ascension. They continue now and will remain until the end of the world, as symbolized by these words:
"The blessings of your father are strengthened by the blessings of his fathers, until the desire of the everlasting hills comes."
The Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, as we mentioned earlier, is God Almighty. The fathers of this Father were not only the patriarchs and prophets, from whose seed he was born according to the flesh, but also his most holy apostles and other just and elect people, who, through their preaching, brought him to life in the hearts of believers.
The blessings from your father are enhanced by the blessings from his ancestors.
It's like saying: The blessings you received from God the Father, which you gained through the grace of baptism and the forgiveness of sins to counteract the curse of the first man by being born, dying, and rising again, are reinforced by the blessings of his forefathers.
Not just the apostles and other holy teachers who have passed away, but also those who, by teaching and baptizing daily in the holy Church, are continually strengthened.
These blessings are renewed every day until the longing for the eternal hills, referring to the seven hundred fifty-seven angels dwelling in the heights of eternity, is fulfilled.
They yearn for the unfolding of this present age so that the choir of chosen people may be completed in number.
At the conclusion of his blessings, the faithful patriarch advises and encourages us to have the same hope and desire.
He says, "Let them be upon the head of Joseph, and upon the crown of the Nazarite among his brothers." This implies: Let these blessings flourish in the minds of leaders, let them prosper in the intentions of the followers, ensuring that in all their actions and desires, they possess such pure minds and holy intentions that they may one day be counted among their brothers, namely the holy angels.
Having conveyed these ideas allegorically according to our capacity, let's turn our focus to the mystical sense of morality and explore more deeply how these words spiritually apply to any perfect leader.
Chapter Eleven: On the Same Blessing of Joseph and Its Moral Significance
Joseph, as we started to discuss, symbolizes the ideal form of every chosen and perfect leader.
Through daily growth in good deeds, he advances consistently in spiritual virtues.
When he grows in this way before his true Father, Jacob, he earns the affectionate title of son not just once, but twice: Joseph is a fruitful son, a fruitful son, as it says in Genesis Chapter Forty-Nine.
This repetition signifies the dual love of God and neighbor.
When a leader fully embraces these, he is rightly called a fruitful son, a fruitful son.
For he is a son of the one he emulates, honors, and aspires to resemble; a fruitful son in the love of God and in uplifting his neighbor.
As he grows inwardly in true and perfect love for his heavenly Father, he strengthens inwardly to uplift his neighbors with God's help.
He is also described as fair in appearance when he strives to remain inwardly free from sin and outwardly refrains from sinful acts, as much as humanly possible, appearing pleasing and lovely in divine sight.
In all he does, he aims either for divine honor or the edification of his neighbors.
Undoubtedly, this desired blessing applies to him: Daughters, he says, ran over the wall.
As mentioned earlier, daughter is a term for weakness.
We can interpret the weak souls of converts as daughters, who begin to run over the wall when they earnestly place the living stone, Christ the cornerstone, which Jacob placed under his head, as the main foundation of their heart.
They align their will with Him and desire to live in a way that pleases Him above all.
It's important to note that it says they ran.
Whoever runs does not stand still or delay but hurries to reach their destination.
So, when daughters run along the wall, it symbolizes the steadfast and strong zeal of the novices.
They are described as running along the wall when they strive to move toward God and in God with energetic zeal-neither sluggish nor lukewarm, but with fervent intensity.
The prophet David foresaw this path for the children of God with the Holy Spirit when he said: "They will go from strength to strength; the God of gods will be seen in Zion" (Psalm 84:7).
But, as long as we are in this life, we must endure hardships and face temptations.
Consequently, it is added: "But they provoked and quarreled and envied those with arrows."
By those with arrows, as mentioned earlier, we understand the hosts of evil spirits, armed with the arrows of temptations. They advance against Joseph and his children, sometimes wounding and overthrowing unwary souls from their state of righteousness, sometimes completely defeating the wounded.
But what does it mean, they provoked, quarreled, envied? These three words highlight three stages of temptation that follow one another. The first is the time of conversion, the second is progress, and the third is perfection or the completion of life. They provoke those beginning, quarrel against those progressing, and attack those reaching completion with the arrows of envy.
At the start, they provoke a person by inflicting a certain anxious bitterness of heart. While the person understands less, whatever is heard or seen externally can more easily hinder or distract the mind from the desire for the heavenly homeland.
But for someone who has broken the shackles of this diabolic bitterness and resolved to walk steadily on the narrow path of spiritual conversion with the hope of a better life, they quarrel against him. They try to hinder him with worldly distractions, his own flesh, and sometimes with prosperity or adversity.
Finally, after overcoming provocations and quarrels, envy follows. Even if they cannot harm those who have reached the peak of perfection, they always wish to do so.
As we mentioned, they become agitated at the start, argue throughout the process, and feel envious at the end of life.
Even at the very last hour, when their final fate arrives, they cannot escape their envy.
For those they truly cannot harm, they boldly aim the arrows of their deceit.
However, those who do not give in to those who aggravate, argue, and envy in the present won't be frightened by their envious false accusations in the end, because, as it is said: "His bow remained steady."
This bow, made of wood and string, aptly symbolizes a person made up of soul and body.
Indeed, the bow, representing the person, dries out its string, which is the flesh, from the humors of vice by frequently twisting and distressing it through vigilance, fasting, and other pious labors, and is stretched firmly here.
After the end of this life, they will sit in strength because they will eternally rest in Christ and with Christ, who is understood as the strong one.
In that perpetual rest, what is figuratively expressed by the order of the following letter will be perfectly fulfilled.
"The shackles of his arms and hands were loosened by the hands of the mighty Jacob," it says.
We understand the same Lord and Redeemer, whom we previously understood as the strong one, also here as Jacob.
Therefore, everyone who will obtain a seat of eternal rest in this strong one, by his hand, meaning his omnipotent operation, and through his wonderful and magnificent compassion, deserves to be mercifully freed from all the shackles of their arms and hands, from all sins contracted from within or without.
But in another way, considering the state of present life through the bow, God Almighty, and in the strong one, in whom the same noble bow deigns to sit, a truly humble person is understood.
For no one is truly strong who is not truly humble, because the one who is truly humble can stand firmly in all things and through all things.
He sits in strength, the bow, because the Lord delights in dwelling and resting in a truly humble heart through the invisible grace of His visitation.
Blessed and truly blessed is the strong and humble one upon whom that bow, which is Christ, rests.
Through His presence and abiding, even in this life, one earns the forgiveness of their sins.
Therefore, it is consequently added: "And the bonds of his arms and hands are undone by the hands of the Mighty One of Jacob."
Through the arms, which are closely connected to the body, the inner senses of a person are rightly expressed; in the hands, the operation of the outer senses is understood.
The bonds of the arms and hands represent the temptations of the devil and carnal desires.
One is said to be bound by arms and hands if, through the devil's suggestion, they are ensnared inwardly by tempting desires and outwardly by tempting actions.
But if they are truly strong, meaning if they persist in humility and present themselves as pleasing to God, who sits with them, the bonds of their arms and hands are loosened.
Because the inner chains of carnal desires are broken by His help, so that even if attacked by the devil's suggestions, they cannot be led to consent or action of sin.
But how is this done, except by the hands of the Mighty One of Jacob?
By the hands of the Mighty One of Jacob, both the operation of divine mercy, as mentioned before, and the virtuous exercise of the person in good deeds can be understood.
It is fitting for the mighty man, Jacob, to be named "supplanter," as he consistently works virtuous deeds with strength and fortitude, by which vices are overthrown and destroyed.
The following words mystically testify to the grace of the heavenly blessing that continually follows such a person: "From there," it says, "the shepherd, the stone of Israel came forth."
What does "from there" mean?
It means from that person who was previously the daughter running along the wall; who, despite being provoked, argued with, and envied by evil spirits, did not yield and, by overcoming the vices, finally earned to be called Jacob.
From that man, a shepherd often emerges who strives every day to live up to the name and duty of a shepherd.
Truly, he can be called a shepherd when he loves to nourish himself through constant reading and the sweetness of prayer.
Nourished by this pasture, he grows nobly in virtues and virtuous deeds because any good seed that sprouts in a person's heart quickly withers if not watered with the moisture of prayer and reading.
The Lord says in the Gospel:
"Some fell on rock, and when it came up, it withered because it had no moisture."
Luke 8:6.
Therefore, whoever willingly and frequently dwells in these pastures, if it's God's will that he becomes a shepherd for others, will be able to provide his sheep with the nourishing and beneficial teachings of heaven. Even if he goes out to care for others, he remains the rock of Israel within himself.
Israel means "a man seeing God."
He is like the rock of Israel when he carries out his pastoral duties while always striving to return to the intimate grace of contemplative sweetness. As he frequently turns his heart and mind to God, he deserves to be established by the Lord with the mercy and blessing that the following words spiritually present.
It follows:
"The God of your father will be your helper, and the Almighty will bless you with blessings of the heavens above, blessings of the deep lying below, blessings of the breasts and womb."
And it is said: The Almighty God, whose son you have become, whose faithful servant you have shown yourself to be in all things, will be your helper, because wherever you go, whatever you begin, He will always be glad to assist you with a father's help.
When you lead the sheep entrusted to you to the pleasant and green pastures of spiritual teaching, He will accompany and help you, preparing the hearts of your subjects to receive the seeds of eternal salvation from your mouth through the grace of His preceding visitation.
Indeed, this blessing is truly magnificent.
When God Almighty touches the hearts of those who hear His voice, the gatekeeper certainly opens the way for them.
The Holy Spirit, with His unseen blessing, prepares the hearts of the disciples to warmly receive the word of the eternal Father.
It is said: He will bless you with the blessings of the heavens above, with the blessings of the depths below, with the blessings of the breasts and the womb.
In the blessings of the heavens above, we recognize the abundance of heavenly sweetness, and in the blessings of the depths below, the bitterness of eternal damnation.
When God's mercy opens the hearts of listeners, the Almighty also blesses the teacher.
Filled with His grace and inspiration, the teacher speaks life-giving words effectively.
Whether he begins his blessing by soothing the souls of the righteous with the joy and glory of eternal happiness and blessed immortality, or by urging sinners towards repentance with the fear of the infernal abyss, it brings forth a sweet and delightful fruit of eternal salvation in the hearts of his followers.
He is also blessed with the blessings of the breasts when those who strive to live by heavenly teachings, conceived in their hearts, eagerly reach for the heavenly homeland through his preaching and teaching.
Moreover, he is blessed with the blessings of the womb when those who have not yet prepared themselves through love eagerly open their hearts to the noble seed of God's word.
Therefore, it is always important and fervently prayed for any leader honored with such divine blessings that these blessings do not diminish in themselves or among their followers, but rather grow and strengthen each day.
The blessing we're about to discuss is often mentioned by the patriarch, especially when it's stated:
"The blessings of your father have surpassed the blessings of his ancestors, until the desire of the everlasting hills comes."
God is the father of every good leader, and as mentioned earlier, the ancestors of this father are understood to be the patriarchs, prophets, and holy apostles.
The everlasting hills aptly symbolize the holy souls of the chosen ones, who, having shed the burdens of earthly concerns, are elevated by holy prayers and just meditations, drawn from the valley of this mortal life to the heights of eternal eternity.
In the longing for these hills, He whom the angels yearn to see is rightfully signified, because He alone is sought and desired above all by them.
This same blessing, though subtly, also suggests what every faithful congregation should humbly wish for their beloved teacher from the Lord.
Therefore, let it be expressed in prayer and desire what the blessed patriarch affirmed:
"May the blessings of your father be strengthened by the blessings of his ancestors, until the desire of the eternal hills comes."
This means: May the blessings you have received from your heavenly Father as a beloved son be strengthened by the deeds, words, prayers, and merits of his ancestors-the patriarchs, prophets, apostles, and all the chosen who now reign with Christ-so that your blessing, which is your teaching and preaching, may never cease until the blessed Son of the eternal Father comes, desired and longed for by those eternal hills, namely, the souls seeking only the glory of eternity, through the visiting and comforting sweetness of His blessing.
Let these blessings be upon the head of Joseph and on the crown of the Nazir among his brothers. On the head of Joseph lies the will of the teacher, and on the crown, the intention of that will.
Therefore, we should hope and pray that one always maintains a good will to uplift their neighbor and carefully protects the intention of their will from seeking human approval.
For if someone aims to please only the eyes of God with their blessings, they could rightly be called a Nazirite, meaning pure among their brothers.
But since it is only through the mercy and compassion of God alone that one can humbly and effectively proclaim the word of God, the faithful congregation should humbly send forth these words of supplication to God, who gives generously to all and does not find fault:
"May the God of your father be your helper, and may the Almighty bless you with the blessings of the heavens above, the blessings of the deep lying below.
So that those who are more perfect may burn with a greater desire for heavenly sweetness as you teach, and that the slower ones, awakened by the terrors of the infernal abyss, may be encouraged to spiritual steadfastness.
May he bless you with the blessings of the breasts and of the womb, so that those who wish to receive the milk of heavenly doctrine within the breasts of their heart may find in your words what they need to be refreshed and filled.
And those who have not yet been worthy to receive the word of God through love may finally begin to conceive it sweetly in the womb of their heart.
May the blessings of your father be strengthened by the blessings of his fathers, the patriarchs, prophets, apostles, and all the righteous, until the desire of the eternal hills comes.
Until those holy souls striving towards the heights of eternity receive him in blessings and with your blessings, whom they thirstily desire above all others and above all things."
May blessings rest on the head of Joseph and on the crown of the Nazirite among his brothers.
Merciful Lord, may it be with the abundant gift of your mercy that whenever he sits among his brothers to speak your word, the will and intention of his heart are such that in his teaching, he seeks, thinks, or desires nothing except that you alone are honored and glorified in him and in the people under his care.
Whose honor and glory last forever and ever.
Amen.