Saint Eugenius was the Bishop of Carthage.
Eugenius, originally from Africa, became the bishop of Carthage in 480, appointed by the Catholics after Huneric, the king of the Vandals, was persuaded by the prayers of Emperor Zeno and Placidia to allow the selection of a bishop.
This came after the bishop's seat had been vacant for 24 years due to the harshness of the Arians.
In 484, Huneric assembled a group of Arian bishops in Carthage for a debate with the Catholics.
Eugenius presented a clear statement of faith to the king, supported by such strong reasoning that it left the heretics both silent and enraged.
Soon after, Huneric exiled him to Tamallula, a city on the border of Tripolitania, where he was subjected to torture by Anthony, a harsh heretic and the local bishop.
Later, as noted by Gregory of Tours in "History of the Franks," Book 2, Chapter 3, Eugenius was taken to the city of Albi in Gaul, where he is believed to have died around 495 or shortly thereafter.
Gennadius, writing about him as if he were still alive, mentions him in the "Catalogue of Writers," Chapter 97, which he compiled that year.
There is a booklet or an extended Confession of Faith presented to King Huneric by the African bishops, included by Victor of Vita in the third book of his work "On the Vandal Persecution," on page 33.
While Victor does not explicitly attribute it to Eugenius, Gennadius firmly places it in the cited location.
It can be found in the Councils, volume 4, page 1128, and in the Library of the Fathers, volume 8, page 683.
According to the same Gennadius, Eugenius also wrote letters to the people under his care shortly before his exile, which have since been lost; he engaged in discussions with the Arian leaders via messengers, addressed to King Huneric; and finally, he offered prayers for the peace of the Catholics, presented as apologies.
This is the Profession of Faith of the Catholic Bishops of Africa, compiled by Eugene of Carthage.
Here's an excerpt from Gregory of Tours about Saint Eugenius of Carthage and other confessors who suffered under King Huneric.
The Vandals, led by King Gunderic, left their homeland and invaded Gaul.
After causing significant destruction, they moved into Spain.
Following them, the Suevi, also known as the Alemanni, occupied Galicia.
It wasn't long before a conflict broke out between these neighboring peoples.
Subsequently, as the Alemanni advanced to Traducta, the Vandals crossed the sea and spread throughout Africa and Mauretania.
During this period, persecution against Christians intensified.
It's worth mentioning some of the things they did to the churches of God and how they were eventually expelled from their kingdom.
After Trasimundus died, having committed crimes against God's saints, Honoricus, who was even more cruel, took over the African kingdom, chosen by the Vandals themselves.
Under his rule, the number of Christians killed for the sacred name of Christ is beyond human comprehension.
Yet, Africa bears witness to this and Christ’s right hand, which crowned them with unfading gems.
We have read about the sufferings of some of these martyrs, a few of which should be recounted to fulfill our promises.
Therefore, Cirola, falsely called a bishop, was seen as the greatest supporter of heretics.
When the king initiated persecution against Christians in various places, he found Saint Eugenius, a bishop of indescribable holiness and renowned wisdom, in the suburbs of his city.
The persecutor seized him so violently that he had no chance to encourage the flock of Christ.
As he was being taken away, he sent a letter to his fellow citizens, urging them to keep the Catholic faith, which read:
LETTER OF SAINT EUGENIUS OF CARTHAGE TO HIS PEOPLE, FOR THE PRESERVATION OF THE CATHOLIC FAITH.
To my dearest and sweetest children in the love of Christ, the sons and daughters of the Church entrusted to me by God, from Eugenius, bishop.
A royal command has been issued, and by decree, we have been called to Carthage to practice the Catholic faith.
Therefore, so I wouldn't leave the Church of God in uncertainty or the flock of Christ without a true shepherd, I felt it necessary to send this letter to you in my stead.
In this letter, I ask, urge, advise, and earnestly beseech you with tears, by the majesty of God and the dreadful day of judgment, and by the terrifying glory of Christ's coming, to hold firmly to the Catholic faith.
Assert that the Son is equal to the Father, and that the Holy Spirit shares the same divinity with the Father and the Son.
Therefore, preserve the grace of the one baptism, safeguarding the anointing of Chrism.
No one should return to the water after being reborn from water.
By God's will, salt is made in water, but if it is returned to water, all its essence is immediately nullified.
Hence, it is not without reason that the Lord says in the Gospel: "If the salt has lost its flavor, how shall it be seasoned?"
And certainly, this is to lose flavor, wanting to be seasoned again after having been made sufficient once.
Did you not hear Christ saying: "He who has bathed once does not need to wash again" (John thirteen)?
Therefore, brothers, and my sons and daughters in the Lord, do not be saddened by my absence: because if you adhere to Catholic discipline, neither distance will make me forget you, nor will death separate me from you.
Know that whatever causes my separation from you, the victory is with me.
If I go into exile, I have the example of the blessed John the Evangelist; if I face death, "For to me, to live is Christ, and to die is gain" (Philippians one, twenty-one).
If I return, brothers, God will fulfill your desire.
However, I believe it is enough that I have not kept silent with you.
I have warned and instructed you as best as I could, so I am free from the blood of those who perish.
I know these letters will be read against them before the judgment seat of Christ, when he comes to repay each one according to their deeds.
If I return, brothers, I will see you in this life; if not, I will see you in the future.
Nevertheless, I say to you, farewell, pray for us, and fast:
because fasting and almsgiving have always turned the Lord towards mercy.
Remember, it is written in the Gospel: Do not fear those who kill the body but cannot kill the soul;
rather, fear him who, after he has killed the body, has the power to destroy the soul and send it to hell.
Matthew
10:28.
The letter from Eugenius concludes, and Gregory returns to his main theme.
Thus, the holy Eugenius was brought before the king with the bishop of the Arians to argue for the Catholic faith.
When Eugenius powerfully defeated him regarding the mystery of the Holy Trinity, and Christ performed many miracles through him, that same bishop was consumed with greater madness by envy.
At that time, there were very wise and holy men with Saint Eugenius, Bishops Vindemialis and Longinus, who were equals in rank and not inferior in virtue.
Saint Vindemialis was said to have raised the dead, while Longinus healed many sick people.
Eugenius also cured not only physical blindness but also blindness of the mind.
Seeing this, the wicked bishop of the Arians called over a man who had been deceived by the same error in which he lived, and said, "I cannot endure that these bishops perform many signs among the people, and everyone follows them, neglecting me. Now agree to what I command, and after receiving fifty gold coins, sit in the street through which we pass, and placing your hand over your closed eyes, when I pass by with the others, shout loudly, saying: I implore you, most blessed Cirola, bishop of our religion, to reveal your glory and power, so that by opening my eyes, I may deserve to see the light I lost."
Carrying out these orders and sitting in the street, as the heretic passed with the saints of God, this man who intended to mock God shouted loudly, saying, "Hear me, most blessed Cirola, hear me, holy priest of God: look upon my blindness. Let me experience the remedies which the other blind have received from you, which the lepers have experienced, and even the dead have sensed. I adjure you by the very power you have, to restore to me the light I desire, for I am struck with severe blindness."
Though he did not know the truth, he spoke the truth: for greed had blinded him, and he thought he could mock the power of Almighty God for money.
The bishop of the heretics stepped aside slightly, as if he was about to revel in his power, filled with vanity and pride.
He placed his hand over his eyes, saying:
"According to our faith, by which we rightly believe in God, may your eyes be opened."
But as soon as these wicked words were spoken, laughter turned to weeping, and the bishop's deceit was exposed for all to see.
A tremendous pain gripped the eyes of the poor man, so severe that he could barely press them with his fingers to keep them from bursting.
Eventually, the miserable man cried out, saying:
"Woe to me, miserable one! I have been deceived by the enemy of divine law.
Woe to me, for I tried to mock God for money and received fifty gold coins to commit this sin."
To the bishop, he said: "Here is your gold, give me back my sight, which I lost through your deceit.
I beg you, most glorious Christians, do not despise the wretched, but quickly help one who is perishing.
For indeed, I have realized that God is not mocked."
Galatians chapter six, verse seven.
Then, moved by the mercy of the holy ones of God, they said: "If you believe, all things are possible for the believer."
He cried out with a loud voice: "Whoever does not believe that Christ is the Son of God and that the Holy Spirit shares equal substance and divinity with God the Father, may today suffer what I endure."
And he added: "I believe in God the Father Almighty, I believe in the Son of God, Jesus Christ, equal to the Father, I believe in the Holy Spirit, consubstantial and coeternal with the Father and the Son."
Upon hearing this, and honoring each other mutually, a holy contention arose among them over who would make the sign of the blessed cross on his eyes.
Vindemialis and Longinus urged Eugenius, but he, in turn, asked them to lay hands on the blind man.
When they did this and held their hands over his head, Saint Eugenius made the sign of the cross over the blind man's eyes, saying:
"In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, the true God, whom we confess as three in one equality and omnipotence, may your eyes be opened."
Immediately, the pain vanished, and he returned to his former health.
It became evident through his blindness how the bishop of the heretics was blinding their hearts with his misleading assertions.
As a result, they couldn't see the true light with the eyes of faith.
Oh, miserable one!
He did not enter through the door, which is Christ, the true door, becoming more of a wolf to the flock than a protector.
Instead of igniting the peace of faith in believers' hearts, he tried to extinguish it with his corrupt intentions.
The holy people of God performed many signs among the people, and there was a unified voice declaring: True God the Father, true God the Son, true God the Holy Spirit, to be worshiped with one faith, feared with one fear, and venerated with the same honor.
It is clear to everyone that what Cirola claims is false.
When King Honoricus saw his claims completely exposed by the glorious faith of the holy ones, and the sect of error was not rising but being destroyed, and the fraud of his bishop was revealed, he ordered the holy people of God to be killed after enduring many tortures, the rack, flames, and claws.
He ordered the blessed Eugene to be beheaded, pretending that if he did not return to the heretical sect when the sword was over his neck, he would not be killed.
This was so Christians would not venerate him as a martyr, but instead, condemn him to exile, which is exactly what happened.
For when, at the brink of death, he was asked if he intended to die for the Catholic faith, he replied: For this is eternal life, to die for justice.
Then, with the sword poised, he was exiled to the city of Albi in Gaul, where he ended his life.
Many virtues and frequent miracles are now shown at his tomb.
He ordered the holy Vindemial to be struck down with a sword, which was fulfilled in this conflict.
Octavian the archdeacon and many thousands of men and women affirming this faith were killed and crippled.
But for the love of glory, these punishments meant nothing to the holy confessors, who, though troubled in peace, understood well that they were to face many trials, as noted by the Apostle in the Book of Romans.
"The sufferings of this present time are not worth comparing to the future glory that will be revealed in us."
Many strayed from their faith by pursuing riches, becoming entangled in numerous sorrows. An unfortunate bishop named Revocatus was drawn away from the Catholic faith during this period.
At that time, even the sun seemed dim and darkened, with only a third of it shining. I believe this was due to the many crimes and the shedding of innocent blood.
Honoricus, following such atrocities, was seized by a demon that had long fed on the blood of saints. He tore at himself with his own teeth, ending his unworthy life in a fitting death.
After him, Childericus came to power, and upon his death, Gelisimiris took over the kingdom. He too was defeated by the republic, ending both his life and rule, leading to the fall of the Vandal kingdom.
In this crypt, where the body of Saint Amarandus was kept, the martyr Eugenius, from the Honorifician persecution, is also honored as the greatest glory of the priestly island.
His exile in this city and the suffering he and his companions endured are recounted. Having great virtues in the world and having emerged victorious from martyrial torments, he knew the Lord would call him to glory. Particularly aware of what was hidden from others, he was to join the martyr Amarandus.
He went to Amarandus's tomb, prostrated on the ground, and prayed to the Lord for a long time. Then, with arms outstretched on the floor, he directed his spirit to heaven. His body was later gathered by Christians and buried in the crypt we mentioned.
During his festival, countless people gathered, and many transactions took place in the courtyard. A local girl approached a stall as if to buy something, and seeing an item she liked, received it from the vendor.
She immediately handed it to another person, denying she had ever received it. The vendor insisted earnestly, "I gave it to you with my own hand, and you accepted it to inspect."
When she denied it, the merchant said, "If you're so stubborn and driven by greed to deny it, let the blessed martyr Eugenius judge.
If you swear at his tomb that you didn't receive it, I'll consider my loss as nothing."
She, confident she could rid herself of this oath, quickly went to the tomb.
With her hands raised to swear, her body suddenly stiffened, her feet became fixed to the floor, and her voice stuck in her throat, leaving her with a wide-open mouth but no speech.
Seeing this, the merchant said to the crowd, "May this sign, which you have brought upon yourself, serve you well, virgin.
Let the vengeance given by Bishop Eugenius be enough for you."
With that, he left the place.
She remained in this torment for a long time until finally, at the martyr's command, she spoke and openly confessed what she had wished to keep hidden.
Oh unfortunate greed, what are you doing?
Why does a woman's mind, rather than a man's, succumb to seeking others' possessions?
Why does a small arrow of desire pierce the strong armor of the mind?
Why do you gather rusty gold talents, only to burn with them in hell?
What good are perishable gains to you, which result in the loss of eternal life, according to the Lord's word:
"What good is it for someone to gain the whole world, yet forfeit their soul?
Or what can anyone give in exchange for their soul?"