Commentary on the Revelation of Saint John
by Primasius of Hadrumetum
Book Three
And I saw seven angels standing before God, and they were given seven trumpets.
In the seven angels, we must recognize the Church according to the preceding rule, which is often commended for its universal sevenfold nature.
This is said to have received the strongest trumpet of proclamation, which, when prevailing, we trust the whole world will believe.
For we read in Isaiah 57: "Like a trumpet, lift up your voice."
Another angel came and stood over the altar of God, holding a golden censer, and many prayers were given to him so that he might offer the prayers of all the saints on the golden altar before the throne of God.
This type of narration should also be noted. Often, someone recounts something slightly different from what they intended to say, and after finishing the interposed obscure part, returns to the intended point. He proposed that seven angels received trumpets, and then another angel came. So, it is thought that this one came after the seven, although he saw it all at once. With the coming of the angel, those seven received trumpets. That is, with the coming of Christ the Lord, his Church received the power to preach.
We understand that he came upon the altar, that is, upon the Church, which is taken as the body of the same priest, to which Peter says in First Peter 2: "A holy nation, a chosen people, a royal priesthood."
Having a golden censer, that is, a body conceived immaculate by the Holy Spirit, which he offered as a sacrifice and offering to God for the redemption of the whole world in a pleasing aroma, and cleansed the conscience of all from dead works. It is also said that he received and offered from the prayers of the saints, because through him the prayers of all can sweetly reach God. Hence the Apostle in Hebrews 13 says: "Through him, we offer a sacrifice of praise to God always, that is, the fruit of lips confessing his name."
For this reason, he is said to intercede not only for our sins but also for the sins of the whole world, as blessed John also says: "And he himself intercedes for our sins." And the smoke of the prayers of the saints ascended from the hand of the angel before God. The angel took the censer, filled it with the fire of God's wrath, and cast it upon the earth.
Rightly does he speak of the censer being full of fire. For it is not measured, he says (John).
God gives the Spirit, which we know is fulfilled in the humanity of Christ, in whom all the fullness of divinity dwells bodily.
Colossians 2
Since He wishes His Church alone to share in this same Spirit, He demonstrated it here in a special way.
Hence, the Lord also says in the Gospel:
Luke 12
"I came to cast fire on the earth, and what do I desire but that it be kindled?"
I believe this fire is what is now signified.
We know that with this fire, sinners are rejected like fragile vessels crumbling in a furnace.
Through a single fire, the wicked do not share the same fate as the righteous, just as straw and gold do not meet the same end-one is consumed, the other is proven.
Likewise, under a single press, there is a clear distinction between oil and dregs.
This fire sent to the earth ignited the minds of preachers.
It is said to have burned a third of the earth, trees, grass, and greenery, as if saying:
"It rejected and destroyed part of the useless vessels, whether they were outside or within the Church."
For if anyone builds on the foundation with wood, grass, or straw, it will all perish in the fire.
First Corinthians 3
Another way: The angel took the censer, filled it with fire from the altar of God, and cast it to the earth.
The Lord took His body, that is, the Church, and by fulfilling the Father's will, filled it with fire from the altar, meaning the power to bind and loose, which lies in the sacrifices and propitiation of God.
Hence it is also said:
Psalm 104
"He makes His angels spirits, and His ministers a flaming fire."
In these, the Church has received all power in heaven and on earth, as it completes God's sacrifice, with the Lord offering Himself primarily, and the saints presenting their bodies as a living, holy offering.
Romans 12
And He sent it to the earth.
Through the Church's preaching, the world will become aware of the future wrath, as Zechariah says:
Zechariah 12
"I will make the leaders of Judah like a fiery torch."
What follows can be applied to both interpretations:
"There were peals of thunder, voices, flashes of lightning, and an earthquake."
All these things are spiritual and belong to the Church.
These are the voices of those rebuking in the fire, saying: "Brood of vipers" (Matthew 3), or "Repent, for the kingdom of heaven is near."
Thunder represents the preaching of the Christian faith; lightning symbolizes the power of healings; earthquakes signify the persecutions that were foretold to come and are endured at various times. He repeats what he proposed, as he is accustomed to dictating the same things in parts.
And he said, "And the seven angels who had the seven trumpets prepared to blow them." The Church, represented by the sevenfold number, prepares itself confidently to preach.
And the first angel blew his trumpet, and there was hail and fire mixed with blood, and it was thrown upon the earth. A third of the earth burned up, a third of the trees burned up, and all green grass burned up.
The earth symbolizes earthly people. The trees represent humans wavering in unbelief, moved by every wind of doctrine (Ephesians 4), about whom the apostle Jude says in chapter 1, "Autumn trees without fruit, uprooted, twice dead." The green grass symbolizes flesh indulging in luxuries, for all flesh is grass (Isaiah 40).
Although he placed three-quarters against one, representing the Church, he now constrains the opposing part to two-thirds: specifically, one-third mixed with good in the Church among false brothers, and the other in the error of paganism and the depravity of heresy, separated by open schism.
Thus, the Church (that is, one-third) fights against twin evils, like simplicity resisting duplicity.
Thus, a king with ten thousand is said to have advanced to fight against one who has twenty thousand in the Gospel (Luke 14).
Thus, God promises through Zechariah, saying (Zechariah...).
XIII: And it will be throughout the land, says the Lord, two parts in it will be dispersed and fail, and the third part will be left in it.
I will lead the third part through fire, refining them as silver is refined, and testing them as gold is tested.
They will call on my name, and I will hear them.
I will say, "You are my people," and they will say, "The Lord is my God."
The wicked, represented by two-thirds, is often depicted in Scripture as a single entity.
When the second angel sounded the trumpet, something like a great mountain burning with fire was cast into the sea.
A third of the sea became blood, a third of the fish died, and a third of the ships were destroyed.
The burning mountain in the sea symbolizes the devil, cast among the people.
The sea turning into blood signifies the wisdom of the flesh, which is hostile to God.
Through it, human souls are destroyed.
The Apostle says in Romans 8:6, "To be carnally minded is death," because flesh and blood will not inherit the kingdom of God.
The sea, trees, ships, and fish represent the world and its inhabitants.
When it says one third turned into blood, signifying souls consumed by death, it further divides into two-thirds, saying, "A third of the fish died, and a third of the ships were destroyed."
In one instance, it shows the type of death, and in another, it specifies the number.
Another interpretation, by saying "having souls," clearly shows them killed by spiritual death, as the Apostle says about the widow in First Timothy 5:6: "She who lives in pleasure is dead while she lives."
It sounds as if one third kills another third through harmful traditions and useless imitation of doctrine.
And the third angel blew his trumpet, and a great star fell from the sky, burning like a torch, onto a third of the rivers and springs of water.
The name of the star is Wormwood, or Absinthium, and a third of the waters became wormwood, and many people died from the bitterness of the waters.
The star falling from the sky symbolizes people falling from the Church, specifically those thought to shine with good merits.
They are compared to stars and torches, which the Apostle Jude rebukes, saying in Jude chapter 1, verse 13: "wandering stars."
For they deceive by the very appearance of brightness.
The Lord also compares them to whitewashed walls and tombs in Matthew chapter 23, verse 27.
And because the fall of prominent people usually troubles many, the star is said to have fallen on a part of the rivers and springs, whose name Wormwood signifies great bitterness.
When such people fall, many are weakened and corrupted by imitating their worst doctrines.
He rightly compared them to wormwood, for if even a small amount of its bitterness is mixed into a sweet drink, it all turns bitter.
Scripture also indicates this elsewhere, saying to such people in Jeremiah chapter 2, verse 21: "I planted you as a choice vine, how then have you turned into the bitterness of a foreign vine?"
This is mentioned as one-third of the evils, for others who should have become more cautious by their example, fall into the same error by imitation.
And the fourth angel blew his trumpet, and a third of the sun was struck, and a third of the moon, and a third of the stars, so that a third of their light was darkened, and a third of the day was without light, and the night likewise.
The sun, moon, and stars represent the Church.
Indeed, it is more fitting for the fourth angel, who wanted to mention the events of the fourth day of creation.
On that day, lights were created to rule over the day and night, dividing light from darkness.
When these evil ones, who are outwardly visible but hidden within, are separated from the Church, they cause the Church's dignity to shine less because of their transgressions.
It's as if taking away a third of the sun, a third of the moon, and a third of the stars, they act contrary to the Creator's design.
Just as the sun, moon, and stars were meant to visibly stand out in creation, the Church was commanded to rule with dignity and glory throughout the world, but these evil ones seek to obscure that.
The Apostle says in Romans chapter 2, that the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles because of you.
Through those by whom our good is blasphemed, the genuine light seems to be obscured.
However, to prevent the thought that this could be done at will and without measure, a limit is somewhat set, signifying a portion of the evil ones in a varied narration.
What was mentioned as a third part in the third angel is recalled here in a tripartite manner, saying a third of the sun, a third of the moon, and a third of the stars were diminished.
Thus, in these lights, two parts remain intact, and the loss or obscurity did not affect any of the elect.
For it is not lost, as it says in Job chapter 17, except the son of perdition.
And in Second Timothy chapter 2, The Lord knows those who are His.
Otherwise, the perfection of any kingdom consists of twelve ounces.
Therefore, he says a third of the sun, a third of the moon, and a third of the stars were darkened, equating to four ounces each, making up the body of all evils, designated variously by many.
But in the good, it is understood that eight ounces remain in each, three times eight, twenty-four, representing the perfection in both leaders and the people.
The third part of the name here signifies the bad parts, specifically two parts: one of the day and one of the night.
Jeremiah says: "I have made your mother like the night."
Thus, it was struck so that the third part of the day and the third part of the night, representing Christ and the devil, would become apparent.
However, he did not say, "It was struck and darkened their third part, and the third part of the day and night appeared," but rather "it was darkened and appeared," because it did not become apparent when it was struck, but it was struck for this purpose: to be given over to its own desires, so that, with sins overflowing, it would be revealed in its own time.
Power was in their tails to harm people for five months.
We recall it is written in Isaiah, Chapter 9: "The elder and honorable, he is the head; and the prophet teaching lies, he is the tail. And those who bless my people, they are deceivers; and those who are blessed, shall fall."
Hence, it is clear that they aim to dominate from that side which all the saints and true teachers strive greatly to guard against: worldly glory and the error of harmful preaching.
Therefore, in their tails, their power for five months again represents this life, where lies can prevail, either to capture the useless or to temporarily torment the spiritual; hence we read in Psalm 119: "I saw the foolish and was grieved, and I held back from sinners."
And they had over them a king, the angel of the abyss, whose name in Hebrew is Armageddon, in Greek Apollyon, and in Latin he has the name Exterminans.
God, supremely good, although hidden, yet with just judgments, allowed a fitting angel to rule over such people.
For whoever is defeated by him becomes his servant; hence the apostle says in Second Peter, Chapter 2, they are handed over in all deception of unrighteousness, because they did not accept the love of the truth to be saved.
And therefore God sends them into a work of error, as it says in Second Thessalonians, Chapter 2, so that they believe the lie, and all who did not believe the truth but consented to unrighteousness will be judged.
The quality of action and the express property of the name agree in him, that is, Exterminans.
One woe has passed, and behold, two more woes follow.
And the sixth angel blew his trumpet.
The first woe is past, and the trumpet of the sixth angel has sounded; this foretells the final proclamation of the sixth age.
And I heard a voice from the four horns of the altar of God, the altar which is before the eyes of God, saying to the sixth angel who had the trumpet:
"Release the four angels who are bound at the great river Euphrates."
Here it shows that the same winds, called angels, are meant; for it was said earlier that the winds were held by the angels, and now it is said that the angels are released by the angel, which is the Church, which retains the power to bind and release Matthew 16, 18; John 20.
Therefore, it is said, he has a trumpet, meaning the power of preaching.
Hence it is said: "Lift up your voice like a trumpet" Isaiah 58.
"Release the four angels who are bound at the river Euphrates," which he had said were at the four corners of the earth, to show that by the name Euphrates the power of the worldly kingdom and the multitude of persecutors are designated, in which the harmful will of the devil is said to be bound because it is not allowed to harm as much as it wants.
The Euphrates is a river of Babylon, which we know is often used in the Scriptures to represent evil.
Jeremiah also says Chapter 46: "That day is the day of the Lord God, a day of vengeance, to avenge His enemies, and the sword will devour them and be filled with their blood, for the Lord God of hosts has a sacrifice in the land of the north, by the river Euphrates."
Here, the sacrifice does not signify peace but slaughter: indeed, the final persecution is foretold to be more severe than the others because then, with the devil released along with his minions, he will be allowed to harm or torment more.
It follows: "And the four angels were released," indicating the beginning of persecution, "who had been prepared for the hour, the day, the month, and the year, to kill a third of humanity."
Here, the four times signify the duration of the persecution, meaning three years and six months.
He spoke about the hour, the day, the month, and the year because hours gradually make up days, days make up months, and months make up years.
Ready to speak, he described the nature of the devil and his angels, who bear relentless hostility against the Church of Christ.
They always wish to cause harm but are restrained by divine power so they cannot harm as much as they desire.
He rightly mentioned locusts, saying they are like horses prepared for battle.
When he speaks of the angels being released, he says he saw horses.
The number of the cavalry soldiers was 80,000; I heard their number: to kill a third of mankind.
This entire body of evil is hinted at in many ways.
Furthermore, 80,000, like the perfection of the number 60 from the number six, prefigures for us an example of good.
Hence, we read in Song of Solomon 6:8, "Sixty are the queens." Similarly, the number 80 sometimes signifies evil. It arises from the number four because of the four well-known qualities of the body: cold, hot, wet, and dry, or due to the four disturbances that often greatly distress life: fear, desire, pain, and joy. When doubled because of the two sexes, these make eight. This number, similarly rising by ten, makes 80, which in a way indicates the part of the evil cavalry soldiers against the body of Christ, which is the Church. Therefore, it follows: "And there are 80 concubines," as if joined not by legitimate marriage but rather fraudulently.
This specifically applies to all heretics because they handle the sacraments of faith, cloaked in the name of Christ, in such a way that, like concubines who do not always stay in the house, they wish to have temporary power or the applause of human praise from the name of Christ.
It is not difficult to distinguish between the merits of queens and concubines with right reason, since even the names themselves reveal the dignity of queens and the disgrace of concubines.
Another translation, which Tychonius explained, has, "And the number of the mounted troops was twice ten thousand times ten thousand."
Without going into too much detail, he only added that he did not specify how many tens of thousands.
However, it seems to us that even in this translation, he symbolized the entirety of the lost people.
Twice ten thousand makes twenty thousand.
This number is mentioned by the Lord in the Gospel regarding a king having twenty thousand, as if the duplicity of evil resists Christian simplicity.
According to this interpretation, where a double twenty opposes a simple ten, he added "tens of thousands"; by not specifying how many, he symbolized an innumerable multitude, as if gathered but not counted, similar to what the prophet in Psalm 40 says, "I proclaimed and spoke, they were multiplied beyond number."
The indiscriminate confusion of this multitude was also signified in the first fishing of the disciples in Luke 5 before the Lord's passion. During this event, the boats were weighed down and the nets were breaking, referring to heretics and false Christians, as the Church is often burdened by internal conflicts and the attacks of heretics. Just as the nets were torn, schisms were shown to have occurred.
In this fishing, the number is similarly unspecified, just like twice ten thousand times ten thousand, as if to say, "Called indeed, but not counted among the fullness of the elect."
For many are called, but few are chosen.
In another fishing in Matthew 20 and John 21 after the Lord's resurrection, the number is given and the greatness of the fish is proclaimed, and the net is said to be unbroken.
Therefore, just as twice ten thousand times ten thousand can be applied to heretics and false Christians, so too to the remaining evils mentioned before and now in the following order. From all these groups, the whole body of the devil is shown to consist, that is, of Jews, heretics, false Christians, and Gentiles.
After a little while, it finally follows, hinting at the error of their paganism:
"And the rest of the people who were not killed by these plagues did not repent of the works of their hands, nor did they stop worshiping demons and idols of gold, silver, bronze, stone, and wood, which cannot see or hear or walk."
This shows the full extent of the evil in their hearts.
And I saw horses in the vision, and those who sat on them had breastplates of fire, red, and sulfur, and their heads were like lions' heads.
The horses represent evil spirits, and the people riding them are the wicked.
Just as we previously mentioned in a good context, "You ride on your horses, your chariots bring salvation"
Habakkuk 3:8, here, in contrast, evil spirits are associated with their riders.
Much has already been said about the heads of lions; however, it should not be overlooked that although there is some similarity between locusts and horses, horses are not found among locusts, as well as lions. Both symbolize heretics through the persons shown.
The breadth of divine speech distinguishes the same thing in different ways.
In the description and qualities of the breastplates, the punishments of the wicked are indicated, as we read in the promise to those who worship the beast:
"The smoke of their torment will rise forever and ever"
(Revelation 14:11).
And because this translation added "red," it showed the merit of their torments, indicating sins by "red," an understanding that the Apostle expresses
(Hebrews 6), speaking of similar land,
because it produces thorns and thistles, it is cursed, whose end is to be burned.
Hence it is said in the original punishment of sin:
"It will produce thorns and thistles for you"
(Genesis 3:18).
And Solomon
(Proverbs 26:9):
"Like a thornbush in a drunkard's hand."
And from their mouths came fire, smoke, and sulfur.
This well signifies what is brought about by the one who causes it.
For they are led to possess and speak these things from their mouths, those who are deceived by their harmful preaching perish, to be tormented by fire, smoke, and sulfur, which came out of their mouths.
Therefore, it is said that they incur these plagues through the words of their leaders, that is, through the teachings of their chiefs.
For the power of the horses was in their mouths and in their tails, that is, in the role of speech.
He considers preachers who are reprobates as tails.
For their tails were like serpents, having heads of dragons, with which they caused harm.
Here, in the likeness of ancient transgression, he rightly recalls serpents, by whose hissing the woman was seduced and boldly acted against the command, and justly lost what she had received.
Just as these have the heads of dragons, that is, the leaders of the world; for dragons are earthly creatures, often living in waters, larger than almost all beasts.
Therefore, by the patronage of the leaders, they harm more by preaching harmful things than if they persuaded by speech alone.
Thus, he says, the heads of dragons by which they harm.
He now speaks about the peoples:
And the rest of the people who were not killed by these plagues did not repent of their evil deeds, nor did they stop worshipping demons and idols of gold, silver, bronze, stone, and wood, which cannot see, hear, or walk.
They did not repent of their murders or their sorceries.
He anticipated this, stating it beforehand, so that he might confine all those who will be on the left.
Here he mentions sorceries in a bad sense, for we often call sorcerers evil-doers.
Therefore, the text of the narrative must be considered, for after describing the final battle and the ways of the peoples, he omits the seventh angel, under whom the final persecution and the manifest coming of the Lord is expected.
He recalls the Church of the present time, suggesting in various ways that, by recapitulating what he had omitted, he seems to narrate two ends.
Therefore, let us remember that when he has brought the prayer to its end, the end must be joined to the concise order.
For he did something unusual, not concluding both narratives with one end.
He separated the preaching of future peace, how strong it will be, how clear it will be on land and sea.
Chapter Ten
And I saw, he said, another mighty angel coming down from heaven, wrapped in a cloud, with a rainbow over his head.
His face was like the sun, and his feet like pillars of fire.
The Lord Christ descended from heaven, wrapped in a cloud, that is, the Church, or clothed in the cloud of flesh, which is called the new bride elsewhere Revelation 21.
Or as Daniel says Daniel 7, the Son of Man came in the clouds of heaven.
The rainbow over his head signifies the promise of mercy enduring for the good, and also those who were honored with martyrdom before the Lord's coming, like Abel and others.
It is fitting that he says the rainbow is over his head, which another translation calls the iris Genesis 4, by which the Church is described as being wrapped around, like members beforehand, yet shown to be connected to the head.
And his face was like the sun, manifesting through the glory of the resurrection of the Lord Jesus Christ, of whom we read Psalm 19: He has set his tent in the sun, where it indeed shines.
For in the face, the manifestation of presence is designated, which longing for, he said Psalm 80: Show us your face, and we will be saved.
His feet, that is, the apostles, are ignited by the words of God and the Holy Spirit to preach.
Did not our heart, he said Luke 24, burn within us while he talked to us on the road and opened the Scriptures to us?
However, pillars are called the Church for their firmness; of these it is said through the prophet: I have made firm its pillars Psalm 75; and, How beautiful on the mountains are the feet of those who bring good news, who proclaim peace Isaiah 52!
and the Apostle, who seemed to be pillars of the Church Galatians 2.
And he had in his hand an open book, and he placed his right foot on the sea and his left foot on the land.
If previously in the sealed book of the Old Testament the deep secrets were known to be hidden, here more fittingly in the open book of the New Testament the revealed grace is believed to have shone clearly, so that the Apostle confidently said 2 Corinthians 3.
We, with unveiled faces, beholding the glory of the Lord, are being transformed into the same image from glory to glory, just as by the Spirit of the Lord.
Therefore, it is said that his face shone like the sun.
Furthermore, he is shown placing his right foot on the sea, symbolizing the strength to endure the assaults of persecution, like navigating through the dangers of the sea with wisdom.
But his left foot is on the land, indicating those who should not face greater dangers.
For God does not allow us to be tempted beyond what we can bear, but with the temptation, He will also provide a way out so that we can endure it.
It is certain, however, that his preaching will spread over land and sea.
And he cried out with a loud voice like a roaring lion, proclaiming boldly through his servants with strength.
Hence the prophet says: And he set the firm strength of his love.
And when he cried out, the seven thunders spoke.
Because of the known significance of the number seven, I think the seven thunders signify the complete modification of ecclesiastical preaching.
The apostle Paul, maintaining this, said to some (First Corinthians 3): I fed you with milk, not solid food, because you were not ready for it.
To others, however (Hebrews 5), he says, Solid food is for the mature; and to others still (Titus 3), Avoid a divisive person after the first and second warning.
Thus, the church is said to proclaim its usual preaching duties rightly.
And I was about to write what the seven thunders spoke, but I heard a voice from heaven saying: Seal up what the seven thunders have said, and do not write it down.
He was commanded not to describe openly what he heard, but to temper it by discreetly sealing it, so that it would not be indiscriminately revealed to all or easily understood and thereby cause contempt.
Therefore, he says: Make a note for yourself, or, as another translation has it, Seal it for yourself, and do not write it, to indicate the allegory by a sign, not to deny understanding.
It is rightly said to Daniel (Daniel...).
Chapter 12: Seal the book and close the message until the appointed time; many will pass through, and knowledge will be greatly increased.
This means either to defer it for a time or to distribute it according to the recipients' capacity.
Hence, the Lord says in John 16: "I have many things to say to you, but you cannot bear them now."
And the angel, whom I saw standing on the sea and on the land, raised his right hand to heaven and swore by the one who lives forever and ever, who created heaven and everything in it, and the earth and everything in it, that there will be no more time. But in the days of the voice of the seventh angel, when he begins to sound the trumpet, the mystery of God will be finished, as he announced to his servants the prophets.
The trumpet of the seventh angel signifies the end of persecution and the coming of the Lord. Therefore, the Apostle also says in First Corinthians 15: "At the last trumpet, it will sound, and the dead will be raised incorruptible."
Thus, the Church predicts the future time when it will receive the promised eternity of heavenly goods, no longer subject to the variety of times, but enjoying the stable eternity of happiness. The mystery is finished, meaning the promise is fulfilled, not taken away.
And I heard a voice from heaven speaking to me again: "Go and take the open book from the hand of the angel standing on the sea and on the land." The voice from heaven is the command of God, who inspires the heart of the Church and commands it to receive what the Church proclaims with an open book about future peace.
It also seems to us that taking the open book from the hand of the angel means understanding the truth of the law and the prophets manifested in Christ. Therefore, it is said to take the open book, not like the sealed one above. For Christ, who is the end of the law for righteousness to everyone who believes. Christ, that is, the Truth, chose to be born from the earth, from Mary, when righteousness looked down from heaven (Psalm 85).
Therefore, I think it is said here, "I heard a voice from heaven speaking to me," as he himself says in John 8: "I am the beginning, who also speaks to you."
And I went to the angel, telling him to give me the book.
The church, moved by divine inspiration, is eager to learn about this mystery.
It says to me: Take and eat it, meaning store it in your innermost being.
It will make your stomach bitter, but in your mouth, it will be sweet as honey.
When you understand it, you will delight in the sweetness of divine words, the hope of promised salvation, and the divine sweetness of justice.
But you will certainly feel bitterness when you begin to preach this to both the devout and the non-devout.
After hearing the preaching of divine judgment, some indeed change for the better through the bitterness of repentance, while others become offended and even more stubborn.
They bear intense hatred towards the preachers.
"Rebuke a wise man, and he will love you; correct a foolish man, and he will hate you even more" (Proverbs 9).
From both types, the preacher experiences bitterness, either sharing tears in compassion with the repentant or suffering bitterness from the faults of the others.
Hence, the Apostle says in Romans 9: "I have great sorrow and continuous pain in my heart. For I could wish that I myself were cursed and cut off from Christ for the sake of my brothers."
This is the bitterness he now recalls. But if sweetness is to be understood from the devout, and bitterness only from the non-devout, I think this fits more aptly. For the spiritual can say: "How sweet are your words to my taste! Sweeter than honey to my mouth" (Psalm 119).
When I took the little book from the angel's hand and ate it, my stomach was immediately filled; and he said to me: "You must prophesy again about many peoples, nations, languages, and kings."
Just as divine Scripture often shifts from the general to the specific but also embraces both, the focus is indeed directed specifically to John, who still had to be freed from exile, not only to bring this revelation to the knowledge of the Church of Christ but also to preach the Gospel more deeply to many peoples, nations, languages, and kings.
Nevertheless, no one doubts that this call also fits the entire Church, which should never cease from preaching.
The confidence in spreading the gospel, symbolized by the reed received like a rod, holds significant meaning.
The gospel is written with the help of a reed, and to avoid thinking the reed is trivial, it is likened to a rod, representing strength and solidity.
This symbolizes the firmness of faith or the measure of belief aligned with the rule, remembering the diverse distribution of graces.
The Apostle Paul mentions in Ephesians chapter 4: "But to each one of us grace has been given as Christ apportioned it."
In this faith, recognize the brightness of wisdom, symbolized by gold, with the manifestation of the flesh received by Christ, who bore it as one person. John both recognized and preached this. It is fitting that the gift of graces is described as given to the members according to measure, but it is specifically noted that it is given to Christ the head without measure. John says in chapter 3: "For God gives the Spirit without measure."
In Him are all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge, and in Him all the fullness of deity dwells, as written in Colossians chapter 2. No measure can define Him.
Chapter Eleven
He gave me, he said, a golden reed like a rod, saying, "Rise and measure the temple of God, and the altar of God, and those who worship there."
Rise.
This signifies the awakening of John or the Church, so that, free from worldly hindrances, we may be more prepared for the duties of eternal blessings.
Measure the temple, and the altar, and those who worship there.
He commands the Church, which is the temple of God, to be spiritually shaped by the measure of divine gifts, especially in faith, without which it is impossible to please God.
Hebrews chapter eleven.
Those who worship there are emphasized because they strive to worship the Lord in spirit and truth, so that true belief and a life that is acceptable shine forth.
For the Father, he says, seeks such true worshipers to worship him.
Alternatively: The altar signifies priests, and the temple signifies the faithful.
Many seem to worship only superficially and are not written in the book.
This is indicated by the following:
But the outer court of the temple, leave it out and do not measure it.
For all the glory of the king's daughter is within.
Psalm forty-five.
Because it has been given to the Gentiles, and they will trample the holy city for forty-two months.
The harmful teachings of false belief and the contagion of unfortunate customs in heretics, Jews, and Gentiles are ordered to be expelled, for it is unworthy for such to approach the Holy of Holies.
For what do I have to do with judging those who are outside? says the Apostle.
First Corinthians chapter five.
All Jews, heretics, and Gentiles continuously attack the Church in various ways, almost trampling it.
The number of months signifies not only the final persecution but also the entire time of Christianity, due to the six ages of the world and the seven days during which all time passes and returns.
For six times seven make forty-two, but I think it refers to both.
And I will give power to my two witnesses, and they will prophesy for one thousand two hundred and sixty days, clothed in sackcloth.
What he had said, "You must prophesy again," means, I will give power to my two witnesses, and they will prophesy.
For John, the two witnesses represent the Church preaching and prophesying with the two Testaments.
Alternatively, there are two kinds of martyrdom: one in disposition and the other in action.
Disposition is known only to God and carried in the heart, even if the time for suffering is not granted.
Action is fulfilled publicly before people when persecution arises.
Sometimes, martyrdom seems to lack spirit; other times, the spirit seems to lack martyrdom.
Hence, the blessed Cyprian says: The first title of victory is to confess the Lord when seized by the hands of the pagans; the second step to glory is to preserve oneself for the Lord by cautious withdrawal.
The former is a public confession, the latter is a private one.
The former conquers the judge of the world, while the latter, content with God as his judge, maintains the integrity of his heart with a pure conscience.
This is clearly proven by the two sons of Zebedee.
James, killed by Herod, is dedicated to martyrdom by public confession; his brother John the Evangelist (Acts 12) is crowned with martyrdom secretly by the Lord.
It is evident that the Lord had long ago said to both: Indeed, you will drink my cup (Matthew 20), one in action and the other in disposition.
Clothed in sackcloth, humility is shown in their confessions.
Therefore, he speaks not of future things but of present ones, saying: These are the two olive trees and the two lampstands standing before the Lord of the earth.
This can be taken to mean the Church, illuminated by the light of the two Testaments.
Concerning the two types of martyrdom mentioned, they are divinely distributed among different members who are armed.
The two lampstands also represent the Church, but he said two because of the number of Testaments, or because it stands gathered from both circumcision and uncircumcision, adhering to the cornerstone.
Thus, from the seven lampstands, if one or more are named for places, it is the whole Church.
And if anyone wishes to harm them, fire comes out of their mouths, consuming their enemies, and if anyone wishes to harm them, so must that person be killed.
This means that if anyone wishes to harm the Church, they will be consumed by fire, condemned by the same judgment they sought to unjustly impose.
They will receive the harm they tried to inflict unjustly.
Or, if someone is spiritually transformed by the prayers of the Church for good, they will improve, as the person is saved from error while the error perishes.
They have the power to close the heavens so that it does not rain during the days of their prophecy.
It says "they have," not "they will have," indicating they possess this power now. Since all power in heaven and on earth has been given to the Son of Man Matthew 28, it can also be understood that the Church, His body, can close the heavens when blessings do not descend on barren earth from it, just as the Lord says about His vineyard Isaiah 5: "And I will command the clouds not to rain upon it."
They have the power to turn all waters into blood and to strike the earth with every plague as often as they wish. They not only hold back the waters but also make the waters that have descended useless. This means turning the waters into blood because those who carnally understand what the Church spiritually examines are justly struck with anathema by the Church and die. From the same source that brings spiritual life and progress to others, they incur the death of failure. As the Apostle says Romans 8: "to set the mind on the flesh is death." Therefore, the good fragrance of Christ from the Church brings death to some as the odor of death leading to death, and life to others as the odor of life leading to life Second Corinthians 2.
Hence, it is also said that they strike the earth with plagues, as they righteously judge each individual with the power of binding and loosing given to them, according to the diversity of merits and sins. And when they have finished their testimony, the beast that comes up from the abyss will make war with them, conquer them, and kill them. It is clearly shown here that these things will happen before the final persecution, as it says, "when they have finished their testimony," meaning the testimony they give until the revelation of the beast that is to come up from the abyss, which is from the hidden depths of the wickedness of the hearts of the Jews. For it is said that the Antichrist will be born from the tribe of Dan.
He will conquer them, he said, among those who have been defeated.
But he will kill those, signifying those who have been killed for their praiseworthy patience in the name of Christ.
He will place their bodies in the middle of that great city, which is spiritually called Sodom and Egypt, where their Lord was also crucified.
Another translation says he placed the body.
He said the body of two, sometimes in subsequent passages bodies, to maintain the number of Testaments and the two martyrdoms, and to show the Church as one body.
He spoke not only of the killed but also of the living.
They will be thrown out, meaning they will be despised, as you have thrown my words behind you (Psalm 49).
In the middle, that is, in plain sight.
Specifically, that Jerusalem that kills the prophets, according to the word of the Lord rebuking (Matthew 23), and stones those sent to her, deservedly earning rejection, not restoration.
And they will see from the peoples, tribes, tongues, and nations, and they will not allow their bodies to be placed in tombs.
When bodies are not allowed to be gathered in proper places, they do not allow the days of their memory to be marked by the sacred celebration of the living.
Otherwise, the vows of such people are expressed, by which the wicked try to take the Church of Christ from the world.
As the psalm says (Psalm 109): Let their name not be remembered anymore, which although they cannot fulfill, they still exercise their harmful will.
And the inhabitants, he said, of the earth, will rejoice over them, and be glad, and they will send gifts to one another, because these two tormented those who dwell on the earth.
It is not surprising if those who are wise in earthly things rejoice in the deaths of the righteous.
Besides the plagues by which mankind is accused because of the testament of God, even the very sight of the righteous burdens the unjust, as it is written (Wisdom 2): He is burdensome to us even to see, not only does he burden, but also causes us to waste away.
Hence the psalm (Psalm 112): The sinner will see and be angry, he will gnash his teeth and waste away.
And after three and a half days, the spirit of life from God entered into them, and they stood on their feet: and whoever saw them, were afraid.
Three and a half days can be understood as three years and six months, which the prophecy of Daniel also predicts will occur in the last week Daniel 9.
Using the language of Scripture, we read about the forty days during which the spies explored the land of Canaan Numbers 13, where a year is counted as a day.
Here, vice versa, a day is used for a year.
To avoid any uncertainty in our interpretation, we should first present the words of the passage along with a fitting explanation, to see how we might uncover the hidden meaning of this passage.
When it speaks of the seventy weeks, it says Daniel 9: "From the time the word goes out to rebuild Jerusalem until the Anointed One, the ruler, comes, there will be sixty-two weeks. After the sixty-two weeks, the Anointed One will be put to death and will have nothing. The people of the ruler who will come will destroy the city and the sanctuary" Daniel 9:25-26. And shortly after: "He will confirm a covenant with many for one week, but in the middle of the week, he will put an end to sacrifice and offering, and at the temple, he will set up an abomination that causes desolation."
These words, referring to the first coming of Christ, find fulfillment in that event. However, the division of weeks-first mentioned as seventy, then sixty-two, and finally one, which is divided into two parts-can fittingly be applied to the end of the first coming of Christ and the beginning of the second.
To clarify this further, I believe it is necessary to refer to both with appropriate explanation. For after the seventy and sixty-two weeks, Christ will be put to death, rejecting those who put him to death. As it is said, the same people will no longer be His, and He will confirm a covenant with many for one week. When all the sayings or deeds of the Old Testament, which typified the coming of Christ, are fulfilled by His presence, He is the end of the law Romans.
It is indeed rightly understood.
However, I also think it fitting that it pertains especially to the final course of this week of the world's existence, as I soon hear in the same place: "And in the middle of the week, the offering and the sacrifice will cease."
For it also says later in the Book of Daniel: "Because in a time, times, and half a time." When the dispersion of the holy people's power is completed, all these things will be fulfilled. Shortly after: "When the continuous sacrifice is taken away, and the abomination of desolation is set up, there will be 1,290 days," which roughly corresponds to three years and six months.
During this period, those two forms of martyrdom, which we previously mentioned as being consistent in appearance and action, will be so confirmed in the middle of Elijah's week of preaching that they cannot be overthrown by the force of persecution. Just as fiercer persecution arises, greater strength will shine forth in the soldiers of Christ who fight invincibly.
For John says of them: "And I will give power to my two witnesses, and they will prophesy for 1,260 days, clothed in sackcloth." Even though for the remaining three years and six months before the violence of the Antichrist, they may either retreat to secluded places as if dead, or suitably hide and not appear due to being divinely warned to stay concealed, they are said to be established and restored for the contest of his battle.
So that, revived by the spirit of life, they stand firm on their feet when the final preaching or persecution will confirm the covenant with many for one week. When others are killed after completing their martyrdom, and others are scattered, they are predicted to rise for the unity of one body. Armed with one spirit and founded in one faith, they migrate spiritually, because if one member suffers, all the members suffer with it, as it says in First Corinthians Chapter 12.
Therefore, the Lord also says of John in the Book of Luke: "In the spirit and power of Elijah."
Elijah has already come, and they did to him whatever they wanted.
This refers to John, who was promised to come in the spirit and power of Elijah.
This makes it clear that, by the same spirit and role, one person would be recognized instead of the other, namely Elijah for John.
Just as he preceded in the first coming, so John precedes in the second coming.
Here too, the Lord says, "Elijah will come, and he will restore everything." When he fulfills the promises, he will restore what was foreshadowed. He will also confirm a covenant with many for one week, all of which are prophetically known to have been promised in Elijah's person. During the same time interval, that is, three years and six months, he hid so it would not rain, as mentioned in First Kings 17. By divine will, he again obtained rain and appeared, and through the sacrifice that was offered, reconciled the hearts of the Israelite people to God, as noted in First Kings 18.
It is not in vain that mention of the rain is made. This suggests that the truth of past events will be revealed in future works. This will occur in the remaining three years and six months, during the persecution of the Antichrist, with Elijah being killed before the middle of the week when the sacrifice will cease. This sacrifice is now solemnly offered in the Church, with the savagery of the Antichrist prevailing.
Finally, during his preaching, the Jews will believe in Christ, whom he rebuked and once deserved to be converted from idolatry. Now, it can be asked whether the preaching of Elijah for the time of three years and six months should be matched to this resurrection, or to the remaining three years of the Antichrist's persecution. It was foretold, "Their bodies will not be allowed to be put in graves, and those who dwell on the earth will rejoice over them," and other things that are either narrated ahead of time, written as if past events, or perhaps ambiguously woven together. This will not be lacking in the half-week of preaching and the half-week of persecution.
And at that hour, there was a great earthquake.
A tenth of the city fell, and seven thousand people were killed.
This earthquake may signify persecution or a recapitulation, or it might mean that the number of deaths was exaggerated.
An hour signifies any time period, and the numbers ten and seven are considered perfect.
If it weren't so, we should understand the whole from the part.
He says that part of the city perished, specifically the wicked ones.
This is similar to what we read in the First Epistle of John, Chapter 2: "They went out from us, but they did not belong to us. For if they had belonged to us, they would have remained with us."
There are two buildings: one on the rock and the other on the sand (Matthew, Chapter 7).
He says this one fell.
The rest were struck with fear and gave glory to the God of heaven and earth.
These are the ones built on the rock (Luke, Chapter 6).
While others fall from their stability during the earthquake, which symbolizes persecution, they glorify God through their confession.
After finishing the recapitulation, which was inserted without mentioning the seventh angel, he resumes the order, saying: "The second woe has passed, behold, the third woe is coming quickly." Earlier, he said that after the battle with the locusts, one woe had passed, and two more woes were coming. This was to clarify that the third woe wouldn't be described immediately, as it needed to be recapitulated. Now, having finished the recapitulation, he says, "The second woe has passed," referring not to the recapitulation but to the horses, which he had described but not concluded.
Thus, the second woe has passed; it is the woe of the horses, and the third woe follows. The seventh angel sounded his trumpet, and there were loud voices in heaven, saying: "The kingdom of our God and His Christ has come, and He will reign forever and ever."
And the twenty-four elders who sit before God on their thrones fell on their faces and worshipped God, saying:
"We give thanks to you, Lord God Almighty, who is and was, because you have taken your great power and have reigned. The nations were angry, and your wrath has come, and the time for the dead to be judged, and to reward your servants the prophets and those who fear your name, both small and great, and to destroy those who corrupt the earth."
Regarding the elders, it's enough to understand what has been mentioned. Now, he recalls the beginning and the end of Christ's dispensation. By saying,
"You have reigned, and the nations were angry," he shows the first coming of Christ. But what follows,
"Your wrath has come and the time for the dead to be judged," or, as another translation says,
"for the dead to be judged," shows the second coming, when the holy ones and prophets, and those who fear his name, both small and great, perfect and imperfect, receive their reward. As it says,
"My imperfection has been seen by your eyes, and all will be written in your book" (Psalm 138).
To prevent the wicked from promising themselves impunity, it is added:
"And to destroy those who corrupt the earth," as the psalm says (Psalm 33):
"The face of the Lord is against those who do evil."
Behold, it says, the third woe comes with the voice of the seventh angel; and when he sounded, it spoke only of the Church praising the Lord and giving thanks, from which we understand that the reward of the good is not without the woe of the wicked. Hence the psalm (Psalm 2):
"When his wrath is kindled in a little while, surely upon the wicked, blessed are all who trust in him."
So now the Church itself says:
"Your wrath has come and the time for the dead to be judged, and to give the reward to your servants," etc. This is the final woe. The birth of the Lord in the flesh having been recapitulated, he indicates that he will speak the same thing differently and more extensively. And the temple of God in heaven was opened, which is the Church. The temple of God can be understood as the body of Christ. Hence the same Lord said:
"Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up" (John 2).
A certain understanding can be sought here under various meanings, so that each thing, when appropriately returned to its own context, can be recognized more clearly.
When the ark generally signifies the Church, the ark of the covenant in the temple suggests something deeper to understand.
By also referring to heaven, it persuades us to uncover some secret meaning: the temple is the Church, and the ark of the covenant represents the mystery of the incarnation of Christ who, carrying the death of that ark and the tablets of the covenant within himself, came not to abolish the law, but to fulfill it.
For as many as the promises of God are, says the Apostle in Second Corinthians, in him they are.
And having a golden jar of manna, as mentioned in Hebrews Nine, because he carries within his body the spiritual food adorned with the splendor of wisdom, to be offered to others.
For the bread of God is that which comes down from heaven and gives life to the world, as written in John Six.
And the rod of Aaron, because he was uniquely begotten by the immaculate virgin in a new birth, within the covering of the flesh like an almond, is said to have all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge hidden within him, as stated in Colossians Two.
Hence the psalm: Arise, O Lord, into your rest, you and the ark of your sanctification, and other things that match this sense.
For God promises through Jeremiah that the ark of the covenant will be removed from the hearts of men, indeed that of the Hebrews, and that Jerusalem, meaning the Church, will be called the throne of the Lord, saying:
When you have multiplied and increased in the land, says the Lord, they will no longer say, the ark of the covenant of the Lord, nor will it come to mind.
In those days and at that time they will call Jerusalem the throne of the Lord, and all nations will gather to it in the name of the Lord, as described in Jeremiah Three.
And there were flashes of lightning and voices and thunder and an earthquake and great hail.
The flashes of lightning are the virtues by which Christ the Lord made his disciples shine.
The voices and thunder are the preachings by which the apostles, like clouds, thundered to the peoples.
The earthquake is the uproar, the commotion of the peoples, who often brought persecutions to the growing Church.
Hailstones always cause more damage by breaking up when they hit the waves, shattering themselves in the process.
In the same way, the cruel masses of pagans who persecuted the Christian faith later diminished in number or disappeared altogether by following it.
He mentioned that these events were described in the preaching of the seven angels from the very advent of the Lord, covering the period from the beginning to the end.
Then, he specifically explained how these things happened, and now as the temple of God in heaven is opened, the battles followed, saying:
Chapter Twelve
A great sign was seen in heaven.
What is seen now in the Church is the wisdom of God, with human nature being united by the Holy Spirit, and from both becoming one and the same Christ, the mediator of God and humans, being preached or believed, as He Himself said John 2: "Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up"; and the evangelist, "But He was speaking of the temple of His body."
A woman clothed with the sun, and the moon under her feet. It is often said that a kind is divided into many species, which are one, for what is heaven, is also the temple in heaven, this woman clothed with the sun, and the moon under her feet, that is, the Church clothed with Christ, because of His love trampling all changeable things. For neither is she snatched away by these changeable things, who adhering to the stable good truly says Psalm 73: "But for me, it is good to be near God."
Hence those voices which we read about the Church Song of Solomon 6: "Beautiful as the moon, bright as the sun"; and again: "As the moon, perfect forever, and a faithful witness in heaven" Psalm 89. He indeed speaks of the pilgrim Church; otherwise, after the human birth of Christ, we have seen many heretics and the same false opinions being brought forth. For about this temple, Valentius said one thing, Bardesanes another, Apollinaris another, Nestorius another, Eutyches another, Timothy Hilary another, the heresiarchs, lied as they pleased, so that as if truth arose from the earth and battles followed, from which the orthodox and faithful gain a reward, those heretics thinking badly of the incarnation of Christ, incur the punishment of eternal damnation.
Hence we remember what Simeon said about Him in the Gospel Luke 2: "Behold, this child is destined for the fall and rising of many in Israel, and for a sign that will be opposed." And on her head a crown of twelve stars, that is the Church; he says it is adorned by the number twelve of the apostles, the beginnings of the soon-established Church. Hence the psalm says Psalm 20: "You placed on his head a crown of precious stones." And she was pregnant in mind, not in body; and she cried out.
In the valley of lamentation, filled with groans and those it births; it never stops giving birth to those already born.
Hence the Apostle (Galatians 4) says: My little children, for whom I am again in the pains of childbirth until Christ is formed in you.
And another sign appeared in the sky: a great red dragon, bloody and fierce, with seven heads and ten horns, and on its heads were seven diadems.
The seven heads are seven kings, and the horns are kingdoms, which we will discuss in due course.
Its tail swept a third of the stars from the sky and cast them to the earth.
The tail represents false prophets, through whom the enemy carries out his wickedness.
Hence Isaiah says (Isaiah 9): The prophet who teaches lies, he is the tail.
Those who follow their teachings are said to be cast down to the earth.
The third part of the stars of the sky refers to all the evil beings, whether they are angels he dragged down from heaven or humans he deceived.
The stars represent those whom the devil turns from good to wicked.
The dragon stood before the woman who was about to give birth, so that when she gave birth, he might devour her child.
This means the devil, the deceiver, aims to destroy the new person created according to God, in whom we are renewed in the spirit of our minds in righteousness and holiness of truth (Ephesians 4) in the Church, as he cunningly tries to stifle emerging faith or extinguish the progress of each believer.
We also remember this happened to a heretic, who, in a fatal stupor, is recorded to have strangled his own offspring to death, which prophetically represents the killing of the new life we are commanded to walk in.
Before the woman, it is said, he stood because she, it is said, will watch your head, and you will lie in wait for her heel (Genesis 3).
And she gave birth to a male child who was to rule all the nations with an iron rod.
The male child signifies victory rightfully due to the male sex as the superior.
Here, the head of the Church, Christ, is said to be born in each member, who is recognized as the ruler.
For He is the author and finisher of faith, in whom we will find strength.
With an iron rod, which symbolizes unbending justice, He will rule over the good and break the wicked.
This also applies to His church as a body and head.
For all, He says, who have been baptized in Christ Jesus have put on Christ (Galatians 3); and, the two shall become one flesh.
This is to be understood in Christ, says the Apostle, and in the Church (Ephesians 5).
His Son was taken up to God and to His throne.
Although Christ, the head, preceded us, having ascended to the Father after His mission was completed, it also applies to the body.
Hence the words of the Apostle (Ephesians 2): He raised us up and made us sit in the heavenly places; and (Philippians 3): our citizenship is in heaven; and (Colossians 3): if you have been raised with Christ, seek the things that are above, where Christ is seated at the right hand of God.
If you want to take this specifically about Christ, except for the pain that it is not believed that Blessed Mary had in childbirth, since we know she did not contract any sin of lust in conception, you can rightly adapt the rest.
If we recognize the snares of the red dragon, the persecutions that Christ endured from His infancy by Herod (Matthew 1); and afterwards willingly faced until His death on the cross, who, when His death was desired and sought, frustrated His resurrection, lamenting that He was taken up to the throne of God, which is at the right hand of the Father.
And the woman fled into the wilderness, where she has a place prepared by God, so that He might nourish her there for one thousand two hundred sixty days.
The wilderness represents the pilgrimage of this life, in which the church lives like a solitary sparrow (Psalm 102) with the unique hope of blessed reward, which has received the power from its King to tread on serpents (Mark 16; Luke 10) and scorpions, and over all the power of the enemy, the red dragon.
For even the people of Israel, led through the desert (Numbers 21), could overcome the fiery serpents by looking at the bronze serpent.
For all these things, says the Apostle (First Corinthians).
These events were meant as examples for us.
Just as He fed them with visible manna, He now feeds the Church with heavenly bread.
There is a prepared place, as the prophet says in Psalm 84:
"In the place He has appointed."
This place is described in First Corinthians 2: "Eye has not seen, nor ear heard, nor has it entered into the heart of man." The heart of man must ascend there, driven by the mutual peace of human speech. Both the appointed place and the prepared place are referenced in Psalm 84:
"Blessed is the man whose strength is in You, in whose heart are the highways to Zion. Passing through the valley of tears, they make it a place of springs."
This place serves as both a refuge for pilgrims and food for hungry servants, who are promised a reward for reigning. These things, which God has prepared, as the Apostle says in First Corinthians 2, are for those who love Him:
"God has revealed them to us by His Spirit," through which even blessed John could penetrate these depths.
The period of three years and six months signifies all the times of Christianity, from the beginning of Christ's preaching to the fruitful end.
A battle occurred in heaven: Michael and his angels fought against the dragon.
We should not think that God's angels fought in heaven without His permission, as even Job could not be tested without it, as written in Job 1.
Here, heaven signifies the Church, where the faithful continually fight against spiritual wickedness. Hence the Apostle says in Ephesians 6:
"For our struggle is not against flesh and blood, but against the rulers, against the authorities, against the powers of this dark world."
Michael is said to fight against the devil with his angels because, according to God's will, he prays and ministers to the pilgrim Church, fighting for it.
As the Apostle says in Hebrews 1, are they not all ministering spirits sent to serve those who will inherit eternal salvation?
The name Michael is interpreted to mean "help of God," and this task is appropriately assigned to him. Daniel said that in the last distress, he would come to help the Church. "At that time," he says, "Michael, the great prince who stands up for the children of your people, will arise. There will be a time of trouble such as never was since there was a nation till that time. And at that time your people shall be delivered, everyone who is found written in the book."
Regarding the saying that they are his angels, this type of speech is used as we read in Matthew 18: "For their angels always see the face of my Father who is in heaven," specifically for those who have begun to be citizens by believing in Christ. Here, they are called his angels because they are believed to be rewarded by one reigning king and blessed by one life-giving Spirit.
"And the dragon fought and his angels, but they did not prevail, nor was their place found anymore in heaven." The devil and his angels are understood to be those who are like him in nature and will, including humans ensnared by their traps who have become followers of such. Regarding the qualities of their wills, it was said of the devil: "An evil man did this" (Matthew 13), and of Judas, "he is a devil" (John 6).
The devil is indeed delivered in his own twofold body but is said to be cast out by those who, after renouncing him and receiving faith in Christ, no longer return to his errors.
In them, charity perseveres with a pure heart, good conscience, and unfeigned faith 1 Timothy 1.
Or when the Church, already separated from all mingling with the wicked and glorified in future blessedness, no longer gives any place to the devil and his angels for either deceiving the wicked or testing the good.
Hence the psalm, noting him, says in Psalm 37: "I passed by, and behold, he was not; I sought him, but his place was not found."
And the dragon, that great and ancient serpent, who is called the devil and Satan, who deceives the whole world, was sent to the earth, and his angels were sent with him.
Here, those who are wise in earthly matters are understood, where that prevailing judgment recognizes the devil to dwell.
"You will eat dust all the days of your life," Genesis 3.
Being excluded from the spiritual ones, he invades those who are suitable for earthly things by their merits. He is cast down from heaven and sent to the earth.
And I heard a loud voice in heaven saying: "Now salvation and strength, and the kingdom of our God, and the power of His Christ have come."
It is clearly shown in which heaven we should understand these things. For in the Church, we know the victory of Christ has brought salvation, through which He also received the power to bind and loose, as He told Peter:
"Whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven," Matthew 16.
About this, the Lord says in Matthew 28:
"All power in heaven and on earth has been given to me,"
not the power He always had, but the power He began to have in the Church from the time He wished as the head in the members.
Because the accuser of our brothers, who accused them before our God day and night, has been cast down. They overcame him by the blood of the Lamb and by the word of their testimony.
Recently, in the style of speech previously mentioned, he says from the perspective of the angels: the accuser of our brothers, that is, our future fellow citizens, but now, strangers. The faithful now strive for that heavenly city, Jerusalem, which the angels happily inhabit. They are said to rejoice in saying that he has been cast out of heaven and sent to earth. They congratulate the redemption of those whom the Lord has deigned to prepare as a temple for dwelling.
For the soul of the just is the seat of wisdom.
Of earthly matters, into which it is said he descended, the angels praise the depths of divine justice by knowing, and they sing about his mercy and judgment over the blessed, since both goodness in the redeemed and divine fairness in the lost are shown.
For it is said that those who conquer by the blood of the Lamb were able to overcome the devil.
And what follows, "They did not love their lives so much as to shrink from death," is believed to have received that love, which is spread in our hearts, not from us, but through the Holy Spirit, who has been given to us Romans 5.
Teaching us to rejoice in this great good, he says: "Therefore rejoice, heavens, and you who dwell in them."
Here, if the Church is recognized as heaven as mentioned above with the angels, it is fitting for both to joyfully celebrate in the Lord, since humans are believed to be united with angels, and angels serve the substance of humans in Christ.
It follows, "Woe to the earth and the sea, because the devil has come down to you with great wrath, knowing that his time is short!"
Just as rejoicing is due for the redeemed, so mourning is due for the perishing.
Hence Ezekiel Chapter 2 says he received a book written with lamentation, mourning, and woe.
In the lamentation, the weeping of the penitent is implied.
In the mourning, the joy of the saints is hinted.
But woe specifically signifies the condemnation of the wicked.
This is also mentioned here, saying: "Woe to the earth and the sea," up to "knowing that his time is short."
Hence, compelled to confess by the Lord's invincible power, he says: "Have you come here to torture us before the appointed time?"
And when the dragon saw that he had been cast down to the earth, he pursued the woman who had given birth to the male child.
This means, as we mentioned before, that the devil wages unending enmity against the Church.
For when he is about to be defeated and cast out, he does not cease to multiply his tricks even more fiercely.
And the woman was given two wings of a great eagle, to fly into the wilderness to her place.
The Church uses the two Testaments as if they were wings, by which she learns to avoid the enemy's snares, instructed by commandments, and overcomes informed by examples.
It is also governed by the love of God and neighbor.
However, the place of solitude is this worldly pilgrimage.
As long as we are in the body, we are away from the Lord.
Second Corinthians 5
This is where the heart directs itself, not by location, but by affection, departing from the world.
The prophet says, Psalm 55: "See, I have fled far off and stayed in solitude. I waited for the one who would save me."
Here, the eagle's likeness is aptly mentioned, as it is known to fly higher than other birds. Yet, when it sees food from afar, driven by natural need, it quickly descends to the ground. Just as the Church, in its spiritual members, seeks and desires what is above Colossians 3 with its mind, but, burdened by bodily weakness, is subject to the needs of physical indigence. For which it groans and labors until now; for creation was subjected to vanity Romans 8, not willingly, but because of Him who subjected it in hope.
Also: Whether we are out of our mind, it is for God; whether we are in our right mind, it is for you. Second Corinthians 5
Where it is nourished for a time, times, and half a time from the face of the Antichrist, that is, from that serpent, for a period of three years and six months. This again signifies the time until the end of the Church of God in Christ, fleeing the worship of idols and all the errors of the serpent. This means from the face of that serpent, which it previously mentioned as a dragon, which it overcame in the blood of the Lamb, so that it can truly sing, Psalm 91: "You will tread on the asp and the basilisk and trample the lion and the dragon."
And that serpent sent water like a river out of its mouth after the woman, to sweep her away. The water signifies the assault of persecutors. Hence the psalm, Psalm 124: "When men rose up against us, they would have swallowed us alive. When their anger burned against us, the waters would have engulfed us. Our soul passed over the torrent," etc. But the earth helped the woman, and the earth opened its mouth and swallowed the river that the dragon had poured out of its mouth.
Although "the earth" can also be understood as the Church here, as in Psalm 102: "He founded the earth upon its stability, it will not be moved forever," meaning the saints whose prayers, teachings, and the administration of salvation nullify the enemy's cunning, it is better understood here as human nature in Christ.
This is the truth that sprang from the earth (Psalm 64), always appearing before the face of God, as the Apostle says in Hebrews Chapter 9, and intercedes for us.
For this earth, swallowing up the death taken into itself, is said to open its mouth when the abundance of its life is known to have swallowed the author of death, as mentioned in Romans Chapter 8.
He taught nonetheless, when sitting on the mountain, as in Matthew Chapter 5, opening his mouth, he gave greater commandments to the disciples, abolishing the law of commandments as stated in Ephesians Chapter 2.
And the dragon, enraged with the woman, went to make war with the rest of her offspring who keep the commandments of God and have the testimony of Jesus Christ.
Seeing that persecution could not continue, nor the harmful vows brought to fruition, by which he thought or hoped that the Church of Christ could be removed from the world, namely, prevailing with the trophy of the Lord's body in the heavens, ruling on the earth, and commanding in the underworld.
For this reason, the Apostle says in Romans Chapter 14, Christ died and rose again, that He might be Lord of both the living and the dead; likewise, in Philippians Chapter 2: That at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, in heaven, on earth, and under the earth.
Seeing this, he indeed strives to continually wage war with the rest of the seed of the Church through each generation, knowing that he can no longer eradicate it from the world altogether, because, as it says, the gates of hell will not prevail against it in Matthew Chapter 26.
Christ, indeed, using this marvelously, opportunely gains for Himself multiplied martyrs.
He has determined that the dragon and his associates will be punished with harsher judgments.
Therefore, I think it is more fitting to conclude this book with the memorable victory of the same Church, whose memory cannot perish from the world.