On Humility and Obedience and on Overcoming Pride
by Novatus the Catholic
On Humility and Obedience and on Overcoming Pride.
We speak differently to those outside the Church than we do to you.
To them, we sometimes use impressive words that lack true power, because they enjoy the sound of words rather than the power of God.
But you, in the name of Christ, do not delight in this; instead, you seek to hear the word of salvation, through which you were called.
You have donned these mournful garments in the world, expecting something better from God.
You already know and understand this.
You have spent a long time here struggling against your adversary, which is not outside but within, in your own body.
We face this opponent in our own members.
For if the flesh desires against the spirit, and the spirit against the flesh, so that we do not do what we want-
Galatians chapter five, verse seventeen-
you see that this adversary is within.
However, this adversary is only defeated by humility and love:
for our Lord Jesus Christ would not have defeated the devil if he had not been humbled, not by necessity but by love.
If he had not loved, he would not have become humble.
Out of love for us, he became humble.
Therefore, if he who made heaven and earth, the sea, and all that is in them-
Psalm one hundred forty-six, verse four-
the Lord of all angels, who created everything, became humble for us, why do we refuse humility for our own sake?
The path of salvation is not open to us unless we are humble.
When you begin humility, seek it for God's sake and endure it for the sake of the community.
And within that community, even though you are equals, each one should consider the other as superior, even if they are not.
Only someone with humility can do that.
For the servants of God, no other reward is necessary, except humility:
because if humility is present in a person, it makes them obedient.
Whoever is obedient, or who follows obedience, does not obey humans but God.
For the Lord said: Whoever listens to you listens to me; whoever listens to me listens to him who sent me-
Luke chapter ten, verse sixteen.
Father Abbot is here, and the following brothers are the Patriarchs.
Anyone among you who leads a good life, practices self-control, stays watchful, and takes care of their body is also like a Father because of their example.
Therefore, practice these virtues among yourselves, ensuring that you maintain humility-not to appear humble to others, but to God.
True humility is shown to God, not to people.
Humility displayed for others is mere pretense, and should be completely foreign to the servants of God.
I don't believe there are such issues among you, but I advise you to guard against them creeping in.
We are human, and we speak to humans.
Therefore, show humility to your brothers as an example, so that true humility is rooted in your heart according to God's standards.
When humility is established in your heart for God, He grants your brother the understanding to imitate your humility.
If humility is not genuine in your heart, God reveals to your brother that it is fake.
The first step to salvation is this: to maintain simple humility for God, not for people; not to please others with it, but to please God.
Let obedience follow humility, and be obedient to one another, just as the parts of a body are obedient to each other.
Do the body parts obey through reasoning, or through natural love?
If the foot is hurt, the hand comes to help, preventing the whole body from being injured and falling.
As the Apostle says: "If one member suffers, all the members suffer with it," from First Corinthians chapter twelve, verse twenty-six.
Where does this come from, if not from love?
Therefore, if you love each other, there will be no disturbances.
Let no one suffer scandals; not because of food, drink, clothing, watchfulness, work, the kitchen, or service.
When you love each other, if someone makes a mistake, that love prevents you from being offended.
Therefore, brothers, embrace humility and obedience, which bring peace, so that you may become children of peace.
As the Apostle says, love is the bond of perfection (Colossians 3:14).
When you possess humility, you imitate Christ, who became humble for us.
When you practice obedience, you follow Christ, who was obedient even to the point of death (Philippians 2:8).
When you embody love, you reflect Christ, for God is love (First John 5:16).
But first, strive to conquer your inner vices.
Let peace first dwell in your soul and heart with God's commandment, so that in the battle against bodily habits and weaknesses, there are two victors: God's commandment and your agreement.
Consider this scenario: the doctor, the patient, and the illness.
If the patient sides with the illness, the doctor is outnumbered, making it two against one, and the doctor is defeated.
But if the patient sides with the doctor, the illness is defeated.
The doctor is Christ; we are the patients; the illness is the habit of sin.
Now, those who have partially renounced the world while still living in it should consider to whom they should cling: the illness or the doctor.
If they do not cling to the doctor, the doctor struggles.
That is why the Gospel calls out to us in the world, saying: "Be in agreement with your adversary quickly while you are on the way with him" (Matthew 5:25).
It doesn't teach us to agree with the adversary, the devil, but to agree with the adversary, the divine commandment, which opposes our evils, our habits, and our iniquities.
If we agree, we align ourselves with God's commandment and accept it almost like God's yoke, prompting the Lord to say: "Come to me, all who labor and are burdened, and I will give you rest. Take my yoke, for it is easy, and my burden is light" (Matthew 11:28).
Consider what is so light?
Finally, think about how those who possess something in this world fear it might be taken away.
How they dread losing what they have gained?
In what ways are they tormented, as if under a very heavy burden of worry?
However, you should focus solely on what the abbot commands.
You're already under guidance, so don't worry about where you live, as that's not something you should dwell on.
There is someone to guide you and care for you.
You shouldn't be concerned with thoughts about food and clothing at all.
Consider what the abbot gives you as if it were given by God: that's true humility.
But if one person has more and another less, see it as if God intended it that way.
If someone sits at a different table and the abbot orders it, accept it as if God commanded it.
Don't question it by thinking, "Tomorrow I'll sit there."
Avoid making it a habit to focus on those desires.
If there's nothing to give, or it seems there's nothing to give, accept it as either there's truly nothing, or it wasn't beneficial to provide it.
Brothers, if you follow these principles, you will surely attain eternal life.
Don't be swayed by negative talk.
If someone weak falls and speaks wrongly, immediately correct them: say, "Don't do that, don't, brother, you're sinning."
Because you're united under one abbot, you should be abbots to each other.
Can one person, with just two eyes and ears, see and hear everyone?
Doesn't he also need to go out and provide something?
Be abbots to each other; and just as you respected the abbot when he was present, respect him even in his absence because God is always present.
Absolutely fear and be in awe of this, for God is always with us.
If one person cares for so many, how much more should all of you care, ensuring there's no reason for him to be angry, grieved, or feel his efforts were in vain?
These teachings can benefit us if we embrace humility, obedience, and charity.
There is no path to God except through humility, obedience, and charity.
He is the way, the truth, and the life.
Some brothers become proud after enduring suffering and fasting for several days, thinking no one else can do what they do.
They believe their feats are unmatched: like walking barefoot or abstaining from even mixed water, yet these are temporary acts because they can't be sustained forever.
Instead, they should focus on humility, piety, charity, and obedience.
These practices should be embraced to weaken the body's strength and tame the flesh, much like a good athlete, but without boasting, so as not to lose the value of their achievements.
Consider the Pharisee who went up to the temple to pray.
Were his deeds insignificant?
They were remarkable: fasting twice a week, giving tithes of all his possessions, avoiding fraud and adultery, an endless list.
But because he boasted in pride, all his deeds turned into pride.
Luke 18:9 and following.
Therefore, David says: May the foot of pride not come against me, and the hand of the sinner not move me.
There they have fallen, all who work iniquity.
Psalm 36:12.
Where did they fall?
In the fall of pride.
For the devil fell from there; he fell through pride.
Therefore, pride should not be present among the servants of God.
Anyone who lives differently now and has arranged their life better should not be like that Pharisee.
The publican, however, humbled himself and didn't dare to lift his eyes to heaven, and by the Lord's judgment, he returned home justified, more than the Pharisee.
We have seen, both in the holy scriptures and among our brothers, that those who follow the path of humility progress and do not perish.