Four Books Against the Objections of the Greeks
by Ratramnus, a Monk of Corbie
Book Two
Chapter One
Proving from the Fathers that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son.
We are discussing the procession of the Holy Spirit, which the Greek emperors claim proceeds only from the Father, denying it comes from the Son.
Because of this, they refuse to communicate with the Roman Church and reject the envoys of the apostolic see.
They accuse the Latin Church of error because it professes and believes that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son.
First, we observe laypeople disregarding ecclesiastical rules by imposing decrees on the faithful.
Those who are not authorized to establish statutes concerning ecclesiastical law, without consulting bishops, are attempting to establish laws of faith.
According to their decrees, some are received into communion while others are excluded.
If they wished to establish anything regarding their faith, it would have been appropriate to call a council of bishops, seek the statutes of the Fathers, and consult the holy scriptures.
By common agreement, the bishops would then decide what should be followed and what should be rejected.
If it was found that certain beliefs or practices existed in some Churches or regions that needed to be changed, it should have first been communicated to them, understanding the reasons behind these practices.
Then, if just religion required it, judgment should be passed.
This should be done under their own governance and the provision of their empire, with Churches established accordingly.
Otherwise, what right do they have to judge or discuss matters of faith, custom, or doctrine in people or Churches not under their jurisdiction?
And if there is disagreement, should they be excommunicated?
Did the Savior grant the Greek emperors the power to bind and loose?
Did He tell them, "You are the light of the world?"
Matthew chapter five, verse fourteen: "You are the light of the world."
Did He command them to teach all nations and baptize them in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit?
Matthew chapter twenty-eight, verse nineteen: "Go therefore and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit."
If you claim that the Holy Spirit proceeds only from the Father and refuse to acknowledge that He also proceeds from the Son, while the entire Latin Church, or indeed the whole Catholic world, professes that He proceeds from both, how do you justify your opinion as superior and backed by truth?
Or do you believe that the truth of the Gospel has reached only you and resides solely with you?
The Apostle Paul describes himself as an apostle set apart for the Gospel of Christ, as mentioned in Romans, chapter fifteen, verse nineteen.
He spread the Gospel from Jerusalem all the way to Illyricum.
He also traveled to Rome and Spain, covering the entire Roman world, either in person or through his writings, preaching Christ.
Does he claim that he preached Christ only to the Greeks, revealing the truth of the Gospel exclusively to Greek emperors?
The Gospel of Christ shines throughout the entire world.
The writings of the apostles are read, and the prophecies of the prophets are recited.
Through these, the teachers of the Churches, established by the apostles from the beginning, continually learn what to believe about the Holy Trinity, what to profess, and what to teach the people in their care.
They learn how to instruct them in morals, shape their way of life, and form their religious beliefs.
Neither the holy scriptures, the teachings of the elders, the precepts of the apostles, nor the sayings and writings of any of the early Church fathers declare that the Greeks alone are to be the teachers of the entire Church of Christ.
Nor do they state that the emperors should learn from them what should be observed throughout the whole Church of Christ, whether in behavior, religion, or doctrine.
Recognizing such an idea as foolish and arrogant, the Roman Church should not be lightly criticized for preserving the traditions of its elders or for not adopting all the practices of the Greeks.
Because, whether it concerns the Holy Trinity or any religious observance, whatever it holds or practices has come from the teachings of Christ's disciples.
And what it believes, teaches, and practices is not contrary to or inconsistent with the holy scriptures.
So, you criticize us for saying that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, while you say He proceeds from the Father.
Chapter Two
The authority of councils addresses the objections of the Greeks.
First, we ask you to consider the authority of the elders, namely the Catholic bishops, by which you uphold the decree you strive so much to defend.
The Council of Nicaea, with 318 bishops gathered against Arius under the first Emperor Constantine, after dictating the Creed about the consubstantiality of the Son with the Father, when it came to the Holy Spirit, said: We believe in the Holy Spirit: nothing more or less decreeing about His substance or procession.
So, where is the rule now, by which you think you are fortified or the Latins are bound, that you may say the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father, and the Romans may not say He proceeds from the Son?
If you wish to add nothing beyond what the authority of the Council of Nicaea decreed, then remove "proceeding from the Father," because it is not contained in the Creed of the Council of Nicaea: and perhaps it is allowable to remove what was added by the Romans, "proceeding from the Son."
But if you answer and say that this was established in the Council of Constantinople with 150 bishops gathered there, we respond that it was not allowed to remove, add, or change anything in the Creed of the Council of Nicaea regarding the faith.
However, if you argue that it was not allowed to add anything to what was determined in that council about the consubstantiality of the Son, but because little was said about the Holy Spirit, it was allowed due to future questions of heretics according to the authority of the Holy Scriptures:
we respond that the same allowance was given to the Romans, due to future questions of heretics according to the authority of the Divine Scriptures.
For you cannot prove that the authority of the city of Constantinople is greater than that of the city of Rome, which is the head of all the Churches of Christ, as is proven by the testimony of your elders as well as ours.
But the authority of one hundred and fifty bishops is not so great that it can dictate to all the bishops of the whole world.
Therefore, what was allowed to them should also be allowed to the Roman Pontiff and all the Churches of Christ.
They also added to the aforementioned creed, stating that the Holy Spirit is to be worshipped and glorified together with the Father and the Son, who spoke through the holy prophets, and many other things.
By adding these, they did not prescribe to the Churches of Christ but set an example.
If anyone wanted to add anything according to the Holy Scriptures about the Holy Spirit, to refute heretics and strengthen the faith of believers, they could.
But if you argue that what cannot be found written in the holy Gospels or other divine pages is this: the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father, and therefore you do not want to accept what is not found written in the Holy Scriptures; just as the Arians did not want to accept that the Father and the Son are of the same substance because the sacred Scriptures did not contain this: tell us where you have read that the Council of Constantinople put in the creed about the Holy Spirit, saying he is to be worshipped and glorified together with the Father and the Son, and who spoke through the holy prophets.
But if you say that these are not found in the Holy Scriptures in plain words, but the power of understanding is contained in them, so that just as he is of the same substance with the Father and the Son, of one power, not a different majesty, and therefore to be worshipped and glorified together with the Father and the Son; grant the same to the Latin Churches.
Although the Gospels do not plainly say that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, they show in many ways that the Spirit is of the Son, just as he is of the Father, and proceeds from the Son, just as he proceeds from the Father: which we believe has been sufficiently demonstrated in the previous little book.
Given these circumstances, the Catholic faith, founded by the Savior and the apostles, has always held and preached that the Holy Spirit shares the same power and substance with the Father and the Son and proceeds from both.
So why now do you criticize the Catholic faith and attempt to go against its teachings?
Are you perhaps trying to revive Arius or Macedonius and bring their long-buried false doctrines back into the Church?
Did your ancestors not know how the Roman Church spoke about the Holy Spirit?
Yet they never separated themselves from the communion of the Roman See, knowing that what it holds and preaches is the truth of the Catholic faith and is not open to criticism because it is based on the authority of the Holy Scriptures.
Until the time of Arius, there was no confusion among believers about the consubstantiality of the Father and the Son, nor was the term homoousion (same substance) preached.
However, the power of that word was deeply ingrained in the minds of believers, as they believed that the all-powerful Son was in no way different from the Father, recalling well the Savior's words: "Whoever has seen me has seen the Father" (John 14:9).
And they knew from John that Christ was the creator of everything: "All things were made through him" (John 1:3).
Yet in the Apostles' Creed, nothing more was included than what we all know: that we must believe in God the Father almighty, and in Jesus Christ, his only Son, our Lord.
This faith was sufficient for the salvation of believers, and it was approved and commended throughout the world by the blood of many martyrs and the testimony of countless confessors.
But when Arius, the attacker of truth, began to go mad against the divinity of Christ and to hurl many blasphemies, the minds of the faithful were moved to piety, and they drew the weapons of truth against the error of impiety.
Together, they pierced the impious doctrine along with its author, which claimed that the Son of God was a creature and not begotten of the Father, and also blasphemed that the Holy Spirit was lesser than the Son.
After Macedonius rose up, agreeing with the Catholics about the Father and the Son, but not accepting the person of the Holy Spirit, Catholic bishops contended against him.
They proved that the Holy Spirit is one in the Holy Trinity, consubstantial with both the Father and the Son, proceeding from the Father, and to be worshipped and glorified together with the Father and the Son.
Then, when Arian madness resurfaced, claiming it was incorrect to say that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father because it seemed blasphemous—suggesting two Fathers, of the Son and of the Holy Spirit—the Church's teachers decided to repel this blasphemy.
They added to the creed that the Holy Spirit also proceeds from the Son.
If He were said to proceed only from the Father, it might be thought that the Son was not the Spirit, nor would He be called the Spirit of the Son, which is impious and blasphemous, and against evangelical and apostolic doctrine.
For if you say that the word "proceed" sufficiently distinguishes, so that the Holy Spirit is not thought to be the Son, know that it is also preached about the Son. For He Himself says in the Gospel of John:
John 8:42: "I came forth from God, and am here."
So, if the Son proceeds from God the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds as well, what will silence the Arians from blaspheming that the Holy Spirit is the Son of the Father?
Chapter Three
Testimonies from Athanasius and Gregory Nazianzen.
Regarding this matter, the teachers of both the Latins and the Greeks have stated that the Son was begotten solely from the Father, but the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
They understood this through the teachings of the divine scriptures, recognizing that the Spirit is from both the Father and the Son, and therefore proceeds from both.
Hence, the blessed Athanasius, bishop of Alexandria, who suffered much at the hands of the Arians for his steadfastness in the Catholic faith, was frequently exiled by their faction.
He assisted his bishop Alexander as a deacon at the Council of Nicaea and fought singularly against the madness of Arius.
In his book on the faith, which he published and proposed to be held by all Catholics, he said among other things:
The Father is made by no one, neither created nor begotten.
The Son is from the Father alone; not made, not created, but begotten.
The Holy Spirit is from the Father and the Son, not made, not created, not begotten, but proceeding.
The bishops of the Latins, confirming this truth of faith from the teachings of the doctors, and considering it a defense against the perverse dogma of Arianism, and understanding it to be derived from the holy Scriptures, added to the symbol of faith, saying of the Holy Spirit: Who proceeds from the Father and the Son.
This faith, from the times of Constantine, under whom the Council of Nicaea with 318 bishops was gathered, up to our times, has been held by the Western Church.
Nor has the Catholic Church of the Greeks renounced it, as it did not want to become alien to the doctrine of truth, as declared by their writings.
And now you accuse this faith, moved by some lightness or deceived by some error, I do not know.
Tell me, do you confess that the Holy Spirit is the Spirit of Christ?
If you deny it, the apostle Paul cries out against you, who says: If anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to him (Romans 8:9).
And Luke cries out, who says: And the Spirit of Jesus did not permit them (Acts 16:7).
And Peter cries out: Therefore, being exalted at the right hand of God, he has poured out this which you now see and hear (Acts 2:33).
The Savior himself also cries out, speaking to his disciples: "If I do not go away, the Comforter will not come to you; but if I go, I will send him to you" John sixteen verse seven. Similarly, after the resurrection, he breathed on the disciples and said to them, "Receive the Holy Spirit" John twenty verse twenty-two. All these things affirm that the Holy Spirit is the Spirit of Christ.
Since you cannot deny this, you are compelled by necessity to admit, whether you like it or not, that the Spirit proceeds from the Son. You cannot claim he is a creature like Arius did, or that he does not exist like Macedonius suggested, as your profession states that he proceeds from the Father. When you say this, how can you try to deny that he proceeds from the Son? Since he is of the substance of both the Father and the Son, he cannot be of the substance of both unless he proceeds from both.
Let us hear what Gregory, Bishop of Nazianzus, says in his sermon on the Holy Spirit, which he delivered before the people in the Church of Constantinople on Pentecost:
"The Holy Spirit," he said, "always was, and is, and will be, having neither beginning nor end, but co-eternal with the Father and the Son. For it is not fitting that either the Son should have ever been absent from the Father, or the Spirit from the Son."
By saying that the Holy Spirit is co-eternal with the Father and the Son, he refutes the Arians, who taught that he was a creature. By saying that he always was, and is, and will be, he confutes Macedonius, who denied his existence. But by professing that the Son was never absent from the Father, nor the Spirit from the Son, he refutes you, who deny that the Spirit proceeds from the Son.
If, according to your opinion, the Holy Spirit were to proceed only from the Father, he ought to have said that neither the Son nor the Holy Spirit were ever absent from the Father. But since he says that the Son was never absent from the Father, nor the Spirit from the Son, he clearly speaks of the Son as being born of the Father without any time interval, and the Spirit proceeding from the Son before all time. He did not, however, deny that the Spirit proceeds from the Father, since there was no question about that, but he said that the Spirit was never absent from the Son, which had come into question.
In the following passages, we'll talk about the Spirit:
The Spirit sanctifies but is not sanctified, makes gods but does not become God himself.
He is unchangeable, immutable, always present to himself, the Father, and the Son; invisible, timeless, of his own power, and of all power.
When it is said that he is always present to himself, the Father, and the Son, it does not imply servitude, but rather that he is unchangeable and immutable.
He retains his own nature as well as the essence of the Father and the Son: his own nature because there is no change in him; immutable to the Father and the Son because he shares the same essence as them.
The Holy Spirit is of that same nature.
He is unchangeable and immutable to the Father, who is the source and origin of all things, and to the Son, from whom he proceeds.
He is not unlike the Son, nor of a different essence.
He is said to be of his own power and of all power because he exists in his own person and accomplishes whatever he wills in all creation.
Furthermore, he is life-giving, light and enlightening, good and goodness.
He is the Lord of all, sending apostles and inspiring where he wills, distributing gifts as he wills.
He is the Spirit of truth, the Spirit of wisdom; through whom the Father is known, and the Son is glorified.
We pass over many things, collecting only those that concern the present question.
The Spirit is said to be life, and the Son says of himself: I am the life John 14:6.
The Spirit is said to be life-giving, and the Son says of himself: As the Father gives life to whom he wills, so the Son gives life to whom he wills John 5:21.
Therefore, if the Spirit is life, the Son is also life; and if the Spirit is life-giving, the Son is also life-giving.
They are of one essence and one operation.
But the Son is life from the Father, and the Spirit is life from the Son; thus the Son is life-giving from the Father, and the Spirit is life-giving from the Son.
The Spirit is also light and enlightening, and the Savior says of himself: I am the light of the world John 8:12.
The evangelist John says of the Son: Who enlightens every man coming into this world John 1:9.
Therefore, if both the Son and the Holy Spirit are light and both are illuminating, they share the same substance and operation.
The Holy Spirit receives light and illumination from the Son, as the Son himself testifies: "He will take from what is mine" (John 16:14).
However, He receives not because He lacks, but because He proceeds from the Son.
Similarly, the Spirit is good, and the Son says of Himself: "I am the good shepherd" (John 10:11).
No sane person will deny the goodness of Christ.
Good and good are not two separate goods, but one; just as there are not two gods, but one God.
The Deity does not multiply itself or increase in number.
Therefore, the good Spirit proceeds from the good Son, not by being born, but by proceeding.
If the Spirit proceeds only from the Father and not from the Son, how can the things of the Son also belong to the Spirit?
Or how does the Spirit receive from the Son?
As Saint Gregory says, the Holy Spirit is the Lord of all, demonstrating His omnipotence because He is the Lord of all things created by the Father through the Son, proceeding eternally from both the Father and the Son.
The Holy Spirit is also said to send the apostles, and the Savior tells them: "Behold, I am sending you out as sheep among wolves" (Matthew 10:16).
The operation of both the Son and the Holy Spirit is shown to be one, cooperating with each other.
This makes it clear that they do not consist of different substances, wills, or powers, as their operation is the same in all things.
The Son is referred to the Father, from whom He is born, and the Holy Spirit is referred to the Son, from whom He proceeds.
Blessed Gregory follows by saying of the Spirit: "He blows where he wills; distributing gifts as he wills." And of the Son: "He ascended on high, he took captivity captive, he gave gifts to men" (Ephesians 4:8).
The majesty of the Holy Spirit is shown to be equal to the Father and the Son in nature, greatness, power, and virtue—not subordinate, imperfect, or less powerful.
The Spirit distributes gifts just as the Son does, with the same gifts, at the same time, and to the same people.
This clearly shows the effect of a single operation and the affection of the same will.
The Son cannot be without the Holy Spirit, nor the Holy Spirit without the Son, as both are of one substance, and the Spirit proceeds from the Son.
The Spirit is also called the Spirit of Truth.
The Savior says of Himself: I am the truth (John 14:6).
Therefore, by saying that the Spirit is the Spirit of Truth, it is clearly taught that the Spirit is the Spirit of Christ, who is the truth.
The Holy Spirit is also called the Spirit of Wisdom.
The Apostle Paul testifies that Christ is the power and wisdom of God (First Corinthians 1:24).
Thus, the Spirit of Wisdom is the Spirit of Christ, who is the wisdom of God.
This clearly shows that the Spirit is of Christ by calling it the Spirit of Truth and the Spirit of Wisdom.
Why then is it the Spirit of Christ, if it is the Spirit of the Lord of all, as the blessed Gregory testifies?
Surely because it proceeds from Christ.
If you deny this, you will admit that it is subordinate, and thereby either a creature or lesser than the Son.
Both of these are blasphemous and far removed from Catholic piety.
Therefore, it is said that what truth has is that the Spirit is of Christ; namely, both the Spirit of Truth and the Spirit of Wisdom, because it proceeds from Christ, that is, it proceeds from truth and wisdom.
It is added: Through whom the Father is known, and the Son is glorified, and by whom alone He is known.
The Son also says to the Father: Father, I have made your name known to the people you gave me (John 17:6).
If the Father is known through the Spirit, and the Son manifests the name of the Father to people, they are shown to be of a single operation.
He also says that the Son is glorified by the Holy Spirit, and the Son says:
"It is my Father who glorifies me"
(John 8:54).
And he speaks to the Father:
"Glorify me, Father, with yourself"
(John 17:5).
If the Spirit glorifies the Son, and the Father glorifies the Son, then the Father and the Spirit work as one.
And by working together, they show they have one will, one essence, and one power.
Therefore, if the Holy Spirit is known only by the Father and the Son, he certainly proceeds from both and is consubstantial with both.
Notice how it is said that the Son is glorified by the Spirit, just as the Son glorifies the Father.
But what does it mean to glorify the Father?
It means to make known to humans that he is begotten of the Father.
Similarly, the Son is glorified by the Spirit, showing that he proceeds from the Son.
Therefore, in many ways, the blessed Gregory proves that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son and is of one substance with the Father and the Son.
Concluding, he says:
"What is the need for more words?
All that the Father is, so is the Son, except that the Father is unbegotten.
All that the Son is, so is the Holy Spirit, except that the Son is begotten."
What does this distinction and order of succession mean?
The Son is what the Father is, except that the Father is unbegotten.
The Holy Spirit is what the Son is, except that the Son is begotten.
He could have said, all that the Father is, so is the Son and the Holy Spirit, except that the Father is not begotten, nor proceeds from another.
But now he speaks of the Son being all that the Father is, and the Holy Spirit being all that the Son is, except the privilege of birth.
Evidently speaking thus, he shows that the Father is not from anyone, the Son is begotten only from the Father, and the Spirit proceeds from the Son.
But that he also proceeds from the Father, he said a little earlier, saying:
"And to the first origin of all, who is the Father,
as all things of the Only Begotten, so also all things of the Holy Spirit are referred."
By saying these things, he showed that everything belonging to the Son is connected to the Father, and everything belonging to the Holy Spirit also refers back to the primary origin of all things.
Even though the Spirit proceeds from the Son, the Son received this from the Father, so that by being born from the Father, the Holy Spirit would proceed from him.
So, everything that belongs to the Son belongs to the Father; and everything that belongs to the Holy Spirit also belongs to the Son; and thus to the Father, from whom the Son received that the Holy Spirit would proceed from him—not as created by the Father, but begotten; not diminished, but equal in power; not of another, but of the same nature.
Likewise, in the latter part: Since Jesus came to us in a bodily form, it was fitting that the Spirit should also appear to us in a bodily form.
When Christ ascended to him, he descended to us; he came as the Lord in power, but was sent as one who is not contrary to God.
This teacher showed the unified operation and will of Jesus and the Holy Spirit, indicating that since Jesus came to us in bodily form, it was fitting that the Holy Spirit should also appear to us in bodily form.
This shows the similarity of their will, with the Holy Spirit willing to show himself bodily to mortals because Jesus willed to show his coming bodily to mortals.
Because he proceeds from him, he is also of one will with him; he is not different in action from the Son, from whom he is not separated in nature; and he is always united in action with him, never lacking in coeternity, always cooperating with the one from whom he proceeds.
When he added, "And when Christ ascended to him, he descended to us," he did not want to show the diminution of the Son, but the assumption of humanity. Through this, Jesus ascended not only to the Holy Spirit but also to himself; because he who was made within all things from humanity, through Divinity was above all things.
He added, "Who indeed came as the Lord in power, but was sent as one who is not contrary to God."
Two things are mentioned: the Holy Spirit has come, and He has been sent.
His coming is by His own power, hence it is said, "As the Lord." His being sent indicates He is from another, and it is said, "As one who is not contrary to the one who sends Him." The sending does not imply subordination, but procession.
He is sent by Christ, to whom Christ ascended; and He is sent as not contrary to God, that is, to Christ, who indeed is God, always united to His will. He is sent by Him because He proceeds from Him.
It is added: Therefore, after Christ, so that we may never be without one Advocate, that is, a defender or comforter. He is called another Advocate to recognize the equality of nature and power; for another means another self. Another self refers to someone of the same substance or nature, not someone different.
When Christ is called an Advocate, and the Holy Spirit is likewise called an Advocate, and the Spirit comes when Christ departs, it clearly shows that they have the same role and share the same name. They succeed each other mutually, as they are said to be of the same will and are shown to have the same operation. When Christ ascends, the Spirit descends, clearly sent by Christ, whose place He represents. This sending is a procession, not a diminishment or subjection.
Another, that is another self, is said of the Holy Spirit, demonstrating complete similarity: for another self cannot be said of someone different, but of someone of the same substance or nature. Therefore, it is shown that the Spirit proceeds from Him whose nature or substance He shares. The Spirit cannot be of the same nature or substance as the Son unless He proceeds from Him.
It is also added below: Therefore, God is fire, and the Holy Spirit is fire. It is written that God is a consuming fire, not indeed natural and corporeal, but spiritual and invisible.
So, God the Father is fire, God the Son is fire, and God the Holy Spirit is fire.
But God the Father is fire from no other fire because He takes His origin from no one.
God the Son is fire from the Father because He is born from Him.
And God the Holy Spirit is fire from the Son because He proceeds from the Son.
Therefore, by saying that God is fire and the Holy Spirit is fire, it shows the one substance of the entire Trinity.
He indeed connects the persons of the Father and the Son by saying, "God is fire," and then adds the Holy Spirit by saying, "And the Holy Spirit is fire." But why did he place the persons of the Father and the Son together under the common name of God and prefer to distinguish the Holy Spirit separately? The reason is clear. He wanted to show by such a distinction that the Holy Spirit, who is fire, proceeds from the Father and the Son, who are also fire.
When Saint Gregory discussed such things about the Holy Spirit in the Church of Constantinople and wrote letters proving that the Holy Spirit is consubstantial with the Father and the Son, and proceeds from the Son, without denying or diminishing His procession from the Father, but equating His omnipotence and dominion with the Father and the Son in all things, was he rejected by the Church? Was his speech disapproved? Was he not received into communion by the citizens or the emperor? Certainly, this venerable doctor lived during the times of the Roman emperors Gratian and Theodosius the Great.
Since then, more than 500 years have passed up to our times, and never was the procession of the Holy Spirit from the Son denied, nor was there any question among Catholics about this, except in your times now. Indeed, the profession of faith regarding the Holy Spirit remained the same and similar in both the Eastern and Western Churches. What has now caused this question to arise after so many centuries, you should see; however, there is no reason of either integrity or wisdom to justify why you have come to this, because by saying such things, you oppose the Catholic faith, resist the truth, and go against the holy scriptures.
Chapter Four
From Ambrose
Ambrose, the Bishop of Milan, a man adorned with the splendor of all virtues, fought many battles against the Arians and suffered many persecutions from them.
In the books he eloquently wrote on the Holy Spirit against Arian heresy and supported with the truth of the Gospel, he says (Book 1 on the Holy Spirit, Chapter 3):
"If you speak of Christ, you have indicated both God the Father, from whom the Son was anointed, and the Son Himself who was anointed, and the Spirit who anointed Him.
And if you speak of the Father, you have equally indicated His Son and the Spirit of His mouth, if you also comprehend this in your heart.
And if you speak of the Spirit, you have indicated both God the Father, from whom the Spirit proceeds, and the Son, because the Spirit is also of the Son."
Blessed Ambrose teaches that when one of them is named, whether the Father, the Son, or the Holy Spirit, the entire Trinity is comprehended, showing such a similarity of equality in the three that one term encompasses the three persons, although not by the distinction of voice, yet by the equality of unity.
As for his statement that the Spirit proceeds from the Father, there is no question here; for you agree with us on this.
But when he says that when the Son is named, the Spirit is also named because the Spirit is of the Son, here we are divided from you.
For you who refuse to profess that the Spirit proceeds from the Son also refuse to say that the Spirit is of the Son: for if He does not proceed from Him, it is not rightly said that He is His Spirit.
But He is called the Spirit of the Father because He proceeds from the Father.
Therefore, when the Son is named, the Holy Spirit is not simultaneously understood; for it cannot be shown that He is comprehended by the name of one of whom He is not the Spirit.
However, holy Ambrose says that the Spirit is of the Son, thus He proceeds from the Son.
In the following, he speaks similarly:
"He who denies the Holy Spirit also denies God the Father and the Son: for the Spirit of God is the same as the Spirit of Christ: no one should doubt that there is one Spirit."
The unity and consubstantiality of the Spirit with the Father and the Son is evident when it says: whoever denies the Spirit also denies the Father and the Son equally, because there is one Spirit of both.
It is from the Father, because it proceeds from the Father, and equally from the Son, because it proceeds from the Son.
It is not two Spirits, but one Spirit.
It is not said to be the Spirit of the Father and another Spirit of the Son, but one Spirit from both; therefore, it proceeds from both.
In Chapter 10, it states: the Spirit is not sent from a place, nor does it proceed from a place when it proceeds from the Son.
The Son himself says, "I came from the Father and have come." He clearly testifies that the Spirit proceeds from the Son. To ensure this procession is not measured by physical spaces, the Son excludes this notion by saying of the Father, "I came from the Father and have come" (John 8:42).
The Son proceeds from the Father, not by spatial distance, but by the exit of birth.
The Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, neither by spatial distance nor by the exit of birth, but by the process of existence.
When speaking about the procession of the Son from the Father, it is said: neither does he depart from a place when he exits from the Father, nor are they separated like a body from a body.
When he is with the Father, he is not enclosed as a body within a body.
Similarly, the Holy Spirit, when proceeding from the Father and the Son, is not separated from the Father, nor is he separated from the Son.
This chief teacher and renowned confessor of Christ, by saying that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and also from the Son, prevented the Arians he was disputing against from blaspheming.
He ensured that those who claimed the Spirit was a creature and lesser not only than the Father but also than the Son, would not prevail.
By hearing that the Spirit proceeds from both, they would understand the Spirit to be consubstantial with the Father and the Son, and equally worthy of worship and glorification with them.
Later, it testifies to the Son saying: "Whoever loves me will keep my word; and my Father will love him, and we will come to him and make our home with him" (John 14:23).
The Spirit comes just as the Father comes; because where the Father is, there is also the Son; and where the Son is, there is also the Holy Spirit.
What does it mean when it says that where the Father is, there is also the Son, if not that the Son is born from the Father, from whom He is never separated?
And what does it mean where the Son is, there is also the Holy Spirit?
It means that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, from whom He is never separated, showing the ineffable shared essence of the entire Trinity.
It testifies that the Son is always in the Father, and the Holy Spirit is always in the Son.
So, where the Father is, there is also the Son; and where the Son is, there is also the Holy Spirit, not divided by place, time, will, action, or essence.
Later, in chapter 12: Just as the Father gave the Son, and the Son gave Himself, understand that the Holy Spirit gave Him.
For it is written: Then Jesus was led by the Spirit into the desert to be tempted by the devil (Matthew 4).
Therefore, the Spirit lovingly gave the Son: for there is one love of the Father and the Son.
When it says there is one love of the Father and the Son, it testifies that there is one Spirit of both; for the Spirit is love.
The Apostle says: For the fruit of the Spirit is love (Galatians 5:22).
Therefore, it is shown that the Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son, whose love it is: for the love of the Father cannot exist unless it proceeds from the Father; because He does not receive love from elsewhere.
Nor can the love of the Son exist unless it proceeds from the Son: in the way that love loves, it proceeds from Him.
As there is one love of the Father and the Son, there is one Spirit proceeding from both.
In the second book, chapter 12, it says: The Holy Spirit received from the Son.
However, He received through the unity of substance, just as the Son received from the Father.
By saying this, it clearly teaches that the Holy Spirit received from the Son.
And what He received, He received by proceeding, just as the Son received from the Father by being born.
Could the Holy Spirit have received anything from the Son that it did not have before, since it is of the same substance and possesses the same power as the Son?
Whatever the Son has, the Holy Spirit also has.
Saint Ambrose adds a testimony from the Gospel: He says, "He will glorify me, because he will take from what is mine and declare it to you. All things that the Father has are mine; therefore I said that he will take from what is mine and declare it to you" (John 16:14).
He follows with: What could be clearer evidence of this unity?
What the Father has belongs to the Son; what the Son has, the Spirit has also received.
These words of Saint Ambrose clearly show that the Holy Spirit proceeds substantially from the Son.
He says: What the Father has belongs to the Son, that is, being substantially born of the Father, what is the Father's is also the Son's.
Similarly, the Holy Spirit, substantially proceeding from the Son, has received from the Son, so that whatever the Son has, the Spirit also has, that is, it is of the same substance as the Son, just as the Son is of the same substance as the Father.
Moreover, in the following: What the Son speaks, the Father speaks; and what the Father speaks, the Son speaks: and concerning the Spirit, the Son of God said: For he does not speak from himself, that is, not without my and the Father's communion (for the Spirit is not divided or separated), but he speaks what he hears (John 16:13): evidently hearing through the unity of substance and the property of knowledge.
While this Catholic teacher confesses that the Holy Spirit does not speak without the communion of the Father and the Son, it is evident that when the Spirit speaks, the Father speaks, and the Son speaks.
This testifies that the Spirit is consubstantial with the Father and the Son, and of the same operation, neither divided nor separated.
And what he added: He speaks what he hears, implies his procession: for the Spirit does not hear the speech of the Father and the Son through certain intervening spaces or some openings, since he is of the same substance.
And just as the Son says: "All things that I have heard from my Father, I have made known to you" (John 15:15).
By being born from the Father and remaining in the Father's substance, not by receiving the Father's speech at intervals: just as the Spirit speaks what He hears, proceeding from the Father and the Son, because He remains substantially in both, and proceeds from both, He hears what He speaks through the unity of substance and the property of knowledge.
The Son has everything from the Father, who said, "All that the Father has is mine" John sixteen, fifteen. What He received through the unity of nature, the Spirit received from Him through the same unity.
As the Lord Jesus Himself declares about His Spirit, saying: "Therefore I said, He will take what is mine and declare it to you" John sixteen, fourteen.
Saying that the Son has everything from the Father, and that the Spirit received everything from the Son through the unity of nature from the Father, doesn't He clearly declare that the Son is born from the Father, that is from the Father's substance, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, that is from the Son's substance?
Just as the Son received everything that belongs to the Father by being born, so too, the Holy Spirit, proceeding from the Son, received whatever belongs to the Son.
Therefore, what the Spirit speaks is from the Son; what the Son gave is from the Father.
So, if what the Spirit speaks is from the Son, this teacher clearly testifies that whatever the Spirit has, He received from the Son, because He proceeds from Him; and if what the Son gave is from the Father, to whom did He give it?
Surely to the Holy Spirit who proceeds from Him: and if what He gave is from the Father, the Son received it from the Father by being born, so that the Holy Spirit proceeds from Him.
He added: Thus, neither the Son nor the Spirit speaks anything on their own, because the Trinity speaks nothing outside itself.
The whole Trinity consists in the Father, the Son, and the Spirit.
However, the Son speaks nothing on His own, because He is not from Himself, but from the Father.
Similarly, the Spirit speaks nothing on His own, because He is not from Himself, but from the Son: only the Father is from no one.
Therefore, when the Son speaks, the whole Trinity speaks; and when the Spirit speaks, the whole Trinity speaks; and when the Father speaks, the whole Trinity speaks.
The Trinity speaks nothing outside itself, as it is neither divided nor separated from itself.
Also, in the third book of the same work, Chapter 1:
According to divinity, the Spirit is not above Christ but in Christ.
Just as the Father is in the Son, and the Son is in the Father, the Spirit of God and the Spirit of Christ are in the Father and the Son.
Blessed Ambrose, by saying that according to divinity the Spirit is not above Christ but in Christ, distinguishes Christ's humanity from His divinity.
In the Gospel, we read that the Holy Spirit came upon the Savior and remained upon Him; and the Father speaks to John: "The one on whom you see the Spirit descending and remaining on Him" (John 1:33).
Therefore, according to humanity, the Spirit came upon Christ and remained on Him; but according to divinity, the Spirit remains in Christ because He is equal to Him, sharing both substances with Him.
As it is written about the Father, He remains in the Son, and the Son in the Father.
The statement that the Spirit of God and the Spirit of Christ remain in the Father or the Son testifies to the unity of both Spirits, as they proceed from both and remain through consubstantiality in both.
He added: "For He remains in God, because He is from God," as it is written: "We have not received the spirit of this world, but the Spirit who is from God" (First Corinthians 2:12); and He remains in Christ because He received from Christ and is in Christ.
It is written again: "He will take from what is mine" (John 16:14).
So, where is the Spirit from God?
Clearly, because He proceeds from God.
And where did He receive from Christ?
Certainly, because He proceeds from Christ.
And where does He remain both in God and in Christ?
Absolutely, because He is consubstantial with both.
In the following chapters 7 and 8, speaking of the Antichrist, it says: "Whom the Lord Jesus will kill with the Spirit of His mouth" (Second Thessalonians 2:8).
Here, grace is not acquired, but unity remains indivisible; because neither can Christ be without the Spirit, nor can the Spirit be without Christ.
For the unity of the divine nature cannot be separated.
Saint Ambrose also discusses the relationship between the humanity and divinity of Christ.
He clarifies that Christ isn't two separate beings—one human and one divine—but rather one perfect God and perfect human.
As a human, Christ became God by grace, but as God, He exists by nature.
When Saint Ambrose said, "Whom the Lord Jesus will kill with the Spirit of His mouth," he emphasized that this grace is not acquired, thus highlighting the divine nature. The Spirit of the mouth that will destroy the Antichrist is understood to be the Holy Spirit, who is a person of the Holy Trinity. So, when he said, "Whom the Lord Jesus will kill with the Spirit of His mouth," it refers to the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of the Lord Jesus.
It's also important to note that when it is said that the Spirit is the Spirit of the mouth of the Lord and now the Spirit of the mouth of the Lord Jesus, it clearly shows that the Holy Spirit proceeds from Jesus as well. This doesn't mean Jesus has a physical mouth in His divine nature, but that the Spirit proceeds from His substance. Just as the Spirit of the mouth of the Lord proceeds from the Father's substance, it is evident that the Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son, as He is the Spirit of both.
Blessed Ambrose continues, showing that the unity of Christ and the Spirit remains indivisible. Neither Christ can be without the Spirit, nor the Spirit without Christ. Christ cannot be without the Spirit because He is consubstantial with Him, and the Spirit proceeds from Him. Similarly, the Spirit cannot be without Christ, as He is consubstantial with Christ and has received everything from Him. This emphasizes that the unity of the divine nature cannot be separated.
By saying this, he acknowledges that the nature of Christ is the nature of the Spirit, and the nature of the Spirit is the nature of Christ.
The bond of unity cannot be separated in any way, except that the Son is born, and the Spirit proceeds.
These do not create substance, but demonstrate a relationship.
He further explains: It is written that the sword of the Word is the Spirit.
Similarly, it is written that the sword of the Holy Spirit is the Word of God Ephesians 6:17.
After considering some assumptions, he concludes: Therefore, since the sword of the Word is the Holy Spirit, and the sword of the Holy Spirit is the Word, there is indeed a unity of power.
But what is the sword of the Word if not the Word itself?
And what is the sword of the Spirit if not the Spirit itself?
From this, we gather that the Holy Spirit is the Spirit of the Word, whose sword it is, and the Word is the Spirit of the Holy Spirit, whose sword it is.
Neither the Word can be without the Holy Spirit, nor the Holy Spirit without the Word, because they operate as one and share the same power.
Since this is so, they cannot be separated in substance, nor divided in will.
Therefore, the Son and the Holy Spirit, being of one substance and one will, proceed from one another.
The Spirit proceeds from the Son, since the Son, born of the Father, gave everything he received by being born from the Father to the Spirit, not as to one lesser, nor as to an outsider, but as to one proceeding from himself.
However, it must be noted that when it is said that the sword of the Holy Spirit is the Word, and the sword of the Word is the Holy Spirit, it does not imply a union of persons, but rather shows the coupling of substance, so that they are of one substance, though they are not one person.
One is from the other, namely the Spirit from the Son, but not the Son from the Spirit, but from the Father.
In this way, Saint Ambrose, in his reflections and debates on the Holy Spirit, did not appear ungrateful or heretical to the Greek emperors, namely Gratian and Theodosius the Great, in whose times he flourished.
They loved the holy man with all their hearts and always held him in the highest veneration.
His debates and tireless work for the Catholic faith defeated, conquered, and suppressed the Arians attacking the Church.
Now, listen, you emperors who strive to either defend the faith or imitate religion: by denying that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, you have opposed Catholic bishops who have overthrown the Arians with their misguided beliefs about the Holy Spirit.
You have overturned the piety of your ancestors—namely, the Roman emperors—who always upheld this faith, fought for it, and cherished it with great reverence.
Chapter Five
From Didymus.
Didymus of Alexandria, who was blinded from childhood but known for his spiritual insight, speaks in his book on the Holy Spirit as follows:
Whoever shares in the Holy Spirit immediately shares in both the Father and the Son.
And whoever has the love of the Father receives it from the Son through the Holy Spirit; and whoever partakes in the grace of Jesus Christ receives that same grace from the Father through the Holy Spirit.
From all of this, we see that the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit work together as one.
Let’s examine this carefully.
He says: Whoever shares in the Holy Spirit, and someone shares in the Spirit by partaking in Him, immediately shares in both the Father and the Son: for they have become a partaker of both the Father and the Son through sharing in the Spirit.
This shows that the Spirit is of the same essence as the Father and the Son, and so united that one cannot have the Spirit without also having the Father and the Son.
He adds: Whoever has the love of the Father receives it from the Son through the Holy Spirit.
Earlier, he showed only the consubstantiality of the Father and the Son, but now he begins to teach about the procession of the Spirit.
He calls the love of the Father the Holy Spirit, as shown by what follows, saying it is given through the Holy Spirit.
The Holy Spirit does not give anything but His own gift when He gives love.
And it is written that love is God; therefore, when the Spirit gives love, He gives Himself, because He is love: but this love is said to be of the Father, because the Spirit is the Spirit of the Father.
And why is He the Spirit of the Father?
Because He proceeds from Him, not as one of the creatures, but as of the same substance as the Father.
Therefore, He is not said to be of the Father as created by Him, but as of the same substance and proceeding from Him.
He says that having the love of the Father is given by the Son through the Holy Spirit: so how does the Son give the gift of the Holy Spirit?
Clearly, as a collaborator with the Father and the Spirit.
But how can one give oneself an equal, or the gift of another, that is, the Holy Spirit?
Certainly, because love, which is from the Father and shared by the Son through the Holy Spirit, is also from the Son.
Whatever belongs to the Father also belongs to the Son.
But is the love, which is the Holy Spirit, so much the Son's, that it is a creature?
Not at all; rather, it is given by the Son because it proceeds from Him, and it is the Son's because it is consubstantial with Him.
It is added: And who is a partaker of the grace of Jesus Christ.
Here, he calls the grace of Jesus Christ what he previously called the love of the Father.
But what is it that he now calls the grace of Jesus Christ, known to be the gift of the Holy Spirit?
Without a doubt, he shows that it is shared by Jesus Christ, whose grace it is.
Just as the love of the Father is said to proceed from the Father, so the same love, called the grace of Jesus Christ, is known to proceed from Jesus Christ.
However, anyone who has this same grace of Christ says it is given to him through the Holy Spirit.
Indeed, we see the whole Trinity working together and understand that the Holy Spirit, who is the love of the Father and the Son, proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
It follows: From all these things, it is clear that the same operation belongs to the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
For those whose operation is the same, their will is also one.
And those whose will is one, their substance is one.
Hence, it is added: For those whose operation is one, their substance is also one.
Because those of the same substance are homousious, they have the same operations.
And those of another substance are dissonant and diverse.
This shows that the Holy Spirit is of one substance with the Father and the Son, because it has the same operation with them.
It has been shown above that the Spirit is from the Father and the Son, because it proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
In the latter, it is said: For when he said, at the time of answering, undoubtedly the Son, that the disciples would be taught by the Spirit what they ought to answer, it follows: For I will give you a wisdom which none of your adversaries will be able to resist or contradict.
Luke 21:15.
This demonstrates that the wisdom given to the disciples by the Son is the wisdom of the Holy Spirit, and that the teaching of the Holy Spirit is the teaching of the Lord.
But how is the wisdom given by the Son also the wisdom of the Holy Spirit?
It's because the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, whose wisdom is also that of the Holy Spirit.
And how can the teaching of the Holy Spirit be considered the teaching of the Lord?
It's because everything that belongs to the Holy Spirit also belongs to the Lord Jesus Christ, since it proceeds from Him.
Thus, it is stated: There is a unity of nature and will between the Spirit and the Son.
This testifies that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, as the Spirit shares the same nature and will with the Son.
Otherwise, if the Spirit did not proceed from Him, it would not share the same will as the Son, since things that are separated in partnership are also separated in will.
It is also stated: And because it has been previously demonstrated that the Spirit is naturally united with the Only Begotten God and God the Father: the Son and the Father are one, according to the statement:
"I and the Father are one" (John 10:30); the Trinity is shown to be undivided and inseparable according to nature.
If the Spirit is naturally united with the Only Begotten God and God the Father, then it proceeds from the Only Begotten God.
If it only proceeds from God the Father and not from the Only Begotten God, it is united with the Father by nature, but not with the Only Begotten God: for it cannot be united by nature to Him from whom it does not proceed.
But the author testifies that the Spirit is naturally united with the Only Begotten God:
therefore, he acknowledges that the Spirit proceeds from the Only Begotten God.
And because he states that the Trinity is undivided and inseparable according to nature, he acknowledges that the Son is begotten of the Father, and the Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
If you teach that the Spirit only proceeds from the Father, then the Trinity is no longer undivided and inseparable, because the Spirit is divided from the Son, from whom it does not proceed: it is separated from the Only Begotten, whose Spirit it is not.
It is far from the belief of the Catholic Church to hold this impious opinion:
the Holy Trinity is undivided and inseparable by nature; the Father is from no one,
the Son is begotten from the Father, and the Holy Spirit proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
Another Gospel states:
"For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father speaking through you"
(Matthew 10:20).
So, if the Spirit of the Father speaks through the apostles, teaching them what to say,
and what is taught by the Spirit is wisdom, which we recognize as the Son,
it clearly shows that the Spirit shares the same nature with the Son and the Father, whose Spirit He is.
Furthermore, the Father and the Son are one.
The author says that the wisdom the Spirit of the Father teaches the apostles
is the Son.
If the wisdom is the Son, and the Holy Spirit speaks this wisdom, which is the Son, through the apostles,
He receives it from the Son.
But how does He receive it?
Certainly by proceeding, not by participating in something He did not have before:
for there was never a time when the Spirit lacked wisdom.
He received it from the Son to always be wise, proceeding from Him;
because He shares the same nature with both the Son and the Father, whose Spirit He is:
which he also referred to as the Spirit of the Son; whose wisdom the Spirit speaks, but as he mentioned earlier:
"For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father" (Matthew 10:20).
He further states: The Father and the Son are one.
If the Father and the Son are one, then the Spirit, who is of the Father,
is also of the Son; and therefore, He proceeds from both.
After discussing many aspects of the consubstantiality of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, he concluded:
From these points, it is clear, although the substance of the Trinity is undivided, that the Father is truly the Father of the Son,
and the Son is truly the Son of the Father, and the Holy Spirit is truly the Spirit of the Father and of God;
and moreover, the Spirit of wisdom and truth, that is, the Son of God.
If the Father is the Father of the Son because He begot Him, and the Son is the Son of the Father because He was begotten by Him, and the Holy Spirit is truly the Spirit of the Father because He proceeds from Him, then He is also the Spirit of wisdom and truth.
In other words, He is the Spirit of the Son of God because He proceeds from the Son, from truth, from wisdom, and from God, which is the Son.
For this reason, when it was said that the Holy Spirit is the Spirit of truth, it was added that He is the Spirit of God, intending to be understood as the person of the Son.
To avoid any confusion, it was later clarified that the Spirit of wisdom and truth is indeed the Son of God.
Later, it was stated: We have frequently shown that the Spirit operates in the same way as the Father and the Son.
There is one substance in this operation, and the operation of those who share the same essence is not different.
The Spirit's operation is the same as that of the Father and the Son because He is consubstantial with both, proceeding from both.
He cannot be part of the same operation if He does not proceed from both.
The substance is divided among those from whom it does not proceed coherently, and He cannot be substantially united to either the Father or the Son in any other way, because as substance, the Spirit is received from both the Father and the Son by proceeding.
Furthermore, in discussing the Spirit of truth who is sent by the Father, if He is the Comforter, the Savior said: For He does not speak from Himself (John 16:13); that is, without me, and without my and the Father's will; because He is inseparable from my and the Father's will.
For this very reason, He subsists and speaks from the Father and me.
I speak the truth, that is, I inspire what He speaks, since He is the Spirit of truth.
Clearly, this teacher instructs us that the Holy Spirit comes from the Son.
When he says, "He does not speak on His own," he shows that the Spirit is not acting independently. Explaining further, he says, "This means without me, and without my and the Father's will," indicating that the Spirit comes from both the Father and the Son, and does not act without their will.
By saying, "For this very thing which exists and speaks, I, the truth, speak," he shows that the Spirit's existence is from the Son. If, when the Spirit speaks, the truth speaks—that is, the Son—it demonstrates that what the Spirit communicates comes from the Son. Emphasizing this point more clearly, he adds, "I inspire what He speaks."
How does He inspire? Clearly, since the Spirit proceeds from Him and connects. Indeed, He is the Spirit of truth, which means He is the Spirit of the Son. All these points demonstrate that the Spirit is from the Son and is inspired by the Son, meaning He proceeds from Him. And since what the Spirit speaks and the Spirit's very existence come from the Son, it shows they are consubstantial and the Spirit proceeds from Him.
Therefore, the Father speaks, and the Son hears; or conversely, the Son speaks, and the Father hears. This signifies the same nature in the Father and the Son and their agreement. The Holy Spirit, who is the Spirit of truth and the Spirit of wisdom, cannot hear something the Son says without already knowing it, as it is expressed by the Son.
Saying that the Father speaks and is heard by the Son demonstrates the Son's origin from the Father. Similarly, when the Son speaks and is heard by the Father, it implies that He was begotten by the Father. Because the Father and the Son share the same nature, they are also in complete agreement. So, when the Father speaks to the Son or the Son speaks to the Father, it reflects a unified will and harmony.
The Holy Spirit, also known as the Spirit of Truth and the Spirit of Wisdom, is acknowledged as the Spirit of the Son.
It's said that He cannot hear anything from the Son that He doesn't already know because, being of the same substance as the Son and proceeding from the Son, what the Son speaks, the Holy Spirit also speaks.
The Spirit is essentially the utterance of the Son, as explained by the current teacher.
After stating that the Holy Spirit cannot hear anything from the Son that He doesn't know, it follows that the Spirit is the very thing that is spoken by the Son.
In other words, the utterance of the Son is the substance of the Spirit.
For it is said that since He is the very thing spoken, it is understood as the Spirit; what is spoken by the Son is what the Son speaks.
If what the Son speaks is the Holy Spirit, as this teacher asserts, it cannot be denied that the Spirit proceeds from the Son.
Indeed, the utterance of the Son proceeds from the Son.
Therefore, since the Spirit is the same as what is spoken by the Son, the Spirit entirely proceeds from the Son.
It adds: Finally, lest anyone should separate Him from the will and fellowship of the Father and the Son, it is written: For He will not speak on His own, but will speak only what He hears (John 16:13).
Similarly, the Savior says about Himself: I judge only as I hear (John 5:30).
The will of the Father is the will of the Son, and the fellowship of both is the Spirit of both, because love, which is the Spirit, unites the will of the Father and the Son.
Nor can the will of the Spirit be separated from the will of the Father and the Son; just as there is the fellowship of both, so there is the same will of both.
And just as the will of the Son is born from the Father, so the will of the Spirit proceeds from the Son.
Hence it is said about the Spirit: For He will not speak on His own, but will speak only what He hears.
From whom does He hear?
Clearly from the Son, from whom He proceeds.
And to hear the Spirit is to proceed from the Son, just as to hear the Son is to be born from the Father.
For to hear the Son and to be born are not different, but the same.
Likewise, to hear the Spirit and to proceed are not different, but one and the same.
And below: It is written: Whatever he does (no doubt the Father), the Son does likewise.
So, if the Father and the Son are working, not in the order of first and second, but at the same time doing the same and similar things, everything that is made exists: and the Son cannot do anything by himself because he cannot be separated from the Father.
Similarly, the Holy Spirit is in no way separated from the Son, because of the sharing of will and nature, and he is believed not to speak by himself; but according to the word and truth of God, he speaks everything.
The Father and the Son do the same works, not at one time the Father and another time the Son, but at the same time together: and the Son cannot work separately, because he is not divided from the Father, since he is born from the Father and of the same substance as the Father: likewise, the Holy Spirit does not speak by himself separated from the Son; because proceeding from the Son, he shares the nature of the Son: and the will is the same as the Son's: for the will does not separate those whom nature joins, but according to the word and truth of God, he speaks everything; because proceeding from the word and truth, he understands what he speaks: for what proceeds is not different from the understanding of speaking, but the understanding of speaking is the existence of the proceeding, just as the proceeding of existence is the understanding of speaking.
And below: Just as we understood above when discussing incorporeal natures, so now we must understand that the Holy Spirit receives from the Son what is of his own nature, and this does not indicate a giver and a receiver, but one substance.
Indeed, the Son is also said to receive the same from the Father, which he himself subsists as: for the Son is not anything else except what is given to him by the Father, nor is the substance of the Holy Spirit anything other than what is given to him by the Son.
He confirms that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son and states that the Holy Spirit receives from the Son what is of His own nature.
This means that the nature of the Spirit comes from the Son, and receiving the Spirit from the Son is the same as proceeding from the Son.
He explains that the giver and the receiver should not be understood as being of different substances.
Instead, the Son gives so that the Spirit exists, and the Spirit receives so that it proceeds from the Son.
He supports his view with the fact that the Son is said to receive from the Father.
The Son is not different from what He receives from the Father; rather, the Son's reception from the Father is His existence.
He further clarifies this by stating that the Son is nothing other than what is given to Him by the Father.
This means it is not permissible to separate what the Father gives to the Son from the substance of the Son, because the substance given by the Father is the Son’s, as He received everything that belongs to the Father through His birth.
Similarly, he acknowledges that the Holy Spirit does not have a different substance apart from what is given to Him by the Son.
The Holy Spirit is not different from what the Son gives to the Spirit; the gift of the Son is the substance of the Holy Spirit.
This clearly shows that the Holy Spirit is from the Son, not as a part, but as the whole, which is the Son; because whatever belongs to the Son also belongs to the Holy Spirit.
The Holy Spirit receives from the Son, proceeding from Him as consubstantial, and having everything that belongs to the Son.
Later on, he explains how he said, "He will take from what is mine," and immediately added, "Everything that the Father has is mine; that is why I said, ‘He will take from what is mine and declare it to you’" (John chapter 16, verses 13 and 14).
In a way, he is saying that although the Spirit of truth proceeds from the Father, and God gives the Holy Spirit to those who ask Him, nevertheless, because everything the Father has is mine, and this very Spirit of the Father is mine, He will take from what is mine.
This statement teaches that the Spirit proceeds from the Son, just as it proceeds from the Father.
It is the Spirit of truth, specifically of Christ, who embodies the truth.
Because the Son has everything that belongs to the Father, this very Spirit of the Father testifies that it is from the Son and receives from the Son.
What does it receive?
It receives its existence by proceeding from Him.
Consequently, the same Spirit is of God and of Christ, bringing and uniting those who have it to the Lord Jesus Christ.
Hence, it is later said:
"But if anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to Him" (Romans 8:9).
If it is the Spirit of God, it is also the Spirit of Christ, as the author confirms.
There is no doubt that there are not two Spirits, one of the Father and one of the Son, but one and the same of both.
And if the Spirit of Christ is the same as the Spirit of God the Father, just as it proceeds from the Father, so it proceeds from the Son.
It is not otherwise called the Spirit of God the Father, except that it proceeds from God the Father.
So it is not otherwise called the Spirit of Christ, except because it proceeds from Christ.
For it is not a creature, to be possessed as inferior, but consubstantial.
Thus, when he adds that not having the Spirit of Christ means not being of Christ, he acknowledges that it proceeds from Christ.
Nor can one be of Christ who does not have His Spirit.
For in whom there is not the Spirit of Christ, there is not Christ.
They are not separated by habitation, who are united by substance.
Hence, we learn that the relationship the Spirit has with Christ, it also has with God the Father.
For it cannot lack the relationship with those to whom it is consubstantial and from whom it exists.
Further below: In the Epistle of Peter, the Holy Spirit is proven to be the Spirit of Christ:
searching and inquiring (that is, the prophets about whom he had spoken earlier) into what or what kind of time the Spirit of Christ in them was indicating, testifying beforehand the sufferings of Christ and the glories that would follow.
And shortly after:
This Holy Spirit is called the Spirit of God, as it says: No one knows the things of God except the Spirit of God First Corinthians 2:11.
Therefore, he acknowledges the Spirit of Christ, who is the Spirit of God, and thus proceeds from both; because there is no other reason why it is called the Spirit of both: for it is equal and of the same substance.
Again, it speaks below: If anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to him Romans 8:9.
And it continues: But if Christ is in you Romans 8:10.
It very clearly shows that the Holy Spirit is inseparable from Christ; because wherever the Spirit is, there also is Christ: and wherever the Spirit of Christ departs, likewise Christ departs.
This union of the Spirit and Christ, which it teaches, is not only of will, but also of substance, and not only of substance, but also of procession: for things that are separate in substance can be united by will; as when Christ speaks to the disciples: Behold, I am with you all the days Matthew 28:20; or as he said in the present passage, where the Spirit of Christ is, there also is Christ.
In those in whom the Spirit of Christ is, Christ also is equally present: they are together indeed, but by will, not by substance.
For God and man are not of one, but of different substances.
Again, they can be united in substance, and also joined by birth, as the Father and the Son.
Again, they are united in substance, not by birth, but by procession, the Son and the Spirit.
Therefore, when he says, wherever the Spirit is, there also is Christ; and wherever the Spirit of Christ departs, likewise Christ departs, he shows this union not only of will and substance, but also of procession; that the Spirit is not only of the same substance as Christ, but also proceeds from him.
Again, taking up the Apostle's testimony later, he says: You have not received a spirit of slavery to fall back into fear Romans.
Romans 8:15 tells us that we refrain from vices, not like servants out of fear and terror of punishments, but because we have been given the Spirit of adoption—the Holy Spirit, also known as the Spirit of the Son, Christ, truth, and wisdom.
What does this mean?
Truth and wisdom are Christ, as the Scripture confirms multiple times.
Christ is undoubtedly the Son of the Father, which affirms the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, from Christ, from truth and wisdom.
They are not different Spirits but the same substance.
Wisdom, truth, and Christ proclaim the Son.
Christ represents the human nature He assumed; He is truth because He said, "I am the truth." He is wisdom as Paul testifies in First Corinthians 1:30, that He was made wisdom for us by God.
What do these points conclude? Without a doubt, the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, whose Spirit He is said to be. He cannot be a part of or subject to the Son. So, where does He come from? By procession or consubstantiality. Consubstantiality shows equality, and equality is not subjected but conferred. Therefore, the Spirit of the Son undoubtedly proceeds from the Son.
These points, briefly collected from the book of Didymus, should suffice. In Alexandria, holding such views about the Holy Spirit, neither the Greeks nor the emperors censured or suspended Didymus from communion. The emperors, reigning not only in Constantinople but also in Rome, understood that this was a Catholic doctrine—the apostolic faith—defeating heretic perfidy and affirming the doctrine of truth.
Now, modern emperors, establishing a new sect of error, consider whose faith you hold and who taught you the doctrine of Christ. You are shown not to be disciples of your predecessors who strengthened the Catholic faith and fought against false doctrines.
Chapter Six
From Paschasius.
Let's explore what the Roman Church thought about the Holy Spirit during those times, to prove that the teaching he preaches is not a new sect, but one that has long been endorsed by the Fathers, upheld throughout the entire body of the Church, and opposed to those who think differently.
We will show that it is wrongly criticized as if it were a new doctrine, when it has always been preached by our predecessors.
Paschasius, an ancient teacher and deacon of the Roman see, following in the footsteps of Didymus of Alexandria, writes in his little book on the Holy Spirit (Book 1, Chapter 2):
"Do not probe into how God exists, whom it is clear exists as God.
Here the reasoning is hidden, the truth is not hidden.
Why do you ask how He is the companion and equal of the King, whom it is established is of royal honor and lineage?
The inquiry about the name is superfluous, where there is no doubt about the sublimity."
This is against the Arians, who denied the divinity of the Holy Spirit, unwilling to confess Him as consubstantial with the Father and the Son, but claimed He was a creature subject to the Son, as if lesser.
Truly refuting them, he preaches that the Holy Spirit is true God and consubstantial with the Father and the Son.
He also clarifies what he believes about the procession by adding:
"Therefore, since the Holy Spirit proceeds from both, he says: 'But if anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, they do not belong to Christ' (Romans 8:9).
And in another place: 'He breathed on them and said, 'Receive the Holy Spirit''" (John 20:22).
He bears witness that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son; he strengthens his assertion both from the Apostle and from the Gospel, equally showing that the Spirit cannot be of Christ unless He proceeds from Him.
Nor does Christ otherwise give the Spirit by breathing, except by sending Him from His own substance, since when He is called the Spirit of Christ, He is shown to have a relation to Christ, not as a servant (for He is not a creature), but as receiving existence by proceeding from Him, not by being created or generated.
Similarly, when he breathes into him by sending, he does not send a stranger, nor from anywhere other than his own nature.
The process from the Son cannot be denied, as it is from the depths of his divinity that he sends.
He further adds, speaking of the same Spirit: Are you asking whether he is begotten or unbegotten?
The holy scriptures have said nothing about this, and it is wrong to break the divine silence.
What God did not indicate in his scriptures, he did not want you to inquire about or know out of unnecessary curiosity.
He judged that what pertains to your salvation should reach your conscience.
He speaks against those who, disparaging the person of the Holy Spirit in the Holy Trinity, did not accept that he is God.
They argue that if he were considered God, he would have to be either begotten or unbegotten.
If begotten, there would be two sons, and the Savior could no longer be called the only-begotten.
This would contradict the Catholic faith, which confesses belief in God the Father Almighty and in Jesus Christ, his only-begotten Son.
Conversely, if he were confessed as unbegotten, there would be two Fathers, which also contradicts the Catholic faith.
For we believe in one God the Father Almighty.
To those contriving such perverse ideas, this Catholic teacher replies piously and cautiously, stating that the Holy Spirit should be called neither begotten nor unbegotten, as the holy scriptures do not speak of this.
Instead, it should be professed what they affirm, namely that the Holy Spirit is consubstantial with the Father and the Son, and proceeds from both.
In later writings, it is said: In the Acts of the Apostles, Peter, speaking of the Lord Jesus Christ, says: Therefore, being exalted by the right hand of God, and having received the promise of the Holy Spirit from the Father, he poured out what you see and hear.
Acts 2:33.
The Son is at the right hand, the Father is in God, and the Holy Spirit is designated by the property of his name.
This testimony confirmed that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son, who said it was poured out by Him.
He poured out what He contained within Himself, not as if confined to a place, but while substantially remaining in Himself.
He did not pour out in such a way as to empty Himself, like a vessel becomes empty when its contents are poured out.
This is the case with physical things; it is not the same with divine things.
When either the Father or the Son pours out the Spirit, they do not empty themselves but share the grace of their gift without losing anything.
And further down, presenting the Apostle's testimony:
"You, however, are not in the flesh but in the Spirit, if indeed the Spirit of God dwells in you. But if anyone does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to Him" (Romans 8:9).
When he says the Spirit of God and consequently the Spirit of Christ, notice that he designates the person of Christ under the name of God.
Or if he signifies the Father, whose Spirit it is, under the name of God, behold the Spirit is declared to be, by the unity of substance, the Spirit of both the Father and the Son.
Rightly, it is known to proceed from both, and in the bond of the Trinity is seen to have a distinct person.
Whoever does not have the Holy Spirit is shown not to have Christ.
Therefore, the Holy Spirit is God, who, if denied, also denies Christ, who said:
"No one comes to the Father except through me" (John 14:6).
Whoever is empty of the Holy Spirit is not of Christ and has lost the way to reach the Father.
He showed with many reasons that the Holy Spirit is God, consubstantial with the Father and the Son, proceeding from both, and cannot be separated from the bond of the Trinity, being of the same nature as the Father and the Son.
He emphasizes that one cannot have Christ without having the Holy Spirit.
Since the Holy Spirit is God, whoever denies the Spirit consequently denies Christ, which would not happen if He did not remain in Christ and was not consubstantial with Him.
To remain in Christ and be consubstantial with Him, the Spirit proceeding from Him demonstrates this: for it cannot proceed from Him unless it remains in Him and is consubstantially attached.
Since Christ is the way to the Father, whoever does not have the Spirit cannot have Christ as the way: for one cannot have one without the other, as they are neither divided in substance nor in dwelling.
Therefore, one who is empty of the Holy Spirit is also found empty of Christ; because whoever does not have the source is not inundated by the source's watering.
By all these things, it is clearly shown that the Holy Spirit proceeds from Christ.
And later (chapter 11): Nothing in the Holy Spirit should be considered half-full, because it is compared to fullness: for He who is given as a pledge in place of God must not be believed to be anything other than God.
Whoever denies that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son considers the Holy Spirit half-full, and whoever does not attribute the procession to the Son denies that He is given as a pledge in place of God.
For God cannot be understood as full, to whom the consubstantiality of the Son is denied; nor can He represent the place of God, to whom the Son is not consubstantial.
But no Catholic feels this way; instead, they confess that God is full and consubstantial with the Father and the Son: they know that the Son proceeds from where He also takes substance; and He who is united in substance to the Father and the Son must necessarily proceed from both.
Again, he adds, citing a chapter from the same Apostle to Titus: He saved us through the washing of regeneration and renewal by the Holy Spirit, which He poured out on us abundantly through Jesus Christ (Titus 3:5).
Behold, even here under the manifest Trinity, the Father through the Son pours out the abundance of the Holy Spirit.
And, what is most noteworthy, he attributes the power of regeneration and renewal to the Holy Spirit Himself.
The Father poured out the Holy Spirit on us abundantly through Jesus Christ: to show that He proceeds from both the Father and Jesus Christ.
While it is poured out for us, the Father pours out the Holy Spirit because He is sent by the Father.
He pours out through Jesus Christ because He works with the Father in this act.
It is not said that the Father pours out through Jesus Christ as if Christ does not participate, for the Father and the Son are unified in action.
The Father pours out through Jesus Christ because when the Father pours out, Jesus Christ also pours out, since He is sent by both.
He proceeds from both the Father and the Son.
This author testifies to the power of the Holy Spirit, equal to that of the Father and the Son.
He states that the power of regeneration and renewal is attributed to the Holy Spirit to show that He possesses the same power as the Father and the Son.
Thus, He is affirmed to be consubstantial and to proceed from both.
Later, in chapter twelve, the Psalmist gives testimony, saying: "Where can I go from Your Spirit?" (Psalm one thirty-nine, verse seven).
This means, where can I hide from His presence, which is undoubtedly everywhere, both inside and outside?
And further, it is clearly understood: "Nor is there anyone who can hide from His heat" (Psalm nineteen, verse six).
His ineffable greatness enters, fills, and encompasses everything, and He is said to be sent by the Father and the Son, proceeding from their substance, and recognized as working as one with them.
By all these things, the majesty and procession of the Holy Spirit are shown.
Since it is testified that no place is remote from the presence of the Holy Spirit, He is compared to the divinity of the Father and the Son, penetrating and containing all things.
Consequently, adding that no one is untouched by the heat of His fire, it is testified that this is also said of the Son: "Who enlightens every man coming into this world" (John one, verse nine).
This shows that He has the same power as the Son, since the Son enlightens every man, and no one is exempt from the heat of the Spirit.
When it is said that He is sent by both the Father and the Son, and that He proceeds from their substance, it shows from whom the Spirit comes and whose power He possesses.
This indicates that He is God, equal to the Father and the Son in both power and substance, because He proceeds from both.
Furthermore, when the Son says: The Advocate who proceeds from the Father (John 15:26), He does not say who is created by the Father, but proceeds from the Father, meaning from the fellowship of the Father’s power and the property of His nature.
This statement shows that when He proceeds from the Father, He has no beginning with the Father.
Do not think that He wanted to deny that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son because He said that He proceeds from the Father.
Earlier, He said that He is sent by the Father and the Son, that He proceeds from their substance, and works as one with them.
Now, He also says that He proceeds from the fellowship of the Father’s power and the property of His nature.
Just as the Father and the Son are not separated in power or nature, they are not separated in the existence of the Spirit.
Since He is the Spirit of both, He proceeds from both, and those who are equal in nature and power are not separated by procession.
He says below: But what is it that the Son is said to be born of God the Father, and the Holy Spirit is indicated to proceed?
The difference between being born and proceeding is that one is born from one, while the other proceeds from both.
He also professes that the Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son.
The reason given is that if we say He proceeds only from the Father, we risk endangering the faith.
How can the Son be called the only begotten of the Father when the Spirit is also of the same?
And how can it be proven that He is not the Son, who exists from the Father like the Son?
Such blasphemy must be avoided to protect the Catholic faith from the attacks of enemies.
It should be said, therefore, as our ancestors did:
The Son is born from the Father, the only one from the only one, and thus the only begotten.
But the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father, yet not from the Father alone.
If we confess that the Spirit proceeds only from the Father, we might seem to preach two Sons.
Therefore, this teacher, following the doctrine of his elders, passed down to his successors what he had received from his predecessors.
Although he proved that the Roman Church holds the same belief about the Holy Spirit as it does today, he did not show that it was ever divided from the Eastern Churches in such faith.
Nor that it ever thought or taught differently about the Holy Spirit.
But now it is astonishing what the discoverers of new doctrine argue.
Why do they separate themselves from the communion that their ancestors always held?
Why do they pass judgment before understanding?
Why do they accuse before hearing?
This is not a judgment of fairness, but a prejudice of injustice.
But if they think it is enough that they know for sure that the Roman Church preaches that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son, and therefore do not want to inquire what they evidently know to be said,
let them know that they judge their ancestors along with the Romans.
While they wish to deprive the Romans of their communion, they equally excommunicate themselves from the society of their own ancestors.
They prove to communicate with no Catholic Church while they make themselves strangers to Roman communion.
Let them quickly consider whose evil deed this is, and not delay in correcting their error.
If they do not wish to communicate with the Romans, they fear being excommunicated from the whole Catholic Church.