Odo's Sermon on Saint Lucian.
CHAPTER ONE. Saint Lucian is Sent to Gaul.
Recounting the victories and deeds of precious martyrs, dear brothers, is essentially praising Christ and proclaiming His triumph through His martyrs to the glory of His name.
In all things, He Himself emerged victorious, as He told His followers: "Take heart, because I have overcome the world" (John 16:33).
Therefore, in all things, the gracious Jesus was victorious, as He fought first for everyone.
Thus, the holy martyrs are honored closer to Christ in glory than anyone else, as they were His imitators in suffering.
Indeed, they completed what was lacking in the sufferings of Christ: and so it is rightly said that Christ suffered in all these, because they were His members.
Hence, in them, He is rightly proclaimed victorious, because He triumphed through them every time a martyr fell, victorious in suffering for Christ.
Therefore, we ought to praise these glorious men, whose teachings make the Church of Christ shine far and wide across the world.
Under the altar of God, clothed in white robes, stained with their own blood and washed in the blood of Christ, they rest happily.
From this assembly came the blessed Lucian, a distinguished and glorious martyr, whom divine grace anointed at baptism, indicating from the start that he would be great in holiness among the people.
Lucian was initially called Lucius by his ancestors according to the flesh, deriving not only his origin but also his name from the great consul Lucius.
However, by the grace of the Holy Spirit, following the custom of the holy Fathers, his name was changed for the better; so that he who was called Lucius by his parents would later be called Lucian by God, with an expanded name.
Thus, it became clear that being born anew in the light, he himself became light in the Lord, and so he should first preach that same light, in which he was reborn in Christ, along with other holy men, to the nations.
It's clear that he was of Roman origin and from a noble family.
But he became even more noble in spirit because he was found to be the son of the eternal King through the grace of adoption.
If you ask whose teaching and guidance he followed, he was truly a disciple of the Apostle Peter, grounded in his faith and filled with heavenly teachings, as the series of events, the time, and the order of things clearly show.
After being reborn in Christ, he lived as a perfect soldier of Christ in Rome, as if in military camps, so that when he eventually went out to the nations, he would be seen as a valiant warrior and a strong defender of the faith.
When he was nourished by God's doctrine into a perfect man, the renowned martyr Dionysius, led by Christ, came to Rome.
There, after the apostles had passed, he found the blessed Clement governing the pinnacle of the apostolic see.
Saint Dionysius, also known as Macarius, was graciously received by him and treated with considerable honor, both for his holiness and their long-standing association in Christ.
They spent a lot of time together with the supreme pontiff, refreshing each other with mutual visits, uplifting each other with divine conversations, and strengthening each other with examples of virtues.
During one of their many holy scripture discussions, blessed Clement, inspired by the divine spirit, said:
"Do you see, my dearest brother Dionysius, how great the harvest is among the nations of the Lord's sowing, and how few the workers are in the word of divine preaching?
Since you are sufficiently instructed in all the teachings of the Catholic faith, imbued with all Christian religion, and strengthened by virtues, I ask you to go, in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, to the western parts, as a good soldier, and fight against the most fearsome enemies in the battles of the Lord your God."
With these orders given, and now that the blessed Dionysius had agreed to set out, Saint Clement began to seek companions and diligent helpers in the word, as well as suitable ones in life and holiness, along with prominent ministers of the divine service and many others.
Among them, the pontiff chose the proven man Lucian to be his companion, whom he also ordained as bishop, because he had been thoroughly instructed in the faith under the teaching of the apostle Peter.
Thus, no duties of ecclesiastical discipline would be lacking among such proven men.
Because he was an older disciple of Christ and Peter, Saint Clement united Lucian with Saint Dionysius so that he would be his interpreter, and to the others, he would be a venerable father and distinguished teacher in doctrine and religious holiness.
With everything thus arranged, among the many teachings of Christ and instructions of piety, he finally addressed them, saying:
"Go, dearest and strongest warriors of Christ. Just as the Lord was with our holy Fathers the apostles and their collaborators, so may He be with you in all the works of the divine word. For you," he said, "will acquire for the Lord a great and innumerable multitude from the nations and bring them into the promised land."
And so, after many sacraments of faith were entrusted to each and revealed to all together, giving peace to everyone, he dismissed them and instructed that holy brotherhood to depart in peace.
CHAPTER Two
He preaches in Italy and comes to Arles.
While traveling and preaching throughout Italy, before reaching Pavia, in a place not far from the city of Parma, it appeared to the most blessed Lucian that he should preach the word of God to the people there.
He aimed to turn them away from their vain superstitions and idol worship, as the psalm says: "Those who sow with tears will reap with songs of joy."
He shared what he had received as a faithful steward with the people.
However, the people of that place, still being pagans and deeply involved in idol worship, could not tolerate the insult to their gods nor the preaching of the divine word to themselves.
They promptly seized the most holy Lucian, subjected him to insults, and placed him in public custody, which is still shown to everyone passing through that place today.
As he entered, he sang with great joy, saying: "Lead me, Lord, in Your way, and I will walk in Your truth"; and also: "Make my steps firm in Your paths, so that my feet do not slip."
In this custody, the holy man conducted himself as if under the shadow of God's wings, placing all his hope in Christ's protection, and he prayed to the Lord, saying: "Bring my soul out of prison, that I may praise Your name; the righteous will surround me because You are good to me."
He prayed that through him, the Savior of the world, Christ, would justify those from the nations who are predestined to life.
While the blessed and holy man sang such praises to the Lord in his heart, his prayer soon reached heaven, so that he would not remain behind without his companions, with whom he desired to go to passion and reach those to whom he had been sent.
The glorious athlete of Christ did not avoid the loss of life for Christ, but devoutly prayed that he might first achieve the fruit promised to him by the Lord, and then finally, with much harvest, reach the palm of martyrdom together with his companions and the reward of life.
And so, divine power soon came to his aid.
There were already some Christians there who had been touched by divine power.
Knowing what had happened to the holy man, they came to him at night in the prison and, with whatever skill they could muster for the love of Christ, freed him from the dungeon.
Together with his holy comrades, they let him go free.
And so, this holy group, enjoying prosperous successes, came to Pavia, the royal city of Italy.
There, while resting a little, they did not cease from divine praises and did not stop preaching the word of God everywhere they went.
You could see their prophecy, because, as it says, "How beautiful are the feet of those who bring good news, who proclaim peace, who bring good tidings" (Romans 10:15).
They moved about confidently, trusting in God's help.
They went joyfully, mindful of what is read in the Acts of the Apostles, that they too had now become participants in the sufferings of Christ and were considered worthy to suffer dishonor for his name (Acts 5:41).
As they traveled together, no one can say how many thousands of people were converted to Christ over time.
They preached and spread the word of salvation to everyone.
Divine power accompanied them, so that people saw them as citizens of heaven, lambs among wolves, shining with signs and miracles, carrying and enlightening the souls of God's elect.
And so, finally leaving Italy, they set out on the sea with favorable winds.
They arrived at the port of the city of Arles, led by the Holy Spirit on a straight path, and joyfully came ashore.
Disembarking from the ship, they were received hospitably by the inhabitants of that city, who showed them great kindness.
While they were gathered together, they began, in the manner of the holy apostles, to discuss which parts each should choose for preaching and who should go together.
Thus, they sent the very holy Marcellinus to Spain with a few others, as it is said.
They also sent Saturninus to Toulouse, the main city of Aquitaine, so they could spread the Gospel of the eternal kingdom far and wide among the nations, and establish the Churches of Christ everywhere up to the British Ocean.
Chapter Three
Bellovaci preaches; Saints Maximianus and Julianus are crowned with martyrdom.
With everything arranged, the Blessed Dionysius, also known as Macarius due to his exceptional holiness, who had received the honor of apostleship from the Blessed Clement and the privilege of preaching to the Gentiles, is known to have kept the sacred Lucian with him until they reached the town of Paris.
From there, having kept a few with him, he sent Saint Lucian, whom faith had united with him and made a brother, along with Saint Maximianus the priest and Julianus the deacon, to evangelize to the Bellovaci.
There, as we read, the Roman military was stationed because the people of Bellovaci were always known to be warlike.
It's recorded in public histories that more than sixty thousand armed men from that district went out to battle against Julius Caesar and the Roman army, along with other citizens of Gaul.
Thus, the Roman army was stationed there for the protection of other cities.
Despite the ferocity of both peoples, the valiant athlete of Christ, supported by his disciples, bravely came equipped with the arms of Christ and strengthened by divine grace.
He was steadfast in faith, eloquent in speech, and admirable in all virtues.
He began to preach the name of the Lord, defeat evil forces, and establish the Church of Christ.
Filled with the Holy Spirit's grace, he taught the people through his actions and his words.
Miracles accompanied him, and by the Lord's power, he healed all diseases.
He had received such grace in exorcising demons that they immediately departed upon hearing his command.
Day and night, he persevered in preaching and establishing the true and only Lord.
He was always engaged in prayer and divine duties, with many vigils and daily fasts.
He abstained from food and practiced various forms of bodily affliction.
Through these practices, he wore himself down daily so that, as the Apostle said, he might present himself as a living sacrifice, acceptable to Christ the Lord.
Romans 12:1.
His constant sustenance was nothing more than a small amount of bread, herbal greens, and cold water.
Yet, he was sustained by divine strength, and his weak limbs were strengthened by the grace of Christ.
He earnestly desired to reach the crown of martyrdom, so that, being already dead to the world, he might carry the cross daily after Christ the Lord.
He knew there were two types of martyrdom: one hidden and the other visible.
He bore the first in secret, although the power of his abstinence was apparent to all, so that he might later be crowned by the Lord.
He was worn out by the mortification of the flesh, adorned with patience, grounded in wonderful humility, and filled with gentleness.
The virtue of good works around him had grown so much that, while still on earth in the body, he seemed in spirit to converse with the angels in heaven.
He always appeared with a pleasant face and a tranquil mind, adorned with wonderful white hair, making him distinguished and remarkable in both demeanor and body.
As his fame spread far and wide, many came to him to be baptized in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
Idols were destroyed where they had been made.
Seeing that he was losing those whom Christ was gaining through his servants, the ancient enemy turned all his schemes against the holy Church of God and inflamed Domitian.
After Nero, the son of perdition, Domitian conducted the second persecution against Christians.
He was so enraged that wherever Christians were found throughout the entire Roman world, they were forced either to sacrifice to the gods or be cruelly killed after various tortures.
From that time, throughout the entire world under his control, in all cities, towns, municipalities, and even villages, a public decree was issued that all officials of the Republic must force Christians to worship idols and sacrifice to the gods or face various punishments.
Persecutors of the Christian name were sent everywhere; among them, Fescenninus Sisinnius was ordered to quickly come to Gaul with the rest of the officials to search for the soldiers of Christ, especially those who had left Rome some time ago, whose fame had already spread, so that the name of Christians might be driven out of Gaul.
Then indeed, three very cruel men were sent: namely, Latinus, Jarius, and Antor, specifically to search for the holy servant of God, Lucian, with their executors.
They were to present him to the governor's audience or kill him immediately with a sword if he refused to sacrifice to idols.
When these men searched the cities and places, they did not find him right away.
Meanwhile, the fame of the man of God reached them, that by preaching the Gospel of the eternal kingdom, he had won over the people of Beauvais.
Upon hearing this, inflamed more and more with anger and indignation, they hurried there with all speed.
Just before they arrived, the blessed martyr, perceiving through the revelation of the Holy Spirit that they were near, stood firm in the place where he was teaching the people the words of life.
With him was a very large crowd, which had already been converted to the faith of Christ through his preaching.
He exhorted them all the more earnestly, as he was confident in the glory of eternal reward, saying:
"Behold, my dear brothers and beloved children, my Lord Jesus Christ will soon deem me worthy to receive the fruits and rewards of my labors, long promised to me.
Therefore, beloved ones, remain strong in the faith of Christ; for I, now weary with extreme old age, joyfully hasten to go to Christ with the palm of martyrdom. But you, remain steadfast in the grace you have received."
Do not let the terror of rulers make you abandon your faith in Christ.
Do not let threats scare you. Do not let persuasive flattery deceive you.
Do not let any promises make you turn back.
So that you may receive eternal joy where unspeakable rewards are prepared for you.
I eagerly hasten without fear, and therefore I do not dread the cruelty of persecutors.
Having said these things, he lifted his eyes to heaven and gave thanks to God in front of everyone, who deemed him worthy to be counted among the holy martyrs and not to be separated from his holy companions.
He said, "I give thanks to you, Lord Jesus Christ, Son of the living God, who joined me with Saint Dionysius and his companions at the end, and equated me with their labors.
Therefore, I ask you to deem me worthy to be counted among them, and to be made a partaker of your kingdom."
After saying these things, he left the city of Beauvais and withdrew a little from the city according to the Lord's command, not out of fear of punishment, but to set an example for the flock according to the Lord's command (Matthew 10:23).
Traveling with the blessed martyrs Maximian and Julian, he did not cease from divine conversations and prayers along the entire way, until he reached the summit of the mountain to which he was heading, a mountain situated almost three miles from the city near the river Thara.
When he arrived there, like a city set on a hill that cannot be hidden, the mountain itself offered a beautiful view over the river and the people.
There, placed as if in a lookout, the blessed man decided to await his martyr's crown.
Meanwhile, the mentioned soldiers quickly arrived at the city of Beauvais.
When they searched for the holy man of God, Lucian, and did not find him, they began to search diligently for where he had gone.
They were told that he was teaching the people not far from the city.
So they immediately remounted their horses and quickly rode to the mountain, where the man of God was staying with the people and his disciples.
Upon arriving there, before any interrogation by judicial authority, they seized the holy men of God, Maximian and Julian.
By chance, to deter the holy old man with their punishments and to bring him back to the worship of the gods, they captured him and, with royal authority and all their fury, commanded him to sacrifice to the idols.
Otherwise, they said, "If you do not sacrifice to the immortal gods, we order you to be punished with the sword immediately."
But they, strong in faith, said they would never sacrifice to the idols because they are vain and the work of human hands. They said, "We know one true Lord, Jesus Christ, the Son of the living God, for whose faith we are prepared to die."
When this was heard, they immediately ordered them to be punished with the sword in the presence of the most blessed Lucian. Having done this, they received the unfading crowns promised to them by the Lord and were received in peace among the number of holy martyrs. For their glory, Blessed Lucian praised the Lord with a joyful voice in front of everyone, saying:
"I rejoice and am glad in you, my God, because I see my children going before me to the crown."
Chapter Four
Saint Lucian is tortured in various ways and killed.
Then Latinus, Iarius, and Antor, with anger and indignation, spoke fiercely to him as if with one voice:
"Are you the one," they asked, "who with your sorcery misleads the people so that they do not obey the commands of the most invincible Emperor and the Roman Senate to offer pleasing sacrifices to the immortal gods?"
To which Saint Lucian replied:
"I am not a sorcerer; I am a servant of Jesus Christ, trained in divine teachings. Therefore, I show God's people the way of truth and make known how they should follow my Lord Jesus Christ, who came into the world to redeem His creation and turn them away from the worship of demons, so that they may be called to the heavenly light and saved from their darkness. It is right that they should bow the neck of their hearts to Him alone, who desired to die crucified for the salvation of all."
But they replied: "How," they asked, "do you claim that God, whom you not only declare dead but also crucified, exists?"
Saint Lucian answered:
"Although your unbelief does not deserve to hear the mysteries of the most merciful King, I will explain briefly for the sake of the crowd present: God, the Son of God, who has always been with the Father before all ages, because of the transgression of the first man, wanted to become true man from a virgin at the end of times for the restoration of humanity, so that He might be true God and true man, and the same God and man, one Christ, true Son of God and man; so that He who was incapable of suffering in divinity, always remaining with the Father, became not only visible but also capable of suffering for us according to humanity."
Hence, He became obedient to God the Father for our redemption even unto death, death on a cross. Otherwise, if the Son of God had not also deigned to become the Son of man, neither would the human race have attained forgiveness, nor would mortals have returned to life."
These and many other actions were taken by the blessed Lucian, which only fueled the soldiers' rage.
They said: "Indeed, old age should have made you wise, but your vanity has led you astray, and your reckless words push you towards death. If you don't come to your senses quickly and stop this boldness, and offer sacrifices to the immortal gods, we will subject your old age to many torments."
Then, as they sat, they ordered him to stand before them. In a threatening voice, they demanded: "Tell us your name and status quickly." To which Lucian, the athlete of Christ, replied: "By my ancestors, I was truly called Lucius, but in the rebirth through Christ, I am known as Lucian. Regarding my status, I am of Roman descent, a respected name worldwide. However, what is more noble to me is that I am a servant of Christ Jesus. To me, living is my Lord Jesus Christ, and dying is gain. Therefore, I rejoice and confess to be His servant."
The soldiers responded: "This is exactly what we were talking about; you are a deceiver and a seducer. You stubbornly continue to speak boldly, ignoring your weary old age. If you are Roman, why have you abandoned the worship of the gods, whom Augustus Caesar and the entire Roman Senate worship, along with the whole world?"
Saint Lucian replied: "Since I was reborn in Christ and came to know my true Lord Jesus Christ, I have renounced the devil, idols, and all their works. But you neither hear nor understand what I speak and confess about Christ the Lord."
Your lack of faith has blinded you, just like Caesar Augustus and the Senate.
You've issued decrees that we rational beings should sacrifice to demons and bow to idols made by human hands.
When Latinus, Januarius, and Antor heard this, they were extremely upset by the insult to Caesar.
They then seized him with bound hands and handed him over to the torturers, who stretched him out and cruelly struck him with dreadful whips.
Despite being severely whipped and tightly bound, the athlete of God endured the tortures for a long time.
He was neither overcome by pain nor frightened by threats.
Instead, he strengthened his nearly decrepit limbs with pure strength of spirit, maintaining the same expression and mind during the beatings.
He did not stop confessing the name of Christ with a living voice, saying:
I believe Christ is the Son of God with my heart, and I will never stop praising Him with my mouth.
Driven by rage, they sentenced him to be struck by the sword.
One of the soldiers drew his sword, and with his holy neck prepared, he cut off his holy and precious head.
As the body of the holy man lay there, still twitching lifelessly, a great light from heaven shone above it, and a great voice accompanied the light, saying:
Well done, good servant Lucian, who did not hesitate to shed your blood for me; come and receive the crown long promised to you, for you will rejoice with the saints in heaven.
Come and receive the mansion of glory long prepared for you with the angels.
This voice was not for him, who had always carried this promise in his heart through faith, but for those present, so they might more faithfully retain the merits of the holy man and the faith in our Lord Jesus Christ, which Saint Lucian had long preached.
This happened on the Sabbath day at the hour on the mountain we mentioned above, three miles from the city, on the 8th of January.
Seeing and hearing this, both the believers and non-believers were struck with extreme terror.
By divine will, some fled; others, astonished and marveling with joy at being freed from the devil's snares, still couldn't bear the brightness of the light and withdrew for a short time.
Chapter Five
The head is carried and buried.
Then, raising the lifeless body of the holy man, he took the severed head with his own hands.
With the firm steps of the grace of the Holy Spirit, whose body and members had been instruments of divine will, he began to walk steadily as if he were still alive.
Carrying the precious head and guided by angels, he crossed a river and reached a place about three miles from the mountain, which the holy man had chosen for his burial.
This place was about one mile from the aforementioned city.
There, in a small public field, the holy man rested in peace with the palm of victory.
From there, very devout men, converted by his preaching, came with spices and wrapped the holy body in clean linen cloths.
They buried him with great honor and reverence in what seemed to be a new tomb at the time.
However, to show that the funeral was conducted with the services of angels, as the most holy body was being laid to rest, a wonderful fragrance suddenly filled the air, which everyone present could smell until the body was covered with earth.
The men, astonished and joyful, said to each other:
"What is this? Glory to you, Lord Jesus Christ, for our noses have never sensed such a wonderful scent."
"Glory to you, Christ the Savior, for we are so filled that we believe no further good can be lacking for us."
The more they spoke of these things, the more the divine fragrance flowed, making it clear that the services of angels had been present at his funeral from the beginning of his passion.
When these rites were properly completed, they all prostrated themselves on the ground with great fear and devotion, crying out and saying:
"We believe in you, Jesus Christ, the true Son of God, reigning in heaven with the Father and the Holy Spirit; as we heard from your holy martyr Lucian with our ears and learned with our minds."
When a large crowd, gathered from different villages and towns as if for a spectacle, saw and heard such things from the believers, it is estimated that about 500 men and women, struck in their hearts, believed in the Lord Jesus Christ, the Son of the living God, on that same day.
Through the preaching of the most blessed Lucian in Gaul, no fewer than 30,000 people of various kinds and ages had already converted.
They abandoned idols and confessed God the Father unbegotten, His only-begotten Son, and the Holy Spirit as the true and one God in the Trinity.
By this faith, reborn and renewed through the washing of regeneration, some of them soon built a basilica most devotedly to the Lord in the same place over the holy body, in honor of this martyr.
The bodies of Saints Maximus and Julian were buried on the mountain where they had been beheaded.
But as the number and devotion of Christians grew, the faithful moved them and joined them with the body of the most blessed Lucian.
Later, a better-constructed and adorned church was built there, and with the help of God the Father, many benefits were rightly granted to those who asked through the merits and intercession of the holy martyrs by the Lord Jesus Christ.
Because they had one faith, one charity, and one confession in martyrdom, we rightly believe that they share one society in eternal blessedness and one fellowship of merits.
Therefore, let us give thanks to our Creator, because the witnesses of Christ, taken in the number of three, faithfully completed their martyrdom on earth for the faith of the Trinity.
Knowing this, we venerate, faithfully remember, and recognize it.
Behold, brothers, even if the whole earth is stained with the blood of martyrs, our city is stained with their blood, sprinkled with the blood of Christ.
Even if heaven flourishes with the crowns of martyrs, our land flourishes, decorated with their virtues.
Other churches are adorned with the memories of martyrs; this one is adorned with their triumphs and consecrated with their relics.
We mark the birthdays of the martyrs, and today we celebrate their ascension into heaven.
At their tomb, signs of virtue are numerous, and the benefits of health are abundant.
The sick come and are healed, the blind receive sight, the lame are cured, and those troubled by demons are freed.
And even greater, the prayers of the faithful are heard, vows are accepted, the bonds of sins are broken, and heaven is opened to those who knock.
The Church's rewards are attained.
The society of blessed martyrs is exceedingly happy and pleasing to God, whose fellowship is rejoiced in by the choirs of angels in heaven.
By their merits and prayers, the worthy petitions of all the faithful are granted on earth, by the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, who with the eternal Father and the Holy Spirit lives and reigns forever and ever.
Amen.