Historical Account. (In Mai's Roman Anthology Volume Five)
Historical Note. In Mai's Spicilegium Romanum, Volume 5.
Peter the Deacon, in his book "On the Illustrious Men of Monte Cassino," chapter 6, mentions:
Lawrence, a monk at the Monte Cassino monastery, was unmatched in knowledge compared to any of his predecessors after the most holy Benedict. He became a bishop and composed an elegant sermon for the vigil of Saint Benedict.
The records of Monte Cassino do not specify Lawrence's episcopal seat; however, Marus, in his notes on Peter the Deacon, notes that Lawrence flourished around the year 950 AD.
I am pleased to present the following sermon from Vatican codex 1202, which was formerly from Monte Cassino and is written in Lombardic letters with beautiful illustrations.
Laurence's Sermon on the Vigil of Saint Benedict
As we prepare to celebrate the feast of our blessed Father Benedict, O most venerable assembly, let us humbly seek the mercy of Almighty God, who allowed him to reach the peak of perfection.
May our minds, cleansed from the stain of sin, patiently await the arrival of our patron with such devotion that we may joyfully embrace his presence.
Indeed, there is no doubt that this most sacred patron is present with us when we strive to honor his glorious feast with heartfelt devotion.
And certainly, although he deems it worthy to visit and strengthen those who always observe his life-giving commandments, during this most holy feast of his, he will graciously be present with a special kindness to his servants, who strive with all their efforts to prepare their hearts to welcome such a Father with even more devotion than usual.
Indeed, it is well known that he is a most important member of the body, as he was deemed worthy to say with the voice of the gospel:
"Where two or three are gathered in my name, there am I in the midst of them."
From the book of Matthew, chapter eighteen, verse twenty.
If, therefore, the head, Christ, deems it worthy to be present with us who are gathered in his name, then certainly his members are not absent.
And if all the chosen members are generally present with him, how much more does our most glorious patron Benedict, clinging to him, support his clients and strive to commend their prayers and worthy vows to that same High Throne?
We undoubtedly believe that he can more easily obtain our salvation from the same God and our Lord, because he has been lifted up in glory of merits and exalted with the effectiveness of great miracles above almost all earthly beings, after the blessed and holy apostles.
Indeed, his distinguished merits are to be admired by human senses, as they seem to far exceed any measure.
In his youth, he was blessed with the grace of the Holy Spirit, becoming wise beyond his years.
He chose to leave behind his family's wealth and rejected the human pomp that many at the time pursued through liberal arts.
He also turned away from the comfort of a devoted nurse and chose a challenging path.
Through his example and gentle teachings, he made this difficult path easy for his followers, echoing the Master's words:
"My yoke is easy, and my burden is light."
Who else, through such remarkable teaching and example, inspired so many monks to dedicate themselves to divine commandments, if not him?
He fulfilled what he taught clearly and sweetly through his deeds.
The approval of his service by God is evident, as he was not allowed to remain hidden in mountain caves for long, being meant as an example to many.
As recorded in his life, sweetly written by the blessed Gregory, he was first instructed to tell a certain priest preparing a meal for the Easter feast to visit his devoted servant, who was starving in the rocky cliffs.
Later, he was to be revealed to herdsmen and many others.
This was a worthy and holy judgment, ensuring that such a shining example of virtues and a brilliant gem of miraculous power would not remain hidden under a bushel for long.
Indeed, I doubt anyone is unaware of the effectiveness of the miracles that accompanied him, as they are so remarkable that, after the saints, it seems that the Savior said specifically to him:
"You will do greater things than these, believing in my name."
Truly believing in his name, he aspired to perform many great miracles, embracing him and setting aside all the fleeting successes of this unstable life.
From this, it is rightly said that heavenly power was granted to him, allowing him to restore life to a dead body through prayer; and among countless other feats, he broke the bonds on prisoners' arms just by looking at them.
The empty vessel was filled powerfully by the supplicant's prayer, along with the oil flask.
Calmly, a boy who had been submerged in the sea was brought back to stable ground by the appearance of his garment through a Moor equally blessed.
And the rest, which I do not doubt will be well-known and celebrated throughout almost the entire world.
He is rightfully celebrated by us, his servants, with proper solemnity, as he peacefully left his earthly burdens and ascended to the heavenly realms to receive those indescribable rewards that, due to their greatness, cannot be fully understood by human estimation.
Rightly so, during his most sacred solemnity, we rejoice with spiritual joy, as he, accompanied by his vigilant companions and adorned for the heavenly journey, joyfully ascended to the heights.
Indeed, it is fitting that we embrace his solemnities with devoted joy, as Christ enriched him with His generosity, taking him from the earth.
It is appropriate to celebrate him more devoutly than other saints, as, with divine kindness, we experience his help daily.
Moreover, it is very inappropriate for his own congregation to neglect glorifying him with all its power, when provinces far and wide, illuminated by the rays of his merits, venerate him with the most devoted services.
Meanwhile, let us consider how our most blessed Father is most pleased, by carefully reading and examining the rule of his holy institution, so that by following his path, we might vigilantly avoid any missteps.
Among other things, the same Father taught the most celebrated virtues, especially commending charity, the bond of perfection, and humility, known to be the guardian of all other virtues.
Your charity is aware of how cautiously and moderately he instructed us to perform the duty of singing, and, to use his words, with what gravity he guided us to present it.
For he says, among other things: Let us stand to sing in such a way that our mind agrees with our voice.
These words clearly show that he values insight into the power of words and a healthy sense of compunction more than the sweetness of sounds or elevated singing.
So, dearest brothers, let's strive to honor the memory of this great Father with fervent love, adorned with humility, and moved by the sweetness of song, so we may be worthy of his protection everywhere.
As the same holy man says, things that need to be done should start with prayer.
Let's humbly seek his protection for a while, so what we've begun with devotion can be happily completed.
We implore you, our shepherd, with bowed minds, to kindly have mercy on us and offer your usual prayers to God the Creator for your flock.
Protect us, your humble servants, from the attacks of the ancient enemy; mercifully strengthen us with the power of love; graciously grant your followers an abundance of gifts, and don't let us be excluded from your company someday.
I also, though less skilled in literary arts and presumptuous in praising you, being the least of your servants, humbly ask for your protection, so that we all, enriched by your gift, may obtain forgiveness for our sins.
Meanwhile, let the conclusion of our page briefly summarize the greatness of this most excellent Father of ours.
But when can our inadequacy fully express the distinguished merits of this man with witty and elegant speech?
Even if Plato or Demosthenes, known for their torrents of eloquence, were to rise from the depths of the underworld where they are tormented, they might be more astonished at the praises of such a Father than able to speak them.
Indeed, such great mercy from the thunderer has marked him with blessedness, granting him the heavenly kingdoms, crowned with the wreath of justice, celebrating, while his relics, which bless the Cassinese monastery, are worshipped with bowed and humble reverence by the kings of the earth.
With such great miracles and wonders, he still stands out at his honorable home, attracting foreign and distant princes to follow him.
And rightly so, he is revered by earthly leaders who, bowing to the King of all kings, strove to serve with utmost dignity throughout his life.
Indeed, he promised through the prophet: "I will honor those who honor me."
Truly, he has glorified and continues to glorify our most holy Father, not only in the heavenly realms but also before people on earth, so that the whole world may recognize the great glory of beatitude to which he is exalted, having humbly strived in this life for his name's sake.
Behold him who once hid in caves, now rejoices in paradise; and whom the fields once knew to be weakened by fasting, now embraces the joys of Olympus with dancing.
Behold, the kings of the earth now offer devout kisses and generous gifts to the footsteps of him whom only Campania once knew.
So now, most excellent Father of fathers, we humbly beg your mercy, that you may extend the hand of your help to us.
Please, having mercy on us sinners, restrain the cruel voices of those who deceitfully seek to entice your servants.
Give your solace, Father, to your humble followers whom you have kindly led to follow your path.
Kindly show us, we ask, the way to reach our homeland, so that none from your flock may encounter danger; that you may return the talents once entrusted to you to the common Lord, doubled for our sake, and thus deserve to obtain a double reward.
Through your intervention, may we, unworthy as we are, at least avoid punishment, since we doubt the reward due to the quality of our merits.
With our Lord Jesus Christ granting this, who has exalted you, most blessed Father, so that you appear inferior to none of the saints after the blessed apostles; indeed, he who lives and reigns with the Father and the Holy Spirit for all ages of ages.
Amen.