The Book of Spiritual Understanding: One Book Addressed to Uranus
by Saint Eucherius, Bishop of Lyon.
I felt it was important to create and share with you some formulas to help understand the spiritual meanings of Latin names, out of a fatherly concern for you.
Once you grasp them, you'll easily comprehend all divine writings and focus on understanding other meanings.
As the letter kills, but the spirit gives life, it’s essential to delve into the spiritual depths of words with the life-giving spirit.
Additionally, we are reminded that all Scripture, both from the Old and the New Testament, should be understood allegorically.
This is highlighted in the Old Testament: "I will open my mouth in parables, I will utter hidden things from of old" Psalm seventy-eight, verse two.
And also in the New Testament: "Jesus spoke all these things to the crowd in parables; he did not say anything to them without using a parable" Mark chapter four, verse sixteen.
It’s no surprise that the divine word, delivered through prophets and apostles, differs significantly from the usual human writing style, with simple meanings on the surface but profound truths within.
The sacred words of God were meant to be distinct from other writings, both in merit and form, so the dignity of heavenly secrets wouldn’t be revealed indiscriminately to everyone.
This is to prevent the holy from being given to dogs, and pearls from being thrown to pigs Matthew chapter seven, verse six; and to ensure that the consecrated vessels of the temple, when covered, wouldn’t be carried or seen by the common people Numbers chapter four, verses fifteen and twenty.
Furthermore, like the dove covered in silver, whose back is speckled with gold Psalm sixty-eight, verse thirteen, the divine scriptures should shine with silver on the surface and glow with gold in the hidden parts.
Therefore, it was rightly arranged that the purity of these words would be covered with a kind of veil of modesty, hidden from the indiscriminate eyes of everyone.
It was well arranged by divine design that these writings were covered, overshadowed by heavenly mysteries, just as divinity itself was concealed in its own secrecy.
Therefore, when we encounter references to the eyes, mouth, womb, hands, feet, and even the arms of the Lord in the holy books, it's important to remember that the Catholic Church does not describe God as having a physical body.
God is invisible, incomprehensible, unchangeable, and infinite.
These descriptions are symbolic, revealed through the Holy Spirit.
In Ezekiel chapter Forty, we find the inner parts of the Lord's temple, where the mysteries of the holy of holies are unveiled.
Sacred Scripture is passed down in three forms: the letter or history, which represents the body; the moral sense, known as the tropological sense, which represents the soul; and the higher understanding, called anagoge, which represents the spirit.
This threefold approach aligns with the confession of the Holy Trinity, sanctifying us entirely so that our spirit, soul, and body may be preserved blameless at the coming and judgment of our Lord Jesus Christ, as mentioned in First Thessalonians chapter Five, verses Twenty-Three to Twenty-Four.
Additionally, worldly wisdom has divided its philosophy into three parts: physics, ethics, and logic—natural, moral, and rational.
The natural part pertains to the causes of nature, the moral part addresses conduct, and the rational part, discussing higher matters, confirms that God is the Father of all.
This tripartite division of philosophy is not so different from the distinctions in our discussions, where learned individuals have suggested that the heavenly philosophy of the Scriptures should be explored through history, tropology, and anagoge.
History instills in us the truth of deeds and the faith of the narrative.
Tropology offers mystical insights for amending life, and anagoge leads us to the sacred secrets of heavenly figures.
Some also believe that allegory should be added as a fourth aspect of this genre of knowledge, suggesting that the narration of deeds foreshadows future events.
To clarify these ideas with examples: historically, the sky is what we see, and morally, it represents the heavenly life.
Allegorically, the waters symbolize baptism, and spiritually, they represent angels.
This is reflected in the phrase: "And the waters above the heavens praise the name of the Lord" Psalm One hundred forty-eight, verse four.
All the teachings of our religion stem from this dual source of knowledge: the practical, which is active, and the theoretical, which is contemplative. The active life is completed through the improvement of morals, while the contemplative is concerned with reflecting on heavenly matters and studying the divine Scriptures.
Practical knowledge extends into various fields, while contemplative knowledge is divided into historical discussion and spiritual interpretation. But for now, let's focus on the forms of spiritual understanding we promised, by examining the figures of each name, commonly found in that divine text.
Let us pray to the Lord to reveal the hidden things of His Scriptures, and express how the deeper meanings should be understood.
1. About divine names.
2. About things referred to as the Lord's members or those that signify Him.
3. About heavenly creatures.
4. About earthly things.
5. About living beings.
6. About various names and terms.
7. About the inner person.
8. About commonly used or present things.
9. About various meanings of words or names.
10. About Jerusalem and its adversaries.
11. About numbers, whose meanings are drawn into allegory.
Now, let's explain the meanings of names and words, as they are mostly interpreted through allegory, as the gift of God suggests.
Chapter One
On the Divine Names.
Almighty God is Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, both one and three.
One in nature, yet three in persons.
He alone is invisible, immense, and incomprehensible.
He alone is boundless, unchangeable, incorporeal, and immortal; present everywhere yet hidden; entirely whole and immense.
He is invisible because, in His essence, He cannot be seen at all, as the Apostle affirms, stating:
"Whom no one has seen or can see" First Timothy 6:16.
And in the Gospel: "No one has ever seen God" (John 1:18).
He is incorporeal because He is not made up of any bodily features.
The truth in the Gospel says: "God is spirit, and those who worship Him must worship in spirit and truth" (John 4:24).
He is immense because His size or nature cannot be measured by any of His creations.
Solomon, in his prayers, said: "If heaven and the highest heaven cannot contain you, how much less this house that I have built" First Kings 8:27.
He is boundless because He cannot be contained.
He is not confined to any place, for He does not move from one place to another, nor is He held in any place, as He testifies about Himself through Isaiah, saying: "Heaven is my throne, and the earth is my footstool" (Isaiah 66:1).
And through Jeremiah: "Do I not fill heaven and earth?" (Jeremiah 23:24).
The prophet confesses His immensity in the psalm, saying to the Lord: "If I ascend to heaven, you are there; if I make my bed in Sheol, you are there" (Psalm 139:8).
About His immensity, it is written in the book of Job: "He is higher than the heavens, what can you do? Deeper than the abyss, what can you know? His measure is longer than the earth and broader than the sea" (Job 11:8): for He who fills heaven and earth, undoubtedly, there is no place absent from His essence.
Above everything, He rules and commands; beneath everything, He supports and carries, not with the burden of labor, but with tireless strength.
No creature created by Him can stand on its own unless supported by Him who created it.
Outside of everything, yet not excluded.
He is unchanging, because He cannot change from what He is, as He says through the prophet Malachi, Malachi, "I am the Lord, and I do not change" (Malachi 3:6).
Therefore, God is said to be unchanging because emotions such as anger, fury, repentance, forgetfulness, remembrance, and similar things do not happen to Him.
His nature is simple, unchangeable, and undisturbed.
He is not one thing and possesses another, but He is what He possesses and what He is.
Immortal, because He cannot die in any way, as the Apostle testifies and says: "He alone has immortality, dwelling in unapproachable light, whom no human has seen or can see" (First Timothy 6:16).
Whenever sacred Scripture describes the movements of the soul or human body parts in God, such as head, hair, eyes, eyelids, ears, and other body parts or movements of the soul, like anger, fury, forgetfulness, repentance, remembrance, and similar things, they should not be understood literally by those who understand correctly.
Unlike the Jews and many heretics who think carnally, believing God to be corporeal and local.
Instead, all things about Him must be understood and confessed spiritually.
If anyone believes that human body parts or movements of the soul exist in God in a human manner, they are undoubtedly creating idols in their heart.
Therefore, as it is said, we read figuratively that the head of God is His divine essence, which precedes and to which all things are subject (First Corinthians 11:3).
The hair of His head should be typically understood as holy angels or powerful chosen ones, about which it is written in the book of Daniel: "I watched until thrones were set up, and the Ancient of Days took His seat. His clothing was white as snow, and the hair of His head was like pure wool" (Daniel 7:9).
This signifies God's purity through His white garments and the hair on His head, representing the holy angels and the multitude of purified saints.
Alternatively, His hair is likened to clean wool, suggesting He is the Ancient of Days.
God is said to have eyes because He sees everything, and nothing is hidden from Him.
As the Apostle says, in His presence, no creature is invisible, for everything is naked and exposed to His eyes.
Hebrews chapter four verse thirteen.
In another sense, His eyes represent the grace of His attention, as in the psalm, "The eyes of the Lord are on the righteous."
Psalm chapter thirty-three verse sixteen.
Alternatively, the eyes of the Lord refer to His commandments, through which the light of knowledge is given to us, as in the psalm, "The commandment of the Lord is clear, enlightening the eyes."
Psalm chapter nineteen verse nine.
The Lord's eyelids suggest His hidden and incomprehensible judgments or the spiritual speech in His divine books.
Regarding these hidden and incomprehensible mysteries and judgments, the psalm says, "His eyelids test the sons of men," meaning they examine.
Psalm chapter eleven verse five.
God is said to have ears because He hears everything, and nothing is hidden from Him in silence.
As written in the Book of Wisdom, "The ear of heaven hears everything, and the murmuring noise will not be hidden."
Wisdom chapter one verse ten.
The nostrils of God symbolize His inspiration in the hearts of the faithful, as in the Book of Kings: "Smoke rose from His nostrils," meaning the tearful contrition of the repentant as His inspiration.
Second Samuel chapter twenty-two verse nine.
The face of God represents His divine knowledge to all, about which it is written in the psalms: "Show us your face, and we shall be saved," meaning, grant us your knowledge, which He made known to humans through the Son of Man.
Psalm chapter eighty verse three.
As He says in the Gospel, "No one knows the Father except the Son, and anyone to whom the Son chooses to reveal Him."
Matthew chapter eleven verse twenty-seven.
Alternatively, the face of God signifies the invisible essence of the divinity of the Son of God.
Regarding this, the Lord replied to Moses through an angel, saying, "You shall see my back, but my face shall not be seen."
Exodus chapter thirty-three verse twenty-three.
It's as if to say, you won't be able to see my divinity.
The mouth of God is the Son of the Father, that is, Christ the Lord.
The prophet Isaiah, speaking on behalf of the Jews, said: "Because we have provoked his mouth to anger" (Isaiah chapter one, verse twenty).
Alternatively, his mouth can be understood as his word or command, as the same prophet said: "The mouth of the Lord has spoken this."
The Word of God is the Son of God the Father, through whom all things were made. As it's written in the psalm, "By the word of the Lord were the heavens made firm" (Psalm chapter thirty-three, verse six).
And elsewhere: "He sent his word, and healed them" (Psalm one hundred seven, verse twenty).
And in the Gospel according to John: "In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God" (John chapter one, verse one).
The tongue of God mystically signifies the Holy Spirit, through whom God the Father revealed his secrets to humans.
Thus, in the psalm: "My tongue is the pen of a ready writer" (Psalm forty-five, verse two).
The lips of God are mystically understood as the harmony of both testaments, about which it's written in Proverbs: "The mouth did not err in judgment" (Proverbs chapter sixteen, verse ten).
The arms of God the Father are understood as his Son and the Holy Spirit, as it is written in Isaiah: "And my arms shall judge the peoples" (Isaiah chapter fifty-one, verse five).
The arm of God is singularly accepted as the Son, about whom Jeremiah said: "And now, Lord God, you brought your people out of the land of Egypt with a strong hand, with an outstretched arm" (Jeremiah chapter thirty-two, verse twenty-one).
Therefore, the Son of God the Father is called the arm because the chosen creation is contained by him.
The right hand of God the Father is accepted as the only-begotten Son, about whom the psalm says from the perspective of the assumed man: "The right hand of the Lord has done valiantly" (Psalm one hundred eighteen, verse sixteen).
Alternatively, the right hand of the Lord signifies the glory of the Father and eternal blessedness, about which the psalm says from the perspective of the Father to the Son: "Sit at my right hand" (Psalm one hundred ten, verse one).
The right hand of God is also called the entire chosen creation in heaven and on earth.
Similarly, his left hand is understood as the reprobate creation, meaning all demons and wicked people, who will be placed on the left to endure eternal punishments (Matthew chapter twenty-five, verse thirty-three).
The Son of God the Father is accepted because, through Him, everything was created.
As it is written in Isaiah:
"My hand made all these things, and so they all came into being" (Isaiah 66:2).
In another sense, the hand of God is understood as His power, as it is written in the book of the prophet Jeremiah:
"As clay in the hand of the potter, so are you in my hand, house of Israel" (Jeremiah 18:6).
The hand of the Lord is also interpreted as a symbol of punishment.
Concerning this punishment, it is written in the prophet Zephaniah:
"I will stretch out my hand against Judah and against all who live in Jerusalem, and I will cut off from this place every remnant of Baal" (Zephaniah 1:4).
Regarding this punishment from the Lord, blessed Job says about himself:
"The hand of the Lord has touched me" (Job 19:21).
The finger of God is uniquely understood as the Holy Spirit, by whom the law is said to have been written on two stone tablets on Mount Sinai (Exodus 32:16).
He wrote who dictated what was to be written, that is, the Holy Spirit.
About whom the Lord in the Gospel says:
"If I drive out demons by the finger of God" (Luke 11:20).
Just as the finger is one with the hand or arm, and the hand or arm is one with the body in its nature, so the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit are three persons but one substance of divinity.
The fingers of God, in the plural, are understood as the holy prophets, through whom the Holy Spirit writes the books of the law and the prophets with His inspiration.
It is written in the psalm:
"I will see the heavens, the work of your fingers" (Psalm 8:4).
By heavens, it is certain that the books of the law and the prophets are mystically indicated, and by fingers, as said, the prophets.
The invisible image of God the Father is His only-begotten Son, about whom the Apostle says:
"The image of the invisible God" (Colossians 1:15).
For the image of God the Father in His Son is such that He begot Him not from another source, but from Himself, that is, from His own substance, similar to Himself in all things and equal.
In another way, the human soul, which He did not beget from Himself, that is, from His own substance, as many heretics have thought, but created from nothing.
Just like a king's image is reflected in his son, whom he has begotten to be like him—a man to a man—it's different when it comes to something like a ring, where an image is merely impressed in wax and isn't the same as the original.
A son naturally possesses what the father is.
The heart of God the Father reveals the secret of His wisdom, from which He begot the Word, His Son, without suffering and without a beginning.
As He says through the prophet:
My heart overflows with a good word
(Psalm 45:1).
God is said to have wings because, like a bird, He gathers and nurtures His chosen ones under Him like chicks, protecting them from the snares of the devil and evil people.
Hence the prophet says,
Protect me under the shadow of Your wings
(Psalm 17:8).
God is described as having shoulders because He carries the weak members of the Church as if on His shoulders.
This is written in the psalm:
He will cover you with His shoulders
(Psalm 91:4).
The belly is understood as the secret origin of His essence.
Thus, the psalm states:
From the womb, before the dawn, I begot you
(Psalm 110:3).
Alternatively, His womb suggests His incomprehensible judgments, which cannot be fathomed.
Regarding His hidden judgment, it is written in the book of Job:
Out of whose womb came the ice, and who gave birth to the frost of heaven?
(Job 38:29).
The back parts refer to the incarnation of the Son of God.
The Son, speaking to Moses on Mount Sinai through an angel, said:
You will see my back, but my face you cannot see
(Exodus 33:23).
The feet of God symbolize the establishment of His power, as He is present everywhere and all things are subject to Him.
As He says through Isaiah:
Heaven is my throne, and the earth is my footstool
(Isaiah 66:1).
Alternatively, the feet of the Son of God represent the incarnation, which is subject to divinity as the feet are to the head.
Just as divinity is expressed through the head, humanity is expressed through the feet, as written in Exodus:
They saw the God of Israel: there was under His feet like pavement of sapphire stone, and like the sky when it is clear
(Exodus 24:10).
Just as heavenly creatures or holy angels are symbolized by the sapphire stone, the serene sky represents the holy Church of the chosen, drawn from humanity, over which the Son of God, who became human, reigns forever.
Regarding this, the psalm states, "You have put everything under their feet" (Psalm 8:8).
The feet of the Lord, meaning Jesus Christ, also symbolize the holy preachers.
It is written in Deuteronomy: "Those who approach his feet will receive his teachings" (Deuteronomy 33:3).
The garment of the Son of God sometimes symbolically refers to his flesh, taken from divinity, as suggested by the divine books.
Isaiah, predicting about this garment of flesh, says: "Who is this who comes from Edom, with dyed garments from Bozrah?" (Isaiah 63:1).
Moreover, the garment of the Lord is understood as the holy Church, which is united with him through faith and love.
It is written in the psalm: "The Lord reigns, he is robed in majesty" (Psalm 93:1).
And in another psalm to the Lord: "You are clothed with honor and majesty, wrapped in light as with a garment" (Psalm 104:2).
The cloak of Christ is seen as the aforementioned Church, about which it is written in the book of Genesis: "He washed his robe in wine," referring to his flesh in the blood of his suffering, and his cloak, meaning his Church, in the blood of the grape (Genesis 49:11).
The shoes of the Lord Jesus Christ mystically signify his incarnation, which he graciously took from the mortality of the human race.
He himself, through the prophet in the psalm, speaks of this incarnation: "I will throw my shoe over Edom," meaning, I will reveal my incarnation to the people of the Gentiles (Psalm 60:10).
The steps of the coming of the Son of God into the world and his return to the Father are described in the psalm: "Your processions are seen, O God, the processions of my God, my King, in the sanctuary" (Psalm 68:25).
He came from heaven into the Virgin's womb, and, being born from the womb, he was placed in a manger (Luke 2:7).
After fulfilling all he was sent to do by the Father, he was hung on the wood of the cross; however, from the cross, he was taken down.
According to the body, he was buried, but according to the soul, he descended to the underworld.
On the third day, through the power of his divinity, he raised his body from the tomb.
On the fortieth day after his resurrection, he ascended into heaven in the sight of the Apostles, and sits at the right hand of the Father.
As stated in Acts chapter one, verse nine, and Mark chapter sixteen, verse nineteen, this means in his glory.
These are the steps of the Son of God: his descent and ascent, which are often read in the Holy Scriptures.
God is said to ascend when the Son took the flesh he assumed from us into heaven, leading captivity captive, as mentioned in Psalm sixty-eight, verse nineteen.
He took the nature of the human race, which was held captive by the devil in the world, with him into heaven, where it had never been before, as if it were a captive.
God is said to hide his face, as in Deuteronomy chapter thirty-two, verse twenty, when he hides his knowledge from some of the nations because of their faults.
We now see this fulfilled in the people of the Jews, who, by denying the Son of God, have lost the knowledge of the true God so much that they became like the nations who do not know the Lord.
God is said to show his face, as in Psalm seventy-nine, verse four, when, by the regard of his grace, he reveals himself through hidden inspiration in the hearts of his chosen ones, and instills his love in them to love him.
God is said to sit not physically in a human manner, but by power, to preside over all creation rationally.
As it is in the psalm: The Lord reigns over all nations, God sits on his holy throne, Psalm forty-seven, verse nine.
God is also said to sit on the Cherubim, as in Psalm ninety-nine, verse one, which is interpreted as the multitude or fullness of knowledge, signifying the holy angels or the minds of spiritual men, in whom God invisibly presides and reigns.
He sits in those who are full of his knowledge and love.
In the Proverbs of Solomon, it is written, His soul is the seat of wisdom; the wisdom of God the Father is Christ, as mentioned in First Corinthians chapter one, verse twenty-four, who is said to sit in the souls of the saints.
God is said to descend into the world when something entirely new is created by humans.
This is similar to the descent of the Son of God, who took on true flesh from the Virgin Mary for our redemption, graciously becoming a true human—not by losing what He was, but by taking on what He was not.
Regarding His descent, or incarnation, it is written in the psalm: "He inclined the heavens and came down, and thick darkness was under His feet" Psalm 18:10.
He inclined the heavens when, before His coming, He sent angels or prophets to announce His arrival to people.
The thick darkness under His feet refers to the fact that wicked people, due to their malice, could not recognize His incarnation, and still cannot.
God is said to stand when He patiently supports His creation, calling for repentance and conversion, as mentioned by the prophet Habakkuk: "He stood and measured the earth; He looked and shook the nations" Habakkuk 3:6.
This signifies that He stood to intervene and freed believers in Him from the bonds of sin.
God is said to pass by when He leaves the hearts of certain people, in whom He was once believed through faith, and then, due to creeping disbelief or sin, He departs and moves to others.
This is akin to moving from the Jews to the Gentiles, from heretics to Catholics, or from irreligious people to the religious.
God is said to withdraw and move to others not physically or visibly, but invisibly and through hidden and just judgment, as is His custom.
God is said to walk, not by moving from place to place, as it would be impious to believe so, but His walking is the delight in the hearts of the saints, as it is written: "I will live with them and walk among them, and I will be their God" Second Corinthians 6:16.
Or certainly, God walks by moving from place to place through His holy preachers.
God speaks invisibly, without the sound of a voice or any noise, by secretly inspiring His will and right understanding into the minds of the saints, or by revealing the future, as He did with the holy prophets.
Some people believe that God communicates in three main ways.
The first way is through a created being, like when He appeared to Moses in the burning bush in Exodus 3:2, to Abraham in Genesis 18, to Jacob in Genesis 32:24, and to other saints through angels.
The second method is through dreams, like those experienced by Jacob in Genesis 28:12, the prophet Zechariah in Zechariah 4:1, Joseph, Mary's husband, in Matthew 1:20, and others to whom He wished to reveal His secrets.
The third way is not through visible creatures or people, but by secretly inspiring their hearts invisibly.
This is reflected in the writings of the prophets, who, suddenly inspired by the divine spirit, would declare, "Thus says the Lord" in Isaiah 7:7.
When God "sees," it means approving good deeds, as in Genesis: "God saw everything that He had made, and indeed, it was very good" Genesis 1:31, indicating He showed goodness to those who understand.
Alternatively, God's "seeing" means knowing and rejecting human evil, as in the prophet Isaiah, "And God saw, and the evil appeared in His eyes" Isaiah 59:15.
Another aspect of God's seeing is making us see, as in the psalm, "Test me, God, and know my heart" Psalm 139:23, and further, "and see if there is any wicked way in me."
This way of speaking is also found in the book of Blessed Job, where regarding the wisdom of God the Father, through whom many great things were spoken, it is added about the Father, "Then He saw it and declared it; He established it and examined it" Job 28:27, meaning He made them see, preach, examine, and announce it to others.
Knowing by God involves making people aware, as He said to Abraham, "Now I know that you fear the Lord" Genesis 22:12.
For He does not learn in time, as He knows everything before it happens. But God is said to know by making people aware, so that what was previously unknown about themselves becomes clear to them through His questioning and testing.
This is similar to the passage in the law of Moses regarding the people of Israel: "I will test them," he says, "to see whether they will follow my commandments or not" Exodus 16:4.
God's act of not knowing refers to rejecting certain people as reprobates, as it is mentioned in the Gospel: "I do not know where you come from; depart from me, all you evildoers" Luke 13:27.
God is described as zealous when He often disciplines, corrects, and punishes His creatures, whom He does not want to perish, bringing them back to Him through punishment. Alternatively, God is said to be zealous when He does not want to leave any sin unpunished. He is just, and therefore all injustice is detestable to Him, which, as mentioned, He does not allow to go unpunished.
God is said to be angry, not because of any emotion or disturbance, which cannot happen to Him at all, but to impose just retribution on the sinning creature, that is, on wicked people and sinners, giving them what they deserve. This divine retribution is called His wrath Psalm 6:1.
God is said to repent, not because He regrets past actions like humans do; for He, who knows before they happen, cannot regret accomplished acts. But God's repentance means changing His decrees, and what was previously one way, changing to another. This might mean changing from good to bad due to the faults of those deserving it, as it is written that the Lord regretted making Saul king First Samuel 15:12. Or, as we now see with the Jewish people, who, although once they were God's people, due to their impiety, became the synagogue of Satan Revelation 2:9.
But changing from bad to good, as happened with the Gentile people, who were not previously God's people, but now through Christ's grace, have been made God's people Romans 9:26.
In this hidden way of God's judgment, Judas the traitor fell from the rank of apostleship Acts 1:18 and was plunged into the abyss of hell. But the thief, who was previously guilty of theft, was transferred from the cross to paradise Luke 23:43.
This change, whether from good to better, as mentioned, or from good to evil, or from evil to good, which happens by the hidden and just judgment of God, either through His severity of justice or through His mercy, is what we call the repentance of God:
this is more clearly written in the book of Jeremiah (Jeremiah 18:8).
God does not repent or change what He has decreed, as it is said in the psalm: God has sworn, and He will not repent; that is, the Father to the Son: You are a Priest forever, according to the order of Melchizedek (Psalm 110:4).
The Son of God is called the Priest of the Father, not according to divinity, but according to humanity, in which He offered Himself as an acceptable sacrifice to God the Father for us through His passion and death, so that He Himself was both the sacrifice and the priest.
God is said to forget when He does not have mercy on certain wicked and sinful people.
He does not do this out of cruelty, which is not in God, but through His hidden and just judgment.
God is said to harden the hearts of some wicked people, as it is written about Pharaoh, king of Egypt (Exodus 7:3); not that the Almighty God hardens their hearts by His power, which is impious to believe, but because of their own sins, when He does not remove the hardness of heart with which they commit all evil acts:
it is as if He hardens them, whom He allows to be hardened by just judgment.
God's sleeping is described when the only begotten Son of the Father was willing to die for us in assumed flesh:
to whom death was rightly predicted as sweet sleep, as He Himself says through the prophet Jeremiah, Therefore I awoke as if from sleep, and I saw, and my sleep was sweet to me (Jeremiah 31:26).
God is also said to sleep when His faith is not awake but sleeps amid the prosperity of this world and in the hearts of some faithful people.
This sleep was signified by Jesus Himself when He slept on the sea amid the waves (Mark 4:38).
Or certainly, God’s sleeping is to help the anxious more slowly, as it is said in the psalm: Arise, why do You sleep, O Lord (Psalm 44:23), etc.
God's waking is to reveal Himself clearly in the defense of His chosen ones.
Chapter Two
About what are called the members of the Lord, or what they signify about Him.
The eyes of the Lord are understood as divine observation.
In the Psalm: The eyes of the Lord are on the righteous (Psalm thirty-three, sixteen).
The eyelids of God represent His judgments that test the children of men; they are not wearied by the obscurities of things, but are exercised.
They are not inflated by knowledge, but are confirmed.
The ears of the Lord, when He chooses to listen.
In the Psalm: And His ears are attentive to their prayers (Psalm thirty-three, sixteen).
The mouth of the Lord signifies His word to people.
In the prophet: The mouth of the Lord has spoken (Isaiah one, twenty).
The word of the Lord refers to the Son.
In the Psalm: My heart has uttered a good word (Psalm forty-five, two).
The arm of the Lord, or hand, is the Son, through whom He made all things.
In the prophet: To whom has the arm of the Lord been revealed (Isaiah fifty-three, one).
The right hand of the Lord, as mentioned in the Psalm: The right hand of the Lord has done mighty things (Psalm one hundred seventeen, sixteen).
The finger of God is said to be the Holy Spirit, because of the distribution of gifts given by Him to each according to their own, whether of men or angels.
No parts of our body show such distribution as the fingers.
And do not be troubled by the diversity of the members, when the unity of the body builds up.
The womb of the Lord, the secret from which He brought forth the Son.
In the Psalm: From the womb before the morning star, I have begotten you (Psalm one hundred ten, three).
The feet of the Lord, the stability of eternity.
In the Psalm: Darkness was under His feet (Psalm eighteen, ten).
The footsteps of the Lord, signs of His secret works.
In the Psalm: And your footsteps were not known (Psalm seventy-six, twenty).
The steps of the Lord, His coming, or visitation.
In the Psalm: Your processions were seen, O God (Psalm sixty-eight, twenty-five).
The armor of the Lord, His help to the saints.
In the Psalm: Take up armor and shield (Psalm thirty-four, two).
The shield, the protection of the Lord.
In the Psalm: Lord, you have crowned us with the shield of your good will (Psalm five, twelve).
The sword, divine vengeance on the wicked.
In the Psalm: Draw out the spear, and close (Psalm thirty-four, three).
The bow, the intention of divine warning.
In the Psalm: He bent His bow and prepared it (Psalm seven, thirteen).
The arrows, divine commands, apostles, or prophets.
In the Psalm: He sent His arrows and scattered them (Psalm one hundred forty-four, six).
Sword, vengeance, or the word of the Lord.
The Apostle says: For the word of God is living, effective, and sharper than any two-edged sword.
Hebrews four, twelve.
Romphea, same as above.
Trumpet of the Lord, clear voice of the Lord.
The Apostle mentions: At the command, and the voice of the archangel, and the trumpet of God.
First Thessalonians four, fifteen.
Chariots of God, seat of God, or the fourfold nature of the Gospels.
In the psalm, it says: The chariots of God are ten thousand fold.
Psalm sixty-eight, eighteen.
Rod of the Lord signifies the kingdom, or correction of discipline.
In the psalm, we read: The rod of uprightness, the rod of your kingdom.
Psalm forty-five, seven.
Hand of the Lord, threats, or his vengeance.
Staff of the Lord, support of the Lord's consolation.
In the psalm: Your rod and your staff, they comfort me.
Psalm twenty-three, four.
Elsewhere, the staff of the Lord signifies the holy cross, or the discipline of the holy Church.
Also, a staff is any support, as in the Book of Tobit: The staff of our old age.
Tobit five, twenty-three.
Chapter Three
About Heavenly Creatures.
Coals symbolize the fire of love, serve as examples, or represent penance.
As mentioned in the psalm: "With burning coals" (Psalm 119:4).
Smoke signifies the beginnings of future repentance or acts as God's warning.
In the psalm, it states: "Smoke went up from His nostrils" (Psalm 18:8).
On another note, smoke can also mean vanity, like smoke that harms the eyes.
Fire represents the Holy Spirit.
In the Acts of the Apostles, it says: "And there appeared to them tongues as of fire, which rested on each of them, and they were all filled with the Holy Spirit" (Acts 2:3).
Heaven refers to apostles or saints because the Lord dwells in them.
"The heavens declare the glory of God" (Psalm 19:1).
In holy Scripture, heavens sometimes symbolize the higher realms of the world, unknown to us in their distinctions.
It is difficult but not impossible to discuss these realms for those to whom God grants understanding, as He did with the Apostle, who was caught up to the third heaven (Second Corinthians 12:2); apart from those material heavens.
The apostles are called heavens, as they are the preachers of the word of truth; through whom, like rain, we have been nourished, allowing the Church's harvest to grow worldwide.
All holy and just souls are also heavens, where God dwells in the temple of faith and action.
Additionally, heaven represents holy Scripture; from which the sun of wisdom, the moon of knowledge, and the stars of examples and virtues from ancient fathers shine upon us.
This heaven is stretched out like a skin (Psalm 104:2), because it is formed by the tongues of the flesh through its writers and is explained before our eyes by the words of teachers.
Clouds symbolize prophets or saints, who rain down the word of the Lord.
In Isaiah, it says: "I will command the clouds above not to rain" (Isaiah 5:6).
Clouds can also represent the times of the wicked in a negative sense: "My salvation has passed by like a cloud" (Job 30:15).
Thunder represents the voices of the Gospel because they resound from heaven with the words of God.
In the psalm: "The voice of Your thunder was in the whirlwind" (Psalm 77:18); this means, throughout.
Lightning signifies the brilliance of the Gospel.
In the psalm, it is written: "Your lightnings lit up the world" (Psalm 77:18).
Lightning, powers, or words of Jesus Christ.
In the psalm: He multiplied the lightning and troubled His enemies, referring to the Jews.
In Holy Scripture, the name of angels often refers to the Lord, as Isaiah testifies: His name shall be called the Angel of Great Counsel.
Sometimes it refers to the angelic choir, as Christ told Peter, "Do you think I cannot ask my Father, and He will provide me with more than twelve legions of angels?" Matthew 26:53.
Other times, it refers to the citizens of the heavenly Jerusalem taken from among humans, as the Lord said in the Gospel, "In the resurrection, they neither marry nor are given in marriage, but are like the angels of God in heaven." Matthew 22:30.
It can also refer to the faithful people, as in, "He set the boundaries of the nations according to the number of the children of Israel." Deuteronomy 32:8.
This name can also designate any righteous person, as the Lord said about John the Baptist, "Behold, I send my messenger before your face." Matthew 11:10.
Sometimes, it refers to preachers or priests, as it is written, "The lips of a priest should keep knowledge, and people should seek the law from his mouth, for he is the angel of the Lord of hosts." Malachi 2:7.
And the Apostle: "A woman should cover her head in the church because of the angels"—referring to the bishops; every faithful person who proclaims good things claims the name of angel for themselves if they live well. First Corinthians 11:10.
Lastly, the devil and his fellow apostates are called evil angels; although they have lost their angelic dignity, they have not lost the subtlety of angelic nature.
Through these evil angels, adversities or illnesses occur by God's permission, when and where He wills.
Thrones, angels, or saints, or the very power of reigning.
In the psalm, "Your throne, O God, is forever and ever." Psalm 45:7.
Also, in another part about the devil: "I will set my throne on the north." Isaiah 14:13.
Seats refer to the same, angels or saints, because the Lord sits in them, and through them, He decrees His judgments.
In the psalm, "God sits on His holy throne." Psalm 47:9.
The Sun, Lord Jesus Christ, who shines upon the earth.
In Solomon's writings, it is mentioned what the wicked will say at the end of time: "So, the sun of justice did not shine upon us" (Wisdom 5:6).
Elsewhere, persecution is symbolized, as in the phrase: "When the sun rose, they withered" (Matthew 3:6).
The moon represents the Church, as it shines during the night of this world.
In the psalm: "He made the moon to mark the seasons" (Psalm 104:19).
It also symbolizes the weakness of our human flesh, as its phases of waning reflect our mortality.
The stars represent the saints, the wise, or those who teach righteousness.
In Daniel: "The wise shall shine like the stars" (Daniel 12:3).
Clouds symbolize the hidden mysteries of God and sometimes represent God's angels.
In the prophet Nahum: "The clouds are the dust of His feet" (Nahum 1:3).
They can also signify the removal of sins, as Isaiah writes: "I have wiped out your iniquity like a cloud, and your sins like a mist" (Isaiah 44:22).
Darkness (or gloom) represents the covering of divine secrets.
In the psalms: "Darkness was under His feet" (Psalm 18:10).
The abyss represents the deep truths of Scripture.
In the psalms: "Deep calls to deep" (Psalm 42:8).
It can also refer to the depth of the Old and New Testaments, as in the idea that "Deep calls to deep"—the Old Testament proclaims the New. Alternatively, the abyss symbolizes the human mind, which cannot fully understand itself. Thus, the prophet says: "The abyss raises its voice from its depths" (Habakkuk 3:10).
Because the human mind cannot penetrate its own depths, it humbly praises God's divine nature, which it cannot comprehend.
The abyss can also signify God's judgments.
In the psalms: "Your judgments are like the great abyss" (Psalm 36:7).
When sinners pass from present evils to eternal punishment—moving from the fire of desire to the flames of hell—this is the hidden judgment of God.
Dew symbolizes the word of the Lord because it refreshes the hearts of people, as in: "Drop down dew, O heavens, from above" (Isaiah 45:8).
In the psalms: "Like the dew of Hermon, which falls on Mount Zion" (Psalm 133:3).
Rain represents the Lord's commandments or teachings, or the words of the apostles, because it waters the earth (meaning it nourishes people).
In the psalms: "God will send abundant rain upon your inheritance" (Psalm 68:10).
Snow symbolizes the purity of justice and the cleansing of baptism.
In the Psalm, Psalm 51:9, it says, "You will wash me, and I will be whiter than snow."
Hail represents the warnings of the Lord, striking the stubborn.
In Psalm 18:13, it mentions, "Hail and burning coals."
Additionally, in Psalm 78:47, it states, "He destroyed their vines with hail."
The coldness of snow and the hardness of hail reflect the life of the wicked, frozen in numbness and perishing through the hardness of evil.
Frost signifies abstinence, as it cools the body's heat.
In Psalm 119:83, it states, "I have become like a wineskin in the frost."
A storm signifies the force of persecutions or tribulations.
In Psalm 55:9, it says, "He rescued me from the spirit of faintness and from the storm."
Ice represents the hardness of sinners.
In Ecclesiasticus 3:17, Solomon states, "As ice in clear weather, your sins will melt away."
Winds symbolize the souls of the saints.
In Psalm 18:10, it says, "He soared on the wings of the wind."
Also, in a negative sense, in Matthew 7:25, it says, "The winds blew."
The north wind represents the devil, unfaithful or evil people, or the coldness of sin.
In Jeremiah 1:14, the prophet states, "From the north, evil will be unleashed upon the earth."
And elsewhere, "From the north, evil will spread."
In the Song of Solomon 4:16, it says, "Awake, O north wind," meaning, "Depart."
The term "right" is used similarly.
In Proverbs 25:23, Solomon states, "The north is a harsh wind."
However, it is called "right" because the devil arrogates to himself the name of "right," as if he were good, or because he becomes "right" to those who look to the west, that is, to sin.
The south wind represents the warmth of faith.
In Psalm 126:4, it states, "Like streams in the south."
It is also the Holy Spirit, as in the Song of Solomon 4:16, "Awake, O north wind, and come, O south wind," meaning, "Depart, devil, and come, nourishing spirit."
Air signifies the expression of vanity.
In First Corinthians 9:26, the Apostle states, "So I fight, not as one beating the air," meaning, not pursuing empty things.
Seasons represent the timely distribution of divine will.
In Psalm 104:19, it states, "He made the moon to mark the seasons."
Spring signifies the renewal of life, either through baptism or resurrection.
In Psalm 74:17, it states, "You made summer and spring."
Summer symbolizes the joy that is yet to come.
In the Psalm, as previously mentioned, winter represents the current life, persecution, or tribulation.
In the Gospel: Pray that your flight will not take place in winter or on the Sabbath (Matthew 24:20).
Years can sometimes symbolize eternity, as seen in: And your years will not fail (Psalm 102:28).
Other times, they represent the fleeting nature of life, as in: Our years are like a spider's web (Psalm 89:3).
The term months, which are made up of days, signifies the gathering of souls or the perfection of the saints, as in: From one month to another (Isaiah 66:23), referring to those at rest, who now have perfection in their actions.
Day and night represent justice and iniquity, faith and disbelief, prosperity and adversity.
In the Psalm: In the day the Lord commands his mercy, and at night he declares it (Psalm 41:9).
The term days also refers to the illumination of divine grace through various gifts of virtues.
Sometimes, day signifies a fallen angel, as Job mentions: Let those who curse the day curse it (Job 3:8).
The term night signifies either the blindness of ignorance or the bitterness of death.
Light and darkness are most often understood as day and night.
In the letter of John: Whoever loves his brother lives in the light, but whoever hates his brother is in the darkness (First John 2:10).
Light also reveals the intention of the heart.
Shadow signifies divine protection.
In the Psalm: Protect me under the shadow of your wings (Psalm 16:8).
Otherwise, it signifies forgetfulness or sins, as in: Sitting in darkness and in the shadow of death (Psalm 106:10).
Sometimes shadow signifies the delight in sins, as in Job: He sleeps under the shadow in secret (Job 40:16).
Again, shadow can mean forgetfulness of the mind, death of the flesh, or imitation of the devil.
The term light signifies the Lord or any righteous person, as in the Gospel: The true light that gives light to every man coming into the world (John 1:9).
And the Apostle: You were once darkness, but now you are light in the Lord (Ephesians 5:8).
It is also used to represent the illumination of faith and life.
Some believe we are in the final era of the world, akin to five hundred years, if a single day represents the whole age.
As stated in the Epistle of John:
My little children, it is the last hour
First John 2:18.
The East symbolizes the Savior, as light rises from there, especially as Luke mentions:
The dawn from on high has visited us
Luke 1:78.
And in Zechariah, it says:
Behold, the man whose name is the Branch
Zechariah 6:12.
The West represents the loss of a better life.
As the prophet states:
Your sun will set at noon
Amos 8:9.
The North is often associated with adversity, as the prophet speaks of the devil:
I will sit on the mount of assembly in the far reaches of the north
Isaiah 14:13;
and elsewhere:
From the north, disaster will be poured out
Jeremiah 1:14.
Morning signifies good deeds, baptism, or the resurrection of the Lord.
In the psalm:
In the morning, I will stand before you and see
Psalm 5:3;
and elsewhere:
From the watch of the morning until night, let Israel hope in the Lord
Psalm 130:6,
meaning from the resurrection of the Lord until the day of judgment.
Morning also represents the prosperity of this life, as mentioned in:
Woe to you, O land, when your king is a child, and your princes feast in the morning
Ecclesiastes 10:16;
they feast in the morning when lifted by worldly prosperity, instead of waiting for eternal happiness.
Noon signifies the clarity of teachings and deeds.
In Solomon:
Where do you rest at noon
Song of Solomon 1:7.
And in a negative sense in the psalm:
From the pestilence that stalks in darkness, nor the destruction that wastes at noonday
Psalm 91:6,
meaning openly.
Evening symbolizes the end of life, the world, or punishment;
as the psalm says:
Weeping may endure for a night, but joy comes in the morning
Psalm 30:5.
Dawn represents the mind of the just, moving from sin's darkness to the light, illuminated by the sun of justice
Song of Solomon 6:10.
Arcturus, shining with the rays of seven stars in the heavens, symbolizes the universal Church, as depicted in Revelation by the seven churches and seven lampstands
Revelation 1:20.
Orions, rising in winter, represent the holy martyrs who endured persecution and emerged into heaven.
The Hyades are named after the Greek letter y because they resemble its shape and are associated with bringing rain when they appear.
They symbolize holy preachers as they shower words and beneficially water the hearts of people.
In Greek, hyetos means rain, which is imber in Latin.
Chapter Four
About Earthly Things.
Earth represents the person himself. In the Gospel: Some fell on good soil.
Mark Chapter 4, Verse 8.
Also: You are dust, and to dust you shall return.
Genesis Chapter 3, Verse 19.
Also in a negative sense, about the sinner: You will eat dust all the days of your life.
Genesis Chapter 3, Verse 14.
In another way, those engaged in earthly deeds, through alms and tears, reach eternal life: as in the Psalms: He called the heavens above, and the earth to judge His people.
Psalm 50, Verse 4.
Dry land represents unfruitful people: in Ecclesiasticus: Cover the dry land with wickedness and deceit.
Ecclesiasticus Chapter 37, Verse 3.
Dust symbolizes sinners or the vanity of the flesh: in the Psalms: Like dust that the wind drives away.
Psalm 1, Verse 4.
Mud signifies the glue of sins: in the Psalms: Deliver me from the mud so that I do not sink.
Psalm 69, Verse 15.
Also in another sense.
In John: He made mud and smeared my eyes.
John Chapter 9, Verse 11.
Mountains represent the Lord, the Church, apostles, or saints, from the height of virtues: in the Psalms: Who descends on Mount Zion.
Psalm 133, Verse 3.
Also the prophet: The mountain of the house of the Lord will be established at the top of the mountains.
Isaiah Chapter 2, Verse 2.
Also in another prophet: Lest your feet stumble on the dark mountains.
Jeremiah Chapter 13, Verse 16.
meaning heretics.
Hills symbolize saints, but of lesser merit: in the Psalms: Mountains and all hills.
Psalm 148, Verse 9.
Also in another sense: in the Gospel: Every mountain and hill will be made low.
Luke Chapter 3, Verse 5.
Valleys represent the contrition of a humble heart: in the Psalms: And the valleys will be filled with grain.
Psalm 65, Verse 14.
Also in another sense: in the prophet: The valley of the sons of Hinnom.
Jeremiah Chapter 19, Verse 2.
Rock symbolizes Christ, from firmness: in the apostle: The rock was Christ.
First Corinthians Chapter 10, Verse 4.
Stones sometimes represent Christ, or saints: in the Psalms: The stone the builders rejected.
Psalm 118, Verse 22.
Also: A stone was cut out of the mountain without hands and filled the whole earth.
Daniel Chapter 2, Verse 35.
Also: You, as living stones, are being built up.
First Peter Chapter 2, Verse 5.
Also in another sense, about the foolish and hard-hearted: God is able to raise up children to Abraham from these stones.
Matthew Chapter 3, Verse 9.
And in another place: I will remove the heart of stone from your flesh.
Ezekiel 36:26. The field, this world: in the Gospel: The field is this world.
Matthew 13:38.
Sometimes, the field represents the discipline of heavenly study, where the treasure is hidden, meaning heavenly desire.
Matthew 13:44.
Fields can also refer to the holy or divine Scriptures, because they provide nourishment for souls, as mentioned in the psalm: And your fields will be filled with abundance.
Psalm 65:12.
In a negative context: In the field of Taneos.
Psalm 78:43.
Additionally, fields symbolize just people because of their equality.
Pasture represents spiritual nourishment, as stated in the psalm: He has placed me in a place of pasture.
Psalm 23:2.
Cultivation refers to the saints who are cultivated by God, as mentioned by the Apostle: You are God's cultivation.
First Corinthians 3:9.
The farmer is God, as stated in the Gospel: I am the true vine, and my Father is the farmer.
John 15:1.
Furrows symbolize the hearts of the saints, as mentioned in the psalm: Drunken are its furrows.
Psalm 65:11.
The seed represents divine preaching, as described in the Gospel: A sower went out to sow his seed.
Luke 8:5.
The harvest signifies the abundance or multitude of the faithful, as stated in the Gospel: Lift up your eyes, and see the regions, for they are white for harvest.
John 4:35;
and in another place: The harvest is the end of the age, and the reapers are angels.
Matthew 13:39.
Sheaves represent the fruits of righteousness, as mentioned in the psalm: Bringing their sheaves.
Psalm 126:6.
Straw refers to those dry to faith or empty, as described by the Apostle: Wood, hay, straw.
First Corinthians 3:12;
and in the prophet: Woe is me, for I have become like one who gathers straw in the harvest, meaning I have found no fruits of good work.
Micah 7:1.
In another place: Straw gathered represents the synagogue of sinners.
Ecclesiasticus 21:10.
The threshing floor symbolizes the Church, as described in the Gospel: And he will clean his threshing floor.
Matthew 3:12.
The winnowing fan represents the examination of God's justice, as stated in the Gospel: His winnowing fan is in his hand.
Wheat symbolizes the word of God, or the holy or chosen ones of God, as mentioned in the Gospel: He will gather his wheat into the barn.
Matthew 3:12.
Barley represents the letter of the law, as described in the Gospel: There is a boy here who has five barley loaves, symbolizing the letter, the five books of Moses.
John 6:9.
Chaff represents sinners, as stated in the Gospel: But he will burn the chaff with unquenchable fire.
Matthew 3:12.
Jerome: What is straw compared to wheat, says the Lord. Jeremiah 23:28.
Weeds, scandals, or those living wickedly: in the Gospel:
An enemy came and sowed weeds among the wheat.
Matthew 13:25.
Vineyard, Church, or people of Israel: in the psalm:
You brought a vine out of Egypt.
Psalm 80:8.
Also in a negative sense:
For their vine is from the vine of Sodom.
Deuteronomy 32:32.
Vine, Christ: in the Gospel:
I am the true vine.
John 15:1.
Also in another sense: in the Song of Moses.
Branches, apostles, or saints: in the Gospel:
I am the true vine, you are the branches.
And in a negative sense: as mentioned above: And their branches are from Gomorrah.
Grapes; fruits of righteousness: in Isaiah:
I expected it to produce grapes.
Isaiah 5:4.
Also in a negative sense: Their grapes are grapes of gall.
Deuteronomy 32:32.
Cluster, Church, or body of the Lord: In Numbers:
Because the children of Israel brought back a cluster from there.
Numbers 13:24.
Harvest, end of the age, or vengeance on the people: in the psalm:
All who pass along the way pluck its fruit.
Psalm 80:13.
And Joel:
Put in the sickle, for the harvest of the earth is ripe.
Joel 3:13.
Winepress, altar, because offerings are gathered there like fruits: as in Isaiah,
And I built a winepress in it.
Isaiah 5:2.
And otherwise, winepress, the pressure of tribulations in the holy Church where the faithful are tested.
In the title of the psalm: For the end, for the winepresses.
Psalm 8:1.
Grass, people, flesh, or vain glory: In Isaiah:
All flesh is grass, and all its glory like the flower of the grass.
Isaiah 40:6.
Herb, joy, or certain rudiments of a progressing soul: In Genesis:
Let the earth bring forth green herbs.
Genesis 1:11.
Also in a negative sense: In the morning it is like the grass that passes away.
Psalm 90:6.
Flowers, Christ, or the example of righteousness or the beginning of good deeds: as in the Song of Songs:
Support me with flowers.
Song of Solomon 2:1.
Lily, Christ, or angels in the brightness of righteousness: In Solomon:
I am the flower of the field and the lily of the valleys.
Song of Solomon.
Roses, martyrs, from the redness of blood: in Solomon.
As a rose blooms over moist streams, confessors are like violets due to the similarity of their bruised bodies.
In the Song of Songs: Flowers have appeared on the earth.
(Song of Solomon, Chapter 2, Verse 12)
Forests and nations are mentioned in the Psalms: We found it in the fields of the forest.
(Psalm 132, Verse 6) From these forests came two bears, specifically Vespasian and Titus, the kings of the Romans, at the command of the figurative Elisha.
After forty-two years of his ascension to the heavens, they devoured the Jewish children.
(Second Kings, Chapter 2, Verse 24)
Thickets, dense or covered, of divine Scripture.
In the Psalms: And He revealed the thickets.
(Psalm 29, Verse 9)
Wood represents sinners destined for fire.
In Ecclesiastes: He who cuts wood will be endangered by it.
(Ecclesiastes, Chapter 10, Verse 9) In a good sense: And he will be like a tree planted.
(Psalm 1, Verse 3)
Sometimes, wood symbolizes the holy cross, as the prophet says: Let us put wood in his bread; meaning to hang Christ on the cross in the flesh.
(Jeremiah, Chapter 11, Verse 19) Also: Behold, I gather two sticks.
(First Kings, Chapter 17, Verse 12)
Wood also signifies the righteous and sinners.
As Solomon says: If a tree falls to the south or to the north, wherever it falls, there it will lie.
(Ecclesiastes, Chapter 11, Verse 3) On the day of death, the righteous falls to the south, the sinner to the north.
The righteous are led to joy through the fervor of the spirit, while the sinner is rejected with the apostate angel in a cold heart.
Root, origin: as mentioned in the Apostle: But if the root is holy, so are the branches.
(Romans, Chapter 11, Verse 16) In a bad sense, in the Psalms: He will uproot your root from the land of the living.
(Psalm 52, Verse 5)
Tree, man, by the fruit of deeds: in the Gospel: Either make the tree good and its fruit good; and in a bad sense: Or make the tree bad and its fruit bad.
(Matthew, Chapter 12, Verse 33) Some believe this tree should be taken as the will of man rather than the man himself.
Christ was also a tree when he resurrected, having been a grain when he died.
Branch, succession: as mentioned in the Apostle: But if the root is holy, so are the branches.
(Romans, Chapter 11, Verse 16) Likewise, in another sense, in Daniel: Cut off its branches.
(Daniel, Chapter 4, Verse 14)
Similarly, branches represent the teachings of the holy Fathers.
In the Gospel, some cut branches from the trees. Matthew twenty-one, verse eight.
A leaf symbolizes a teaching word.
As stated in the psalm: And its leaf will not wither.
Psalm one, verse three.
In another sense, a leaf represents clothing and beauty under the protection of divine grace.
Negatively, when He found no fruit on it because of the leaves.
Matthew twenty-one, verse nineteen.
This suggests words without substance.
Hence, the Apostle advises us to love not just in words or speech but in actions and truth.
First John three, verse eighteen.
A person is also likened to a leaf, having fallen from the tree in paradise.
Apples, representing the virtues of the saints, are mentioned in the Song of Songs: And eat the fruit of his apples.
Song of Solomon five, verse one.
The palm signifies perfection or victory.
As noted in the psalm: The righteous will flourish like a palm tree.
Psalm ninety-two, verse twelve.
The palm grows slowly but remains vibrant for a long time.
Thus, the holy Church, through many challenges, reaches a state of faith and aims to endure for the gathering of many into the glory of the same faith.
The palm is tightly bound below by its bark layers but expands above with its lush green foliage.
Similarly, the life of the chosen is often undervalued below but beautiful above.
The palm has a unique quality distinguishing it from other trees.
While most trees are sturdy near the ground and narrow as they rise, the palm grows stronger near its branches and fruit.
What starts slender below broadens at the top.
To whom are such trees similar, if not to earthly minds?
They are broad below, narrow above.
Indeed, worldly loves are strong in earthly matters but weak in heavenly ones.
People strive for temporal glory even unto death, yet for the hope of eternity, they endure little effort.
For earthly gains, they tolerate many injuries, but for heavenly reward, they refuse even the smallest insult of a single word.
They can stand all day before an earthly judge, showing great strength.
Yet, in prayer before the Lord, they tire in less than an hour.
Often, they endure exposure, sleeplessness, and hunger to gain wealth and honors, inflicting much self-denial upon themselves.
On the other hand, the progress of a righteous life is symbolized by the evenness of palm trees.
These people are not strong in earthly pursuits and weak in heavenly ones; instead, they show more devotion to God than they remember showing to the world.
Therefore, it is rightly written, as I have reminded you: "The righteous will flourish like a palm tree."
Cedar trees represent men of greater power: "He will grow like a cedar of Lebanon" (Psalm 92:15).
And in a bad sense, they represent the proud and arrogant: "The Lord will break the cedars of Lebanon" (Psalm 29:5).
The olive tree symbolizes a holy person abundant in mercy: "But I am like a fruitful olive tree in the house of God" (Psalm 52:10).
The wild olive tree represents a person without fruit, or a Gentile: "If you were cut from a wild olive tree" (Romans 11:24).
The fig tree sometimes represents the synagogue: "The fig tree withered immediately" (Matthew 21:19).
And in Habakkuk: "The fig tree will not bear fruit" (Habakkuk 3:17).
The fig tree is understood in both good and bad senses, as in Isaiah: "And he showed me very good figs, and very bad ones" (Jeremiah 24:3).
And the Lord said to Nathanael: "When you were under the fig tree that is, under original sin, I saw you to redeem you" (John 1:48).
The fig tree also represents human nature or the unbelieving synagogue, which, though well-created, fell of its own accord and did not produce the fruit of God's command or good works.
Thus, the Lord sought fruit from it for three years and found none because He visited, admonished, and sought it during three periods (Luke 13:7).
That is, before the law, under the law, and under grace.
Before the law, He sustained it by sparing it; under grace, He demonstrated His presence in His incarnation; under the law, He taught by commanding.
Yet, during these three periods, it remained fruitless and withered from the roots.
The sycamore, known as the foolish fig tree, was climbed by little Zacchaeus (Luke 19:4).
He saw the Lord because those who humbly embrace worldly wisdom can subtly perceive the wisdom of God.
We climb the sycamore wisely if we hold onto the commendable and divinely commanded foolishness.
What seems more foolish in this world than not seeking what's lost, giving away what we have, letting go to those who take, and not returning injury for injury?
Yet, according to the Lord's command, we show patience in all things.
Hyssop, a humble herb that clings to the stone it grows on, is known for its roots that penetrate rock.
It especially heals the lungs.
Pride is associated with the lungs: where there's inflation, there's breath.
Thus, hyssop symbolizes humility and patience.
Buckthorn, nettles, thistles, brambles, and thorny plants symbolize the cruel, deceitful, proud, and wicked, whom no good or gentle person can touch or chastise without feeling remorse.
They also represent vices and the struggles of temptation, as mentioned in Genesis: "Thorns and thistles shall it bring forth for you" (Genesis 3:18).
The pomegranate represents the Church, drawing from many nations or possessing diverse graces, as noted in the Song of Songs: "Your branches are a paradise of pomegranates with the fruit of apples" (Song of Songs 4:3).
Alternatively, apples are seen as the fruits of good deeds with a pleasant fragrance, symbolizing the grace of a good reputation and the fruits of good character.
A reed represents a sinner, someone fragile in faith, or under some temptation, as mentioned in the Gospel: "A bruised reed he will not break" (Matthew 12:20).
A reed also signifies weak support, as described in Isaiah: "Why do you rely on this reed-like staff of Egypt? If anyone leans on it, it will break and pierce his hand..." (Isaiah 36:6).
The bramble is thought by some to prefigure the Virgin Mary because, from the thorny human condition, she brought forth the Savior like a rose, or because she bore the divine brilliance without a man's involvement.
In Exodus: "The Lord appeared to him in a flame of fire from the midst of a bush, and he saw that the bush was burning, yet it was not consumed" (Exodus 3:2).
The burning bush, which was not consumed, symbolizes the Jewish people, who received the flame of God's law yet faced the consequences of sin.
Thorns sometimes represent the harmful worries of wealth, suffocating the mind and the anxieties of this world.
As the Gospel states:
Some fell among thorns (Luke chapter eight, verse six);
and again:
They are choked by worries, riches, and pleasures (Luke chapter eight, verse fourteen).
Thistles symbolize the sharp points of vices or temptations, as mentioned in Genesis:
Thorns and thistles will it bring forth to you (Genesis chapter three, verse eighteen).
Springs represent baptism, as indicated in the psalm:
As the deer longs for streams of water (Psalm forty-two, verse two).
The spring also represents Christ, as seen in the psalm:
My soul thirsts for God, the living spring (Psalm forty-two, verse two);
and in Isaiah:
On that day a spring will be open to the house of David (Zechariah chapter thirteen, verse one).
In a negative sense, the Apostle refers to:
Springs without water (Second Peter chapter two, verse seventeen).
Waters often represent temptations, as noted in the psalm:
Perhaps the waters would have overwhelmed us (Psalm one hundred twenty-four, verse four).
Also:
The waters have come up to my soul (Psalm sixty-nine, verse two).
In a positive sense, Jeremiah states:
They have forsaken me, the spring of living water (Jeremiah chapter two, verse thirteen);
and in Isaiah:
You who are thirsty, go to the water (Isaiah chapter fifty-five, verse one),
referring to the teaching.
In Holy Scripture, water sometimes signifies the Holy Spirit.
This is illustrated by the outpouring of the Holy Spirit: as mentioned in the Gospel:
Whoever believes in me, rivers of living water will flow from within them (John chapter seven, verse thirty-eight).
The angelic choir is also expressed through water, as in the psalm:
Let the waters above the heavens praise the name of the Lord (Psalm one hundred forty-eight, verse four).
Additionally, sacred knowledge is symbolized by water, as in the Book of Wisdom:
They will drink the water of wisdom (Ecclesiasticus chapter fifteen, verse three).
Furthermore:
The words from a man's mouth are deep waters (Proverbs chapter eighteen, verse four).
Perverse knowledge is also described through water.
As Solomon states, the woman symbolizing heresy flatters with cunning persuasions, saying,
Stolen water is sweeter (Proverbs chapter nine, verse seventeen).
Water can also signify the prosperity of this world, as in the psalm:
We went through fire and water, and you brought us to a place of abundance (Psalm sixty-six, verse twelve).
Fire and water are both dangerous, as noted in the Gospel: "It often threw him into fire and into water to destroy him."
Mark Chapter 9, Verse 22.
When challenges and hardships arise in life, it's like facing fire.
When prosperity and abundance overflow, it's like water.
Water also represents people, as stated in Revelation: "The many waters are many peoples."
Revelation Chapter 17, Verse 15.
Water not only signifies the movement of people but also represents the minds of good individuals following the teachings of faith, as mentioned in Isaiah: "Blessed are you who sow beside all waters."
Isaiah Chapter 32, Verse 20.
Water also symbolizes baptism, as the Evangelist John says: "There are three that testify on earth: the Spirit, the water, and the blood."
First John Chapter 5, Verse 8.
The Spirit makes us children of God through adoption.
The water of the sacred font cleanses us.
The blood of the Lord redeems us.
A torrent refers to the rush of persecution or the slipping away of death, as in the psalm: "He drinks from the torrent along the way."
Psalm 110, Verse 7.
Also: "The torrent has overwhelmed my soul."
Psalm 124, Verse 5.
And in a positive sense: "You give them drink from your river of delights."
Psalm 36, Verse 8.
Torrents are also likened to holy preachers who, during this life, flow to us with divine words, gathered like waters in winter.
When the summer sun comes, they withdraw, for when the light of the eternal homeland shines, they will cease to preach.
Rivers can represent the peoples of unbelievers, as in the psalm: "By the rivers of Babylon."
Psalm 137, Verse 1.
Also in a positive sense: "Rivers of living water will flow from within them;" meaning various gifts of the Spirit.
John Chapter 7, Verse 38.
Thus in the psalm: "The river's flow brings joy to the city of God."
Psalm 46, Verse 4.
The lake represents hell, as in the psalm: "You have put me in the lowest pit;" that is, in that place of hell where sinners are kept in penal custody.
Psalm 88, Verse 6.
The sea signifies the world or the peoples, as mentioned in the psalm: "This great and wide sea."
Psalm 104, Verse 25.
The sea also signifies sacred Scriptures, as in Ezekiel: "The appearance of the wheels and their work was like the vision of the sea."
So, holy scriptures are aptly likened to the vision of the sea, as the words are affirmed by the sacrament of baptism.
Fish can symbolize both saints and sinners.
In the Gospel: "And they hauled in a net full of large fish" John 21:11.
Also, in a negative sense: "But the bad ones they threw away" Matthew 13:48.
Again, fish express genuine faith; just as a fish is born, lives, and thrives under water, so faith in God, which brings the joys of another life through current sorrows and unceasing tears, is sanctified in the heart by the unseen grace of the spirit through baptism.
It is sustained by the invisible aid of divine protection, so it does not falter.
It does good as much as it can by the unseen promise of rewards, remembering the words of the Apostle: "For the things which are seen are temporary, but the things which are not seen are eternal" Second Corinthians 4:18.
Moreover, the roasted fish signifies suffering; the waves signify temptations.
In the psalms: "All your waves and billows have gone over me" Psalm 41:8.
Waves also signify the fear of God, as in the book of Job: "For I have always feared the Lord like swollen waves over me" Job 31:23.
Thus, as mentioned earlier in the Song: "The waves congealed in the heart of the sea" Exodus 15:8.
Islands represent souls or the Churches of God, which face various waves of temptations.
In the psalms: "Let many islands be glad" Psalm 96:1.
The shore represents the end of the world.
In the Gospel: "And sitting by the shore, they chose the good ones into vessels" Matthew 13:48.
The sand of the sea represents the countless multitudes of people.
In Genesis: "And I will multiply your descendants, that is, the saints, like the stars of heaven, and like the sand, sinners, which is by the seashore" Genesis 22:17.
Chapter Five
About Living Creatures.
Birds, the holy ones, soar upward with their hearts.
In the Gospel, it says: "And it grew large branches, so that the birds of the air could nest in its shade" Mark 4:32.
Birds can also symbolize excessive thoughts, as shown by Abraham, who drove away birds that swooped down on his sacrifice to God Genesis 15:11.
During the sacrifice of prayer, unwelcome thoughts can intrude and pollute the hearts of the just.
But when these thoughts are quickly driven away with discretion, it prevents the shadow of temptation from covering the heart, which might have been touched by illicit pleasure.
Flying represents the holy ones' transcendence into God or understanding of Scriptures.
In Psalms, it says: "I will fly away and be at rest" Psalm 55:7.
Birds, in a positive sense, reflect what we've discussed about them.
In a negative sense, they symbolize proud demons, as the Lord says in the Gospel: "Other seed fell by the path, and the birds of the air devoured it" Luke 8:5.
Evil spirits besiege human minds, planting harmful thoughts and snatching the word of life from memory.
Wings symbolize the two Testaments.
In Ezekiel, it says: "Each covered its body with two wings" Ezekiel 1:23.
Wings also represent the virtues of the holy ones, through which they fly to contemplation or heavenly things, or divine protection.
Feathers symbolize Scripture.
In the psalm, it mentions: "The wings of a dove covered with silver" Psalm 68:14.
The nest represents the Church or a place of high rest for the holy ones.
In the psalm, it states: "The turtledove has found a nest for itself, where it may lay its young" Psalm 84:4.
Alternatively, a nest signifies a good conscience, where good thoughts are nurtured and brought into action, later becoming known as children.
In the psalm, it says: "Your children will be like olive shoots around your table" Psalm 128:3.
Chicks symbolize the holy ones.
This is mentioned in the psalm, as noted earlier.
In the book of Job, it says: "Its young ones drink blood" Job 39:30.
This refers to the children of the holy Church, who partake in the blood of Christ.
And in a negative sense.
In Solomon, it says: "And may the ravens of the valley pick it out" Proverbs 30:17.
Eagles symbolize the holy ones.
In the Gospel, it says: Wherever the body is, there the eagles will gather.
This verse is from the book of Matthew, chapter twenty-four, verse twenty-eight.
It suggests that holy souls, upon leaving the body, are gathered to Christ, who took on a body and died for them.
The eagle also symbolizes Christ, as Solomon notes: The way of the eagle in the sky.
This is from Proverbs, chapter thirty, verse nineteen, referring to Christ's ascension.
In a negative context, it is said: May the eagle's chicks devour him.
Similarly, in Jeremiah, regarding evil spirits: Our pursuers were swifter than eagles.
This is from Lamentations, chapter four, verse nineteen.
The eagle can also represent earthly storms.
The ostrich symbolizes any heretic, philosopher, or hypocrite, who seems to possess the wings of wisdom but does not fly.
In Isaiah, it states: It will be a habitation of dragons, and a pasture for ostriches.
This is from Isaiah, chapter thirty-four, verse thirteen.
The ostrich lays eggs but does not nurture its young, much like a hypocrite who preaches well but fails to lead by example.
As noted in the book of Job: The ostrich leaves its eggs on the ground and forgets that a foot may crush them.
This is from Job, chapter thirty-nine, verse fourteen.
The pelican represents the Lord Christ in His Passion or a holy man dedicated to solitude.
As mentioned in the psalm: I am like a pelican of the wilderness.
This is from Psalm one hundred two, verse seven.
The raven symbolizes the darkness of sins or demons.
In Proverbs, it says: Let the ravens of the valley pick it out or the young eagles.
This is from Proverbs, chapter thirty, verse seventeen.
However, in a positive sense, in the Song of Songs about the bridegroom: His locks are like clusters of dates, black as a raven.
This is from Song of Solomon, chapter five, verse eleven.
The partridge is a symbol of the devil.
As stated by the prophet: The partridge called, gathering what it did not lay.
This is from Jeremiah, chapter seventeen, verse eleven.
The dove represents the Holy Spirit.
In the Gospel, it is written: And I saw the Spirit of God descending like a dove.
This is from John, chapter one, verse thirty-two.
In a negative sense, as the prophet says: And Ephraim is like a dove, silly and without sense.
This is from Hosea, chapter seven, verse eleven.
The turtledove symbolizes the Holy Spirit, a holy person, or spiritual understanding.
In the Song of Songs, it says: The voice of the turtledove is heard in our land.
This is from Song of Solomon, chapter two, verse twelve.
The dove is called the Holy Spirit when there is a clear explanation of the holy Scriptures.
The turtledove is considered the Holy Spirit when the Scriptures are elevated with deep and obscure mysteries.
The dove symbolizes simplicity, while the turtledove signifies chastity because it doesn't seek another mate after losing its first.
The kite, I think, represents a greedy or arrogant person.
In the psalm, according to the Hebrews: The fir tree is the kite's home.
The hawk sometimes symbolizes a holy person who captures the kingdom of God.
By shedding its old feathers and casting off deceitful habits, it embraces a new life of simple, righteous living.
In the Book of Job: Does the hawk soar by your wisdom?
The night heron represents Christ or a holy person who is despised by unbelievers.
In the psalm: I have become like an owl in a ruined house (Psalm 102:7).
The sparrow sometimes represents the Lord or a holy person.
In the psalm: Even the sparrow finds a home (Psalm 84:3).
And elsewhere, it's about any Christian told by heretics, who believe they alone possess Christ, referred to as the mountain in the Scriptures: Fly to the mountain like a sparrow (Psalm 11:1).
The rooster, I believe, represents the Lord or a holy person.
In Solomon: The rooster walks proudly among the hens (Proverbs 30:31).
And in Job: Who gave the rooster understanding?
(Job 38:36).
And on the other hand: I will carry you away like a rooster (Isaiah 22:17).
The name of the rooster signifies holy preachers who, amidst the darkness of this life, announce the coming light as if singing.
They say: The night is gone, and the day is near.
The rooster is also described as walking with girded loins (Proverbs 30:31), because these holy preachers, announcing the true morning in this night's darkness, restrain the excesses of lust in their bodies, to whom the Lord says, Let your loins be girded (Luke 12:35).
The rooster is also granted understanding from above because the teacher of truth is divinely provided with discernment to know what, to whom, when, and how to impart, as not every exhortation suits everyone, since not everyone follows the same moral path.
The hen represents wisdom, the Church, or the soul.
In the Gospel: As a hen gathers her chicks under her wings (Matthew 23:37).
Bats are creatures of darkness associated with idols.
In the prophet it is written: "So that you may worship moles and bats" (Isaiah 2:20).
There are also impure thoughts that demons introduce.
In reference to the beetle, the prophet says: "And the beetle will cry out from the wood," which some interpret as relating to the Lord.
Locusts refer to people.
In the Gospel, it says: "His food was locusts" (Matthew 3:4).
The term locusts sometimes describes the people of the Jews, at other times converted gentiles, flattering speech, or even the resurrection of the Lord.
It can also signify the life of preachers.
The bee symbolizes virginity or wisdom.
In Solomon it is written: "Go to the bee and learn how industrious it is" (Proverbs 6:6).
In a negative sense, the prophet mentions: "And the bee that is in Assyria" (Isaiah 7:18).
And in Psalms: "They surrounded me like bees" (Psalm 118:12), referring to the malicious and angry.
Bees can also represent those who speak sweetly but secretly harm, like those who offer the sweetness of honey while inflicting a sting.
This name can indicate wise sayings as well, such as: "Pleasant words are like a honeycomb" (Proverbs 16:24).
The fly can symbolize the devil, his servant, or the impurity of idolatry.
As Solomon says: "Dead flies spoil the perfume's fragrance" (Ecclesiastes 10:1).
Beasts can signify the devil or fierce humans.
In the psalm it says: "Do not hand over the souls who confess to you to the beasts" (Psalm 74:19).
The lion represents the Lord, as the Apostle writes: "The Lion of the tribe of Judah has triumphed" (Revelation 5:5).
But also in a negative sense: "Lest he tear my soul like a lion" (Psalm 7:2).
Additionally: "Our adversary the devil prowls around like a roaring lion" (First Peter 5:8).
A lioness signifies the proud or headstrong.
The leopard can symbolize the devil or a sinner with varied behavior, as the prophet asks: "Can an Ethiopian change his skin, or a leopard its spots?" (Jeremiah 13:23).
The elephant represents a massive sinner.
In Kings it is noted: "They brought to Solomon apes and elephants" (First Kings 10:22).
The bear symbolizes the devil, cruel leaders, or plotters.
As mentioned in Kings: "And two bears came out and ate them" (Second Kings 2:24).
This is because Vespasian and Titus, the Roman emperors, destroyed the Jews.
The deer symbolizes Christ or the saints.
In the Psalm, it says: As the deer longs for streams of water.
(Psalm 42:2)
And again in the Psalm: The high mountains are for the deer; the rocks are a refuge for the hedgehogs.
(Psalm 104:18)
This signifies those dedicated to the contemplative life.
The wolf represents the devil or a heretic.
In the Gospel, it is said: Inwardly they are ravenous wolves.
(Matthew 7:15)
Also, in a positive sense, Benjamin is described as a ravenous wolf, representing the Apostle Paul.
(Genesis 49:27)
The boar signifies the devil.
As stated in the Psalm: The boar from the forest will ravage it.
(Psalm 80:14)
The tiger sometimes represents feminine arrogance.
In the book of Job, according to the Hebrew, it's written: The tiger perished because it had no prey.
(Job 4:11)
The unicorn signifies singular power or saints who uphold the unique word of God.
In the Psalm, it says: And the beloved is like a young wild ox.
(Psalm 29:6)
In another sense, it is used in: And from the horns of the unicorns, my humility.
(Psalm 22:21)
In a negative sense, it refers to anyone proud and violent, or holding only one testament, as the Psalmist, in the person of the Lord, says: Deliver me, Lord, from the horns of the unicorns.
The rhinoceros, known for strength and bravery, is used in both positive and negative contexts.
In the book of Job, according to the Hebrew, it asks: Will the rhinoceros consent to serve you?
(Job 39:9)
The wild donkey represents a hermit or those who live away from the crowds.
In Job, it is written: Who let the wild donkey go free?
(Job 39:5)
The Jewish people are also referred to as a wild donkey, as it continues in the same book: And who untied its bonds, the bonds of the commandments indeed.
The fawn signifies Christ or the saints, for the variety of graces.
In Solomon, it says: You are like a gazelle, or a young stag.
(Song of Solomon 2:9)
The hare represents one who fears God.
In the Psalm, it is written: The rock is a refuge for the hares and hedgehogs.
(Psalm 104:18)
The hedgehog, as mentioned earlier, represents a weak people who made their homes in the rocks.
The fox can represent a heretic, the devil, or a cunning sinner.
In the Gospel, it says: Go and tell that fox.
(Luke 13:32)
The animal symbolizes a carnal man.
In the Apostle:
"But the natural man does not accept the things of the Spirit of God"
First Corinthians 2:14.
An animal, lacking understanding or speech, can sometimes be obedient.
In the Psalm:
"I became like a beast before you"
Psalm 73:22, sometimes indulgent, as in:
"The beasts rotted in their dung"
Joel 1:17.
Horse, a holy man. In Habakkuk:
"You ride on your horses"
Habakkuk 3:8.
And in a negative sense:
"A horse is a false hope for salvation"
Psalm 33:17, referring to anyone who is irrational.
In the Psalm:
"Do not be like a horse or a mule, without understanding"
Psalm 32:9.
Donkey, representing the human body or the people of the Gentiles. In the Gospel:
"They brought to Jesus the donkey and her colt, and they placed their cloaks on them, and he sat on them"
Matthew 21:7.
The name of donkeys signifies the laziness of fools, as Moses testifies:
"You shall not plow with an ox and a donkey together"
Deuteronomy 22:10, which means, in preaching, do not join the wise with the foolish; for the simplicity of the faithful is expressed by this name, which Christ leads to Jerusalem, that is, the vision of peace, by guiding and presiding.
Hence it is said:
"The ox knows its owner, and the donkey its master's manger"
Isaiah 1:3: again, the donkey represents the excessive wantonness of the reckless, as the prophet says:
"Their flesh is like the flesh of donkeys"
Ezekiel 23:20.
Donkey, symbolizing flesh or people lacking knowledge of God. As mentioned in the Gospel.
Camel, representing the rich burdened with worldly goods, or those distorted in morals. In the Gospel:
"It is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle than for a rich man to enter the kingdom of heaven"
Matthew 19:24.
The camel also signifies the Lord himself, as in:
"You strain out a gnat but swallow a camel"
Matthew 23:24: here the Lord is clearly designated, who, humbled willingly, carried the burdens of our weakness, and the needle's point, and the narrowness of the hole in the pain of his passion.
A gnat stings by buzzing, but a camel willingly bends to take on burdens.
The Jews overlooked the gnat when they asked for the release of a rebellious thief, yet they swallowed the camel when they sought to destroy the one who came down to bear the burdens of our mortality.
Bulls symbolize the leaders of the people.
In the psalm, Fat bulls surround me (Psalm 22:13).
Oxen represent the apostles, who, having taken on the yoke of Christ, plowed the world with the plow of the Gospel.
In the psalm, I will offer you oxen with goats (Psalm 66:15).
Oxen also signify the foolishness of the ignorant, as Solomon rightly said: "Immediately he followed her, as an ox led to the slaughter" (Proverbs 7:22).
The term ox also expresses the life of each worker, as noted by Moses: "Do not muzzle an ox while it is treading out the grain" (Deuteronomy 25:4); and by the Lord: "The worker deserves his food" (Matthew 10:10).
Cows are full of carnal vices.
In the psalm: "Among the cows of the peoples" (Psalm 68:31).
Cows also represent all the faithful in the Church, who, while contemplating the precepts of sacred teachings, carry the Lord's ark upon themselves.
Many are bound outwardly by carnal desires but do not stray from the right path because they carry the Lord's ark in their minds (First Samuel 6:12).
The calf represents Christ or the saints.
In the psalm: "Then they will offer young bulls on your altar" (Psalm 51:21).
And in another part: "Many bulls have surrounded me" (Psalm 22:13), referring to those who are wanton.
Pigs are unclean sinners.
In the letter of Peter: "And the sow that is washed returns to wallowing in the mud" (Second Peter 2:22).
Rams are apostles or leaders of the Churches.
In the psalm: "Ascribe to the Lord, sons of rams" (Psalm 29:1).
Sheep are the faithful people.
In the Gospel: "My sheep hear my voice" (John 10:27).
Animals refer to those simpler ones, less endowed with reasoning subtlety.
In Solomon: "Know well the condition of your flocks" (Proverbs 27:23).
Goats are sinners or gentiles.
In Daniel: "And behold, a goat came from the west across the face of the whole earth" (Daniel 8:5).
Also in a good sense: "I will offer you oxen with goats" (Psalm 66:15).
Numbers sixty-five, fifteen.
Goats, the righteous sometimes coming from the nations.
In Solomon: Your hair is like a flock of goats that appear from Gilead.
(Song of Solomon 6:4).
Just as goats often seek pasture in high places, so do the saints of the world desire nourishment from baptism and repentance above.
Hence the apostle: Our citizenship is in heaven.
(Philippians 3:20).
Goats are souls made wilder by the vain doctrine of philosophers, but now within the holy Church through the holy Gospel.
Lambs are Christ, or the apostles, or the saints.
In the Gospel: Feed my lambs.
(John 1:15).
Kids are sinners, or carnal impulses.
In the Gospel: But the kids on the left.
(Matthew 25:33).
Moles, idols, or heretics who do not see the truth.
In Isaiah: To worship moles and bats.
(Isaiah 2:20).
Dog, the devil, or Jew, or gentile.
In the psalm: And from the hand of the dog, my only one.
(Psalm 21:21).
And in another part, in Ecclesiastes: A living dog is better than a dead lion.
(Ecclesiastes 9:4).
Here they think the lion is the devil, but the dog is the gentile or sinful man: because he can come to faith or repentance, but the other does not.
Also, a dog represents lazy preachers, as there: Mute dogs unable to bark.
(Isaiah 56:10).
Frogs, demons.
In Revelation: And I saw three unclean spirits like frogs come out of the mouth of the dragon.
They are the spirits of demons.
(Revelation 16:13).
Similarly, frogs are heretics who, dwelling in the mire of vile thoughts, do not cease to croak with empty chatter.
Ant, the prudent or worker.
In Solomon: Go to the ant, you sluggard.
(Proverbs 6:6).
Worm, Christ in the humility of assumed human nature.
In the psalm: But I am a worm and not a man.
(Psalm 22:7).
Also in another part.
In Isaiah: Their worm will not die (Isaiah 66:24), meaning either the worm itself, or the conscience of sin, or the unrest of wicked thoughts.
Spider, human frailty.
In the psalm: And you have made my soul waste away like a spider.
(Psalm 39:2).
Spider webs are creations driven by fleeting desires, lacking strength and easily swept away by the winds of time.
A serpent can symbolize the devil or wicked people.
In the Gospel: "Serpents, brood of vipers" Matthew 23:33.
Similarly, in another context in the Gospel: "Just as Moses lifted up the serpent in the desert" John 3:14.
The serpent also represents those who are wise, as in: "Be as wise as serpents" Matthew 10:16.
A dragon can signify the devil or an open persecutor; as mentioned in the psalm: "You crushed the heads of the dragon, you gave him as food for the people of Ethiopia" Psalm 74:14.
A scorpion represents the devil or his servants; in the Gospel: "I have given you power to tread on serpents and scorpions" Luke 10:19.
A viper is similar to what was previously mentioned; in the Gospel: "Brood of vipers" Luke 3:7.
Chapter Six On the Various Names and Titles.
Man, or the whole person, or mind.
In Genesis: God made man in His own image and likeness.
And in a negative sense; in the Psalm: Arise, Lord, let not man prevail, meaning flesh, or the devil.
It also signifies the reproach of man, as in the Apostle's words: For when there is jealousy and strife among you, are you not worldly, and behaving like mere humans?
And elsewhere: An enemy has done this, referring to the devil.
The Apostle also mentions the man of sin and the son of perdition, meaning the Antichrist; but the term flesh also signifies humans, as in: And all flesh shall see the salvation of God.
Soul is used for both humans and animals; as in Job: The soul of every living thing and the breath of all mankind is in the control of the Almighty.
It elevates the rational soul of humans to spiritual understanding and animates the soul of irrational beings to physical sensations.
Man, spirit, meaning mind.
In the Apostle: The head of the woman is the man.
Also, man in a negative sense.
In Genesis: A virgin very beautiful to behold, whom no man had known, meaning the devil, who often corrupts the mind with thoughts.
Woman, soul, or human flesh.
In the Apostle: The head of the woman is the man.
Woman by gender, as in: God sent His Son, born of a woman, born under the law.
For weakness, as in Wisdom: Better is the wickedness of a man than the goodness of a woman.
Virgin, the Church, or holy souls.
In the Apostle: For I have betrothed you to one husband, to present you as a pure virgin to Christ.
And in a negative sense: Come down, sit in the dust, virgin daughter of Babylon, meaning a soul barren of goodness, which becomes a daughter of confusion through hypocrisy or malice.
King, Lord.
In the Apostle: King of kings and Lord of lords.
And in a negative sense, as of the devil: He is king over all the children of pride.
Queen, the Church.
In the psalm: "The queen stands at your right hand" (Psalm 45:10).
Here, the queen represents the soul ruling over the body.
"Father" signifies Lord. As mentioned in the prophet: "And I will be a father to you, and you will be my sons and daughters," says the Almighty Lord (Jeremiah 31:9).
And in the Gospel: "For one is your Father, who is in heaven" (Matthew 23:9).
Speaking of the devil: "Because he is a liar and his father," the father of lies and of all who do not remain in the truth (John 8:44).
"Mother" refers to the Church or heavenly Jerusalem. As the Apostle says: "But the Jerusalem above is free, which is our mother" (Galatians 4:26).
Similarly, those who teach and nurture others in Christ, being witnesses themselves, are considered mothers in both genders.
"Brother" signifies Christ or a neighbor. In the psalm: "I will declare your name to my brothers" (Psalm 22:23).
And Christ himself said: "Go, tell my brothers" (Matthew 28:10).
"Sister" means Church, Synagogue, or the soul of Christ. In the Song of Songs: "My sister, my bride" (Song of Solomon 4:9).
"Husband and wife" symbolize Christ and the Church, spiritual understanding, and the history of the Scriptures. As the Apostle states: "Husbands, love your wives, just as Christ loved the Church" (Ephesians 5:25).
"Bridegroom" refers to Christ, who was promised by the Father from the beginning. In the psalm: "And he is like a bridegroom coming out of his chamber" (Psalm 19:5).
And in the Gospel: "He who has the bride is the bridegroom" (John 3:29).
"Bride" represents the Church, promised through divine promises. In the Song of Songs: "Come from Lebanon, my bride, come from Lebanon" (Song of Solomon 4:8).
"Son" signifies the community of believers. As the Apostle writes: "You are no longer a slave, but a son; and if a son, then an heir through God" (Galatians 4:7).
"Son" also means Lord; as in "if the Son sets you free" (John 8:36).
"Daughter" refers to a faithful soul or the Church. In the psalm: "Listen, daughter, and see" (Psalm 45:11).
And in a negative sense: "Set a guard over a wayward daughter", meaning the fickleness of the soul (Ecclesiasticus 42:11).
Neighbors are those close in faith and who show mercy to the needy.
In the Song of Solomon: "Come, eat and drink, and get drunk, friends" Friends, united in God.
In the Gospel: "You are my friends" Elders, perfected in righteousness.
In Genesis: "And Abraham died at a good old age, full of years" In the Wisdom of Solomon: "Gray hair is human wisdom, and the age of old age is a blameless life."
And in a negative way, about Solomon: "When he was old, his heart was turned away" Young people, eager for God.
In the First Letter of John: "I am writing to you, young people, because you are strong, and the word of God lives in you, and you have overcome the evil one."
And in a negative way, in the First Book of Kings about Rehoboam: "He abandoned the advice of the elders and spoke according to the advice of the young men" Also there: "Woe to you, land, whose king is a youth."
A child, humble and simple in mind.
In the Gospel: "You have hidden these things from the wise and learned and revealed them to little children" And in the Gospel: "Unless you become like little children, you will never enter the kingdom of heaven."
And the Apostle: "Be like children in malice, but perfect in understanding."
Also in another sense; in the Apostle: "When I was a child, I spoke like a child."
Even Christ is understood as a child, who humbled himself unto death.
Prostitute, sinful soul, who, having left her heavenly husband, that is, Christ, conceived sinful fruits from the devil.
In Jeremiah: "You have the brazen look of a prostitute."
Workers, apostles, or preachers of the Gospel.
In the Gospel: "The harvest is plentiful, but the workers are few."
Shepherd, the Lord: "I am the good shepherd" Also the Apostle as a shepherd.
In the Gospel: "Feed my sheep" and in a negative way: "And he went to feed pigs," that is, those with impure thoughts.
Hired workers, serving the Lord not just for divine love, but for temporary reward.
In the Gospel, it says, "How many of my father's hired workers have bread in abundance?" (Luke 15:17).
This refers to those who receive spiritual nourishment.
Fishermen symbolize apostles or teachers.
In the Gospel: "I will make you fishers of men" (Matthew 4:15).
A Physician represents Christ or a wise teacher.
In Solomon: "A gentle person is a healer of the heart," and in Luke: "The healthy do not need a doctor, but the sick do" (Luke 5:31).
The Rich Man symbolizes the faithful who are rich in spiritual blessings.
Paul writes, "You were made rich in Him in all knowledge and all speech" (1 Corinthians 1:5).
Christ is also described as rich: "Rich in all who call upon Him" (Romans 10:10).
On the other hand, the rich can also represent spiritual corruption, as in, "Woe to you who are rich" (Luke 6:24).
The Poor symbolize humility.
In the Gospel: "And Lazarus was a poor man" (Luke 16:24), and "Blessed are the poor in spirit" (Matthew 5:3).
Christ is also described as poor: "Christ became poor for us, though He was rich" (2 Corinthians 8:9).
On the negative side, the poor may symbolize destitution, as in the psalm: "We have become very poor" (Psalm 78:8).
Clothed refers to having the integrity of baptism, faith, or righteousness.
In the Gospel: "He saw there a man not wearing a wedding garment" (Matthew 22:11).
Paul writes: "All who have been baptized into Christ have clothed themselves with Christ" (Galatians 3:27).
Naked symbolizes a lack of baptism, divine assistance, or good works.
In Revelation: "You are naked and miserable" (Revelation 3:17).
However, in a good sense, it can also mean being free from earthly attachments, as in, "He fled naked, leaving behind the linen cloth" (Mark 14:52).
The Living symbolize the righteous.
In the psalm: "I will please the Lord in the land of the living" (Psalm 114:9).
On the other hand, it can also refer to the morally corrupt, as in Solomon: "I praised the dead more than the living" (Ecclesiastes 4:2).
The Dead symbolize sinners or unbelievers.
In the Gospel: "Let the dead bury their own dead" (Matthew 8:22).
But in a good sense, it refers to those who die in faith: "Blessed are the dead who die in the Lord" (Revelation 14:13) and "You have died, and your life is hidden with Christ in God" (Colossians 3:3).
Corpses symbolize the bodies of unbelievers.
In the prophet: "I will fill the Valley of Jehoshaphat with the corpses of the dead" (Joel 3:14).
In another part:
They have laid the bodies of your servants
Psalm seventy-eight verse two.
Also, this:
They will see the bodies of the men who were unbelievers thrown out
Isaiah sixty-six verse twenty-four.
A tomb, holding within the body of a sinner, a soul dead from sins.
In the Gospel:
You are like whitewashed tombs, which appear beautiful to people on the outside, but inside are full of dead people's bones
Matthew twenty-three verse twenty-seven.
In contrast, the prophet says about the Lord's tomb:
And his tomb will be glorious
Isaiah eleven verse ten.
Chapter Seven
In the Inner Man.
The Inner Man, the Rational Soul.
In the Apostle: For Christ to dwell in your hearts by faith in the inner man.
Ephesians 3:16.
His head, Christ.
In the Apostle: The head of a man is Christ.
First Corinthians 11:3.
The top, the height of justice.
In Solomon: For your head will receive a crown of grace.
Proverbs 4:9.
Similarly, in another passage: The head of those walking in their sins, meaning the height of wickedness.
Psalm 68:22.
Hair, the adornment of justice or understanding.
In the Gospel: Even the hairs of your head are all numbered.
Matthew 10:30.
Neck, holy Scripture, as in the Song of Songs: Your neck is like the tower of Lebanon, from which hang a thousand shields, all the armor of the mighty.
Song of Solomon 4:4.
This refers to the testimonies of holy Scriptures, while elsewhere it signifies pride: As the daughters of Zion walked with outstretched necks.
Isaiah 3:16.
Stiff neck, pride, as in: Stiff-necked people.
Acts 7:51.
Eyes, faithful and simple understanding.
In the Gospel: Blessed are your eyes because they see.
Matthew 13:16.
And elsewhere: The eyes of the wise are in his head, meaning understanding in the heart of the prudent.
Ecclesiastes 2:14.
And in a negative sense; in the Gospel: If your eye is evil.
Matthew 6:23.
Ears, faithful obedience.
In the Gospel: And your ears that hear.
Matthew 13:16.
Nostrils, the breath of faith and good virtues.
In Job: And the Divine spirit in my nostrils.
Job 27:3.
Also: Your nose is like the tower that is in Lebanon.
Song of Solomon 7:4.
And in a negative sense: Smoke comes out of his nostrils, referring to the devil.
Job 41:11.
Throat, judgment of understanding.
In the book of Job: And do not my throat meditate wisdom?
And in a negative sense: My throat has become hoarse.
Psalm 69:4.
Mouth, the word itself.
In the psalm: The mouth of the righteous speaks wisdom.
Psalm 37:30.
Tongue, the same as above.
In the psalm: And his tongue speaks justice, or Scripture, as in: My tongue is the pen of a skillful writer.
Psalm 45:2.
Your teeth are like a flock of shorn sheep coming up from the washing, each one paired, with none missing.
Song of Solomon, Chapter Four, Verse Two.
Similarly, the inner senses are described in Jeremiah:
Lamentations, Chapter Three, Verse Sixteen: He has broken my teeth with gravel.
Teeth, as they consider each thing, are like how they eat, chew, and send to the memory's stomach.
Armpits, the beginnings of arms, signify the start of good deeds, which the lazy are accused of neglecting, as Scripture says:
The lazy person hides his hand under his armpit.
Proverbs, Chapter Nineteen, Verse Twenty-Four.
Shoulders represent the strength to carry; the prophet speaks of the Lord bearing the cross:
Authority is upon his shoulder.
Isaiah, Chapter Nine, Verse Six.
Hands symbolize work.
In the Psalm: I wash my hands among the innocent.
Psalm Twenty-Six, Verse Six.
And power, as in: Your hands have made me.
Psalm One Hundred Nineteen, Verse Seventy-Three.
The right hand stands for good works.
In the Gospel: Do not let your left hand know what your right hand is doing.
Matthew, Chapter Six, Verse Three.
The right hand also symbolizes eternal life, while the left hand represents the present life, as mentioned in:
His left hand is under my head, and his right hand embraces me.
Song of Solomon, Chapter Two, Verse Six.
The chest holds the secret of understanding.
In the Gospel: The disciple whom Jesus loved was reclining on the Lord's chest.
John, Chapter Thirteen, Verse Twenty-Three.
The belly represents the capacity of reason.
In Habakkuk: My belly trembled within me.
Habakkuk, Chapter Three, Verse Sixteen.
The belly also signifies the mind, as Jeremiah says:
My belly hurts, referring to the spiritual, not the physical belly, adding: The feelings of my heart are troubled.
Jeremiah, Chapter Four, Verse Nineteen.
And the Lord in the Gospel:
Whoever believes in me, rivers of living water will flow from his belly.
John, Chapter Seven, Verse Thirty-Eight.
Loins represent the inner senses.
In the Psalm: Even at night my loins instruct me.
Psalm Sixteen, Verse Seven.
Nothing is more hidden in a person than the heart and loins; hence Scripture says:
God searches hearts and loins.
Psalm Seven, Verse Nine.
Loins symbolize the strength of the mind.
In the Apostle's words: Gird up the loins of your mind.
First Peter, Chapter One, Verse Thirteen.
And concerning readiness, as in the Gospel:
Let your loins be girded.
Luke, Chapter Twelve, Verse Thirty-Five.
In Matthew 12:35, and in Job: "Gird up your loins like a man" (Job 38:3).
The navel symbolizes the desire of lust.
In Job: "And his strength is in the muscles of his belly" (Job 40:16); meaning it signifies the female genitalia, just as in the loins of men.
Fat represents the richness of divine grace or the fullness of heavenly wisdom.
In the Psalm: "My soul shall be satisfied as with fat and abundance" (Psalm 63:5).
Also, in a negative sense, fat represents the thickness of wickedness.
In the Psalm: "They have enclosed themselves in their own fat" (Psalm 17:10).
Bones symbolize the firmness of spirit.
In the Psalm: "All my bones shall say, 'Lord, who is like you?'" (Psalm 35:10).
And in a negative sense, in Job: "His bones are like tubes of bronze" (Job 40:18).
Likewise, deceitful plans of the ministers of the Antichrist, as in the Psalm: "God has scattered the bones of those who please men" (Psalm 53:5).
Marrow represents the infusion of charity and other virtues, as in the Psalm: "I will offer you burnt offerings of marrow" (Psalm 66:15).
Bowels symbolize the affection of piety and mercy.
In the Apostle: "If there is any affection of mercy" (Philippians 2:1).
And in another sense, in the Acts of the Apostles about Judas: "And all his bowels gushed out" (Acts 1:18).
Skin is a sign of mortality.
In Genesis: "And He made them coats of skins" (Genesis 3:21).
The skin represents those who focus only on outward things and wither inwardly.
Hair represents thoughts of the old life, which need to be cut off, as Moses ordered: "The Levites shall shave all the hair of their bodies" (Numbers 8:7).
Blood signifies the actions of the flesh; in the Psalm: "Deliver me from bloodguilt, O God, the God of my salvation" (Psalm 51:14).
And also: "Flesh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God" (First Corinthians 15:50).
And Isaiah: "Blood touches blood" (Hosea 4:2).
Also in a good sense, as the Apostle says: "And the blood of Jesus Christ cleanses us from all sin" (Hebrews 9:14).
Flesh represents the outer human.
In the Apostle: "For the flesh desires against the spirit, and the spirit against the flesh" (Galatians 5:17).
Flesh according to nature, as in: "This is now bone of my bones and flesh of my flesh" (Genesis 2:23), and there: "The Word became flesh" (John 1:14).
The Apostle says: "You, however, are not in the flesh but in the spirit" Romans 8:9.
Similarly, the flesh is associated with guilt, as in: "My spirit shall not remain in these humans, because they are flesh" Genesis 6:3.
Knees symbolize the confession of humility. In the Song of Songs, it says: "And now I bend the knees of my heart" Ephesians 3:14, and in the psalm: "My knees are weak from fasting" Psalm 109:24.
Sometimes, knees represent the strength of faith, as seen in the prophet: "I have left for myself seven thousand men who have not bowed their knees to Baal" First Kings 19:18.
Feet can signify the course of life, mental stability, or faith. In the psalm: "Our feet were standing" Psalm 122:2. And in a negative sense, in the prophet: "Why do you falter with both feet?" First Kings 18:21. And, "Their feet are swift to shed blood" Psalm 14:3.
The heel signifies overcoming vices. In Genesis: "He shall bruise your head, and you shall bruise his heel" Genesis 3:15. It also represents the end of an action, as in the psalm: "They will observe my heel" Psalm 56:7.
Steps symbolize progress in works. As mentioned in the psalm: "Make my steps firm in your paths" Psalm 17:5. Footprints are signs of virtues, as in the psalm: "So that my footsteps may not slip." Conversely, Solomon says: "The life of the wicked will pass like a footprint in the sea."
A robe represents the garment of baptism or faith. In the Gospel: "Quickly bring out the best robe" Luke 15:22. Sackcloth is a testimony of repentance. In the Gospel: "They would have repented long ago in sackcloth and ashes" Matthew 11:21.
A belt signifies readiness for spiritual work. As stated in the psalm: "You have clothed me with joy" Psalm 30:12. A girdle represents purity of heart. The Apostle mentions: "Girded about the waist with golden belts" Revelation 15:6.
Shoes symbolize the preparation of peace. As the Apostle states: "Having your feet fitted with the preparation of the gospel of peace." The armor of the inner person is also mentioned by the Apostle: "Put on the breastplate of righteousness, the shield of faith, the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the spirit, which is the Word of God" Ephesians 6:15.
Chapter Eight
On things that are used and in the midst.
Bread represents Christ or the word of God.
In the Gospel: I am the living bread John 6:41.
And elsewhere: Let us put wood in his bread Jeremiah 11:19, meaning the cross in his body.
Bread signifies doctrine, and also evil, as seen here: Stolen bread is sweeter Proverbs 9:17.
Wine similarly holds significance.
In Solomon: And drink the wine I have mixed for you Proverbs 9:5.
Wine also symbolizes the security of righteousness, as in: Pouring oil and wine Luke 10:34, where wounds are stung by wine and soothed by oil.
Oil represents mercy or the Holy Spirit.
In the psalm, I have anointed him with my holy oil Psalm 88:21.
Conversely: But let not the oil of the sinner anoint my head Psalm 140:5, referring to flattery.
Pork symbolizes sins.
In the psalm, I am filled with pork.
Unleavened bread represents sincerity of heart, free from the leaven of malice.
In the Apostle: With the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth First Corinthians 5:8.
Egg signifies the sure hope of the faithful.
Yet, in a negative sense: He who eats of their eggs will die Isaiah 59:5, referring to the wicked and poorly taught.
Fine flour represents purity of mind and strength of charity.
In Leviticus: If anyone offers a grain offering to God, let his offering be of fine flour Leviticus 2:1.
Ash cake signifies the offering of humility.
In Genesis: Quickly knead three measures of fine flour, and make cakes Genesis 18:6.
In a negative sense: Ephraim is like an ash cake Hosea 7:8.
Milk represents sincerity of mind.
In the Epistle of Peter: Desire the pure spiritual milk without deceit First Peter 2:2.
Also, for the inexperienced in the Church: I gave you milk to drink, not solid food; for you were not yet able First Corinthians 3:2.
Here, milk means limited understanding.
Curdled milk represents being hardened by sins.
In the psalm: Their heart is as fat as curdled milk Psalm 119:70.
Salt represents the seasoning of wisdom.
In the Gospel: You are the salt of the earth Matthew 5:13, and have salt in yourselves Mark 9:49.
Honey symbolizes the sweetness of God's commandments.
In the psalm: How sweet are your words to my taste, O Lord, more than honey and honeycomb to my mouth Psalm 119:103.
Here's another perspective from Solomon:
When you find honey, eat only what you need, so you won't feel too full and get sick.
(Proverbs 25:18)
The meaning here is not to seek things beyond your understanding.
(Ecclesiasticus 3:22)
Gall represents the bitterness of wickedness.
In the Psalm, it says: They gave me gall for food.
(Psalm 69:22)
Vinegar signifies the harshness of a corrupted mind.
In the Psalm: And in my thirst, they gave me vinegar to drink.
(Psalm 69:22)
Additionally, vinegar represents the correction of the wise.
As Solomon says: Like vinegar on a wound is someone who sings songs with a bad heart.
(Proverbs 25:20)
Pitch symbolizes the stain and darkness of sins.
In Solomon: Whoever touches pitch will be stained by it.
(Ecclesiastes 13:1)
Strong drink represents a concoction of malice and wickedness.
In the Gospel: He shall not drink wine or strong drink.
(Luke 1:15)
The cup represents the suffering of the Lord.
In the Psalm: I will take the cup of salvation.
(Psalm 116:13)
And the Lord Himself says: Father, take this cup away from me.
(Mark 14:36)
In a negative sense, consider the golden cup of Babylon.
(Jeremiah 51:7)
Pure wine symbolizes the sincerity of judgment or truth, or the warmth of faith.
In the Psalm: A full cup of mixed wine.
(Psalm 75:9)
Dregs represent the final judgment.
In the Psalm: Yet its dregs are not emptied.
Also, it refers to those who rest securely in sins; hence the prophet says: He rested on his lees.
(Jeremiah 48:11)
Food symbolizes the word or will of the Lord.
In the Gospel: My food is to do the will of Him who sent me, my Father.
(John 4:34)
Drink symbolizes the same concept.
In the Psalm: You will give them drink from the river of your pleasures, meaning the Holy Spirit.
(Psalm 36:9)
And the Psalmist says: I mingled my drink with my tears while I was grieving.
(Psalm 102:10)
Also, in another sense: The Kingdom of God is not food and drink.
(Romans 14:17)
Storehouses symbolize the chambers of the heart.
In the Song of Deuteronomy: The fear in their storehouses.
A bag represents the concern for sustenance and the hindrances of the world.
In the Gospel: No bag for the journey.
(Matthew 10:9)
A purse symbolizes storing up treasure in God.
In the Gospel: Make for yourselves purses that do not wear out.
(Luke 12:33)
In another sense, it refers to having a common purse, meaning greed.
(Proverbs 1:14)
Money symbolizes divine words.
In the Gospel: "You should have put my money in the bank" (Matthew 25:27).
Wisdom is also referenced, as Solomon says: "Hidden wisdom and unseen treasure—what benefit is there in either?" (Ecclesiasticus 20:32).
Fleece symbolizes the people, as in the psalm: "He came down like rain upon the fleece" (Psalm 72:6).
Linen represents spiritual strength, purity, or the subtlety of the Scriptures.
In Exodus: "You shall prepare linen tunics for Aaron’s sons" (Exodus 28:30).
On the negative side, it also symbolizes improper mixing, as in: "Do not wear clothing made of wool and linen woven together" (Deuteronomy 22:11).
Wineskins represent the human body.
In the Gospel: "New wine must be put into new wineskins" (Luke 5:38).
Flour symbolizes good works or knowledge.
In the Gospel: "A woman hid leaven in three measures of flour" (Luke 13:21).
On the negative side, flour can represent vain thoughts, as in the prophet: "Take the millstone and grind flour" (Isaiah 47:2).
The millstone represents one’s way of life.
In the Gospel: "Two women will be grinding at the mill" (Matthew 24:41).
The two millstones can also symbolize the two Testaments, through which the labor of study grinds the wheat of the Old Testament into the flour of the Gospel.
These terms, when they appear in the sacred text, are to be understood as they are most clearly expressed, although they often take on different meanings depending on the person, time, or place.
They also take on figurative meanings appropriate to the context for allegorical interpretation.
For example, the abyss can mean the depth of Scripture, as mentioned earlier, or the vastness of water, as in: "The fountains of the great abyss were broken open" (Genesis 7:11).
It can also symbolize the unfathomable judgments of God, as in the psalm: "Your judgments are a great abyss" (Psalm 36:7).
The abyss can also mean hell, as in: "Who will descend into the abyss?" (Romans 10:7), meaning to bring Christ up from the dead.
Alternatively, it can represent the darkened hearts of people burdened by sin, as in Job: "The abyss says, 'It is not in me,'" referring to wisdom (Job 28:14).
Fire, as mentioned earlier, can represent the Holy Spirit, as Paul says: "Our God is a consuming fire" (Hebrews 12:29).
Fire also symbolizes love, as in: "Its flames are flames of fire" (Song of Songs 8:6).
Fire and tribulation.
In the Psalms, it says: "You have tested us with fire, as silver is tested with fire" (Psalm Sixty-Six, Verses Ten to Eleven).
It also mentions: "We went through fire and water."
Fire can symbolize anger: "And I will consume them in the fire of my wrath," says the Lord.
Fire can also represent lust: "All are adulterers, like an oven heated by their heart."
Furthermore, fire can signify malice of the mind, as in: "Then the fire will consume the adversaries" (Hebrews Ten, Verse Twenty-Seven).
It can also reflect the power of charity, as in: "The chariots of God are flames of fire, its wheels are burning fire" (Daniel Seven, Verse Nine).
As we've mentioned, shadow signifies divine protection.
However, sometimes shadow can represent sins: "Sitting in darkness and in the shadow of death" (Psalm One Hundred Seven, Verse Ten).
Other times, shadow symbolizes punishment, as in Job: "The shadow of death and no order" (Job Ten, Verse Twenty-Two).
And because a shadow is close to what it reflects, death is also near the punishment that brings it about.
Sometimes shadow indicates delight in sins; in Job, it describes the devil: "He sleeps under the shadow among the reeds in hidden places" (Job Forty, Verse Sixteen).
Additionally, certain appearances can signify multiple things at once.
For example, the two testaments can be likened to these two millstones we've discussed.
The two testaments are also symbolized by the two cherubim in Exodus (Exodus Twenty-Five, Verse Twenty); two animals in Habakkuk; two rocks in Exodus (Exodus Seventeen, Verse Six) and the Song of Songs (Song of Songs Two, Verse Fourteen), under which the bride and Moses are protected; and two bronze mountains in Zechariah, from which chariots with red, black, white, and spotted horses emerge (Zechariah Six, Verse One).
However, exploring all these meanings for each name would be not only a tremendous task but also impossible.
So now, let's return to the manner and order of interpretation, which we briefly paused for this discussion.
Baskets symbolize apostles.
In the Gospel, it states: "And they took up twelve baskets full of broken pieces" (Matthew Fourteen, Verse Twenty).
Another passage says: "His hands served in the basket" (Psalm Eighty-One, Verse Seven), referring to servitude or tribulation imposed by the Egyptians.
The chair represents doctrine.
In the psalm, it says: "and let them praise Him in the assembly of the elders" (Psalm ...).
Additionally, in another section:
He did not sit in the seat of the pestilence, as mentioned in Psalm one, verse one, referring to the teachings of heretics.
The term "footstool" symbolizes the subjection of the humbled.
In the Psalm it states: Until I make your enemies your footstool, from Psalm one hundred ten, verse one.
Also, the humanity of Christ is highlighted in the Psalm: Worship at his footstool, found in Psalm ninety-nine, verse five.
"Balance" signifies fairness or the power of divine governance.
In Isaiah, it says: And he measured the mountains in scales and the hills in a balance, from Isaiah forty, verse twelve.
"Ashes" represent the vanity of human frailty.
In the words of Solomon: Why are you proud, earth and ashes, found in Ecclesiastes ten, verse nine?
The term "pot" can refer to lineage.
In the Psalm: Moab is my washbasin, from Psalm sixty, verse ten, indicating that from Ruth the Moabitess came the lineage of Christ according to the flesh.
Additionally, in another context, "pot" signifies the refining of tribulation; as the prophet says: And I saw a boiling pot, facing away from the north from Jeremiah one, verse thirteen.
"Lamps" signify the souls shining with justice.
In the Gospel: And they prepared their lamps, from Matthew twenty-five, verse seven.
Moreover, lamps can represent the brightness of miracles or the words of preachers, which fools despise, as mentioned in Job: A lamp is despised in the thoughts of the fool, from Job twelve, verse five.
"Darkness" can mean pleasures or corrupt teachings, as in the Psalm: They walk in darkness, from Psalm eighty-two, verse five.
It also refers to the hidden judgments of God, as in the Psalm: He made darkness his hiding place, from Psalm eighteen, verse twelve.
Additionally, darkness can imply correction or adversity, as stated in Isaiah: I am the Lord who forms light and creates darkness, from Isaiah forty-five, verse seven.
"Lamp" can symbolize the Church or the soul.
In the Gospel: Let your loins be girded and your lamps burning, from Luke twelve, verse fifty-five.
Sometimes, lamps represent good works: Let your light shine, so that they may see your good works, from Matthew five, verse sixteen.
"Measure" can refer to the human body, the letter of the law, or the people of the Jews.
In the Gospel: No one lights a lamp and puts it under a basket, from Matthew five, verse fifteen.
It also indicates just judgment or the balance of the mind in the equal balance of God and neighbor.
As Moses said: Let your measure be just, found in Leviticus nineteen, verse thirty-six.
"Lampstand" can symbolize the Church, the body of the Lord, or the Holy Scripture.
In the prophet: And I saw two burning lampstands to the right of the altar, from Zechariah four, verses two and three.
The "table" can represent the altar or spiritual nourishment.
In the Psalm: "You have prepared a table before me" Psalm 23:5.
This is key, the opening of spiritual knowledge.
In Luke: "Woe to you experts in the law, because you have taken away the key to knowledge; you yourselves have not entered, and you have hindered those who were entering" Luke 11:52.
Here, keys represent the virtues of justice, mercy, and piety.
In the Gospel: "I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven" Matthew 16:19.
The nail signifies the fear of God, as in the Psalm: "Pierce my flesh with your fear" Psalm 119:120.
Nails also symbolize strong teachers of knowledge, as Solomon says: "The words of the wise are like goads, and like nails firmly fixed" Ecclesiastes 12:11.
Bars serve as barriers against the wicked, for divine commandments.
In the Psalm: "For he has strengthened the bars of your gates" Psalm 147:13.
The ax or hatchet represents the persecution of the wicked.
In the Psalm: "With axes and hatchets they cut it down" Psalm 74:6.
The double-edged ax signifies doubled affliction, as mentioned in the Psalm.
The sword represents the soul of the righteous, as the righteous will abound and the sword will be poured out.
It also signifies death, as in the Psalm: "Deliver my soul from the sword, O God" Psalm 22:21.
Additionally, the sword is the word of God.
The Apostle says: "The sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God" Ephesians 6:17.
It also represents the tongue of a false witness, as in the Psalm: "Their teeth are weapons and arrows, and their tongue a sharp sword" Psalm 57:4.
The ship represents the Church.
In the Gospel: "The boat was tossed by the waves in the midst of the sea" Matthew 14:24.
A person is often called a boat, highlighting the thoughts guiding people.
Nets symbolize preaching.
In the Gospel: "Let down the nets for a catch" Luke 5:4.
Beams represent a more serious sin.
In the Gospel: "First remove the beam from your own eye" Matthew 7:5.
The speck represents a less serious sin.
In the Gospel: "Then you will see clearly to remove the speck from your brother's eye."
A snare symbolizes deceit.
In the Psalm: "They prepared a snare for my feet" Psalm 57:6.
Cords represent a lot or inheritance.
In the Psalm: "The boundary lines have fallen for me in pleasant places" Psalm 16:6.
Cords also symbolize sins: "Woe to those who draw sin along with cords of deceit" Isaiah 5:18.
And again: "The cords of the wicked have wrapped around me" Psalm 119:61.
The wheel represents the world or human life.
The voice of your thunder was in the whirlwind.
Psalm Seventy-Seven, verse eighteen. My God, make them like a wheel.
Psalm Eighty-Three, verse thirteen, meaning to make them fickle or unstable in their wickedness.
Also, both testaments, as found in Ezekiel.
Ezekiel chapter one, verse sixteen.
A sponge represents the hollow unfaithfulness of the Jews.
In the Gospel, they soaked a sponge in vinegar, put it on a hyssop plant, and lifted it to Jesus' lips.
John chapter nineteen, verse twenty-nine.
A ladder symbolizes the progress of the saints.
In Genesis, he had a dream where he saw a stairway resting on the earth, with its top reaching to heaven, and the angels of God were ascending and descending on it.
Genesis chapter twenty-eight, verse twelve.
Brooms signify the care of superstition through vain glory.
In the Gospel, then it goes and finds the house unoccupied, swept clean, and put in order.
Matthew chapter twelve, verse forty-four.
Tow represents the gathering of the wicked through vice and sin, as the prophet says, the assembly of sinners is like towed flax.
Ecclesiasticus chapter twenty-one, verse ten.
A pearl symbolizes the teaching of the gospel or the hope of the kingdom of heaven.
In the Gospel, when he found one of great value, he went away, sold everything he had, and bought it.
Matthew chapter thirteen, verse forty-six.
A ring represents the seal of faith.
In the Gospel, put a ring on his finger.
Luke chapter fifteen, verse twenty-two.
Also in the psalm, the light of your countenance is sealed upon us, O Lord.
A cloak symbolizes the adornment of praise.
In Solomon, she makes coverings for her bed.
Proverbs chapter thirty-one, verse twenty-two, meaning a garment made of two colors, as if made from the two testaments.
Psalm Four, verse seven.
Gold represents the inner understanding of the Scriptures.
In the psalm, the wings of the dove covered with silver, its feathers with shining gold.
Psalm Sixty-Eight, verse thirteen.
Also, the divinity of Christ, as it is said of the bridegroom in the Song of Songs, his head is purest gold.
Song of Solomon chapter five, verse eleven.
Also, the splendor of the heavenly city of Jerusalem, which John testifies he saw, the city was pure gold.
Revelation chapter twenty-one, verse eighteen.
Also, wisdom, as Solomon says, a desirable treasure rests on the mouth of the wise.
Also, the splendor of holiness, which Jeremiah laments as suddenly changed, how the gold has grown dim, the finest gold has changed.
Lamentations chapter four, verse one.
Silver represents divine words, or the understanding of the letter, or history.
In the psalm, the words of the Lord are described as pure words, like silver tested in a furnace
Psalm 12:6.
On the other hand, in a negative sense: "Their gold and silver are corroded"
James 5:3.
Scum or rust, which silver deposits in the furnace, is likened to sinners when the furnace of hell consumes them.
Precious stones symbolize apostles, saints, or virtuous works.
In Revelation, it says: "The foundations of the city's wall were decorated with every kind of precious stone" (Revelation 21).
Bronze represents the vanity or emptiness of faith.
In the Apostle's words: "I have become like a sounding brass"
First Corinthians 13:1.
In another sense: "You have made my arms like a bronze bow."
Here, bronze signifies strength or firmness.
Iron signifies tribulation or man himself.
In the psalm: "Iron pierced his soul"
Psalm 105:18.
Lead represents the weight of sins.
As the prophet says: "And I saw wickedness over a talent of lead."
Clay signifies the fragility of the flesh.
In the Apostle's words: "We have this treasure in jars of clay"
Second Corinthians 4:7.
Chapter Nine
On the different meanings of words as expressed through the Infinitive.
To build means to do good works or to teach well.
As the Apostle says: "If anyone builds on this foundation with gold, silver, precious stones" indicating works of various virtues. (First Corinthians 3:12)
To destroy means to do evil works or to teach badly.
As Solomon puts it: "One builds, and one destroys." (Ecclesiasticus 34:28)
To cleanse means to purge vices.
In the Gospel, it says: "Jesus touched him, saying, 'I want to, be cleansed,' and immediately his leprosy was cleansed." (Matthew 8:3)
To stand means to remain in faith.
The Apostle encourages: "Stand firm in the faith." (First Corinthians 16:13)
To walk means to strive towards God.
As the psalm states: "And I walked in freedom." (Psalm 119:45)
To sit means to rest humbly in God.
The Gospel advises: "But you, sit in the city." (Luke 24:49)
To lie means to succumb to vices or temptations.
As found in the Gospel: "And found her lying in bed." (Mark 7:30)
To run means to hasten in good works.
The Apostle motivates: "Run in such a way as to get the prize." (First Corinthians 9:24)
To watch means to guard the heart or to rise to God.
As the psalm expresses: "From the morning watch until night." (Psalm 130:6) And the Apostle adds: "Awake to righteousness, and do not sin." (First Corinthians 15:34) Elsewhere: "Watch, stand firm in the faith, be courageous." (First Corinthians 16:13)
To sleep, after passing on, means to rest with God.
As the psalm questions: "Will he who sleeps not add to rise again?" (Psalm 41:9) Otherwise, to sleep means to be numb in the sleep of sins.
The Apostle advises: "Awake, you who sleep." (Ephesians 5:14)
To be ashamed in evil is best, in good is worst; hence it is said: "There is a shame that brings sin, and a shame that brings glory." (Ecclesiasticus 4:25)
Ascent means progress in God: As the psalm notes: "Ascent in his heart." (Psalm 84:6)
Descent means a falling away from God.
In the Gospel, it is written: "A certain man went down from Jerusalem to Jericho." (Luke 10:30)
The way means Christ.
The Gospel declares: "I am the way, the truth, and the life." (John 14:6) Otherwise, the way means the life of man.
As the psalm reflects: "I have declared my ways, and you answered me." (Psalm 119:26) And Solomon: "They will eat the fruit of their ways." (Proverbs)
Beautiful, yet drawn in by the allure of vices.
In the Gospel: The wide gate and broad road lead to destruction.
Matthew seven thirteen.
Narrow and strict, or pressed by tribulations, which lead to life.
In the Gospel: How narrow the gate and restricted the way that leads to life.
Matthew seven fourteen.
Straight, ordered by the commands of God.
In Isaiah: Make straight his paths.
Isaiah forty three.
Crooked, deviating from God's commands.
In Isaiah: The crooked shall become straight, and the rough places smooth.
Isaiah forty four.
Smooth, leveled by obedience to commands.
In Isaiah, chapter forty, verse four.
Rough, bristling with the harshness of disobedience, as mentioned earlier.
On the right, representing the side of justice.
In the Gospel: He will indeed place the sheep on the right, but the goats on the left.
Mark twenty five thirty-three.
On the left, representing the side of injustice, as mentioned in the Gospel.
The pit, symbolizing deceit or a fall into death.
In the psalm: They dug a pit in front of me.
Psalm fifty-six seventeen.
The well, symbolizing the devil or hell.
In the psalm: Let not the well open its mouth over me.
Psalm sixty-eight sixteen.
And in a positive sense; in Genesis: To the well of the oath, that is, to the water of faith.
Genesis forty-six one.
Also, the beginning of faith, as in the Song of Songs: A fountain of gardens, a well of living waters.
Song of Solomon four fifteen.
The fountain, representing Christ, as in the psalm: My soul thirsted for the living God.
Psalm forty-one three.
Also, the gifts of God, as in the psalm: And the fountains of waters appeared.
Psalm eighteen sixteen.
Also in a negative sense, referring to teachers of perverse doctrines and those acting unjustly, as Peter mentioned: These are wells without water.
Second Peter two seventeen.
The torrent, symbolizing the force of temptations driving the mind, as in the psalm: Our soul passed through the torrent.
Psalm one twenty-three five.
Also, the cold of sins, from which David desires to be freed, saying: Restore, O Lord, our captivity, like streams in the south.
Psalm one twenty-six four.
Health, representing integrity of mind; in the psalm: I cried to you, and you healed me.
Psalm thirty thirty-four.
Weakness, representing the disease of vices; in the psalm: Who heals all your diseases.
Psalm one hundred three three.
And in the Gospel: He took our infirmities.
Isaiah fifty-three four.
Leprosy, representing the contamination of sins.
In the Gospel: And immediately his leprosy was cleansed.
Matthew eight three.
Chapter Ten About Jerusalem, or its adversities.
Jerusalem, the Church, or the soul.
In the psalm: Praise, Jerusalem Psalm one hundred forty-seven, verse twelve.
It's important to note that what applies to the Church can also be attributed to the soul.
Zion, the same as above.
In the psalm: Praise your God, Zion Psalm one hundred forty-seven, verse twelve.
Sons of Zion, sons of the Church.
In the psalm: And the sons of Zion rejoiced over their king Psalm one hundred forty-nine, verse two.
Daughters of Jerusalem, the same as above: that is, souls dedicated to the heavenly life.
Alternatively, the daughters are infernal souls, as in the Book of Wisdom: You have daughters, guard their bodies Ecclesiastes chapter seven, verse twenty-six.
Tabernacle, the body of the Lord, or the Church.
In the psalm: He has set up a tabernacle in the sun Psalm nineteen, verse six.
Also, the heavenly homeland, as in the psalm: I will go into the place of the tabernacle Psalm forty-two, verse five.
Ark, the body of the Lord, or hearts full of God.
In the psalm: You and the ark of your sanctification Psalm one hundred thirty-two, verse eight.
Also, the ark, the Church, within which those to be saved are enclosed.
In Genesis: Only Noah and those with him in the ark remained Genesis chapter seven, verse twenty-three.
Two stone tablets, as I think, for the two covenants, or for the two commandments of love of God and neighbor.
In Exodus: And the Lord said to Moses: Cut two tablets for yourself Exodus chapter thirty-four, verse one.
Law, divine commandments.
In the psalm: The law of the Lord is perfect Psalm nineteen, verse eight.
Handwriting, the writing of a sinful man with the devil by the hand of iniquity.
In the Apostle: The handwriting of sin which was against us Colossians chapter two, verse fourteen.
Covenant, the agreement of divine grace with man.
In the psalm: I saw those not keeping the covenant.
Testament, confirmation of divine will.
In the prophet: And I will confirm my covenant over the house of Judah Hebrews chapter eight, verse eight.
Iron stylus Job chapter nineteen, verse twenty-four, the strong sentence of the divine word.
Foreskin, pagan life.
In the Apostle: If someone was called in foreskin, let him not be circumcised First Corinthians chapter seven, verse eighteen, meaning even those who came to the faith of Christ from the Gentiles should not be circumcised in the body.
Circumcision, the stripping away of vices.
In the Apostle's writings: You have been circumcised with a circumcision not done by hands, by removing the physical body of flesh.
The horn symbolizes strength or a kingdom.
In First Samuel: And he exalted the horn of his anointed one.
Purple represents the form of martyrdom through blood.
In Exodus: Everyone who is moved in heart shall bring offerings to the Lord: gold, silver, bronze, blue, purple, scarlet yarn, and fine linen.
Fringes are words of faith to be carefully retained, as in the Psalm: All the glory of the king's daughter is within, adorned with fringes.
Scarlet signifies the ardor of charity or the mention of the cross.
Fine linen symbolizes the brilliance of chastity or continence.
Blue represents the bruises of confessors.
The ephod represents deeds carried by the shoulders.
In Exodus: And they made the ephod of gold, blue, purple, scarlet yarn, and twisted fine linen.
The breastpiece signifies the declaration of doctrine or reason from the chest.
In Exodus: And they made the breastpiece, the work of a skilled craftsman, like the work of the ephod.
The robe represents a more secret and perfect doctrine.
In Exodus: And they made the robe of the ephod entirely of blue cloth.
The golden plate on the forehead prefigures the cross.
In Exodus: And they made a gold plate, and inscribed upon it letters, the holy crown of the Lord, that is, the tetragrammaton name of the Lord.
The temple signifies the body of the Lord, or the holy ones.
In the Apostle's writings: For you are the temple of the living God.
And he said: Destroy this temple.
The altar represents the height of faith.
In the Psalm: Then they will place young bulls on your altar.
Sacrifice signifies the offering of justice.
In the Psalm: Sacrifice the sacrifices of righteousness.
Also the praise of God, as in the Psalm: The sacrifice of praise will honor me.
A burnt offering is entirely consumed by faith.
In the Psalm: I will offer you burnt offerings of fat animals.
The victim represents Christ, or a soul dedicated to God.
The offering and sacrifice to God, described as a sweet-smelling aroma.
(Ephesians 5:2)
Myrrh, a symbol of mortality.
As mentioned in the psalm: Myrrh, aloes, and cassia are from your garments.
(Psalm 45:9)
Incense represents the power of prayer, as noted in the psalm: Let my prayer be set before you like incense.
(Psalm 141:2)
Ointment signifies the grace of the name of Christ being spread out.
In Solomon: Your name is ointment poured forth.
(Song of Solomon 1:3)
The Holy of Holies refers to the inner mysteries of the Lord, or the kingdom of heaven.
As stated in the Letter to the Hebrews: For Jesus did not enter into holy places made with hands, which are copies of the true, but into heaven itself, to appear in the presence of God for us.
(Hebrews 9:24)
Sabbath symbolizes spiritual rest.
In Genesis: And the Lord rested from all his works.
(Genesis 2:2)
Also, in Isaiah: If you turn away your foot from the Sabbath.
(Isaiah 58:13)
And in a negative sense: Her enemies saw her and laughed at her Sabbaths.
(Lamentations 1:7)
Lent is a symbol of present life and labor.
In the Gospel: And when he had fasted for forty days and forty nights.
(Matthew 4:2)
Passover marks the announcement of the Lord’s passing.
As noted in the Gospel: Now before the feast of the Passover, Jesus, knowing that his hour had come to depart from this world to the Father.
(John 13:1)
Pentecost signifies the manifestation of future happiness or forgiveness.
In Leviticus: You shall count seven full weeks until the day after the seventh week, making fifty days.
(Leviticus 23:15)
Jubilee represents the sign of future rest.
In Leviticus: It is the year of remission, a holy sign for you.
(Leviticus 25:10)
The City of God refers to the Church or the soul.
As mentioned in the psalm: In the city of our God.
(Psalm 48:2)
Citizens are the faithful.
In the Apostle's letter: But you are fellow citizens with the saints and members of the household of God.
(Ephesians 2:19)
Walls symbolize the defenses of divine Scripture, prophets, or saints.
In the psalm: Build up the walls of Jerusalem.
(Psalm 51:18)
Also in another sense: With my God, I can scale a wall.
(Psalm 18:29)
Towers represent apostles, or all who are perfect.
As described in the psalm: And abundance in your towers.
(Psalm 122:7)
Gates can refer to the holy scriptures, righteousness, apostles, or angels.
As mentioned in the Psalm: "Be lifted up, you everlasting doors" (Psalm 24:7).
Additionally, in another part: "For wide is the gate and broad is the way that leads to death" (Matthew 7:13).
Streets symbolize the broadness opened for the holy ones.
In Revelation, it says: "And the street of the city was pure gold, like transparent glass" (Revelation 21:21).
Foundation represents Christ or faith, as the Apostle states: "No one can lay any foundation other than the one already laid, which is Jesus Christ" (First Corinthians 3:11).
A wall signifies law or the protection of angels.
In the Song of Isaiah: "I will make a wall around it and affix poles and plant a vineyard" (Isaiah 5:2).
A house represents the soul where Christ dwells or the Church.
As the Psalm says: "We will go into the house of the Lord" (Psalm 122:1).
The upper room signifies the height of merits or knowledge.
In the Gospel: "And he will show you a large upper room" (Luke 22:12).
The door signifies the opening of faith.
As the Apostle says: "A great and effective door has opened to me" (First Corinthians 16:9).
The gatekeeper signifies Christ, who says: "If anyone enters by me, he will be saved" (John 10:9).
Pillars signify the foundation or spiritual stability.
As the Apostle mentions: "James, John, and Cephas, who seemed to be pillars" (Galatians 2:9).
A wall sometimes signifies the structure of good works.
In the Song of Songs: "Look, he stands behind our wall, gazing through the windows" (Song of Solomon 2:9).
Windows signify sight and hearing, or other senses, as previously mentioned: "Gazing through the windows."
Also, in a negative sense: "Death has entered through our windows" (Jeremiah 9:21).
Steps signify spiritual ascension.
In the title of the Psalms: "A song of ascents" (Psalm 120:1).
And also: "They will go from strength to strength" (Psalm 84:7).
The floor signifies humiliation or affliction of the soul, or a decline to earthly things.
As stated in the Psalm: "My soul clings to the dust" (Psalm 119:25).
The psaltery signifies good works.
As mentioned in the Psalm: "A joyful psaltery with the harp" (Psalm 81:2).
The harp signifies a devoted heart, where virtues are like strings, that is, spiritual goods.
In the Psalm: "Awake, psaltery and harp" (Psalm 108:2).
Number ninety-six, verse nine, refers to works done with faith or about the Lord himself, including the resurrection of the body with divine power.
The ten-stringed instrument symbolizes the Ten Commandments, or when doubled, represents the five external senses combined with the internal ones.
In Psalm ninety-two, verse four, it says, "On the ten-stringed psaltery, with a song and harp."
The organ symbolizes a man or someone who is taken by the Lord.
In the psalm: "Praise him with strings and organ" (Psalm one hundred fifty, verse four).
The drum represents the body, thinned by fasting.
In the psalter: "Praise him with drum and choir."
The choir signifies harmony.
This is mentioned similarly in the psalm.
The trumpet symbolizes the exaltation of the voice in divine preaching.
In the prophet: "Raise your voice like a trumpet" (Isaiah fifty-eight, verse one).
Cymbals represent lips confessing the Lord or the love of God and neighbor.
In the psalm: "Praise him with loud cymbals" (Psalm one hundred fifty, verse five).
Jubilation is a shout expressed with spiritual fervor.
In the psalm: "Praise him with cymbals of jubilation."
Egypt represents this world or the people of the Gentiles.
In the psalm: "Envoys will come from Egypt" (Psalm sixty-eight, verse thirty-two).
Ethiopia symbolizes the Church from the nations.
In the psalm: "Ethiopia will stretch out its hands to God."
Also, in another part of the psalm: "You gave him food for the people of the Ethiopians" (Psalm seventy-four, verse fourteen).
Babylon represents either the world or Rome.
In Revelation: "And Babylon the great came into remembrance before God to give her the cup of the wine of the indignation of his wrath" (Revelation sixteen, verse nineteen).
Enemies symbolize the devil or vices.
In the psalm: "He will not be put to shame when he speaks with his enemies in the gate" (Psalm one hundred twenty-seven, verse five).
Thieves represent heretics and false prophets.
In the Gospel: "All who came before me were thieves and robbers" (John ten, verse eight).
Nations symbolize vices.
In the Pentateuch: "When the Lord your God brings you into the land you are entering to possess, and drives out many nations before you" (Deuteronomy seven, verse one).
Also, in another part: "All nations, clap your hands" (Psalm forty-seven, verse two).
Battle represents a struggle against spiritual wickedness or a conflict against vices.
In the Apostle: "Thus I fight, not as one beating the air" (First Corinthians nine, verse twenty-six).
Peace signifies the peace of the flesh in goodness and the harmony of the spirit.
In the psalm: "Pray for the peace of Jerusalem" (Psalm one hundred twenty-two, verse six).
Also, peace represents Christ.
In the Apostle: For he is our peace. Ephesians 2:14.
This signifies victory and triumph over the devil or adversities.
In the Apostle: But thanks be to God, who gives us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
First Corinthians 15:57.
The prize is the reward for completed merits.
In the Apostle: I press on toward the goal for the prize of the heavenly calling of God.
Philippians 3:14.
The crown represents the reward of eternal glory for righteousness.
In the Apostle: From now on there is reserved for me the crown of righteousness.
Second Timothy 4:8.
Since the completion of spiritual progress leads to the crown, it is fitting that the spiritual interpretation of these names concludes with the crown.
However, it is challenging to encompass all these names, just as it is to express everything that holds double significance.
Chapter Eleven On Numbers.
Now that we've finished discussing these terms, let's take a quick look at numbers, which have gained importance among sacred symbols due to their mystical significance.
One: This number symbolizes the unity of the Godhead.
In the Pentateuch: "Hear, O Israel, the Lord your God is one" (Deuteronomy 6:4).
And from the Apostle: "One God, one faith, one baptism" (Ephesians 4:5).
Noah's ark, representing the holy Church, is completed in one cubit (Genesis 6:16) because eternal rest is found through the contemplation of one God.
Two: This represents the two testaments of divine law.
As in First Kings: "And he made in Debir two cherubim of ten cubits in size" (First Kings 6:23).
The two commandments of love, loving God and neighbor.
The holy Gospel mentions two in the field, two at the mill, two in bed (Luke 17:34).
Three: Symbolizing the Trinity.
In John's Epistle: "There are three who bear witness in heaven: the Father, the Word, and the Holy Spirit, and there are three who bear witness on earth: the spirit, the water, and the blood" (First John 5:7).
And in Genesis: "Three branches" (Genesis 40:10).
Four: Representing the four Gospels.
In Ezekiel: "And from their midst came the likeness of four living creatures" (Ezekiel 1:5).
Just like the four rivers of paradise (Genesis 2:10).
The Tetragrammaton is written with four Hebrew letters.
The holy cross is marked by four horns, as in Habakkuk: "Horns in his hands" (Habakkuk 3:4).
Five: Referring to the five books of Moses, the five porticoes (John 5:2), the five loaves (John 6:9), and the five wounds on the body of the Lord (John 20:25).
The Apostle says: "In the Church I would rather speak five words with my understanding" (First Corinthians 14).
Six: Relating to the sixth day when the Lord created man along with all the living creatures of the earth.
In Genesis: "Let us make man in our image and likeness" (Genesis 1:26).
Further on: "And it was evening, and it was morning, the sixth day" (Genesis 1:31).
The number six signifies completeness: God completed the world in six days, and so to these five, one is added, fulfilling the law through the Gospel.
There are six ages of the world: five have passed, and the sixth extends from John the Baptist and the incarnation of Christ to the end of the world.
God created man in His image on the sixth day because, in this sixth age, the reformation of our minds in the likeness of Him who created us is revealed through the Gospel.
These six ages are symbolized by the six water jars that the Lord ordered to be filled with water, where the water turned into wine as described in the book of John, Chapter Two, Verse Six.
This is so we can understand Christ, now revealed, in the law and the prophets.
Those six times were arranged and distinguished like sections and would have been like empty vessels if not filled by Christ.
Truly, times would pass in vain unless the Lord Jesus Christ was preached in them.
The jars are filled meaning the prophecies are fulfilled.
To the seventh day, on which the Lord rested after completing everything.
In Genesis, it is written: And God rested on the seventh day from all the work He had done Genesis, Chapter Two, Verse Two.
This number signifies the highest perfection for human reason because it consists of the first even and the first odd numbers: from the first that can be divided and from the first that cannot be divided.
Hence the jubilee, which expresses perfect rest, consists of seven weeks.
Hence the seven spirits, who are before the throne of God Revelation, Chapter One, Verse Four.
The seven loaves, with which Christ fed four thousand people, symbolized the sevenfold grace of the Holy Spirit Matthew, Chapter Fifteen, Verse Thirty-Four.
To the Lord's Day of resurrection, the eighth day.
In the title of the psalm, For the end, for the eighth Psalm, Chapter Six, Verse One.
To the sacrament of the ninth hour, when the Lord gave up His spirit.
In the Gospel: And about the ninth hour, Jesus cried out with a loud voice Matthew, Chapter Twenty-Seven, Verse Forty-Six.
There are also nine names of precious stones and nine orders of angels.
To the Decalogue, the ten words, which are written on two tablets.
In the psalm: I will sing to You with a ten-stringed harp Psalm One Forty-Four, Verse Nine.
To the apostles.
In the Gospel: But the eleven disciples went to Galilee Matthew, Chapter Twenty-Eight, Verse Sixteen.
The number eleven, when it goes beyond ten, is often associated with transgression and criticism.
That's why the Apostle Peter didn't let the number of apostles stay at eleven; he chose Matthias to be the twelfth.
Acts 1:26.
In the old law, eleven curtains of goat hair were instructed to be made, symbolizing acts of penance for sins.
Exodus 26:7.
At the eleventh hour, the Gentiles and the elderly are called.
Matthew 20:6.
Twelve.
Referring to the apostles in the Gospel: Now the names of the twelve apostles are these.
Matthew 10:2.
This number represents the entire multitude of judges, with two parts of seven often signifying universality: these two parts, three and four, multiply to make twelve.
Matthew 19:28.
Fourteen.
Connected to the sacrament of the Lord’s lineage.
In the Gospel, from Abraham to David, there are fourteen generations.
Matthew 1:17.
Fifteen.
Relates to the fifteen steps of the temple that Solomon made, corresponding to the fifteen psalms titled Song of Ascents.
These range from the Psalm, "In my distress I cried to the Lord," to "Praise the name of the Lord."
Psalm 119:1.
Sixteen.
Associated with the number of prophets.
Twenty-two.
Linked to the sacrament of the divine volumes, according to the Hebrew letters.
Twenty-four.
Connected to the mystery of the number of elders.
In Revelation: And upon the thrones, twenty-four elders.
Revelation 4:4.
By twenty-four lots, King David distributed priests in the ministry of the temple.
First Chronicles 24:7.
Thirty.
Relates to the fruits of faithful marriages.
In the Gospel: And some will yield a hundredfold, some sixty, some thirty.
Matthew 13:8.
This refers to the married, sixty to widows, and a hundred to virgins.
Thirty-three.
Refers to the mystery of the age at which the Lord lived in the flesh; as it seems to some from this, until we all reach unity in the faith and knowledge of the Son of God, to a perfect man, to the measure of the stature of the fullness of Christ.
Ephesians 4:13.
Forty.
Relates to the sacrament of Lent.
In the Gospel, he was led by the Spirit into the desert for 40 days
Luke 4:2.
The strength of the Ten Commandments is fulfilled through the four books of the Gospel.
We fulfill the Ten Commandments if we perfectly keep the four holy books of the Gospel.
Through self-control, vigils, prayers, and other practices mentioned by the Apostle, the weapons of righteousness
Second Corinthians 6:7 lead us to the rewards of immortal life.
42.
Reflects the number of encampments in the wilderness, or the generations from Abraham to the Lord Jesus Christ
Matthew 1.
46.
The temple was built in 46 years
John 2:20, for the Jews returning from exile, as the second building after Solomon.
This number of years fittingly corresponds to the perfection of the Lord’s body.
50.
Relates to Pentecost; in the Acts of the Apostles: And when the day of Pentecost was fully come
Acts 2:1.
60.
Pertains to the fruit owed to widows or those who are continent.
In the Gospel: And they will yield fruit, some sixtyfold
Matthew 13:8.
72.
Matches the number of Moses' elders
Numbers 11:24, or the disciples whom the Lord chose.
In the Gospel: After this, the Lord appointed 72 others and sent them two by two ahead of him to every town
Luke 10:1.
100.
Corresponds to the fruit of martyrs or virgins.
In the Gospel: They will yield fruit, some a hundredfold
Matthew 15:8.
This number signifies complete perfection, as it is said of the chosen: Whoever leaves house, or brothers, or sisters, and so forth, will receive a hundredfold and will inherit eternal life
Matthew 19:29.
A hundred also indicates a measure of time, as Isaiah says, A child will die a hundred years old, and so forth
Isaiah 65:20.
There is also in the Gospel the hundredth sheep
Luke 15:4, which Christ, placing on his sacred shoulders, carried to the heavenly homeland.
1,000.
The number one thousand is set for the perfection of all numbers and the perfect action of all good things.
As Peter says in the Epistle: But do not let this one thing escape your notice, beloved, that with the Lord one day is like a thousand years
Peter 3:8.
In the knowledge of God, the past, present, and future are all equally present.
What seems to us like long or short periods of time are all the same to God.
We've highlighted these specific sacred numbers merely as examples.
Besides these, there are many more, and almost all are sacred.
As a student of divine reading, you'll discover how they are made.