Historical Account of Saint Leo
Leo the Third was a Roman by birth, the son of Azuppius, and he served for twenty years, five months, and seventeen days.
From a young age, he was raised and educated within the patriarchate's wardrobe, becoming spiritually trained in all church disciplines, excelling in the Psalms and the sacred divine Scriptures.
He became a subdeacon and was later elevated to the priesthood.
Known for his chastity, eloquence, and steadfast spirit, he always sought to engage in divine conversations and prayer whenever he encountered an exceptional monk or servant of God.
He was also known for his cheerful almsgiving and his dedication to visiting the sick, preaching to them scripturally to encourage them to redeem their souls through alms.
Many who agreed with his teachings secretly gave to the poor, day and night, following his recommendations for Christ.
He often presented the fruits of souls healthily to God, and during his time in the wardrobe, his diligence was cherished, and he was dearly loved by all.
Therefore, by divine inspiration and with unanimous agreement from priests, nobility, the entire clergy, and the Roman people by God's will, he was elected on the feast of Saint Stephen, the first martyr.
The next day, during the feast of Saint John the Apostle and Evangelist, he was ordained as the pontiff in the Apostolic See to the praise and glory of Almighty God.
He was a defender of church matters, a strong opponent of adversaries, exceedingly gentle, and a well-wishing and distinguished lover of the Church.
Slow to anger and quick to show mercy, he did not return evil for evil, nor did he seek vengeance, but remained pious and merciful.
From the time of his ordination, he endeavored to ensure justice for all and notably expanded the stipend for his clergy in the priesthood.
In the Basilica of Saint Peter, dedicated to the prince of the apostles, he crafted a golden censer for his protector, weighing 17 pounds, and placed it at the entrance of the altar.
Additionally, at the confession of the same apostle, he adorned the space with pure gold drapes embedded with various gems weighing 49 pounds, along with three large silver crowns weighing 307 pounds.
Moreover, there were white silk curtains with roses, featuring a cross made of gold thread in the center, and one curtain with a fringe.
He restored the roofs of the Basilica of Saint Peter the Apostle, including the main nave and another nave above the altar, featuring a four-columned portico and a fountain, as well as the area in front of the silver doors; and also the tower with its chambers from bottom to top.
Notably, he placed an image of the Savior, along with other beautifully painted images, at the arch's peak to enhance the beauty of the church.
Similarly, he created and installed similar images in the Basilica of Saint Paul the Apostle and in the Basilica of the Savior.
He also restored the roofs of the Church of Saint Anastasia, which had decayed over time due to neglect and were on the verge of collapse, with great dedication.
In the same manner, he carefully renovated the Church of Saint Sabina.
In this temple, the same distinguished bishop crafted five silver crowns weighing 14 pounds, two baskets weighing 3 and a half pounds, and nine engraved dishes weighing 11 pounds.
Furthermore, in the Basilica of the Blessed Mother of God, known as "Ad Praesepe," he created a ciborium made of pure silver weighing 611 pounds.
Additionally, silver drapes at the presbytery entrance weighed 80 pounds, along with a large white silk curtain featuring a fringe and a cross made of gold thread.
On the most sacred main altar, he crafted a garment of gold thread depicting the Nativity story, Saint Simeon, and cherubim at its center.
At the same time, in the church chamber and the portico, there were three silver crowns weighing 145 pounds and 9 ounces.
Meanwhile, in the basilica of the blessed martyr of Christ, Lawrence, located outside the walls, he crafted three silver images of the Savior, the blessed apostle Peter, and Saint Lawrence, all weighing 54 and a half pounds.
On the holy altar, there was a silk garment embroidered with the story of the Lord's passion and resurrection.
He also renovated the roofs of the blessed martyrs Felix and Adauctus, near Saint Paul the Apostle, as well as the basilica of Saint Menna, the title of the blessed martyr Vitalis of Christ, and the cemetery of the blessed Sixtus and Cornelius on the Appian Way.
Likewise, he worked on the cemetery of Saint Zoticus on the Lavican Way and the church of the Holy Mother of God, our lady the ever-virgin Mary, located in Fonticana, which had decayed over time.
This bishop also created a confession in the basilica of the teacher of the world, the blessed apostle Paul, with folds of pure gold adorned with precious gems, weighing 156 pounds, resembling those of the blessed apostle Peter.
Above the holy altar, there was a golden image of the Savior and the twelve apostles, weighing 75 pounds.
Additionally, he newly constructed the chamber of the same basilica in the manner of the blessed apostle Peter, with three silver crowns, one weighing 220 pounds.
He also provided larger silk curtains with embroidery and a cross made of bathin, totaling fifteen.
Larger mixed curtains adorned fourfold, hanging on 43 arches.
Smaller sealed curtains hung on smaller arches, decorated fourfold twenty.
There were also smaller curtains of stauracin, hanging on ten arches, and another set of ten, three of which had embroidery with gold thread.
Additionally, there were four curtains with Alexandrian thread and a curtain with an authentic pattern featuring embroidery, wheels with latticework, and in the middle, a cross with gems, along with four wheels of Tyrian thread.
In the Basilica of Saint Andrew at Saint Peter the Apostle, he crafted silver draperies weighing 80 pounds.
Additionally, in the Basilica of the Savior, known as the Constantinian Basilica, he built a chamber of impressive size.
This kind-hearted bishop adorned the main altar of Saint Peter, the chief of the apostles, with a garment featuring gold-embroidered stripes and precious gems.
It depicted stories of the Savior granting Saint Peter the power to bind and loose, as well as illustrating the passion of the chief apostles Peter and Paul, shown in splendid size on the apostles' feast day.
He also crafted a garment at the title of Eudoxia over the altar, showcasing larger griffins, two gold-striped wheels with a cross, and decorations in purple, gold stripes, and a gold-embroidered band.
This distinguished bishop also created in the Basilica of Saint Peter the Apostle a silver lantern in front of the presbytery with 30 silver bowls and an octagonal basket in the middle weighing 63 pounds.
He placed silver candlesticks both around the altar and in the presbytery, with a total weight of 212 pounds.
On the altar of Saint Petronilla, he placed a single garment made of stauracin with decorations in purple or a gold-embroidered band.
He also made a garment in the Basilica of the Savior, also called the Constantinian, depicting the story of the crucifixion and resurrection of our Lord Jesus Christ, with decorations in a gold-embroidered band.
Furthermore, in the Basilica of Saint Clement, he crafted a single garment of stauracin with decorations in a gold-embroidered band.
He also created very beautiful curtains of stauracin in the silver arches of the Church of God the Apostle.
The chief high priest himself, at the Church of Saint Susanna where he had been ordained, expanded the building out of great love after it had been briefly destroyed and the remains had decayed over time.
He dug deep for a new construction and laid a very strong foundation.
On the flat surface, he wondrously built a church with a large apse and marvelous mosaics on the ceiling, decorating it, along with the presbytery and the floor, with beautiful marble.
He also constructed its portico on both the right and left with marble columns.
He established a baptistery there, where he presented gifts, including three golden plates weighing four and a half pounds;
two golden crosses with gems weighing one pound;
silver rods weighing three pounds and seven ounces;
a silver lamp weighing five pounds;
and three silver images weighing thirty-five pounds.
He also made the confession of the same altar from purest silver, weighing one hundred three pounds and two ounces.
Eight silver columns, two gammadia, and two arches with five silver crosses, along with fifteen plates weighing a total of one hundred fifty pounds.
A diacopton cross weighing fourteen pounds.
A basket from the wood of Cafotii weighing twelve and a half pounds.
One large silver crown with thirty-two dolphins weighing thirty-two pounds.
Also, one silver basket weighing eighteen pounds, and another silver basket weighing eighteen pounds.
Silver gilded straining vessels weighing four pounds and three ounces.
Silver plates with gilded griffins weighing two pounds.
Two silver crowns with eighteen dolphins weighing nineteen pounds.
Indeed, the same chief bishop made in the same church a chrysoclabam garment with periclysi, along with another purple garment having a cross of chrysoclabam in the middle.
There were four gold-embroidered panels adorned with gems and four more on the garment itself, all with gold-embroidered borders.
In the Lateran Patriarchate, he also created a larger dining hall, decorated more lavishly than any other, showcasing his greatness.
He laid the strongest foundations for it, surrounded it with marble slabs, and paved it with various marble patterns.
The room was adorned with different columns, both porphyry and white, sculpted with vases and lilies.
The apse ceiling was decorated with mosaic, and two other apses featured different stories painted on the marble incrustation, similarly decorated all around.
In the Basilica of Saint Prisca, the same bishop crafted a gold-plated chalice and three crowns-one with ten dolphins and the other two with nine each-as well as eight bowls weighing a total of twenty-nine pounds.
There was also a white silk garment trimmed with Byzantine purple and featuring a gold-embroidered cross on the front.
While this venerable and most holy bishop lived within the holy Catholic and Apostolic Roman Church, he adhered to the ecclesiastical order and the orthodox faith.
He constructed and elaborately decorated large buildings in various churches and the patriarchate.
On one particular day, as was customary, he participated in the Litanies, known as the Greater Litanies, where people gathered in sacred reverence to meet him.
According to annual custom, he celebrated the litanies and solemn masses with the priests, offering prayers to Almighty God for the salvation of the Christian people.
Following the tradition of the Roman Church's litany, when the litany was announced by a notary of the holy Roman Church in the Church of Saint George, Christ's martyr, on his feast day, all the devout men and women gathered at the Church of Saint Lawrence, Christ's martyr, known as Lucina, where the assembly took place.
When the respected bishop left the patriarchate, the deceitful Paschal, who cannot truly be called a leader, met him without his cloak and hypocritically asked for forgiveness, claiming:
"I am sick, and that's why I came without my cloak."
The most holy bishop forgave him.
Similarly, Campulus, the treasurer, joined in their deception, pretending to support the bishop, speaking sweet words they didn't mean. Evil and deceitful, these false Christians, truly pagans, sons of the devil, gathered with wicked intentions on their journey before the monastery of Saints Stephen and Sylvester, founded by Pope Paul.
Secretly armed, they lay in wait and suddenly sprang from hiding to mercilessly attack him, with Paschal at his head and Campulus at his feet, following their wicked plan.
When this occurred, all the people around him, unarmed and devoted to God's service, were terrified by the weapons and fled.
The assailants, like Judas, showed no respect for divine or human decency. They seized him like a wild animal, threw him to the ground, and, without mercy, stripped him, cruelly attempting to blind him completely.
They cut his tongue, and, believing they had left him blind and mute, abandoned him in the street.
But the wicked Paschal and Campulus, like true pagans and impious men, dragged him to the church of the monastery, and before the venerable altar, cruelly gouged his eyes and tongue again, beating him with various blows and clubs, leaving him half-dead and bloodied before the altar.
Later, they kept him under guard in the monastery.
Driven by the fear that they had stolen from the Christians, they devised a wicked plan, as confessed by the head of the monastery of Saint Erasmus himself.
Under the cover of night, they secretly brought him to them-both the malicious Pachalis, who was the chief officer, and Campulus, the treasurer, along with Maurus of Nepi.
Together, they sent him to the monastery of Saint Sylvester with many of their deceitful accomplices.
They took him away at night to the monastery of Saint Erasmus and locked him in a small, cramped cell.
However, Almighty God, who had long foreseen their wickedness, miraculously thwarted their evil plans.
Through God's intervention and the support of the blessed Apostle Peter, when the pope was being taken into custody at the monastery of Saint Erasmus, by the Lord's will and the help of the blessed keeper of the keys of the kingdom of heaven, he regained his sight and his ability to speak was restored.
To demonstrate His usual mercy and perform a great miracle for His servant, divine guidance led to him being secretly removed from the cloister by faithful Christian men, including Albinus the chamberlain and other God-fearing believers.
They brought him to the basilica of the blessed Peter, prince of the apostles, where his most sacred body rests.
Everyone who witnessed these wonders glorified the Lord God, who delivered the innocent and just pope from his enemies, saying:
"Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, who alone does great wonders and has not abandoned those who hope in Him"
(Psalm Seventy-Two).
He fulfilled His mercy in him so that the glory of God and His miracles might be revealed, as promised to those who hope in Him, as the psalmist says:
"The Lord is my light and my salvation; whom shall I fear? The Lord is the defender of my life; of whom shall I be afraid?"
(Psalm Twenty-Seven).
And again:
"Your word is a lamp to my feet, and a light to my path"
(Psalm One Hundred Nineteen).
And truly, the Lord rescued him from darkness, restored his light, and returned his speech.
He strengthened all his limbs and wonderfully guided him in all his works.
While the Christians and faithful people were filled with joy, those overwhelmed with grief and sorrow didn't know what to do.
Feeling endangered, they even considered taking their own lives.
When they couldn't find any other options, they plundered and destroyed the house of Albinus, a faithful servant of the blessed Apostle Peter and the pope.
As they joined the hall of the blessed Apostle Peter, the glorious Duke Winichis of Spoleto met them with his army.
Upon seeing the pope able to see and speak, he received him with reverence and led him to Spoleto, glorifying and praising God, who made him renowned through such wonders.
When this news spread to various cities, the faithful Romans came to meet him.
Along with some bishops, priests, Roman clerics, and city leaders, they set out to meet the most excellent Lord Charles, King of the Franks and Lombards and Patrician of the Romans.
This most Christian, orthodox, noble, and merciful king, upon hearing, immediately sent Archbishop Hildivald, his chaplain, and Count Ascharius to greet him.
Later, he sent his own son, the most excellent King Pippin, with other counts to meet him again until the great king himself met him.
As the vicar of the blessed Apostle Peter, he was received with reverence and honor, with hymns and spiritual songs.
Embracing each other with tears, they kissed.
As the aforementioned pope began "Glory to God in the highest," all the clergy joined in, and a prayer was offered for all the people.
Then the most gracious Lord Charles the Great, King, upon seeing the pope, gave thanks to God, who performed such great wonders for His servant through the support of the chief apostles Peter and Paul, and vanquished the wicked men.
After honoring him greatly for some time, those wicked ones, described as sons of the devil, committed terrible and unjust arsons on the possessions and properties of the blessed apostle Peter.
They attempted, with God opposing them, to falsely accuse the holy pope and send these accusations to the king, which they could never prove.
Through their plots and injustices, they sought to bring forward unspeakable matters to humiliate the holy Church.
But while the pope was staying in great and fitting honor with the merciful king, archbishops, bishops, and other priests, along with the advice of the devoted king and all the distinguished Franks, under God's guidance, sent him back to Rome to his apostolic seat with much honor, as was fitting.
In each city, they guided him to Rome as if receiving the apostle himself.
The Romans, with overwhelming joy, welcomed their shepherd.
On the eve of Saint Andrew the Apostle, all the leaders of the clergy with all clerics, as well as the nobility, the senate, all the soldiers, the entire Roman people with the nuns, deaconesses, noble matrons, and all the women, along with all the schools of foreigners, namely the Franks, Frisians, Saxons, and Lombards, gathered at the Milvian Bridge with signs, banners, and spiritual songs to receive him and led him to the church of Saint Peter the Apostle, where he celebrated the solemn masses.
And together, they all faithfully participated in the body and blood of our Lord Jesus Christ.
On another day, following the usual tradition, while celebrating the feast of Saint Andrew the Apostle, he entered Rome with great joy and happiness and proceeded to the Lateran Palace.
A few days later, he sent his most faithful companions who came with him for papal service, including the very reverend archbishops Hildivald and Arno, the reverend and holy bishops Cunibert, Bernhard, Hatto, and Tesso, as well as Bishop-elect Flacco, along with the distinguished counts Helmgoth, Rothegarius, and Germanus.
They gathered in Pope Leo's hall.
For more than a week, they investigated those most wicked wrongdoers to see what wrongs they had suffered from their own pope.
Paschalis and Campulus, along with their followers, had nothing to say against him.
Then, the king's messengers arrested them and sent them to France.
Shortly after, when the great king was in the Basilica of Saint Peter the Apostle, he was received with great honor and gathered in the same church the archbishops, bishops, abbots, and all the nobility of the Franks and Romans.
Both the great king and the blessed pope sat together and had the most holy archbishops and abbots sit, while the other priests and nobles of the Franks and Romans stood, to address the charges made against the beloved pope.
All the archbishops, bishops, and abbots listened unanimously and said:
"We do not dare to judge the apostolic see, which is the head of all the Churches of God, for we are all judged by it and its vicar; it is judged by no one, as was the custom in ancient times, but we will canonically obey as the supreme pontiff himself decides."
The venerable prelate said:
"I follow in the footsteps of my predecessors, the pontiffs, and I am prepared to clear myself of such false accusations that have wickedly arisen against me."
On another day at the same church of Blessed Peter the Apostle, everyone was gathered: archbishops, bishops, abbots, all the Franks in service of the great king, and all the Romans in the same church of Blessed Peter.
The venerable pope embraced the holy Gospels of Christ before everyone, went up to the pulpit, and with a clear voice, under oath, declared:
"I have no knowledge of these false crimes that the Romans, who unjustly persecuted me, accused me of, nor do I admit to having done such things."
After this, all the archbishops, bishops, abbots, and clergy sang a litany, giving praise to God, to the Mother of God, our Lady Mary, ever-virgin, and to Blessed Peter, the Prince of the Apostles, and all the saints of God.
Following these events, as the birthday of our Lord Jesus Christ approached, everyone gathered again in the basilica of Blessed Peter the Apostle. The venerable and kind-hearted pope, with his own hands, crowned him with a most precious crown.
Then all the faithful Romans, witnessing his defense and love for the holy Roman Church and its vicar, unanimously shouted with a loud voice, by the will of God and Blessed Peter, the key-bearer of the kingdom of heaven:
"To Charles, the most pious Augustus, crowned by God, the great, peaceful emperor, life and victory."
Before the sacred confession of Blessed Peter the Apostle, invoking many saints, this was proclaimed three times, and he was appointed by all as emperor of the Romans.
Immediately, the most holy bishop and pope anointed Charles and his most excellent son as king with holy oil on the day of the birth of our Lord Jesus Christ. After the celebration of Mass, the most serene Lord Emperor himself offered a silver table with its legs weighing pounds...
Additionally, in the confession of the same Apostle of God, he offered, along with his outstanding son the king and his daughters, various vessels of the purest gold for the ministry of that table weighing pounds...
There's also a golden crown with large gemstones, weighing 55 pounds, that hangs above the altar.
Additionally, there's a larger golden paten adorned with various gemstones, weighing 30 pounds.
There's a larger chalice with gemstones and two handles, weighing 58 pounds.
Another larger chalice features a base and a handle, weighing 37 pounds.
Indeed, yet another larger chalice with a base, weighing 36 pounds.
He also offered at the most sacred altar of the blessed Apostle Peter, and in the basilica of the blessed Apostle Paul, a smaller silver table with its feet, weighing 55 pounds, along with various silver vessels of remarkable size used for the table itself.
In the basilica of our Lord Jesus the Savior, known as the Constantinian Basilica, he offered a cross with sapphire gemstones, which the holy pope decided should lead the procession at the request of the most pious emperor.
Indeed, there was also an altar with silver columns and a canopy.
Truly, there was also a Gospel made of the purest gold adorned with gemstones, weighing.
.
Additionally, in the Basilica of the Blessed Mother of God Mary at the Manger, he offered larger silver shekels, weighing.
Later, when those most wicked criminals, namely Paschal and Campulus and their followers, were brought before the most pious lord emperor, with the noblest Franks and Romans standing around, all reproaching them for their evil plans and deeds, Campulus rebuked Paschal, saying, "I saw your face at a bad time, because you sent me into this danger"; and the others similarly, each condemning the other, revealed their own crimes.
When the most pious emperor realized how cruel and wicked they were, he sent them into exile in the regions of France.
The most holy pontiff adorned the apse in the main dining hall near the church of Saint Peter the Apostle with beautiful mosaics.
He also embellished two apses on the right and left with shining marble and paintings, and laid out the floor with marble patterns.
This was in addition to other large buildings, both on the staircase and behind the dining hall.
Furthermore, he created a golden robe adorned with precious gems, depicting the story of the Lord's resurrection in the basilica of Saint Peter the Apostle.
He also placed white silk curtains and beautiful staurac curtains between the silver arches.
Upon his return, out of great love, he made a new marble presbytery of great beauty for the same church, finely sculpted and erected.
Moreover, he placed four complete silk curtains with rods and golden roses over the main altar.
On the same altar, he crafted a Tyrian robe with the story of the Lord's crucifixion.
In the church of Saint Paul the Apostle, he placed four complete silk curtains and a Tyrian robe on the altar with the story of the holy resurrection.
Another golden robe depicted the story of the Lord's nativity and the holy Innocents.
Additionally, another Tyrian robe illustrated the story of the healing of the blind and the resurrection.
The same most holy bishop crafted a white golden robe in the basilica of Saint Mary at the Crib with the story of the holy resurrection.
Another robe with golden circles depicted the stories of the Annunciation and Saints Joachim and Anne.
In the church of Saint Lawrence outside the walls, the same bishop made a white rose-colored robe with gold, and another white robe over his holy body of staurac with gold and pearls.
In the title of Calixtus, he fashioned a golden robe from Byzantine cloth with the story of the Lord's nativity and Saint Simeon.
Also, in the church of Saint Pancras, he crafted a Tyrian robe with the story of the Lord's ascension, and similarly in Saint Mary at the Martyrs, he made a Tyrian robe as mentioned earlier.
In the church of Saint Sabina, as previously mentioned.
And in the deaconry of Saint Boniface, also as mentioned before.
And in the deaconry of Saint Mary, known as Cosmidin, as before.
In the basilica of Saints Cosmas and Damian, he created a garment from Byzantine silk adorned with gold embroidery and pearls.
At the church of Saint Valentine, he crafted a garment with gold embroidery and another from exquisite fabric.
In the deaconry of Saints Nereus and Achilleus, he made a garment from stauracin.
And in the deaconry of the Holy Mother of God, called Dominica, he also made a garment from stauracin.
The generous pope crafted a silver vessel with its basket weighing twelve pounds for the venerable monastery of Saint Saba.
He also made a garment from stauracin with gold embroidery and pearls.
In the monastery of Saint Erasmus, he created a garment from stauracin featuring a cross and bands, beautifully decorated with gold embroidery.
In the church of Pammachius, he made two garments, one from stauracin with gold embroidery.
And another from purple fabric.
The frequently mentioned holy bishop repaired the roof of the church of the blessed Apostle Andrew, located thirty miles along the Appian Way in Scilice, including the baptistery and the portico.
In this church, he established a presbytery and offered gifts in silver, as well as in clothes and books.
However, during the ninth indiction, as our sins loomed, an earthquake struck on the day before the Kalends of May, causing the church of the blessed Apostle Paul to collapse entirely.
Witnessing this, the great and renowned pope was deeply troubled, lamenting the loss of silver and other items that were destroyed.
But with the Lord's favor and the protection of the blessed prince of the apostles, the pope, with all his efforts, restored it to a better state, striving to return it to its ancient glory with great strength.
To enhance its appearance, he adorned the church with marble, covering both the presbytery and the entire church, and renovated its porticos.
In the nave above the altar, he restored the entire roof and placed three golden images there, featuring our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ and the blessed chief apostles Peter and Paul.
He also installed another gilded silver image of the Savior over the entrance posts, weighing 60 pounds.
He repaired all the damaged silver and beautifully decorated the church windows with Cyprian metal.
This same pontiff crafted two altar cloths in the Basilica of the Savior, known as the Constantinian.
One depicted the story of the Savior entering the holy city with gold embroidery and gems, while the other illustrated the Lord's resurrection, also with gold embroidery and precious gems.
He placed four red silk veils and four white ones with gold embroidery around the altar.
He also made three veils with a border before the images and 37 additional white silk ones.
On the altar of Saint Venantius, he crafted a cloth with two veils.
In the oratories of Saints John the Baptist and John the Evangelist, he made stauracin garments with gold embroidery and two veils.
On the altar of Saint Peter the Apostle, he created a garment adorned with pure gold vines, precious gems, and pearls, featuring the face of the Savior, Mary, the Mother of God, and the twelve apostles, and placed 25 pounds of gold there.
He also made another garment with gold embroidery depicting the story of the great litany.
Additionally, he crafted a garment with three gold-embroidered panels illustrating the story of the Lord's Passion, inscribed with: "This is my body, which is given for you," and more.
He also created a larger foundation curtain.
He crafted Easter curtains featuring five silver arches adorned with intricate staurach embroidery in gold thread, totaling ninety-three in number.
On these arches, he added forty-eight larger white curtains.
He also made fifteen bowls of the purest gold, adorned with gems, which hung in the pergola in front of the altar, weighing sixty-five and a half pounds.
Additionally, he crafted a table in front of the confession area from the purest gold, weighing twenty-nine pounds.
He placed two gilded silver images on the larger royal arches, each weighing ninety pounds.
Moreover, he created two silver drinking vessels in the presbytery, weighing fifty pounds, and embellished the church windows with Cyprian metal.
Other windows were decorated with glass of various colors.
In the basilica of the Doctor of the World, the blessed Apostle Paul, he fashioned a garment with gold thread that depicted the Savior in the center, with Saints Peter and Paul preaching to the nations on either side, all adorned with embroidered gold thread and precious gems.
Over the altar of Saint Andrew, he made a garment with gold thread and pearls, and also decorated the presbytery with marbles.
At the altar of Saint Petronilla, he crafted a white silk garment with gold-threaded panels and a cross, and decorated the presbytery with carved marbles.
He also made six silver columns and two regular ones of purest silver, with a combined weight of eighty pounds.
Over the body of the blessed confessor and bishop Gregory, he created a white silk garment with gold-threaded panels and a cross.
Additionally, in the basilica of the Holy Mother of God at the Crib, he made an Alexandrian curtain with staurach embroidery, another white one with staurach embroidery, and another white one with blatthin embroidery, which hung over the altar, and in front of the crib, white curtains with blatthin embroidery.
Moreover, within the larger rugs and in front of the secretarium, totaling twelve, and inside the crib, he made a garment of alythin with gold thread.
Furthermore, in the basilica of the blessed martyr Lawrence outside the walls, he crafted a Tyrian curtain with staurach embroidery.
In the basilica of Saint Pancras the Martyr, he crafted a ciborium from the purest silver, weighing 367 pounds.
At the Church of Callistus, in honor of the holy Mother of God and ever-virgin Mary, he created a ciborium from silver weighing 504 and a half pounds.
At the Church of Eudoxia, he crafted a white garment with a border of gold thread.
At the Church of Saint Cecilia, he made a garment of decorated fabric.
Also, at the Church of Saint Eusebius, he fashioned a garment of woven fabric.
At the Church of Saint Vitalis, he designed a garment of decorated fabric with a cross of gold thread.
Similarly, at the Church of Saint Pudentiana, he created a garment as mentioned before.
At the Church of Saint Anastasia, he produced a garment of woven fabric.
At the Church of Saint Praxedes, he made a garment of decorated fabric with borders of a special blue fabric.
In the basilica of Saint Lawrence in Formoso, he fashioned a garment of quadruple fabric.
In the monastery of Saint Anastasius, he created a garment of gold thread with the martyr's passion depicted, and a silver lighthouse with an eight-sided basket weighing 25 pounds.
In the monastery of Saint Sylvester, he made two garments: one in the major Byzantine basilica with gold thread, and another of woven fabric in the chapel.
In the monastery of Saint Lucia in Renatis, he crafted a garment of woven fabric with gold thread.
In Saint Angelo in Fabiano, he made a garment of woven fabric.
In the diaconate of Saint Lucia on the Seven Roads, he produced a garment of woven fabric.
In the diaconate of Saints Sergius and Bacchus, he fashioned a garment of decorated fabric.
In the diaconate of Saint Lucia in Orfea, he created a garment of decorated fabric.
In the diaconate of Saint Eustace, he made a garment of woven fabric.
The venerable and kind pontiff, protected by God, crafted in the basilica of Saint Peter the Apostle, his protector, a crucifix from the purest silver weighing 72 pounds in the middle of the basilica.
He also created a remarkably large dining hall in the Lateran Palace, decorated with a mosaic apse.
Alongside it, there were ten additional apses on both sides, painted with various stories of apostles preaching to the nations, all connected to the Constantinian Basilica.
In this location, he placed couches and, in the center, a porphyry basin that poured water.
Moreover, he laid the floor with different types of marble.
In the church of Saint Cyriacus, he crafted a stauracin garment with blattin borders, featuring a gold-embroidered band and a cross of pearls in the middle.
Likewise, at the cemetery of Saint Sixtus on the Appian Way, he made a stauracin garment with a gold-embroidered cross in the center.
Furthermore, in the church of Callistus, above the altar behind the apse, he fashioned a stauracin garment with a gold-embroidered cross in the middle, along with six stauracin curtains.
In the church of the Four Holy Crowned Ones, he made a stauracin garment with a gold-embroidered cross in the center.
In the church of Saint Marcellus, he also crafted a stauracin garment.
Similarly, in the church of Saint Sabina the martyr, he created a woven fabric garment with blattin borders and a gold-embroidered cross in the middle.
Additionally, in the basilica of Saint Lawrence in Formoso, he made a woven fabric garment.
Regarding the church of the blessed Apostle Paul, known as the convent, located in the territory of Orbetello within the boundaries of Suana, Clusium, Tuscia, and Castrum, which had fallen into decay and become a refuge for animals, from which relics had been removed, the same most holy bishop ordered it to be cleaned and restored all its roofs in the porticoes.
He placed a stauracin garment on its altar and commanded the relics to be reinstalled.
Similarly, in the basilica of the blessed Apostle Peter located in Albano, which was also falling into ruin due to age, he restored all its roofs.
The benevolent pope crafted two brocade garments in the basilica of the blessed Hippolytus the martyr in the city of Porto-one for his body and another for the main altar.
In the church of Saint Sabina the martyr, he designed brocade canopies with blue cloth borders.
Additionally, in the chapel of the Holy Mother of God located in the hostel in Firmis, he created a very beautiful brocade garment.
This God-protected and distinguished pope decreed that litanies should be celebrated on the three days before the Lord's Ascension.
On Monday, the pope, along with all the clergy and people, would process with hymns and spiritual songs from the church of the Mother of God to the Manger, ending at the church of the Savior, known as the Constantinian.
On Tuesday, they would start at the church of Saint Sabina the martyr and proceed to the church of blessed Paul the apostle.
On Wednesday, they would begin at the church of Jerusalem and move towards the church of Saint Lawrence the martyr outside the walls.
He also crafted a brocade garment with a gold-thread cross in the middle in the church of the four crowned saints.
This same most holy bishop made a brocade garment with woven fabric borders and a gold-thread cross in the middle in the basilica of the blessed Agapitus the martyr in the city of Palestrina.
The same bishop also created a brocade garment in the church of Saint Clement, located in Velletri.
Similarly, in the church of Saint Chrysogonus, he crafted a brocade garment with blue cloth borders.
In the church of Saint Lawrence in Lucina, he made a brocade garment with blue cloth borders.
At the church of Saint Mark, he designed a brocade garment with borders.
In the church of Saint Lawrence in Damaso, he made a similar garment.
In the church of Saint Sixtus, he crafted a brocade garment with blue cloth borders, and similarly in the deaconry of Saint Adrian, the church of Saint Martina, and the old deaconry, he made garments of brocade with borders.
In a similar manner, while serving the blessed archangel, he crafted three garments.
One was made of stauracin with purple borders, and the other two were Tyrian with purple borders.
Additionally, he created two more Tyrian garments with borders of embroidered fabric featuring an elephant design.
Furthermore, in honor of Saint Theodore, he made a garment of stauracin with purple borders.
For Saint George, he designed a garment with embroidered fabric showcasing an elephant design or various other designs with embroidered borders.
He also made a garment of stauracin with purple borders for the service at Gyro.
Likewise, for the service on the Via Lata, he produced two Tyrian garments with purple borders.
For Saint Agatha, he fashioned a garment of stauracin with purple borders.
In the basilica of the blessed archangel, situated in the Seventh Region, he crafted a garment of stauracin with purple borders.
At the monastery of Saint Agapitus, located at the Chains, he made a garment of stauracin.
The compassionate bishop also created a garment of embroidered fabric with purple borders in the church of Saint Agnes the martyr, where her body lies.
In the church of Saint Apollinaris, he produced a garment of stauracin with purple borders.
This same merciful bishop crafted two stauracin garments for the title of Saint Martin and Sylvester, one with embroidered fabric borders and the other with purple borders.
For Saint Vitus, he made a garment of stauracin with embroidered fabric borders.
Indeed, in the church of Saint Eugenia, where her holy body rests, he crafted a garment of stauracin with purple borders.
In the church of Saint Stephen on the Caelian Hill, he made two stauracin garments, one for the main altar and another over the bodies of the holy martyrs Primus and Felician.
Similarly, in the basilica of Saint Euphemia, he crafted a garment of stauracin.
Additionally, in the basilica of the blessed archangel on Patrician Street, he made a garment of stauracin.
Over the tomb of Saint Sebastian the martyr on the Appian Way at the Catacombs, he created two larger garments, one of stauracin and another of embroidered fabric.
And there, over the tombs of the apostles Peter and Paul, he crafted two garments from stauracin and fundato, also known as blatthin.
The same most holy bishop also created a garment from stauracin in the basilica of Saint Lawrence the Martyr, located within the city of Tivoli.
Additionally, he made a garment from stauracin in the oratory of Saint Stephen in Saint Peter's, which is referred to as the major.
Furthermore, he fashioned a very beautiful garment from stauracin in the basilica of Saint Hyacinth located in the Sabines, where his body also rests.
The same God-protected and illustrious pope created a remarkable garment from chrysoclavus over the altar of Saint Peter the Apostle, his patron, featuring the story of the Lord's Nativity, adorned with precious gems and pearls.
Moreover, in the aforementioned church, he crafted curtains of stauracin and fundato that hang between the larger columns on both sides, totaling 65.
And three other large white silk curtains hang in front of the royal doors at the entrance.
There, his blessedness made a crucifix from the purest silver, which stands next to the main altar and is of remarkable size, weighing 52 pounds.
Above it, he fashioned six bowls with a cross from the purest silver, which hang in front of the main arch on both sides, weighing a total of 12 and a half pounds.
Indeed, even there, the illustrious pope created curtains from stauracin that hang on silver arches around the altar and in the presbytery, numbering 96.
Among these, two have crosses of chrysoclavus in the middle with orbs, and eight others have borders of chrysoclavus.
He also constructed arches with their columns from the purest silver in the aforementioned church, with the middle presbytery weighing a total of 251 and a half pounds.
The same nourishing pope also crafted a carved cross from the purest gold, hanging in the pergula before the altar, complete with twelve candles, weighing 13 pounds.
The aforementioned venerable bishop crafted larger chalices for the basilica of the blessed Paul the Apostle, the teacher of the world, using the purest silver from the Apostle's gifts.
These chalices hang on the main arch, totaling eleven, along with others hanging between the larger columns on the right and left, making forty in all, weighing a total of two hundred sixty-seven pounds.
This blessed bishop, inspired by divine guidance, also created a canopy with columns over the altar in the basilica of the blessed Paul the Apostle.
It is remarkably large and beautiful, adorned with the purest silver, weighing two thousand fifteen pounds.
Additionally, he fashioned a cross in bas-relief from the purest gold, which hangs in the pergola before the altar, weighing thirteen pounds, along with a red veil featuring a cross made of gold and precious stones in the center.
Similarly, in the basilica of the Holy Mother of God at the Crib, he crafted five bowls of the purest gold, weighing eight and a half pounds, a cross of the purest gold weighing ten pounds, and a larger crown of the purest silver weighing thirty-six pounds.
Furthermore, he created white silk veils that hang between the larger columns on the right and left, totaling forty-two, with eleven of them being rose-colored.
Around the altar, as previously mentioned, he made other white silk rose-colored veils hanging in a set of four on the canopy's arch, one adorned with gold and pearls, and a larger white veil that hangs before the main royal entrance.
He also repaired all the roofs of the church of the blessed Aurea in Ostia.
The church of the blessed Marcellus, located in the fourteenth district, which had been damaged by fire, was fully restored by this same blessed bishop.
The distinguished bishop also created four white silk veils around the altar in the basilica of the Savior, known as the Constantinian, one featuring a panel with a cross made of gold and precious stones in the center.
In the basilica of our Lord Jesus Christ the Savior, he renovated the main altar, which is impressively large and decorated with pure silver weighing 69 pounds.
He also crafted a garment in the basilica of the Holy Mother of God at the Manger, featuring gold embroidery and adorned with pearls, illustrating the story of the Lord's birth.
Furthermore, he created two silver arches in the presbytery with four columns, along with an additional five arches weighing 133 pounds.
This distinguished prelate also made a red alythinian garment in the basilica of the Holy Mother of God at the Manger, featuring a central panel of gold embroidery with the story of our Lord Jesus Christ and Saint Simeon during the temple presentation.
It was surrounded by a border of gold embroidery.
Another garment, embroidered with gold, depicted the passing of the Holy Mother of God, showcasing remarkable size and beauty, decorated with precious gems and pearls, and finished with gold embroidery borders.
Similarly, in the diaconia of the same Mother of God, known as Dominica, he created a red alythinian garment with a central panel of gold embroidery depicting the story of the Mother of God, adorned with pearls and gold embroidery borders.
In the diaconia of the same Mother of God, called Antiqua, he also made a canopy over the main altar from pure silver, weighing 212 pounds.
This venerable and illustrious bishop crafted a bowl of pure gold with embossed work, adorned with precious gems, for the basilica of the blessed apostle Peter, his nourisher.
It hangs in front of the apostle's image at the entrance of the vestibule, weighing 7 and a half pounds.
The front of the sacred altar, dedicated to the chief of the apostles, is beautifully decorated with lights from top to bottom.
Inside the confession, the Savior is depicted standing with the blessed apostles Peter and Paul on either side.
Each of them holds crowns crafted from precious gems.
The floor of this confession is covered in gold, weighing an impressive four hundred fifty-three pounds and six ounces.
Additionally, he created a garment for the sacred altar, bordered with gold, illustrating the stories of the Lord's Ascension and Pentecost.
He also crafted an image of the chief of the apostles on the men's gate, decorated with purest gold and stunning precious gems, weighing nineteen pounds and three ounces.
Moreover, the same blessed pontiff designed lattices at the entrance of the presbytery, on both the right and left sides, as well as at the vestibule entrance, all made from purest silver, with a combined weight of one thousand five hundred seventy-three pounds.
He also created flying columns at the entrance for both men and women, weighing a total of one hundred ninety pounds, along with eight silver arches weighing one hundred forty-three pounds altogether.
In the basilica of Saint Andrew, the same blessed pontiff crafted a crown of purest gold adorned with precious gems, weighing two pounds and five ounces.
Additionally, on the altar of Saint Petronilla, he made a golden crown with the finest gems, weighing two pounds and three ounces.
Similarly, on the altar of the holy Mother of God, known as Mediana, he created a garment bordered with gold, depicting the story of the Lord's Annunciation.
The same blessed pontiff also made forty-seven baskets of pure silver for the basilica of the teacher of the world, the blessed Apostle Paul, weighing a total of two hundred forty-seven pounds.
At the monastery of Saint Agatha the Martyr, over Suburra, he crafted a red alythinian garment featuring a central panel and borders of gold-threaded fabric.
In the monastery of Saint Pancras, located behind the Basilica of the Savior, known as the Constantinian, he created a garment from woven material.
For the blessed Apostle Peter, his patron, he made golden gospels adorned with large green, blue, and white gems, weighing seventeen pounds and four ounces.
He crafted a special golden chalice decorated with various precious stones, weighing twenty-eight pounds.
Similarly, he made a golden dish weighing twenty-eight pounds and nine ounces.
In the basilica of the same apostle, he created four cherubim of the purest silver, gilded, standing over the heads of silver columns with a canopy, weighing ninety-three pounds.
He also made a golden image of the Savior, positioned on the beam above the vestibule entrance, weighing seventy-nine pounds.
In the basilica of the blessed Apostle Paul, the teacher of the world, he crafted two angels of the purest silver, gilded, placed next to the Savior's image at the vestibule entrance, weighing one hundred and a half pounds.
He made a purple chandelier hanging in the pergola in front of the confession, with golden chains weighing one pound.
At the entrance of the basilica, above the major royal doors, he created five silver images weighing two hundred twenty-nine pounds.
Additionally, he made two pairs of gold-plated handwashing basins there, weighing fourteen pounds together.
The wise bishop also crafted larger movable candelabras of the purest silver, weighing eighty-six pounds and eight ounces in total.
He made larger cast lamps with embossed designs, two of which weigh fifty-seven pounds, and decreed they should burn every night before the same apostle's altar.
Inspired by divine grace, he adorned the main beam beneath the principal arch with the purest silver, weighing one thousand three hundred fifty-two pounds.
This distinguished bishop also crafted a magnificent golden garment for the main altar, beautifully decorated with the story of our Lord Jesus Christ the Savior, His holy Mother, and the twelve apostles, all adorned with pearls and gold embroidery on both sides.
He chose to display this during the apostles' feast.
Moreover, he created a golden cross, richly adorned with precious gems, weighing forty-two pounds and two ounces.
He also invested in four pairs of embroidered draperies, gilded with silver, collectively weighing seventy-seven pounds.
This venerable and distinguished bishop also made a canopy over the altar of blessed Petronilla, with columns of pure silver of extraordinary size, weighing three hundred forty-eight pounds, along with a silver statue under the arch of the canopy, weighing ten and a half pounds.
This God-protected and illustrious bishop also contributed to the basilica of the world's teacher, blessed Apostle Paul, by creating a golden garment for the main altar, featuring the story of Christ's resurrection, adorned with pearls and gold embroidery.
He also fashioned two silver-gilt images of the apostles, adorned with pearls, weighing eighty-six pounds.
This merciful bishop also created a golden garment in the basilica of the Holy Mother of God at the Manger, on the altar, featuring the story of Christ's resurrection.
This garment was of great size and beauty, decorated with gold embroidery and adorned with pearls.
In the church of the Holy Mother of God, known as Callisti, he made a canopy of pure gold, hanging over the main altar, adorned with precious gems, weighing one pound.
For the ministry dedicated to the Mother of God, known as the Lord's, he crafted a kingdom of purest gold that hangs over the main altar, adorned with precious gems weighing two pounds.
This blessed bishop, inspired by divine guidance, created royal doors made of purest silver for the Basilica of the Mother of God at the Manger, located at the entrance.
These doors together weigh one hundred and twenty-seven pounds.
Above them, a small veil with a gold-threaded border was placed.
He also designed three Tyrian veils with embroidered patterns for the main doors at the entrance of the basilica.
Additionally, this distinguished bishop crafted larger chalices of purest silver for the Basilica of Saint Peter the Apostle.
These chalices rest on silver beams, totaling eighteen in number and weighing one hundred and eighty-two pounds combined.
Furthermore, he created large cast candelabras of purest silver, positioned before the confession, weighing one hundred and ninety-eight pounds.
He invested in a silver beam of purest silver over the golden image at the vestibule entrance, weighing one hundred twenty-six and a half pounds.
Moreover, he made two cast lamps of purest silver weighing a total of twenty-seven pounds.
He decreed that on Sundays or during holy celebrations, these lamps should be placed on either side of the lectern to shine brightly for reading the sacred lessons.
For the blessed Apostle Andrew, he crafted a ciborium of purest silver over the main altar, weighing three hundred and five pounds.
The chief bishop, divinely inspired, noticed that the baptistery was on the brink of ruin due to its age and was too small for the people coming for baptism.
This prelate decided to rebuild the baptistery from the ground up, giving it a larger, round shape and elevating it to a better condition.
He established the holy font in a more spacious central area.
He adorned the baptistery with porphyry columns around it and placed a column in the middle of the font with a lamb made of the purest silver pouring water, weighing 18 pounds and 10 ounces.
Additionally, he constructed the main altar under the apse, decorating its front and the confession, or folds, for the altar's beauty with the purest silver weighing 48 pounds.
He also placed a stauracium cloth over it and made a standard covering of the purest silver.
He set an arch and gammadias of silver over this standard, weighing a total of 80 pounds.
Furthermore, he placed three images there, weighing 37 pounds and 10 ounces.
The baptistery was also decorated with various paintings around it.
The oratory of the Holy Cross, which was also nearing collapse due to its age, was rebuilt from the foundations with a new structure for the apse by this chief pastor, bringing it to completion.
He decorated the apse with mosaics and various paintings and adorned it with marbles of remarkable splendor.
He offered a ciborium over the altar with its columns, adorning the face of the altar with the purest silver weighing 121 pounds and 2 ounces.
The spanoclystum crown made of the purest gold, with a cross hanging in the middle over the altar, weighed 1 pound and 11 ounces.
Additionally, there were four other silver columns and a standard covering of the purest silver over these columns, weighing 64 pounds and 3 ounces.
Three silver arches weighed 43 pounds and 8 ounces.
Images made of gilded silver, weighing a total of 30 pounds.
There are also twelve inlaid silver baskets weighing 78 pounds together, twenty-one inlaid silver goblets, and one cross, with a total weight of 50 pounds.
One patterned cloth is placed on the altar, along with another of purple with gold embroidery, and a white garment with rose and gold embroidery.
A small gold-embroidered veil is adorned with a crucifix and pearls.
There are seven veils of staurac, four patterned veils, and six small veils that regularly hang in front of Tyrian images.
Twelve white silk veils are decorated around the edges with patterns.
One large white veil with a rose design features quadruple embroidery, and there's another red veil with bull hide, which hangs in front of the larger royal images.
There are also four small veils of staurac that hang regularly in front of images, and eleven other assorted silk veils.
As mentioned earlier, three Tyrian veils were made at the fountains, which hang regularly in front of images, along with twenty-one other silk veils.
For the blessed apostle Peter, his protector, a special golden chalice was crafted, adorned with various precious stones, weighing 30 pounds.
In the same manner, a golden paten was made, similarly adorned with various precious stones, weighing 25 pounds.
Indeed, on the canopy of the main altar for the blessed apostle Peter, four larger vessels of the purest silver were made, containing in the middle gilded silver candles, weighing a total of 140 pounds.
The aforementioned and distinguished pontiff also created an apostolic censer of the purest gold, weighing 2 pounds and 5 ounces.
Furthermore, he crafted a gold-embroidered garment decorated with various illustrations for the major altar, intended for placement during the four seasons of the year in twelve readings.
Additionally, he made four larger crowns of the purest silver, weighing 154 and a half pounds together.
He crafted a lectern from pure silver of remarkable size, weighing 143 pounds.
He also made silver candlesticks of the finest quality, positioned next to the lectern, with a combined weight of 49 pounds.
Additionally, he created two cast lamps above these candlesticks from pure silver, weighing 27 pounds.
He decreed that on Sundays or holy festivals, these should stand beside the lectern to illuminate the sacred readings with their light.
He made 14 candelabra in the presbytery from the finest silver, with a total weight of 433 pounds.
Moreover, he constructed eight columns and four arches from silver, weighing 173 pounds.
He also crafted silver chalices, which hang between the larger columns on the right and left of the basilica, numbering 64 and weighing 461 pounds.
The same insightful bishop adorned the main altar dedicated to the blessed Apostle Andrew with pure silver, gilded and decorated with wondrous beauty, weighing 135 pounds in total.
He made 12 silver jugs weighing 52 pounds altogether.
He created 12 baskets from silver, weighing 78 pounds.
He adorned the altar of Saint Petronilla with gilded pure silver, decorated with various paintings, weighing 162 pounds and 8 ounces in total.
Additionally, he adorned the altar of Saint Gregory the Confessor and Bishop with gilded silver, weighing 127 pounds in total.
In the nave of the basilica of the blessed Apostle Peter, he made a larger Alexandrian silk canopy with an attached foundation in the middle and decorated all around with a foundation.
The same distinguished bishop crafted two apostolic incense burners from the purest gold.
One, weighing two pounds, was placed over his body, while the other, weighing two pounds and eight ounces, was used throughout the stations.
This generous bishop created these incense burners for the basilica of Saint Paul the Apostle.
He adorned the altar of the Holy Mother of God at the Crib with pure, decorated silver, weighing eighty-six pounds.
Additionally, he made two crowns from the purest silver, weighing fifty-four pounds.
He embellished larger Alexandrian silk curtains with embroidery.
Through the generosity of Almighty God and blessed Peter, the gatekeeper of the kingdom of heaven, this distinguished bishop offered crowns and baskets made of the purest silver to the sacred churches throughout the beloved city of Rome for the pardon of his sins.
In the church of Our Lord Savior, known as the Constantinian, he made crowns from the purest silver weighing twenty-three pounds.
In the basilica of the Holy Mother of God at the Crib, he made a crown from pure silver weighing thirteen pounds.
In the basilica of the Holy Mother of God in the title of Callistus, he crafted a crown from silver weighing thirteen pounds and three ounces.
In the deaconry of the same Mother of God, called the Ancient, he similarly made a crown from silver weighing thirteen pounds.
In the church of the Holy Mother of God at the Martyrs, he made a crown from silver weighing twelve pounds and three ounces.
In the deaconry of the same Mother of God, known as Cosmedin, he made a crown from silver weighing twelve pounds.
In the deaconry of the Holy Mother of God, called Dominica, he crafted a crown from silver weighing nine pounds.
In the deaconry of the Holy Mother of God, located on the Via Lata, he made a crown from silver weighing nine pounds.
In the deaconry of Saint Mary in Cyro, he crafted a crown weighing eight pounds.
Indeed, in honor of the blessed Mother of God, outside the gate of the blessed Apostle Peter, he crafted a silver crown weighing 5 pounds and 3 ounces.
For the service of the Mother of God at Adriano, he created a silver crown weighing 5 pounds.
Additionally, in the oratory of the holy Mother of God, located in the hospice of Firmis, he made a silver basket weighing 2 pounds and 7 ounces.
In the church of the blessed Apostle Peter, he fashioned a basket of purest silver weighing 22 pounds.
Similarly, in the church of the blessed Apostle Paul, he crafted a silver basket weighing 22 pounds and 12 ounces.
In the church of the blessed Apostle Andrew, known as Eudoxia, he created a silver crown weighing 9 pounds.
Also, in the church of the blessed John the Baptist, near the Lateran Palace, he crafted a silver crown weighing 5 pounds.
In the church of the blessed John the Evangelist, located in the same area, he made a silver crown weighing 5 pounds.
Likewise, in the church of the blessed Stephen on the Caelian Hill, he fashioned a silver crown weighing 7 pounds and 11 ounces.
In the basilica of the apostles on the Via Lata, he made a silver crown weighing 13 pounds.
In the mausoleum of the blessed Petronilla, near the blessed Apostle Peter, he crafted a silver crown weighing 20 pounds.
In the church of Jerusalem at the Sessorian, he created a silver crown weighing 5 pounds.
In the church of the blessed Lawrence, outside the walls, he similarly crafted a silver crown weighing 13 pounds.
In the church of the blessed Apollinaris the martyr, he made a crown weighing 5 pounds and 4 ounces.
Also, in the basilica of the blessed Pancras the martyr, outside the walls, he created a silver crown weighing 8 pounds.
He also crafted a silver crown weighing six pounds for the church of Saint Valentine, the martyr, located outside the wall where his body rests.
In the church of Saint Clement, the martyr and pope, he fashioned a silver crown weighing fifteen pounds.
For the church of the blessed Aquila and Prisca, he made a silver crown weighing six pounds.
Similarly, he did the same for the church of Saint Balbina.
In the church of Saint Sixtus, the martyr and pope, he created a similar crown.
At the church of Saint Lawrence, the martyr, located at Lucinae, he made one weighing four pounds and ten ounces.
In the church of Saint Lawrence, known as Damasi, he crafted a silver crown weighing five pounds.
For the church of the same martyr at Formosus, he made a silver basket weighing two pounds and seven ounces.
In the church of Pammachius, he designed a silver crown weighing ten pounds.
At the church of Aemiliana, he crafted a silver crown weighing four pounds.
Furthermore, in the church of Saint Eusebius, he made a silver crown weighing six pounds.
In the church of Praxedis, he fashioned a crown weighing five pounds.
For the church of Pudentis, he made a silver crown weighing nine pounds.
Moreover, in the church of Saint Vitalis, the martyr, he crafted a silver crown weighing nine pounds and three ounces.
In the church of Saint Susanna, the martyr, he created a crown weighing ten pounds.
In the church of Saint Cyriacus, he made a silver crown weighing five pounds.
At the church of Saint Marcellus, the martyr, he crafted a silver crown weighing ten pounds.
Likewise, in the church of Saint Marcus, the martyr, he fashioned a similar crown.
For the church of Saint Anastasia, he made a crown weighing seven pounds and nine ounces.
Furthermore, in the church of Caecilia, he created a silver crown weighing ten pounds and one ounce.
In the church of Saint Chrysogonus, the martyr, he fashioned a silver crown weighing five pounds.
For Saints Nereus and Achilleus, he crafted a silver crown weighing 6 pounds and 5 ounces.
For Saint Lucy, located on the Seven Roads, he made a silver crown weighing 6 pounds and 7 ounces.
For Saint Boniface, he created a crown weighing 7 pounds.
For Saint George, he made a silver crown weighing 5 pounds.
For Saint Theodore, he crafted a crown weighing 6 pounds and 8 ounces.
For Saints Sergius and Bacchus, he made a silver crown weighing 6 pounds.
For Saints Cosmas and Damian, he crafted a crown weighing 5 pounds and 8 ounces.
For Saint Adrian the martyr, he made a silver crown weighing 6 pounds.
For Saint Michael the Archangel, he crafted a silver crown weighing 6 pounds.
For Saint Eustace, he made a crown weighing 6 pounds and 5 ounces.
For Saint Lucy in Orfea, he crafted a silver crown weighing 6 pounds and 2 ounces.
For Saint Vitus the martyr in Macello, he made a silver crown weighing 6 pounds.
For Saint Agatha, he created a silver crown weighing 5 pounds.
He also crafted a silver crown weighing 4 pounds for Saint Sylvester, located next to the blessed Apostle Peter.
For Saint Martin, next to the blessed Apostle Peter, he made a silver crown weighing 5 pounds and 3 ounces.
For the title of Saints Sylvester and Martin, located next to Orfea, he crafted a silver crown weighing 6 pounds and 2 ounces.
The divinely protected and distinguished pontiff crafted a silver crown weighing 8 pounds and 10 ounces in the monastery of Saint Sabbas.
He crafted a silver crown weighing 8 pounds, 4 ounces, and a half at the monastery of Saint Anastasius the martyr.
Similarly, at the monastery of Saint Andrew on the Clivus Scauri, he created a pure silver crown weighing 5 pounds.
He did the same at the monastery of Saint Agatha the martyr, located above the Suburra.
Additionally, at the monastery of Saint Erasmus on the Caelian Hill, he made a silver crown weighing 4 pounds and 2 ounces.
In the same manner, he crafted a silver crown in the monastery of Saint Sylvester, weighing 6 pounds and 3 ounces.
At the monastery of Saint Lawrence the martyr, called Pallacini, he made a silver basket weighing 2 pounds and 7 ounces.
Moreover, at the monastery of Saint Pancras near the Basilica of the Savior, he fashioned a silver crown weighing 5 pounds and a half.
He also made a silver basket weighing 3 pounds at the monastery of Saints Andrew and Bartholomew, known as Honorius.
In the monastery of Saint Stephen near the Lateran, he crafted a silver basket weighing 2 pounds.
Similarly, in the monastery of the same first martyr Stephen at Saint Peter the Apostle, he made a silver basket weighing 3 pounds and a half.
This benevolent bishop also made a silver basket weighing 3 pounds in the monastery of Saints John and Paul, located near Saint Peter the Apostle.
In a similar fashion, at the monastery of Saint Martin, as previously mentioned, he made a basket weighing 4 pounds and 2 ounces.
At the monastery of Saint Stephen, referred to earlier as Catagalla Patricia, he fashioned a silver basket weighing 2 pounds and a half.
Likewise, in the monastery of Saint Caesarius at Saint Paul the Apostle, he made a similar silver basket weighing 3 pounds.
At the aforementioned monastery of Saint Stephen, he crafted a basket weighing 2 pounds.
Indeed, at the monastery of Saints Cosmas and Damian, located near the Manger, he crafted a silver basket weighing 2 pounds and 2 ounces.
Similarly, at the monastery of Saint Andrew, known as Massa Juliana, he made a silver basket weighing 2 pounds.
Also, at the monastery of Saint Adrian, near the Manger, he crafted a basket weighing 2 pounds.
And at the monastery of Saint Cassian, located near the blessed martyr Lawrence outside the wall, he created a silver basket weighing 4 pounds.
He also made, at the monastery of Saint Stephen, as mentioned before, a silver basket weighing 2 and a half pounds.
Moreover, at the monastery of Saint Victoria, located at Saint Pancras, he crafted a silver basket weighing 2 pounds and 7 ounces.
At the monastery of Saint Chrysogonus, he similarly made a basket weighing 3 pounds.
This generous bishop also created a silver basket weighing 2 pounds at the monastery of Saint Mary, called Ambrosii.
In the same way, he crafted one at the monastery of Saint Mary, known as Julia, as mentioned previously.
And at the monastery of Saint Andrew, near the Basilica of the Apostles, he did likewise.
Also, in the oratory of Saint Stephen, located in Dulciti, he made a silver basket weighing 2 pounds and 5 ounces.
Indeed, in the oratory of Saints Sergius and Bacchus, located in Callinico, he made a basket in the same fashion.
Further, at the monastery of Saint Agapitus, near the title of Eudoxia, he similarly crafted a silver basket weighing 2 and a half pounds.
Likewise, in the oratory of Saint Agnes, at the monastery called Duo Furna, he made a silver basket weighing 2 pounds and 8 ounces.
Also, in the oratory of Saint Vitus, at the monastery known as de Sardas, he crafted a silver basket weighing 3 pounds.
And at the monastery of Saint Bibiana, he similarly made a silver basket weighing 2 pounds and 9 ounces.
He also made a silver basket weighing 2 pounds for the chapel of Saint Lucia, located in the monastery of Renati.
Similarly, he crafted another silver basket weighing 2 pounds and 2 ounces for the chapel of Saint Mary in the monastery of Michael.
In the same manner, he created a silver basket weighing 3 pounds for the monastery of Saint Sergius.
The same generous bishop fashioned a silver basket weighing 3 pounds for the chapel of Saint Agatha, located in the monastery near Afric.
Additionally, he made a basket weighing 5 pounds in the monastery of Saints Euphemia and Archangel, near the title of Pudens.
He also created a similar basket in the monastery of Saint Isidore.
Likewise, he crafted another basket in the chapel of Saint Agatha, located in the monastery of the Temple.
In the chapel of Saint Caesarius, within the monastery of Corsas, he made a basket weighing 2 pounds and 3 ounces.
Indeed, he fashioned a similar silver basket in the monastery of Saint Semetrius.
He did the same in the chapel of Saint Mary, situated in the monastery of Aquae Salviae.
He made a similar silver basket weighing 2 pounds and 5 ounces in the monastery of Saint Donatus, near the title of Saint Prisca.
In the monastery of Saint John, located on the Aventine, he crafted a similar silver basket weighing 2 pounds.
In the chapel of Saint Mary, located in the monastery of Lutara, he made silver baskets weighing 2 and a half pounds.
He also fashioned a silver basket weighing 2 pounds in the monastery of Jerusalem, at the blessed Peter the Apostle.
Similarly, he crafted silver baskets weighing 5 pounds in the monastery of Saint Agnes, situated outside the Numentan Gate.
At the monastery of Saint Eugenia, located outside the Latin Gate, he created a silver basket weighing 5 pounds.
Similarly, in the oratory of Saint Gregory in the Field of Mars, he crafted silver baskets weighing 3 pounds.
The blessed bishop also made a pure silver crown weighing 8 pounds for the church of Saint Sabina.
Likewise, he crafted a silver crown weighing 6 pounds and 2 ounces for the diaconia of Saints Sylvester and Martin, near Orfea.
He also produced a silver basket weighing 2 pounds and 4 ounces for the oratory of Saint Lucia in the hospice.
Additionally, in the oratory of Saint Abbacyrus, also located in the hospice, he made a silver basket weighing 2 pounds.
In the oratory of Saints Cosmas and Damian, in the hospice called Tucium, he crafted a silver basket weighing 2 pounds and 1 ounce.
Moreover, in the oratory of Saint Peregrine at the Lord's hospital in the Naumachia, he created silver baskets weighing 5 pounds and 1 ounce.
The bishop crafted two chrysoclavus garments in the basilica of Our Lord Jesus Christ, known as the Constantinian, over the main altar: one depicting the story of the Lord's resurrection and the other illustrating the life-giving and venerated cross of the Lord.
He made eight silver jugs with a combined weight of 27 pounds and 6 ounces.
He invested in rugs made of pure silver, weighing 48 pounds and 8 ounces, for the area before the altar entrance.
Additionally, he made crowns of pure silver weighing 12 pounds.
He designed ten white silk canopies to adorn the fountains in the same location.
He also restored the church roof, including its quadriporticus and the area around the fountains.
Furthermore, he enclosed and decorated the apse windows with glass of various colors.
He repaired other windows of the basilica using Cyprian metal.
In the main part of the basilica, he crafted two curtains: one larger, plain white and the other smaller, white with a pink hue.
This same bishop also made, in the Basilica of the Holy Mother of God, known as the Manger, pink with gold embroidery, two pure silver jugs weighing 23 pounds, and two columns weighing 21 pounds and 5 ounces.
There was also a cross with a pure silver base, weighing a total of 5 pounds.
In the deaconry of the Mother of God, known as Antique, he crafted four decorated curtains with quadruple borders.
In the oratory of Saint Andrew above, he made two silk curtains decorated similarly.
In the title of the Mother of God, known as Callisti, he crafted a white silk garment with a pink hue, featuring a panel of gold embroidery in the center depicting the presentation of our Lord Jesus Christ and Saint Simeon, with purple embroidery.
He also made four red silk curtains with crosses, Greek letters, and purple embroidery around them.
There was a larger purple veil hanging before the image, with one purple embroidery.
Additionally, three smaller red silk curtains with incense in the middle, hanging before silver images with purple embroidery.
He created one larger silk curtain in the main part of the basilica and made gilded silver images, one adorned with gems, and a silver arch with its own Greek letters.
Above the wax lights, there was one lamp and two censers weighing a total of 95 pounds and 7 ounces.
The same foresighted bishop made a golden chalice adorned with various precious stones for blessed Peter the apostle, which precedes through the stations, weighing 13 pounds.
In the basilica of the apostle, he crafted a golden embroidered veil hanging above the entrance of the vestibule.
Additionally, there was another larger veil with golden embroidery hanging on a silver beam before the image of the Savior above the entrance of the vestibule.
He also made a larger crown of the purest silver, weighing 53 pounds and 8 ounces.
There's a silver lamp hanging below the crown itself, weighing 23 pounds.
Additionally, there are four silver crowns that weigh 57 pounds.
Eight baskets have a total weight of 40 pounds.
Out of love and care for the orthodox faith, he crafted two silver shields, each inscribed with a symbol-one in Greek letters and the other in Latin.
These hang on the right and left above the entrance of the building, weighing 94 pounds and 6 ounces.
In the basilica's nave, he made a larger silk curtain, decorated around the border with embroidery.
There's also a larger white silk, rose-colored veil hanging on the main beam above the golden images, also embroidered around the border.
Above the fountains, he crafted nine white silk veils, each beautifully embroidered.
As mentioned, he invested in the altar of the most blessed Leo, confessor and pontiff, with the finest gilded silver weighing a total of 109 pounds.
Similarly, he invested in the altar of the blessed Gregory, confessor and pontiff, with the same quality of gilded silver, weighing 127 pounds in total.
The prefect, guided by God, invested in the altar of the blessed Apostle Paul using the purest silver, weighing 155 pounds.
He also adorned the confession and face of the altar with the purest gold, weighing 121 pounds and 8 ounces.
Above the entrance of the building, he made a shield of the purest silver, inscribed with the symbol of the orthodox faith, weighing 32 pounds.
He crafted three larger crowns of the purest silver, with a combined weight of 93 pounds.
In the basilica, he also made a larger silk curtain, quadruple in size and exquisitely beautiful.
The distinguished bishop created a grand canopy over the main altar in the basilica of the blessed Apostle Peter, his patron.
This canopy features four columns of the purest gilded silver, beautifully adorned with various intricate scenes, and it weighs an impressive 2,704 pounds and three ounces.
The previous canopy was relocated to the main altar in the Basilica of the Blessed Mother of God, also known as at the Manger.
There, a cross made of pure silver was placed, weighing 12 pounds and three ounces.
Additionally, he crafted four red silk curtains, one of which was embellished with gold thread.
In the mausoleum of the blessed Petronilla, situated at the blessed Apostle Peter, he created three large white veils and eight smaller ones, all decorated around the edges with embroidery.
This esteemed bishop also fashioned angels of the purest silver, positioned on the right and left before the confession of the prince of the apostles, weighing 146 pounds.
Furthermore, he created two other gilded angels of the purest silver that stand on the large beam above the entrance of the vestibule, flanking the golden image of the Savior, weighing a combined 63 pounds.
Additionally, he made four smaller gilded angels of the purest silver in the same location, weighing a total of 68 pounds.
He also constructed six gilded silver columns at the entrance of the vestibule, adorned with various scenes, weighing a total of 147 pounds.
Next to the main altar, he placed a larger cross of the purest gilded silver, weighing 22 pounds.
At the entrance of the vestibule, he built a larger arch of the purest gilded silver, weighing 131 and a half pounds.
Inside the confession of the blessed Leo, confessor and bishop, he created a gospel book of the purest gilded silver, also located at the entrance of the vestibule, weighing 48 and a half pounds.
As mentioned earlier, he made a single column of pure silver weighing 17 pounds.
Under the protection of God and a distinguished pope, he crafted in the diaconate of the blessed Archangel a paten and chalice of pure silver, weighing 10 pounds together.
Inspired by divine guidance, he created a canopy in the Basilica of the Savior, also known as the Constantinian Basilica, supported by four columns of pure silver.
These columns were adorned with various historical depictions, along with screens and columns of remarkable size and beauty, totaling a weight of 1,227 pounds.
He also completely renovated the roof of the Basilica of Saint Mary, Mother of God and ever Virgin, known as the Basilica of the Nativity.
The rooms adjacent to the church of the blessed Peter, chief of the apostles, which had decayed over time and were nearly collapsing, were rebuilt from the ground up into a stronger and better state by this excellent prelate.
Beside the larger column, he constructed a round structure, beautifully decorated and set above.
He newly restored the steps at the entrance of the same basilica, both above the portico and in the atrium.
Additionally, next to those steps, on the right side of the atrium, he built a house from the ground up, decorated with remarkable size and beauty, where he also placed couches.
He constructed a bath next to that house, wonderfully decorated, for the support of Christ's poor and pilgrims.
This distinguished bishop, divinely inspired, built a hospital dedicated to the blessed Peter the apostle in the place called Naumachia, adorning various buildings there.
He constructed a new church in honor of the blessed Peter, chief of the apostles, where he relocated and reinterred the bodies of the martyrs of the Church of Christ, and provided everything necessary for the aforementioned hospital.
He provided urban and rural estates for the support of Christ's poor and for welcoming strangers and pilgrims from distant regions, all for the glory of the holy Church of God and the well-being of the Roman people.
Notably, he completely rebuilt the monastery of Saint Stephen, the first martyr of Christ, known as Catagalla Patricia.
It had fallen into significant disrepair and partially collapsed due to age.
This visionary pontiff laid a strong foundation with an oratory, elevating it to a better state.
He renewed the steps leading from the Apostle Saint Andrew to the church of the blessed Apostle Peter, which had worn out over time.
Similarly, he almost entirely rebuilt the monastery of Saint Martin, confessor and pontiff, which had suffered severe damage from age.
He restored the roofs of the basilica of Saint Andrew the Apostle, called Catabarhara Patricia, which had deteriorated over many years.
In the same manner, he also renewed the roofs of the blessed martyr Lucia, located in Orfea.
Likewise, he improved the roofs of the blessed martyr Balbina, which were nearly collapsing, restoring them to a better state.
Similarly, he marvelously restored the roofs of the basilica of the blessed martyrs Cosmas and Damian, located on the Sacred Way.
He also improved the roofs of the basilica of the blessed martyr Martina, located in Tribus Fatis.
Additionally, he newly restored the roofs of the title of the blessed martyr Lawrence, called Damasi.
This very holy and distinguished pontiff carefully renewed the roofs of the basilica of the blessed martyr Valentine, located on the Flaminian Way, which had nearly collapsed due to age.
He repaired all the roofs of the quadriporticus of the basilica of the Apostles on the Via Lata, both inside and outside.
Furthermore, he repaired the roofs of the basilica of the blessed martyr Agatha, located above the Suburra, which had decayed significantly due to age.
Here, the very holy bishop constructed an oratory from the ground up in the Lateran Palace in honor of the blessed archangel, showcasing remarkable craftsmanship.
He adorned it with mosaics, various paintings, and beautifully colored marbles and metals.
He also donated treasures of all kinds, including gold and silver, as well as various cloths.
He restored the roof of the Lateran Palace, which extended from the field beyond the images of the apostles and was close to collapsing due to its extreme age.
He rebuilt it from the foundation, repaired the entire roof, and restored the upper floor with the finest marbles.
He redesigned the ceiling and beautifully decorated it with various historical paintings.
This venerable and distinguished pope, protected by God, crafted four red silk curtains around the altar of his nurturer, the blessed apostle Peter.
These curtains are adorned with panels or circles of gold embroidery, depicting various histories with gold-embroidered stars.
In the center, there are crosses of gold embroidery, adorned with pearls of amazing size and beauty, displayed on festive days for decoration.
Similarly, he made other white silk curtains with rose patterns for the Easter season, featuring panels and circles of gold embroidery, as well as crosses adorned with pearls and gems.
Additionally, he crafted four small curtains on each column of the canopy, featuring tigers embroidered in gold, with blue cloth around them.
In the same way, he placed four small curtains with the same design on the columns of the canopy in the basilica of the blessed apostle Paul, the teacher of the world.
The aforementioned venerable pope restored the roof of the basilica of the blessed martyr Agapitus in the city of Palestrina, as well as the roof of another nearby basilica, both of which were close to collapsing due to extreme age.
He renewed everything and restored them for the better.
He repaired the roof of the Church of Saint Stephen, the first martyr, located on the Latin road at the third mile marker.
It had been worn down over many years and was close to ruin.
He also restored the roof of the Church of Saint Basilides the Martyr, located in Merulana.
This venerable and distinguished pope, protected by God, created in the Basilica of our Lord Jesus Christ the Savior, known as the Constantinian Basilica, five crowns with dolphins, thirty-five baskets, and eight bowls from his own silver, all together weighing 276 pounds.
He also crafted a curtain of woven fabric, beautifully embroidered, for the Basilica of the Holy Mother of God and ever Virgin Mary, known as at the Manger, hanging in the portico over an ornately adorned seat.
Forty mixed veils, both woven and embroidered with stauraci and decorated with embroidery, were also made.
He crafted a silver light in the manner of a net with five baskets, weighing 37 and a half pounds, positioned before the entrance of the manger.
The same holy bishop, inspired by the Holy Spirit, created a special gold chalice for the blessed apostle Peter, adorned with various precious stones, weighing 32 pounds.
He also made a golden paten, of remarkable size and beauty, weighing 25 pounds and 9 ounces.
In the aforementioned basilica, he crafted a silver light in the manner of a net with a basket, and crosses of pure silver, which hang beneath the main gold.
Additionally, he made a larger silver light in the manner of a net with twenty baskets hanging under a larger beam, weighing 2,104 pounds and 7 ounces, for the decoration of the holy Church of God.
In the basilica dedicated to the teacher of the world, the blessed Apostle Paul, he created a crucifix from the purest silver, remarkably large and weighing fifty-two pounds.
He also crafted four white silk veils with rose patterns, one of which featured a gold-threaded cross in the center and gold-threaded borders.
Additionally, he made nine white silk veils adorned around the edges with Tyrian purple.
He fashioned eight silver bowls, which hang on an iron lighthouse at the center of the basilica, weighing fourteen pounds.
The entrance to the body was elegantly adorned by the same prelate with white marble, where he also installed bronze gates.
On the marble columns that surround the altar of the same teacher of the world, where wooden beams once stood but had withered due to age, this holy bishop placed lilies.
On these lilies, he mounted metal plates made of marble, embellishing them with paintings of remarkable size.
He also created five larger Alexandrian veils, which hang splendidly decorated above the larger gates at the basilica's entrance.
This most holy and renowned pontiff crafted in the basilica of Saint Mary Mother of God, ever Virgin, our Lady, near the Manger, four white silk veils with rose patterns, beautifully decorated.
Within the manger, he made a white silk garment with rose patterns, adorned around the edges with gold thread, featuring a gold-threaded cross with circles in the middle.
He also made four white silk veils with rose patterns, trimmed around the edges with Tyrian purple.
In the diaconia of the Mother of God, called Dominica, he crafted a white silk garment with rose patterns, featuring a panel of Tyrian purple in the middle depicting the story of the crucifix.
He decorated the wheels with gold thread around the fourfold border.
There, he also made a curtain adorned with purple around the edges.
In the church dedicated to the Mother of God, known as Cosmedin, he crafted a white silk garment featuring a gold-embroidered panel that depicts the story of the Lord's resurrection, bordered with intricate gold embroidery.
For Saint Mary of the Martyrs, he created a white silk garment with rose patterns and a panel of Tyrian purple, illustrating the story of the crucifixion, surrounded by gold embroidery accented with Tyrian purple.
He also placed a garment in the church of the aforementioned Mother of God outside the gate of the blessed Apostle Peter, made of Tyrian purple and beautifully adorned.
This venerable and distinguished pontiff crafted, in the basilica of the blessed Apostle Peter, his patron, baskets with openwork designs of the purest silver, both in the portico and in the nave of the basilica, totaling 22 and collectively weighing 125 pounds.
He made silver lamps with Christian symbols, which hang in the portico and in the bronze lighthouse in the middle of the basilica, numbering 48 and collectively weighing 101 and a half pounds.
He crafted three silver lamps standing on silver beams, weighing 93 pounds.
Two silver arches weighing 41 pounds and 8 ounces.
Large blue curtains hanging on silver beams to the right and left of the presbytery, numbering 30, adorned with quadruple trimming.
Small curtains with foundation, numbering 47, adorned with Byzantine blue and covered with Neapolitan blue.
In the nave of the basilica, he crafted a larger Alexandrian curtain of remarkable size and beauty, decorated and adorned with Tyrian purple.
Small white silk curtains with rose patterns, numbering 25, adorned with blue, with one featuring crossed embroidery.
Above the altar of the blessed Andrew, he created a white silk garment with rose patterns and a panel of gold embroidery, depicting the story of the Lord's resurrection, bordered with intricate gold embroidery.
Indeed, he crafted a white silk cloth with a rose hue and a gold thread panel for the altar of blessed Petronilla, depicting the story of the Lord's resurrection, surrounded by a gold thread border.
Similarly, in the oratory of the Holy Mother of God, he created a white silk cloth with rose coloring, featuring a gold thread cross in the center, and adorned it with Tyrian embellishments.
In the same oratory of the Mother of God, known as that of Lord Pope Paul, he made a white silk cloth decorated with mizilo.
Likewise, in the monastery of Saint Martin, he crafted a white silk cloth with a rose tint, a gold thread cross in the center, and Tyrian decorations.
In the basilica of the apostles on the Via Lata, above the main altar, he created a white silk cloth with a rose hue, featuring a stauraci panel in the center that tells the story of the Lord's resurrection, surrounded by a gold thread cloth.
Additionally, there were circles of gold thread with Tyrian decorations.
Small red veils were decorated with foundation, one of which included gold thread.
Two small red Alexandrian veils were adorned with stauraci.
In the nave of the basilica, he crafted a larger curtain with a foundation beautifully adorned, decorated with Tyrian, and featuring crosses of Tyrian in the center.
This distinguished prelate also made a white silk cloth with a rose hue in the title of Saint Sabina the martyr, above the main altar, featuring a stauraci panel in the center with the story of the Lord's resurrection, bordered by gold thread.
Similarly, in the title of Saint Susanna the martyr, above the main altar, he crafted a white silk cloth with a rose hue, featuring a gold thread panel in the center with the story of the Lord's resurrection, bordered by gold thread.
He also made in the basilica of Saint Stephen the first martyr on the Caelian Hill a white silk cloth with a rose hue, featuring a stauraci panel in the center with the story of the Lord's resurrection, and a gold thread cross.
During the diaconate of the blessed martyr George, he crafted a white silk garment adorned with roses for the main altar.
In the middle, it featured an embroidered panel depicting the story of the crucifix, enriched with Tyrian purple and gold-threaded roses.
This venerable and distinguished bishop, protected by God, demonstrated his devotion in the basilica of the holy Mother of God, known as "at the Manger." Out of love for our Lady, he created a lighthouse from the purest silver, complete with a lamp and wax, weighing a total of 40 and a half pounds.
He decreed that on Sundays or holy celebrations, this lighthouse should be placed near the lectern to illuminate the reading of the sacred lessons with its bright glow.
Similarly, in the church of Saint Peter the Apostle, he crafted another lighthouse from the purest gilded silver, of remarkable beauty, also adorned with a lamp and wax, weighing 90 and a half pounds.
At the same location, in Saint Peter the Apostle's church, beneath the image of our Savior Lord Jesus Christ crucified, he fashioned a crown from the purest silver. Out of love for our Lord Jesus Christ, he placed it there to enhance the brilliance of the lights, carefully weighing it in pounds.
The basilica of the blessed Apollinaris, bishop and martyr, near the city of Ravenna, had beams that had decayed significantly over the years due to extreme age.
At that point, they were nearly collapsing, but the same venerable father, divinely inspired, restored it.
He carefully and thoughtfully renewed all the roofs of the church and its porticoes, bringing it to a much better state.
On the altar of the sacred basilica, in honor of Almighty God and blessed Peter the Apostle, he crafted a silk robe with roses in the middle and a cross of gold thread with circles.
Silk wheels depicted the Annunciation, the birth of our Lord Jesus Christ, the passion, resurrection, ascension into heaven, and Pentecost, all similarly adorned around it, just like the robe of gold thread.
He also created a basket of the purest silver with chains weighing 15 pounds.
The bishop's residence in Albano, along with the church founded in the name of blessed Pancras, was burned from the foundations to the top roof due to certain negligence or carelessness, influenced by devilish forces, after the morning praises.
However, the most merciful and diligent bishop, inspired by God, laid a firm foundation and wonderfully restored the church anew.
With God's help, he brought it to a better state with repaired roofs.
As a true lover of God and worshipper of the holy churches of God, he made two vestments over the main altar of the aforementioned church.
One of these featured larger wheels with griffins, ornamented with a pattern, and he crafted four silk veils of fine Tyrian purple around the same altar.
In the church of the blessed Apostle Peter, he created a rose-colored garment illustrating the story of our Lord Jesus Christ, specifically when He reached out His hand to save the blessed Apostle Peter from the sea's waves.
This most blessed and renowned pope also crafted a white silk garment with a decorative border in the basilica of Saint Cyriacus, featuring the story of the resurrection in the center.
Surrounding the altar were four white curtains with a purple border.
In the church of Saint Vitalis, he made a similar white silk garment with a decorative border, depicting the story of the resurrection in the middle.
At the deaconry of Saint Archangel, he placed a white silk garment with a purple border, featuring the story of the ascension in the center.
He also offered a similar garment on the altar of Saint Abbacyrus.
Furthermore, in the deaconry of Saint Agatha, the martyr, this most holy pope crafted a white silk garment with purple accents, illustrating the story of the resurrection in the middle.
In the church of Pammachius, on the altar of Saints John and Paul, he made a white silk garment adorned with a decorative border, depicting the stories of the crucifixion, ascension, and Pentecost.
Similarly, in the church of the blessed martyr and pope Clement, he crafted a white garment with a gold-embroidered border, depicting the stories of the resurrection, the ascension, and Pentecost.
Additionally, in the church of Saint Cyriacus on the Ostian Way, he created five fourfold curtains illustrating the Savior calling the disciples from the boat.
On the holy altar of this martyr, he placed a decorative garment.
This God-protected and renowned pope also crafted silver crowns and twelve dolphins weighing a total of 202 pounds and 9 ounces in the basilica of the Holy Mother of God, ever Virgin Mary, our Lady at the manger.
He also made seven silver bowls with dolphins, weighing 85 and a half pounds.
The same blessed bishop crafted a revolving lamp of pure silver, adorned with crowns and crosses, weighing 35 pounds and 6 ounces, in the basilica of Saint Peter the Apostle, his patron, in front of the presbytery.
Additionally, in the lower part where the sacred body of the prince of the apostles rests, he renewed a golden image featuring the face of our Lord Jesus Christ the Savior, the holy Mother of God, our Lady Mary, and the blessed apostles Peter, Paul, and Andrew, as well as the blessed martyr Petronilla, adding 21 pounds and 3 ounces of refined gold.
Above it, in front of Saint Andrew, he embellished the altar of Saint Martin, a confessor of Christ, with gilded pure silver from the former abbot Fridigisus, weighing 17 and a half pounds.
He also created a lamp with five silver dolphins in the basilica of Saint Paul the Apostle, teacher of the nations, weighing 67 pounds and 4 ounces.
This venerable and illustrious pontiff, inspired by God, noticed that the church of the blessed martyrs Nereus and Achilleus was deteriorating due to age and flooding waters.
He constructed a new church next to it from the ground up in a higher location, featuring remarkable size and beauty.
In this new church, he offered these gifts: six silver baskets collectively weighing 15 pounds.
A ciborium of pure silver weighing 215 pounds.
A chalice and paten of gilded pure silver weighing 12 pounds and 10 ounces.
A gold crown adorned with various precious stones on the altar, weighing 2 pounds and 6 ounces.
Two garments, one made of white silk with scenes of the Lord's nativity, resurrection, ascension, and Pentecost, decorated with gold embroidery, and another of Tyrian purple.
Similarly, he crafted a crown in the basilica of the Blessed Mother of God at the manger, using the purest gold and various precious stones, with a total weight of four pounds and seven ounces.
He also created communion vessels from the purest silver for each region, which were to be carried by acolytes through the stations.
These numbered twenty-four in total.
In the same way, in the basilica of the blessed apostle, his patron, he made a crown from the purest gold adorned with various precious stones, weighing seven pounds.
He also crafted mixed silk veils for the diaconate of Saints Nereus and Achilleus.
He restored the vaulted roof of the blessed martyr Agapitus, located next to the basilica of the blessed martyr Lawrence outside the wall, as it had deteriorated due to its age.
In the church of Saint Praxedes, he created a white silk garment embellished with Tyrian purple.
This most blessed pope gloriously led the Roman and apostolic seat for twenty years, five months, and sixteen days before passing into eternal rest.
During his tenure, he conducted three ordinations in March, ordaining thirty priests, eleven deacons, and one hundred twenty-six bishops in various locations.
He was laid to rest in the basilica of the blessed apostle Peter on the day before the Ides of June, in the ninth indiction, leaving a ten-day vacancy in the episcopate.
The Letters of Saint Leo the Third
The First Letter from Kenulph, King of Mercia, to Pope Leo the Third.
It concerns the abolition of the archbishopric of Lichfield and the restoration of the Church of Canterbury's dignity, which Pope Adrian the First and King Offa had divided.
To the most blessed and truly beloved Leo, pontiff of the holy and apostolic Roman chair, Kenulph, by the grace of God, King of Mercia, along with the bishops, leaders, and all ranks of dignity under our authority, sends the sincerest greetings in Christ.
We always give thanks to Almighty God, who, having acquired the Church with His precious blood, continually guides it through the various storms of this world by appointing new leaders, taking the previous ones to eternal life, to bring it to the harbor of salvation and fill it with new light.
This ensures it is not obscured by any error of darkness but walks the path of truth with sure footing.
Hence, the whole Church throughout the world rightly rejoices because, while the true rewarder of all good things has taken the most glorious shepherd of His flock, Adrian, to be rewarded forever above the heavens, He has nevertheless provided a reward of kind providence to His sheep, knowing how to lead the fold of the Lord to the pastures of life.
We too, who are at the ends of the earth, have reason to boast in the same way, above others, because his greatness is our salvation, his prosperity is our eternal joy.
For from where your apostolic dignity comes, the truth of faith has become known to us.
Therefore, I consider it appropriate to humbly incline the ear of our obedience to your holy commands and to fully carry out those things that seem right to follow according to your piety, but to quickly turn away and completely cut off from us those things found contrary to reason.
But now I, Kenulph, King by the grace of God, humbly ask Your Excellency to let me speak to you about our progress, hoping not to offend your spirit.
May you welcome me into your kind embrace with peaceful tranquility, and may your abundant blessings enrich me to govern your people, as I have no merit of my own.
Together with me, may your apostolic authority, which instilled the rudiments of faith in this nation, through your intercession, empower us against external forces, and may God Himself, who gave us this kingdom, choose to expand it.
All those who ruled Mercia with the scepter before me earned this blessing from your predecessors; I humbly ask for it myself and hope to obtain it from you, O most holy one, so that, first and foremost, you may accept me as your son in adoption, just as I love you as a father and always embrace you with all the strength of obedience.
Indeed, among such great persons, the holy faith should be preserved and undisturbed love maintained, for the happiness of children in God is believed to be rooted in paternal kindness, according to the words of Hezekiah: "The father will make known your truth to the children, Lord."
In these words, I implore you, beloved father, not to deny your unworthy son the knowledge of the Lord's truth through your sacred words, so that, with your sound instruction and God's help, I may deserve to reach the goal of a better life.
Moreover, dearest one, along with all our bishops and any person of dignity among us, I beseech you to kindly respond to us regarding the many inquiries we have deemed worthy of your great wisdom, so that the tradition of the holy Fathers, passed down to us, is not corrupted in any way. May your word come to us in love and gentleness, so that through God's mercy, it may bring forth a beneficial outcome in us.
First, let's discuss what our esteemed bishops have been saying: there is a division of the Archbishop of Canterbury's authority into two parishes, which goes against the canons and apostolic statutes established by the blessed father Gregory.
According to his command, twelve bishops should fall under this jurisdiction, as stated in the letter he sent to our churches.
This letter was directed to his brother and fellow bishop Augustine, concerning the two metropolitan bishops of London and York, which we're sure you also possess.
Originally, the primary pontifical position, meant for London with the honor of the pallium, was instead given to Canterbury.
Since Augustine, blessed in memory, who preached the word of God to the English people under Gregory's order, gloriously led the churches of Saxony, and died in Canterbury, his body was laid in the church of blessed Peter, the chief apostle.
His successor, Saint Laurence, consecrated this church.
It seemed fitting to all our wise people that the metropolitan honor should remain in the city where his body rests, as he planted the faith's truth in this region.
As you know, King Offa attempted to divert this honor due to his conflict with the venerable Lambert and the people of Kent, dividing it into two parishes.
Your pious fellow bishop and predecessor Adrian started something unprecedented at the king's request and elevated the bishop of Mercia with the pallium.
However, we don't place blame on either of them, as we believe Christ triumphs in eternal victory.
However, we humbly ask you, your excellency, to whom God has rightfully granted the key of wisdom, to consult with your wise advisors on this matter.
Whatever you find appropriate, please write back so we may follow your guidance, to prevent any division or schism within the seamless robe of Christ.
We hope it leads us towards true peace through your sound teaching, as we earnestly desire.
With great humility and love, we have written these words to you, most blessed Pope, sincerely praying for your kindness to respond justly and graciously to what we have presented.
Also, please kindly examine with pious love the letter that Archbishop Atherald sent to you concerning his and all of Britain's issues and needs, in the presence of all our provincial bishops.
We ask you to reveal to us the truth about any matters of faith mentioned in it.
Last year, I also sent my delegation, along with the bishops, through Abbot Wadan; however, he handled the mission sluggishly and even foolishly.
But now, beloved father, I send you a small gift of love through Priest Brine and my ministers Fildas and Ceolberth, which is 120 mancuses with a letter, asking you to kindly accept it and grant us your blessing.
May Almighty God keep you safe for a long time to the praise of His holy Church.
This is the second letter from Pope Leo the Third to Kenulf, King of the Mercians.
He responds to the earlier letter, happily granting all the requests.
To my esteemed son, Kenulf, King of the Mercians in the province of Saxony, from Pope Leo.
When our revered brother Atherald, Archbishop of the Church of Canterbury, arrived at the holy shrines of the blessed apostles Peter and Paul, he faithfully fulfilled his vows of prayer and presented the cause of his priesthood to our apostolic seat.
He also delivered your letters of royal excellence to us.
In the two letters you sent, filled with true faith, we found your great humility.
We give thanks to Almighty God, who has adorned and honored your wise excellence in all things concerning the blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, and has shown love for us, agreeing humbly to all apostolic judgments.
Furthermore, in one of those letters, we learned that if you had been nearby, you would have graciously offered your life for the grace of our apostolic function.
Indeed, you greatly rejoice in the Lord for our prosperity, and when our letters of sweet admonition reach your ears, you acknowledge them with all sweetness and spiritual joy of heart, like a son receiving a paternal gift.
You also mentioned that you commanded a small blessing from your resources to be offered to us-one hundred and twenty gold coins-which we accepted with great love for the salvation of your soul.
And we received the aforementioned archbishop and his companions honorably and kindly, gladly assisting him in his needs.
Meanwhile, trusting in your most prudent excellence, as declared in your royal documents, no Christian dares to oppose our apostolic decrees.
Therefore, we strive with all our efforts to issue and proclaim what benefits your kingdom.
Our brother, Archbishop Atheraldus, along with the entire synod of evangelical and apostolic doctrine, the holy Fathers, and the canonical rulings of our predecessors, the holy bishops, should explain to your royal excellence, all the leaders of your people, and the entire people of God, that you should in no way oppose their orthodox doctrine.
As our Lord and Redeemer says in the Gospel: "He who receives you receives me; and he who receives a prophet in the name of a prophet will receive a prophet's reward." Matthew ten.
How much more for this often-praised lord archbishop, whom you have highly commended to us, as he truly is a very distinguished and skilled person. You know him to be wise and adorned with good morals, worthy before God and humans.
Behold, most beloved and noble son, excellent and good king, in these assertions, we praise Almighty God for showing you such a bishop. Like a true shepherd, he is able to declare worthy repentance according to the doctrine of the Holy Scriptures, saving the souls under his priestly authority from the lower hell, leading them from unquenchable fire, bringing them into the harbor of salvation, and offering on their behalf a worthy and unblemished sacrifice in the presence of the divine majesty of Almighty God.
Because the aforementioned archbishop impressed us greatly with his holiness and way of life, we placed a lot of trust in him.
We granted him authority through the power of the blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, whose office we hold unworthily.
If anyone among his subjects, whether kings, princes, or the general population, disobeys the Lord's commands, he has the authority to excommunicate them until they repent.
If they remain unrepentant, they should be treated like a Gentile and a tax collector, as stated in Matthew 18.
Regarding Atherald, now appointed as the archbishop of the Church of Canterbury, we were asked by your bishops to ensure justice concerning his dioceses, both bishops, and monasteries, from which he was unlawfully removed, as you know, and taken away from the venerable seat he held long ago.
We carefully examined everything and found in our holy archive that Saint Gregory, our predecessor, had completely entrusted and confirmed those dioceses with twelve parishes to the blessed Augustine, his archbishop, and granted the authority to consecrate bishops.
Having discovered this truth, we restored the ordinations and confirmations to him in full, as they were in ancient times, by our apostolic authority, and granted him the privilege of confirmation to be observed according to the rules of the sacred canons of his Church.
LETTER THREE. TO CHARLES THE GREAT. On the Privilege of the Chapel in Eresburg.
Leo, servant of the servants of God, to Charles the Great, Emperor of the Romans.
We are overjoyed by your pious request and promptly grant what you have commanded.
Therefore, we declare that the mountain of Eresburg, which you conquered and offered to God along with all of Saxony, and which you consecrated through us to Saint Peter, shall be free from human authority.
We decree that it shall only be governed by the brothers gathered there for the service of Christ.
To ensure they do not face any hindrance, and to prevent rebellion by invaders of your kingdom, we forbid under the anathema and authority of Saint Peter that anyone ever place military garrisons on this mountain.
No one should attempt to seize the lands or tithes you granted around the mountain for two Saxon miles as you designated.
May peace from God the Father be upon those who uphold this.
For those who violate it, may there be excommunication and separation from the community of the blessed forever.
Given at Eresburg by the hands of the librarian and chancellor of the Roman Church on December twenty-sixth, in the year of our Lord.
Leo the Third, four, indiction seven, on the day of the dedication of the chapel in Eresburg.
Chapter Four: To the Same Charlemagne. On the Accusers.
LETTER 5. TO THE SAME PERSON.
Exploring how the Sicilians formed an alliance with the Saracens, leading to the return of captives.
Letter six. To the same person. Regarding the killing of the Moors in Greece.
Letter Seven to the Same: On the Unjust Plan Made
Letter Eight to the Same: Of Thanksgiving
Letter Nine: On Received Favors, To the Same Person
Letter Ten: To the Same Person. Questions to be Resolved.
Letter Eleven to the Same: Intercessions and Others
Letter Twelve to the Same: How a Certain Bishop Was Found in Exile
Letter Thirteen to the Same: How Those Sent to Administer Justice Caused Harm
Letter 14: To Riculph, Bishop of Mainz.
He expresses gratitude for the gifts sent by him and, in return, sends the requested relics of Saint Caesarius.
Leo, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to the most reverend and holy Bishop Riculph.
When at the tombs of the blessed apostles, the venerable Bishop Bernharius, along with the devout Abbot Adalhard, emissaries of our son, the most serene ruler Charles, visited us and shared all the good and healthy news about our aforementioned son, as well as his distinguished offspring and loyal followers, we gave immense thanks to Almighty God.
Meanwhile, Bishop Bernharius presented us with your holiness's beautiful gift and letters.
Upon reading these letters, we thanked your reverend kindness because you remember us in your prayers, which are pleasing to God.
As for the many gifts you generously give us for the love of the blessed apostle Peter, we trust in Almighty God that you will receive a fitting reward here and in the future from the very keeper of the kingdom of heaven.
Regarding the relics of Saint Caesarius, as you requested, we have sent them to your holiness through the same venerable Bishop Bernharius.
Letter 15: The Creed of the Orthodox Faith of Pope Leo.
Leo, bishop and servant of the servants of God, addresses all the Eastern Churches.
We are sending you this creed of the orthodox faith so that both you and the entire world may uphold the faith rightly and unbreakably, as taught by the Roman holy catholic and apostolic Church.
We believe in the holy Trinity: the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, one almighty God, of one substance, one essence, and one power.
The creator of all creatures, from whom all things originate, through whom all things exist, and in whom all things reside:
The Father, who is from himself, not from another;
the Son, begotten of the Father, true God from true God, true light from true light, not two lights, but one light;
the Holy Spirit, proceeding equally from the Father and the Son, consubstantial and coeternal with the Father and the Son.
The Father is fully God in himself, the Son is fully God begotten from the Father, and the Holy Spirit is fully God proceeding from the Father and the Son.
Yet, we do not speak of three Gods, but one almighty, eternal, invisible, unchangeable God, who is wholly present everywhere.
Not divided into parts, but whole in everything, not locally but personally, who created changeable things without changing himself and governs what is created.
Always remaining what he is, to whom nothing can happen, because nothing can be added to or taken away from the simple nature of divinity, who always is, who is always first, who is eternal.
For whom being, living, and understanding are the same.
And these three are one God.
These three are the same God and Lord, a true and eternal trinity in persons, a true and eternal unity in substance, because the substance of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit is one.
Indeed, this holy Trinity is nothing more in the three persons named together than in any one person spoken of alone, since each person is a full substance in itself.
Yet not three substances, but one God, one substance, one essence, one eternity, one greatness, one goodness: the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
The Father shares the same nature as the Son and the Holy Spirit, and they are not different from the Father in nature, as they all share one nature.
However, the Father is one person, the Son is another, and the Holy Spirit is yet another person.
In the Father, there is eternity; in the Son, equality; and in the Holy Spirit, the connection of eternity and equality.
They are united in substance and essence, omnipotence, and divinity.
Just as the Holy Trinity is inseparable in substance, it is also inseparable in works, even though certain works of God are attributed to specific persons.
For instance, the voice from heaven that spoke over Christ at His baptism is attributed to the Father.
The assumption of humanity is attributed solely to the Son, and the appearance of the dove, in which the Holy Spirit descended upon the baptized Son, is properly attributed to the Holy Spirit.
Nonetheless, without any doubt, the entire Holy Trinity was involved in creating that voice and that dove, in the humanity of Christ, whose works are inseparable.
We believe that the same Son of God, the Word, was eternally born from the Father, being consubstantial with the Father in all things, and was born in time from the Holy Spirit and the Virgin Mary, having two births: one eternal from the Father and the other temporal from the mother.
This same Son of God was conceived by the conception of His flesh and was born through the birth of His flesh.
We acknowledge the true God conceived and the true God born, the same true God and true man, one Christ, the only begotten Son of God, perfect in both natures in the singularity of one person, incapable of suffering and capable of suffering, mortal and immortal.
Crucified in our weakness, and the same ever-living in his power, he died a death of his own flesh and was buried.
From the underworld, having defeated and stripped the ruler of all wickedness, he returned and rose again on the third day, and with the triumph of glory, ascended into heaven before his disciples.
Seated at the right hand of the Father, that is, the majesty of divinity, from where he will come to judge the living and the dead.
The wicked will see him judging in the form in which he was crucified, not in the humility in which he was unjustly judged, but in the glory in which he will justly judge the world.
The vision of whose majesty is the eternal happiness of all the saints.
Whoever does not believe according to this true faith, the holy, catholic, and apostolic Church condemns, which was founded by Jesus Christ himself our Lord, to whom be glory forever.
Amen.
LETTER 16. TO ATHELARD, ARCHBISHOP OF CANTERBURY.
He sends the pallium and acknowledges him as the Primate of all England.
Leo, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to Athelard, archbishop of the Church of Canterbury forever.
It is fitting for wise Church leaders, according to their unwavering faith, to heed the requests of bishops and grant their desires through blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, and us, as long as these do not contradict canonical laws.
By fulfilling their desires, they become more fervent in their love for religion.
Therefore, we've found it fitting and necessary to encourage and pray for your brotherly kindness regarding the dioceses of England entrusted to you, including the bishops, monasteries of both monks and clerics, and women.
Just as your Church has held them from ancient times, as we discovered in our sacred archive, we confirm that they must be held by you and your successors.
All the Churches of the English people were ordained and confirmed in the Catholic faith by the holy Pope Gregory for the blessed Augustine, the archbishop, his assistant, to be subject to him forever through the sacred use of the pallium.
Therefore, we write to you by the authority of blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, to whom the Lord God gave power, saying:
"You are Peter, and on this rock, I will build my Church, and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it."
"I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven; and whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven; and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven" (Matthew 16).
Indeed, according to the established judgment of the holy canons, although unworthy, we represent the same blessed Peter, the key-bearer of the kingdom of heaven, and we grant to you, Athelard, and your successors, all the Churches of the English people, as they have been from ancient times, to be held perpetually at your metropolitan seat, through the acknowledgment of subjection, by an unbreakable right.
If anyone, though we hope it doesn't happen, challenges the authority of this definition or apostolic privilege, we decree by apostolic authority that, if it is an archbishop or bishop, they should be removed from their office.
Similarly, if it is a priest, deacon, or any other minister of sacred ministry, they should be deposed from their position.
If it is a layperson, whether a king or prince, or any significant or minor individual, they should know they are excluded from participating in holy communion.
We grant this privilege, by the authority of blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, whose ministry we serve, to you, Athelard, and your successors forever.
To confirm this, we have signed it with our hands and ordered it to be signed in our name.
We also instructed our scribe, Sergius, to write it in the month of January.
Given on January 18 by the hand of Eustace, the chief of the holy apostolic see, under the rule of Lord Charles, the most pious, consul Augustus, crowned by God, the great and peaceful emperor, in the second year after his consulship, in the tenth indiction.
Letter Seventeen. Fragment.
It appears to go against the judgments of the holy Fathers if a secular person or layperson attempts to remove priests from the churches where they were appointed at the time of their ordination.
LETTER 18. FROM ALL THE BISHOPS AND PRIESTS OF ALL BRITAIN TO LEO.
Concerning the succession of the archbishops of Canterbury.
All the bishops and priests across the island of Britain send greetings in Christ to the venerable Pope Leo.
We wish to inform you, as noted in the histories of the English by the historian Bede, our esteemed teacher, that our predecessors did not face the significant burden of traveling all the way to Rome for the pallium, as became customary later.
Bede wrote that Blessed Pope Gregory sent Augustine as a preacher to the English people, not as an ordained bishop but as a monk, along with others of the same religious order.
After converting the people, Augustine was ordained as archbishop by Aetherius, the archbishop of Arles, following the instructions from the holy father Gregory.
Later, Augustine, still alive, appointed Laurence as his successor, following the example of Blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, who is said to have consecrated Clement as his assistant and successor.
After Laurence, Mellitus took over the seat of the Canterbury Church.
And after Mellitus, Justus; both received letters from Boniface, the pontiff of the Roman and apostolic see, granting them the authority to ordain bishops.
This authority is expressed as follows.
To the beloved brother Justus, Boniface.
We have sent the pallium to your brotherhood through the bearer of these presents, invited by your acts of kindness, also granting you the ordination of bishops as the opportunity arises, with the Lord's mercy leading the way, so that the gospel of Christ may be spread through the preaching of many among all peoples who are not yet converted, and so forth.
For Justus was previously ordained a bishop by Augustine, as was Mellitus.
Justus also ordained Paulinus as a bishop, and Pope Honorius sent the pallium to Paulinus upon learning that the people of Northumbria, along with their king, had converted to the faith of Christ through Paulinus's evangelization.
After the passing of Justus, Paulinus appointed Honorius as the Archbishop of Canterbury.
Pope Honorius also sent him a pallium along with a letter, which read:
To my beloved brother Honorius, greetings from Honorius.
In response to your request and that of our sons, the kings, we grant you, through this decree, the authority on behalf of the blessed Peter, the chief of the apostles.
This means that when one of you is called to the grace of God, the survivor may appoint a bishop in the place of the deceased.
For this reason, we have sent each of you a pallium to use in the ordination ceremony, allowing you to conduct an ordination pleasing to God with the authority of our decree.
Despite the great distances of land and sea between us, we have made this concession to ensure no harm comes to your churches under any pretext, and to fully promote the devotion of the people entrusted to you.
May God keep you safe, my beloved brother.
Additionally, Albinus or Alcuin, a renowned scribe, wrote to Offa, King of the English, stating that an archbishop should always be ordained by another archbishop and that the pallium should be sent by the Holy Father.
However, the disputes among the kings disrupted this ordination, preventing what should have been done, even though the holy canons had firmly decreed that church statutes should never be violated due to royal disputes.
At that time, holy and apostolic men fulfilled the praiseworthy command of our Savior, who said: "Freely you have received, freely give" Matthew 10:8.
Consequently, the heresy of simony weakened, as the gift of God was not bought with money but given freely, as He had commanded.
However, those who sell the grace of God should fear what the Apostle Peter said to Simon: "Your money perish with you; you have no part or share in this matter" Acts 8.
Admonition
In the Following Summary of the Letter of Pope Leo the Third
This is from a letter of Leo to Alcuin, discussing the practice of triple immersion in baptism.
And here's a letter from Charlemagne to Offa, the King of Mercia.
Charlemagne, by the grace of God, King of the Franks and Lombards and Patrician of the Romans, sends greetings of present prosperity and eternal happiness in Christ to the esteemed and most beloved brother Offa, King of the Mercians.
Among those of royal dignity and other high-ranking individuals, maintaining bonds of friendship and harmony of holy charity in the unity of peace from the depths of the heart is often beneficial.
And if we are commanded by the Lord's precept to dissolve the knots of enmity, how much more should we strive to strengthen the ties of charity?
Therefore, dearest brother, remembering our ancient agreement, we have taken care to send these letters to your reverence so that the alliance rooted in faith may flourish in the fruit of charity.
And having read your brotherly letters, which were indeed delivered to us at various times by the hands of your envoys, we endeavor to respond suitably to the suggestions of your authority.
First, we give thanks to Almighty God for the sincerity of the Catholic faith, which we have laudably found inscribed in your pages, recognizing you not only as strong protectors of your earthly country but also as devoted defenders of the holy faith.
Regarding pilgrims who, for the love of God and the salvation of their souls, wish to visit the sacred thresholds of the blessed apostles, as we previously granted, let them travel in peace without any disturbance, carrying with them what they need.
However, we have found that some fraudulently intermingle for the purpose of trading, seeking profit, not serving religion.
If such are found among them, let them pay the tolls set in the appropriate places; the rest may go in peace.
Regarding merchants, you wrote to us, whom we wish, by our mandate, to have protection and sponsorship in our kingdom legally, according to the ancient custom of trading.
If anyone is unjustly oppressed, they should appeal to us or our judges, and we will ensure that full justice is served.
Similarly, if any of our people face injustice under your authority, they should appeal to your fair judgment, so that no disturbances arise among us.
Regarding Odhberht the priest, who is returning from Rome and intends to travel for the love of God, he is not coming to accuse you.
Know that we sent him with other exiles.
They fled under our protection out of fear of death, heading to Rome, so their case might be heard and judged under the presence of the Lord Apostolic and your archbishop N.
, to whom they are bound by vow, as your letters indicated.
Where mercy has not been effective, fairness will be sought.
What could be safer for us than having the judgment of apostolic authority resolve a matter where opinions differ?
I have sent you the black stones you requested.
Please send a messenger to see which kind your spirit desires, and wherever they are found, we will gladly arrange for them to be provided and assisted in transport.
Just as you specified the length of the stones, our people request the length of the garments, so you may have them made as they used to be in ancient times.
Also know that we have sent some blessings from our dalmatics or cloaks to each episcopal seat in your kingdom, or Aethelred's, as alms for Lord Adrian, our apostolic father and your beloved.
We ask you to diligently intercede for his soul, not doubting that his blessed soul is at rest, but to show faith and love for a dear friend to us.
As the blessed Augustine commands, intercessions of ecclesiastical piety should be made for all, asserting that interceding for a good person benefits the one who does it.
From the wealth of human affairs, which the Lord Jesus has generously granted us, we have sent gifts through the metropolitan cities.
These include one belt, one Hun sword, and two silk robes to ensure that everywhere among Christians, divine mercy is proclaimed, and the name of our Lord Jesus Christ is glorified forever.
We ask you to continuously pray for us, our faithful ones, and indeed all Christians, so that the gentle kingdom of the heavenly King may protect, exalt, and expand the realm of the holy Church.
May Almighty God preserve your esteemed dignity in lasting prosperity for the protection of His holy Church, most beloved brother.
Often, a wolf following a lamb is held back by a voice.
Often, a fleeing sheep looks back at the eager wolf.
Many times, dogs and hares have rested together under one shade, and the blue stood close by on the rock.
Without dispute, the talkative crow sat with the bird of Pallas, and the dove was joined with the hawk.
I laughed at the deceived one who pretended to love; the fowler had fallen into his own traps.
Love enters minds, and practice is learned by doing.
He who can pretend to be healthy will be healthy.
Letter of Nicephorus of Constantinople to Leo the Supreme Pontiff, translated by Theodor Peltan, theologian of the Society of Jesus
Due to the devil's schemes, frequent setbacks in life, the harsh criticism from malicious individuals, the weight of responsibilities, and many other similar challenges, it is taught that fulfilling the role of a bishop with dignity and for public benefit is difficult.
Therefore, since he can barely manage his own life correctly, he adds that he should not have been chosen for this role.
He describes the life he led before becoming a bishop and how he eventually came to the patriarchate of Constantinople.
He seeks the help of the Roman pope and his intercession with God.
He praises the faith of the Romans, which was also praised by the Apostle, and he joins in that praise.
Nonetheless, he adds that the grace of faith belongs not only to Old Rome but also to New Rome and indeed to all peoples and nations, because the apostolic word has spread throughout the entire world.
He includes his and his Church's confession, where he thoroughly and elegantly declares himself free from all errors and heresies that have ever arisen, either in Constantinople or elsewhere, against Christ and his Church.
Thus, in all things and through all things, he embraces the faith of the Roman Church, which is the mother of the rest, every council celebrated by its authority, and finally everything that pertains to the unity of faith.
Therefore, this letter was rightly placed among others that pertain to the union of Churches.
Finally, he apologizes for writing to the Roman pope and explaining the reasons for his faith later than was proper.
It becomes clear that Leo, to whom this letter is addressed, was the second or third pope of that name, as he mentions the Second Council of Nicaea, known to have been celebrated during the pontificate of Adrian the First, was held in his time.
Leo the Third succeeded Adrian.
To the most holy and blessed brother and fellow servant, Lord Leo, Pope of Old Rome, from Nicephorus, by the grace of God Bishop of Constantinople, greetings.
He is truly great, admirable, and worthy of all praise, whoever that faithful servant may be, as described in the parables of those sacred and gospel proclamations.
Appointed by the Lord in His house, he manages the entrusted responsibilities with judgment, not spending wastefully and lavishly, but using them appropriately for what is entrusted.
He gladly gives the food allowance to his fellow servants, distributing and providing each their due portion.
For these actions, he earns the full favor and goodwill of the master and receives a reward from him, managing all that he is appointed to oversee, and acquiring the promise of being placed in charge.
Being very skilled and excellent, he combines and presents both faith and the utmost wisdom.
He shows loyalty and gratitude towards his master, not neglecting any of what is entrusted to him.
With proper reasoning, clear-mindedness, attention, and integrity, he navigates freely among those entitled to the expenditures, having already been deemed worthy of such stewardship by the master.
He will hear, "Well done, good and faithful servant; you have been faithful over a little, I will set you over much," and he will be rightly commanded to enter into the joy of his Lord.
Such are the rewards and deeds of that servant.
I'm not among those who can manage and direct these things; instead, I'm someone who needs guidance and leadership.
Since I'm quite small, the least of all, and completely lacking in good fortune and prosperity, I don't feel ready to be entrusted even with the Church, which is, in an apostolic sense, the house of God.
Due to my weak and sluggish nature and my inadequate memory of divine matters, it's more accurate to say that, having not organized my own affairs or risen above lowly and humble things, I've never chosen to take on the responsibility and care of souls.
Those who don't participate in their own betterment will hardly manage the affairs of others well.
At the same time, I judge and consider myself unworthy of that gift and grace, not deserving of that blessedness, nor of being wretched and tormented justly, nor of the opposite fate, nor of the mindset of the wicked and evil servant, who, through laziness and lack of self-control, neglects the master's guidance, becomes burdensome and intolerable to fellow servants, and associates with drunkards.
The master, arriving unexpectedly, will cut him in two and assign him a place with the hypocrites.
This is not to mention the one who received the talent and buried it underground, hiding it.
Therefore, he will be bitterly accused, not only failing to gain interest and profit but also losing even the principal and being cast into outer darkness.
May I not be caught in these things, set as an example to many, and regarded with a shake of the head by those who observe.
Once accused and condemned by the one who knows and examines all our affairs, and subjected to the scourge of unholy actions, will I sufficiently pay the penalty, so that those guilty of similar things, discovered through my suffering, may be corrected and embrace improvement.
Since, by God's permission and allowance, I was brought under His yoke, I accepted this service and ministry-not willingly, as I was compelled by circumstances.
Considering what has happened before and the state I have reached, as almost everyone here knows, I come to speak.
Everyone chooses a different pursuit or craft, some more significant, some less, driven by their own will and carrying the choice of their actions within themselves.
Just as human opinions are diverse and their deliberations varied, so are their customs different and their ways manifold.
Thus, life choices are divided and scattered in many ways, leading to infinite diversity and abundance.
Some choose to leave behind the wretched and misguided life of the artisans; others seem devoted to the laborious task of agriculture.
Some pursue the profit and wealth of commerce, or the love of travel and the danger of seafaring, while others engage in various manual crafts.
Not to mention each individually, they proceed, while a few distinguished ones embrace the ascetic and philosophical life, purifying both soul and body, and are thus deemed worthy to approach God and hurry towards the heavenly and blessed end.
Or, adorned with logical sciences and arts and esteemed for their virtuous manners, they cultivate their souls, following what seems pleasant and dear to them, as nature inclines.
For me, this is how life has unfolded.
When I came of age, leaving behind my youth, already attending the royal courts, I obtained a military command-not idle and relaxed, but one that required work with both hands and pen.
I happened to be one of the royal secretaries, which the Latin language calls a secretis.
For a while, caught up in worldly matters and tied down by human affairs, I realized the fleeting nature of life.
I pondered deeply, thinking that while it's difficult and nearly impossible for those pursuing higher goals to achieve them, anyone with a better hope will not miss it.
I considered some things trivial and others serious, advising joy in the former and avoiding the latter as much as possible.
I examined myself to see if I might be better regarded in these matters, aiming to appear improved in the future.
Educated by the best of prophets, I learned to be my own guide, recognizing that everything here is vanity of vanities, and as another wise person said, what does a person gain from all their labor under the sun?
Another wise person suggested letting the form of this world pass away, as the chosen vessel proclaimed.
Listening to similar teachings from other sacred scriptures, I remembered what some renowned wise people said: it's better to be a private individual than to have great authority and achieve nothing worthwhile.
I adorned the present life like a stage play that would soon fade away.
Now, I turn to examine myself.
Having been helped by God, I have become indifferent to this rank, moving away from the royal court and urban noise, settling far away.
I occupy a remote and rugged place, just a few miles from the Propontic area, separated from the imperial city.
I made efforts to spend time here, hoping to embrace a solitary life, something I had long desired.
I had a strong desire for solitude and quiet, longing for life's end to find me here and nowhere else.
However, since it's impossible for everything to turn out as everyone wishes, there are times when necessity prevails, and as God wills, He determines the outcome of our efforts.
This has happened to me as well.
I've failed in things that aligned with my desires, and I don't know by what judgments God, who allowed and overlooked these things, understands them.
I was pulled from my beloved solitude and brought to the royal court, as witnessed by God, by the decision and judgment of those who were then seated on the royal thrones, the holy system of the Church, and the Senate council, insisting without exception and without leniency.
Since the head of the capital had already passed away, as any human would, despite having elevated someone lacking in many respects, and audaciously to this sacred throne, an act more of tyranny than persuasion.
Therefore, even though I did not wish for this burden, I have undertaken these responsibilities unworthily, not as was fitting to grace.
I fear first the varied and intricate schemes of the sophist of evil and the uprising of wicked and invisible spirits, lest they find me unarmed and unguarded from the achievements of virtue.
For they have not yet recognized me as trained in spiritual and divine matters, nor have they seen me exercising or competing in wrestling, so those pierced by the arrows of sin might tear apart the God-chosen congregation of the Church and destroy its orderly representation, laughing at the downfall of one who leads unwillingly and ignorantly.
Then, seeing the unexpected and envied nature of leadership from those who envy, I am aware of the deceitful and malicious who eagerly seek to observe our affairs both favorably and otherwise.
They do not see the beams in their own eyes, nor choose to clear the splinter from their eyes, but busy themselves with others' specks.
For the sake of trivial and worthless matters, they unholily arm their tongues against those who are prominent, striking bitterly and unjustly from both sides.
Having embarked on this struggle, to whom else can I turn for help and support, if not to God who permits these challenges?
I seek guidance and assistance from Him, hoping He looks upon my humility with compassion and favor, holding my right hand, and guiding me according to His will and the leadership of those devoted to salvation.
He may delay during these tough and troubling times, either due to our wrongdoings to encourage our improvement or to reveal the wicked and stubborn aspects within us.
This ensures that any hidden bitterness does not remain secretly in the soul but instead surfaces and is exposed.
If a brother supports another, like a fortified city and a well-defended kingdom, as Solomon said, then I request even more prayers for help, especially from all of you, my dearly beloved and holy brotherhood.
Your sacred prayers and mediation to God provide the greatest benefit and support, as those who draw near to God and are elevated to the heavenly and spiritual altar, engaging purely in conversation, listening, in silence, and in calling out.
Just as those around Moses and Samuel were heard, and others like them in spirit.
Therefore, help me in my weakness, and raise holy hands on high.
We believe that by embracing openness and seeking mercy from above, we can make God favorable to us.
This will empower and strengthen what is weak and lacking.
By putting on the armor of faith and wearing the helmet of salvation, we stand bravely against rulers and authorities, against the powers of this dark world, and against spiritual forces of evil, which is the battle we are engaged in.
Our goal is to keep our souls firm and unshakable, even when faced with those who try to persuade and oppose us, and to handle matters skillfully and wisely.
As children of the Church, we welcome these individuals, preparing them as sheep of Christ's chosen flock, and making them dwell in the divine fold of the Church, safe from merciless wolves.
We seal them as symbols of harmony and unity, making them unassailable and invincible, so that they may submit to Christ, the head and chief shepherd of us all, and offer their necks obediently to Him.
To be cleansed and made bright, becoming children of perfect light, so we can share brightness and purification with others.
To be given the right words when we speak, filling our listeners with the spirit and preaching tirelessly and vigorously the power of the mysteries among us.
By the grace of the one who can make the tongue of the mute clear and strengthen the feet of the lame, enabling them to run well in preparation for the Gospel.
To multiply the talent we've been given and return it with interest to the master at the right time.
To work in the good vineyard and carry out acceptable tasks, enduring bravely the heavy and burdensome toil, and nobly bearing the heat of the day.
And to be counted worthy among those who enter at the eleventh hour in the distribution of rewards.
To be enlightened in our understanding and to gaze intently through the lens of the spirit, becoming listeners of prophetic voices, eager servants of divine commands, and to receive this gift.
To cleanse and wash away what clouds the eye of the soul and casts a shadow over our intellect, to guard ourselves on all sides, and remain unassailable against the attacks of adversaries.
To foresee the sword, when it comes divinely upon those who sin, so that if God permits, when announcing the coming of divine retribution, both the preacher and the listeners might escape from wrath.
But if not, at least to save my own soul, like Lot, the righteous one, who managed to save his soul from destruction.
And let these be your prayer and spiritual alliance here.
Now is the time to observe the great trumpet of truth, the loudest herald of the Gospel, Paul, who is greatly revered among the faithful Romans of old.
It's as if he were leaping in spirit, eager and fervent in their faith, taking pride, witnessing, echoing, and proclaiming to the ends of the world.
He proudly states: through him, he writes to them, "I thank my God, because your faith is proclaimed throughout the whole world."
Since the faith of our Gospel is pure and unadulterated, and there is no other beyond it, it is neither restricted by Roman boundaries nor defined by worldly limits. Instead, it is spread and poured out, urged by prophetic and apostolic voices to declare, "Their voice has gone out to all the earth, and their words to the ends of the world."
And if it is necessary to speak even higher than these, this faith is also freely expressed in heaven to the highest and spiritual powers. For if there is one Church in heaven and on earth, and we hear of the Church of the firstborn justified in heaven, and the city of those justified by faith, the upper Jerusalem, whose architect and builder is God, who has reconciled the heavenly with the earthly and broken down the dividing wall of hostility, and carried the lost on his shoulders through ineffable condescension, mixing with those who are saved and remain.
In this, we rightly have unity and indivisibility when creation agrees with faith in understanding and harmony. For God is not known in Judea alone. Those who have inherited the new name of Romans, built upon one and the same foundation of faith, we indeed speak of the all-wise creations of apostles and prophets, with the cornerstone laid by our Savior Christ and God, we bring nothing inferior in faith to the elders.
In the Church of God, there is no distinction between us; just as there is no Jew, no Greek, no barbarian, no slave, or free person, we are all one in Christ.
Therefore, let the divine Paul take pride and be honored for connecting the old with the new and comparing doctrines and teachings.
We follow his teachings and advice, deeply rooted and strengthened by the confession of our faith, in which we stand and rejoice.
We openly declare our beliefs, which are inherent to our glorious and blameless religion, with unveiled faces as we worship God.
We continually embrace the divine light that shines according to the traditions of the enlightened, preserving its existence in real things, not just in names, recognized by one divinity, and glorified by all creation, both visible and invisible.
Of those considered within the Trinity, the Father is without beginning and exists without cause, for He is not from anything, having existence in Himself.
The Son is not without beginning, for He is from the Father, with the Father as the cause.
However, if you consider the beginning from time, then He is also without beginning, for He is the creator of time, not bound by it.
He shines forth from the Father as the radiance of glory and the exact representation of the Father's nature.
The Holy Spirit derives its existence from the Father, not by generation but by procession, eternally considered with the Father and the Son.
It is not without beginning because of its procession from the Father, for the Father is also its beginning according to the cause, but it is without beginning in terms of time.
Therefore, there is one God, the Father, from whom are all things, one Lord Jesus Christ, through whom are all things, and one Holy Spirit in whom are all things.
Among the three perfect entities, one stands out as supremely perfect and preeminent, which is the divine nature.
They are distinct from each other by unique and personal characteristics.
Each of these, naturally inseparable due to the unity of essence, is recognized by us as God when considered individually, and is believed to possess the fullness of all divine attributes.
Together, these three are worshipped by us as one God: threefold in person, unique in essence, and honored as a monarchy, not a polyarchy, avoiding the disorder and division found in Greek confusion.
It is a monarchy, not defined by a single person, avoiding the incompleteness and immaturity of Jewish interpretations, but rather one shown by the equality of nature, harmony of will, and unity of motion, and the unity originating from it, which is impossible in created nature.
As the great theologian Gregory states, nothing connected and inherent in the Trinity is divided.
Let the heresy and madness of the destructive Arius be cut off from us, for the Trinity is indivisible, not divided or alienated in glory and eternity, nor do the divine persons change into or mix with each other, maintaining unchanged eternity in each of them.
Let the deceptive confusion of the vain Sabellius be driven away and expelled.
I honor and worship the mystery established before all ages, revealed in the last times for the salvation of all humanity, and completed through the great condescension and ineffable plan of the one holy and life-giving Trinity, Christ, our true God, so that from whom we have our being through his unspeakable goodness, we may also be granted our well-being.
I confess and believe in Jesus, the one Son and Word of God, who is eternally worshiped and glorified with the Father and the Holy Spirit.
He is of the same essence and shares the divine throne, driven by infinite love for humanity.
With the Father's approval and compassion, and through the grace and cooperation of the Holy Spirit, He came down from heaven to live among us.
His purpose was to save us, who were long ago condemned by sin and expelled from paradise, and to make us partakers of the divine nature.
He dwelled in the womb of the Virgin Mary, truly and rightfully called Theotokos, her soul and body purified by the Spirit.
He took our human nature from her, as He originally created humanity, and He became incarnate, while remaining God.
He preserved the Virgin even after childbirth, maintaining her purity, showcasing the true nature of His unchanged and immutable birth.
Being one with the Father, He became like us in every way, except for sin, and took on the seed of Abraham, sharing our blood and flesh.
He assumed a body animated by a rational and intellectual soul, united with it in an inseparable union, believed to be one rational, living flesh.
He did not dwell in us by grace alone but was fully united with human nature.
This union was accomplished without confusion, division, or alteration, so that the divine and human natures remained distinct in their essence and did not transform into each other.
Though we might piously consider the union of the natures through the connection of names, we honor that they are distinguished by thought only and not in reality, due to the extraordinary union of the things that have come together.
We believe that the unique and unified nature of existence remains intact and unbroken.
Let the false ideas of Eutyches and Dioscorus be cast down.
We acknowledge the same being as both created and uncreated, eternal and beyond time, heavenly and earthly, visible and invisible, capable of suffering and beyond suffering, without mother and without father.
This is due to the ineffable, beginningless, and eternal birth from the Father, and also due to the secret and mysterious union with us.
We proclaim His two births, which are incomprehensible and beyond explanation.
For the only begotten Son, who exists in the form of God and resides in the bosom of the Father-that is, who is eternally of the Father's essence-emptied Himself at the end of the ages and took on the form of a servant, which is our own essence.
Thus, the union in Christ according to the essence brings together the different elements from which the Savior is made, such as the invisible and the visible, the suffering and the incorruptible, without making them different from each other.
We confess the same perfect and true God and perfect human as one.
Recognizing the distinct natures, we know Him as one and the same, even after the incarnation, not dividing into two sons because of the union in essence of the differing natures.
This is so that the irrational Nestorius may be cast out of the divine court, having accomplished all His divine-human activity.
As God, He performed divine acts, working miracles and signs; as a human, He willingly accepted suffering and insults.
Therefore, with the two natures, I glorify His equal number of natural activities, as they reveal and constitute the essence, that is, the natures, according to the pious and fitting traditions of our God-wise fathers.
Similarly, I also advocate for two natural wills, or desires, of the one Lord and our God Jesus Christ.
I recognize him as having a will according to one of the natures from which and in which he exists and is understood.
Just as he acts, so also he wills; he willingly went to the saving passion.
I believe he was crucified not in the essence in which he shines with the Father, although it is said that the Lord of glory was crucified, according to the word of exchange.
But in our human nature, in which he took upon himself our earthly form, and became a curse for us, so that he might make us partakers of the blessing found in him.
He endured the death meant for wrongdoers in the flesh, so that he might condemn sin in his flesh and destroy the one who holds the power of death, that is, the devil.
Though his body was given to burial, it was preserved incorrupt and never separated from the divine and indescribable union.
Even though his logical and intellectual soul was separated during the three-day period, with which he descended into Hades, and to the spirits in prison, as the chief and divine Peter said, he went and proclaimed the resurrection.
He granted freedom and redemption, becoming the firstfruits of incorruption for us, in which he was the firstborn from the dead to rise.
For he rose as God, having trampled down death, paving the way for the resurrection of all flesh, and he raised us up, who had fallen through the sin of transgression.
Appearing to the women after the resurrection, announcing joy to them, and removing the sorrow that came upon us from the female, and appearing also to his divine disciples, confirming the mystery of his resurrection.
Showing who he was even before the resurrection through both eating and the touching by the wise Thomas on the divine side, he ascended into the heavens and sat at the right hand of God the Father with the assumed humanity, with which he will come again in divine glory and authority over all creation.
He will sit as judge, giving to each according to their deeds; for we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ.
After this, I believe in the resurrection of the body, when the world will be transformed so that our mortal bodies can become immortal, and the perishable can be clothed with imperishability.
I also acknowledge one baptism for the forgiveness of sins, conducted in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, according to evangelical and divine tradition.
These are the revered doctrines and mysteries of our orthodox and sacred worship, in line with the high and pure theology passed down by divine initiators, and the saving plan of the Word of God for us, along with all similar teachings, which I fully embrace and uphold with faith.
I also accept and seek their intercessions and prayers to God: first and foremost, and especially, from our all-holy, immaculate, and ever-virgin Lady, the Mother of God; then from the divine and heavenly powers, the holy and renowned apostles, the blessed prophets, the glorious and victorious martyrs, the God-bearing Fathers, and all the saints who have pleased the Lord throughout the ages.
They live forever in Him, for the souls of the righteous are in the hand of the Lord, and I gain the greatest salvation of soul and body from this.
I venerate and embrace their venerable relics as a source of healing for soul and body ailments.
Therefore, I honor their noble and divine way of life and their renowned struggles and contests.
I glorify their tombs and crown them with the highest honors because they shed their blood for the glory of our Savior God, and they disregarded temporary life out of love for Him, becoming imitators of His life-giving and saving passion.
I also revere the venerable icon of our Savior Christ, the all-holy Mother of God, and their revered and holy images, offering them veneration of honor.
I gladly accept and honor the seven holy and ecumenical councils, along with the divine, extraordinary, and saving doctrines established and proclaimed in them by our holy and God-bearing Fathers, appointed by the Holy Spirit to shepherd and govern His Church.
First, the council gathered in Nicaea by our renowned Fathers, stood against the impious and frenzied Arius.
It expelled him from the Church and presented us with a true and straightforward faith through its sacred and divine creed.
This council rightly taught that the Word of God, the Son of God, is not a creature, but is of the same essence as the Father and co-eternal, as a true God and creator of all.
Next, the council convened in this imperial city with 381 God-inspired Fathers.
It deposed the impious Macedonius, who fought against the Spirit, and clarified the meaning of the sacred creed.
They affirmed with the words of the Holy Spirit that He is a true God, of the same essence as the Father and the Son, and not a creature.
It also condemned Apollinaris of Laodicea, truly foolish and senseless, from the Church.
Following that, the holy council assembled earlier in Ephesus with 200 sacred teachers, to confront the vain-minded Nestorius and his blasphemies.
They deposed him and wisely established one hypostasis of our Christ and God in union, with two natures, without confusion and without division.
Affirming Him as both God and man, they confessed the holy Mary as truly and properly the Mother of God.
Finally, the council of 630 God-inspired and God-bearing Fathers gathered in Chalcedon.
This council condemned the impious Eutyches and Dioscorus and their dark and confused doctrines, anathematizing them.
They piously proclaimed our Christ and God as perfect God and perfect man, in two natures and one hypostasis, without confusion and without division.
Furthermore, I embrace the sacred Fifth Council of our 165 holy Fathers, convened in the God-protected city.
This council condemned the impious teachings of Theodore and Nestorius, as well as Origen, Didymus, and Evagrius, and their followers.
These teachings had been hidden among many but eventually emerged and spread.
They followed Jewish and Greek myths instead of Christian doctrine.
Next, the Sixth Ecumenical Council of 180 holy men gathered in the royal city.
It proclaimed the distinct natures of Christ, along with their natural activities and wills, and anathematized Theodore, Bishop of Pharan, Honorius, Cyrus, Sergius, Pyrrhus, Paul, and Peter, who were introduced into the priesthood with God's permission.
Also, Macarius, named the leader of Antioch, and his disciple Stephanus, as well as Polychronius, the foolish old man, who glorified one will and one activity in our Savior and God, Christ.
Moreover, the Seventh Holy Council of 318 Fathers gathered in Nicaea in our times.
It confirmed all the preceding holy councils and accepted the veneration of sacred and holy icons, as handed down from the beginning to the Church, decreeing they should be honored similarly to the life-giving cross.
We have cast out from the Church those who, in arrogance and destruction, spoke empty words about these icons and accused Christians of worshipping them as gods; namely, Theodosius, Basil, and Sisinnius, who began to rule the priestly thrones with the neglect of God's sight.
I accept these holy ecumenical councils and embrace the doctrines and writings of all the chosen and blessed Fathers as impeccable teaching and the foundation of salvation.
I accept those whom the Catholic Church receives and reject those whom it turns away.
I completely reject and turn away from the followers of Simon the Magician, who have strayed from piety to this day.
They are caught up in evil doctrines and destructive beliefs, having rejected the teachings of the saints.
They have dared to mix the bitter seed of weeds with the field of Orthodoxy.
I renounce them and all who follow them, condemning them as a plague upon the Church of Christ and subjecting them to anathema.
We share these thoughts with you, most blessed and God-taught ones, adhering to the established church rules as a living proclamation.
We also use our letter to convey the promises of love in Christ, as well as harmony and unity among one another.
May your cherished brotherhood in the Lord respond to us, first with prayers to the Lord, and then with words and actions that strengthen and instruct,
so that we may stand firm in your laws and teachings with unwavering and complete faith.
Let us keep all the mysteries within it, as handed down from above, undisturbed,
and within the boundaries of the church's courtyard, surrounded by divine harmony, echoing with the clear sound of apostolic and spiritual teaching.
Gathering all the rational creatures of the sacred flock with God-inspired sounds, and preserving them safe from the plotting beasts,
marked with the anointing and name of Christ the chief shepherd.
Fulfill what is lacking in us through yourselves, as loving brothers and kind-hearted ones,
so that your abundance may meet our need.
May what is lacking in words and deeds be built up and increased by your holy and dignified life, not being petty about the gift given to you.
For it does not diminish those who give generously, but timely returns the fruits abundantly to those who choose them.
They watch over us as weaker beings with their God-given power, guiding our steps onto the path of the Gospel and advising us on things that are beneficial and lead to salvation.
Let us not neglect these things so that, as we remain united and undivided in agreement, we may also be joined together in the bond of love, maintaining the inseparable gift of peace in the ministry entrusted to us.
This unity ensures the Church remains intact and harmonious, so the spiritual city of the great King is fortified and protected, remaining unassailable and unbreachable against every assault and trick of unseen enemies and those surrounding it, seeking to overwhelm any of its registered and spiritually marked members.
Against these foes, we do not wield worldly weapons but spiritual ones, such as the shield of faith and the sword of the Word, which is the Word of God, to demolish the strongholds and devices of sin, casting away and driving off their wild audacity with the sling of the Spirit, deemed worthy of divine protection and guidance.
This establishes our conduct as peaceful and calm, so that at the resurrection, at the last trumpet, we may be deemed worthy to meet the author of our life, coming without condemnation in the glory of the Father with His holy angels, and to enter the bridal chamber with the wise virgins and enjoy the angelic feast.
We become heirs of the good things reserved for the worthy in Christ, the true God, through the intercession of His pure and blameless mother and all the saints.
Amen.
If we have come to these matters so late, let no one be surprised or accuse us of negligence, but know, beloved brothers, that a strict and unyielding decree has prevailed, preventing us from using what is given, not because of any priestly indifference or failure, nor out of any negligence of what is necessary and belonging to ecclesiastical men.
Allow your sacred soul to understand, if there is any blame for delay, that I am in a trial myself.
It is not easy to resist powerful forces when driven by one's own desires and eager to fulfill everything as they wish.
It seemed right to the one who imposed the task to offer a favorable excuse for us because of what was accomplished for the anointing.
As you separated yourselves from the Church, he spread rumors and grew angry.
Therefore, you too, having suffered under compulsion, can be understanding towards those who involuntarily find themselves in similar situations.
For these reasons, I believe there is no need for more words about the lack of reason.
They are clearly noted for you, and the completed actions speak for themselves.
Since the key has been broken, the gate opened, and the stones blocking the road have been removed, every smooth and untrodden path has been made straight.
Distress has now vanished, scandals have become distant, and the troubles of hostility are set aside.
The obstacles from there have been loosened, and a liberating light has shone upon the Church.
For this reason, love has found its place, and the prevailing priestly customs are being advanced and fulfilled.
However, there are those for whom divine matters did not matter, and for the sake of their own glory, they hastened to see what kind of divine judgment will meet them.
While they seek fame and glory, focusing on each other, we remain dedicated to the glory of God, the honor of the Church, unity, and preserving sacred traditions.
We stand firm in our beliefs, and for the pious and mighty king, a true child of the Church who shines with godly character and good deeds, we offer fervent prayers and supplications to God who has crowned him and reigns with him.
We pray for a peaceful life and a long-lasting reign for him, adorned with victories over adversaries and successful governance of the Christian people, committed to the zeal of orthodoxy and the observance of divine commandments, ensuring a prosperous future for his children in authority.
To Michael, the most holy metropolitan of the Christ-loving city of Philadelphia, we have entrusted our current synodal letters to our beloved and longed-for brotherhood.
We are confident from his previous encounter and conversation that he will be warmly welcomed and accepted by you.
We also ask, due to our humility, that the reception, honor, and rest you provide him be genuine and heartfelt.
For he has earned genuine warmth and sincerity in your love and shows eagerness and readiness in Church matters, excelling in word, life, and virtue.
With God's help, he intends to bring us the symbols of love and unity, namely your esteemed letters and transcripts, for our greater spiritual joy and to strengthen our friendly disposition in the Lord.
We extend our warmest greetings to the entire brotherhood with you in Christ.
In the Lord, be strong in your prayers for us, most holy and blessed brother.
You have the great and chief apostle as your mediator and collaborator with God, our common protector and helper.
Do not hesitate to bring your prayers on behalf of us, His unworthy servants.
As a symbol of love that unites us in the Lord, we have sent to your blessed brotherhood a golden medallion.
One side is enclosed with crystal, and the other is engraved with enamel, containing another medallion inside, in which pieces of the precious wood are embedded.
Along with this, a white tunic and a brown unsewn vestment, a stole, and a maniple, all embroidered with gold.
Receiving these, with God's blessing and protection, may you be moved towards compassion.
We have ensured that these items are skillfully wrapped in linen and sealed with a lead seal as a remembrance.
To Leo, Pope of ancient Rome, our brother and co-minister,
Most holy and blessed in all things, Nicephorus, by the mercy of God, Bishop of Constantinople, sends greetings in the Lord.
Truly great and worthy of all praise and admiration is the faithful and prudent servant described in the sacred parables of the Gospel.
This servant is appointed by the Lord over His household, dispensing the word to the flock entrusted to him.
Not wastefully, not prodigally, not imprudently, but with judgment and according to the need and benefit of the needy.
Distributing the measure of wheat to his fellow servants at the right time, and ensuring each receives a proper and necessary portion.
He earns unusual favor and goodwill from his lord and surely attains the prize of promised blessedness.
Indeed, excelling in everything he is appointed to steward, diligently attending to the obtaining of promises, and applying faith with prudence and skill, as well as due care and attention everywhere,
He excellently demonstrates his goodwill and grateful mind towards his lord.
Why, then, even though he loses none of those who have been entrusted to him, does he truly promote each person's safety and freedom with suitable prudence, sobriety, diligence, and sincerity, and eagerly provide the necessary support to achieve it?
It's because, favored by the Lord and graciously visited by his presence, he still hears that joyful Gospel:
"Well done, good and faithful servant; you have been faithful over a few things, I will make you ruler over many things. Enter into the joy of your Lord" Matthew 25:23.
These are the works and rewards of that faithful servant. But truly, I am not the one who can rightly manage and dispense these matters, but someone who clearly needs the guidance and direction of others.
For I am indeed very small, truly the least of all, and utterly unworthy of such a distinguished role and great function.
Therefore, the Church, which the Apostle defines as the house of God, should in no way have been entrusted to a man of such weak and frail nature, and mostly still lacking the benefit of divine purification.
Nor should I, since I have not yet sufficiently learned to rule and compose myself properly, nor have I yet sufficiently despised those vile and earthly things, have undertaken the care and governance of souls in any way.
Since even those endowed with greater gifts of mind and body struggle greatly to achieve the end of this administration.
After being elevated to this position, which I've always felt unworthy of and still do, I hope that, even if I don't fully deserve the praise of blessedness, I might at least avoid falling into calamities and miseries.
Misled by a stubborn and perverse mindset, I aim to avoid the opposite fate-the disaster and downfall of that wicked servant.
He, indulging excessively in laziness, ignored his master's return and was severe and unbearable to his fellow servants, associating with drunkards.
Unprepared for his master's sudden arrival, he was cut off and met the same fate as the hypocrites in the fiery lake.
I certainly hope not to be like the one who, after burying the talent he received, was bitterly and severely accused.
Not only was he asked for the interest and its multiplication, but he was also stripped of his life and cast into outer darkness.
Matthew Twenty-Five.
I hope not to be found among these, nor to be an example of ridicule and a shaking of the head to all who see.
Condemned by Him who knows and examines all our deeds, I do not wish to someday be forced to pay the deserved penalties for unjust actions.
So that those who might fall into similar offenses, warned by my example and punishment, may refrain from crime and correct their lives.
Since, by God's permission and tolerance, I have taken up this yoke and accepted this ministry and service unwillingly and almost by force, I will briefly explain how, as is nearly known to all, my past years of work and way of life have been.
Others have different studies and tasks, greater or lesser, according to their desires, and each person chooses what they hope will be beneficial, according to their own judgment.
Just as there are various opinions among people and different plans, with diverse habits and customs, so too are the choices and ways of living varied, almost to infinity.
Some people choose to endure a mechanical life, no matter how cheap, miserable, and uncertain it may be.
You might see others devoted to the labor and challenges of farming.
Some are driven by the pursuit of commerce and the desire to accumulate wealth.
There are also those who, compelled by a desire to explore foreign places, face the dangers of sailing.
Without listing each individually, others engage in various demanding arts, while a few more refined individuals embrace a solitary and philosophical way of living.
They exercise and cleanse both their minds and bodies, drawing closer to God in this way, and thus attain that heavenly and blessed life.
You may also come across some who, dedicated to eloquence and the logical sciences and disciplines, cultivate their minds as workshops of the muses.
Ultimately, as it pleases each person and as their natural inclination guides them, they embrace different ways of life.
However, my way of life has been different.
As soon as I became a man, I was quickly drawn into the courts of princes, where I secured a position that was neither cheap nor idle, but rather efficient and noble.
This was largely achieved through diligent work; I was appointed a royal notary, which the Latins call a secretary.
Moreover, after being involved in this service for some time and entangled in worldly affairs, I began to seriously contemplate the instability of this present life.
Through frequent and varied reflections, I realized how difficult, almost impossible, it is for those caught up in worldly matters to reach higher and more divine things.
Seeing these worldly pursuits as trivial and fleeting, and the others as serious and eternal, I decided and resolved to abandon the former as soon as possible and devote myself entirely to the latter.
It occurred to me that it was better to excel even moderately in higher pursuits and be seen as praiseworthy, than to be esteemed as the most elegant and splendid in lesser things.
It was far more preferable to possess myself and be, in a way, my own law, than to care for external matters.
Reflecting on these matters repeatedly, and considering that, according to the voice of the most excellent prophet, everything is subject to vanity and nothing remains for a man from all his toil under the sun.
Ecclesiastes Chapter One, Verse Two.
And according to the wisdom of the sage, the form of this world is passing away.
First Corinthians Chapter Seven, Verse Thirty-One.
Keeping in mind the opinion of the chosen vessel, and diligently considering many other Scriptures that speak in the same sense, I silently pondered the saying of a very renowned philosopher:
"It is better," he said, "to live a private life than to hold the greatest power if you are not going to achieve anything remarkable."
I considered all present glory that flatters like a tale.
So, with my mind turning inward and promising myself God's certain help, I decided to renounce all honor and authority.
I detached myself from the royal court and its civil unrest, retreating to a secluded place-a rough, almost inaccessible rock, several miles from the region of the Propontis and the royal city.
There, I firmly resolved to spend my life, testing the life of solitude (which I had long desired), and planned to breathe my last breath in that place.
However, not everything can turn out as we wish-for fate seems to rule in many matters, and human efforts often lead to outcomes not as we desire, but as God wills.
This very thing happened to me: my hopes and intentions were frustrated.
From that pleasant and friendly solitude, by some judgment-known only to God, who allowed or perhaps ordained it-I was drawn back to the royal palace.
This was certainly by the will of those holding the throne at the time, and through the common agreement of the entire clergy and senate, who were orchestrating an unavoidable event.
By their decision-as the bishop of the royal city had passed away-I was unwillingly, and with much protest (God is my witness), promoted to this episcopal seat.
It was more by force than by choice or persuasion, and I was appointed to govern others.
Although I have reluctantly accepted the responsibility of caring for souls, I am deeply concerned about the complex schemes and traps set by the author of all malice.
I also fear the attacks from malevolent and unseen spirits and their inherent cruelty.
I worry that they might suddenly attack me, as I am unprepared and lack the virtues needed for protection.
They know I am not yet well-trained in spiritual and divine practices and are aware that I am not skilled in fighting against them.
They could wound me with the arrows of sin, scattering the church flock, disrupting order, and challenging the battle led by someone inexperienced like me.
Furthermore, I see that leadership is often targeted by envy and slander, and I am suspicious of the deceit and depravity of the envious.
They are curious about our affairs, whether good or bad.
While they ignore their own flaws, they eagerly point out the faults in others.
They speak harshly and unfairly against leaders over trivial matters, throwing bitter accusations.
Having taken on this struggle against such powerful enemies, whose help and protection should I seek but God's?
Therefore, I constantly call upon His strength and assistance, asking Him to look upon my weakness with mercy.
Support me with His right hand, and guide me according to His will and the well-being of my subjects.
If, in the midst of our current challenges, His assistance seems less evident, it's often due to our own shortcomings, encouraging us to better our lives.
Alternatively, it might be to reveal the malice and deception within, so that the hidden poison in our minds doesn't stay concealed, and whatever is hidden in our hearts comes to light.
As Solomon points out in Proverbs chapter eighteen, a brother who helps his brother is like a fortified city, a palace secured with bars.
Therefore, I sincerely ask for many prayers, as I am in need of much support.
More than anything, I deeply long for and desire the holy prayers and intercessions to God from your most holy and spiritually cherished brotherhood.
Your prayers, much like those of Moses and Samuel, reach very close to God due to their purity and are carried directly to the heavenly and spiritual altar.
We have no doubt they will bring us great help and benefit.
So, please support my weakness and lift your holy hands on high.
We believe that the strength of your faith will not falter and that God's mercy and kindness, inspired by this, will come to us swiftly.
This will strengthen and fortify our weakness and frailty, so that we are clothed with the armor of faith and the helmet of hope, as described in Ephesians chapter six and First Thessalonians.
Let us boldly stand against the rulers, authorities, and powers of this dark world, and the spiritual forces of evil with whom we constantly struggle.
Let's maintain a firm and unwavering resolve.
Moreover, let's skillfully and properly win over those who have been rebellious and opposed until now, bringing them to Christ.
Let's restore them as children of adoption to the holy Church of God, make them part of Christ's chosen and rational flock, and lead them into the sacred enclosures of the Church, so they are not seized and torn apart by wolves.
In this way, all of them, protected by the signs of unity and agreement, will not be torn apart by any traps or bites.
Instead, they will submit to Christ, the head of all of us, and bow their necks willingly and obediently to him.
Pray, I beseech you, and earnestly ask that he may deign to enlighten and cleanse us, so that, having become children of perfect light, we may also be able to enlighten and cleanse others.
May he provide us with words to speak, so that we may fill our listeners with spirit and diligently proclaim the power of our mysteries with great zeal, always relying on his grace from the Letter to the Ephesians, Chapter Six, who makes the tongues of the speechless eloquent and strengthens the feet of the lame to eagerly run to preach the Gospel.
May he also multiply the entrusted talent, so that at the right time, what is owed to the head of the household may be returned with interest.
And may he grant us not only to work in that fertile vineyard but, having patiently endured the hardship and toil of the day, to also receive the reward for our labor and be equaled in reward to those who entered without an agreement at the eleventh hour from the Book of Matthew.
Finally, let's enlighten the eye of our mind.
With spiritual light brightening our vision and removing what's clouding our soul and understanding, we can better grasp the meaning of the prophetic words.
Let's engage eagerly in serving divine commandments and diligently guard against the arrows of adversaries.
We must protect ourselves and carefully anticipate the sword of divine wrath hanging over sinners.
By understanding the danger and appeasing the divine will, we can hopefully escape the coming wrath, both for ourselves and those we lead.
But if we can't achieve both, at least let me save my soul, just like the righteous Lot who strove to save his soul from the fire Genesis 19:22.
So, let your prayers and efforts for spiritual protection be directed towards this goal.
As the occasion demands, I am pleased to hear now that great and eloquent trumpet, the foremost herald of the Gospel, the apostle Paul.
He, rejoicing greatly in spirit over the fervor and steadfastness of the ancient Romans in faith and religion, writes to them in his letter, with a kind of holy boasting, proclaiming their piety and faith to be celebrated throughout the whole world.
Among other things, he writes: I thank my God through Jesus Christ for all of you, because your faith is being reported all over the world Romans 1:8.
But is this pure and sincere faith of our Gospel, outside of which there is no other, confined only within the boundaries of the Romans?
Absolutely not.
It's not limited to any specific place.
The prophetic and apostolic voices, bursting forth, have spread all over the earth with the sound of divine preaching, and the words of the heavenly heralds have reached the ends of the world Romans 2; Psalm 10.
In fact, it's not even excluded from the heavens or from the supreme and intellectual virtues.
Even though the higher Church of the firstborn in heaven is justified, the city of those justified by faith, the heavenly Jerusalem, has God as its creator and builder.
He will reconcile the earthly with the heavenly, breaking down the wall of separation, and saving the lost sheep, lifted on His shoulder through an incredible descent and profound humility.
He grafted in those who persevered and is known by other similar names.
However, it is not different but one and the same Church of heaven and earth.
Therefore, it is reasonable to have one and the same indivisible society everywhere through the unity of faith.
For God is known not only in Judea but wherever the mind or senses can reach.
Hence, we too, who have taken the name of New Rome, stand on the same foundation of faith, that of the apostles and prophets, who are indeed the wisest architects, with Christ and God, our Savior, as the cornerstone and foundation beneath.
Regarding the integrity of faith, we do not believe in the old Romans.
For in the holy Churches of God, there is no distinction of former or latter, just as there is no difference between Jew and Greek, slave and free, barbarian and Scythian, but all are one in Christ.
Let Saint Paul also glory in us and think magnificently, joining the new with the old, doctrine with doctrine, and committing preaching to preaching, exulting equally in both.
Indeed, like them, we have embraced and followed this teaching and instruction.
We stand firm in it, rooted and confirmed in our confession of faith.
We take pride in it and openly proclaim our glorious and blameless view of religion, in which we serve God and, as long as we live, wish to persevere unyieldingly.
Strengthened and established by heavenly grace, we hope to leave this life.
For there is no other way to rightly and sacredly conduct this present life and surely attain the good things awaiting the worthy in the future age.
Therefore, I confess to believe in one God, the Father Almighty, creator of all, master and lord of all.
And in His only Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, true God, eternal Word, born of the Father in a manner that is ineffable and incomprehensible from eternity, in a way that no spiritual or sensible creature can understand.
And in the Holy Spirit, life-giving and most holy.
I believe in the consubstantial Trinity, supersubstantial, unseen, incomprehensible, indivisible, unchangeable, eternal, undivided, simple, lacking any part, composition, body, quantity, or quality.
Possessing the same honor, glory, and divinity, approachable by no touch or contact, free of any form, infinitely good, knowing no diminishing light, thrice-luminous, supremely splendid.
Always affected in the same equal way, a power seeing all things and accomplishing all.
Spiritually and indivisibly illuminating all with reason and understanding through the present ray of divine light, preserving all things that exist in both being and well-being suitably, according to each one's nature.
Known in subsisting things, not just in mere names.
Glorified in one divinity, equal power, equal majesty of the kingdom, worshipped and adored by all visible and invisible creatures.
Among the three persons we consider in the Trinity, one is the Father, who has no beginning and no cause for His existence, as He is not from another, but from Himself and has being in Himself.
Another is the Son, who does have a beginning, for He is from the Father: the Father is the source and origin of the Son.
If you consider the beginning of time, the Son is equally without beginning as the Father, for He is the creator of time, not subject to it.
Through an inseparable and eternal generation, He shines forth from the Father, like the radiance of His glory and the exact representation of His being.
Lastly, there is the Holy Spirit, who has His substance from the Father not by a newness, but by procession, and He shares the same eternity with the Father and the Son.
He is eternal, yet not without beginning, as He proceeds from the Father: for the Father is the source and beginning of Him as well.
But concerning time, He too is without beginning.
Therefore, there is one God the Father from whom all things exist, and one Lord Jesus Christ through whom all things exist, and one Holy Spirit in whom all things exist.
From these three perfect persons, there is one most perfect, indeed in itself absolutely complete divinity, with distinct properties and personal characteristics that distinguish the persons from one another.
For each person, even though it cannot be separated from another due to the unity of essence, is still distinguished from another by personal property and the concept of the mind, and is known and believed to be a perfect God, adorned with all the properties of divinity, yet all are one in divinity.
Once again, even though three are joined together, we still worship one God.
This Trinity maintains both substance and unity in essence.
Against the chaotic confusion and rebellion of pagan madness, we do not worship many rulers, but one ruler.
However, this rule isn't confined to one person, avoiding the imperfection and immaturity of Jewish narrowness.
Instead, it reveals the equality of nature, harmony of thought, identity of motion, and a shared will towards one.
According to the supreme theologian Gregory, this unity doesn't occur in created nature.
The unity and kinship of the deity in the Trinity are not divided or split, unlike created things when multiplied.
Let us reject the insane opinions and rage of Arius.
The Trinity is, in every way, undivided in glory and eternity, and no part is alienated from itself.
Yet, the divine persons do not permeate or transform into one another.
Each remains immutable, unconfused, and eternal.
Let the misleading confusion of the foolish Sabellius be sent far away and expelled.
I also venerate and adore the mystery of the incarnation, predetermined before all ages but revealed in the last times for the salvation of the entire human race.
This was accomplished through the descent of the great and admirable one, a person of the holy and life-giving Trinity, namely Christ, our true God, and his ineffable dispensation.
So that from where we were granted to exist through his indescribable goodness, we might also receive well-being.
I confess and believe in the unique nature of the most wealthy and blessed Trinity: the Son of God and the Word, worshipped and glorified alongside God the Father and the Holy Spirit for all eternity, sharing the same essence and equality with them.
With infinite kindness and mercy towards His creation, and with the Father's will and compassion, along with the grace and cooperation of the Holy Spirit, He descended from heaven to live among humans.
This was to save us, who were long condemned because of sin, expelled from the delights of paradise, and subject to corruption, through grace, and to make us participants in the divine nature.
Truly dwelling in the womb of the Virgin, who rightly gave birth to God, and by the Holy Spirit adopting a soul and body, assuming our entire nature as He had formed man in the beginning, God became incarnate.
The Virgin, who supernaturally and indescribably gave birth, remained a virgin after childbirth, with her virginity intact and unchanged, showing that through the process of the second birth, her nature experienced no change or alteration whatsoever.
Therefore, He, who shares the same nature as the Father, became of the same essence with us in every way, except for sin.
Taking the seed of Abraham, He became partaker of flesh and blood just like us, assuming flesh animated by an intelligent soul, not pre-existing in any way before that supreme union, but simultaneously united with the flesh and the soul endowed with reason, and united with the Word.
He did not dwell in our nature merely through grace, but was wholly united to the entirety of human nature, achieving an unconfused, indivisible, and supernatural union.
The divine and human natures, coming together, persist and endure in their natural properties unchanged, nor are they transformed into each other in any way.
However, due to that natural union and connection, we believe that the mutual sharing and exchange of names should be granted appropriately.
This is because of the physical and wonderful union of the natures coming together, not in reality but in imagination, leading us to establish a certain distinction of one and the same thing here.
Furthermore, the singularity and uninterrupted unity of the same person always remain consistent, even with the distinction of natures.
For we reject the monstrous confusion and blending of the impostors Eutyches and Dioscorus.
Thus, we acknowledge the same one as both created and uncreated, eternal and temporal, heavenly and earthly, limited and unlimited, capable of suffering and incapable of suffering, without a mother and without a father.
One due to the ineffable, eternal, and timeless birth from the Father, and the other due to the mysterious and incomprehensible union with our nature.
We recognize his two births, which go beyond all understanding and reason.
For the only-begotten Son, existing in the form of God and in the bosom, that is, the essence of the Father, and shining from him eternally, at the end of the ages emptied himself and took on the form of a servant, that is, our substance.
Thus, the union in Christ according to the hypostasis joins one to the other, such as the visible to the invisible, the capable of suffering to the incapable of suffering, and the other elements from which the Savior is constituted.
Yet, this does not constitute a different person, far from it.
We confess one and the same perfect God and perfect man.
For even if we attribute the difference of natures to Christ, we still recognize him as one and the same even after the incarnation.
And so that the foolish Nestorius may be removed from the divine enclosures, we do not introduce two sons or a duality of sons due to the diversity of natures coming together into a hypostatic union, but we attribute all actions of Christ, which were indeed theandric, that is, of God and man together, to one.
Because He was God, He performed divine works, including signs and miracles.
Yet, as a human, He willingly endured suffering and faced insults and disgrace.
Thus, in line with His two natures, as is fitting and necessary, following the holy and divine traditions of our forefathers, I glorify His two natural operations, which indicate and establish these natures and substances.
Similarly, I also honor the two natural wills of our one and the same God and Lord Jesus Christ.
For according to each nature, from which and in which He exists and is understood, we attribute to Him the capability of will:
just as He acts and willingly exposes Himself to the saving passion, so He also wills.
I believe He was crucified, not in the nature in which He shines and reigns with the Father-although He is called crucified as the Lord of glory because of the communication of properties-but in the earthly nature, in which He took on our earthly form and became cursed because of our sins.
This was so He might make us participants in His blessing; and He patiently endured the death of the flesh inflicted by the wicked, so that He might condemn sin, the sting of death, in His flesh, and destroy him who had the power of death, that is, the devil.
I believe His body was entrusted to the tomb, preserved incorrupt, in no way separated from that mysterious and inexplicable union, even though it was deprived of the soul during that three-day interval.
With that soul, He also descended to the dead, and to those spirits who were in the flesh, as the divine leader of the apostles, Peter, explains.
He proclaimed resurrection, imparted freedom and redemption, and became for us, as the firstborn of the dead, a beginning of incorruption through resurrection.
For He rose as God, conquering death, and opening the way to resurrection for all flesh; raising us, who had fallen into death through the fall of sin, together with Himself in a certain way.
I believe that after His resurrection, He appeared to the women and brought them joy and happiness, removing the sadness that had come to us through a woman.
I believe He revealed Himself alive to His divine disciples, affirming the mystery of His resurrection.
He showed He was the same as before the resurrection by eating and allowing His sacred side to be touched by wise Thomas.
I believe finally that He ascended into heaven and sat at the right hand of God the Father.
He will return in glory and divine majesty, with the body He assumed, to judge, and will reward each according to the way they lived.
For we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ.
I believe that after this world is renewed and transformed, there will be the resurrection of the flesh, so that this mortal body may become immortal and the perishable may become imperishable.
Romans Fourteen.
I also confess one baptism for the forgiveness of sins, conducted according to the evangelical and apostolic tradition in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
These venerable doctrines and divine mysteries of our orthodox and sacred worship, which the divine and holy teachers have passed down to us according to sublime and sincere theology, as well as the saving dispensation of the divine word towards us, and all other similar and agreeable teachings and preachings, I embrace and uphold with complete acceptance and faith.
Nevertheless, I embrace and seek the protection and intercession of the saints with God: first and foremost, the most holy and pure ever-virgin, our lady, the Mother of God.
Then, the divine and heavenly powers, the praised apostles, the blessed prophets, the glorious and undefeated martyrs, the divine Fathers, and all the saints who have pleased the Lord from the beginning of the world and continue to live in Him without end.
(For the souls of the righteous are in the hand of God.)
This is so that I may gain the greatest possible health of soul and body.
I also venerate and adore their venerable relics, as they provide health and healing to the diseases of souls and bodies.
Furthermore, I embrace and praise their divine conduct, their celebrated struggles and battles, and I honor and venerate their sacred tombs and graves.
I consider them worthy of the highest honors and greatest praises, for they shed their blood for the glory of God, the Savior of us all, and courageously scorned this fleeting life for their love of God, imitating His life-giving and saving sufferings.
I likewise embrace and accept not only the venerable icons of Christ, the Savior of us all, and the images of the most holy Mother of God, but also the sacred images of all the saints, giving them the veneration they rightfully deserve.
Furthermore, I reverently and fully venerate and embrace the seven sacred and ecumenical councils and all the supernatural and saving doctrines and decrees established in them by our holy and divine Fathers, whom the Holy Spirit appointed to guide and shepherd His Church.
First, the sacred council of 318 renowned Fathers, who once gathered in the city of Nicaea against the impious and raging Arius, expelled the author of impiety from the Church and clarified the true and correct faith for us through that sacred divine creed.
They firmly established that the Word of God and Son of God is not a creature, as Arius claimed, but is of the same substance as the Father-a true and certain God, and the creator of all things.
Then, the council of 150 most holy and divine Fathers, convened after Nicaea in this imperial city, deposed the most impious Macedonius, the attacker of the Holy Spirit.
They demonstrated that the Holy Spirit is not something created but a true God, equal in every way to the Father and the Son.
They elaborated on the sacred creed with words about the Holy Spirit, and also expelled from the Church the truly foolish and insane Apollinaris.
After this, I accept the sacred council of 200 holy Fathers and learned men, which met in Ephesus against the mad Nestorius and his blasphemous words, removing him from his rank and position.
They determined that Christ our God is one person, and that his two natures are united without any confusion or division, declaring again that he is the same one God and man.
They finally pronounced that the sacred virgin Mary is truly and properly the Mother of God.
I embrace fourthly the sacred council of 630 divinely inspired Fathers convened in Chalcedon, which condemned the most impious Eutyches and Dioscorus, along with their obscure and dark confusion.
By anathematizing them, it piously proclaimed that Christ our God and Lord is one and the same-a perfect man and perfect God, existing in two natures, yet in one person, without confusion and without division.
Then again, the fifth holy synod of 165 holy Fathers, held in this divine city dedicated to God, rightly condemned the impious doctrines of Theodore, Nestorius, Origen, Didymus, Evagrius, and other heretics.
These doctrines had been hidden among many for a long time but began producing bitter branches and shoots once more.
What they deliriously and fancifully professed was more aligned with the imagination of Jews and pagans than with the Christian faith.
After this, I also honor the sixth holy and ecumenical synod of 170 holy men, gathered once again in this royal city.
This synod clarified and proclaimed the nature of Christ, along with His natural properties, operations, and wills.
It anathematized Theodore, Bishop of Pharan, Honorius, Cyrus, Sergius, Pyrrhus, Paul, Peter-who, by God's permission, had infiltrated the priesthood of the Church through corruption and deceit-Macarius, Bishop of Antioch, and Stephen, disciple of Macarius, and Polychronius, a childish and insane old man.
For they taught that only one will and one operation should be attributed to Christ, our Savior.
Lastly, I accept the seventh holy synod of 150 holy Fathers, celebrated in our age in the city of Nicaea.
This synod confirmed and, in some way, sealed all the preceding holy synods, their doctrines, and decrees.
It defined that the worship and veneration of holy and venerable images, handed down from the beginning to the churches, should be recognized as worthy of veneration, just like the image of the life-giving cross.
Therefore, we expel from the churches those who insult Christians with trivial chatter, in contempt and overthrow of these images, as if they have so far held and venerated them in the place of gods, such as Theodosius, Basil, and Sisinnius, who, by God's permission, presided over episcopal seats.
I accept these holy and ecumenical councils and wholeheartedly embrace the teachings and writings of all the chosen and blessed Fathers, as they contain doctrine free from reproach and serve as the foundation of salvation.
I accept all whom the Catholic Church accepts, and I reject all whom it rejects.
I also condemn and utterly despise those who, following Simon Magus, have abandoned all piety and continue to weaken the tradition of the saints with wicked and destructive doctrines, sowing the poisonous seeds of heresy into the field of the orthodox faith even today.
I denounce all of them and their followers, and I reject and anathematize them as plagues upon the Churches of Christ.
Therefore, in accordance with the sanction of the Churches, which has prevailed from the beginning, we use these letters as a kind of living herald and as pledges of charity in Christ and mutual harmony and friendship among us, to greet you and convey our opinion to your most blessed and God-taught selves in this manner.
In return, your greatly desired brotherhood in the Lord, through prayers offered to the Lord and timely words and deeds, may confirm and guide us, so that supported by your laws and doctrine, we may remain steadfast, simple, and free from all deficiency in this faith, retaining all the mysteries handed down from the beginning, unshaken.
Finally, we gather our entire rational flock, marked by the name and anointing of the supreme shepherd, within the enclosures of the ecclesiastical fold, with the clear proclamation of divine and apostolic spiritual doctrine and divinely inspired voices, keeping it unharmed from the bites of lurking beasts.
If we've left anything out, please feel free to complete it with a friendly and paternal affection, so that your abundance can fill our gaps.
Whatever we're missing, whether in words or actions, please add to it and build upon it with the venerable and worthy authority of a priest in our lives.
The gift shared with you won't suffer any loss this way.
In fact, generous sharing doesn't reduce what we have; instead, at the right time, it brings back many glorious fruits.
With your divine strength, support us, who are weaker, and guide our steps along the path of the Gospel.
Please suggest anything that seems beneficial or useful, so that as we maintain unity and harmony in faith and confession, we remain bound together by the bond of love, preserving the undivided gift of peace that fosters the unity and harmony of the Churches.
Let us continue to uphold this in the ministry entrusted to us, so the city of the great King, fortified and surrounded on all sides, stays impervious to the deceptions and attacks of unseen enemies, who eagerly wait to devour anyone marked by the Spirit.
Against these invisible foes, we wield not physical weapons, but spiritual ones-namely, the shield of faith and the sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God.
By demolishing and attacking the strongholds and schemes of sin with the sling of the Spirit, we repel and crush their cruel audacity.
In this way, with divine protection and assistance, may our lives be peaceful and calm, and when the final trumpet sounds at the time of regeneration, may we be deemed worthy to meet the coming Lord in the glory of the Father with His holy angels.
Together, may we enter the bridal chamber with the wise virgins, to enjoy the spiritual and angelic feast forever, and become heirs of the blessings reserved in Christ the true God for those who are deserving.
All this we pray through the intercession of His immaculate and blameless mother and all the saints.
Amen.
Let no one be surprised that we've addressed this matter later than expected, as we've explained so far, and let no one question our reputation because of it.
Instead, know that the priestly tradition has not been ignored, nor have we neglected any duties out of contempt or laziness.
It was the harsh decision of an overpowering authority that prevented us from following decrees.
So, may your blessed soul forgive me if my delay has caused any harm, and consider how difficult it is to oppose those in power who act on their own will.
Believing they had a reason to hinder us, those already initiated into the priesthood, they accused us, claiming you were estranged from the Church of Constantinople and had rashly separated from it.
When this matter, whether through force or injustice, also concerns you, may you pardon those constrained by similar necessity against their will.
Since we've already reported the current state of the Church to your holiness and plan to update you at the appropriate time, I see no need for a lengthy explanation now.
The barrier that was hindering us has been broken through, the door opened, and the obstacles cleared from the path.
The troubles have vanished, and the disputes have ceased.
Finally, all obstacles are gone, and the original light of the Church has been restored.
Therefore, the love and priestly tradition can once again be practiced without difficulty.
However, there are still some who disregard the divine and pursue their own schemes without considering the judgment of God that awaits them.
However, while it's common and enjoyable for them to eagerly seek present glory and splendor, and to conspire among themselves for this reason, it is indeed fitting that we focus all our efforts on divine glory, ecclesiastical decorum, harmony, and the observance of sacred canons.
We should dedicate ourselves to our duties day and night, offering continuous prayers and supplications to God for our most pious and powerful emperor, now recognized as a true and genuine son of the Church, and distinguished by a life of conduct that is pleasing to God.
We pray that God, who crowns him and governs the kingdom with him, grants him a peaceful life and a long-lasting reign, adorns him with victories over the barbarians, ensures successful governance of the Christian order, inspires zeal for the orthodox faith, and perfects him in observing the divine commandments.
We hope he may pass on to his children not just the longevity of the kingdom and power, but also uncommon honor and glory.
Furthermore, we have entrusted these synodal letters to Michael, the most holy and Christ-beloved metropolitan of the city of Philadelphia, to be delivered to your beloved and cherished fraternity.
Although we have no doubt, based on our conversations and interactions with him, that you will receive him with all courtesy and greet him warmly, we nonetheless ask, in humility, that you genuinely, familiarly, and honorably welcome and provide for him.
He embraces your love with sincere and fervent affection, demonstrates great zeal and readiness in ecclesiastical matters, and seems to excel in speech, integrity of life, and virtue.
Guided by God and the inspiration of your spirit, he will return to us, bringing us greater spiritual joy and a more perfect affection of our love in the Lord, symbolized by your venerable letters in response to these present ones.
We send our warmest greetings to the entire brotherhood with you in Christ.
Farewell in the Lord.
Pray for us, most holy and blessed brother, as a mediator and supporter before God, our common patron and benefactor.
Having obtained the great prince of the apostles, do not hesitate to offer intercessions for us unworthy servants.
As a sign of the love that exists between us in the Lord, we have sent your brotherly blessedness a golden medallion.
One side is enclosed in crystal, the other crafted in relief work.
It contains within it another medallion, into which carved fragments of precious woods are inserted.
Along with this comes a white stole, a phenoilum woven in chestnut color, an epitrachelion, and a book adorned and decorated with gold.
We have taken care to wrap these as a souvenir, to be humbly offered to that merciful apostleship under God's guidance.
They are elegantly wrapped in cloth and sealed with a leaden seal.