The Acts of Saint Sebastian the Martyr
Chapter One
Saint Sebastian Encourages the Martyrs.
Saint Sebastian, a devout Christian, was educated in Milan but was actually a citizen of Narbonne.
He was so cherished by Emperors Diocletian and Maximian that they appointed him as the leader of the first cohort, commanding him to always stay in their presence.
He was a man of great wisdom, honest in speech, just in judgment, prudent in counsel, faithful in his duties, strong in support, notable for his kindness, and distinguished by his integrity.
The soldiers respected him as a father, and everyone in charge of the palace held him in high regard.
Indeed, he was a true worshiper of God, and it was fitting that someone filled with God's grace was loved by all.
Thus, he devoted himself diligently to Christ every day, making sure to keep it hidden from the sacrilegious rulers.
He was neither frightened by the fear of suffering nor constrained by love for his possessions.
He served as a hidden soldier of Christ under the guise of earthly authority, strengthening the spirits of Christians he saw weakening under torture and returning to God the souls the devil sought to claim.
After he rescued many martyrs' minds from the fear of suffering and encouraged them toward the crown of eternal glory, it was clear who he was, as a light cannot remain hidden in darkness.
To the noble men, Marcellian and Mark, twin brothers imprisoned for the name of Christ, he offered daily comfort.
To them and their servants, who were imprisoned with them, he provided wise counsel, helping them reject the fleeting temptations of the world and not fear temporary forms of torture.
Chapter Two
The Strong Opposition Faced by Marcellianus and Marcus.
As they embraced the most blessed comforts and endured the torturers' beatings with unwavering spirit, they were sentenced to death.
However, they were told that if, at the moment of their execution, they agreed to make sacrifices, they would be reunited with their parents, wives, children, and possessions.
They were not only men of noble birth but also wealthy.
Their father was named Tranquillinus, and their mother was Marcia.
Their wives and children followed them, deeply attached to their grandchildren.
As a result, they were granted a thirty-day reprieve from Agrestius Chromatius, the prefect of Rome, during which time efforts were made to persuade them to consent to offering incense to the idols.
Their friends approached them, saying:
"How can you be so hard-hearted and unfeeling to abandon your father's grey hairs and bring new birth pains to your already aged mother?
She overcame the pains of labor with joy when she gave birth to two sons in one, bringing twin joys to their father.
Now, however, it is an unbearable pain, an inconsolable penalty, an irremediable torment, an incomparable birth, where hope and joy are taken away, life is despised, glory is rejected, and, ignoring all feelings of piety, the horror of death is sought rather than feared.
We beg you, dear friends, to finally put an end to these disasters and remember that you are the fathers of sweet children."
While their friends were speaking these and similar words, their mother arrived, lamenting miserably.
With her hair undone, revealing the white hairs of her old age, she tore the garment covering her chest in their sight.
As everyone wept, she showed them the sagging breasts they had nursed from, and through her tears, she recalled the tenderness she had shown during their infancy.
He would say to both of them:
"You have always flattered me more, son, and you were more respectful. In this one, I see my own image; in you, I see your father's looks. You are more useful to your father, while this one is more similar to me.
Woe is me! I am surrounded by incomparable grief, unheard-of misery, and a double loss that cannot be compared to any other tribulations.
I won't even mention the sons who rush to death voluntarily. If enemies were to take them from me, I would follow through the battle lines of warriors; if harsh judgments were to imprison them, I would break into the prison, ready to die alongside them.
This is a new kind of suffering, where execution is requested, life is wished to end, and death is invited to come.
This is a new grief, a new misery, where the youth of the children is willingly lost, and the pitiable old age of the parents is forced to continue.
As the mother continued with these and similar words, the father, weak and burdened with age, was brought forward by the hands of servants. Spreading dust on his swan-like head, he lifted his voice to heaven:
"I have come to bid farewell to my sons who are willingly setting out to die, so that all the burial rites I had prepared for them to perform for me, I, in my sadness, will now provide for them.
O sons, the support of my old age, the twin light of my heart, born happily and raised prosperously, of most excellent memory and unique intelligence, filled with knowledge of all the liberal arts, what sudden madness, born of your own will, has made you lovers of death?
This has never pleased the living, nor has it introduced its love to the dying. To whoever it could reach, it was forced upon them, and was never willingly accepted by any living person.
If a destitute debtor suffers this under a greedy moneylender, he cannot reasonably love it; he is known not only not to love it but to fear it.
By what reasoning does someone who has everything and owes nothing desire it?
Come here, old men, and weep with me over sons who feel their father's heart.
Come here, young men, and weep over the young men who are perishing willingly."
Fathers, come here and stop these things, so you don't have to suffer from them.
My eyes fail from weeping and grow dark as I pour out rivers of tears;
I don't want to see those killed by the sword, whom I feared even when touched by a light rod;
when I saw them troubled even slightly, I was terrified.
So, while the elder was dealing with these and other matters, behold, the wives of both, with their children, came and showed their infants, pouring out these wailing cries:
To whom are you leaving us to serve?
To whom are you giving the love of our marriage?
Who do you think will become the masters of these children and the greedy invaders of your homes?
Who will occupy your family?
Or who will divide among themselves the servants you raised?
Alas, how iron-hearted, how cruelly unkind you are to despise your parents, reject friends, abandon wives, disown children, and willingly hand yourselves over to the executioner!
Chapter Three
Saint Sebastian Strengthens the Wavering.
Meanwhile, as these events unfolded, amidst the tears of wives and the sighs of children, the soldiers of Christ began to weaken and let sorrow creep into their spirits.
Saint Sebastian, whom we mentioned earlier, was present during this scene.
He was a deeply devout Christian, whose military attire concealed his identity, and whose cloak obscured his appearance.
But seeing the athletes of God worn down by the immense struggle, he stepped forward and said:
"O bravest soldiers of Christ, O most prepared warriors of the divine battle, through great strength of spirit you have bravely reached the prize, and now are you setting aside the eternal crown due to miserable temptations?
Let Christ’s soldiers learn through you to be armed with faith rather than with iron.
Do not discard the insignia of your victories due to the allurements of women, and do not allow the defeated enemy’s necks, which are under your feet, to rise again for renewed battles.
Though its persistence against you has been fierce and unjust, rage becomes even fiercer when repeated.
So, raise the glorious trophy of your contest above earthly affections, and do not lose it to the tears of little ones."
"Those whom you see weeping would rejoice today if they understood what you know; for they believe this life is the only one, and if it ends, no living part of the soul remains once the body fails.
If they knew there was another life, untouched by death, free from sadness, where immortality reigns, and everlasting joys dwell, surely they would hurry to reach it with you, valuing this life as nothing, and desiring that one, which remains in joy and knows no end.
For this life is fleeting and so unfaithful that it cannot keep faith even with its lovers.
From the beginning of the world, it has deceived those who believed in it, disappointed all who awaited it, mocked all who relied on it, and thus made no one certain, proving itself false to all."
Oh, how I wish it were only the fault of lies, and that it didn't compel its lovers to commit all sorts of crimes.
This force drives the greedy to gluttony, leads the intoxicated to drunkenness, and causes adulterers to the shipwreck of shame.
It also passes vile perversity to the incestuous.
It urges the thief to steal, the angry to rage, and the liar to deceive.
It sows divorces between spouses, discord among friends, quarrels among the peaceful, and injustice among the just, even causing scandals among brothers.
It strips justice from judges, modesty from the chaste, skill from artisans, and removes discipline from morals.
And to mention the more serious crimes it imposes on its lovers: if a brother ever kills his own brother, if a son murders his father, or if a friend is killed by a friend, by whose urging were these crimes committed?
By whose sight, hope, and trust were these wicked acts done?
Surely, they commit these acts, seduced by the love of this present life, and while they love it more than is just, they pursue others with unjust hatred.
Why does a pirate kill a sailor, why does a robber slay a traveler, a rich man oppress a poor man, a proud one a humble one, and every wrongdoer oppress any innocent person they can?
They commit these evil acts because they desire to serve this life, believing they will endure longer in its love.
Therefore, crimes are committed for no other reason but to serve this most wretched carnal life by carnal people.
It is indeed the force that commands them to commit crimes, orders wicked deeds, and persuades unjust acts; and after it has been fed with all cruelty and every filth, it hands those serving it over to its daughter, which is eternal death.
For from it, and from its womb, eternal death was born at the time when the first humans served their gluttony, lust, and the pleasures of the eyes.
Thus, those who were made for eternal life were cast into this region of death, from which they were again cast down to the underworld, carrying nothing with them except their sins.
This is the life that misleads you, my dearest friends,
causing you to urge your friends, who are on their path to eternal life, to return with misguided counsel.
Chapter Four
The Punishments of Hell and the Joys of Heaven, Explained to the Souls of Martyrs.
This encourages you, O most holy parents, not to call back your children who are departing to join the company of heaven, to partake in incorruptible honor, and to enjoy the friendships of the eternal ruler, with foolish lamentations.
This is what has led you, O most chaste wives of the Blessed, to betray the intentions of the Martyrs under the guise of piety, bringing death instead of deliverance.
If they had agreed to your recall, they could indeed have been with you for a short time; but later they would have been separated, and so separated from you that you would only see them amidst perpetual torments.
Where the devouring flame consumes the souls of unbelievers, where dragons devour the lips of blasphemers, where serpents consume the hearts of unbelievers with their bites.
There, cries and groans echo, and a confused clamor is stirred by the force of torments, and the burning of the fire extracts.
But this very tribulation, which will take unbelievers there, is defined by no limit, concluded by no end, nor is it consumed even after the burning of the fierce flames, as those who have been burned are restored for renewed fires again.
Therefore, allow them to escape this punishment and consider saving yourselves.
Let them reach the destined crown in the meantime.
Do not be afraid; they will not be separated from you, but will go to prepare heavenly mansions for you, where you and your children will remain in everlasting joy with them.
If you are delighted by your stone houses, how much more should the beauty of those heavenly homes invite you, where dining rooms gleam with pure gold, and ceilings are adorned with gems and pearls?
There, the purple flower of roses never withers: there, blooming groves flourish in perpetual greenness: there, fresh meadows always flow with honeyed streams.
There, grasses fragrant with saffron flowers, and fields exhale exceedingly pleasant aromas.
Breezes there, having eternal life, breathe a nectarous scent for the nostrils.
In this place, a light shines without the sun's rays, and clarity exists without clouds or the darkness of night, allowing the eyes to enjoy the day.
The delights here are never interrupted by any occupation, and no worries disturb the peace.
No sounds like lowing, howling, groaning, lamentation, or mourning are ever heard or mentioned here.
Nothing ugly, deformed, terrifying, or filthy is ever seen by the inhabitants.
The beauty and charm of the groves, the brightness of the pleasant air, and all elegance and beauty are endlessly enjoyed by the open eyes.
Nothing disturbs the mind through the ears.
Musical instruments continuously play hymns here, sung by angels and archangels to praise the king.
Bitterness and the harshness of gall do not exist here; thunder is never heard, and lightning never appears.
The shrubs produce cinnamon, and the trees bring forth balsam.
The fragrance of the air spreads delight through every part of the body, and no food here produces waste.
Just as the ears are filled with good news, the nose with good scents, and the eyes with good sights, this refreshment cannot lead to digestion.
Likewise, the refreshment that the mouth receives tastes sweet like honey to everyone, bringing pleasure.
Indeed, whatever the soul desires is immediately fulfilled, and everything serves its delights perfectly.
For whoever, in this mortal life, has fought against their desires and pleasures and has not indulged in them here will fully receive them from their Creator there.
For he created humans in such a way that they might live:
placing death close to the entrance of pleasure,
so those who wish to escape the fear of death might seek eternal life.
Once they learn there is another life beyond this one,
they might wonder whether that life can be ended by old age or concluded by death.
When they recognize that it is immortal,
they might question whether that eternity can bestow honor on the just
or impose punishment on the unjust.
Chapter Five
The Use of Wealth and Luxury.
15.
After establishing this point, the question arises: Why did the Creator make wealth if it is to be scorned by His law?
Or why create various animals, birds, and reptiles if we are meant to renounce them?
Why did the Creator instill deep natural pleasure in our bodies as a motivation for desire, if using it not only brings guilt but also subjects one to eternal punishment?
So, why did the Creator give us wealth if it is to be despised?
We answer: These riches, created by the Creator, in a way speak to their admirers, saying: Love us in such a way that we are never parted from you.
We cannot follow you in death, but we can precede you in life, if only you command it.
A greedy moneylender hands over gold expecting it back doubled, while a miserly farmer plants seeds hoping for them to return a hundredfold.
The debtor repays the lender with double, and the earth gives back a hundredfold to the farmer.
Alas!
The debtor can repay the lender, and the earth can return a hundredfold; can God not multiply His riches returned to Him?
16.
Now you ask: Why did He give me wealth if it is to be given back to Him?
He entrusted it to you so you could understand the rest, pleasure, luxury, and delight it provides.
So that by loving your wealth, you choose to entrust it to our Lord Jesus Christ for safekeeping.
If you decide not to entrust it to Him, either gluttony will consume it, the mother of lust will seize it, or, as you well know, death will suddenly take it away from you.
In such a way that you will no longer anticipate having it, nor will you see it again.
Imagine passing through enemy lines and finding a strong man who has always loved you.
He gives you a purse full of money and says, "Give me the money I gave you to keep, because these enemies are plotting to take it from you. Once they have it, they will attack you with their swords." Wouldn't you fall at his feet and beg him to take it back, knowing he would return even more than he received and save you from the enemies?
Now, you can have Christ as the guardian of your riches.
Let's talk about pleasures.
Those who have ears to hear will understand this: "If you truly love us, entrust us to the one who can return us to you whole and untouched in that place where we can remain with you forever.
In this life, if we wish to engage in your service, having tested it here, we will completely deny the service of our work there.
Meanwhile, let us serve those who are dying, for the days of mortals have been shortened so that we can serve the immortals forever."
As it is written in Matthew 24:22: "For the sake of the elect, the days will be shortened, so that our service is not long."
We do indeed serve the unjust in a hurry: we serve the impious, wicked, and shameful not willingly, but because of him who subjected us.
However, we will be freed from the slavery of corruption and called back to the freedom of the glory of the children of God.
Therefore, all delight saved for the future life is not lost; just as hidden treasures are not considered non-existent by the one who buried them in the earth. In fact, the more securely he believes them to be, the more secretly and safely he has placed them.
So, let the abundance of all delights be stored away so they are not touched in this life, which passes away; because if they are used here, they will be lost in that life which never passes away.
Imagine living for a hundred years.
When the final day comes, wouldn't it feel as if it had all just vanished, leaving only the traces of a guest who stayed for just a day?
On the other hand, there's a life that lasts forever, becoming younger and stronger as the years go by, renewing itself from the point where it seems to end.
How truly unfortunate is the person who isn't drawn to the love of such a beautiful life!
Who fears letting go of this life that will fade away, and embracing the one that will never end, where pleasures, delights, riches, and joys begin and never cease.
They start in such a way that they can never possibly end.
The person who doesn't embrace this splendid life not only loses this one but also misses out on the eternal one, as I've mentioned before, and is caught by perpetual death.
Where the flame never dies, the suffering never ends, and punishment is everlasting.
Where fierce angels dwell, arms like dragon heads, eyes firing arrows of flame, teeth like elephants, inflicting pain like scorpion tails.
Their voices roar like lions, their appearance causes both fear and pain, and ultimately, death.
If only death could come in such dire circumstances!
But what's even more bitter is that one lives for this torment, constantly renewed, with limbs repeatedly attacked by serpent bites over and over.
Chapter SixThe Happiness and Glory of the Martyrs.
This is the essence of the struggle, teaching us that the sufferings of martyrdom should be endured with patience.
So, friends, parents, and beloved spouses of the saints, do not call back those you love from death.
Do not lead them from joy to sorrow, from light to darkness.
And do not summon them from eternal rest to everlasting torment.
Doing so is like casting a hook with the devil, inviting a small sweetness that hides inner agony and the death of the soul, wrung out by torment.
Is it not choosing fleeting joys over the rewards of eternal delight, and for a little laughter, subjecting oneself to eternal tears?
We all condemn this in gladiators who willingly offer themselves, considering the pleasures of a single year without thinking about the consequences.
They are tortured by the blows of swords or by the mutual slaughter of their insides.
With their bellies torn open, they present themselves before the people, so that the fat, born of mindless indulgence, is offered for the devil to devour.
With this enemy's plan, they do these things, and by the same plan, the martyrs of God, who are headed for eternal life, are called back.
Those who, to live a few more days, are persuaded to incur perpetual torment and eternal death, which is particularly to be feared, and not to be underestimated.
You might ask: Why does the Christian not fear torment, and why aren't they terrified by the torturer's punishment?
They are not broken by fear or led by pain because they know they are securing the joy of eternal health at the price of temporary pain.
Through momentary tribulation, they reach eternal happiness and everlasting joy.
If this pain is to be feared, if the executioner is to be feared, if the new and exquisite cruelty of the torturer is to be feared, what is more to be feared, more dreadful, and more to be avoided?
Is it that which boils up today and vanishes tomorrow?
That which burns today and cools tomorrow?
Is this pain, which arrives at one moment and departs at another, or is it the kind that never ends, untouched by time and unaffected by age?
This pain is either mild and tolerable or severe, offering a swift end through a noble struggle.
But the agony of the fire, reserved for those who love this life, is more intense than any other torment.
It never ceases and only grows fiercer without any limit.
There is no end; it carries all kinds of punishments, constantly renewing and intensifying, inflamed to burn even more fiercely.
So, let's encourage our loved ones to escape this destruction, and let's prepare ourselves bravely to do the same.
We shouldn't fear enduring bodily pain for a short while if we wish to rejoice with Christ forever.
Let's allow our soul to leave this body with the honor of martyrdom, so we can avoid eternal punishments and reach heavenly delights.
Let's turn our tears into joy, for we shouldn't mourn those we believe will reign with Christ, as if they were dying.
Let's celebrate the victors over enemies, with their foes defeated beneath them.
Let's rejoice with those clothed in the robe of martyrdom and take pride in them becoming heavenly consuls.
Look at the day the tyrant thought he was victorious, yet while capturing, he was captured; while holding, he was bound; while torturing, he was tortured; while mocking, he was mocked; while killing, he was killed.
Now, let's also stir our hearts towards the love of martyrdom so that we can capture him who sought victory through our captivity.
Awakened from a heavy sleep, let's open the eyes of our souls.
Seeing the traps the enemy set for our destruction, we may escape with God's help.
And as the devil and his followers fall into the pit they prepared, we can say with the prophet: "They dug a pit before me, and they themselves have fallen into it" (Psalm 57:6).
Chapter Seven
Through Sebastian's speech and miracles, Zoe and Nicostratus are converted.
23.
As the most blessed Sebastian, dressed in a cloak and belt, was speaking, he was suddenly illuminated by an intense brightness from heaven for nearly an hour.
In this light, seven radiant angels clothed him in a pure white robe, and a young man appeared beside him, offering peace and saying, "You will always be with me."
24. These events occurred in the house of Nicostratus, the Primiscrinius, where Marcellianus and Marcus were held.
Nicostratus had a wife named Zoe.
She had been mute for six years due to a severe illness, though her ability to hear and understand remained, even improving.
Upon grasping everything Sebastian said and witnessing the miraculous light, Zoe, while others were amazed and trembling, gestured reproachfully at those who doubted such clear evidence.
She fell to her knees, pleading with him through gestures.
Saint Sebastian, realizing she couldn’t voice the secrets of her heart, inquired about her silence and learned it was caused by her illness.
Blessed Sebastian then declared, "If I am a true servant of Christ, and if everything this woman heard from me and believed is true, let my Lord Jesus Christ command her to speak again, just as He opened the mouth of His prophet Zechariah."
He made the sign of the cross on her mouth.
At the sound of Saint Sebastian's voice, the woman cried out loudly, "Blessed are you, and blessed is the word from your mouth; and blessed are those who believe in Christ, the Son of the living God, through you.
For I have seen with my own eyes an angel coming to you from heaven, holding a book from which all the words of your speech were read."
Blessed are those who believe in everything you have said, and cursed are those who doubt or question even one word of all they have heard.
Just as the dawn dispels all the darkness of the night and brings back the light that the blind night had denied, so do your words dispel all darkness and the blindness of ignorance, restoring clarity to the eyes of those who truly believe.
For me, it not only drove away the darkness of disbelief but also opened the door of my speech, which had been closed for six years.
Seeing this, Nicostratus, her husband, recognized the great power of Christ celebrated in his wife.
He began to fall at her feet and ask for forgiveness for having kept the Saints of God in chains by imperial and official order.
Removing the iron chains from their hands, he embraced their knees and pleaded with them to leave, saying, "Oh, how blessed I would be if I could be bound for your salvation!
Perhaps by shedding my blood, I would be cleansed and escape that death of eternal punishments, reaching the life that God has graciously revealed to us through my master Sebastian."
Chapter Seven
The Steadfastness of Marcellian and Marcus, Address to the Newly Baptized.
When he asked Marcellian and Marcus to leave, they responded:
"If you've received the glory of faith, which you never had before, how can we abandon the faith we've known since childhood and offer you our cup of suffering, which we can extend to you but never give away?"
Christ is rich in all things, and with His abundant generosity, He offers greater blessings to everyone who comes to Him than they ever ask for.
If, as unbelievers, you were granted the gift of recognizing the light of truth, how much more will you receive now that you believe?
Divine mercy is always ready to offer you everything freely, multiplying the gift of grace in each person according to the depth of their faith.
Your faith began with teaching, and in just an hour, you've grasped what years of learning can hardly provide.
No memory of parents holds you back from believing.
No tender affection for your children and family calls you back.
You have suddenly turned away from what you always loved and now seek what you never knew.
Having embarked on unknown paths, you've swiftly reached Christ, and in your hearts, you're already in heaven because you sought no earthly comforts.
Oh, the incomparable testimony of your actions!
Oh, what an admirable example of virtue!
You haven't yet been led to Christ through the sacred waters of baptism, nor have you taken the signs of initiation; yet you already take up arms for the true King, freeing His soldiers from iron chains, willing to be killed in place of the condemned.
Upon hearing this, everyone was moved to tears of repentance for their past beliefs, and Marcus said:
"Learn, dearest parents, and let your conjugal affection, oh spouses, learn to oppose the shield of virtues against the devil's attacks and all temptations of carnal desires."
"Do not yield to the enemy in the tyrant's army, but fight more fiercely, hold your ground, and bravely reach the King."
Let them rise as much as they want, and let the followers of demons rage; they can inflict any punishments on our bodies they choose, but they cannot conquer the soul that fights for the truth of faith.
Wounds received for the Emperor make soldiers more glorious: in this, the devil now rages in the fury of his tyranny, knowing he can be tormented by the trophy of your perseverance.
Therefore, he inflicts torments so that his hope does not perish: he threatens death to instill fear; he promises life only to take it away; he offers security just to remove it.
This is the entire cunning of war, the plan of deceit, to rescue the body from punishments and to subjugate the soul with vices.
We, on the other hand, must strive not to yield to the enemy, to disregard the body, and to aid the soul.
Why should the bravest leaders turn away from the most wretched soldiers and fail in a battle where they can be victors?
Or why should they fear death, knowing it is the nature of man, not a punishment?
Why, I ask, should they fear death, who believe this life is false and that true life is only found by rejecting this false and fleeting life from their soul, which commands nothing but sins to its lovers, urges wicked deeds, imposes crimes, and demands nothing else from its lovers except that they do not think at all about eternal life and despair of the kingdom of God to come?
Now let us see the situations and dangers the servant girl faces, so that, proving she cannot govern herself, we may remove our servitude from her domination and find another worthy of service.
How many of her lovers have been suddenly crushed by heavy ruin, struck by the crash of the sky, burned by lightning, destroyed by shipwrecks, covered by chaos, swallowed by Charybdis, or slain by the sword!
And the unfortunate, losing this life with their pains, cannot find that other life at all!
For indeed, torture does not lead to that life, but reason does.
Ultimately, by the same kind of punishment, eternal salvation is given to the innocent, while punishment is imposed on the guilty.
Chapter Nine
Others Converted by Sebastian Along with Prisoners.
29.
As Marcus continued with these matters, everyone present began to give thanks to God.
They were all in tears, repenting for having valued the love of the flesh over the love of God.
They regretted trying to dissuade the saints from the courage needed for martyrdom.
When everyone who had come to deceive the saints began to believe in Christ, Nicostratus, along with his wife, insisted, saying:
"I will not eat or drink until the mystery of the Christian faith is taught to me."
Saint Sebastian responded:
"Change your status and become more of a servant of Christ than a prefect.
Here’s my advice:
gather all those held in prison, bound in chains, and confined, into one place.
Once you've done this, I'll bring in a bishop of the holy law, so that everyone who wishes to believe can receive the sacrament of the mystery.
If the devil has tried to take the saints away from Christ, shouldn’t we, with piety, care for those whom the devil has unjustly claimed and restore them to their Creator?"
Nicostratus replied:
"How can sacred things be entrusted to the wicked and criminal?"
Saint Sebastian explained:
"Our Savior chose to present himself to us for sinners and revealed the mystery by which all sins and crimes can be removed, and all virtues of the Lord can be bestowed.
As you begin your conversion, offering this service to Christ will earn you the reward of martyrdom—the crown of unfading virtues, bringing eternal joy."
Hearing this, Nicostratus went to Claudius the Clerk and ordered all the prisoners to be brought to his house, saying:
"Since everyone is to be examined at the next session, I want them to be present with the Christians who are with me, so that no one is missing from the prefect's examination."
30.
So, when everyone was brought to the chief jailer's house, chained and bound, the man of God, Sebastian, spoke to them like this:
"If the devil's wrongdoings give way to divine virtues, your guilt is removed from death and recalled from fleeting pleasures.
The unjust enemy, through his agents, tried to overthrow the spirits of Christ's soldiers, who had reached great heights of virtue, and drag those at the peak of perfection into the darkness of the underworld.
That's why the enemy's spirit was stirred to fight, so we might take you, whom the enemy had captured, from his grasp and return you to your Creator.
The devil is neither your lord, creator, nor father: but God is proven to be your Father, Lord, and Creator.
And if you left Him to go to the enemy, who was against you to the point of leading you to eternal death and bringing you to this deadly end, how much more should you return to Him, who gave His only Son to suffering and death to free us from eternal suffering and perpetual death?"
As Saint Sebastian continued with these and similar words, they all fell to the ground in tears, began to express their heartfelt groans on bended knees, and cried out in repentance for their sins and wicked actions.
They shed bitter tears and, united in voice, declared their wish to believe in Christ.
Then Blessed Sebastian ordered all of them to be released from their chains.
Chapter Ten
Everyone Prepared for Baptism by Polycarp.
After this, Saint Sebastian went to Polycarp, the priest, who was hiding due to the persecution, and shared everything that had happened.
Upon hearing this, Saint Polycarp thanked God and, together with him, went to the house of Nicostratus, the chief secretary.
Seeing the crowds of believers, he greeted them with great joy and said:
Blessed are all of you who have heard the voice of our Lord Jesus Christ saying:
Come to me, all you who labor and are burdened, and I will give you rest.
Take my yoke upon you, and learn from me, for I am gentle and humble in heart; and you will find rest for your souls.
For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.
Matthew 11:28 and following.
Therefore, our brothers, who have not yet been washed by the waters of baptism and made the most beloved children of Almighty God through consecration, because you tried to dissuade the most blessed soldiers of Christ from their holy purpose, it was necessary for you to do penance so that through it you might come to forgiveness.
But now, since you have reached such glory that you even desire gladly to run towards the very passion you once wished to avoid, and embrace it willingly, know that you have reached forgiveness and touched the prize.
This is an ancient craft of Christ.
For he whom he deemed worthy to be a chosen vessel and wanted to give as a teacher to the nations, who not only tried to turn the faithful away from their pious purpose but also stoned those unwilling to depart from Christ; the Lord himself granted us this man as an apostle and gave us Paul from Saul, making an apostle from an apostate, and gave his Church a teacher from a persecutor.
He who was once the author of persecution became a lover of suffering: and he who once rejoiced in the afflictions of others later rejoiced in his own persecutions.
He, who showed this power through his apostle back then, is the same one who now, from the depths of the underworld and the jaws of dragons, has rescued your souls from captivity.
He has opened the gates of eternal life for you as you return from darkness to light.
Because all the demons, the children of darkness, are saddened, and all the holy angels, the children of light, rejoice, let each of you come forward and give your name.
As today progresses until evening with fasting, find the right time for the joyful sacrament of baptism.
It is fitting that light, leaving the mortal world, should come to our immortal souls, so that we, who have been in the darkness of this world, may be washed and cleansed by the water of sanctification and clothed in purity, eagerly going to Christ.
As Saint Polycarp continued with these and similar words, everyone rejoiced, each hurrying to offer their name before being asked.
Chapter Eleven
Baptized catechumens, including Claudius and his sons.
During these events, Claudius, the clerk, visited Nicostratus, the chief secretary, where everything was unfolding.
He told Nicostratus, "The prefecture is quite disturbed because you had the accused transferred to your house."
For this reason, the prefect has ordered you to appear before him.
Be prepared to explain your actions if questioned."
When Nicostratus went to the prefect and was asked why he moved the prisoners to his home, he answered, "By your excellency's command, I brought these Christians into my house to keep them in custody."
I associated them with the accused to instill fear of suffering so that, even if not by their own choice, they might be persuaded through others' experiences to comply."
The prefect, pleased to hear this, dismissed him, saying, "I will ensure you are richly rewarded by their parents when their children return safely because of you."
Back at his house with Claudius, Nicostratus, the chief secretary, recounted everything.
He shared how Saint Sebastian, despite being a friend of the emperors, was a devout Christian and excellent in divine teaching.
He told how Saint Sebastian had brought back the souls of Christians through his encouragement and convincingly taught that this life is fleeting and deceptive.
Thus, while it seems to be secure, it is taken away.
He also described how a sudden heavenly light illuminated him and enabled his wife, who had been mute for six years, to speak.
After Nicostratus shared these stories with Claudius, Claudius fell at his feet, saying, "From my deceased wife, I have two sons: one suffers from dropsy, and the other has various wounds."
I beg you to have them healed."
I am certain that the one who made your wife speak after six years can also, if he wishes, restore health to my children.
With that, she hurried home and brought her two sons back with her.
Bringing them into the house where the holy men of God were, she placed them at their feet, saying:
"There is no doubt left in my heart. I believe wholeheartedly that Christ, whom you worship, is the true God. I've brought my two children here, believing they can be saved from the brink of death through you."
All the holy men of God replied to her:
"All who are afflicted with illness today will be healed as soon as they become Christians."
When Claudius declared that he believed and wished to become a Christian, Saint Polycarp asked everyone to state their names.
First to speak was Tranquillinus, the father of Marcellian and Marcus. Following him were six of their friends: Ariston, Crescentianus, Eutychianus, Urbanus, Vitalis, and Justus; then Nicostratus, the chief clerk, and his brother Castorius, and Claudius, the clerk.
Next were Claudius’s sons, Felicissimus and Felix. After them were Marcia, the mother of Marcellian and Marcus, along with their wives and children; also Symphorosa, Claudius’s wife, and Zoe, Nicostratus’s wife.
Following them, the entire household of Nicostratus, totaling thirty-three people of various ages and sexes, and then all those who had been imprisoned and brought from the filth of the prison, totaling sixteen people.
Consequently, all these sixty-eight people were baptized by Saint Polycarp, the presbyter, and welcomed by Saint Sebastian. The women were cared for by Beatrix and Lucina.
First, Claudius’s sons, one suffering from dropsy and the other covered in wounds, were immediately healed when they were baptized in the name of the Holy Trinity.
They emerged from the font completely healthy, with no trace of their previous illnesses.
After them, the little ones were...
Marcellianus and Marcus were so severely afflicted with gout and hand disease that, as previously mentioned, they could barely be carried by others.
While they were removing his clothes, and he said he was being tortured by unbearable pain, Polycarp the priest asked him:
"Tranquillinus, if you truly believe in your heart that the only Son of God, the Lord Jesus Christ, can bring you salvation and forgive all your sins, declare it with your own mouth."
Tranquillinus replied:
"I hope for and believe that my sins will be forgiven. Furthermore, even if I suffer pain after the sanctification of this baptism, I will not doubt the faith of Christ. For I have tested and wholeheartedly believed, and have agreed in my mind, that the Son of God is the Lord Jesus Christ, who can grant salvation to both souls and bodies, and who can call us from eternal death to everlasting life."
When he said this loudly, all the saints wept for joy and prayed to the Lord that the fruits of his faith might be shown. Therefore, Saint Polycarp, the confessor and priest, as soon as he anointed him with the oil of chrism, asked him again if he believed in the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit. As soon as he replied, "I believe," his hands, which were knotted, were freed, and his knees and the soles of his feet were restored to such health that he descended into the font with renewed feet like a little child, shouting and saying:
"You are the one true God, whom this wretched world does not know."
After he was baptized in this order, all were baptized as was fitting. For the ten days that remained of the delay they were granted, they continued in the praises of God, spending days and nights in hymns and songs. They prepared their spirits as faithful soldiers to fight for the name of Christ in the battle of martyrdom, so that even among women and little children the love for martyrdom was fervent, and they prepared each other for the confession of the holy name against the diabolical forces.
Chapter Twelve
The Errors of the Gentiles Refuted by Tranquillinus in the Presence of Chromatius, Prefect of the City.
When the allotted days of delay had passed, Agrestius Chromatius, the prefect of Rome, called upon Tranquillinus, the father of Marcellianus and Marcus, to meet with him.
He asked about the decision regarding his sons, to which Tranquillinus responded, "I can't thank you enough for your kindness."
"If your careful judgment hadn't prevailed, I would've lost my sons, and they wouldn't have had a father."
"Everyone who shares the love of a parent rejoices with me, and love compels them."
"I also believe your excellency shares in my joy, for life was given back to those who were about to die, joy was restored to the anxious, and peace returned to the troubled."
Then the prefect, thinking that his sons intended to worship idols, said, "On the appointed day, let your sons offer incense to the gods."
"By doing this, you will remain unharmed with your sons, and they will be spared for you."
Upon hearing this, Tranquillinus said, "Most illustrious among men, if you weigh the judgment concerning me and my sons fairly, you'll see that this Christian name holds great virtue."
The prefect responded, "You are insane, Tranquillinus."
Tranquillinus replied, "I was indeed lost in madness, both in soul and body; but once I believed in Christ, I regained health in both."
The prefect remarked, "It seems now I am known to have granted your wicked sons a reprieve, and instead of correcting their errors, they have ensnared you with them."
Tranquillinus responded, "By your glory, examine what is truly called error and see which deeds bear that name."
The prefect asked, "Tell me, what deeds are called by the name of error?"
Tranquillinus explained, "The first error is to abandon the path of life and willingly walk the path of death."
The prefect inquired, "And what is the path of death?"
Tranquillinus said: Doesn't it seem to you like a path of death to call dead people divine and worship their images made of wood and stone?
The Prefect said: So, are the gods we worship not truly gods?
Tranquillinus said: They are far from being gods; public records show how poorly they were born, how unjust, cruel, and wicked their parents were, how deceitfully they lived, and how miserably they died.
Was there no God in heaven before Saturn ruled over Crete and ate the flesh of his own children, or did Crete have a king, and the heavens had no God?
Anyone who thinks Jupiter, his son, ruled with thunderbolts is greatly mistaken, as he was merely mortal, ruled by malice and lust.
Who did he not pursue, showing no mercy even to his own father?
What disgrace did he not commit, taking his own sister as his wife?
Every day, we read in the forum, on the streets, in houses, everywhere, that the foul Juno boasts of being both sister and wife: and the most shameful and incestuous honor of the abducted Ganymede is not denied by Jupiter's worshippers.
Therefore, you are not mistaken, noble man, to worship those whom Roman laws condemn for their deeds, and having forsaken the Almighty God who reigns in heaven, you say to a stone, "You are my god," and to wood, "Help me"?
The Prefect said: Since you began to blaspheme the gods and depart from their worship, the Roman world has suffered various disasters.
Tranquillinus replied: That is not true.
If you review the decades recorded by Livy, you will find that while offering incense to Jupiter, twenty-three thousand young men of the Roman army fell in a single day.
And you're aware that the Senones Gauls even occupied the Capitol and mocked the entire Roman force.
The Roman world endured various famines, countless plagues, captivities, and bloodshed before men worshiped one God.
Since believers started worshipping the invisible and true God, the Roman Empire has enjoyed greater peace.
However, the unfortunate part is that this God, who provides these blessings, is not recognized; instead, people attribute what the Creator provides to His creation.
The Prefect said: If we are to worship the one who benefits humanity, then none other than the sun should be considered a god.
As its appearance revitalizes the earth, bringing forth the seeds it holds and nurturing the grains to grow on the stalk.
The sun provides light, restoration, and strength to all the essentials of our well-being.
Tranquillinus responded: This is a huge mistake.
If someone provides for their clients through a servant, it would be foolish to neglect the provider and honor the servant.
To illustrate this, when ships deliver supplies to the Romans, do we thank the ships instead of the rulers?
If people attribute what is delivered not to the sailors but to the commanders, how much more should we give thanks to God alone?
By His command, these elements serve all our needs, and the sun itself sets over the land and sea at day's end and rises again with the dawn.
Chapter Thirteen
Explanation of the Incarnation to a Gentile.
The Prefect asked: If you worship one invisible God, do you not also worship Christ, whom the Jews crucified?
Tranquillinus replied: Your questions would be valid if you were open to believing.
For those who refuse to believe, everything they reject seems pointless.
Once a person's will goes astray, they want everything they criticize to be criticized by others, and everything they praise to be universally praised.
However, a wise person seeks to offer criticism or praise based on true merit.
The Prefect inquired: I am asking about your Christ.
If you worship what cannot be seen with the eyes, don't you worship Christ, who was seen, heard, questioned, and is recorded to have endured all human frailties in his suffering?
Tranquillinus explained: Listen to this analogy for clarity:
Imagine seeing your ring with a precious gem fall into a sewer or get covered in filth.
You send your servants to retrieve it, but if they can't and end up dirtying themselves, you might remove your fine clothes, put on a servant's outfit, go into the sewer, and personally retrieve both the ring and the gem.
You would then celebrate with friends, rejoicing that the ring and gem were saved from the filth.
The Prefect asked: How does this analogy relate?
Tranquillinus answered: It illustrates that we worship one invisible God.
The Prefect queried: What represents the gold?
And what is the gem rolling in the filth?
Tranquillinus replied: The gold represents the human body, and the gem is the soul, which resides within the body.
Together, the body and soul form one person, just as gold and a gem together make one ring.
However precious the ring might be to you, a person is far more precious and cherished by Christ a hundred times over.
You sent your servants to rescue the ring from the filth, but they couldn't retrieve it.
Similarly, God sent His prophets from heaven to speak to us and rescue humanity from the filth of this world, but they couldn't succeed by any means.
You took off your fine clothes, dressed yourself in a servant's attire, and went down into the sewer, reaching into the filth to free the ring.
Likewise, the majesty of His Divinity set aside its splendor, without abandoning the heavenly realm, and took on the form of our human body.
Descending from heaven into the sewer of this world, He reached into the filth of our sufferings; and accepting the suffering that our deeds deserved upon Himself, He restored us to the glory of His hands.
For those of us who wallowed in the world's filth due to disbelief are cleansed by faith, and like your ring, we are restored by divine hands.
Could your servants, who denied you as their master while seeing you in a servant's attire, not have been killed as rebels?
In the same way, those who deny Christ as their Lord for humbling Himself from majesty and taking on the form of a servant will not be able to escape the punishment of eternal fire.
Therefore, for us who believe in Him, the water of the eternal fountain helps us, so that eternal fire is conquered by the eternal fountain, and disbelief is overcome by faithfulness.
The Prefect said: As I see it, you did not request a delay to remove your sons from this course of action, but to bring these old wives' tales to our court.
Tranquillinus replied: The disciples of Christ do not plan what to say in front of judges.
For He warned us by saying: When they hand you over to the authorities of this world because of My name, do not worry about how or what you should speak, for what you should say will be given to you by God at that time.
For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of God who speaks in you.
Matthew 10:19.
Therefore, I did not find my Creator by thinking, but by believing.
And though I was crippled and shaken by gout and joint pain, as soon as I believed in Christ, I regained the health of all my limbs as if I were a child.
So, it is clear to my mind that the one who renewed me is the same who created me.
Just as he restored my body, he also promised to restore my soul after this life, provided I am not swayed by the doubts or fears of human threats.
Instead, I must endure in confessing his name, keeping the faith whole that God helped me find.
The Prefect said: "Tranquillinus, are you unaware of the great anger of the most invincible emperors against Christians?
That is why you proceed without fear, as if you are safe."
Tranquillinus replied: "It is foolish to fear human anger more than divine.
If we were to come among barking dogs and they began to attack us with their senseless fury, could they take away from us our rational human nature, while they remain dogs, irrational, and insane?
In the same way, those who are angry with us for believing rightly can indeed rage and inflict unjust punishments, but they can never take away from our hearts the belief that Jesus Christ is our Lord and Creator, and we rejoice that he is our Redeemer and Restorer."
Then the Prefect ordered him to be taken back to the records, saying: "I will hear you at the next session."
Chapter Fourteen
Chromatius, the city prefect, is instructed in the faith.
After this, he summoned him and arranged for him to be brought secretly at night.
Offering him an enormous amount of gold, he said:
"Show me the remedy that restored your health."
Tranquillinus replied:
"Understand that those who think they can buy or sell God's grace will face His great wrath.
If you wish to be freed from your gout pain, believe in Christ, the Son of God, and you will be healed. Just as I am today, you will be saved.
I was once barely able to stand, bound by pain in all my joints for eleven years, and needed others to feed me.
As soon as I believed that Christ is the true God, I regained my health and am well because I recognized Him as my savior."
Then the prefect dismissed him, saying:
"Bring to me the one who made you a Christian, so that if he promises me health, I too may become a Christian."
Tranquillinus immediately went to Saint Polycarp the priest and told him everything.
He led him secretly into the house and presented him to the prefect.
The prefect said:
"Even though the harsh judgments of the rulers oppose Christians, in hopes of regaining my health, I will give you whatever it takes, up to half of my family's wealth, if my joints are freed from this pain."
Saint Polycarp, smiling, said:
"The Lord Jesus Christ can open your eyes and show you that He is the healer of your body.
Offering money does not cure those in pain but rather brings an incurable disease upon themselves."
The prefect asked:
"Tell me, then, what should I do to achieve what I hope for."
Polycarp replied:
"If you believe with all your heart, as Tranquillinus did, you will be saved."
The prefect asked:
"Explain how I should believe."
Saint Polycarp then instructed him to fast for three days.
He invited Saint Sebastian to join him, and together, they fasted for three days and nights.
With tears, they prayed for the Lord to reveal the faith of His name for the salvation of the one who wished to believe.
Chapter Fifteen
The Idols Broken by Chromatius.
49. When the appointed third day arrived, they hurried to the prefect's house.
Upon entering, they greeted him, saying, "Peace to your faith."
He warmly returned the greeting and invited them to sit beside him, saying, "The reasoning from Tranquillinus’ mouth is confirmed by what I see with my own eyes.
I see him completely healthy now, though he was previously crippled by gout and joint pain.
When I asked him about the remedy that healed him, he responded:
'While I placed my faith in idols, I suffered from severe and excessive illness; but once I learned about the one God in heaven through the testimony of Christians, I renounced all that I had worshiped without reason and committed my soul's faith to Christ.
As soon as I confessed that the one true God reigns in heaven, all the health I had lost for eleven years returned to me, and all weakness instantly left me.'
I heard this with my ears, verified it with my eyes, and believed it with my heart.
Now, I ask you to do for me what you did for Tranquillinus so that I may regain my health."
50.
Polycarp, the priest, said, "If the temporary pains are unbearable for the human soul, what will it do with those pains that never end and offer no relief?
These pains are a likeness of those eternal pains, and the difference between a living fire and its picture is like the difference between the pains the body experiences now and those the soul will endure if it lives this present life unaware of its Creator.
Therefore, join us in considering those eternal pains and be concerned about that punishment, with its ever-burning fire and ever-consuming worm."
51.
Then Chromatius, the prefect of Rome, along with his only son Tiburtius, declared his faith, saying, "In this, you can be certain of my faith, as I also wish for my son to become a Christian with me."
Saint Sebastian said:
"Don't hope to become a Christian just to heal your body.
Instead, do it with the hope of eternal life,
and purify your mind to understand the truth.
Without recognizing your Creator,
you won't find the salvation you seek."
Chromatius said:
"Don't we see that even the simplest and most uneducated people are Christians?
Among a thousand men, few can even master words.
Could they all have reached such understanding when they became Christians?"
Saint Sebastian replied:
"Your response actually supports our point.
From the beginning, God favored farmers and shepherds,
and towards the end, He chose not scholars or orators,
but fishermen and simple people, entrusting them with His knowledge."
Chromatius said:
"Why then must I first recognize my Creator
if I cannot find salvation without doing so?"
Saint Sebastian said:
"Because you have worshiped many gods and goddesses.
Unless you expel these from your heart, destroy their images,
and recognize the one true God, you cannot find life and salvation."
Chromatius said:
"Then tell me who the one true God is."
Saint Sebastian replied:
"If you send your servant to fetch water, when he reaches the fountain,
he first checks if any dirt is in the jug,
and he won't fill it with water unless it's clean;
how can we offer you the fountain of truth unless you remove all the dirt and filth of idols first?"
Chromatius said:
"And how can I rid myself of these things?"
Saint Sebastian said:
"Allow us to break all the stone idols in your house,
burn the wooden ones, melt the golden, silver, or bronze ones,
and give their value to the needy."
Chromatius said:
"And once you've done these things, what benefit will I gain?"
Saint Sebastian said:
"You will quickly regain the health of all your nerves, which are currently bound.
It will be as if you never felt any pain, and you will start running with ease.
You will realize that you loved the gods who were enemies of your well-being,
but this is your true Father, who will restore and save you once you find knowledge and worship of Him."
Chromatius said:
"Do not lower yourselves to this insult; instead, I will command my servants, and they will break everything."
Saint Sebastian said:
"If those who are doubtful, timid, and unfaithful break them,
the devil will find an opportunity to harm them due to their negligence.
As soon as they are harmed, the unfaithful will claim they suffered because they broke the idols.
For if one does not have armor, they are not protected from the blows of arrows.
A skilled hand uses a helmet, shield, and spear in battle, gaining courage from the protection of armor and the strength of striking, and does not turn away.
Similarly, the soldiers of God, protected by the shield of faith and covered by the armor of Christ, having the helmet of faith and salvation,
are safe to enter the fight.
They fight fiercely and win bravely because they battle tirelessly against the invisible enemy day and night,
and they are protected in all their limbs, armed more by faith than by iron."
Chromatius said:
"Let God's will and yours be done."
Then Saint Polycarp the priest and Blessed Sebastian prepared themselves and prayed,
and after prayer, breaking over 200 idols, they began to give thanks to their God.
Chapter Sixteen
Chromatius is healed after the instruments of judicial astrology are broken.
After this, they approached Chromatius and said:
"You should have been healed when we destroyed the idols, unless you still have some doubts in your mind.
We believe that either something remains unbroken, or if everything has indeed been destroyed, let us know what you're still holding onto mentally."
Then Chromatius replied, "I have a room made entirely of glass, where all the teachings of the stars and mathematical mechanics are intricately designed.
It is known that my father, Tarquinius, spent over 200 pounds of gold on its creation."
To this, Saint Sebastian responded, "If you wish to keep this intact, you're only harming yourself."
Chromatius asked, "Why?
Is it because mathematics or star charts are used for sacrifices, when they merely track the courses of months and years with precision over time?
The phases of the moon are predicted by simple calculations, reason, and computations."
Saint Polycarp the priest explained, "There are signs like Leo, Capricorn, Sagittarius, Scorpio, and Taurus, the moon in Aries, the hour in Cancer; a star in Jupiter, tropical in Mercury, Mars in Venus.
All of this is recognized as an art hostile to God.
Christians reject these practices so thoroughly that they not only avoid engaging with them, but they also refuse to let their minds be occupied with such nonsense.
These are all false and deceptive: they may resemble truth but are not the truth itself."
Chromatius then asked, "What about when they sometimes predict the future?"
Saint Sebastian replied, "We have learned from Christ that all these things are completely vain and false, which we will now explain to you more clearly."
Imagine calling a math teacher over today, and telling them about the tough challenges you faced back then, asking what stars might have caused this misfortune.
They would likely say that a troublesome Mars was in control, or Saturn was in retrograde, or your year was directly affected, or critical moments aligned against you, or there was a conjunction with malice, or it was hidden, or in a certain pattern, or an unchanging course surrounded you in the stars.
After explaining these things, they try to give you a reasonable explanation and prove it.
Now, go ask another mathematician, and tell them those times were full of good fortunes for you.
You'll see them immediately provide endless reasonable patterns, proving that good things should have happened to you then.
They hold a unified view, drawing from various sources, using it to say whatever they want.
Since they can't fully predict the future, they call them critical moments, uncertain safe havens of the nature of things.
People born at different times perished in the same shipwreck, and those born at the same hour, one ends up begging while another rises to power.
In one battle, countless fall, and in one day, or even one moment, in one house, two women—one very chaste, the other becomes unchaste.
Comparing their stars' merit, neither should blame the unchaste nor praise the chaste.
Certainly, lawmakers and leaders punish those who break the laws, which is why courts, judges, and laws exist, so the righteous are rightly praised, and the unjust justly punished.
And don't think this is idle talk—you don't yet consider yourself saved.
If you completely rejected the enemy of humanity's ceremonies, you would have found the truth within yourself.
Upon hearing this, Chromatius said: That true God is proven to have worshippers like you.
Every word you speak is filled with wisdom, so much so that even animals are drawn to true understanding.
Therefore, the decorations in my house, which I seemed to have accepted, should be removed to ensure they don't hinder my salvation.
I believe, and have faith, that if I completely distance myself from anything that Christianity's laws abhor and prohibit, I can achieve both present and future salvation.
Upon hearing this, his son Tiburtius said, "I will not allow this precious, exceptional, and incomparable work to be destroyed for any reason. However, so that I don't seem to oppose my father's salvation, let's bring two furnaces and light them in front of the bedroom door. If it is destroyed by them and my father doesn't regain his health, both can be thrown into the burning furnaces." Hearing this, his father forbade it. Yet, the saints not only did not fear the promised destruction but also firmly encouraged the preparation of the furnaces.
Then they approached all the crystal and glass idols and all that mechanical work. Suddenly, as the saints were breaking them, a young man appeared before Chromatius. His face shone with a fiery glow, and he said, "My Lord Jesus Christ, whom you have believed in, has sent me so that you may regain the health of all your limbs." At his words, Chromatius was restored to perfect health and tried to chase after the young man to kiss his feet. But the young man said, "Be careful not to touch me, because the sanctification of baptism has not yet cleansed you from the filth of idols."
Witnessing this, his son Tiburtius threw himself at the feet of Saint Polycarp. Chromatius, the prefect, held onto the feet of Saint Sebastian, and together they cried out, "Christ is the true God, true and all-powerful, the only-begotten Son of God, whom you, His good servants, proclaim."
Chapter Seventeen
The Baptism of Chromatius and Tiburtius.
Then Blessed Sebastian said to Chromatius:
As you know, I hold the rank of leader of the first cohort.
However, I decided long ago not to dedicate myself to the service of man.
I only wanted to remain hidden under the cloak, so that I could guide wavering minds and strengthen those who were doubtful, ensuring they would not yield to the pains of suffering, those whom faith had made warriors.
But you, bearing the pinnacle of vast power, cannot remove yourself from the spectacles, nor be absent from judging matters.
Therefore, pretend to be ill and ask for a successor, so that you can be free from worldly occupations and receive the teachings of the future life.
With a second birth, you may again become a child to eternal parents.
On the same day, he sent to his friends in the palace, through whom he received testimonial letters, and he embraced the trial of divine service before he was baptized.
Why should I mention how full of faith he was, and how keen his mind stood against the claims of the unbelievers?
The following passage makes it clear.
From the beginning, when he was washed by the waters of the holy font, the faith of his mind shone clearly.
Asked if he believed, he said: I believe.
Asked again if he renounced all idols, he replied: I renounce.
The priest's questioning continued, asking if he renounced all sins, and he said:
This you should have inquired first, before I entered these halls of the heavenly king.
Now, however, I will clothe myself again, not yet baptized, so that I may first forgive everyone with whom I am angry and return all promissory notes to my debtors.
If I have taken anything by force, I will order it to be returned in full:
I have two concubines after my wife's death, and I will give them dowries and husbands, releasing myself from every bond of servitude, whether private or public, of my actions:
Only then will I promise to renounce all sinful acts and worldly pleasures.
Polycarp the priest says to him: "A more blessed heavenly wave will wash over you when you swiftly fulfill what you choose to do."
The time of Lent is set for those to be baptized, so that during these days, they can learn to renounce all the arts of the enemy and the dealings of the world, if they truly wish to become Christians."
Then Tiburtius, a very wise young man, said: "Father, if time is needed to renounce these matters, I, who was about to take on the business of the forum, will give up the desire to pursue it."
And I, who was going to advocate for the causes of mortals, will embrace Christianity to pursue angelic actions, as I start to be one of those who receive eternal life and become advocates of holiness."
Then blessed Sebastian embraced him. When Saint Polycarp baptized him, he became his godfather.
Therefore, after only a few days, Chromatius renounced all worldly affairs and received the sacred baptism. Along with him, one thousand four hundred souls from his household, both men and women, whom he first freed from the bond of servitude, equipping them with the best gifts, saying:
"Those who begin to have God as their Father should not be slaves of man."
Chapter Eighteen
Chromatius, after stepping down as Prefect of the City, aids Christians during a time of persecution.
At that time, Caius was the pope of Rome, known for his wisdom and virtue, during the reign of Carinus, Diocletian, and Maximian.
Diocletian and Maximian were in the City, while Carinus was with the army in Gaul.
Because of his influence, Diocletian's persecution of Christians began to lessen, as Carinus had friends who respected the Christian faith.
After Carinus was killed in Mainz during the consulship of Maximian and Aquilinus, a severe persecution arose where people could neither buy nor sell unless they offered incense to idols at the marketplace.
Across the islands, villages, and even at fountains, guards enforced this rule, denying purchases and access to water unless sacrifices were made to idols.
With the advice of Saint Caius, Chromatius, a notable figure, welcomed Christians into his home, ensuring none were forced to sacrifice.
However, as the persecution was so intense that he couldn't hide his faith, Chromatius obtained a sacred decree allowing him to stay for health reasons on the Campanian coast, where he had a large estate, offering refuge to any Christian who wished to escape the persecution.
A disagreement arose between Saint Polycarp and Blessed Sebastian about who should remain in the City and who should go with Chromatius, who sheltered many Christians.
As they debated, Pope Caius wisely intervened:
While both of you strive for martyrdom, you must not neglect those who have come to the Lord.
Therefore, my suggestion is that you, brother Polycarp, with your priestly wisdom and knowledge of God, should go to strengthen the believers and support those who are uncertain.
Upon hearing this, he remained calm and accepted the gentle guidance of the Pope with composure.
Then, Sunday, the Lord's day, arrived, and Bishop Caius, while attending to God's matters in Chromatius's house, addressed everyone with these words:
Our Lord Jesus Christ, aware of human frailty, established two paths for believers: confession and martyrdom.
This way, those who feel unable to bear the burden of martyrdom can embrace the grace of confession, supporting the soldiers of Christ who fight in His name.
Therefore, those who wish to accompany our sons Chromatius and Tiburtius, and those who wish to remain with me in this city, should stay.
The distances between lands do not separate us, as the love of Christ binds us, and even in your absence, we see you with the eyes of the inner spirit.
After Pope Caius spoke these and similar words, Tiburtius, a distinguished man, exclaimed:
I beg you, father and bishop of bishops, do not let me turn my back on the persecutors.
It is a great joy and desire for me to be killed a thousand times for the true God, to attain the dignity of a life that no successor can take away and no time can end.
Then Saint Caius, rejoicing in his faith, shed tears, praying for all who remained to emerge victorious in the struggle, achieving the triumph of martyrdom.
Chapter Nineteen
The Glorious Deeds of Saints Sebastian, Tiburtius, and Others in the City.
These individuals remained with the venerable Pope Caius: Marcellianus and Marcus, along with their father, the distinguished Tranquillinus.
Also present were the Blessed Sebastian and the young man of remarkable beauty, both in appearance and mind, Saint Tiburtius.
Additionally, there was Nicostratus, one of the chief secretaries, with his brother Castorius, and his wife, named Zoe.
Claudius was there too, with his brother Victorinus and his son Symphorian, who had been cured of dropsy.
These people stayed with Bishop Caius while everyone else left with Chromatius.
He ordained Marcus and Marcellianus as deacons, and their father, Tranquillinus, as a priest.
He appointed Saint Sebastian, who was secretly serving as a soldier for the benefit of many, as a defender of the Church, and made the others subdeacons.
Since there was no safe place to hide, they all stayed with a Christian named Castulus, a palace official.
Castulus lived in a very high and upper part of the palace.
This residence was considered suitable because Castulus himself, along with his entire household, was devoutly Christian.
And since the law concerning sacrifices was causing turmoil everywhere, they hid among those connected to the palace, as no suspicion could fall on them.
So, as mentioned, all these people were staying with the holy Pope Caius at Castulus's place, in the upper parts of the palace, occupied day and night with sighs, tears, fasting, and prayers.
They were asking the Lord to consider them worthy to endure His confession and to be counted among the holy martyrs.
Religious men and women secretly came to visit them, receiving various healing graces from the Saints.
Strengthened by the firmness of true faith and grounded in the foundation of virtues, the grace of healings followed them.
Even the eyes of the blind were opened by their prayers.
The sick were healed, and demons were driven out from possessed bodies.
Meanwhile, Blessed Tiburtius came across a man who had fallen from a height, shattering his head and all his limbs.
His family, recognizing him as their son, were preparing for his burial.
As they wept, he said to them, "Let me pray over him; perhaps he will regain his health." When they gave him space, he approached and slowly recited the Lord's Prayer and the Creed over his wounds. Miraculously, his bones, head, and all his insides were made whole, as if nothing had happened, and he was restored to health.
After doing these things, he began to leave. However, his parents held him back, saying, "Come and take him as your servant, and we will give you all our possessions with him, because you have given back to us alive the only son we had, who was already dead." He replied, "If you do what I tell you, I will greatly reward the healing of this man."
His parents said to him, "We cannot refuse if you will have us as your servants; rather, we wish it if you judge us worthy." Then, taking their hands, he separated them from the crowds and revealed to them the power of the name of Christ. Seeing their hearts firmly set in the fear of the Lord, he brought them to Pope Caius and said, "Venerable pope and teacher of the divine law, here are those whom Christ has won through me today, in whom my faith, like a young tree, has first borne fruit."
Then Saint Caius the bishop baptized them, that is, the young man with his parents, giving thanks to God.
Chapter Twenty
The Murders of Saints Zoe, Tranquillinus, and Others.
There are too many remarkable deeds that Christ accomplished through them to recount them all.
So, let's explore how each one attained the crown of martyrdom.
The blessed Zoe, while praying at the Apostle's Confession during the feast of the Apostles, was captured by pagan spies and taken to the patron of the Naumachia region.
She was forced to offer incense to a statue of Mars there.
She responded, "You force a woman to sacrifice to Mars to show that your Mars finds pleasure in women.
But he who could strip modesty from even the most shameless Venus cannot defeat me, as I bear the trophy of faith on my forehead.
I do not fight him with my own strength, but trust in the power of my Lord Jesus Christ, and I laugh and scorn both you and him."
The regional patron then sent her to a very dark prison, ensuring for five days that she neither saw light nor received food or drink.
The only voice she heard was the one who had locked her up, saying, "You will die here from hunger, thirst, and blindness unless you promise to offer libations to the gods."
After six days, they reported her situation to the enraged prefect, who ordered her to be hung by her neck and hair from a tall tree, with smoke from manure rising beneath her.
As soon as she was suspended, she gave up her spirit in the confession of the Lord.
They took her body, tied it to a rock, and threw it into the Tiber River, saying, "Let not the Christians take her body and make her a goddess for themselves."
After her martyrdom was celebrated, she appeared in a dream to the blessed Sebastian and revealed how she had accepted the martyrdom of the Lord.
When Saint Sebastian shared this, Saint Tranquillinus exclaimed, "Women are going ahead to the crown; why do we live?"
On the eighth day of the Apostles' feast, he also went down to visit the Confession of Saint Paul.
However, he encountered plots, was captured, and was stoned to death by the people, with his body thrown into the Tiber River.
Similarly, Nicostratus and Claudius, along with Castor, Victorinus, and Symphorian, were searching for the bodies of the Saints along the banks of the Tiber when they were captured by persecutors and taken to the city's prefect.
The judge was Fabian, who urged them to make sacrifices.
For ten days, he tried to persuade them using threats and flattery, but he couldn't sway them at all.
He then reported them to the emperors, who ordered that they be tortured up to three times.
When they didn't yield to the tortures, he ordered them to be thrown into the sea.
Weighted down by heavy burdens, they were cast into the waves and, in a pure place among the waters, they celebrated the crown of martyrdom.
Thus, the unfaithful plotted against the faithful, driven by wicked fury, unable to even bear hearing the name Christian.
Chapter Twenty-One
The Martyrdom of Saint Tiburtius.
Meanwhile, a certain man joined Bishop Saint Caius, pretending to be a Christian.
However, this man was an apostate, deceitful in all his words, and cunning in his actions.
In short, he was often reprimanded by Blessed Tiburtius, a scholarly, noble, and holy man, for styling his hair like a barber, indulging in food, playing during meals, attracting the attention of women, and neglecting fasting and prayers.
He was so fond of sleep that he didn't stay awake during the nightly hymns to God.
As mentioned, while he was sternly reproved by Blessed Tiburtius for these behaviors, he pretended to accept the advice calmly and plotted to have Saint Tiburtius captured by unbelievers while he was praying.
During this arrest, he also arranged to be taken and brought to the secret chamber of the furious judge.
When they were brought in, Prefect Fabianus asked the man who had deceitfully surrendered himself, "What is your name?"
He replied, "Torquatus."
Fabianus said, "What do you profess?"
Torquatus answered, "I am a Christian."
Fabianus said, "Are you not aware that the most invincible princes have decreed that those who refuse to sacrifice to the gods will be tortured with various punishments?"
Torquatus replied, "This is my teacher, and he has always taught me that whatever he does, I must do."
Fabianus turned to Saint Tiburtius and asked, "Did you hear what Torquatus claims? What do you say to this?"
Saint Tiburtius responded, "Torquatus has long pretended to be a Christian, for the power of that holy name bears it gravely and with difficulty when usurped by those who do not love it.
Indeed, most illustrious man, this Christian name is of divine virtue, followed by those who truly philosophized, who were truly called Christians, and who bravely fought to conquer desires."
Do you believe, most illustrious man, that someone is truly a Christian if they fuss over their hair with fringes, adore the barber, carry themselves with delicate grace, stride improperly, ignore men, and focus more intently on women?
Christ has never considered such people worthy to be his followers.
But since he claims to imitate me here, you will see him proven false in your presence.
For he will now clearly reveal his true nature.
Fabian said: You would be wiser to ensure your own safety and not ignore the decrees of the rulers.
Saint Tiburtius replied: I protect my safety better by rejecting the gods and goddesses and declaring that my sole Lord, Jesus Christ, is God.
Torquatus said: He is not only a cruel Christian himself, but he also persuades many, deceiving them and teaching that all gods are demons; he, along with his companions, practices magical arts and spends day and night with incantations.
Saint Tiburtius responded: A false witness will not go unpunished.
And he said to the judge: This man, whom you see, most illustrious man, consumed by his own malice, joined the Christians only to think about how he might pretend to be one of us; how he might falsely present himself as most faithful to others.
Yet I reproached him for his excessive gluttony, his shame drowned in wine, and the sanctity of the divine name buried.
Drunk, he suffered thirst and hunger while vomiting: he did not eat, drink, and vomit as a Christian, but as a certain Antonian reveler, and now he attacks Christians, accuses them, incites a mild judge against us, hands a sword to an unwilling judge, and urges us to submit to demons.
We see your desire, we see your bloody plans; and with wicked art, we observe the poison of your words in your heart.
Prepare yourself now, most cruel one: take on the role of executioner; claim for yourself and the voice of the judge himself; apply the spikes, hang the Christians, condemn, strike, burn, use all the tortures, you have welcomed us well.
If you threaten exile, know that for philosophers, the whole world is their home.
If it's punishment, we escape the prison of this world.
If it's fire, we overcome even greater challenges through our desires.
Decide what you will; every punishment is worthless to us when a clear conscience is our companion.
Fabian, the prefect, said: Return to your family and be what nature intended you to be.
You were born noble and have fallen to such depths that you're willing to endure punishment, dishonor, and death.
Saint Tiburtius said: O wisest of men, and judge appointed by the Romans!
Because I refuse to worship Venus the prostitute, Jupiter the incestuous, Mercury the deceiver, and Saturn the child-killer, I incur the disgrace of nobility.
And because I worship and revere the one true God, who reigns in heaven, you threaten to torture me.
We do not yield to your persuasion; we do not deny that Christ, the Son of God, came down from heaven to earth so that mankind might ascend from earth to heaven.
Therefore, I trample underfoot all these useless images you worship without reason and submit myself to Almighty God.
Then Fabian ordered burning coals to be spread before his feet and said: Choose one of two things, either sprinkle incense on these coals or walk barefoot over them.
Then Blessed Tiburtius, making the sign of the cross, confidently walked barefoot over them and said to the prefect: Abandon your unbelief and learn that this is the only God, whom we confess to rule over all creation.
Put your hand, if you can, into hot water in the name of your god Jupiter; and if your Jupiter can, let him make it so you do not feel the heat of the burning.
For in the name of my Lord Jesus Christ, it feels to me as if I walk over rose petals because creation serves the command of its Creator.
Fabian said: Who doesn't know that your Christ taught you magic?
Saint Tiburtius said: Be silent, wretch, and do not insult my ears by making me listen to your rabid mouth speaking the sweetly-flowing name of his holiness.
Then, in anger, Fabian pronounced the sentence, declaring:
"Blasphemer of the gods, and guilty of terrible offenses, let him be punished with the sword."
He was led along the Lavican Way, three miles from the City, and after offering a prayer to the Lord,
he was struck once with the sword and passed away.
In that same place, he was buried by a Christian relative.
It is in this place that Christ has continued to grant many blessings to the praise of His name up to the present day.
Chapter Twenty-Two
The killing of Saints Castulus, Marcellianus, and Marcus.
Eighty-three.
After this, Torquatus arranged for Castulus, a chamberlain of the palace and host of the Saints, to be arrested.
When he was captured, he was suspended and questioned three times, but he remained steadfast in his faith in the Lord.
He was then thrown into a pit, and sand was poured over him.
Thus, with the palm of martyrdom, he departed to the Lord.
Eighty-four.
After this, Marcellianus and Marcus were arrested.
Both were tied to a post and had sharp nails driven into their feet.
The extremely cruel Fabianus told them: "You will stand with your feet fixed until you fulfill your duty to the gods."
Then both brothers, nailed to one piece of wood, sang, saying: "Behold how good and pleasant it is for brothers to dwell together in unity."
Fabianus said to them: "Unfortunate and miserable ones, abandon your madness and free yourselves from the torture that awaits you."
Both replied to him: "We have never feasted so well. We have just begun to be fixed in the love of Christ. If only you would allow us to be as we are for as long as we are clothed in this body."
After one day and one night had passed, and they continued in psalms and hymns, he ordered them both to be pierced with spears through their sides where they stood.
Thus, through the glory of martyrdom, they ascended to the heavenly kingdom.
They were also buried on the Appian Way, two miles from the City, in a place called Ad Arenas, because there were sand quarries there, from which the City's walls were constructed.
Chapter Twenty-Three
The Glorious Struggle of Saint Sebastian.
Following these events, Blessed Sebastian was ambushed by conspirators.
As we mentioned, he seemed to be hiding under a cloak while being a truly worthy soldier of Christ.
The prefect reported him to Emperor Diocletian.
Diocletian summoned him and said:
"I have always considered you among the foremost in my palace.
And yet, you have secretly acted against my safety and insulted the gods."
Saint Sebastian replied:
"For your well-being, I have always worshiped Christ, and for the stability of the Roman world, I have always adored Him who is in the heavens, understanding that seeking help from stones is the sign of a foolish and vain mind."
In a fit of anger, Diocletian ordered him to be taken to an open field, tied up like a target for arrows, and commanded archers to shoot him.
The soldiers placed him in the middle of the field and filled him with arrows from all sides until he resembled a hedgehog bristling with arrow strikes.
Believing him to be dead, they left.
That night, the widow of the martyr Castulus, named Irene, went to retrieve and bury his body.
Finding him alive, she took him to her home on a high staircase near the palace, where he fully recovered within a few days.
When all the Christians gathered around him, they urged him to leave.
However, after praying, he descended and stood on the steps of the Temple of Elagabalus.
As the emperors approached, he declared:
"The high priests of the temples are besieging the minds of your empire with deceitful plots, suggesting false accusations against Christians, claiming they are enemies of the Republic.
Yet, through their prayers, the Republic itself improves and grows; they do not cease praying for your empire and the safety of the Roman army."
While he was saying these and similar things, Diocletian asked:
"Are you Sebastian, whom we ordered to be killed with arrows some time ago?"
Saint Sebastian said:
My Lord Jesus Christ has given me the honor of being resurrected to meet you and testify before everyone, that your unjust judgment has led to the persecution of Christ's servants.
Then he ordered him to be taken to the palace's racetrack and whipped until he drew his last breath.
They took his body at night and threw it into the Cloaca Maxima, saying: lest the Christians make a martyr of him.
Then Blessed Sebastian appeared in a dream to a very religious matron named Saint Lucina, saying:
In that sewer, which is next to the circus, you will find my body hanging on a stake.
When you lift it, take it to the catacombs and bury it at the entrance of the crypt near the footsteps of the Apostles.
Then Blessed Lucina went herself with her servants in the middle of the night.
Lifting him, she placed him on her peacock and took him to the place he had instructed, burying him with great care.
Saint Lucina herself did not leave that holy place for thirty days.
After some years, peace was restored to the Church:
as soon as the Church received the glory of peace, she turned her house into a church.
Leaving all her wealth to the rest of the Christians, she made the Church her heir in Christ, who lives and reigns with God the Father and the Holy Spirit, equal in power, forever and ever.
Amen.