First Work: On the Vigils of the Servants of God
Chapter One
It's a good, worthy, and holy thing, and completely appropriate to talk now about the holy vigils and discuss them, especially when this diligent watchfulness is practiced by those who are thoughtful and devout.
The night is dark, providing the necessary darkness for both humans and animals to sleep, so that, with their strength restored through rest, they can handle the day's work while awake.
God, in His goodness, foresaw and established this so that a person, going out to their work and labor until evening, would have a time to rest from hard work and much fatigue.
Psalms 104:23.
Therefore, He made the day for work and the night for rest; and for this, as for everything, we should give thanks to Him who provided it.
However, we know that many people, either to please their superiors or to gain some benefit, set aside part of the night for a little work and consider it a gain that they accomplished something by stealing from their own sleep.
If those who stay awake for physical needs, like food and clothing, are not criticized but praised, how much more should we observe and love the holy vigils, which are so fruitful in spiritual work-prayers, hymns, and readings-so that we may receive a reward from the Lord God?
Chapter Two
There are indeed people who criticize these things, but they are strangers to the Catholic faith and religion.
But this is not surprising.
How can religious things please the wicked and the profane?
If they were pleased, they would be ours, as we are indeed Christians.
If they are offended by the holy and life-giving acts of vigils, without suspecting anything worse about them, they are either lazy, sleepy, old, or infirm.
If they are lazy, let them be ashamed; because the Proverbs of Solomon echo for them: Go to the ant, lazy person, and imitate its ways.
Proverbs Chapter Six, Verse Six.
If they are sleepy, let them wake up, as Scripture proclaims: Lazy person, how long will you sleep?
When will you rise from your slumber?
You sleep a little, sit a little, doze a little, and fold your hands to rest a little.
Then poverty will come upon you like a traveler, and need like a swift runner.
Proverbs Chapter Six, Verses Nine to Eleven.
If they are old, who compels them to stay awake?
Although they should stay awake for their age and pray to the Lord God more earnestly.
Therefore, they should keep vigil while sitting if they cannot stand.
But if they are infirm, they should not blame what they cannot do themselves:
Rather, according to the prophet, they should soak their bed with tears and say: Thus I remembered you on my bed.
Psalm Sixty-Three, Verse Six.
They should also commend those who keep vigil, so that they may help them with their prayers, that they may sometimes deserve to sing to the Lord on their bed of pain, saying: In the morning, I will meditate on you, Lord, because you have been my help.
Psalm Sixty-Three, Verse Seven.
Otherwise, it is foolish and quite foreign to religion to disparage those who run well because we cannot ourselves;
Because even if we cannot, we should not envy but congratulate those who can.
For just as one who consents to wickedness shares in the punishment, so participation in glory is to be hoped for from consent to goodness.
Love crowns some, while holy will brings joy to others.
Certainly, it shouldn't feel burdensome or difficult, even for those with delicate or weak bodies, to dedicate some time to God's service on two nights of the week, specifically Saturday and Sunday.
This serves as a purification after the five days or nights during which we become burdened by physical exhaustion or indulge in worldly activities.
No one should feel ashamed in the pursuit of holiness, as the wicked are not ashamed when committing acts of disgrace.
Rightly, therefore, Scripture in Proverbs says:
"There is a shame that brings sin" Ecclesiasticus Chapter 4, Verse 25.
Being ashamed of doing good is a sin, just as not being ashamed of doing evil is disastrous.
If you are saints, cherish keeping watch; by staying awake to guard your treasure, you keep yourselves holy.
If you are sinners, you should be even more eager to purify yourselves by watching and praying to God. Beat your chests and cry out to the Lord with all your heart, saying:
"Cleanse me from my hidden faults, O Lord, and spare your servant from others" Psalm Chapter 19, Verse 13.
For those who want to be cleansed from hidden sins, I don't understand how they could find delight in being tainted by the same miseries.
Chapter Three
It's time, my dear ones, to talk a bit about the authority, antiquity, and usefulness of vigils.
After all, any task is more willingly undertaken when its benefits are clearly understood.
The practice of vigils is ancient and well-known to all the saints.
The prophet Isaiah calls to the Lord, saying:
"My spirit watches for you in the night, O God, because your commandments are the light upon the earth" (Isaiah 26:9, according to the Septuagint).
David, anointed with royal and prophetic spirit, sings:
"O Lord, God of my salvation, I cried out during the day and in the night before you" (Psalm 88:2).
He also says:
"I remembered your name in the night, O Lord, and kept your law" (Psalm 119:55).
Listen to another voice of the same prophet, which shows both the time and the manner of prayer:
"In the night, lift up your hands in the sanctuary, and bless the Lord" (Psalm 134:2).
And to ensure you don't think only evening hours are called nights, he also says:
"At midnight, I rise to praise you for your righteous judgments" (Psalm 119:62).
Here you have both the specific time and the commitment to rise and praise God, clearly shown.
As I further consider the intention of the saints, something greater and more demanding comes to mind, suggesting something beyond the human condition, when I hear the same prophet singing:
"If I ascend to the bed of my couch: if I give sleep to my eyes, and slumber to my eyelids, or rest to my temples, until I find a place for the Lord, a dwelling for the God of Jacob" (Psalm 132:3).
Who wouldn't be amazed at such devotion of spirit in the love of God; that he completely denied himself sleep, without which human bodies surely fail, until he found a place and temple for the Lord to be built by the king and prophet?
This should strongly remind us that if we ourselves want to be a place for God, and wish to be his dwelling and temple forever, as the Apostle Paul asserts by saying:
"You are the temple of God" (Second Corinthians).
Let's embrace the practice of vigilant love like the saints, so that it won't be said of us:
"They have slept a sleep, and found nothing" Psalm 76:5.
Instead, may each of you joyfully declare:
"In the day of my trouble I sought the Lord; my hands were stretched out in the night without ceasing, and I was not deceived" Psalm 77:2.
"For it is good to give thanks to the Lord, and to sing praises to your name, O Most High; to declare your loving-kindness in the morning, and your faithfulness every night" Psalm 92:1-2.
The saints sang and wrote of such noble things so that we, their descendants, might be inspired by their examples to remain vigilant for our salvation, even at night.
Let's transition from the old to the new, from the ministers of the Law to the ministers of the Gospel, to affirm the importance of vigilance from the New Testament.
Anna, the daughter of Phanuel, a widow who served with constant prayers and fasting, never left the temple, worshiping day and night.
It's written in the Gospel that those holy shepherds, while watching over their flock at night, were privileged to see angels in their glory and be the first to hear of Christ's birth on earth.
Indeed, doesn't the Savior's teaching urge all listeners to stay vigilant?
In the parable of the good sower, he teaches: "While people slept, the enemy came and sowed weeds among the wheat, and went away" Matthew 13:25.
Had they been awake, perhaps the enemy wouldn't have sown weeds.
Or when he says: "Let your loins be girded, and your lamps burning; and be like those who wait for their master when he returns from the wedding. Blessed are those servants whom the master, when he comes, will find watching" Luke 12:35-37.
And he adds: "Whether he comes in the evening, or at midnight, or at the crowing of the rooster, and finds them watching, blessed are they" Mark 13:35-37.
Therefore, be ready, for the Son of Man is coming at an hour you do not expect Matthew 24:44.
He not only taught vigilance with his words but also demonstrated it by example.
The Gospel testifies that Jesus spent the night in prayer to God Luke 6:12.
He spent the night, not for himself, but to show us what we should all do.
He rebukes Peter during his suffering, saying:
"Couldn't you stay awake with me for one hour?"
Now, he tells everyone:
"Stay awake and pray, so you do not fall into temptation"
(Matthew 26:40, 41).
With these words as an example, I ask, who cannot be awakened from the depths of death in a similar way?
Instructed by these teachings and confirmed by these proofs, the blessed Apostles also stayed awake and urged others to do the same.
The Apostle Peter was awakened at night in prison by an angel, and he reached the house of Mary, where many had gathered, not sleeping, but praying, as the angel opened the iron gate.
He writes in his letter, saying:
"Be sober, and stay awake, because your adversary the devil prowls around like a roaring lion looking for someone to devour"
(First Peter 5:8).
Paul and Silas are remembered for praying and singing a hymn in public custody around midnight, with the prisoners listening
(Acts 16:25);
when suddenly, after an earthquake, the foundations of the prison were shaken, the doors opened, and everyone's chains were immediately loosed.
In the same way, the blessed Apostle Paul urges the Thessalonians to keep watch, saying:
"Stay awake, stand firm in the faith, be strong and act courageously"
(First Corinthians 16:13).
Chapter Four
We've discussed the authority and antiquity of the holy vigils.
Now, as promised, let's talk about their usefulness.
While this can be better felt through practice than explained in words, experiencing it reveals the goodness of the Lord.
Those who have experienced it understand how staying awake removes impurities, shakes off mental dullness, and illuminates the soul of those who watch and pray.
It brings grace and holy visitation, filling the one who keeps vigil with joy.
By staying awake, fear is banished, confidence is born, the flesh is disciplined, vices diminish, chastity is strengthened, foolishness fades, wisdom grows, the mind sharpens, error dulls, and the devil, the source of sin, is wounded by the sword of the spirit.
What could be more necessary than these benefits, more advantageous than these holy gains, sweeter than this delight, or happier than this bliss?
The prophet testifies to this, describing a blessed man at the start of his Psalms, placing the essence of happiness in the verse:
Psalm Thirty-Four, verse nine: "If he meditates on the law of the Lord day and night"
Psalm One, verse two.
Daytime meditation is good, and prayer is good, but nighttime meditation is even more pleasing and effective. During the day, various necessities create noise, occupations disturb the mind, and many concerns scatter our attention.
Night, however, is secret, quiet, and convenient for prayer, most suitable for those who keep vigil, as it frees them from earthly distractions and focuses all their senses on the divine presence.
Therefore, know that vigils are pleasing to God as a celebration of His blessing.
Only, dearest ones, let those who keep watch with their eyes also watch with their hearts; let those who pray in spirit also pray with their minds. For it's not enough to keep watch with the eyes while the mind slumbers, since Scripture, speaking from the Church's perspective, says: "I sleep, but my heart is awake"
Song of Solomon Five, verse two.
We must ensure that we don't burden our vigilant hearts with too much food or drink.
Otherwise, we risk experiencing indigestion and drunkenness, making ourselves unpleasant and possibly being deemed unworthy of the Holy Spirit's grace.
A respected shepherd once said:
"Just as smoke drives away bees, an undigested belch can drive away and reject the gifts of the Holy Spirit."
Therefore, as we prepare to celebrate the divine mystery, it's essential to start with abstinence, so we can remain whole and alert.
Let's also clear any evil thoughts so that the prayers of those keeping watch don't become sinful, as it is written:
"May his prayer become sin" (Psalms One Zero Nine:7).
There are also cursed vigils from the wicked, as noted in Proverbs:
"For their sleep is taken away unless they have done evil" (Proverbs Four Sixteen).
But such vigils should be far removed from this gathering; instead, let the hearts of those keeping watch be closed to the devil and open to Christ, so that we can hold in our hearts what we proclaim with our lips.
Then our vigils will be acceptable to God, and our overnight prayer will be beneficial if our ministry is offered to divine eyes with appropriate diligence and sincere devotion.
What has been said about the authority and antiquity of vigils, as well as their holy usefulness, is sufficient.
Regarding the devotion of hymns and psalms, and how pleasing and acceptable they are to God, I would say more now, but a more extensive discussion would require another volume, which will be provided with the Lord's help in the next reading.
Treatise Two: On the Goodness of Psalmody
Chapter One
Let's talk about the goodness of psalmody, which God has graciously given us.
So, dear friends, as we are all guided by the teachings of the prophets, the Gospels, and the apostles, let's remember their words and actions, for through them we are who we are.
Let's recognize how pleasing and acceptable spiritual songs are to God, recalling from the beginning with those same authors.
If we look for the first person to introduce this practice, we find Moses, who led a glorious song to God when, after Egypt was struck by ten plagues and Pharaoh was drowned, the people joyfully went through the unusual paths of the sea to the desert, saying, "Let us sing to the Lord; for he has triumphed gloriously."
Exodus 15:1.
So, Moses was the first to establish the choirs of the tribes of Israel, teaching both genders in separate groups, with himself and his sister leading, to sing a triumphant song to the Lord.
Later, Deborah, a noble woman, is found performing this service in the Book of Judges.
However, as Moses was about to leave this life, he reiterated a powerful song in Deuteronomy, which he left written for the people as part of the covenant, so they would understand what punishment and tribulations would follow if they turned away from the Lord.
It's unfortunate for those who, despite such a clear warning, did not care to avoid sins and illicit superstitions.
Even later, you find many, not only men but also women filled with the divine Spirit, who sang the mysteries of God, even before David, who was specially chosen by the Lord for this role from his youth and became the chief of singers and a treasure of songs.
While still a boy, he played the lyre sweetly and powerfully, calming the evil spirit affecting Saul-not because the lyre had such great power, but because the figure of the cross of Christ, mystically represented in the wood and the stretching of the strings, already subdued the demonic spirit.
What won't you find in these Psalms that contributes to the benefit and upliftment of the human race, regardless of condition, gender, or age?
In the Psalms, a baby finds nourishment, a child finds praise, a teenager receives guidance to correct their path, a young person gains inspiration to follow, and an elder discovers what to pray for.
A woman learns modesty, orphans find a father, widows find a judge, the poor find a supporter, strangers find a protector, and kings and judges learn what to fear.
A Psalm comforts the sad, moderates the joyful, soothes the angry, refreshes the poor, reminds the rich to recognize themselves, and warns them against pride.
A Psalm offers healing to everyone who accepts it; it does not despise sinners but provides a remedy through tearful repentance.
Therefore, the Lord our God, through His servant David, created a potion that is sweet in taste through song and effective in healing the wounds of sins by its power.
A Psalm is pleasantly heard when sung; it penetrates the soul while it delights.
Psalms are easily remembered if they are sung often; and what the harshness of the law could not extract from human minds, these achieve through the sweetness of song.
Whatever the Prophets and the Gospels command is contained in these songs with the sweet delight of meditating on them.
God is shown to be feared, idols are mocked, justice is instilled, iniquity is prohibited, mercy is praised, unbelief is rejected, truth is sought, lies are condemned, deceit is accused, innocence is praised, pride is cast down, humility is exalted, repentance is preached, and peace is proclaimed to be pursued.
Protection against enemies is sought, vengeance is promised, and certain hope is nurtured.
Above all else, the sacraments of Christ are sung in the Psalms.
His lineage is expressed, the rejection of a wicked people is noted, the inheritance of the nations is named, the virtues of the Lord are sung, His venerable passion is depicted, His glorious resurrection is shown, and His seat at the right hand is wonderfully depicted.
Then, the fiery arrival of the Lord is revealed, unfolding the terrifying judgment of both the living and the dead.
What's more, the sending out of the creative Spirit and the renewal of the earth are also revealed.
After this, there will be the eternal kingdom of the righteous in the glory of the Lord, and the everlasting punishment of sinners.
Chapter Two
These are the songs of God that the Catholic Church of God sings.
Our assembly practices them with the sound of voices: these songs not only focus the singer, but they also bring them closer to the divine.
These songs please God, as everything done here is aimed at glorifying the Creator.
The prophet rightly encourages everyone and everything to praise God, who governs all, saying: "Let every spirit praise the Lord" Psalm 150:6.
He also promises to be a praiser himself, saying: "I will praise the name of the Lord with a song and will magnify Him with praise" Psalm 63:31.
Praise the Lord in your life, offering God a sacrifice of praise from your soul and your life, and through Him, you will be shown how to reach His salvation.
Our Lord delights in praise that comes from a pure conscience, as the same hymn writer encourages, saying: "Praise the Lord, for a psalm is good; let praise be pleasant and fitting to our God" Psalm 135:3.
Knowing that this duty is pleasing to God, the same Psalmist testifies: "Seven times a day I have praised you" Psalm 119:164.
And he promises something even more: "And my tongue shall meditate on your righteousness, all day on your praise" Psalm 35:28.
He undoubtedly felt the benefit of such devotion, as he himself says, remembering: "I will call upon the Lord with praise, and I will be saved from my enemies" Psalm 26:4.
Armed with this protection and shield, he struck down the mighty giant Goliath and often won victories over foreigners.
Chapter Three
It would take a long time, dear ones, to recount everything in the stories of the saints, especially since it's necessary to bring forth some things from the New Testament for the confirmation of the old and for your instruction.
You'll first find that Zechariah, the father of the great John, prophesied in the form of a hymn after a long silence.
Elizabeth, who was barren for years, continually praised God with her soul after having a son as promised.
When Christ was born on earth, an army of angels sang praises: Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace to people of good will Luke chapter two, verse fourteen.
The children in the temple announced, shouting Hosanna to the Son of David Matthew chapter twenty-one, verse fifteen; and when the Pharisees complained with jealousy, the Lord did not silence the mouths of the innocent but instead opened them, saying: Have you not read the scripture: Out of the mouths of infants and nursing babies, you have perfected praise?
And if these are silent, the stones will cry out Matthew chapter twenty-one, verse sixteen.
The Lord himself, a teacher in words and perfect in deeds, demonstrated that the service of hymns was most pleasing.
He went out with his disciples to the Mount of Olives after they had sung a hymn.
Who would doubt the religious significance of psalms and hymns with such an example?
When He, who is worshiped and praised by all heavenly beings, is reported to have sung a hymn with his disciples?
And John, in the Book of Revelation, reports that, with the Spirit revealing it to him, he saw and heard the voice of many waters and mighty thunderings saying Alleluia.
From this, no one should doubt that this ministry of holy vigils, if celebrated with true faith and devotion, is joined with the angels, who ceaselessly praise God in the heavens without sleep or distraction and bless the Savior.
Given these things, brothers, let us now fulfill the mystery of hymns with fuller confidence, believing that we have obtained great grace from God.
We have been granted the privilege to join with such great and holy ones, I mean prophets and martyrs, in the miracles of the eternal God.
.
Here with David, we acknowledge the Lord's goodness; with Moses, we declare the Lord's power through those magnificent songs.
With Anna, representing the Church, once barren but now fruitful, we find strength in praising God.
With Isaiah, we sing while keeping watch at night; with Habakkuk, Jeremiah, and Jonah, the most holy prophets, we sing in prayer.
With the three young men, as if placed in a furnace, we call upon all creation to bless the Creator of all.
What could be more beneficial than this experience, and what could be more delightful than this joy, as we are delighted by Psalms, refreshed by prayers, and nourished by readings interspersed among them?
Just as good guests enjoy a variety of dishes, our souls are nourished by the diverse readings and presentations of hymns.
Therefore, dear ones, setting aside unnecessary stories, let us sing with focused attention and an alert mind, so that we do not displease God.
The psalm encourages us by saying: "For God is the King of all the earth, sing praises with understanding" (Psalm 47:7), meaning intelligently, so that we sing not only with spirit, that is, the sound of our voice, but also with our mind.
We must think about what we are singing so that our minds, distracted by stories and foreign thoughts, do not end up in fruitless labor.
The sound or melody should also align with holy religion, not crying out in tragic difficulties, but demonstrating true Christianity within us; not resembling anything theatrical, but fostering repentance for sins.
The voice of all should be harmonious, not discordant.
Let not one person sing foolishly drawn out, or one humble and another raise their voice; rather, let each person humbly strive to blend their voice within the choir, not raising or extending outwardly to show off, nor seeking to please people.
We should celebrate everything as if in the sight of God, not with the desire to please people.
We have an example of this harmony of voice from the three most blessed youths mentioned by the prophet Daniel.
He says, "Then these three spoke as if with one voice, singing a hymn and glorifying God in the furnace, saying: Blessed are you, Lord God of our ancestors" Daniel 3:51, 52.
You can see this as an example of how these three youths humbly and reverently praised God with one voice. We, too, should all sing the same psalms together in unison. If someone cannot keep up with the others, it's better for them to remain silent or sing softly rather than disrupt everyone with a loud voice. This way, they fulfill their duty without disturbing the community's humble singing.
If our collective voice is harmonious, like the sound of well-played cymbals, it will please us, uplift those who listen, and be sweet to our God, who, as it is written, helps us live in unity in His house.
When it's time to sing, let everyone sing. When a reading is taking place, maintain silence so that everyone can listen, without any loud voices disrupting the reader. Everyone should gather before the reading starts. If someone arrives while the reading is in progress, they should worship God, cross themselves, and listen attentively to God's word.
There is a set time for praying together, and there are times when you can pray privately as often as you wish. Don't worry about missing the reading because it's not always available to everyone, but there will always be time.
Don't underestimate the value of hearing the sacred reading, as prayer becomes richer when the mind is nourished by fresh insights and moves through the divine images it has recently encountered.
Remember Mary, the sister of Martha, who sat at Jesus' feet and listened intently to His words, neglecting her sister. Jesus affirmed that she chose the better part.
For this reason, the deacon clearly reminds everyone in the house of God with a holy proclamation: whether you're praying, kneeling, singing psalms, or listening attentively to readings, unity should be maintained by all.
God loves people who are of one mind, and He makes them dwell in His house.
Those who live there are pronounced blessed in the psalm, as they will praise the Lord forever and ever.
Psalm Eighty-Four, Verse Five.
Amen.