The greatness of God's mercy towards us is truly remarkable.
Through the one by whom we lost the nobility of our original blessed creation, due to Adam's offense, we now have the chance to regain what was lost.
Back then, the devil harmed us out of envy; now, when he tries to harm us, he is defeated.
He exploits the weakness of our flesh, deploying all his weapons by inciting us to lust, leading us to drunkenness, provoking us to hatred, driving us to greed, instructing us to murder, and urging us to curse.
But when the strength of our spirit overcomes these temptations, we are cleansed from sin through the glory of this victory; as it was said:
"Or how can one born of a woman be pure?" (Job 25:4).
Because if there is no enemy, there will be no war; and when the war ends, victory will be missing.
But if we do not conquer the vices that confront us, there will be no cleansing from these vices.
When the pirate, who targets our body, is defeated, we are purified through the struggle against the passions that challenge us.
Therefore, let's be mindful and aware that our bodies are the source of all vices, making us impure and flawed.
Let us rejoice that we have an enemy, for in this struggle, we engage in our own battle for purity.
So, what guidance had Job received that led him to avoid all evil, knowing he worshipped God with a pure mind?
Worshiping God, after all, is the true duty of justice.
From the Introduction to the Commentary on the Gospel of Matthew, Chapter 3.
It was necessary for us that the only-begotten God became human for our sake, which He was not before.
Likewise, from the same source, the fourth point is that it was fitting for God to be born as a man in the world, and so on.
When Scripture mentions Christ, like in First Timothy 2:5, or when it states Christ died, as in Romans 8:34, and when it says the Word was made flesh, like in John 1:14;
The word shouldn't be stripped of its explanations by any reader's deceit.
Where it mentions the man Christ, it's preceded by, "Mediator between God and humans," indicating that he embodies both God and man, uniting both natures within himself.
But when Christ died, it follows with, "who was raised, who is at the right hand of God."
In his death, we see the weakness of our flesh; in the resurrection, his power; and in the presence of God, his dignity.
From the book to Emperor Constantius. The Son of God became man and is God.
God became the Son of man so that man could become God, not that God became man, and the Son of man became the Son of God.
The greatness of the Lord surpassed the smallness of the servant's form, transforming the servant's form, which He took on, from servile to exalted through the Lord who assumed it.
For if those who are not naturally sons of God become sons of God through Him, then how much more did He, who is naturally the Son of God, elevate the one with whom He was conceived and born by His own will in the virgin's womb, to the point that at His name every knee should bend, in heaven and on earth and under the earth, and every tongue confess that the Lord Jesus Christ is in the glory of God the Father.
From the uncertain work. Seven.
Give us today our daily bread, as written in
Luke
eleven:three.
What does God want more than for Christ, who is the bread of life and the bread from heaven, to dwell in us every day?
And because it is a daily prayer, it is also prayed for daily to be given.
Here's another point.
When Christ came in the likeness of sinful flesh, He did not possess sin, even though He had a human body.
Since all flesh is descended from sin, inherited specifically from Adam, He appeared in the likeness of sinful flesh.
However, in Him, there was no sin, only the appearance of sinful flesh.
A doubtful fragment. In which all have sinned.
This means that in Adam, all have sinned.
It's clear that everyone sinned in Adam, almost as if we were all part of one whole.
Because Adam himself was corrupted by sin, he caused everyone born from him to be under sin.
Let's explore Hilary's teachings on the procession of the Holy Spirit.
Saint Hilary, in his commentaries on the Apostle, discusses the Father and the Son and states that there is no duplicity in the Holy Spirit because both the Father and the Son give existence to him.
Thus, they are the single principle of the Holy Spirit.
Observe the remarkable and clear doctrine of this great Father against the schismatic Greeks regarding the procession of the Holy Spirit, with the Father and the Son as one principle!
Indeed, the Second Council of Hispalis, canon thirteen, confirmed that Saint Hilary wrote commentaries on Paul's Epistles, as recorded in Aquirrium, volume three, page three hundred fifty-three.
Now, let's look at a splendid fragment from that lost work preserved by the Greeks.
This is found in Spicilegium Romanum, volume six, page seventy-three.