On the Prophet Micah
Chapter One
The word of the Lord that came to Micah of Moresheth during the days of Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, which he saw concerning Samaria and Jerusalem.
Micah the prophet, whose name means "Who is like God?" or "Humility," is the sixth in the order of the twelve prophets.
So, we should expect profound mysteries from him, as he stands in the middle, like the heart of the prophetic order.
He was from Moresheth, a village in Palestine.
Moresheth means "heir."
It's fitting that Micah, whose name means humility, is born of the hope of inheritance, because whoever strives to uphold the virtue of humility for God will merit to be an heir of God and co-heir with Christ, who humbled himself for us and invites us to imitate his humility, saying: "Learn from me, for I am gentle and humble in heart."
This prophet threatens Samaria with the wrath of God and captivity, announcing the destruction that will come upon the people of Israel for abandoning God to serve idols.
He also clearly announces the place of Christ's birth.
We know that during the reign of Hezekiah, son of Ahaz, the ten tribes were taken into captivity by the Assyrians; later, during the reign of Zedekiah, the two tribes known as Judah were captured along with their king, and Jerusalem was destroyed.
Therefore, the title of the prophet is placed according to the order of the captivity:
First, as mentioned, Samaria, the capital of the ten tribes, was captured, and later Jerusalem, the capital of Judah.
Samaria is set as a symbol of heretics, and Jerusalem as a figure of the Church.
Listen, all you peoples, pay attention, earth and all that is in it, and let the Lord God be a witness against you, the Lord from his holy temple.
Notice that the people are commanded to listen and the earth to pay attention.
In the people, it refers to the ecclesiastical men; in the earth, it refers to the heretics, whose doctrine is earthly.
The Apostle also lists heresies among the works of the flesh.
So, those who are in the Church, if they listen, and those who are outside, if they pay attention, will be able to escape what the prophetic word threatens.
The prophet wishes for God to be a witness for them, not from elsewhere, but from His holy temple, which is the Church.
Through the Church, God bears witness to the truth.
The temple of God is the Son Himself, in whom the Father dwells and through whose mouth He speaks.
Behold, the Lord will come out of His place, come down, and tread upon the high places of the earth.
The mountains will melt under Him, and the valleys will be torn apart like wax before the fire, like waters pouring down a steep slope.
All this is due to the transgression of Jacob and the sins of the house of Israel.
What is the transgression of Jacob?
Is it not Samaria?
And what are the high places of Judah?
Are they not Jerusalem?
The place of God is mercy because He is naturally merciful and kind.
But He who is gentle and merciful to us sinners is, in a way, compelled to change His nature.
He comes out of His place, taking on a persona of cruelty, which is not His natural disposition.
His coming down is His majesty descending to the lower regions.
To tread upon the high places of the earth is to crush the mighty of the earth.
The mountains will melt under Him, and the valleys will be torn apart.
By the mountains, we understand the princes, and by the valleys, the subjected peoples.
As wax melts before the fire, and as waters run down a steep place, so all the pride of the wicked will dissolve and disappear at the coming of the Lord.
This will happen because of the sins of the ten tribes, which He calls Jacob or Samaria and Israel, and because of the transgression of Judah.
In the ten tribes, the capital was Samaria, which is now called Sebaste, and in Judah, Jerusalem was the chief city.
Tropologically, the holy place of God is the people of whom it is said: I will dwell in them and walk among them.
From these holy ones, the Lord comes out, not leaving them, but through them, preaching and announcing the punishment of the wicked and the reward of the righteous.
For we read that the word has gone out from the Lord.
He comes down and treads, not upon the lowly earth, that is, not upon those who are downcast, but upon the high places of the earth, that is, the holy ones, who understand the majesty of His coming.
Although they are holy, they will nevertheless be moved, meaning they will fear His presence.
The valleys, meaning the sinners and those who do not seek God, will not be able to withstand His presence.
Everything hard within them will be torn apart and flow away like water.
This will happen because of the impiety of Jacob, which refers to the heretics, and because of the sin of Judah, referring to those in the Church who claim to know God but deny Him through their actions.
In another interpretation, the Lord has left His place, abandoning the Jews among whom He once dwelled, due to their sin against Christ.
As He Himself warned them: "Your house will be left desolate."
He has tread upon the heights of the earth, coming to the Gentiles, who have been exalted by His grace and deserved to be lifted from earthly things. The mountains, representing the doctrines of philosophers, have been shaken, and the power of kings has been disturbed. With all impiety consumed within them, justice has grown: pride has been destroyed, and humility has been exalted.
"I will make Samaria like a heap of stones in a field when a vineyard is planted, and I will drag her stones into the valley, and I will reveal her foundations. All her carved images will be cut down, and all her wages will be burned with fire. I will put all her idols into perdition because they were gathered from the wages of a prostitute."
Because Samaria, which represents the ten tribes, sinned first, abandoning the temple of God and making golden calves for themselves, she was the first to be destroyed by the coming Assyrians. "I will make Samaria like a heap of stones," He says.
Since the city of Samaria is situated on a mountain, it is fittingly described as being turned into heaps of stones, so that not only the walls and buildings but also the very foundations will be torn down to the last stone. The carved images and idols they worshiped, along with the heaps of various works, are proclaimed to be burned with fire.
What He says, "and they will return to the wages of a prostitute," means that just as they prostituted themselves with the idols they made in their own land, they will go to another land of prostitution, namely to the Assyrians, and there similarly worship idols.
Over this, I will mourn and wail; I will go stripped and naked.
I will lament like dragons and mourn like ostriches because its wound is incurable.
It has reached Judah and touched the gate of my people, all the way to Jerusalem.
Up to this point, it's been about Samaria, but now he predicts woes for Judah, which has sinned in a similar way.
Thus, the prophet takes on the emotion of mourning.
I will lament like dragons, as stated before.
Just as dragons make a terrifying hiss when defeated by elephants, and just as ostriches, which cannot fly far due to their short wings, leave their eggs forgetfully in the sand to be trampled by the feet of beasts—though the eggs are not lost, they mourn as if they were—so too (says the prophet) will I go stripped and naked, having lost my children and with them taken into captivity.
Because its wound is incurable, that is, Samaria’s, and the same sin and punishment that destroyed Samaria has reached Judah and even the gates of Jerusalem.
Just as Samaria was overthrown by the Assyrians, so will Jerusalem be overthrown by the Chaldeans.
All of this is mystically to be referred to heretics, whom God threatens with a beneficial overthrow, so that when their various doctrines are destroyed and consumed by the fire about which the Lord says: I have come to cast fire upon the earth, they will mourn their errors, remove their sandals from their feet, which means to cast off the works of the dead.
They especially mourn because they wanted to introduce their error even to Judea (that is, to the Catholics), but they could not.
It reached the gates (that is, the ears) of the people of God, but could not penetrate the city, meaning it could not deceive a mind solidified in faith.
Do not announce it in Gath; do not weep with tears; cover yourselves with dust in the house of dust.
Gath is one of the five cities of the Philistines, from which Goliath of Gath came.
We know that the Philistines were always enemies of the Jews.
Therefore, the prophet says: Do not announce the coming evil in Gath, so that your enemies do not rejoice.
Do not weep with tears, even though your heart is in pain; hide your tears so that your enemies do not rejoice.
In the house of dust, the one that is about to collapse and turn into dust, sprinkle yourselves with dust—not in the streets, so your enemies don’t see and rejoice.
Pass through the beautiful dwelling, shamed and disgraced.
For beautiful, the Septuagint used the Hebrew word, scaphir.
Both the Syriac and Hebrew languages call beautiful scaphir, which is also the name Samaria is called because it was located in a very beautiful and fertile place.
So, it is said to her: O beautiful and fertile Samaria, because you are shamed with disgrace, pass through and proceed into captivity in such a way that, if possible, even the foreign enemy doesn't notice.
She who lives in the exit has not gone out.
Here, the Hebrew word used is senna.
Senna means exit, signifying that captivity is already at the exit and at the doors.
When it says, "She has not gone out," it means she wasn’t willingly or voluntarily taken into captivity but was forced and unwillingly led into it.
The lament of the neighboring house will be taken from you, which stood by itself. Here, the Hebrew word used in the Septuagint is Azel. The order is: The house of Azel will take lament from you. Azel means neighbor or next to. Therefore, it calls the house of Azel the house of Judah, which was near Samaria and next to it, and which received lament upon hearing the disaster of Samaria. The house of Azel stood by itself, meaning that Samaria, captured, remained in the state of its kingdom, protected by God because of Hezekiah. It was weakened for its own good, humbled for its own progress when Rabshakeh blasphemed the living God.
She who lives in Ramoth, which means in bitterness. For that is what Ramoth means. In bitterness and sadness, the people with King Hezekiah dwelled while Sennacherib was besieging them. Calamity descended from the Lord to the gate of Jerusalem. For the king of Assyria, after devastating Samaria, came against Jerusalem when Rabshakeh was sent from Lachish to Hezekiah to surrender to the Assyrians, mocking the Lord and saying: How could He save His people from the hand of the Assyrians?
The noise of the chariot, the astonishment of the inhabitants of Lachish.
Lachish is a city in Judah, the first to receive idols from the ten tribes, allowing idolatry to spread to Jerusalem.
It means: O Lachish, the cavalry and tumult of the Assyrians will come to you, leaving you in shock.
This marks the beginning of sin for the daughter of Zion, because in you were found the crimes of Israel, and through you, idolatry entered Jerusalem.
Therefore, he will send messengers over the inheritance of Gath: the house of lies, deceiving the kings of Israel.
Not only will chariots and tumult come over Lachish, but also over Gath, the metropolis of Palestine.
He calls the messengers robbers, sent by the king of Assyria to Gath, a house of idolatry and lies, deceiving the kings of Israel.
I will bring an heir to you, who dwells in Mareshah, that is, in the inheritance.
He refers to the arrival of the enemies as an heir.
Therefore, God says through the prophet that he will bring the Assyrians to possess Gath as an inheritance, because it deceived the kings of Israel.
The glory of Israel will come as far as Adullam.
Adullam was a noble city among the Jews, and it too will face the hostility of the Assyrians.
Some manuscripts say, "The glory of Israel," meaning captivity will move from Gath to Adullam, the city of Israel's glory.
Or it could be understood ironically, meaning that evil from Lachish, Mareshah, and Gath will reach Adullam.
Here, it should be distinguished, and with a slightly suppressed voice, inferred ironically, "It is glory," meaning the disgrace and dishonor of Israel's people.
According to the letter, let us briefly see the mystery they contain: Gath is interpreted as the winepress.
It signifies the heretics, who exalted themselves, claiming to have the wine of Soreth, spiritual and divine knowledge. However, their wine (that is, doctrine) was from the vineyard of the Sodomites and the suburbs of Gomorrah.
They are called the house of dust because they focus on earthly matters and are prey for the serpent, that is, the devil, to whom it was said, "You will eat dust all the days of your life."
The prophet urges them not to exalt themselves but to do penance, saying, "In the house of dust, sprinkle yourselves with dust, lest when the time of vengeance comes, and the house that seemed beautiful to you falls, you perish together, and your vain labor provides laughter to those who see it."
It has not left because it dwells in exile, which means the Church that resides in exile, hoping to receive the heavenly kingdom. It has not abandoned the purpose of the divine Scriptures nor violated the statutes of the Fathers. The lamentation of the neighboring house will come from you. The neighboring house is the Church, where there are no heretics, but they are close to it.
"They went out from us," says the Apostle, "but they were not of us." Therefore, the house of heretics is near to the Church of the faithful, but it is built on sand and has no foundation. And the meaning is: O heretics, who only neighbor the Church but always rise against it, mourn yourselves, for from you the enemy and avenger, the devil, will receive lamentation. That is, you will be the cause of your own destruction, and from you, the devil, to whom you have been handed over, will receive the material for punishment.
It stood by itself because it was weakened for its own good, to be joined to the higher where it is said, "It has not left which dwells in exile, which stood by itself." The Church stood by itself because it remained stable in truth. It was weakened, that is, afflicted by various tribulations, but this was for its good, because the more it was weakened, the more it was strengthened in faith, according to the Apostle who says, "When I am weak, then I am strong." Hence the Psalmist says about the same Church, "It was weakened, but you have perfected it." This very Church dwells in Ramoth, that is, in bitterness, because pressed by the weight of persecution, it has nothing sweet in the present. However, evil descended from the Lord to the gate of Jerusalem, that is, the plots of heretics reached the hearing of the Church.
But they cannot penetrate the Church, because it is internally protected by the mind and does not go outside to be violated, like Dinah once did, of whom it is said that she went out to see the women of that region.
Evil is said to descend from the Lord, because nothing happens unless permitted by the Lord, who allows heretics in the Church either to test or to exercise.
It follows, "The commotion of the chariot of astonishment to the inhabitant of Lachish," etc. Lachish, which means "wandering," signifies those heretics who are vagabonds, roaming through different doctrines of errors, and who are carried around by every wind of doctrine, about whom it is said, "Some in chariots and some in horses," etc.
Therefore, these were the leaders of the sin of the daughter of Zion, which means "watchtower," because all calamity of the Church, all error and sin, proceeded from heretics.
Therefore, I will place messengers over the inheritance of Gath. The messengers are demons or visible enemies who, by the just judgment of God, are sent over Gath, which means "winepress," that is, over heretics who think they have the wine of the purest truth but are the house of lies and deceive whomever they can.
What follows is, "He will still bring heirs to you who dwell in Mareshah." Mareshah in Latin means "inheritance," signifying those who from the inheritance of Christ (that is, from the society of the Church) were transferred to heretics.
It is promised to them, therefore, that if they are willing to convert, the Lord will bring them heirs, holy teachers, who will separate them from errors and lead them to the inheritance of the Lord and the society of the Church.
The glory of Israel will come to Adullam.
Adullam means "testimony of exhaustion." He says, "Let not the heretics boast, the glory of Israel will come, the boasting of the heretics will reach Adullam," that is, to the testimony of their exhaustion, that is, to judgment, when they will drain and drink the measure of their works.
Shave your heads and cut your hair for the children of your delight; enlarge your baldness like an eagle, for they have been taken captive from you.
This is specifically about Samaria, the ten tribes, and generally about all the people of Israel who were taken captive.
They are therefore commanded to shave their heads, as was customary in mourning, cut their hair, and weep for their children.
Just as an eagle loses its feathers and remains bare for a time, Israel should lay aside all its former glory and lament for its children taken by enemies.
Even now, we see the Jewish people shaven and the grace they once had is completely gone.
Mystically, it is said to the sinful soul:
O soul, you who once enjoyed paradise and soared like an eagle contemplating the heavens, take on the habit of repentance and weep for your children, that is, the deeds you have done, because they have been taken captive under the law of sin.
Chapter Two
Woe to those who plan useless things and do evil in their beds.
In the morning light, they act on it, because their hands are against God.
Woe to the people of the Jews, and woe to all who think useless things, meditating on how to offend God and planning to do wrong while in their beds.
The definition of will is taken as the effect of the work.
Whatever evil they plot at night, they hurry to fulfill it as soon as the morning light shines, not considering that their hands are against the Lord.
The prophet continues, explaining what those things are that they think and do:
They covet fields and seize them violently, rob houses, and oppress a man and his house, a man and his inheritance.
These things happened then, and unfortunately, many do them now.
Hence, just retribution follows immediately:
Therefore, thus says the Lord: Behold, I am planning evil against this family, from which you will not remove your necks, and you will not walk proudly, for it is an evil time.
Because you planned useless things, I am planning evil against you.
Not that the scourge of God is evil, but it seems so to those who endure it.
The evil will be such that you will not be able to lift your necks, pressed down by the weight of captivity.
On that day, a proverb will be taken up against you, and a song will be sung with sadness, saying: We are devastated by desolation.
This will be sung often like a song and taken up as a proverb.
The portion of my people is changed, signifies the temple, which was more sacred among all nations, being turned into ruin.
How will it depart from me, you understand, the Assyrian, when he who divides our regions returns?
These are like the words of a fearful people.
For Sennacherib, king of the Assyrians, when he came against Jerusalem, heard about Taharqa, king of Ethiopia, coming out to fight against him.
Then he withdrew from Jerusalem, yet as if he would return after victory.
So, the people who knew he had withdrawn said:
"How can you say the Assyrian will withdraw from us, when he will soon return to divide our fields by lot? Because of this, you will not have anyone to measure out the line of the lot in the assembly of the Lord."
Because you have done these things mentioned above, O family of Israel, against whom I think evil, you will not have a part in the assembly of the Lord, that is, in the inheritance of the righteous.
This can also refer to the final captivity, which was carried out by Titus. They endured all these things because they were proud against God and condemned Christ to the cross.
These can morally refer to a sinning soul, which thinks evil in the secret of the heart and completes it in action. Therefore, the Lord thinks evil against us, from which we cannot lift our necks and walk upright. The apostles are sent to lament with Jeremiah and take up a parable against us.
With the Apostle, they mourn many who have sinned and have not repented.
Part of the Lord's people is divided by the line when souls departing through various vices are divided by demons. One extends a line of greed, another extends a line of lust into the inheritance of the Lord and the fields of sanctity, fragrant with the scents of virtues. According to what Isaac said:
"Behold, the smell of my son is like the smell of a full field." They are handed over to the king of the Assyrians and Babylonians, that is, to the devil.
O Israel, do not listen to those who say: "It will not fall upon us, confusion will not grasp us," says the house of Jacob.
Is the spirit of the Lord shortened, or are these his thoughts? O house of Jacob, do not deceive yourselves by presuming too much on the mercy of God. Do not say, as many still do, "God is good and merciful, the evil of captivity which we fear will not come upon us."
For he who is abundant in mercy to all will also be merciful to us, nor will his goodness be shortened because of us alone. For his thoughts are not like those of humans, so that, like a man, he is suddenly stirred to anger.
These are like the words of those to whom it is said, "Do not speak those who speak."
Aren't my words good for those who walk uprightly?
Yet, my people have risen up against me.
He introduces the Lord responding: I am good, as you say, and my words sound merciful, but only to those who walk uprightly.
But you do not act rightly; instead, you rise up against me with a tyrannical spirit.
Then he recalls their actions: You have taken away the cloak from above the robe, stripping away clothing or divine help, and those who were passing by innocently, you have turned into war.
Or those who were acquiescing to authority, you have turned into war, so they would not accept the edicts of the teachers, nor believe their instructors.
It is also morally commanded that we should not think we please God just by reading his words in writings.
For the words of the Lord are good and benefit the readers if they are fulfilled in deed, if the heart and lips agree.
The tunic and cloak are garments of faith and virtues, as the Apostle says: Clothe yourselves as God's chosen ones, holy and beloved, with heartfelt compassion, humility, etc.
, or even divine help and protection.
Heretics or wicked priests take all these things away from the people entrusted to them by living wickedly.
You have driven the women of my people out of their houses of delight: you have taken my praise from their little ones forever.
Not only have you done these things, but you have also made once delicate matrons go captive: or you have desolated cities, driving out or killing the inhabitants, which he metaphorically calls women or daughters.
With the cities desolated, no one remained, not even a child, to sing psalms and praises to God.
Therefore, rise and go into captivity, because in this land you have no rest: because of its uncleanness, its crimes and impieties, your land will be corrupted with the worst decay.
Your captivity will not be brief, but will last a long time, and it will be corrupted with the worst decay, that is, Babylonian or Roman captivity.
Immoral leaders of the Church drive away women, who are often seen as simple and naturally weak souls, from their homes—meaning from the Church—through their bad examples, casting them into outer darkness.
Therefore, it is also said to these leaders that they should rise and leave, because they are corrupted by the worst decay, which is a long habit of sinning, corrupting both soul and body.
I wish I were not a man with the Holy Spirit, and instead spoke lies: I will pour out wine and drunkenness upon you, and it will fall upon this people.
O Jewish people, to whom promises were made, and from whom Christ was born according to the flesh, do not think I speak willingly or predict these bad things of my own accord.
I wish I were not a man with the Holy Spirit, but rather spoke with a demonic spirit, and were considered among false prophets, so that what I say would not be true, and the bad things I foretell would not come to pass.
But because I am a prophet, and I speak with the Holy Spirit, I will pour out wine upon you, so that you will be drunk with my words as with the strongest wine, and fall.
As I pour out, this people will receive the drops of my prophecy, and whether they want to or not, they will endure what I say.
However, do not think I only prophesy adversity; I will also announce good things to you.
Therefore, he introduces the Lord Himself speaking and promising good things: I will surely gather Jacob.
I will come, He says, through Myself, be born of a Virgin, and gather Jacob—that is, I will gather believers from the Jews to My faith.
Or, in another sense: Because you did not want to believe in Me in the humility of the flesh, I will come at the end of the world in majesty, and then I will pour out upon you—that is, I will offer the wine of the Holy Spirit, the wine of the divine word with which the apostles were filled on the day of Pentecost, and of which it is said through the Psalmist: You made us drink the wine of compunction.
I will bring together all the remnants of Israel into one.
I will place them together as a flock in a fold, as sheep in the middle of a pen—that is, I will join believers from both peoples together in the fold of eternal rest.
They will be tumultuous from the multitude of people.
Now he clearly shows which sheep or flocks he was talking about.
They will make noise—that is, they will shout, praising the good shepherd who will go before them and open the way for them.
He himself will lead them to him.
Hence it follows:
"For he will go up, opening the way before them; they will break through and pass the gate, and go out through it: and their king will pass before them, and the Lord at their head, meaning the leader and guide to the heavenly pastures."
Chapter Three
And I said, Listen, leaders of Jacob, and rulers of the house of Israel: Is it not for you to know justice?
You who hate good and love evil?
You who violently take their skins and flesh from them, who eat the flesh of my people, strip off their skin, break their bones, and chop them up like meat in a pot, like flesh in a cauldron.
Then they will cry out to the Lord, but he will not hear them; he will hide his face from them at that time because they have acted wickedly.
Using the metaphor of lions or robbers, the cruelty of the leaders of the Jews is described.
They robbed the poor and killed them, crushing their flesh and bones like wild beasts.
Just as meat is cooked in a pot, they afflicted countless people in Jerusalem.
Therefore, he threatens them with the evil of captivity, either Chaldean or Roman.
Even if they cry out to him, he will not hear them but will repay them for their wicked deeds and the crimes they continuously invented.
This is what the Lord says to the prophets who deceive my people, who bite with their teeth and proclaim peace.
But if anyone does not give them something, they declare war against him.
Therefore, night will be for you instead of vision, and darkness instead of divination; the sun will set on the prophets, and the day will darken over them.
The seers will be ashamed, and the diviners will be confounded; they will all cover their faces because there is no answer from God.
At that time, there were false prophets among the people of Israel who, in order to receive gifts, proclaimed peace that was not given to them.
This is what he means when he says they bite with their teeth, to show the greed of those who receive.
But if anyone gave them nothing, even if he was holy, they would predict that the wrath of God was coming upon him.
Hence, he says their word is not prophecy, but divination, and it does not bring light, but darkness and error.
And when the things they promised do not come to pass, the sun will set on them, and they will be covered in shame, because it will be known that it was not the response of God, but a deceit of demons wanting to deceive people.
However, I am filled with the strength of the Spirit of the Lord, with judgment and power, to announce to Jacob his crime, and to Israel his sin.
The prophet now speaks of himself.
While the false prophets prophesy falsely and are covered in shame, he speaks by the inspiration of the Holy Spirit, and announces the judgment of the Lord and the truth.
He does not preach peace as they do to gain something, but announces to Jacob his crime, and to Israel his sin, because they worshipped idols instead of God, and because they crucified Christ.
These words can be referred to the worst teachers, who deceive God's people by flattering them, saying: Have faith, it will save you; it is not necessary to live a virtuous life.
They do this to gain earthly benefits, and to devour them, either by taking their possessions or by spiritually killing their souls.
Upon such prophets, the Sun of justice will set, and then they will be shamed, and their faces will be covered in confusion.
Hear this, leaders of the house of Jacob, and judges of the house of Israel, who despise judgment, and pervert all that is right, who build Zion with blood, and Jerusalem with iniquity.
Its leaders judge for bribes, its priests teach for a price, and its prophets tell fortunes for money, and rely on the Lord, saying: Is not the Lord in our midst?
No harm will come upon us.
Earlier, there was a warning against judges and false prophets.
Now, the message is directed at them, as well as the priests and all who flatter themselves with their knowledge of God.
They are accused not only of failing to act justly but also of despising justice and perverting what is right.
They build their houses with bloodshed and the city of Jerusalem with iniquity—plundering the poor, killing the innocent, and murdering the saints.
Furthermore, the leaders judge for bribes, the prophets prophesy for money, and they sell the grace of God.
While doing all these things, they rest on the Lord, saying, "We are the people of God; the Lord is among us; evil will not come upon us."
For all these actions, the prophet, or rather the Lord through the prophet, threatens them, saying, "Because of you, Zion will be plowed like a field, Jerusalem will become a heap of stones, and the mountain of the temple will become a high place in a forest."
He teaches that the temple of God, which once shone with gold and precious stones, will be brought to utter ruin.
All these things happened to the Jews because of what was previously mentioned, especially the shedding of the Lord's blood.
These can be morally referred to the Church.
It is indeed the house of Jacob and the house of Israel.
Thus, he speaks of the corrupt teachers and leaders or judges of the Church, who, while committing the evil they can, rest on the Lord and falsely promise themselves prosperity from His mercy, saying, "Evil will not come upon us."
Chapter Four
In the last days, the mountain of the house of the Lord will be established at the top of the mountains, exalted above the hills, and all people will flock to it.
Many nations will hurry and say: Come.
Because the leaders of the Jews have despised judgment and built Zion with blood, Mount Zion, the mountain of the Lord, is elevated, which is Christ.
This mountain was revealed in the last days, at the end of the ages, when the Savior appeared through the saving sacrifice, taking away the sins of the world.
"Prepared" means manifest, which was hidden for so many thousands of years.
It will be prepared not only in the mountains but also above the tops of the mountains.
The mountains indeed are the holy prophets, who wrote all holy things and those pertaining to human salvation. Yet, in comparison to this prophecy, in which they foretold the advent of the Savior, the rest are humble and do not reach the tops of the mountains.
This mountain is exalted above the hills because the man assumed by the Word of God surpassed the grace and merit of all the saints.
Because he humbled himself to death, God the Father exalted him and gave him the name above every name.
To this mountain, all nations will be gathered, or as the Septuagint says, all nations will flow, and like rivers, innumerable people will come believing.
We now see people from all nations, known to the Roman Empire, believing in Christ and through faith flowing to this mountain.
But what do those coming say?
Let us go up to the mountain of the Lord.
An ascent is needed if we want to come to Christ and to the house of the God of Jacob, which is the Church, the house of God, according to the Apostle, the pillar and foundation of truth.
But he calls Christ the God of Jacob.
Why do they come?
They add: and he will teach us his ways, through teachers and pastors who preside over the Church, whom John in the Apocalypse calls angels, or through the Scriptures, which show the way of the Lord, that is, Christ, who says: I am the way.
We will walk in His paths, meaning we will follow and imitate His apostles, who are His representatives through whom we believe in Him.
From Zion, that is, from the early Church, will come the spiritual law, the preaching of the Gospel to the nations.
The word of the Lord, referring to the Son of God the Father, who is His Word, will come from Jerusalem, which means from Judea, where He took on flesh.
He will judge between many peoples.
For the Father judges no one, but has given all judgment to the Son.
He will correct strong nations far away, meaning the wise and philosophers of the world, whom He catches in their cleverness.
He judges the peoples by discerning who is worthy of salvation and who is not.
They will beat their swords into plowshares, and their spears into pruning hooks.
Nation will not lift up sword against nation, and they will not learn war anymore.
Every man will sit under his vine and fig tree, and no one will make them afraid.
All efforts in war will cease when He comes, and everyone will turn to peace.
There will be such great rest that in both cities and villages, there will be utmost security.
Each one will sit under his vine because the mouth of the Lord of hosts has spoken.
Let us read the histories, and we will see that before the coming of Christ, the whole world was in conflict; everything was boiling with both external and civil wars, and travel between nations was unsafe.
But after Christ came, preparing the Roman Empire by preaching the Gospel, the world became traversable.
Tropologically, turning swords and spears into rural tools represents the end of anger and persecution, which unbelievers previously directed at holy preachers.
These have been transformed so that spiritual fruits can grow from the darts of insults.
These things will happen because the Lord has spoken, whose every word is true, and whose saying is doing.
All the peoples will walk each in the name of their god, but we will walk in the name of our God forever and ever.
The rest of the nations, he says, after their error, we who go up to the mountain of the Lord will walk in the name of the Lord our God, Jesus Christ, because he is the true mountain and God, and we are called Christians from his name.
On that day, when the true sun shines, the Lord says, "I will gather the lame, and the one I have cast out I will collect, and the one I have afflicted I will comfort, and I will make the lame a remnant, and the one who labored, a strong nation."
This means the Jewish people who are crushed and cannot walk uprightly, and are cast out and rejected. They will be gathered to be accepted, made a remnant, and a strong nation.
This is what Isaiah says, "Unless the Lord of hosts had left us offspring, we would have been like Sodom, and we would have been like Gomorrah."
This happened when the apostles preached, as it is read in the Acts of the Apostles: "In one day three thousand believed, another day five thousand, and thereafter many thousands."
But it will be more fully completed at the end of the age, because when the fullness of the Gentiles has come in, then all Israel will be saved.
And the Lord will reign over them, that is, over the gathered ones, on Mount Zion, that is, in the Church, which is in contemplation of spiritual life. From now on and forever, that is from this present age until the future.
And you, tower of the flock cloudy, daughter of Zion, to you it will come, and the former dominion will come, the kingdom of the daughter of Jerusalem.
He calls the tower of the flock cloudy, the place which is called Eder, that is, tower of the flock, because of the gathering of shepherds. It is one mile east of Bethlehem.
In this place, the angel appeared to the three shepherds and announced that God was born, and they rest there venerably buried. He calls it the cloudy tower because of the obscurity of the heavenly mysteries revealed there.
The former dominion refers to the angelic powers, who sang "Glory to God in the highest" with exultation, and this is the kingdom of the daughter of Jerusalem, that is, the heavenly city, where the angelic powers behold the God of hosts.
Allegorically, the tower of Nebusola represents the people of Israel or the temple of God built by Solomon in Jerusalem.
Isaiah speaks of this tower: "And he built a tower in the midst of it," which means in the middle of the vineyard.
This tower, symbolizing the Jewish people, had a wall for angelic protection and a winepress as the altar, making it inaccessible to the devil and not obscure, but rather the city of God.
Being set on a mountain, representing the height of virtues, it could not be hidden.
However, after defiling itself with the blood of the Lord, it became obscure and squalid.
The first power, the Son, who speaks in Revelation, "I am the Alpha and the Omega, the beginning and the end," and who, from the perspective of the assumed man, says, "The Lord possessed me at the beginning of His ways," came to this.
This power is the kingdom of the daughter of Jerusalem.
Thus, the first power came into this world to create the second power.
For it cannot be called the first unless there is a second.
Thus, the second power was made in the apostles, so that as they are called light from the Light Christ, and bread from the living Bread Christ, as Paul says:
"We, being many, are one bread in Christ," so from the first power they are called power and kingdom.
Now why are you distressed with sorrow?
When he says the first power is going to come to you, why are you distressed with sorrow and humiliated?
Is there no king for you, or has your counselor perished, that pain has seized you like a woman in labor?
By asking, he affirms that it is just for her to grieve and mourn, because her king, Christ, who is both counselor and angel of great counsel, has perished for her, crucified by them.
As far as they were concerned, he perished.
According to the Gospel parable, they cast out the heir and killed him outside the vineyard, and they themselves were devastated by the Roman army.
Just as a woman in labor cannot escape pain, so that people could not avoid the imminent danger and devastation.
Grieve and strive, daughter of Zion, like a woman in labor, because now you will go out from the city, dwell in the region, and come to Babylon:
There you will be delivered, and the Lord will redeem you from the hand of your enemies.
The daughter of Zion — often referring to the people of Israel — is commanded to mourn, leave the city, and live in the countryside because it is God's decree that they go into captivity, and His judgment cannot be changed.
Therefore, they are advised to endure patiently and go to Babylon, knowing that if they bravely endure the punishment, they will soon be redeemed from the hand of their enemies.
When they are freed, they can say:
"Do not rejoice over me, my enemy, because I have fallen, I will rise;"
and along with the Psalmist:
"The Lord will not be angry forever, nor will He threaten forever."
According to the letter, the people taken into captivity were freed and returned after seventy years under Joshua, Zerubbabel, and Ezra. Morally, the soul, driven out of the city — that is, the Church — because of sin, handed over to the enemy for the destruction of the flesh, is commanded to come to Babylon, which symbolizes the confusion of vices and its own degradation. After proper repentance, it may be freed from the captivity of sin and, returning to the father's house, may deserve to be received by the most merciful Father.
According to the blessed Gregory, it often happens that a soul, called the daughter of Zion, which ought to contemplate God, is devastated by some spiritual and hidden vice — for example, pride or envy. The merciful God sometimes allows it to fall into open sin of the flesh and come to Babylon, that is, to confusion, so that, confounded by the foulness of open sin, it may be freed from the captivity of hidden vice.
And now many nations are gathered against you, who say:
"Let her be stoned, and let our eye look upon Zion."
The voice of the prophet:
"O Jerusalem, to whom I predict impending captivity, meanwhile, until it comes, many nations are already gathered against you, who speak as if about an adulterous woman and say: 'Let her be stoned, and let our eye look upon Zion,' that is, against Zion, so that we may insult and rejoice in her misfortunes."
And they say this: They themselves did not know the thoughts of the Lord and did not understand His plan, because He gathered them like sheaves to the threshing floor.
Who gathered them together for this reason, so that you would crush them like hay and straw on the threshing floor?
So rise and thresh, daughter of Zion, because I will make your horn iron, and I will make your hooves bronze, giving you invincible strength.
In this way, you will crush many nations, and dedicate their loot to the Lord, and their strength to the Lord of all the earth, consecrating them to the Lord your God.
The Lord delights in such a sacrifice, but the horn and the hooves are metaphorical, representing those who thresh from the enemies.
Morally, the multitudes of spiritual wickedness are gathered against the Church of God, insulting and reproaching the deaths of its children, not knowing the plan of the Lord nor His thoughts.
He allows them to prevail for a time, so the patience of the righteous may be rewarded, and the wickedness of the unrighteous may be punished.
The Lord gathers them to be crushed, and their just condemnation will contribute to the praise of the Creator.
Their loot and strength will be turned into a sacrifice to the Lord.
Chapter Five
Now you will be devastated, daughter of the thief: they have laid siege against us, with a rod they will strike the cheek of the judge of Israel.
I promised you (says the prophet) that you would thresh and crush all the nations gathered against you and offer their spoils to the Lord your God.
But since this will not happen now, but when the fullness of the nations enters at the end of the age, in the meantime, you are devastated for your deeds.
Hence, I no longer call you my daughter, but the daughter of the thief, that is, the devil, who is always ready to plunder.
They have laid siege against us.
It is the voice of God the Father speaking to the Son and the Holy Spirit, and the Trinity of persons is clearly shown.
They laid siege against the Son of God, the Jews, when they were plotting against Him, saying: "Teacher, we know that you are truthful."
For they were almost besieging Him, those who were thinking of capturing Him.
But since the injury to the Son is an injury to the Father and the Holy Spirit, therefore it is said in the plural "against us."
As for what follows: "With a rod they will strike the cheek of the judge of Israel," this shows that the soldiers struck the head of the Lord with a reed, which was an insult to the Son that reverberated through the entire Trinity.
Because of these crimes, I will no longer delay vengeance, and now and in the present, you will be devastated by the Assyrians or the Romans.
And you, Bethlehem Ephrathah, you are small among the thousands of Judah, from you will come forth for me one who is to be ruler in Israel.
The prophet speaks from the person of God the Father, promising the incarnation of His Son, and designating the place of His birth.
And you, Bethlehem, who were formerly called Ephrathah, and are so small that compared to the thousands of Judah, you are scarcely considered a small village, from this small town will come forth Christ, who will be ruler in Israel.
And do not think that He is only from the lineage of David, since indeed He is seen as true man, and His origin is from the beginning, from the days of eternity.
He was begotten from my substance before the ages, because "In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God" (John 1:1).
Bethlehem is interpreted as the house of bread, because there was born the bread that came down from heaven.
Ephrata turns into fury, referring to Herod, who became very angry upon realizing he had been deceived by the wise men.
Because of this, the Lord will give them time until the woman in labor gives birth, and then the remnants of her brothers will return to the children of Israel.
Therefore, he says he will give them, the Jews, dominion until the time when the virgin gives birth in a new order.
But after she has given birth, and the newborn has fulfilled his mission, with the Jewish people taken captive or killed, the remnants of his brothers, the apostles, will return to the faith of the patriarchs and prophets.
It can also be understood this way: He will give the Jews time to observe the shadow of his law until the Church, the mother, spiritually gives birth to the Gentiles in faith.
And until the barren woman gives birth to many, and the one who had many children becomes weak.
With the fullness of the Gentiles entering, all Israel will finally be saved.
Then the remnants of his brothers will return to the children of Israel, and with Elijah preaching, the hearts of the fathers will turn to the children, and the hearts of the children to their fathers.
The last people will join the first, and they will truly be the children of Abraham by believing in him whom Abraham saw and rejoiced.
And he will stand and feed in the strength of the Lord, in the majesty of the name of the Lord his God.
They will return because now he will be magnified to the ends of the earth.
When he says the woman in labor gives birth, and the sun of righteousness, Christ, fills the whole world, then the Lord himself, who first walked as a man, will stand when he is believed in and worshiped as God by all.
And he will feed them, the believers, in the strength of the Lord, in the power of divinity; and they will be able to say: The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want.
He will also feed in the majesty of the Lord's name, according to what he prayed to God the Father near the time of his passion: Holy Father, keep them in your name.
And they will turn from the love with which they loved Christ carnally, and begin to love him as God.
Will they turn and start seeking spiritual and eternal things, instead of earthly and temporal ones?
This shift happens because Christ has been exalted to the ends of the earth, and His voice has reached every corner of the world.
He will bring peace when the Assyrian comes into our land and treads in our houses.
The Assyrian, representing the devil, will try to devastate the faith of those nourished by the Lord and invade our homes, which symbolize our bodies, the dwellings of our souls.
But Christ will be our peace within, as no tribulation or distress can separate the chosen from His love.
For instance, the Assyrian attacked Paul, bringing many labors, dangers, and challenges into his life.
Yet, through Christ's love, Paul overcame all these adversities.
We will raise up over him seven shepherds and eight principal men.
Here, God the Father speaks, promising good things.
"We," referring to the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, will raise seven shepherds, representing patriarchs and prophets who upheld the sevenfold law, the Sabbath. Additionally, eight principal men, who are observers of the New Testament, have been raised by the Lord in the Church from the apostles' time to the present. The number seven relates to the Old Testament because of the Sabbath, while the number eight signifies the grace of the New Testament, representing the Lord's resurrection on the eighth day. As Solomon says, "Give a portion to seven, yes even to eight."
They will conquer the land of Assyria with the sword, symbolizing the word of God. As the Apostle says, "The word of God is living and effective, sharper than any two-edged sword, penetrating even to the division of soul and spirit." This sword was sent by Him who declared He came to set a man against his father and a daughter against her mother, and so forth.
They will also strike the land of Nimrod with their spears, delivering it from Assyria when it invades our land and crosses our borders.
Nimrod, a mighty hunter before the Lord, reigned in Assyria.
His name means "descending temptation" and signifies the devil, who fell from heaven because of pride.
The land of Nimrod, meaning the people he controlled, will be guided by shepherds and leaders, such as the prophets and apostles. The spears symbolize divine preaching. Once the Assyrian is defeated and the land of Nimrod is diminished, the Lord Christ will deliver us from Assyria, which came to invade our land.
The remnant of Jacob will be among the nations, in the midst of many peoples, like dew from the Lord, and like drops on the grass. After we are freed from Assyria, representing the devil who leads his followers to destruction, the remnant of Jacob, referring to the apostles or the early Church, will be among the peoples like dew from the Lord. They will cool the heat of sins that burned all nations and extinguish the fiery darts of the devil.
It is said that an angel descended into the burning furnace where the three boys had been thrown and made the furnace feel like a cool wind of dew. Therefore, the teaching of the apostles will be among all nations like dew from the Lord and like drops on the grass. This heavenly preaching is compared to drops that fall from roofs.
When it is said that this dew does not wait for man or expect the sons of men, it means that the nations did not anticipate any teacher or preacher to bring them the dew of preaching and nurture them with spiritual teaching.
The remnant of Jacob will be among the nations, in the midst of many peoples, like a lion among the beasts of the forest, and like a young lion among flocks of sheep, trampling and capturing with no one able to rescue. And your hand will be exalted over your enemies. The lion is Christ, as stated in Revelation: The Lion of the tribe of Judah has conquered.
He is also the lion cub mentioned in Genesis under the persona of Judah:
"You are a lion's cub, Judah. You have gone up to the prey, my son."
Therefore, the one who is the lion gave the apostles the power to be lions too when he told them:
"Go, teach all nations,"
etc. Just as no one can resist a lion, those who were freed from the hand of the Assyrians received the power to seek out beasts of burden, or irrational humans who lack the word of God.
"Man, though in honor, did not understand,"
etc. They will seize these people, not to tear them apart, but to separate them from the unbelievers. No persecutor will be able to resist them, and the hand of the Lord will be raised over those who afflicted either the Lord himself or his apostles. All your enemies will perish, not by destruction, but by being transformed from enemies and unbelievers into friends and faithful ones.
And on that day, when your hand, O Israel, is exalted over your enemies, I will remove your horses from among you, meaning all lustful impulses of the mind, about which it is said:
"Do not be like the horse or the mule."
I will destroy your chariots, ruin the cities of your land, and demolish all your fortifications. I will also take away your chariots and carriages, meaning the crimes in which you gloried as if triumphing. I will destroy the cities of your land, representing the confidence you had in earthly riches, and, like Cain who first built a city on the earth, you placed your hope in them.
I will take away all your fortifications, namely the diversions and pomp of the world, the eloquence of orators, and the sophistries of dialecticians. I will remove sorceries from your hand and divinations, understood as demonic, by which you were deceived and deceived others. They will not be in you; or he refers to divination as the teachings of the unlearned, who want to teach what they do not know, and as if divining, they teach uncertain things as certain. I will destroy your idols, meaning all false presumptions and perverse doctrines.
And I will remove your idols from among you, and you will no longer worship the works of your hands.
I will uproot your sacred groves from among you and destroy your cities, meaning the false religion and superstition.
Therefore, in the law, it is forbidden to plant a grove in the temple of the Lord.
And the poorly built cities, which were previously called the cities of the land, He threatens to destroy and demolish.
And I will take vengeance in my fury and indignation on all the nations that did not listen.
Because they refused to accept the dew of my word, I will take vengeance in my fury and rage on the nations that were willing to listen, meaning, to obey.
Chapter Six
Listen to what the Lord says:
Rise, argue your case against the mountains, and let the hills hear your voice.
Let the mountains hear the judgment of the Lord.
The prophet speaks, commanding us to listen to what the Lord says.
The mountains metaphorically represent the powerful and wealthy, while the hills represent the subjects and the less powerful.
Then the Lord Himself speaks to the prophet:
Rise, argue your case against the mountains, and let the hills hear your voice.
Again, the prophet, as commanded, speaks to the mountains and the strong foundations of the earth, explaining why he compels them to listen: because the judgment of the Lord is with His people, and with Israel it will be decided.
The mountains and hills can be interpreted as angels, to whom the administration of human affairs is entrusted.
The Apostle calls the angels ministering spirits, sent to serve those who will inherit salvation.
Argue your case with the mountains, that is, with the angels, so that if they are found not to have properly managed human affairs, the blame may be lifted from the people and referred to the leaders, or to me, who appointed such leaders.
In the Book of Revelation, we read that the angels, the leaders of the Churches, are either praised or criticized based on the lives of those they oversee.
Therefore, God, who could inflict punishments for the crimes of a sinful people, does not want to exercise power, but justice, and urges the people of Israel, in the presence of angels and all creation, to speak if they have anything, so that according to the Psalmist, God may be justified in His words and prevail when He is judged.
My people, what have I done to you, and how have I burdened you?
Answer me, because I brought you out of the land of Egypt, freed you from the house of slavery, and sent before you Moses, Aaron, and Miriam.
God speaks to Israel, calling him to judgment and giving him permission to argue against Him.
What have I done that I should not have, or how have I burdened you by oppressing you with hardships?
Did you consider my benefits to be insults, grieving that you lost the cucumbers and pots of Egypt?
I brought you out of the house of slavery with a strong hand, and I provided you with teachers to help you understand my will.
And so that these things do not seem insignificant, my people, please remember what Balak, the king of Moab, planned and how Balaam, the son of Beor, responded to him from Shittim to Gilgal, so that you would know the righteousness of the Lord.
Shittim is a place in the wilderness named after the many trees that grow there, similar to what we call the white thorn.
Gilgal is the place where, after the death of Moses, the people were circumcised by Joshua.
That's why the place was called Gilgal, meaning the hill of foreskins.
Throughout all the places in the wilderness, I have walked with you, moving camps, and always watching over you.
From Shittim, where Israel sinned with the Midianites, to Gilgal, where King Saul was first anointed, I have never left you during this journey.
Even though you often blasphemed against me, I did not allow Balaam to curse you; instead, I made him bless you.
This can be seen morally, referring to us who are in the Church.
Therefore, the Lord disputes with us and argues by giving his Son for our sake into death.
He sent Moses, representing the law, and Aaron, which means mountain of strength, symbolizing Christ, our great high priest.
He also sent Miriam, representing the prophecies of the prophets.
When Balak, whose name means the one who chooses, representing the devil who seeks to devour everyone, and is the king of Moab, meaning from the father of all, to whom it is said: You are from your father the devil.
When Balak wanted to deceive you through Balaam, whose name means a vain people, and is the son of Beor, meaning in the skin, referring to those given to the dead works of the flesh, God did not allow him to harm us.
Instead, he turned Balaam's curse, the curse of the vain people, into a blessing.
The vain people are the Gentiles, born of him who is in the skin, meaning those who always remain in their pleasures.
Their curses and insults have turned into blessings, because now they glorify those they once persecuted and killed.
What worthy offering shall I make to the Lord?
Should I kneel before the Almighty God?
Should I offer Him burnt offerings and year-old calves?
Can the Lord be pleased with thousands of rams or with tens of thousands of fat goats?
God had called the people to judgment, but knowing he had sinned, he did not want to enter into judgment with God; instead, he turned entirely to prayer.
Yet, even in his prayers, he had no confidence because there was nothing worthy enough to offer God for sins.
It is impossible for the blood of goats and calves to take away sins.
Should I give my firstborn for my transgression?
As it is written in the Book of Kings, Moab did this when besieged by the Jews; he climbed the wall and sacrificed his son in front of everyone.
The fruit of my body for the sin of my soul.
And like Jephthah, who offered his daughter for a reckless vow.
But even as we do penance, let us know that there is nothing worthy we can give to please God.
Only through the blood of the spotless and unique Lamb can we be saved, if we imitate His passion and are ready to die for Him.
For the Psalmist, when he asked, "What shall I return to the Lord?" answered himself, "I will take the cup of salvation and call upon the name of the Lord."
If He, who is God, died for us without sin, we who are human and sinners should always be ready to die for Him. I will tell you, O man, what is good and what the Lord requires of you: surely, to do justice and to love mercy. This is said not only to the people of one nation but generally to all humanity: Because you doubt, humanity, that you can please God for your sins, I will tell you what God seeks: surely, to do justice, etc. Moses said something similar in Deuteronomy: "And now, Israel, what does the Lord your God ask of you but to love the Lord your God, to walk in His ways, and to love Him," etc.
God asks us to bring about our own salvation by making judgments, ensuring that we do nothing without advice and reason.
Love mercy, so that we perform acts of kindness not out of necessity or compulsion, but willingly, because God loves a cheerful giver.
And walk humbly with God, so that we are never complacent, always expecting the coming of the Master of the house.
At the very least, we should not stray from His commandments but diligently follow in His footsteps.
For whoever says they abide in Christ ought to walk in the same way He walked.
The voice of the Lord cries to the city, and salvation will come to those who fear His name.
According to the story, the voice refers to the words of Micah, the prophet proclaiming.
The meaning is: The Lord's threat against Samaria is such that the people of Judah, upon hearing of these punishments, will fear and attain salvation.
But also, sinners who fear the punishments they see others suffer are corrected by their example.
What is written is fulfilled in them: When the pestilent is scourged, the foolish become wiser.
Hear, tribes, and who will approve of it?
The fire still burns in the house of the wicked, the treasures of iniquity, and the smaller measure full of wrath.
O ten tribes, who are called Samaria, hear what the Lord bears witness to.
And who has approved it?
That is, rare is the one who wills to act according to what the Lord commands.
The fire, which is iniquity, is still in the house of the wicked, and treasures of impiety are in the royal house.
Then it continues item by item, detailing the evils that will devastate.
The smaller measure, which is injustice, is full of wrath, provoking God's anger.
The unjust scales and differing weights, so that they sell goods with one weight and buy with another.
What is worse, it's not the poor doing this out of necessity, but the rich, more filled with iniquity than with goods.
Hence it follows: Shall I justify wicked scales and deceitful weights in the bag?
In which its rich are filled with iniquity, and its inhabitants speak lies.
From riches follows deception, because a hand accustomed to gathering wealth possesses a fraudulent tongue.
When your leaders committed these and other acts, I didn't want to destroy you immediately.
Instead, I waited and gradually began to strike you with plagues, as a warning to correct yourselves.
I sent hunger, thirst, diseases, and the destruction of crops by enemies.
I made your vineyards barren.
Yet, you continued to serve idolatry and followed the ceremonies established by the wicked King Omri and the works of Ahab and Jezebel.
Therefore, I was compelled to make you a disgrace.
You bore the shame of my people while enemies taunted, saying that God's people had been captured and defeated.
My name was blasphemed through you.
Their deceitful tongues are in their mouths.
So, I began to strike you with destruction for your sins.
You will eat and not be satisfied; your humiliation will be in your midst.
You will grab hold but will not save, and those you save I will give to the sword.
You will sow but will not reap; you will tread olives but will not anoint yourselves with oil.
You will crush grapes but will not drink wine.
You followed the precepts of Omri and all the works of Ahab's house.
You walked in their pleasures, so I will give you to destruction, and all who dwell in it to disgrace.
You will bear the shame of my people.
Chapter Seven
Woe is me, for I have become like someone who gathers grapes in the autumn harvest.
There are no clusters of grapes to eat, and my soul desires early figs.
Now he foretells the captivity of both Judah and Israel, that is, the ten tribes and the two tribes, and laments that there is no one righteous in this people who can resist God’s wrath.
In vain, he says, I have spoken, predicting impending evils; in vain I wanted to convert some from the lost city and gather the remaining grapes from the already harvested vineyard.
And when I could not find any grapes, I wanted at least to eat the immature figs, that is, the unripe figs, because I could not find good ripe ones.
It is like someone saying, because I could not find bread, I wanted to eat scraps and bran due to the great famine.
The prophet himself explains this analogy, saying:
The holy has perished from the earth, and there is no upright person among men.
Everyone lies in wait to shed blood; a man hunts his brother to death, and the evil deeds of their hands they call good.
Not only do they commit these evils, but they also defend them, perversely calling what is good evil, and what is evil good.
The prince demands, and the judge is in return.
Because they do not take gifts from those who offer willingly, but force their subjects to give.
Therefore, the judge is in return, because he judges another as he himself is judged by another, so they protect each other with mutual favor.
And the great one speaks the desire of his soul.
He who is great among them and most learned in the law, speaks not God’s will, but his own.
And they have troubled it, that is, the city or the land, of which he said: The holy has perished from the earth.
The best among them is like a thorn bush, pricking and wounding anyone who approaches.
And the upright is like a thorn from the hedge, so that pain is felt where help was expected.
The day of your watch, your visitation has come; now will be their devastation.
Do not trust a friend.
He calls the day of watch the devastation of Samaria or Jerusalem, which he foretells will come.
He calls that devastation visitation.
Now comes the desolation of the inhabitants.
Therefore, do not believe the words of any prophets, nor lend your ear to the flattery of deceivers.
If faith is rare among friends and relatives, how much more so among those who lie to gain something by flattering?
Therefore, do not believe a friend, because Ahithophel betrayed his friend David, and Judas betrayed Christ.
And do not trust in a leader, like the Shechemites trusted Abimelech, whom they made king, only to be killed by him.
Guard the doors of your mouth from her who lies in your bosom, lest you suffer what Samson did from Delilah.
A son dishonors his father, like Absalom did to David, defiling his father's concubines.
A daughter rises against her mother, as we see daily.
A daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law, like Esau's wife against Rebekah.
A man's enemies are the members of his own household.
Since these things are so, do not believe, O citizens of Samaria or Jerusalem, in false prophets.
I do not trust in their false promises; I look to the Lord and His mercy.
I will wait for my God, my Savior, and I am certain that the Lord my God will hear me.
Do not rejoice over me, my enemy, because although I have fallen, I will rise again.
When I sit in darkness, the Lord is my light.
I will bear the wrath of the Lord, because I have sinned against Him, until He judges my case and executes my judgment.
He will bring me out into the light, I will see His justice, and my enemy will see me and be covered with shame, she who said to me: Where is the Lord your God?
My eyes will see her, now she will be trampled down like mud in the streets.
The voice of Jerusalem against Babylon and the other nations that rejoiced in her downfall: O Babylon, my enemy, do not rejoice, do not be glad over me, because I have fallen due to my own fault.
For after I bear the wrath of the Lord, I will rise again, because He is my light in the darkness of tribulations.
I know that my God will lead me out of distress, and my eyes will see His justice, which means the vengeance He will bring soon.
In their presence, they will be trampled down and devastated by the Medes and Persians.
This is the voice of Jerusalem or the prophet, speaking on behalf of the people:
Now, the message is directed to Jerusalem itself:
O Jerusalem, the days have come for your walls, which were destroyed by the Chaldeans, to be rebuilt.
On that day, the command that you serve them will be far removed, and you will no longer be subjected to Babylonian rule.
On that day, when your walls are being rebuilt, Assyria will come to you, and to the fortified cities, from the river to the sea, and from mountain to mountain, and the land will be desolate because of its inhabitants.
This means the Assyrians, fleeing, will come even from the fortified cities they had abandoned, to the Jordan River, and to the Dead Sea, from the Red Sea to Mount Zion, and from the mountains of the Persians and Medes, to whom Israel had previously been taken.
The land of the Chaldeans will be desolate because of its inhabitants and the evil deeds, which are the fruits of their evil thoughts.
These things can be morally applied to the faithful soul, which is Jerusalem, and in which is the temple of God, or which is the temple of God.
When it is tempted by the devil because of its sins or is worn down by various tribulations, it should not despair of mercy but should rise up against the enemies, meaning the demons, who mock our misfortunes and say: I will arise because the Lord is my light; He will lead me from darkness into light.
For all tribulation in the present seems not to be of joy, but afterward, it will yield the most peaceful fruit of righteousness to those who have been trained by it.
When the Lord rescues us from many troubles, the enemies of the soul, the evil spirits of Babylon— which means the followers of confusion—will see it and be ashamed.
They will be trampled and despised, while the saints rejoice and celebrate their liberation and the just condemnation of the wicked.
Feed your people with your staff, the flock of your inheritance.
The voice of God the Father speaks to the Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, who is the good shepherd, and commands Him to feed the people with the staff and the flock of His inheritance.
Speaking clearly, He shows that the people are one thing and the flock another, as the Psalmist also says: We are your people and the sheep of your pasture.
The people are those who use reason and know how to distinguish truth from falsehood, while the sheep are the simple ones who need to be guided by teachers.
So when He says: Feed the people and the flock of your inheritance, He shows that both the people and the sheep need the staff to be governed by the Lord, just as Moses was told when he was sent to Pharaoh: You will take the staff of God in your hand.
Therefore, they need to be fed and governed with the staff because they live alone in the forest, which we understand as those who separate themselves from the Church and live in the forest of the Gentiles, enjoying their friendships.
Or those who, because of pride, separate themselves from the company of other people to appear holier.
This is what we read that many Gentiles did, who, detesting the communion of the human race, lived in the forest of vices and were trampled by beasts, that is, demons.
However, the holy hermits were alone but did not live in the forest; they lived in the pleasantness of virtues.
Therefore, those who are alone and live in the forest of vices need to be fed and governed with the staff.
For the good shepherd does not abandon such people but calls them back and corrects them.
Hence it follows: In the midst of Carmel, they will graze in Bashan and Gilead as in the days of old, according to the days of your exodus from the land of Egypt, I will show him wonders.
The nations will see and be ashamed of all their might.
Mount Carmel is very fertile.
It's called Carmel in Greek and Latin, and Chermel in Hebrew.
Carmel means "knowledge of circumcision," Basan means "confusion," and Galaad means "migration of testimony."
So, the Gentile people, who were once without a shepherd and wandered in the forest of error, will be brought to Carmel, which signifies the knowledge of true circumcision, and they will serve the Lord in spirit.
Recognizing their mistakes, they will experience a useful confusion, bringing glory, as Basan suggests. When they are confused because of their sins, they will be nourished in Galaad, meaning "migration of testimony." This means they will return to the Church, to which the testimonies of the old law have migrated. This will happen according to ancient times, of which Moses also says: "Remember the days of old," etc.
They will remember the days of old, those who do not focus on the present but on the things above, where Christ is seated at the right hand of God. He will also show them wonders that no eye has seen and no ear has heard.
Then all the nations that once afflicted the people of God will see and be confused about all their strength, which they used against the saints of God. But the good will have this confusion because they will understand their sins. They will put their hands over their mouths and will not have the freedom to speak.
They are said to put their hands over their mouths because hands represent work, and being ashamed of their evil deeds, they will remain silent. On the other hand, the righteous open their mouths with their hands, because through good works they gain the ability to speak with the Lord.
Their ears will also be deaf because they did not want to hear the voice of Christ. Like deaf serpents, they stopped their ears to avoid hearing the voice of the charmer, that is, Christ wisely preaching about whom it is still said: "They will lick the dust like serpents, like crawling things of the earth, they will be disturbed from their houses."
Serpents crawl on their bellies and drag the earth as they move, and they eat the earth. Similarly, the wicked engage in earthly works and consume the earth because they are nourished by earthly temptations.
They crawl on their stomachs because they serve their bellies and throats, making their stomach their god.
They drag themselves toward the day of God's righteous judgment.
They will be troubled in their homes or in confinements when they find themselves trapped and confined.
They do not fear their Lord God, but ours, because they do not yet deserve Him as their God.
They will long for the Lord our God, and they will fear you.
While referring to them in the third person, he suddenly turns to Christ and says: They will fear you, therefore they will be silenced and endure what has been said, so that they may fear you, O Christ, because the beginning of wisdom is the fear of the Lord.
Who, God, is like you, who takes away iniquity and overlooks the sin of the remnants of your heritage?
The prophet, understanding that the Lord is angry with the nations to trouble and confuse them, hopes He will spare the troubled and confused, take away their sins, and grant them salvation.
He marvels and praises the goodness of God, saying: Who, God, is like you?
No one.
Who takes away iniquity and overlooks the sin of the remnants of your heritage?
Just as once in Egypt, the destroying angel, seeing the blood on the doors of the Israelites, passed over and did not harm them, He will no longer unleash His rage because He desires mercy.
He will return and have mercy on us.
He will take away our iniquities and cast all our sins into the depths of the sea, meaning He will not be angry forever but will sometimes have mercy on the Jewish people, just as He had mercy on the nations.
For God, desiring mercy because He is merciful, will return by showing mercy to those He had rejected.
He casts our sins into the depths of the sea so they no longer appear.
You will give truth to Jacob and mercy to Abraham, which you swore to our fathers from days of old.
That truth, he says, which you promised to your servant Jacob, and the mercy which you promised to your beloved Abraham, you will give to those who believe in you from both peoples.
For by Jacob, who is called the supplanter, the ancient people of the Jews is understood, who, believing in Christ, supplanted unbelief.
So, He will fulfill the rewards He promised them through Abraham, the father of many nations.
This implies a multitude of nations, who by believing in Christ, have become the children of Abraham.
He will graciously grant them mercy and justify them from their sins by His own merit.
You swore, or immutably promised, to the fathers of true faith that from the entire multitude of people, You would save some by truth and others by mercy.
For all the ways of the Lord are mercy and truth.