Exhortation to the Bride of Christ
We learn about the immense happiness that holy virginity holds in heaven, not only from the testimonies of Scripture but also from the customs of the Church.
We understand that it has a special merit because it has a unique consecration.
While the entire crowd of believers receives the same gifts of grace and all boast in the same blessings of the Sacraments, these have something special.
From the holy and immaculate flock of the Church, they are chosen by the Holy Spirit as holier and purer offerings due to their merits of will and are offered on the altar by the highest Priest of God.
The offering of such a valuable being is a worthy sacrifice to the Lord, and no sacrifice pleases Him more than the offering of His own image.
I believe the Apostle particularly referred to this when he said:
Romans twelve, verse one:
"I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God, that you present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God."
Therefore, virginity possesses what others have and what others do not have:
it receives both common and special grace, and enjoys, so to speak, a unique privilege of consecration.
Ecclesiastical authority allows us to call virgins the brides of Christ; it veils those it consecrates to the Lord in the manner of brides, showing that they will have a spiritual marriage the most, who have avoided carnal companionship.
They are worthily united spiritually to God through the comparison of marriage, who have rejected human marriages for the sake of His love.
In them, the saying of the Apostle is most fully realized:
First Corinthians six, verse seventeen:
"But he who is joined to the Lord is one spirit."
It is a great and immortal thing, almost beyond bodily nature, to subdue luxury, extinguish the flame of youthful lust with the strength of the mind, and exclude the power of genuine pleasure through spiritual effort.
To live against the custom of the human race, to despise the comforts of spouses, to scorn the sweetness of children, and to reckon all the conveniences of the present life as nothing in the hope of future happiness.
This is great, as I said, and an admirable virtue, not undeservedly awarded a great reward for its vast labor.
The Lord says, "I will give my eunuchs in my house and within my walls a memorial and a name better than sons and daughters; I will give them an everlasting name that will not be cut off" (Isaiah fifty-six, verse four).
About these eunuchs, the Lord repeats in the Gospel, saying: "For there are eunuchs who have made themselves eunuchs for the sake of the kingdom of heaven" (Matthew nineteen, verse twelve).
Indeed, the labor of chastity is great, but the reward is greater: the vigilance is temporary, but the reward is eternal.
About these, the blessed apostle John also speaks, saying that they follow the Lamb wherever he goes (Revelation fourteen, verse four).
This means that no place in the heavenly court is closed to them, and all the dwellings of the divine mansions are opened to them.
To make the merit of virginity shine more brightly, and to understand more clearly how worthy it is of God, consider this: our Lord and Savior God, when he deigned to take on human nature for the salvation of mankind, chose no other than a virginal womb.
To show that this pleases him greatly, and to intimate the good of chastity to both sexes, he had a virgin mother while remaining a virgin himself.
He provided an example of virginity to men in himself and to women in his mother, so that it might be shown that blessed integrity is held in both sexes from the fullness of divinity; all that was in the mother was also in the son.
But why do I strive to reveal the excellent and sublime merit of chastity and to show the good of glorious virginity, when many have already spoken on this matter, proving its blessedness with the clearest reasons?
It cannot come into doubt for any wise person that the thing of greater merit is the one that involves greater labor.
For whoever considers chastity to be of no reward, or of little reward, it is certain that he either does not know, or does not willingly bear the labor.
Hence, those who always disparage chastity are those who either do not have it or are forced to have it unwillingly.
Now, since it's allowed to show both the effort and the value of integrity to a few, we must be diligent so that something of great virtue and significant reward does not go without its due benefits.
The more precious something is, the more carefully it must be guarded.
Many things lack intrinsic value unless supported by others-like honey, which loses its grace without the protection of wax and the honeycomb, or wine, which loses its sweetness unless kept in a good vessel and refreshed often.
We need to be even more attentive in these cases.
Therefore, we must ensure that virginity does not fail to bear fruit without the necessary support.
Great effort will be of no benefit if it lacks the essential elements to be genuinely useful.
Chastity is preserved for the reward of the heavenly kingdom, which cannot be achieved without the merit of eternal life.
Scripture tells us that eternal life is earned by keeping all divine commandments, saying: "If you want to enter life, keep the commandments" (Matthew 19:17).
Therefore, only those who keep all the commandments have life; and without life, one cannot possess the heavenly kingdom, where the living, not the dead, shall reign.
Thus, virginity alone is not enough for those who hope for the glory of the heavenly kingdom; it must be accompanied by the promise of eternal life, through which the reward of the heavenly kingdom is attained.
Therefore, those who preserve chastity and integrity and hope for its reward from God's justice must keep the commandments, so that the effort of glorious chastity and continence is not in vain.
No wise reader is unaware that virginity is above a commandment or precept, as the Apostle says: "Now concerning virgins, I have no commandment of the Lord, but I give my judgment" (First Corinthians 7:25).
Since he gives advice on obtaining virginity, he does not establish it as a command.
He declared it to be above a mandate or command.
Therefore, whoever maintains virginity does more than what is commanded.
It is more advantageous to have done more than what is commanded if you do what is commanded.
If you desire to fulfill the divine counsel, above all, keep the commandment.
If you want to obtain the reward of virginity, embrace the merits of life, so that your chastity may be rewarded.
Just as keeping the commandments grants life, breaking them leads to death.
And whoever is condemned to death by transgression cannot hope for the crown of virginity, nor can he expect the reward of chastity if he is destined for punishment.
There are three ways to enter the heavenly kingdom.
The first is chastity, the second is contempt of the world, and the third is justice.
These, when connected, greatly benefit those who possess them.
But when divided, they can hardly be beneficial, as each is required not only for itself but for the sake of the others.
Therefore, chastity is sought first, so that contempt of the world may more easily follow.
For the world can be more easily despised by those who are not bound by marital ties.
Contempt of the world is then needed to preserve justice, which those entangled in secular goods and worldly pleasures can hardly fulfill!
Whoever possesses chastity but does not attain contempt of the world almost possesses chastity in vain, since he does not have contempt of the world, for which chastity was sought.
And if he possesses chastity and contempt of the world but lacks justice, he labors in vain.
For chastity and contempt of the world are especially required for the sake of justice.
What benefit is it to have chastity for the sake of contempt of the world if you do not have what you sought it for?
Or why despise worldly things if you do not keep justice, for which you ought to have chastity and contempt of the world?
Because just as the first thing exists for the sake of the second, the first and second exist for the sake of the third.
If the third does not exist, neither the first nor the second will be of any use.
You may say, "Then teach me what justice is so that if I understand it, I can more easily fulfill it." I will speak as briefly as I can and use simple, common words because the matter we are discussing should not be obscured by eloquent speeches but explained with simpler expressions. A matter necessary to the community should be shown in common language.
Therefore, justice is nothing other than not sinning.
Not sinning means keeping the commandments of the law.
The keeping of the commandments is preserved in two ways: by not doing what is forbidden and by striving to do all that is commanded.
This is what is meant by: Turn away from evil and do good.
I do not want you to think that justice consists only in not doing evil; since not doing good is also evil, and in both cases, the law is violated.
For the same one who said, "Turn away from evil," also said, "do good."
If you turn away from evil and do not do good, you are a transgressor of the law; which is fulfilled not only in the abhorrence of evil actions but also in the perfection of good works.
Indeed, it is not only commanded that you do not steal clothes from the clothed, but also that you clothe the naked with your own clothes: not only that you do not take bread from someone who has it, but that you generously share your bread with those who do not have any: not only that you do not turn away a poor person from their lodging, but that you receive the expelled and the homeless into your own home.
For we are commanded, "Weep with those who weep."
How can we weep with them if we do not share in any of their needs, nor offer them any help in the causes for which they weep?
God doesn't seek the unfruitful moisture of our tears.
Tears are a sign of sorrow, and He wants you to feel another's distress as if it were your own.
Just as you would wish to be helped in such a tribulation if you were in it, you should help another because:
"Whatever you want people to do for you, do likewise for them"
Matthew 7:11.
To weep with someone and offer nothing when you can is a sign of mockery, not piety.
Indeed, our Savior wept with Mary and Martha, the sisters of Lazarus. By shedding tears, He showed a great sense of mercy. True signs of piety were soon followed by action when Lazarus, for whom the tears were shed, was raised and returned to his sisters. This was to weep piously with those who weep, to remove the cause of weeping.
You might say, He did this as someone powerful. Yet nothing impossible is commanded of you: He who did what He could accomplished everything.
As we began to say, it is not enough for a Christian to abstain from evil unless he also fulfills the duties of good works. This is confirmed especially by the testimony that the Lord threatens eternal fire for those who, although they have done no evil, have not done all that is good, saying:
"Then the King will say to those on His left: Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels. For I was hungry, and you did not give me food," etc.
Matthew 25:41.
He did not say: Depart from me, you cursed, because you committed murder, adultery, or theft. They are not condemned because they did evil; but because they did not do good, they are condemned and consigned to the punishments of eternal hell. Not because they committed prohibited acts; but because they refused to perform the commanded ones.
Hence, it should be noted what hope those can have who still commit any of the prohibited acts; when even those are condemned who did not do what was commanded.
I don't want you to comfort yourself by thinking that if you haven't done some things, it's okay because you've done others.
It is written: "Whoever keeps the whole law but fails in one point has become guilty of all of it" (James 2:10).
Adam sinned once and died; do you think you can live while committing often what killed another when he did it once?
Do you think he committed a great crime and deserved a harsher punishment?
Let's see what he did against the command.
He ate from the fruit of the tree.
So, did God punish man with death because of the fruit of the tree?
Not because of the fruit, but because of the contempt for the command.
Therefore, it's not about the quality of the sin but the transgression of the command.
The one who told Adam not to eat the fruit of the tree also commanded you: not to curse, not to lie, not to slander, not to listen to slanderers, not to swear at all, not to lust, not to envy, not to be lukewarm, not to be greedy; not to return evil for evil, to love your enemies, to bless those who curse you, to pray for those who slander and persecute you, to offer the other cheek to the one who strikes you, not to argue in secular courts, to gladly lose what someone wants to take from you, not to let anger, jealousy, or spite into your heart, to avoid the crime of greed, to beware of all pride and boasting, and to live humbly and gently like Christ; avoiding the company of the wicked so much that you do not even eat with fornicators, or the greedy, or those who curse, or the envious, or slanderers, or drunkards, or robbers.
If you despise any of these commands, if He spared Adam, He will spare you too.
No, Adam should have been spared more, as he was still inexperienced and new, without the example of anyone else who had sinned and died because of it.
But you, after so much evidence, after the law, after the Prophets, after the Gospels, after the Apostles, if you choose to sin, I don't know how He could forgive you.
Do you comfort yourself with the privilege of virginity?
Remember that Adam and Eve, being virgins, sinned, and their bodily purity did not help them when they sinned.
A virgin who sins should be compared to Eve, not Mary.
We do not deny that there is a remedy for repentance at present; but we urge that one should hope more for the reward than for forgiveness.
It is disgraceful for those who expect the reward of virginity to seek indulgence for their sin.
It is wrong to do anything illicit for those who have even abstained from lawful acts.
While it is lawful to enter into the partnership of marriage, those who, for the love of Christ and the glory of the heavenly kingdom, have chosen to renounce marriage are to be praised.
However, those who, in their pursuit of innocence, misuse the apostolic remedy without being devoted to God are not to be condemned.
Therefore, as we said, those who despise marriage, despise what is lawful, not what is illicit.
But if such people swear, curse, slander, endure hearing slanderers, repay evil for evil, fall into the crime of greed or avarice, harbor jealousy or envy, speak or think indecent things against legal and apostolic institutions, or indulge in worldly desires while adorned and dressed finely, what benefit is there in despising what was lawful and doing what is not lawful?
If you want the benefit of having renounced what was lawful, see to it that you do not engage in what is unlawful.
For it is foolish to fear what is less and not to fear what is greater, or to avoid what is permitted only to fall into what is prohibited.
For the Apostle says: The unmarried woman cares about the things of the Lord, how she may please God, that she may be holy both in body and spirit.
But the married woman cares about the things of this world, how she may please her husband (First Corinthians 7:34).
He asserts that the married woman pleases her husband by caring about worldly things, but the unmarried woman pleases God because she has no concern for worldly matters.
Let the woman who does not have a husband and yet cares about worldly things tell me whom she desires to please.
Will not the married woman begin to be preferred to her?
Because she, thinking about worldly things, pleases her husband.
But the unmarried woman, who has no husband, can please neither her husband nor God.
We should not overlook what was said:
"The unmarried woman thinks about the things of the Lord, how she may please God, to be holy in body and spirit" (First Corinthians 7:34).
So, what are the things of the Lord?
The Apostle says: "Whatever is holy, whatever is just, whatever is lovely, whatever is of good report. If there is any virtue, if there is any praise of discipline" (Psalm 4:8).
These are the things of the Lord, which holy and true virgins meditate on and think about day and night without interruption.
The kingdom of heaven belongs to the Lord; the resurrection of the dead belongs to the Lord; immortality belongs to the Lord; incorruption belongs to the Lord; the splendor of the sun promised to the saints belongs to the Lord, as it is written in the Gospel:
"Then the righteous will shine like the sun in the kingdom of their Father" (Matthew 13).
Many mansions of the saints in heaven belong to the Lord; the thirtyfold, sixtyfold, and hundredfold fruit belong to the Lord.
These are what they think about and consider, how they can deserve the things of the Lord.
The law of the New and Old Testament also belongs to the Lord, in which His holy words shine.
If virgins meditate on these things without cessation, they think about the things of the Lord; and it is fulfilled in them that prophetic statement:
"Eternal foundations on solid rock; and the commandments of the Lord in the heart of a holy woman" (Ecclesiasticus 26:24).
It follows:
"How to please God."
God, I say, not men:
"To be holy in body and spirit" (First Corinthians 7:34).
He did not say to be holy in just one member or only in the body; but to be holy in both body and spirit.
For a member is just one part of the body: the body is the union of all members.
So, when he says to be holy in body, he means she should be sanctified in all her members.
Because the sanctification of the other members will not benefit if corruption is found in even one.
And she will no longer be holy in body, which consists of all members, if it is polluted by the defilement of even one.
To make my point clearer and more understandable:
Imagine that all parts of the body are purified through sanctification, but the tongue alone sins, whether by blaspheming or bearing false witness.
Will all the other parts save the one?
Or will all be judged because of the one?
Therefore, if the sanctification of other parts won't help when there's a flaw in one, how much more, if all are corrupted by various grievous sins, will the integrity of one part be of no benefit?
Hence, I urge you, virgin, do not take pride only in your chastity, nor trust in the integrity of a single part: but according to the Apostle, keep the sanctity of the body for God alone.
Cleanse your head from all pollution, for it is a crime to defile it with paint or powder after the sanctification of chrism, saffron, or any other pigment; or to adorn it with gold or gems of any earthly kind when it already shines with the splendor of heavenly adornment.
Indeed, it is a great insult to divine grace to prefer worldly and secular ornamentation.
Cleanse your forehead, so that it may not be ashamed of human works but may accept that shame which brings not sin but the glory of God, as Scripture says: "There is a shame that leads to sin, and there is a shame that leads to glory"
Sirach 4:25.
Cleanse your neck, so that your hair does not bear golden nets and hanging necklaces, but rather wears those ornaments of which Scripture says: "Let not mercy and truth forsake you; bind them around your neck"
Proverbs 3:13.
Cleanse your eyes by withdrawing them from all lust and never turning away from the sight of the poor, and keep them free from all cosmetics, preserving their purity as created by God.
Cleanse your tongue from lying, for "a lying mouth kills the soul"
Wisdom 1:11.
Cleanse it from slander, swearing, flattery, and perjury.
Do not find it odd that I said the tongue should be cleansed from swearing before perjury, for you will more easily avoid perjury if you do not swear at all.
Let this message take root in you:
Keep your tongue from evil and your lips from speaking deceit.
Psalm 34.
And remember what the Apostle says:
Bless and do not curse.
Romans 12:14.
But keep this in mind even more often:
See that no one repays evil for good to anyone, nor curse for curse, but on the contrary, bless: because you were called to this, that you might inherit a blessing.
First Peter 3:9;
and also this: If anyone does not offend in speech, he is a perfect man.
James 3:2.
It is wrong for the lips that confess, pray, bless, and praise the Lord to be tainted by sin.
How can someone pray to God with the same lips they use to lie, curse, or slander?
God hears holy lips and quickly grants the prayers of an unblemished tongue.
Cleanse your ears to listen only to holy and true words;
never accept obscene, foul, or worldly words, nor listen to slander, as it is written: Hedge your ears with thorns, and do not listen to a wicked tongue.
Ecclesiasticus 28:29;
So that you may be among the righteous, who neither sin with their ears nor with their eyes.
Let your hands not be eager to receive but rather quick to give, not ready to strike but eager for all works of mercy and piety.
Cleanse your feet so they do not walk the broad and spacious path leading to worldly pleasures; walk the hard and narrow path that leads to heaven, as it is written:
Make a straight path for your feet.
Isaiah 57:14.
Recognize that your limbs were formed by God not for vice, but for virtue:
and when you have cleansed all your limbs from every stain of sin, and have sanctified your whole body, then you will understand the value of chastity, and with confidence, expect the reward of virginity.
What it means to be holy in body, I believe I have explained briefly but fully.
Now, we should understand what follows: to be holy in spirit.
This means that what is wrong to do should not even be conceived in thought.
For she is holy both in body and spirit, who neither sins in mind nor heart; knowing that God is the inspector of the heart.
Therefore, she strives to keep both her mind and body pure from sin, knowing it is written:
"Above all else, guard your heart" (Proverbs 4:23); and again: "The Lord loves holy hearts; and all who are blameless are accepted by Him"; and elsewhere: "Blessed are the pure in heart, for they shall see God" (Matthew 5:8).
I believe this is said of those whose conscience does not accuse them of any sin.
About whom John says in his Epistle:
"If our heart does not condemn us, we have confidence before God, and we receive from Him whatever we ask" (First John 3:20).
Do not think you have escaped the crime of sin if the will is not followed by the act, since it is written:
"Whoever looks at a woman to lust for her has already committed adultery with her in his heart" (Matthew 5:28).
Nor should you say, "I thought about it, but did not do it," because even to lust is wrong. Hence, blessed Peter commanded, saying: "Purify your souls" (First Peter 1:22), for if he knew of no defilement of the soul, he would not have desired it to be purified.
We should carefully consider and pay attention to the passage that contains:
"These are the ones who did not defile themselves with women, for they remained virgins. They follow the Lamb wherever He goes" (Revelation 14:4), and understand whether solely by the merit of chastity they are joined to the divine company and traverse all the realms of heaven, or if there are other things by which virginity achieves such great glory.
But how can we know this?
From the following, if I am not mistaken, in which it is written:
"These were redeemed from among men, the firstfruits to God and the Lamb, and in their mouth no lie was found; they are blameless" (Revelation 14:5).
You see, therefore, that it's not just one person who is called to follow the Lord's footsteps, but also those who, besides living in virginity, have led a life free from any sin.
This is why a virgin often scorns marriage, to better guard herself from sin and fulfill all the commandments of the law, which are also expected of those who marry.
If she does not marry but still follows the same rules as married women, what advantage is there in remaining single?
While no Christian is permitted to sin and all who are cleansed by spiritual washing should live a pure life to be part of the Church-described as without stain, wrinkle, or any blemish-it is even more crucial for a virgin to uphold this, as she is not hindered by the obligations of a husband or children.
If she sins, she cannot be excused.
O Virgin, uphold the commitment destined for you with great reward.
The virtue of virginity and chastity is splendid before God if it remains untainted by other sins and evils.
Recognize your state, recognize your place, recognize your commitment.
You are called the bride of Christ; ensure you do nothing unworthy of Him to whom you are betrothed.
He will quickly write a repudiation if He sees even one act of infidelity in you.
Just as a person engaged with human betrothals eagerly inquires about the character of their future spouse-asking domestic servants, acquaintances, friends, and servants about what the groom likes, how he lives, and what he delights in-
when she learns these things, she moderates herself in all aspects so that her service, joy, diligence, and life align with the groom's character.
And you, who have Christ as your bridegroom, ask his household and close friends about your bridegroom's ways.
Diligently and skillfully inquire what he especially delights in, what kind of clothing he prefers you to wear, and what kind of adornment he desires.
Let Peter, his closest friend, tell you.
He doesn't even permit physical adornment for married women, as he wrote in his letter:
"Likewise, wives be subject to your own husbands, so that if some do not believe the word, they may be won without a word by the conduct of their wives, when they see your respectful and pure conduct."
"Do not let your adorning be external-the braiding of hair and the putting on of gold jewelry, or the clothing you wear-but let your adorning be the hidden person of the heart with the imperishable beauty of a gentle and quiet spirit, which in God's sight is very precious."
This is from the First Letter of Peter, chapter three.
Let another apostle, the blessed Paul, who wrote to Timothy, a bishop, testify the same about the discipline of faithful women:
"Likewise, women should adorn themselves in respectable apparel, with modesty and self-control, not with braided hair and gold or pearls or costly attire, but with what is proper for women who profess godliness-with good works."
This is from the First Letter to Timothy, chapter two.
But perhaps you ask: why did the apostles not give these instructions to virgins as well? Because they did not judge it necessary, lest such a reminder might seem more like an insult than an improvement to virgins. Nor did they ever believe that virgins would be so reckless as to presume to use even the worldly ornaments allowed to married women.
Indeed, a virgin ought to adorn and arrange herself. How could she please her bridegroom if she did not appear adorned and arranged? She should certainly adorn herself, but with inner adornments, and be arranged spiritually, not carnally, for God considers the beauty of the soul, not of the body.
Therefore, you too, whoever you are, who desire your soul to be loved and inhabited by God, arrange it with all diligence and adorn it with spiritual garments. Let nothing shameful or disgraceful appear in it.
Let the gold of justice shine, let the gems of holiness sparkle, and let the most precious pearl of chastity glisten.
Instead of fine linen and silk, be clothed with the tunic of mercy and piety, as it is written:
"Put on therefore, as God's chosen ones, holy and beloved, hearts of mercy, kindness, humility," etc.
Colossians 3:12.
Do not seek the beauty of white lead or any other paint, but have the brightness of innocence and simplicity. Possess the rosy color of modesty and the purple blush of bashfulness and shame.
Be washed with the heavenly nitre of doctrine, and cleansed with spiritual tears. Let no stain of malice, no spot of the devil remain in you; and to avoid the odor of sin, be anointed with the most pleasant perfume of wisdom and knowledge.
This is the kind of adornment God seeks, and He desires a soul composed in this manner. Remember that you are called the daughter of God as He says:
"Listen, daughter, and see" (Psalm 45:11).
Every time you call God Father, you testify that you are a daughter of God.
Therefore, if you are a daughter of God, ensure you do nothing inappropriate for God the Father; do everything as a daughter of God.
Consider how the daughters of nobility in this world conduct themselves, what manners they are accustomed to, and what disciplines they follow.
Some exhibit such great modesty, dignity, and self-control that they surpass the customs of others by the grace of their natural nobility.
To avoid bringing disgrace upon their honorable parents, they strive to create another nature for themselves through their habits.
Therefore, remember your origin, consider your lineage, and take note of the glory of your nobility: recognize that you are the daughter not of a human, but of God, and adorned with the nobility of divine birth.
Conduct yourself in a way that your heavenly birth is evident in you, and your divine nobility shines forth.
Let there be in you a new sense of seriousness, admirable honesty, stunning modesty, remarkable patience, a virginal demeanor, genuine chastity, and always modest speech, spoken at the right time.
So that anyone who sees you may marvel and say: What kind of patience is this new seriousness among people?
What kind of modesty is this chastity?
What kind of modesty is this honesty?
What kind of maturity is this wisdom?
This is not a human teaching, nor a mortal discipline; it seems heavenly in a human body.
I think that God lives in some people.
And when they know you are a servant of Christ, they will be even more in awe and will think about what kind of Lord He is, whose servant is so extraordinary.
If you want to be with Christ and share in Christ, you must live by Christ's example, who was so free from all malice and wickedness that He did not repay even His enemies, but rather prayed for them.
I do not want you to consider those souls as Christians who do not love their brothers or sisters, not to mention hating them, but who do not love their neighbors with all their heart and conscience before God's witness; since Christians, in the likeness of Christ, must also love their enemies.
If you wish to have the company of saints, cleanse your heart from thoughts of malice and wickedness.
Let no one deceive you, let no one seduce you with false speech.
Only the holy, righteous, simple, innocent, and pure will be accepted in the heavenly court.
Malice has no place with God.
Whoever wishes to reign with Christ must be free from all wickedness and deceit.
Nothing is so contrary, nothing is so detestable to God, as to hate someone or to want to harm someone: nothing is so commendable as to love everyone.
The Prophet, knowing this, testifies by saying: You who love the Lord, hate evil.
(Psalm 97:10)
See that you do not love human glory in anything; lest your portion be counted among those of whom it was said: How can you believe, who receive glory from one another?
(John 5:44) And about whom the Prophet says: Increase their troubles, increase the troubles of the proud of the earth.
Be ashamed of your boasting, of your disgrace in the sight of God.
I do not want you to look at those who are virgins of the world, not of Christ; who forget their purpose and profession, rejoice in luxuries, delight in wealth, and take pride in their noble birth.
If they truly believed they were daughters of God, they would never admire human nobility after divine birth, nor boast in any honored father.
If they felt they had God as their Father, they would not love earthly nobility.
Why do you flatter yourself with noble lineage?
God made two humans from the beginning, from whom the entire human race descended.
Worldly nobility was not given by the fairness of nature, but by the ambition of greed.
Surely we are all made equal through the rebirth of divine baptism, and there can be no distinction among those born of the second birth; through which both rich and poor, free and slave, noble and ignoble, become Children of God.
Earthly nobility is overshadowed by the splendor of heavenly glory, and it no longer appears at all.
Those who were unequal in worldly honors are equally clothed in the glory of heavenly and divine nobility.
There is no place for lowliness, nor is anyone degenerate, whom the greatness of divine birth adorns, except among those who do not think that heavenly things should be preferred over human things.
Or if they do think so, how vain it is to prefer themselves in lesser things to those whom they know to be equal to themselves in greater things.
And who they believe to be equal with them in heavenly matters, they consider to be below them on earth?
But you, whoever you are, a virgin of Christ, not of the world, flee all the glory of this present life, so that you may attain that which is promised in the future.
Avoid words of contention and reasons for hostility; also avoid occasions of discord and disputes.
For if, according to the teaching of the Apostle: The servant of the Lord must not quarrel,
to
Timothy
2:24
How much more so for the handmaiden of God?
Whose sex is more modest, her mind should be even more modest.
Restrain your tongue from speaking evil, and put the bridle of the Law on your mouth.
If you must speak when it would be a sin to remain silent, be careful not to say anything reproachable.
A spoken word is like a thrown stone; therefore, consider it for a long time before speaking.
Blessed are those lips that never utter what they would wish to take back.
The speech of a pure mind should also be pure, always building up rather than sometimes destroying the listeners, as the Apostle commanded, saying:
Let no evil talk come out of your mouths, but only what is good for building up faith, so that it may give grace to those who hear.
Precious to God is the tongue that constructs words only in divine matters; and holy is the mouth from which heavenly words are always spoken.
Deter those who speak ill of the absent as if they were malicious, by the authority of Scripture: for the Prophet mentions among the virtues of a perfect man that if a wicked person is brought to nothing before the sight of the just, he who speaks unfounded accusations against his neighbor should be silenced.
Do not patiently listen to the slander of another; because you would not wish your own to be received by others.
It is unjust to do anything against the Gospel of Christ if you endure something being inflicted on another that you would find distressing if done to you.
Always train your tongue to speak of good things, and adapt your hearing more to the praise of good deeds than to the criticism of bad ones.
Ensure that you do everything for the sake of God; knowing that you will only receive a reward from the Lord for what you have accomplished out of fear and love of Him.
Seek to be holy more than to seem holy; for it does no good to be thought of as what you are not, and it is a double fault to lack what is believed about you and to pretend to have what you do not.
Delight more in fasting than in feasting, remembering that widow who did not leave the temple, serving God with fasting and prayers night and day.
And if such a widow existed in Judea, how much more fitting it is for a virgin of Christ to be so now.
Value the feast of divine reading and yearn to be filled with spiritual foods.
Seek nourishment for the soul more than the body.
Avoid meats and wines that can stir up heat and incite lust, and only use a small amount of wine if stomach pain or extreme bodily weakness compels you.
Overcome anger, restrain animosity, and avoid anything that brings regret afterward, as if it were a despicable crime against your neighbor.
A mind that desires to be the dwelling place of God should be peaceful, calm, and free from disturbances of fury.
As He testifies through the Prophet, saying: "On whom shall I rest but on the humble and quiet one who trembles at my words?" (Isaiah 66:3).
Believe that God observes all your actions and thoughts, and ensure you do nothing unworthy in His sight, in either action or thought.
When you desire to pray, present yourself as if you are about to speak with the Lord.
When you recite a psalm, recognize whose words you are saying, and take more delight in the contrition of the soul than in the sweetness of a melodious voice.
For God approves the tears of the one singing more than the grace of the voice, as the Prophet says: "Serve the Lord with fear and rejoice with trembling" (Psalm 2:11).
Where there is fear and trembling, there is no elevation of the voice, but rather the weeping and tearful humbling of the soul.
Apply diligence to all your actions, because it is written: "Cursed is the one who does the work of the Lord negligently" (Jeremiah 46:10).
Let grace grow in you with years, let justice grow with age, and let your faith appear more perfect the older you get.
Our Lord Jesus, who left us an example of how to live, advanced not only in bodily age but also in wisdom and spiritual grace before God and men (Luke 2:25).
Consider any time in which you do not feel yourself becoming better as time lost.
Commit to virginity and uphold it until the end.
It is not just starting, but finishing that shows virtue.
As the Lord says in the Gospel: Whoever endures to the end will be saved (Matthew 24:13)
Be careful not to give anyone a reason for desire, because your spouse, God, is jealous.
An adulteress of Christ is guiltier than one of a husband.
Therefore, the Roman Church, inspired by the Apostolic spirit it embodies, has recently established a severe judgment on this matter, scarcely considering anyone who has defiled the sanctified body of God with lustful contamination worthy of repentance.
Be a model of living for everyone.
Lead by example, guiding those whom you surpass in the sanctification of chastity.
Show yourself as a virgin in all things.
Let no corruption be attributed to your head, whose body remains intact, so that your conduct stays inviolable.
As we mentioned at the beginning of the letter, you have become a sacrifice to God, which undoubtedly imparts its sanctity to others.
Whoever partakes of it worthily also shares in the sanctification.
Likewise, let others be sanctified through you, as through a divine sacrifice.
Present yourself in all things so that whoever encounters your life, either by hearing or seeing, feels the power of sanctification.
Understand that grace flows to them from your conduct, so that while they desire to imitate you, they too may be worthy of God's sacrifice.