HISTORICAL NOTICE.
(From Gallia Christiana, volume 9, page 520.)
In the year 949, as Flodoard mentions in his Chronicle, the people of Laon, who were loyal to King Louis, selected Rorico, a deacon and the king's brother, as their bishop.
Rorico was the illegitimate son of Charles the Simple.
Although Artold, the archbishop of Reims, consecrated him, he wasn't accepted in Laon and stayed at the fortress by the bridge of Petra.
In 955, he was present at the ordination of Hadulf, the bishop of Noyon.
In 961, after the death of Artold, he served as archchancellor until Odalric took over as archbishop.
That same year, he reinstated the monks in the abbey of Saint-Vincent, replacing the canons.
In 962, he attended a synod of thirteen bishops in the region of Meaux, where he worked with Gibwin of Chalons to stop the see of Reims from being returned to Hugh, Artold's rival.
During that year, he laid hands on Odalric, who was consecrated by Guy of Soissons.
On June 3, 969, he agreed to donate half of the abbey of Saint-Hilary, along with the church, to the monastery of Saint-Vincent.
In 973, he gave the church of Saint-Medard in the village of Caprimiac to the same monastery.
In 976, as noted by Flodoard in his Chronicle, he was afflicted by paralysis.
Despite this, he gave thanks to God for his infirmity and passed away on the eve of Saint Thomas the Apostle after morning praises to God.
The Vincentian Necrology notes: On December 20, Rorico, bishop of Laon, passed away.
He established a new rule for this monastery and donated many possessions, including lands and altars.
Atso the monk attests to his learning in the book about the Antichrist, which he wrote at the request of Queen Gerberga.
Restoration of the Monks in the Monastery of St.
Vincent (Acts of the Ecclesiastical Province of Reims Volume One Page Six Hundred Twenty-Six)
With the help of heavenly grace, I, Rorico, though unworthy, have assumed the leadership of the holy Church of Laon.
I realize that the final summons is imminent for me, as it is for others.
Burdened by my sins, I began to consider what would benefit this seat, which I preside over by the will of God, and what is necessary to address my sins.
On the mountain's side, overlooked by the city, there is a church dedicated to the worship and honor of the great martyr Saint Vincent.
In ancient times, it was known for its monastic life, but in modern times, it fell into poverty and neglect.
My predecessor Adelelmus established a community of twelve canons living a religious life there, supported by various sources.
After his death, due to the troubles of various plagues, it nearly returned to its previous desolate state.
I could not remain calm about this, especially since it served as a burial place for both the bishops of this seat and for nobles and laypeople.
Calling a general assembly and with its advice, I decided to restore it to its former monastic state and to gather as many monks as the opportunity of the time allowed.
After inviting twelve monks from the monastery of Saint Benedict, situated above the Loire, I appointed the venerable Melchan as their abbot.
I established him and the other monks in the same monastery to serve God.
Among various benefits I provided, I confirmed the dignity of the second seat of the bishopric, which had been granted to the Church by our ancient predecessors.
I also granted them the burial rights of bishops, canons, priests, custodians, chaplains, and their servants and families, along with jurisdiction over the valley and mountain.
To ensure this authority held stronger validity, we decided to endorse it with both our seal and the testimony of our clerics and noble laity.
The sign of Roricon, the unworthy bishop of Laon.
We decided to send it to the venerable synod, held at Mont Sainte-Marie in the district of Tardenois in May, where it was read in the presence of Lord Adalbero, the archbishop, along with his fellow bishops, and strengthened by their common consent.
Adalbero, archbishop of the holy Church of Reims, I have signed and confirmed it.
Done in Laon in the year of the Incarnation of our Lord Jesus Christ nine sixty-one, in the fourth indiction, on the first of October in the seventh year of King Lothair.