A Book Against the Foolish Belief of the Common People About Hail and Thunderstorms
In these regions, almost everyone, both noble and common, city dwellers and country folk, old and young, believe that hail and thunderstorms can be created by human will.
They say that as soon as they hear thunder and see lightning, it is because of a "lifting wind."
When asked what this "lifting wind" is, some respond with embarrassment and a slightly guilty conscience, while others answer confidently, as is often the case with the unlearned. They claim that it is raised by the incantations of people called "storm-makers," and hence it is known as the "lifting wind."
Whether this belief is true, as commonly held, must be proven by the authority of the Holy Scriptures. But if it is false, as we undoubtedly believe, it must be strongly emphasized how serious a lie it is to attribute a divine work to a human. For by this, one is caught between two great and deadly lies: claiming that a human can do what only God can do, and that God does not do what He does.
If lesser lies hold true, as it is written: "A dark saying will not go in vain; but the mouth that lies, kills the soul" (Wisdom of Solomon 1:11).
And again: "You will destroy all who speak lies." And: "A false witness will perish." Or: "A false witness will not go unpunished." Or even what is read in the Revelation of John the Apostle: "Blessed are those who wash their robes, so that they may have the right to the tree of life and may enter the city by the gates. Outside are the dogs, and sorcerers, and the sexually immoral, and murderers, and idolaters, and everyone who loves and practices falsehood."
How much more serious is such a grave lie, as this belief we are discussing, which is no less than the lies of some heretics.
The blessed Apostle Paul says: "We are even found to be false witnesses about God, because we have testified about God that He raised Christ, whom He did not raise if the dead are not raised: for if the dead are not raised, then Christ has not been raised." (First Corinthians 15:15-16)
Therefore, just as those who preach that Christ the Lord was raised by the Father would be found false witnesses of God if the dead do not rise, so too is the person who attributes the wonderful and terrifying work of God to man undoubtedly a false witness of God.
However, we have seen and heard of many people overwhelmed by such madness and alienated by such foolishness that they believe and say there is a certain region called Magonia.
They claim that ships come from there in the clouds, carrying crops that fall due to hailstorms and perish in tempests, to that region.
Supposedly, these aerial sailors give payment to the Storm-makers and receive grains or other crops in return.
From those blinded by such deep foolishness, we saw many in a certain gathering of people present four individuals in chains—three men and one woman—claiming they had fallen from those ships.
These people were held in chains for several days and eventually, as I said, they were presented before us at a gathering of people to be stoned.
But truth prevailed, and after much reasoning, those who had presented them were confounded according to the prophetic saying, as a thief is confounded when caught.
However, since this error, which generally possesses the minds of almost everyone in this region, must be judged by all who have reason, let us bring forth testimonies of the Scriptures by which it can be judged.
Upon examining these, not we, but the truth itself, will refute this most foolish error.
And all who align with the truth will rebuke the vessels of error, saying with the Apostle: "Every lie is not from the truth." And what is not from the truth is certainly not from God; and what is not from God does not hear His words. As the Truth itself says: "Whoever is from God hears the words of God. Therefore, you do not hear because you are not from God." In another place, it says with different words: "My sheep hear my voice. Therefore, you do not hear because you are not my sheep."
Everyone who is of the truth hears my voice.
Therefore, everyone who believes in a lie, speaks, or asserts what is not, and by holding on to anything that is not, to what does he tend except to non-existence?
Because again, he tends to non-existence; without a doubt, he moves away from the one who is, who said to Moses: "This is what you are to say to the Israelites: 'I AM has sent me to you.'"
And about whom the blessed Job speaks: "For he is alone."
To speak more clearly, truth has essence, or rather, essence exists in its own substance, because it subsists; but falsehood, since it has no essence, is nothing and does not subsist.
Therefore, only God is, because only He truly exists, who did not receive existence from another.
However, all things created by Him indeed exist; but they do not have that true and supreme existence, because they received their existence.
Moreover, falsehoods, because they did not receive existence, have no existence.
Therefore, he who clings to falsehood clings to something that does not exist: although it should not even be called something.
But he who clings to what does not exist not only moves away from the one who made him, but also from what he was made to be; since there are no more than two beings: one supreme, which did not receive its existence from another; the other great, which received its existence from God; that is, the Creator and the creature.
Therefore, falsehood, because it is not the creator, is not supreme being; because it is not the creature, it is not great being; because it has no essence, it is not any being.
Therefore, he who wants to persist in what is should not move away from the one who gave him existence.
But he who does not want to move away from the one who truly is should flee from what is absolutely not, that is, falsehood.
Because every liar is an affirmer of falsehood, and every affirmer of falsehood is a false witness, acting against the truth.
Let us now see if those who say that a divine work is done by a human author have any authority.
In the sacred Scriptures, where hail is first introduced, in those plagues by which Egypt was struck, it is found.
Indeed, the seventh plague of Egypt is this.
The Lord said:
Behold, at this very hour tomorrow, I will rain very heavy hail, such as has never been in Egypt from the day it was founded until now.
In these words, the Lord declares that He Himself will send hail tomorrow, not any human, certainly not Moses or Aaron, who were righteous men of God, nor Jannes and Jambres, the magicians of the Egyptians, who are known as Pharaoh's magicians and resisted Moses just as these resist the truth.
Indeed, as it is written, by Egyptian incantations and certain secrets, each threw down their rods before Pharaoh, and they were turned into serpents, although Aaron's rod devoured their rods.
They had already turned the waters into blood and produced frogs from the rivers, although they could not stop them, as Moses did by the word of the Lord, so that the frogs only remained in the river.
But when it came to gnats, and they could do nothing about it, they said that the finger of God was against them and attempted nothing further like this.
Certainly, if any man could have sent the hail, Jannes and Jambres would have done it, because they turned the waters into blood and produced frogs from the rivers, which those who are now called Tempestarii cannot do.
The Scripture continues: Moses stretched out his rod toward heaven, and the Lord sent thunder and hail, and lightning ran along the ground.
The Lord rained hail upon the land of Egypt, and hail and fire mingled together were carried.
Even here, this passage shows only the Lord as the creator and author of the hail, not any human.
Perhaps those who attribute this to humans will say that Moses stretched out his rod toward heaven, and therefore the storm was sent by a man.
Certainly, Moses was a good and righteous servant of the Lord.
But those whom they call Tempestarii, they do not dare to claim are good and righteous, but rather evil, wicked, and deserving of temporal and eternal damnation, nor servants of God, except perhaps by condition, but not by voluntary service.
If men were the authors of hail, imitating Moses, they would certainly be servants of God, not servants of the devil.
However, the preceding sentences show that they are not the authors but rather the omnipotent God.
The Psalmist, who mentions hail, says about God:
"He destroyed their vines with hail and their sycamore-figs with frost. He gave over their cattle to the hail, their livestock to bolts of lightning"
Psalms 78:47-48.
Since the Psalmist adds that the hail was sent through evil angels, it should be understood that God uses the scourges of vengeance or trials through evil ministers. These ministers have the will to harm on their own, but they receive the power to do so from God.
Just as their will to harm is their own, the power to act on it comes solely from the Lord. It is not the power of men, whether good or bad, nor opposing forces, but only the Lord who grants power to their evil will as much as He wishes and cancels it as much as He does not wish them to be able.
In another psalm, the Psalmist also says about God:
"He turned their rain into hail, with lightning throughout their land; he struck down their vines and fig trees and shattered the trees of their country."
He truly struck down and shattered; it was not a man, nor an evil angel, but only God. Without Him, even a legion of evil angels could not harm pigs or drive them into the sea.
It is definitely God, of whom it is said:
"At the brightness that was before him his thick clouds passed, hail stones and coals of fire. The LORD also thundered in the heavens, and the Highest gave his voice; hail stones and coals of fire."
And to whom we sang:
"Flash forth lightning and scatter them; shoot your arrows and rout them."
He covers the sky with clouds, prepares rain for the earth, gives snow like wool, scatters frost like ashes, sends out his word and melts them; he makes his wind blow, and the waters flow.
Who is praised from the earth, not only by the dragons of the abyss, but also by fire, hail, snow, ice, and the windstorms that follow His command?
It is not the word of man, nor the word of an evil angel.
We also read about hail in the book of Joshua:
The five kings of the Amorites—the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, and the king of Eglon—joined forces.
They and their troops moved up and took positions against Gibeon and attacked it.
Then, shortly after:
The Lord said to Joshua, "Do not be afraid of them; I have given them into your hands."
And shortly after that:
As they fled before Israel on the road down from Beth Horon to Azekah, the Lord hurled large hailstones down on them, and more of them died from the hail than were killed by the swords of the Israelites (Joshua, chapter 10, verses 5, 8, and following).
So here, it is clear, without any human curse, that the Lord sent hail upon those He judged worthy of such a punishment.
If wicked men, like those mistakenly called Storm-makers, could do this, surely the hail would fall upon the Israelites, not upon their enemies.
But because neither the wicked nor the good can do this, it is clearly demonstrated in this passage.
The book of Wisdom also attests, saying to the Lord:
"It is impossible to escape your hand. For those who denied knowing you, the wicked, were scourged by the strength of your arm, with new waters, hail, and rains. They faced persecution and were finally consumed by fire. What was miraculous was that in water, which extinguishes everything, fire had more power. For the world is the avenger of the righteous."
And shortly after:
"Snow and ice endured the force of fire and did not melt; so that it might be known that the fire, blazing in the hail and flashing in the rain, destroyed the fruits of the enemies" (Wisdom, chapter 16, verse 15 and following).
If Almighty God, with the strength of His arm, punishes the enemies of the righteous with new waters, hailstones, and rains, from whose hand it is impossible to escape, then those who believe that humans can do these things are completely ignorant of God.
For if humans could send hail, they would certainly be able to send rain as well.
No one has ever seen hail without rain.
They could also take vengeance on their enemies, not only by destroying crops but also by taking lives.
When it happens that the enemies of these supposed Storm-bringers are on the road or in the fields, so that they could kill them, they could pour multiplied hailstones upon them in one heap and bury them.
Some even say that they know such Storm-bringers who cause scattered hail to fall widely across the region, flowing into one place like a river or a barren forest, or upon one, as they say, vat, under which they themselves hide.
We have often heard many say that they know such things happened in certain places, but we have yet to hear anyone testify that they have seen these things themselves.
It was once said to me about someone that he claimed to have seen these things.
I took great pains to see him, which I did.
When I spoke with him and he tried to say he had seen it, I bound him with many prayers and adjurations, including divine threats, asking that he not say it unless it was true.
Then he indeed affirmed that what he was saying was true, naming the person, time, and place; but he confessed that he was not present at that time.
Also, in the Book of Ecclesiasticus, which is noted as the work of Jesus, the son of Sirach, it is written:
"There are spirits who were created for vengeance, and in their fury they reinforced their torments, and in the time of the end, they will pour out their strength, and the fury of Him who made them will confound them.
Fire, hail, famine, and death—all these were created for vengeance.
The teeth of wild beasts, and scorpions, and serpents, and a sword taking vengeance upon the ungodly"
(Ecclesiasticus 39:33 and following).
If hail is created, just like everything else mentioned here, it is certainly created by God, not by man.
Also, in the aforementioned book, we read:
Look at the rainbow and praise the one who made it.
It is very beautiful in its brightness.
It encircles the sky with its glory; the hands of the Most High have opened it.
By His command, He hastens the snow and speeds the lightning of His judgment.
The storehouses are opened, and the clouds fly out like birds.
In His greatness, He placed the clouds, and the hailstones were shattered.
In His presence, the mountains will be shaken, and by His will, the south wind will blow.
The sound of His thunder strikes the earth, the storm from the north, and the gathering of the wind; and like a bird settling down, He sprinkles the snow; and like a locust descending, so is His descent.
The eye will marvel at the beauty of its color, and the heart will tremble at its rain.
He pours frost like salt upon the earth, and when it freezes, it becomes like thorny branches.
The cold north wind blows, and the ice freezes from the water, resting on all the gatherings of water, and it covers the waters like a breastplate.
It devours the mountains, burns the desert, and extinguishes the greenery like fire.
The remedy for all is the swiftness of the cloud, and the dew meeting the coming heat will make it humble.
At His word, the wind is silent, by His thought He calms the abyss, and the Lord Jesus will plant it.
Ecclesiasticus 43:12-25.
Behold, in this extensive passage from the book of Ecclesiasticus, with utmost admiration, everything that happens in the air is attributed to the command of God:
Everything that descends from the air to the earth, everything in the sea and the winds; the appearance, brightness, and arc of the rainbow; the swiftness of snow, the terror of lightning, the speed of clouds, the suspension of winds, the shaking of the earth, the conflict of breezes, and the freezing of water, not only in clouds like hail and snow, but also on the earth: snow, rain, and standing waters or running rivers.
The drying up of green things from frost, as we often see, as well as the dissolution of all these things, happens during the time of dewy mists and the south and west winds.
At the word of God, all these things are said to calm down and be at peace.
Therefore, a human helper should not be sought in such matters, because none will be found, except perhaps the saints of God, who have obtained much and will obtain much more:
Some of whom will have the power to shut the heavens, so that it does not rain during the days of their prophecy, like Elijah, and to turn waters into blood, and to strike the earth with every plague as often as they wish, like Moses and Aaron in Egypt.
Truly, no one else sends hail in summer, except the one who also sends snow in winter.
For the reason for both is the same: it happens when the clouds are raised higher than usual at both times.
In the book of blessed Job, it is also written:
Job 37:9 and following: "From its chamber comes the whirlwind, and cold from the scattering winds. By the breath of God, ice is given, and the broad waters are frozen fast."
It must be carefully heard what is said: "The clouds turn around by His guidance, to accomplish all that He commands them on the face of the habitable world."
If God governs them, then a wicked man cannot turn them in another direction, because he cannot command God, nor does he deserve to obtain it by prayers.
What follows concerns everything God commanded over the face of the earth.
This includes all that God directed the clouds to do, whether for punishment or for human aid, such as snow, hail, rain, lightning, or thunder, which often bring down tall buildings.
These events occur not by human command but by God's command, as stated in this passage:
"Do you know when God commanded the rains to show the light of His clouds? Do you know the paths of the great clouds and perfect knowledge?"
These words indicate that if humans do not know the paths of the clouds or their perfect knowledge, they understand even less how their functions benefit or harm humans. However, as mentioned, the saints, according to God's will, can accomplish many things through Him who grants them power, not through their own strength or any contrary force, but by the will of the Creator. Many of God's servants have often obtained rain during droughts through prayer.
Thus, the blessed Apostle James, presenting the example of the prophet Elijah, exhorts us to turn to prayer in times of sorrow, illness, and for the forgiveness of sins, saying: "Pray for one another so that you may be healed. The prayer of a righteous person is very powerful and effective. Elijah was a human being like us. He prayed earnestly that it would not rain, and it did not rain on the land for three years and six months. Again he prayed, and the heavens gave rain, and the earth produced its crops."
Elijah prayed that it would not rain, and it did not rain for three years and six months. He did this for the correction and improvement of his people. First, to correct their waywardness because they had abandoned the worship of Almighty God and turned to the filth of idols. Then, once chastised and wearied by the expectation of rain, they might be corrected and return to the Lord God whom they had abandoned.
So Samuel, the prophet and leader of the people of Israel, rebuked the people for their frequent transgressions.
He reminded them of the benefits granted by Almighty God and their disobedience in return, making them understand the great evil they had committed by asking for a king.
Through prayer, Samuel obtained a terrifying storm with thunder and lightning at an unusual time.
It is written that Samuel said to the people:
"Stand and see this great thing which the Lord will do before your eyes. Is it not the wheat harvest today? I will call upon the Lord, and He will give thunder and rain; and you will know and see that you have done a great evil in the sight of the Lord by asking for a king over you."
And Samuel called to the Lord, and the Lord gave thunder and rain that day; and all the people greatly feared the Lord and Samuel.
And all the people said to Samuel:
"Pray for your servants to the Lord your God, that we may not die. For we have added to all our sins this evil, to ask for a king for ourselves" (First Samuel 12:16 and following).
Terrified by the thunder and lightning, the people sought the intercession of the holy prophet.
Despite being sinners, they were faithful, unlike some today who, at the slightest sign of thunder or even a light breeze, curse and say:
"Cursed be that tongue, and may it wither; it should have been cut off already for this. Tell me, whom do you curse? The righteous or the sinner? For a sinner and partially unfaithful like you could not raise the breeze, as you say, because neither by his own power could he do it, nor could he command evil angels: although they do not have power in this matter."
He did not ask the Lord to grant it through prayer because, like you, those you consider weather-makers believe these things happen through evil tricks, not by God's will.
Even if they asked the Lord God, they wouldn't deserve to attain it, as it is meant for the just, not the wicked.
In such matters, even if they ask something of the Lord, they do so unfaithfully and with a double mind, lacking the certainty of faith.
Moreover, during the drought in Israel caused by Elijah's prayer, even the pasture for livestock was scarce.
As it is written, Ahab said to Obadiah, "Go into the land to all the springs of water and to all the valleys. Perhaps we may find grass and save the horses and mules so that not all the livestock will perish."
First Kings 18:5
You see, desperate for rain that would only come according to Elijah's words, they sought grass for the livestock near springs and streams of water. They already knew that what Elijah had told Ahab was true: "The Lord God of Israel lives, before whom I stand, there will be no dew or rain for these years, except by my word."
And indeed, Elijah specified the number of years. So, as I mentioned, why didn't Ahab ask the weather-makers to lift the storms and send favorable winds, as you say, to provide grass for his horses and mules and other livestock, which he was concerned about? Especially since he wasn't worried about losing crops in the fields and vineyards, which were nonexistent at that time.
We also see that sometimes, when the harvests and vintages are collected, farmers can't sow due to drought. Why don't you ask your weather-makers to send favorable winds to water the land so you can sow afterward?
But since you have neither done this nor seen or heard it done, listen now to what the Lord Himself, the creator, ruler, governor, organizer, and dispenser of all things, says to His servant blessed Job, even about these matters.
Indeed, when the devil, the inventor of evil, the prince and leader of all evils, the accuser of the brothers, accused the blessed Job before the Lord, he claimed that Job did not serve with the right intention—to please and enjoy Him alone—but for the increase and protection of earthly things.
The devil asked to test Job to prove this was true.
The wicked, proud, and most foolish devil acted as if he knew the mind of God's man better than his Creator.
The Lord, who is just and merciful, granted the devil power: first over all things, then over Job's children, next over his health, through the persuasion of his wife, and finally through the reproach and various scorn from his servants.
But the devil, defeated and confounded, departed; the servant of the Lord grew victorious and triumphant.
Therefore, the pious Lord, desiring, as the Apostle says about himself, that the greatness of the revelations might not make him proud, wanted to humble Job so that the greatness of his victory would not make him arrogant.
He did this not by taking away the things Job had lost, not by striking his body—through which he had already been tested like gold in a furnace—nor by comparing him to some great man, for there was no one like him on earth, as he was great among the people of the East.
Instead, He began to humble Job greatly, sublimely showing him the immensity of His power, so that the faithful servant, by recognizing the ineffable and boundless wonders of his Creator, would despise himself, and by despising himself, bow down, as indeed happened.
This is evident in Job's words, where he says: "Therefore I retract, and I repent in dust and ashes" (Job 42:6).
Another translation explains it more clearly, saying: "I despised myself, and melted away, and considered myself as dust and ashes."
In this moment of humility, Almighty God questions His faithful servant about whether he could do certain things, or if he knew who did them, or where he was when these things happened.
He asks about things that only the Almighty can do, saying:
Where were you when I laid the foundation of the earth?
Who determined its measurements, or on what were its bases sunk?
Who shut in the sea with doors?
Can you bind the chains of the Pleiades, or loosen the cords of Orion?
Do you know the ordinances of the heavens?
Can you send forth lightnings so that they may go?
Among these many and great things, He also asks:
Have you entered the storehouses of the snow, or seen the storehouses of the hail, which I have reserved for times of trouble, for the day of battle and war?
By what way is the light distributed, or the east wind scattered over the earth?
Who has cleft a channel for the torrents of rain, and a way for the thunderbolt, to bring rain on a land where no man is, on the desert in which there is no man, to satisfy the waste and desolate land, and to make the ground sprout with grass?
Who is the father of the rain?
Or who has begotten the drops of dew?
From whose womb did the ice come forth, and who has given birth to the frost of the heavens?
The waters become hard like stone, and the face of the deep is frozen.
(Job chapter 38, verse 4 and following).
Behold the great works of God, which even blessed Job could not fully comprehend before.
If the Lord has the storehouses of the hail, and He alone sees them, which blessed Job had not seen, where do these Storm-makers find them?
Blessed Job did not find them, nor can we, nor can we even estimate where they might be.
The Lord questions His faithful servant, asking if he knows who has cleft a channel for the torrents of rain, and a way for the thunderbolt.
These individuals, whom this discourse targets, are depicted as lacking holiness, justice, and wisdom—they are devoid of faith and truth, and even despised by their neighbors.
They assert that these neighbors can control the heaviest rains, violent storms, and gentle breezes.
The Lord states that He has prepared these phenomena for the time of the enemy, meaning for vengeance.
These same enemies and adversaries of justice—those who move boundaries, take a widow's ox as collateral, oppress orphans, leave people without clothing, drive the needy from their homes, and cause sorrow—must be avenged.
It is said that they wield the power that the Lord has set aside for the retribution of His enemies.
The Lord affirms that He is the father of rain and that He generates frost from heaven.
These most wretched individuals claim to play a significant role in this dispensation.
The Lord presents it as a marvel that water hardens into the likeness of a stone.
If these wretched people could truly will this to happen, it would no longer be a marvel.
This folly is a significant part of infidelity; and this evil has grown so much that in many places, there are wretched people who claim they do not know how to bring about storms but know how to protect the inhabitants of a place from a storm.
They have a set amount of their produce to give, which they call the canon.
Many, however, never willingly give a tenth to priests, nor do they give alms to widows, orphans, and other needy people, as is frequently preached to them, often read to them, and constantly encouraged.
Yet, they do not comply.
But the canon, as they call it, they willingly pay to their protectors (from whom they believe they are defended from the storm), without anyone preaching, admonishing, or exhorting them, driven by the devil.
Finally, they place a great part of their hope for their lives in such people, as if their existence depends on them.
This is not just a part, but almost the fullness of unfaithfulness.
If we examine it carefully, we will undoubtedly declare it to be the fullness of unfaithfulness.
There are three virtues, according to the divine Scriptures, in which all worship is contained and through which God is worshiped: faith, hope, and love.
Whoever divides his faith and hope, so that he partly believes in God, partly believes that what belongs to God belongs to men, and partly hopes in God, but partly hopes in man, God certainly does not accept this divided faith and hope.
Thus, he cannot be counted among the faithful.
Whoever is separated from the number of the faithful by divided faith and hope is undoubtedly swallowed by the abyss of unfaithfulness.
Rightly does such a person incur that curse of the prophet who says: Cursed is the man who puts his hope in man.
Nor should he flatter himself by saying: I hope more in God than in man.
Hope cannot be divided into parts.
It will either be whole and secure, or insecure and nothing at all.
A few years ago, a certain foolishness spread when there was a mortality of cattle.
Grimoald, Duke of Benevento, had sent men with powders to be scattered across fields, mountains, meadows, and springs because he was an enemy of the most Christian Emperor Charles.
Cattle died from the scattered powder.
Because of this, we heard and saw many being arrested, some being killed, and many being tied to boards, thrown into the river, and drowned.
What is very surprising is that those who were arrested testified against themselves, saying they had such powder and were spreading it.
For the devil, by God's hidden and just judgment, having received power over them, was so successful that they were false witnesses against themselves unto death.
Neither discipline, nor torture, nor even death deterred them from daring to speak falsely against themselves.
This was believed by everyone, so that there were almost none to whom it seemed utterly absurd.
They didn't reasonably consider how a powder could be made that would only kill cattle and not other animals, or how it could be spread over such wide regions, which people cannot cover with powder.
Not even if the men and women of Benevento, old and young, had left the region with three carts loaded with powder.
Such great foolishness has now overcome the miserable world, that Christians believe such absurd things now, which no one could have ever persuaded the pagans, who were ignorant of the creator of all things, to believe before.
We bring this matter up because it is similar to what we are talking about, and it provides an example of empty deception and a true lack of sense.