Homily of Saint Radbod about Saint Lebwinus.
(From the Supplement to the Lives of the Saints, Twelfth November)
Often, dear brothers, it happens that during meals, a fanciful story entertains those dining, and a mind burdened by physical food chases after a hunger for fiction.
When the mind, temporarily forgetful of itself due to the body's fullness, ignores spiritual nourishment, it craves the allure of vanities, which amuse the ears, rather than the sweetness of heavenly teachings that truly satisfy the soul.
However, in today's reading, we are pleased that things are different for us; the more we hear it, the more eagerly we embrace it.
We don't hesitate to cultivate the same hunger for fulfillment after experiencing satisfaction, a renewed hunger after happy fulfillment.
So, to make it clearer what spiritual delights are promised to those who hunger spiritually through this kind of story, let us now set upon the heavenly table dishes more delightful than all worldly pleasures.
By partaking in the sweetest meals of eternal life, let us give thanks to God, the author of such joyous refreshment.
Each year, He kindly lifts our spirits with this sweetest feast, presenting us with the memory of the blessed Lebwinus, during the annual celebration of his birth, as if offering us bread of angels from the basket of his piety.
As we devoutly partake in this, we hunger healthily, are abundantly fed, and rejoice cheerfully.
This is accompanied by the most beautiful disposition of mind, invincible strength, continuous health, disdain for the world, desire for heavenly things, and hope for the future.
Therefore, brothers, we must consider how great these delights are, so that we do not hesitate to embrace them with eager hearts:
being filled with them, we fear no enemy schemes, nor are we daunted by the storms of the world.
To achieve this through divine mercy, we believe that the example of this most holy man is enough for us.
Like the Tower of Zion and the gate of Jerusalem, protected by angels, he stood firm against the challenges of harsh fortune in both the trials and successes of the world.
By overcoming these obstacles, he remained steadfast in his eternal faith.
He reached great perfection through natural goodness, which lifted him higher, allowing him to rise above worldly matters and reach the heights of the heavens.
As a child, he was loved by both God and people.
With a teachable mind, gentle spirit, humble in spirit, and rich in virtues, he embraced the religious life, encouraged by respected individuals.
He was so devoted to Christ and His Church that he excelled his peers in literary skill, was obedient to his elders, and, with true humility, followed the instructions of the wise as if they were from God.
In his youth, he sought the wisdom of the elders with moral integrity, blending a simple, innocent life with heavenly teachings.
During his teenage years, he avoided the temptations of a reckless spirit.
Instead, he controlled youthful impulses with frugality and constant work, disciplining his body to ensure that, after guiding others, he wouldn't fall short himself.
He knew that many esteemed teachers of this philosophy existed in the holy Church.
Among them, he learned that the bishops Willibrord and Boniface, of blessed memory, had worked hard in the service of the Lord's vineyard.
Therefore, he dedicated his mind to pleasing God, hoping to join those he admired as fathers in Christianity as companions in eternal happiness.
Since we've mentioned the families of such great figures of Christ in our stories, like a ray of venerable light, we've paused our previous style to remember these men with eager minds and to praise them with worthy commendations for the honor of God, as best as we can.
Our Lebuinus grows in glory because he is said to have lived a more virtuous life than those before him.
He did not stray from their path and followed in the footsteps of these great leaders with utmost effort.
When their religiousness is expressed, he is praised; when their studies are noted, his character is fully portrayed; and when their battles against the powers of the air are recounted, his triumph is clearly highlighted.
From these observations, it is easy to see that the memory of those who came before is illuminated by the lives of those who follow, and the honor of the children is increased when supported by the authority of their gloriously living fathers.
We do not doubt that the men we mentioned earlier were very holy, one of whom deserved to join the company of the Lamb through confession, and the other through martyrdom.
They now have an inheritance with Christ, as they were never separated from Him in this life.
Divine grace has certainly given us these examples to imitate, so that anyone deterred by the sword of a violent executioner might compare themselves to the great Willibrord and serve the Lord praiseworthily in the peace of divine tranquility.
And whoever considers themselves comparable to the fighters should not fear following Saint Boniface, who shed his blood for the love of Christ.
If the cruelty of the killer is absent, let him arm himself with the divine sword and become both spiritual persecutor and martyr, ensuring he does not neglect to achieve the purity of one in peace or the victory of the other in martyrdom.
Having briefly mentioned these points, let's return to the story we said we were neglecting earlier.
However, it wasn't entirely left out, as it kept surfacing amidst other thoughts with a persistent affection, wrapped in an unknown sweetness, while composing the previous sections with the fingers of the rest, yet always weighing on the heart of Lebuinus.
Certainly, since he initially decided to write about him, even though he introduced some very remarkable men, his focused intention couldn't be diverted from this view; because the good things that can be said about him come naturally.
If someone attempted to explain them all, they would need the eloquence of Cicero or Plautus.
Blessed Lebuinus, therefore, found himself among the wild and semi-barbaric manners of people, but he maintained the innocence of a lamb, mindful of the Lord's words, which said he would send apostles like lambs among wolves.
The holy man was not lacking in serpent-like wisdom either; for if anyone tried to harm his head, meaning Christ, he would undoubtedly offer his whole body for Him.
Thus, it happened that in the power of the Most High, he connected the members to the divine head, inserting himself amidst these things like a bond of charity, linking the lowly to the highest, striving to equate human weakness with angelic dignity.
A truly wise architect, building a heavenly home, had laid the rock in the foundation, so that the raging winds, the boiling storms, and finally all the assaults of adversity wouldn't damage the seal of virtues.
The rock, however, was Christ.
So, for anyone who wishes to listen, does anything seem to you either healthier than that connection or more solid than that firmness, as what is joined there isn't loosened by any separation: what is founded here isn't overthrown by any storm.
If you're interested in or enjoy listening to tales of monsters, and find yourself indifferent to true stories due to vanity, you might indulge in the musings of poets.
These poets are so caught up in their imaginative fictions that they sometimes can't even recognize when their own claims are the most false.
We have the Church as a witness to the truth of what we say about the holy man of God, Lebuinus.
The Church, enriched by his blessings, frequently acknowledges his significance before God through the many miracles that occur.
Indeed, the stories we share about him are welcomed by the Church, as shown by the large crowds who gather to listen.
Even those who seem secure worry about being overwhelmed by the crowd, and it's rare for someone to leave without thanking God for hearing and feeling the support of Lebuinus.
Therefore, we believe no one will mind if we speak briefly, since the Word of God declares that He built a temple in him and made it His dwelling place.
This will be sung during morning praises, I believe, but it shouldn't be left out of the reading, so that both through song and speech, we can celebrate how esteemed this man, beloved in Christ, is among his people.
The introduction is as follows: The Holy Spirit, as Scripture says, dwells in the heart of a righteous man.
For his soul, free from all iniquity, is His temple, where not physical sacrifices, but spiritual offerings are made.
And there, not only is the body purified, but true forgiveness of sin and the abolition of eternal death are granted.
Blessed Lebuinus earned the right to be called and to be this temple, as through the Lord's help, he was cleansed from the contagion of sins, through Him who lives and reigns forever and ever.
Amen.