A book against the superstition of those who think that adoration should be given to the pictures and images of the saints.
by Agobard of Lyon
The first commandment of the Decalogue is spoken by God:
I am the Lord your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of slavery.
You shall have no other gods before me.
You shall not make for yourself a carved image, nor any likeness of anything that is in heaven above, or that is on the earth beneath, or that is in the waters under the earth.
You shall not bow down to them or serve them.
To these words, blessed Augustine briefly adds:
In the first commandment, any likeness of God made by human hands is forbidden; not because God does not have an image, but because no image of Him should be worshiped, except that which is Himself, nor that in place of Him, but with Him.
By saying this, blessed Augustine teaches us how to understand the rest of such commandments.
When it is said that no likeness should be made of anything in heaven or on earth, it refers not only to foreign gods but also to heavenly creatures, or anything that human sense could devise in honor of the creator.
Therefore, Moses speaks clearly to the people:
The Lord spoke to you out of the midst of the fire.
You heard the sound of His words but saw no form; there was only a voice.
And after a little while:
Therefore watch yourselves very carefully.
You did not see any form on the day the Lord spoke to you at Horeb from the midst of the fire, so that you would not be led astray and make for yourselves a carved image or the likeness of any male or female figure.
This includes the likeness of any animal on the earth, any bird that flies under the sky, any creature that moves on the ground, or any fish that lives in the waters under the earth.
You might look up to the sky and see the sun and all the stars of the heavens and be led astray to worship and serve them.
These words emphasize that if the works of God's hands are not to be worshipped and served, then how much more should the works of human hands not be worshipped and served, even if they are made to honor those whose likeness they represent.
The first commandment of the Decalogue says, "I am the Lord your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of slavery. You shall have no other gods before me. You shall not make for yourself a carved image, or any likeness of anything that is in heaven above, or that is on the earth beneath, or that is in the waters under the earth. You shall not bow down to them or serve them."
Blessed Augustine briefly adds to these words, saying (Homily on Exodus 1): "In the first commandment, it is forbidden to make any likeness of God in the creations of man; not because God does not have an image, but because no image of him should be worshipped, except the one that is what he is, and not that one in place of him, but along with him."
By saying this, Blessed Augustine teaches us how to understand the other similar commandments. It is clearly stated that no likeness of anything in heaven or on earth is to be made. This applies not only to the likenesses of foreign gods but also to heavenly creatures or anything that human sense could conceive in honor of the creator.
For this reason, Moses speaks openly to the people, saying: "The Lord spoke to you out of the midst of the fire. You heard the sound of words, but saw no form; there was only a voice." And shortly after: "Therefore, watch yourselves very carefully."
You didn't see any form on the day the Lord spoke to you at Horeb from the midst of the fire, so that you might not be deceived into making for yourselves a carved image in the form of any figure:
the likeness of a male or female, the likeness of any animal on the earth, any winged bird that flies in the sky, any creature that moves along the ground, or any fish in the waters below.
And so that when you look up to the sky and see the sun, moon, and stars—all the heavenly array—you might not be led astray to bow down to them and worship them.
In these words, it is especially important to note that if the works of God's hands are not to be worshipped and served, how much more the works of human hands are not to be worshipped and served, not even in honor of those whose likenesses they are said to be.
From the book of Saint Augustine, "The City of God," Book 10, Chapter 1, on the ways in which worship is described:
We must examine and discuss, as much as God grants, how the immortal and blessed beings in the heavenly places—the dominions, principalities, and powers—whom these people call gods, and among whom they even name some as good demons or angels with us, should be believed to want us to maintain religion and piety.
To say it more clearly, whether it pleases them that we perform sacred rites and offer sacrifices to them, or dedicate anything of ours, or even ourselves, through religious ceremonies, or whether this is pleasing only to their God, who is also our God.
This is the worship owed to divinity, or, to be more explicit, to deity.
Because I do not find a sufficiently suitable Latin word to signify this in one word, I use the Greek term where necessary to express what I want to say.
For our interpreters have translated "latria" wherever it occurs in the Holy Scriptures as "service."
But that service which is due to humans, according to which the Apostle commands that slaves should be subject to their masters, is usually called by another name in Greek.
However, "latria," according to the custom by which those who composed the divine writings spoke, is always or almost always used to mean the service that pertains to the worship of God.
Therefore, if it is only called worship, it does not seem to be owed solely to God.
We also honor people whom we frequently visit or remember with respect.
Not only do we subject ourselves with religious humility, but even certain things that are subject to us are said to be honored.
The term "farmers" and "tenants" come from this idea. Even the gods are called "heaven-dwellers" because they inhabit heaven, not by worshiping, but by residing there, like certain inhabitants of heaven. Unlike tenants who owe their condition to the landowners, as Virgil says in the Aeneid:
"There was an ancient city, the Tyrian settlers held."
He called them settlers because they inhabited, not because of agriculture. Hence, cities founded by larger cities are called colonies. Therefore, it is true that worship should be owed only to God by a specific notion of this word. But because the worship of other things is also spoken of, it cannot be signified in Latin by one word as worship due to God. Even the term religion, although it seems to specifically signify the worship of God, is used in various contexts. In both learned and common speech, religion is shown in human relationships, affinities, and bonds, which creates ambiguity when discussing divine worship. Piety is usually understood as the worship of God, which the Greeks call "reverence." However, it is also used to describe the duty towards parents. Commonly, this term is also used in acts of mercy.
I believe this happened because God specifically commands these actions to be done, and He testifies that they please Him, either as sacrifices or even more than sacrifices.
From this way of speaking, God Himself is called pious, a term the Greeks do not use in their language.
Instead, they use "to show reverence," although they also use "reverence" to mean mercy.
Therefore, in some places in the Scriptures, to make the distinction clearer, they preferred to say "worship of God" instead of "reverence," which comes from good worship, as it resonates with the worship of God. However, we cannot express either of these with one word.
Thus, what is called "service" in Greek and is interpreted as service in Latin is what we use to worship God. Or, what is called "religion" in Greek and is called religion in Latin is directed toward God. Or, what they call "worship of God," we cannot express in one word, but we can call it the worship of God. We say this is owed only to the true God, who makes His worshippers gods.
Therefore, whoever is immortal and blessed in the heavenly dwellings, if they do not love us nor want us to be blessed, should certainly not be worshipped. But if they love us and want us to be blessed, they surely want it from the same source as where they are.
From the book of Saint Augustine on the City of God, Book Ten (Chapter One), on the ways of worship:
It must be seen and discussed, as much as God grants, how the immortal and blessed beings in the heavenly seats—dominions, principalities, and powers—whom these people call gods, and among whom they name some as either good demons or angels with us, should be believed to desire us to maintain religion and piety.
That is, to speak more plainly, whether it pleases them that we make sacrifices and offer sacred rites either to themselves or only to their God, who is also our God, or consecrate some of our things or ourselves to religious rites.
For this is the worship due to divinity, or to speak more clearly, deity.
Since no suitable Latin word occurs to me to signify this with one word, I use the Greek where necessary to indicate what I mean.
Latriam means "service" in sacred Scriptures.
However, the type of service owed to humans, as per the Apostle's command that servants should be subject to their masters, is usually called by another name in Greek.
According to those who recorded the divine words for us, "latria" is almost always used to describe the service that pertains to worshiping God.
Therefore, if the term "worship" is used alone, it does not seem to be owed solely to God.
We also say that we "worship" people whom we honor, either through remembrance or presence.
Not only do we subject ourselves to those we honor with religious humility, but we also say we "worship" certain things that are subject to us.
From this word, we get "farmers," "colonists," and "inhabitants."
Even the gods are called "heaven-dwellers" because they are thought to inhabit heaven; not by worshiping it, but by living in it, like colonists of heaven.
They are not called "colonists" like those who owe their status to the land they cultivate under the dominion of landowners, but as a great Latin author (Virgil in Aeneid Book 1, Line 16) said: "There was an ancient city, held by Tyrian colonists."
He called them "colonists" from inhabiting, not from farming.
Hence, cities founded by larger cities, like offshoots of populations, are called "colonies."
Therefore, it is entirely true that worship should be owed only to God, in a specific sense.
But because "worship" is also used for other things, it cannot be signified in Latin by a single word as worship due to God.
For even religion itself, although it may seem to signify nothing more than the worship of God—from which our people have interpreted this word to mean what is called "religion" in Greek—nevertheless, in the Latin-speaking tradition, not only among the uneducated but also among the most learned, religion is said to be shown in familial relationships and affinities, and in any necessities. Therefore, the term is not avoided as ambiguous when discussing the worship of the deity.
Thus, we can confidently say that religion is nothing other than the worship of God: "because this word seems to be taken away insolently from signifying the observance of human kinship."
Piety is also usually understood as the worship of God, which the Greeks call "reverence." However, it is also said to be dutifully shown towards parents. By custom, this name is frequently used in works of mercy.
I think this happened because God especially commands these acts and testifies that they are pleasing to Him, either as sacrifices or in place of sacrifices. From this way of speaking, it has come about that even God Himself is called pious, which the Greeks indeed do not call "to show reverence" in their language, although the common people use "reverence" for mercy.
Hence, in some places in the Scriptures, to make the distinction clearer, they preferred to say "worship of God," which resonates as composed from the worship of God, rather than "reverence," which comes from good worship. However, we cannot express either of these in one word.
What is called "service" in Greek, and interpreted in Latin as servitude, is the term by which we worship God. Or what is called "religion" in Greek, and in Latin is called religion, is what we have towards God. Or what they call "worship of God," which we cannot express in one word, but can call the worship of God: we say this is due only to the one true God, who makes His worshippers gods.
Therefore, whoever is immortal and blessed in the heavenly dwellings, if they do not love us and do not wish us to be blessed, they surely are not to be worshipped. But if they love us and wish us to be blessed, they certainly wish it from that source from which they themselves also come.
In the same book, a few chapters later.
We owe this service, which is called latria in Greek, whether in sacraments or within ourselves.
We are all his temple together, and each of us is a temple because he finds it worthy to dwell both in our collective harmony and in each individual.
He is greater in each of us than in all of us together because he is not spread by size nor diminished by division.
When he is above, our heart is his altar; we appease him through his only begotten priest.
We offer him bloody sacrifices when we strive for his truth, even to the point of shedding blood.
We burn the sweetest incense for him when we burn with pious and holy love in his sight.
We vow and return to him his gifts within us and ourselves.
We dedicate to him the sacred memory of his benefits with festive celebrations and appointed days so that ungrateful oblivion does not creep in over time.
We sacrifice the victim of humility and praise on the altar of the heart with the fire of fervent charity.
To see him as he can be seen and to cleave to him, we cleanse ourselves from all stain of sins and evil desires, and we consecrate ourselves in his name.
For he is the source of our happiness and the end of all our desires.
By choosing him again, for we had lost him through negligence, we strive towards him with love so that by reaching him we may find rest; hence we are blessed because we are perfected by that end.
We owe this service, which is called latria in Greek, whether in sacraments or within ourselves.
We are all his temple together, and each of us is a temple because he finds it worthy to dwell both in our collective harmony and in each individual.
He is greater in each of us than in all of us together because he is not spread by size nor diminished by division.
When he is above, our heart is his altar; we appease him through his only begotten priest.
We offer him bloody sacrifices when we strive for his truth, even to the point of shedding blood.
We burn the sweetest incense for him when we burn with pious and holy love in his sight.
His gifts reside within us, and we dedicate ourselves to Him.
We celebrate His blessings with solemn festivals and appointed days to keep the sacred memory alive, preventing ungrateful forgetfulness over time.
We offer Him a sacrifice of humility and praise on the altar of the heart, fueled by fervent love.
To see Him, as much as He can be seen, and to cling to Him, we cleanse ourselves from every stain of sin and evil desires, and we consecrate ourselves in His name.
He is the source of our happiness and the fulfillment of all our desires.
By choosing Him again, for we had lost Him through neglect, we strive towards Him with love, seeking rest and perfection in that ultimate goal.
We should not seek any other mediator between God and humans, except for Him who is both God and man.
From book nine of Saint Augustine's work, Chapter 15: "The multitude that is blessed becomes blessed by participation in the one God. The wretched multitude of evil angels, by depriving themselves of this participation, obstructs rather than aids in achieving beatitude. We are to be led to the beatific goal by one mediator, not many. This mediator, the Word of God, is not created but made all things. The Word is not the mediator because it is the Word, but because it became man. This shows that to reach the blessed and beatifying good, we do not need other mediators. The blessed and peaceful God, by becoming a participant in our humanity, provided a direct path to participation in His divinity."
He does not free us from mortality and misery to lead us to the immortal and blessed angels in such a way that by sharing in their nature, we too become immortal and blessed.
Instead, He leads us to the Trinity, by whose participation the angels are also blessed.
Therefore, when He chose to be below the angels in the form of a servant as a mediator, He remained above the angels in the form of God.
The same one who is the way of life among the lower beings is life among the higher beings.
There should be no other mediator sought between God and humans except the one who is both God and man.
From Book Nine of Saint Augustine, Chapter Fifteen:
"The multitude that is blessed becomes blessed by sharing in one God. By being deprived of this sharing, the miserable multitude of evil angels, which instead of helping to happiness, rather obstructs it, also somewhat hinders by its very multitude, so that it cannot reach that one blessed entity. We needed not many but one mediator to lead us, and this is the one by whose participation we become blessed, that is, the Word of God, not created, but through whom all things were made.
Yet He is not a mediator because He is the Word; for the most immortal and most blessed Word is far from mortal and miserable beings. He is a mediator by being human, thereby showing us that to reach that not only blessed but also blessing good, we should not seek other mediators through whom we think we must climb the steps of reaching it. The blessed and peaceful God, having partaken in our humanity, has provided a shortcut for us to partake in His divinity.
He does not free us from mortality and misery to lead us to the immortal and blessed angels in such a way that by sharing in their nature, we too become immortal and blessed. Instead, He leads us to the Trinity, by whose participation the angels are also blessed. Therefore, when He chose to be below the angels in the form of a servant as a mediator, He remained above the angels in the form of God. The same one who is the way of life among the lower beings is life among the higher beings."
IV.
From book ten of the same work, Blessed Augustine teaches by the example of the Lord Jesus Christ that no creature should be sacrificed to, explaining this in Chapters 19 and 20:
"Those who believe that visible sacrifices are appropriate for other gods, but that the highest God, being invisible, should have invisible and greater sacrifices—like the duties of a pure mind and good will—don't realize that these are signs of those, just as spoken words are signs of things.
Therefore, just as when praying and praising, we direct our meaningful words to Him, to whom we offer the things themselves in our hearts; so when sacrificing, we should understand that a visible sacrifice should not be offered to anyone other than Him, whose invisible sacrifice we must be in our hearts.
Then the angels and higher powers, stronger in goodness and piety, favor us, rejoice with us, and help us to the best of their ability in this very thing. But if we wish to offer these to them, they do not accept them willingly; and when they are sent to people so that their presence is felt, they very clearly forbid it.
There are examples of this in the holy scriptures. Some thought that honor should be given to angels, either by worshiping or sacrificing, which is due to God; and they were admonished by them and instructed to give this only to Him, to whom alone it is rightful.
The holy men of God also imitated the holy angels. When Paul and Barnabas performed a miracle of healing in Lycaonia, they were thought to be gods, and the Lycaonians wanted to sacrifice victims to them. But rejecting this with humble piety, they proclaimed to them the God in whom they should believe.
Those deceitful ones arrogantly demand this for themselves for no other reason than because they know it is due to the true God. For indeed, they do not rejoice in the odors of dead bodies but in divine honors. They have ample supply of odors from all around, and if they wanted more, they could provide it for themselves."
Those spirits who arrogantly claim divinity for themselves are not pleased by the smoke from any body but rather by the soul of a supplicant, whom they deceive and dominate, blocking the path to the true God.
Thus, a person becomes their sacrifice when they offer sacrifices to anyone other than Him.
This is why the true mediator, Jesus Christ, who became a mediator between God and humans by taking on the form of a servant, preferred to be a sacrifice rather than to take a sacrifice, so that no one would think it appropriate to offer sacrifices to any creature.
From Book 10 of the same work, where Blessed Augustine clearly teaches by the example of the Lord Jesus Christ that no sacrifice is to be offered to any creature, he teaches this in Chapters 19 and 20:
“Those who think that visible sacrifices are appropriate for other gods, but that invisible and greater sacrifices are for the highest and true God, such as the duties of a pure mind and good will, undoubtedly do not understand that these visible sacrifices are signs of the invisible ones, just as spoken words are signs of things.
Therefore, just as when we pray and praise, we direct our meaningful words to Him to whom we offer the things we signify inwardly in our hearts, so when we sacrifice, we should know that no visible sacrifice should be offered to anyone other than Him, to whom we should be an invisible sacrifice in our hearts.
Then the angels and superior powers, who are more powerful by their goodness and piety, favor us, rejoice with us, and help us to the best of their ability.
But if we try to offer these things to them, they do not willingly accept them; and when they are sent to humans in such a way that their presence is felt, they explicitly forbid it.
There are examples of this in the holy writings.
Some thought that honor should be given to angels, either by worshiping or sacrificing, which is due to God; and they were prohibited by the angels and instructed to give this honor to Him alone, whom they knew it was right to honor.
The holy men of God also imitated the holy angels.
”
Because Paul and Barnabas performed a miracle of healing in Lycaonia, the people there thought they were gods and wanted to offer sacrifices to them.
However, Paul and Barnabas humbly rejected this and proclaimed to them the God in whom they should believe.
Those deceitful ones arrogantly demand this for themselves because they know it is owed to the true God.
They do not, as Porphyry says and some think, delight in the fumes of dead bodies but in divine honors.
They have plenty of fumes all around, and if they wanted more, they could provide them for themselves.
Therefore, the spirits who claim divinity for themselves do not delight in the smoke of any body but in the soul of the one who supplicates.
They deceive and dominate, blocking the way to the true God so that people do not make their sacrifices to Him while sacrificing to anyone else.
Hence, the true mediator, in taking the form of a servant, became the mediator between God and humans, Christ Jesus.
While in the form of God, He receives the sacrifice with the Father, with whom He is also one God.
Yet in the form of a servant, He preferred to be the sacrifice rather than to receive it, so that no one would think a sacrifice should be made to any creature.
From Book 10 of the aforementioned work, which states that no creature worshiping God wants to be worshipped in place of Him to whom it is also subject (Chapter 4):
"Any immortal power, no matter how great its virtue, if it loves us as itself, wants us to be subject to Him so that we may be blessed, to whom it is also subject and blessed. Therefore, if it does not worship God, it is miserable because it is deprived of God. For it rather supports the divine sentence and favors the power of love, by which it is written, 'Whoever sacrifices to gods shall be uprooted unless it is to the Lord alone.' To leave aside other things that pertain to the religious service by which God is worshipped, certainly no human being dares to say that sacrifice is owed to anyone except God. Many elements of divine worship have indeed been usurped and conferred upon human honors, whether out of excessive humility or deadly flattery; yet those to whom these honors are conferred are considered to be humans, who are said to be worshipped and revered; if much more is added to them, even adored."
Who then considered it necessary to offer sacrifices, except to the one whom they either knew to be God, thought to be God, or imagined to be God?
From book 10 of the aforementioned work, which states that no creature worshiping God would want to be worshiped in place of Him to whom it is also subject:
"Therefore, any immortal power endowed with any amount of virtue, if it loves us as it loves itself, wants us to be subject to the one to whom it is also subject, so that we may be blessed as it is blessed.
If it does not worship God, it is miserable because it is deprived of God.
For it rather supports the divine judgment and favors the power of love, as it is written: Those who sacrifice to gods shall be uprooted unless it is to the Lord alone.
For now, I will not speak of other matters that pertain to the service of religion in which God is worshiped, but certainly no human would dare to say that sacrifice is owed to anyone except God.
Many things, indeed, have been taken from divine worship and are given in honor to humans, whether out of excessive humility or harmful flattery; however, those to whom these honors are given are considered as people who are to be respected and revered; but if much more is added, then they are to be worshiped.
Who then considered it necessary to offer sacrifices, except to the one whom they either knew to be God, thought to be God, or imagined to be God?"
From the book "On True Religion" by Saint Augustine, about where the true God should be sought (Chapter 15):
"Therefore, we must first follow those who declare that there is only one supreme true God and that He alone should be worshiped.
If truth does not shine forth among them, then we must move on.
For just as in the nature of things the authority of one who brings everything back to one is greater, and in the human race there is no power except that of a consenting multitude; so, in religion, those who call to one should have greater and more credible authority."
From the book "On True Religion" by Saint Augustine, about where the true God should be sought (Chapter 15):
"Therefore, we must first follow those who declare that there is only one supreme true God and that He alone should be worshiped.
If truth does not shine forth among them, then we must move on."
Just as in the nature of things, the authority of one who unites everything is greater, and in humanity, power comes from consensus; so in religion, those who guide towards unity should hold greater and more trustworthy authority.
From the twenty-fifth homily of Saint Gregory the Pope on the Gospels, about seeking God among saints:
The watchmen who guard the city find us while we search;
because the holy Fathers, who protect the Church, meet our efforts with their teachings:
when we pass them by, we find the one we love.
Because our Redeemer, though humble as a man among men, is divine and above men.
Therefore, when we pass by the watchmen, we find the beloved:
because when we see the prophets and apostles below Him, we recognize Him, by nature, as God above men.
From the Song of Songs (where the holy Church says: The watchmen who guard the city found me. Have you seen the one whom my soul loves? When I had just passed them, I found the one whom my soul loves:)
briefly noted from the aforementioned homily, let's now see what the same Father says about these words in the eighteenth book of his explanation on Job.
When the Church was seeking its redeemer, it did not want to place its hope in the ancient preachers, as it says: "After I had passed by them a little, I found him whom my soul loves." For she could not have found him if she had not passed by them.
Blessed Augustine speaks in harmony with this understanding in his first homily on the Gospel according to John, saying: "John is one of those mountains; about whom we sang a little earlier, saying: 'I lift up my eyes to the mountains, from where will my help come?' Therefore, dearest brothers, if you want to understand, lift up your eyes to this mountain, that is, raise yourselves to the evangelist, raise yourselves to his understanding. But because these mountains receive peace, and one cannot be in peace who places hope in man, do not lift up your eyes to the mountain in such a way that you think your hope should be placed in man, and thus say: 'I lift up my eyes to the mountains, from where will my help come?' so that you immediately add: 'My help is from the Lord, who made heaven and earth.' Therefore, let us lift up our eyes to the mountains, from where help will come to us. And yet, it is not the mountains themselves in which our hope should be placed. For the mountains receive what they minister to you. From where also the mountains receive where hope should be placed, when we lift our eyes to the Scriptures, because the Scriptures were ministered through men. We lifted our eyes to the mountains from where help will come. But yet, because the men who wrote the Scriptures did not shine by themselves; (but he was their light who illuminates every man coming into this world; and that mountain was John the Baptist, who said, 'I am not the Christ,' lest anyone, placing hope in the mountain, fall away from him who illuminates the mountains. And he himself confessed, saying: 'For from his fullness we have all received.') so you should say: 'I lift up my eyes to the mountains, from where my help will come.
' Do not attribute the help that comes to you to the mountains, but follow and say: 'My help is from the Lord, who made heaven and earth.
'"
Therefore, brothers, I have advised you so that when you lift your hearts to the Scriptures, as the Gospel says: "In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God," and so on. These things were read so that you might understand you have lifted your eyes to the mountains.
If these things were not said, you would not entirely think of them, and you would not find them. Thus, help comes to you from the mountains, so that you might hear these things: if you cannot yet understand what you heard, call for help from the Lord who made heaven and earth. Because the mountains could speak in such a way that they could not illuminate themselves, as they were also illuminated by hearing.
From there, John, brothers, who reclined on the Lord's chest and drank from the Lord's chest what he would offer us, received this. But he offered words. However, the understanding from which you should draw must be where he himself drank, who offered it to you.
This same teacher also speaks similarly in the twelfth homily of the aforementioned work when he dealt with the words of John the Baptist, who answered his disciples, saying: "A man cannot receive anything unless it has been given to him from heaven. You yourselves bear witness to me that I said: I am not the Christ." As if saying: Why do you deceive yourselves? How did you propose this question to me? What did you say to me?
Rabbi, the one who was with you across the Jordan, to whom you bore witness? Do you know what kind of testimony I bore to him now? I am going to say that he is not the one I said I was, who received something from heaven, so that I could be something. Do you want me to be empty, to speak against the truth? "A man cannot receive anything unless it has been given to him from heaven. You yourselves bear witness to me that I said: I am not the Christ. You are not the Christ!"
But what if you are greater than him because you baptized him? I was sent. I am a herald, he is the judge.
And listen to a much stronger, much clearer testimony. See what is happening with us. See what we should love. See that loving any man above Christ is adultery. Why do I say this? Let us heed the voice of John.
There might have been a mistake in this matter; perhaps he was mistaken for someone else.
He rejected false honor to hold on to the solid truth.
Let's see what he says about Christ and about himself:
"He who has the bride is the bridegroom."
Be chaste, love the bridegroom. But who are you? What do you tell us?
"He who has the bride is the bridegroom; but the friend of the bridegroom, who stands and listens to him, rejoices greatly because of the bridegroom's voice."
And a little later:
"Look," he says, "standing firm: I am not worthy to untie the strap of his sandal."
You humble yourself well, you stand deservedly, you do not fall deservedly, you listen deservedly, and you rejoice greatly because of the bridegroom's voice. Similarly, the Apostle, the friend of the bridegroom, is zealous, not for himself, but for the bridegroom. Let him hear the voice of one who is zealous with the zeal of God. He speaks with zeal, not his own, but with the zeal of God.
From where? How? For whom are you zealous?
"For I have betrothed you to one man, to present you as a pure virgin to Christ."
So what do you fear? Why are you zealous?
"I fear," he says, "that as the serpent deceived Eve with his cunning, so your minds may be corrupted from the purity that is in Christ."
The whole Church is called a virgin. You see and rejoice that the members of the Church have different gifts. Some are married men, some are married women; some are widowed men who do not seek wives anymore; some are widowed women who do not seek husbands anymore; some keep their purity from a young age; some have vowed their virginity to God. The gifts are different, but all these form one virgin.
Where is this virginity? Not in the body. In the body, it is in a few women. Even if virginity can be spoken of in men, it is the sanctity of a few. Purity of the body is also in the Church and is an honorable member. But there are other members in the body: all of them keep virginity in the mind. What is the virginity of the mind? Whole faith, solid hope, sincere charity. This virginity was feared by the one who was zealous for the bridegroom, fearing it might be corrupted by the serpent.
Just as a part of the body can be harmed in a specific place, the deception of the tongue can violate the purity of the heart.
This idea is reflected in the Song of Songs, where the holy Church says: "The watchmen who patrol the city found me. Have you seen the one my soul loves? After I had passed by them a little, I found the one my soul loves," as noted in the homily.
Now, let's see what the same Father says in the eighteenth book of his explanation on Job regarding these words. In Chapter Thirty-Three, he says: "When the Church was seeking its Redeemer, it did not want to place its hope in the very ancient preachers, which says: After I had passed by them a little, I found the one my soul loves. It could not have found Him if it had not passed by them."
Blessed Augustine speaks in harmony with this understanding in his first homily on the Gospel according to John. In Tractate One, he says: "John is among these mountains, about which we sang earlier, saying: 'I lift up my eyes to the mountains; from where will my help come?' Therefore, dearest brothers, if you wish to understand, lift your eyes to this mountain, that is, raise yourselves to the evangelist, raise yourselves to his meaning. But because these mountains receive peace, and one cannot be in peace who places hope in man, do not lift your eyes to the mountain in such a way that you think your hope should be placed in man. Instead, say: 'I lift up my eyes to the mountains; from where will my help come?' and immediately add: 'My help is from the Lord, who made heaven and earth.' Therefore, let us lift our eyes to the mountains from where help will come to us. And yet, it is not in these mountains that our hope should be placed. For the mountains receive what they minister to you. Therefore, the mountains receive where hope is to be placed when we lift our eyes to the Scriptures, because the Scriptures were ministered by men. We have lifted our eyes to the mountains from where help will come."
But still, because the same people who wrote the Scriptures did not shine by themselves, it was He who was their light, the one who enlightens every person coming into this world.
That mountain was John the Baptist, who said, "I am not the Christ," so no one placing hope in the mountain might fall away from Him who illuminates the mountains. And he himself confessed, saying, "For from his fullness we have all received."
You should say, "I lifted my eyes to the mountains, from where shall my help come?" Do not attribute the help that comes to you to the mountains, but instead follow and say, "My help comes from the Lord who made heaven and earth."
Therefore, brothers, I remind you of this so that when you raise your heart to the Scriptures, when the Gospel resounds, "In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God," and the rest. Understand that you have lifted your eyes to the mountains. For if they did not say these things, from where would you even think? You would not find.
Therefore, help comes to you from the mountains so that you might at least hear these things: if you cannot yet understand what you heard, invoke help from the Lord who made heaven and earth. The mountains could speak in such a way, but they cannot enlighten themselves, because they too were enlightened by hearing. From where did he who said these things receive? That John, brothers, who reclined on the Lord’s chest and drank from the Lord’s chest what he would offer us. But he offered words. You should understand the meaning from where he drank, who offered to you.
This same teacher speaks similarly in the twelfth homily of his aforementioned work when he discussed the words of John the Baptist, who responded to his disciples, saying, "A person cannot receive anything unless it has been given to him from heaven." You yourselves bear me witness that I said, "I am not the Christ." As if saying, why do you deceive yourselves? How did you pose this question to me? What did you say to me? Rabbi, the one who was with you across the Jordan, to whom you bore witness? You know what testimony I bore to him now?
I want to clarify that I am not who I said I was before.
I am someone who has received a calling from heaven.
You want me to remain silent, to deny the truth.
But no one can receive anything unless it is given from heaven.
You yourselves have heard me say: I am not the Christ.
And you are not the Christ either!
But what if you are greater because you baptized Him?
I was sent as a messenger; He is the judge.
Now, listen to a more passionate testimony.
Look at what is happening to us.
Understand what we should truly love.
To love anyone more than Christ is like committing adultery.
Why do I say this?
Let’s hear John’s words.
He could have been mistaken about his identity; he could have been perceived as someone he was not.
Yet, he rejected false honor to hold on to the truth.
Listen to what he says about Christ and himself: He who has the bride is the bridegroom.
Be pure and love the bridegroom.
But who are you?
What do you tell us?
He who has the bride is the bridegroom, but the friend of the bridegroom, who stands and listens, rejoices greatly at the bridegroom's voice.
And a little later, he said: He is standing on solid ground.
I am not worthy to untie the strap of His sandal.
You humble yourself well, you stand deservedly, you do not fall deservedly, you listen deservedly, and you rejoice greatly at the bridegroom's voice.
Thus, the Apostle, the friend of the bridegroom, is zealous, not for himself, but for the bridegroom.
Listen to the voice of one who is zealous with God's zeal.
He spoke with zeal, not for himself, but with the zeal of God.
Why?
For whom are you zealous?
For I have betrothed you to one husband, to present you as a pure virgin to Christ.
Why then do you fear?
Why are you zealous?
I fear, he said, lest as the serpent deceived Eve by his craftiness, so your minds may be corrupted from the simplicity that is in Christ.
The whole Church is called a virgin.
You see and rejoice that the members of the Church are diverse and endowed with different gifts.
Some are married men, some are married women; some are widowed men who seek wives no more; some are widowed women who seek husbands no more; some have preserved their purity from an early age; some have vowed their virginity to God.
There are different gifts, but all these are one virgin.
Where is this virginity?
It's not about the physical body.
Even if virginity exists in men, true holiness belongs to a select few.
Integrity of the body is also found in the Church, and it is an honorable member.
However, there are other members of the body, and all of them maintain virginity in the mind.
What is virginity of the mind?
It is pure faith, solid hope, and sincere love.
This is the virginity that he feared would be corrupted by the serpent for the spouse.
Just as a physical member can be violated in a certain place, the deception of the tongue violates the virginity of the heart.
Chapter 8 from the book "The City of God" by Saint Augustine, Chapter 23:
Although holy angels and men are called gods, they can never be called gods of gods, that is, gods of holy men. From this, it is clear that if holy angels cannot be called gods of men, much less can men be.
So the same doctor says: "Nevertheless, when we are asked if men are called gods because they are gods among the people whom God addresses through angels or men; how much more should the immortals, who enjoy that blessedness which men desire to reach by worshiping God, be worthy of that name; what will we answer, except that it is not for nothing that men are more expressly called gods in the holy Scriptures, than those immortals and blessed ones, to whom it is promised that we will be equal in the resurrection; lest, on account of their excellence, unbelieving weakness dares to make one of them our God.
This is easy to avoid in a man. And men should more evidently be called gods among the people of God, so that they may become certain and confident that He is their God, who is called the God of gods. Because even if those immortals and blessed ones in heaven are called gods, they are not called gods of gods, that is, gods of men among the people of God, to whom it was said: I said: you are gods, and all of you are sons of the Most High."
Hence, the Apostle says: Even if there are beings called gods, whether in heaven or on earth, (as there are many gods and many lords), for us there is one God, the Father, from whom all things come and for whom we live; and one Lord, Jesus Christ, through whom all things came and through whom we live.
From the book "The City of God" by Saint Augustine, Book 9, Chapter 23:
Although holy angels and men may be called gods, they cannot be called gods of gods, that is, gods of holy men.
From this, it is clear that if holy angels cannot be called gods of men, much less can men be called gods.
Thus, the same teacher says: "When we are asked if men are called gods because they are among the people whom God speaks to through angels or men, how much more deserving of that name are the immortals who enjoy that happiness which men strive to attain by worshiping God. What will we answer, except that it is not in vain that men are called gods more explicitly in the Holy Scriptures than those immortals and blessed ones, with whom we are promised to be equal in the resurrection? This is so that, due to their excellence, no one might dare to set up any of them as our God through weak faith.
This is easy to avoid in man.
It was more clearly necessary to call men gods among the people of God, so that they might be certain and confident that He is their God, who is called the God of gods.
For even if those immortals and blessed ones in heaven are called gods, they are not called gods of gods, that is, gods of men among the people of God, to whom it was said: I said, 'You are gods, and all of you are children of the Most High.'
Hence, the Apostle says: Even if there are beings called gods, whether in heaven or on earth, (as there are many gods and many lords), for us there is one God, the Father, from whom all things come and for whom we live; and one Lord, Jesus Christ, through whom all things came and through whom we live.
Given these circumstances, there is a way of divine, evangelical, or even human glory.
As Alchimus Avitus, bishop of Vienne, says in his Dialogue with King Gundobad:
"However, that which excludes the Father and Son from the equality of heavenly glory, excluding the angelic creation in the same way, you wrongfully attribute to me as a certain envy of the honor conferred upon the heavenly powers. You say: Therefore, we must also give glory to angels and archangels and whatever is in the heights. Although it is not relevant to the cause, even now I do not entirely reject it, as if we are afraid to give glory to a sublime and excellent creation.
Indeed, there is a way of divine, angelic, and even human glory, which is found in many places in the Scriptures and is attributed without fault of flattery to the merits of the saints and the crowns of kings. Among humans, the foremost glory is this: glory to all his saints; and in the Gospel, the Lord says that even Solomon in all his glory was not dressed like the little flower of the lily in its natural beauty."
Given these circumstances, there is a way of divine, evangelical, or even human glory. As Alchimus Avitus, bishop of Vienne, says in his Dialogue with King Gundobad:
"However, that which excludes the Father and Son from the equality of heavenly glory, excluding the angelic creation in the same way, you wrongfully attribute to me as a certain envy of the honor conferred upon the heavenly powers. You say: Therefore, we must also give glory to angels and archangels and whatever is in the heights. Although it is not relevant to the cause, even now I do not entirely reject it, as if we are afraid to give glory to a sublime and excellent creation.
Indeed, there is a way of divine, angelic, and even human glory, which is found in many places in the Scriptures and is attributed without fault of flattery to the merits of the saints and the crowns of kings.
Among humans, the greatest glory is the glory of all His saints.
In the Gospel, the Lord says that even Solomon, in all his glory, was not dressed as beautifully as a simple lily.
Now, let's listen to similar words from the blessed Jerome in his letter to the priest Riparius regarding the schism of Vigilantius:
"We do not worship or venerate, not just the relics of martyrs, but also not the sun and moon, angels, archangels, seraphim, cherubim, or any other name in this age or the future, so that we do not serve the creation rather than the Creator, who is blessed forever.
However, we honor the relics of martyrs to worship Him whose martyrs they are. We honor them so that the respect for the servants reflects on the Lord, who said: 'He who receives you receives Me.'"
Blessed Augustine agrees with this in the first book of "The City of God" (Chapter 13), where he says:
"The bodies of the deceased righteous should not be despised and discarded, as the Holy Spirit used them as instruments and vessels for all good works. Just as a father's garment or ring is cherished by descendants, the more affection they have for their parents, the bodies themselves should be respected, as we wear them much more intimately than any garments."
These practices are not merely decorative or external, but integral to our humanity.
That's why, in ancient times, funerals of the righteous were conducted with deep reverence, their rites were celebrated, and their burials were carefully arranged.
While alive, they instructed their children on how to handle their burial or even transferring their bodies.
The Lord Himself, who was to rise on the third day, praises the devout woman who anointed His body with precious ointment for His burial.
Those who respectfully took His body down from the cross to bury it are also honorably mentioned in the Gospel.
However, these actions do not imply that the dead have any sensation.
Instead, they signify that the bodies of the deceased are under God's care, and He is pleased with such acts of piety, reinforcing our faith in the resurrection.
Saint Augustine supports this view in his first book of "The City of God" (Chapter 13), where he says, "The bodies of deceased righteous should not be disregarded or discarded, as they were instruments and vessels for all good works by the Holy Spirit. Just as descendants cherish a father's garment or ring, they should hold the bodies, which are even more closely connected to us, in high regard.
These practices are not merely decorative or external, but integral to our humanity. That's why, in ancient times, funerals of the righteous were conducted with deep reverence, their rites were celebrated, and their burials were carefully arranged. While alive, they instructed their children on how to handle their burial or even transferring their bodies. The Lord Himself, who was to rise on the third day, praises the devout woman who anointed His body with precious ointment for His burial."
They are commendably mentioned in the Gospel, those who took his body down from the cross and carefully and honorably prepared it for burial.
However, this does not suggest that corpses have any feeling; instead, it signifies that such acts of piety are pleasing to God and are under his providence, affirming faith in the resurrection.
Similarly, Augustine in the eighth book of the same work (Chapter 27) says: "We do not establish temples, priesthoods, sacred rites, and sacrifices for martyrs, because it is not they but their God who is our God. We honor their memories as holy men of God who fought for the truth until their bodily deaths, so that the true religion would become known, exposing falsehoods and deceptions. Even those who felt this earlier were restrained by fear. But who has ever heard a faithful priest standing at the altar, even over the holy body of a martyr, constructed for the honor and worship of God, say in prayers: 'I offer you a sacrifice, Peter, or Paul, or Cyprian?' When it is offered to God at their memories, who made them both men and martyrs, and joined them with his holy angels in heavenly honor; so that through that celebration, we give thanks to the true God for their victories, and we are encouraged by their memory to strive for such crowns and palms, calling upon the same for help."
Therefore, whatever acts of devotion are performed at the places of martyrs, they are decorations of their memories, not sacred rites or sacrifices for the dead as if they were gods. Even those who bring their meals there, which better Christians do not do, and in many lands, there is no such custom: however, those who do it, when they have set them down, pray and take them away to eat, or even share them with the needy. They wish them to be sanctified there through the merits of the martyrs in the name of the Lord of the martyrs. But anyone who knows the one sacrifice of Christians knows that these are not sacrifices for the martyrs, which is also offered there.
We do not worship our martyrs with divine honors or human crimes like pagans worship their gods.
We do not offer sacrifices to them, nor do we turn their insults into sacred rites.
Likewise, Augustine in the eighth book of the same work (Chapter 27) says:
We do not establish temples, priesthoods, sacred rites, and sacrifices for the martyrs.
It is not they, but their God who is our God.
We honor their memories as holy people of God who fought for the truth even unto death, so that the true religion might be known, exposing false and fictitious beliefs.
Even those who previously believed otherwise were restrained by fear.
But who has ever heard of a faithful priest standing at the altar, even over the holy body of a martyr, saying in prayers: I offer you a sacrifice, Peter, or Paul, or Cyprian?
When at their memorials, it is offered to God, who made them both human and martyrs, and associated them with his holy angels in heavenly honor.
By this celebration, we give thanks to the true God for their victories, and we are inspired by the renewal of their memory to strive for such crowns and palms, calling upon the same God for help.
Therefore, whatever acts of religious devotion are performed at the places of the martyrs, they are decorations of the memories, not sacred rites or sacrifices for the dead as if they were gods.
Even those who bring their meals there, which is not done by better Christians, and in many lands, there is no such custom.
Yet whoever does so, when they set them out, they pray and take them away to eat, or they also distribute them to the needy, wishing them to be sanctified there through the merits of the martyrs in the name of the Lord of the martyrs.
But anyone who knows that there is one Christian sacrifice offered there also knows that these are not sacrifices for the martyrs.
Therefore, we do not worship our martyrs with divine honors or human accusations, as pagans worship their gods.
We do not offer sacrifices to them, nor do we turn their disgrace into sacred rites.
He also says in the book he wrote about the work of the six days, Questions on Genesis, Book 1, Chapter 84 that Jacob set up the stone he had placed under his head and made it a pillar, and he poured oil on it.
He did not do anything similar to idolatry.
For neither then nor later did he frequent the stone by worshiping or sacrificing to it; rather, it was a sign clearly established in prophecy, which pertains to anointing.
Hence, the name Christ comes from the anointing.
Not only should we not sacrifice to a stone, but neither to any physical or spiritual creature, nor should we build a temple in honor of anyone other than the living God alone.
Blessed Augustine, in his debate with Maximus the Manichaean, confirms this with these words: "If God the Holy Spirit were not, He would not have us as His temple. For it is written in the Apostle: Do you not know that you are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwells in you? And again: Do you not know that your bodies are the temple of the Holy Spirit within you, whom you have from God? Would we not be anathematized from the truth of Christ and from the Church of God if we made a temple of wood and stone for any most excellent holy angel, since we would be offering to a creature the service that is due only to God?"
We shouldn't offer sacrifices to a stone, nor should we offer them to any physical or spiritual creature, or build a temple in honor of anyone other than the living God alone.
Blessed Augustine proves this in various ways, especially in his debate with Maximus the Manichaean, with these words:
"If God the Holy Spirit were not present, He would not have a temple in us. For it is written by the Apostle: Do you not know that you are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwells in you?
And again: Do you not know that your bodies are the temple of the Holy Spirit, which you have from God?
If we were to make a temple out of wood and stones for any holy angel, even the most excellent one, we would be cursed by the truth of Christ and by the Church of God, because we would be giving the worship due to God alone to a creature."
Thus, God alone is the one in whom we should place our hope for happiness, as we have shown many times before. The same Father indicates this in the first book of "On Christian Doctrine" with these words (Book I, chapters 32, 33):
"When we show mercy and provide counsel to someone, we do it for their benefit and consider their well-being. But somehow, it also benefits us, because God does not leave without reward the mercy we extend to the needy.
This greatest reward is that we may enjoy Him, and that all who enjoy Him may also enjoy each other in Him.
For if we do this for ourselves, we remain on the path and place our hope for happiness in a person or an angel. A proud person or a proud angel would arrogantly accept this and take pleasure in having others place their hope in them.
But a holy person and a holy angel, seeing us weary and wanting to rest in them, do not let us remain but rather refresh us and compel us to go to Him, so that we may be happy together by enjoying Him.
For the Apostle exclaims: Was Paul crucified for you? Or were you baptized in the name of Paul?"
The one who plants is nothing, nor the one who waters—it's God who gives the growth.
An angel advises a person worshipping him to worship the one under whom he too is a fellow servant to the Lord.
When you enjoy fellowship with someone in God, you are enjoying fellowship with God rather than just the person.
By enjoying Him, you become blessed and will rejoice in reaching Him, in whom you've placed your hope.
Paul writes to Philemon: "Yes, brother," he says, "let me benefit from you in the Lord." If he hadn't added "in the Lord" and only said "let me benefit from you," it would have placed his hope of happiness in him.
Therefore, as we've shown many times, God alone is the one in whom we should place our hope of happiness. As the same Father hints in his book "On Christian Doctrine" (Book 1, Chapters 32, 33): "When we have mercy on someone and give them advice, we do it for their benefit and consider their well-being. But somehow, it also benefits us, because God does not leave unrewarded the mercy we show to the needy without seeking any payment. This highest reward is that we enjoy Him, and all who enjoy Him also enjoy each other in Him. For if we do this for ourselves, we remain on the way and place our hope of happiness in a person or an angel, which both a proud person and a proud angel arrogantly claim for themselves, and they delight in having others place their hope in them. However, a holy person and a holy angel refresh us when we are weary and wanting to rest in them, either with the provision they received on our behalf or even with the provision they received on their own behalf; yet they received it, and so refreshed, they compel us to go to Him, where we can be blessed together by enjoying Him."
As the Apostle exclaims: "Was Paul crucified for you? Or were you baptized in the name of Paul?"
The one who plants is nothing, nor the one who waters—it's God who gives the growth. An angel advises a person worshipping him to worship the one under whom he too is a fellow servant to the Lord.
When you enjoy fellowship with someone in God, you are enjoying fellowship with God rather than just the person.
You will enjoy what makes you happy, and you will rejoice when you achieve your hopes.
Therefore, Paul says to Philemon:
Philemon "Yes, brother, I will benefit from you in the Lord." If he had not added "in the Lord" and had only said "I will benefit from you," he would have placed his hope of happiness in him.
However, only a rational creature can be made happy, and this good comes only from God. The same teacher attests to this in the book "The City of God" 12 (Chapter 1), saying, "The good, by which a rational or intellectual creature is made happy, is nothing other than God."
Therefore, although not every creature can be made happy (for this privilege is not granted to or comprehended by wild animals, trees, stones, or anything of that sort), the one that can be made happy cannot achieve it by itself, because it was created from nothing, but rather from Him who created it.
By gaining this good, it becomes happy, and by losing it, it becomes miserable.
But He who is happy by His own good, and not by another, cannot be miserable because He cannot lose Himself.
We say, therefore, that the unchangeable good is none other than the one true blessed God.
However, the things He made are good because they are from Him, yet they are changeable because they were made from nothing, not from Him.
Therefore, although they are not the highest good, which is greater than God, they are great changeable goods that can cling to the unchangeable good to be happy, and such is their good that without it, they must necessarily be miserable.
"
Someone who is happy because of their own goodness, and not because of anything else, cannot be miserable because they cannot lose themselves.
Therefore, we say that the unchangeable good is none other than the one true blessed God.
The things He made are indeed good because they come from Him, but they are changeable because they were made from nothing, not from Him.
Although these things are not the highest good, which God is, they are great changeable goods that can cling to the unchangeable good to be blessed, which is so much their good that without it, they must be miserable.
From the book "On True Religion" (Chapter 55):
Therefore, let our religion not be the worship of heavenly and celestial bodies, but of Him whose contemplation makes one blessed.
For we are not blessed by seeing an angel, but by seeing the truth, through which we also love the angels and rejoice with them.
We do not envy them for enjoying such readiness without any troubles, but we love them more because we are commanded by our common Lord to hope for something similar.
Therefore, we honor them with love, not servitude.
We do not build temples for them.
They do not want to be honored by us in this way because they know that we ourselves, when we are good, are the temples of the highest God.
For when angels hear us, God hears as if in His true and not man-made temple, just as in all His saints, and His eternal commands, seen without law, become temporarily fulfilled.
Do not be troubled by the fact that, although He is invisible, it is often mentioned that He appeared visibly to the patriarchs.
Just as a sound that is heard is not the same as the meaning understood in silent intelligence, the form in which God was seen, though invisible by nature, was not what He actually is.
Nevertheless, He is seen in that bodily form, just as meaning is heard in the sound of a voice.
They did not ignore that they were seeing the invisible God in bodily form, which He was not.
For Moses conversed with the One speaking, and he still said to Him: "If I have found favor in Your sight, show me Yourself clearly, so that I may see You." When the angels hear, God listens as though in His true and unmade temple, just as in all His saints, and His eternal commands are carried out without being seen by law.
Do not be troubled by the fact that, although He is invisible, it is often mentioned that He appeared visibly to the patriarchs. Just as a sound that is heard is not the same as the meaning understood in silent intelligence, the form in which God was seen, though invisible by nature, was not what He actually is. Nevertheless, He is seen in that bodily form, just as meaning is heard in the sound of a voice. They did not ignore that they were seeing the invisible God in bodily form, which He was not.
For Moses conversed with the One speaking, and he still said to Him: "If I have found favor in Your sight, show me Yourself clearly, so that I may see You."
Also, Augustine in the fifth book (Chapter 14).
.
About the Trinity, it says: "The things said about the unchangeable and invisible nature, the supreme living being, and self-sufficient entity should not be measured by the standards of visible, changeable, mortal, or needy things."
But even in these matters, he says, even those that are adjacent to our bodily senses, or what we are within our inner selves, we strive to understand through knowledge and yet we are not sufficient. However, faithful piety still passionately seeks the divine and ineffable things above, not out of the arrogance of one's own strength, but inflamed by the grace of the Creator and Savior Himself.
For with what understanding does man grasp God, who does not yet grasp his own understanding with which he wants to comprehend Him? And if he already grasps this understanding, let him carefully consider that there is nothing better in his nature, and see whether he perceives any lines of forms, brilliance of colors, spacious grandeur, distance of parts, distinction of mass, any movements through intervals of places, or anything of that sort.
Certainly, we find none of these in what we consider the best in our nature, that is, in our intellect, by which we grasp wisdom as much as we are capable. Therefore, what we do not find in our best, we should not look for in that which is far better than our best.
So let us understand God, if we can, as much as we can: great without quantity, creator without need, present without place, containing all without form, everywhere whole without location, eternal without time, making changeable things without any change in Himself, and suffering nothing.
Whoever thinks of God in this way, although he might not yet fully discover what He is, still piously avoids, as much as he can, thinking anything about Him that He is not.
Likewise, Augustine in the fifth book (Chapter 14).
On the Trinity, he says:
"The things that are said about the unchangeable and invisible nature, the supreme living being, and the self-sufficient, should not be measured by the standards of visible, changeable, mortal, or needy things."
He adds that even in those things that are adjacent to our bodily senses, or what we ourselves are in our inner self, we struggle to comprehend with knowledge and are not sufficient.
Nevertheless, faithful piety burns fervently for those divine and ineffable things above, not inflated by the arrogance of its own strength, but inflamed by the grace of the Creator and Savior himself.
For how does a human mind grasp God, when it has not yet grasped its own understanding with which it wishes to grasp God?
If, however, it already grasps this, let it carefully note that there is nothing better in its own nature and see whether it sees any outlines of forms, brightness of colors, spacious size, distance of parts, distinction of mass, or any movements through intervals of space, or anything of that sort.
Certainly, we find none of these in the best part of our nature, that is, in our intellect by which we grasp wisdom, as much as we are capable.
Therefore, what we do not find in our better part, we should not seek in that which is far better than our better part.
Let us thus understand God, if we can, as much as we can: great without quantity, creator without need, present without position, containing all without habit, whole everywhere without place, eternal without time, making changeable things without any change in himself, and suffering nothing.
Whoever thinks of God in this way, although they may not yet fully discover what He is, piously avoids, as much as possible, thinking anything about Him that He is not.
However, regarding how much visible things hinder the grasping of invisible things, and how much the love of bodily things, even good ones, hinders the contemplation of spiritual things, the Lord himself demonstrates, saying:
"I tell you the truth. It is to your advantage that I go away. For if I do not go away, the Helper will not come to you. But if I go, I will send him to you."
John 16:7
Father Augustine often highlights this meaning in his Tractate 95 on John chapter 16:
"It is good for you that this form of a servant is taken away from you. The Word made flesh indeed dwells within you; but I do not want you to love me carnally anymore and be content with this milk, always desiring to remain infants. If I do not take away the tender nourishment with which I have fed you, you will not hunger for solid food; if you do not stop craving carnally, you will not be able to receive the Spirit."
What does it mean, "If I do not go away, the Comforter will not come to you"? Could He not send Him while still present here? Who would say that? Even where He was, the Comforter did not leave from there.
So what does it mean, "If I do not go away, the Comforter will not come to you," except that, "You cannot receive the Spirit unless you cease to love Christ carnally."
Hence, the one who had already received the Spirit said: "Even if we have known Christ according to the flesh, yet now we know Him thus no longer."
He did not call the very flesh of Christ according to the flesh, who spiritually recognized the Word made flesh.
This is undoubtedly what the good teacher meant by saying: "For if I do not go away, the Comforter will not come. But if I go, I will send Him to you."
While Christ descended bodily, not only the Holy Spirit, but the Father and the Son were also present with them spiritually.
Thus, when they were to become spiritual from being carnal, they would indeed have the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit more fully.
The Lord himself shows how much visible things hinder the understanding of invisible things, and how the love of bodily things, even good ones, hinders the contemplation of spiritual things, by saying: "I tell you the truth. It is good for you that I go away. For if I do not go away, the Comforter will not come to you. But if I go, I will send Him to you" (John 16:7).
Father Augustine often highlights this meaning in his Tractate 95 on John chapter 16: "It is good for you that this form of a servant is taken away from you. The Word made flesh indeed dwells within you; but I do not want you to love me carnally anymore, and be content with this milk, always desiring to remain infants."
If I didn't take away the tender food I fed you with, you wouldn't hunger for solid food.
If you keep hungering in a worldly way, you won't be able to take in the Spirit.
What does it mean, "If I don't go away, the Comforter won't come to you?"
Could He not send Him while He was here?
Who would say that?
For indeed, where He was, the other did not depart.
So what does it mean, "If I don't go away, the Comforter won't come to you?"
Unless it means, "You can't receive the Spirit unless you stop loving Christ in a worldly way."
Hence, the one who had already received the Spirit said, "Even though we knew Christ according to the flesh, we no longer know Him that way now."
For he who knows the Word made flesh spiritually does not call the very flesh of Christ according to the flesh.
Surely, this is what the good teacher meant by saying, "If I don't go away, the Comforter won't come. But if I go, I will send Him to you."
When Christ descended bodily, not only the Holy Spirit but also the Father and the Son were spiritually present with them.
Therefore, since they were to become spiritual from being worldly, they would certainly have the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit more fully.
No wise person is unaware that a faithful man, to progress from external things, must be drawn inward, not cast outward from inner things, to fail.
For he ought to move from the flesh to the soul, from the body to the spirit, from visible things to invisible things, from the world to God.
This is called progress if one moves to better things, not worse.
It is better to be a soul and worse to be a body, higher to be a spirit, and lower to be flesh, as anyone who has read and understood the words of Saint Augustine knows.
But even fools agree that what human and fleshly presumption fabricates is much worse than these.
In these situations, we find images that are called holy not only by the sacrilegious, who give divine worship to the works of their hands, but also by the foolish, who attribute holiness to lifeless images.
Additionally, they foolishly grant sanctification, which the Apostle says is achieved through the Word of God, to idols that have never spoken.
For example, Gideon, who was described by the angel as the bravest of men and is said to have died at a good old age, requested golden earrings from the spoils of his comrades, as recounted in divine Scripture.
He received them and made an Ephod, placing it in his city, Ophrah.
All Israel committed idolatry with it, and it became a ruin for Gideon and his entire household.
Even though he did this in honor of God, because he placed it in his own city rather than the location chosen by the Lord, which the law prohibited, his house faced destruction instead of elevation as he expected.
To understand that Gideon did not do this for foreign gods, it is noted that immediately after Gideon's death, the children of Israel turned away and committed idolatry with the Baals.
When they committed idolatry with the Ephod, it is not said that they turned away from God, nor is any idol named like Baalim or Astaroth.
However, when foreign gods are involved, Baalim is quickly mentioned, a plural term in Hebrew often representing idols in divine Scripture.
Just as when the people, erring, made a calf in the wilderness and said: These are your gods, Israel, who brought you out of the land of Egypt.
No wise person can be ignorant that a faithful individual, to progress from external things, must be drawn inward, not cast outward from internal things.
They must move from flesh to soul, from body to spirit, from visible to invisible, from the world to God.
This is called progress if one moves to better things, not worse.
It's better for the soul to be good, the body to be weaker, the spirit to be higher, and the flesh to be the lowest.
As anyone who reads and understands the words of Saint Augustine knows, what human and carnal presumption invents is much worse than this.
In this context, those images called sacred are also included, not only by the sacrilegious who give divine worship to the work of their hands, but also by the foolish who attribute sanctity to lifeless images.
They foolishly grant sanctification, which the Apostle says is achieved through the Word of God, to idols that have never spoken.
Finally, Gideon, who the angel said was the bravest of men and is said to have died at a good old age, requested the golden earrings from the spoils of his companions, as narrated in the Divine Scripture.
He received them and made an Ephod, placing it in his city, Ophrah.
All Israel worshiped it, and it became a downfall for Gideon and his entire house.
Although he did this in honor of God, because he placed it in his own city rather than where the Lord had chosen, which the law had forbidden, his house met destruction instead of elevation.
To make it clear Gideon did not do this for foreign gods, it immediately follows: But after Gideon died, the children of Israel turned away and worshiped the Baals.
When they worshiped the Ephod, it does not say they turned away from God; nor are Baals, Astartes, or any idols mentioned.
But when they turned to foreign gods, Baals are immediately specified, which in Hebrew is plural and usually signifies idols in the Divine Scripture.
Just as when the erring people made one calf in the desert, it was said: These are your gods, Israel, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt.
Exodus 32:4.
Not only is it wrong to give divine honor to those who do not deserve it, but it is also wrong to ambitiously honor the memories of the saints to gain popular glory.
The Lord rebukes the Pharisees for their actions in the Gospel, as witnessed by the blessed Jerome, with these words:
Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, who build the tombs of the prophets and decorate the monuments of the righteous, and say,
"If we had been in the days of our fathers, we would not have been partners with them in the blood of the prophets."
Matthew 23:29, 30.
Jerome then argues wisely that they are accused of being the children of murderers. While pretending to be good and seeking glory among the people, they build the tombs of the prophets whom their ancestors killed.
And say, in Matthew chapter 23,
"If we had been in that time, we would not have done what our fathers did."
Even if they don't say this in words, they show it through their actions by ambitiously and magnificently building the memorials of those killed, whom they don't deny were slaughtered by their fathers.
It's not only wrong to give divine honor to those who shouldn't receive it, but it's also reprehensible to ambitiously honor the memories of the saints just to gain popular glory.
The Lord rebukes the Pharisees for these actions in the Gospel, as witnessed by the blessed Jerome, with these words:
Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, who build the tombs of the prophets and decorate the monuments of the righteous, and say,
"If we had been in the days of our fathers, we would not have been partners with them in the blood of the prophets."
Matthew 23:29, 30.
Jerome then argues wisely that they are accused of being the children of murderers. While pretending to be good and seeking glory among the people, they build the tombs of the prophets whom their ancestors killed.
And say, in Matthew chapter 23,
"If we had been in that time, we would not have done what our fathers did."
Even if they don't say this in words, they show it through their actions by ambitiously and magnificently building the memorials of those killed, whom they don't deny were slaughtered by their fathers.
To emphasize that the testimony of individual saints should not be disregarded, I want to share the testimony of not just one person, but an entire Church.
This will clearly illustrate the divine honor and love that the early faithful had for the memories of the saints.
Specifically, the Church of God, which speaks among Catholics about the passion of Polycarp and the veneration of holy martyrs, says (Eusebius, Book 4, Chapter 15):
"But that adversary of all good and enemy of all the righteous, after seeing that Polycarp was crowned with the glory of martyrdom and the virtues of an exemplary life, and had obtained the rewards of immortality through death, began to act so that his remains would not be granted for burial to those who desired them.
Thus, Nicetas, Herod's father and Herod's brother, was urged to approach the judge to ask that the body not be allowed to be buried, lest Christians, abandoning the one who was crucified, start to worship him.
This was primarily plotted by the Jews, who also watched us so closely, lest we take him from the still-burning flames, poor souls not knowing that we can neither ever abandon Christ, who suffered death for the salvation of the whole world, nor worship anyone else, since we know who the true God is and who alone deserves worship.
We love and venerate the martyrs as disciples of the Lord and as those who fully kept faith with their teacher and Lord, and we also wish to be partakers in their faith and perseverance in love.
But when the centurion saw the obstinate contention of the Jews, he burned the body placed in the middle.
Thus, afterward, we collected the burnt bones, more precious than the most valuable gems and more esteemed than gold, and buried them as was fitting according to custom.
In that place, with the Lord's favor, we now hold our solemn and celebrated gatherings, especially on the day of his passion.
And when we celebrate the memories of those who suffered before, we do so in order to inspire the minds of those who follow with the exemplary path of their predecessors."
To ensure that no one thinks the testimony of individual saints should be disregarded, I want to share the testimony of not just one person, but an entire Church.
This will clearly show the divine honor given to the ancient faithful and their love for the memories of the saints.
The Church of God, which recounts the suffering of Polycarp among other things concerning the veneration of holy martyrs, says this (Eusebius, Book 4, Chapter 15):
"But the enemy of all good and adversary of the righteous, after seeing that Polycarp was crowned with the glory of martyrdom for his outstanding virtues in life and had received the rewards of immortality through death, began to take action to prevent our people from burying his remains.
Nicetas, Herod's father and brother of Dalca, was urged to approach the judge and ask him not to allow the body to be buried, fearing that Christians might start to worship Polycarp instead of the one who was crucified.
The Jews, especially, were behind this scheme, closely watching to ensure we did not take the body from the still-burning flames. They did not realize that we can never abandon Christ, who suffered death for the salvation of the world, nor worship anyone else, as we know him to be the true God who alone is to be worshipped.
We do, however, love and venerate the martyrs as disciples and followers of the Lord, because of their unbroken faith and steadfastness to their master and Lord, and we hope to be their companions in faith and perseverance in love.
When the centurion saw the stubborn insistence of the Jews, he burned the body in the middle of the place.
We then gathered up the burnt bones, which are more valuable to us than precious gems and more esteemed than gold, and buried them properly according to our custom.
In this place, with the Lord's favor, we now hold solemn and celebratory gatherings, especially on the day of his martyrdom."
When we celebrate the memories of those who suffered before, we do it to inspire the spirits of those who follow with the remarkable examples of their predecessors.
This is taken from the fourth book of Ecclesiastical History, so it may hold a place among the other authorities of divine law or the holy Fathers.
Since everyone agrees that religious worship is owed to God alone, what remains for the faithful is to cleanse their minds from all profane servitude to falsehoods and fight with all our strength, so we may truly say what is written:
"For the invention of man's wicked art has not led us into error, nor has the labor of painting's shadow, nor the sculpted image through various colors, whose sight gives desire to the foolish and loves the lifeless image without a soul. Lovers of evil are those who place hope in such things, and those who make them, and those who love, and those who worship them. And again: No man can make a god like himself. For being mortal, you create a dead thing with wicked hands. For he is better than those whom he worships: because he indeed lived, though mortal, but they never did" (Wisdom 15:4 and following).
He is superior to those he worships because he himself lived as a mortal, but they never did.
Wisdom Fifteen: Four and following
Some might argue that they don't believe the image they worship is divine,
but they venerate it to honor the one it represents.
To this, it's easy to respond: if the image being worshipped isn't God, it shouldn't be venerated at all.
This is for honoring the saints, who do not claim divine honors for themselves,
as many testimonies have shown.
It's also worth remembering that, as mentioned in the eleventh book of the cited history,
when the temples and idol statues in Alexandria were destroyed,
such a fervor of Christianity ignited among those converted from demons to Christ that everyone painted the sign of the Lord’s Cross
on doorposts, entrances, windows, walls, and columns.
Oh, how sincere is this religion!
The banner of the Cross was painted everywhere, not any likeness of a human face;
evidently, God arranged this marvelously, perhaps even without them knowing.
For if those who had abandoned the worship of demons were told to venerate the images of saints,
it might seem to them that they had merely exchanged one set of images for another.
Some might argue that they don't believe the image they worship is divine,
but they venerate it to honor the one it represents.
To this, it's easy to respond: if the image being worshipped isn't God, it shouldn't be venerated at all.
This is for honoring the saints, who do not claim divine honors for themselves,
as many testimonies have shown.
It's also worth remembering that, as mentioned in the eleventh book of the cited history,
when the temples and idol statues in Alexandria were destroyed,
such a fervor of Christianity ignited among those converted from demons to Christ that everyone painted the sign of the Lord’s Cross
on doorposts, entrances, windows, walls, and columns.
Oh, how sincere is this religion!
The cross's banner was painted everywhere, without any likeness of a human face.
Clearly, God arranged these things wonderfully, perhaps even without their knowledge.
If those who had abandoned the worship of demons were ordered to venerate images of saints, they might think they had not abandoned idols, but merely changed the images.
However, Eusebius of Caesarea shows in the seventh book (Chapter 18) of Ecclesiastical History that the images of the apostles and of the Lord himself were created and preserved by the ancients more out of love and remembrance than out of religious honor or veneration like the pagans.
He includes a narrative of this kind, touching upon some things he discovered in Caesarea Philippi.
He says:
"Since we have mentioned this city, it seems right to also recall an event that we deemed worthy of history. The Gospels record that the woman healed by the Savior from an issue of blood was a citizen of this city, and her house is still shown there. In front of her house, a pedestal is displayed in a higher place, on which an image of the woman is depicted as if she were kneeling and stretching out her hands in supplication. Another statue, also made of bronze, stands nearby, depicting a man dressed in a robe, reaching out his right hand to the woman. At the foot of this statue, a certain herb of a new kind grows from the base. When it sprouts, it usually grows up to the hem of the bronze robe. When the herb touches the hem with its tip, it acquires the power to drive away all diseases and ailments; so that whatever the body's infirmity, it is cured by a small dose of the herb's juice. However, it has no power at all if it is picked before it touches the top of the bronze hem. This statue was said to be made in the likeness of Jesus' face: it remained until our times, as we have seen with our own eyes."
It's no surprise that those Gentiles who believed and received benefits from the Savior seemed to offer gifts in return.
Even now, we see images of the apostles Peter and Paul, and of the Savior himself, being made and paintings being created.
We've also seen old images of them preserved by certain people.
This practice seems to be influenced by the Gentile custom of honoring those they deem worthy in this way.
Preserving the insignia of the ancients for posterity shows honor and love for those who keep them.
Moreover, the chair of James, the first bishop on earth, elected by the Savior and the apostles in Jerusalem, and designated by writings as the brother of Christ, is still preserved there to this day.
All who have held the priesthood of that seat have sat in it.
So far, Eusebius.
Eusebius of Caesarea, in the seventh book, Chapter 18, of Ecclesiastical History, shows that the images of the apostles and the Lord himself were preserved more out of love and remembrance than for religious honor or veneration like the Gentiles.
He narrates an event he learned happened at Caesarea Philippi:
"Since we have mentioned this city, it seems right to recall an event there worthy of history. The Gospels record that the woman who was suffering from a flow of blood and was healed by the Savior was a citizen of this city; and her house is still shown there to this day.
Moreover, before the doors of her house, there is a base set in an elevated place, showing an image of the woman kneeling with her hands outstretched in supplication, cast in bronze.
Another bronze statue stands nearby, dressed in the attire of a man, with a neatly draped cloak, extending his right hand to the woman."
At the foot of this statue, a unique herb with a new appearance grows from the base.
When it sprouts, it tends to grow up to the hem of the aerial robe.
When the herb reaches its highest point and touches the hem, it gains the power to dispel all diseases and weaknesses.
Thus, whatever the bodily ailment may be, it is cured by a small dose of this beneficial herb, provided that the herb has not been picked before it touches the highest point of the hem.
They said that this statue was made in the likeness of the face of Jesus.
It has remained until our own times, as we have seen with our own eyes.
It is not surprising that those who believed from the nations, for the benefits they received from the Savior, seemed to offer such a gift.
Even now, we see images of the apostles Peter or Paul and of the Savior himself being depicted and painted on tablets, and we have also seen some old images of them preserved.
This practice seems to be observed indifferently due to a custom from the Gentiles, who are accustomed to honoring those they consider worthy of honor in this way.
Indeed, preserving the insignia of the ancients for the memory of posterity is a sign of respect for them and love for the latter.
Finally, the chair of James, who was the first bishop on earth chosen by the Savior himself and by the apostles in Jerusalem, whom the scriptures designate as the brother of Christ, is still preserved there to this day.
Thus, all those who have held the priesthood of that seat up to the present time sit in it.
So far, Eusebius.
Twenty-one.
Bede, an Englishman by birth, was well-versed in divine scriptures in his time.
When he discussed the sea that was made in the temple of the Lord by Solomon, he added these words:
It should be noted that some believe it is prohibited by God's law to carve or paint likenesses of humans, animals, or things in the Church or any other place because the Decalogue of the law says: 'You shall not make for yourself a carved image, or any likeness of anything that is in heaven above, or that is on the earth beneath, or that is in the waters under the earth.
'
However, they wouldn't hold this view if they remembered Solomon's work, where he made palms and cherubim inside the temple with various carvings.
On its columns, he made pomegranates and nets, and on the bronze sea, he made twelve oxen and sculpted imagery.
Similarly, in the basins' sides, as read later, he made lions with oxen, palms, axles, and wheels, along with cherubim and various types of pictures.
Or if they considered Moses' works, who, by the Lord's command, made cherubim on the mercy seat and later made a bronze serpent in the desert, by whose sight the people were saved from the venom of wild serpents.
For if it was allowed to exalt a bronze serpent on a pole, which when looked at by the children of Israel, they lived; why is it not allowed to depict the exaltation of the Lord Savior on the cross, by which he conquered death, to bring it to the faithful's memory?
Or to depict his other miracles and healings, by which he wonderfully triumphed over the author of death?
Since the sight of these often provides great compunction to viewers and to those who are illiterate, it unfolds the living reading of the Lord's history.
For in Greek, painting is called ζωγραφία, which means living writing.
If it was permissible to make twelve bronze oxen, which bore the sea and faced the four corners of the world in groups of three; what prevents us from painting the twelve apostles, showing them going forth, baptizing all nations in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit, as a living scripture before everyone's eyes?
If it wasn't against the law to create engraved sculptures in a circle of ten cubits on the same sea, how can it be illegal to carve or paint the stories of saints and martyrs of Christ on panels, who, by keeping the divine law, deserved the glory of eternal reward?
But if we carefully consider the words of the law, it becomes clear that it doesn't forbid making images of things or animals, but rather it absolutely prohibits making them for the sake of idolatry.
When the Lord was going to speak on the holy mountain, He said: "You shall not make for yourself a carved image, or any likeness." He prefaced it with: "You shall have no other gods before me."
Then He added: "You shall not make for yourself a carved image, or any likeness of anything in heaven above, on the earth beneath, or in the water under the earth."
And He concluded: "You shall not bow down to them or worship them" Deuteronomy 5:8-9.
These words clearly state that those likenesses, which impious men make for the veneration of foreign gods and which wandering paganism has discovered for worship and adoration, are prohibited.
However, as I believe, no part of the divine law simply forbids making these things.
Otherwise, when the Pharisees tested Him about paying tribute to Caesar and mentioned the name and image of Caesar on the coin, the Lord wouldn't have answered: "Give to Caesar what is Caesar's, and to God what is God's."
Instead, He would have corrected their error, saying: "It is not lawful for you to make an image of Caesar on your coin, because such a sculpture is forbidden by divine law."
It would have been appropriate for Him to say this upon being shown the coin, if the image of Caesar, formed for idolatry and not for the judgment of royal authority, had been on it.
This should be enough to take from the booklet of the aforementioned man.
Bede, an Englishman moderately learned in divine scriptures, discussed Solomon's sea in the Temple of the Lord and added the following words:
"Some believe that God's law forbids carving or painting likenesses of humans, animals, or anything else in the Church or any other place, because the Decalogue says:
'You shall not make for yourself a carved image, nor any likeness of anything in heaven above, on the earth beneath, or in the waters under the earth.'
They wouldn't think this if they remembered Solomon’s work, who made palms and cherubim with various carvings inside the temple, and on its columns, pomegranates and nets, and in the bronze sea, twelve oxen with sculpted designs. As it reads later, there were also lions, oxen, palms, axles, wheels, cherubim, and various kinds of pictures on the sides of the vessels.
Or if they considered the works of Moses himself, who, by the Lord’s command, first made cherubim on the mercy seat, and later a bronze serpent in the desert, which saved the people from serpent venom when they looked at it.
If it was allowed to raise a bronze serpent on a pole for the Israelites to look at and live, why isn't it allowed to depict the exaltation of the Lord Savior on the cross, by which he conquered death, to remind the faithful;
or other miracles and healings, by which he triumphed over the author of death? The sight of these often moves viewers deeply, and for those who cannot read, it brings the story of the Lord to life.
Painting in Greek is called ζωγραφία, which means living writing.
If it was allowed to make twelve bronze oxen facing the four directions of the world in groups of three, what prohibits painting the twelve apostles as they went out, baptizing all nations in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, displayed as living writing before everyone's eyes?"
If it wasn't against the law to create carved images in a circle ten cubits in diameter on the same sea, how can it be considered unlawful to carve or paint the stories of saints and martyrs of Christ on panels?
These individuals, through adherence to divine law, have earned the glory of eternal reward.
But if we carefully examine the words of the law, it becomes clear that making images of things or animals isn't forbidden.
What is absolutely prohibited is making these images for the sake of idolatry.
When the Lord was about to speak on the holy mountain, he said: "You shall not make for yourself a carved image, or any likeness," and prefaced it with: "You shall have no other gods before me." Then he added: "You shall not make for yourself a carved image, or any likeness of anything that is in heaven above, or that is on the earth beneath, or that is in the waters under the earth. You shall not bow down to them or serve them" (Deuteronomy 5:8-9).
These words clearly declare that the forbidden likenesses are those usually made for the worship of foreign gods, which erring pagans use for worship and adoration.
Otherwise, no letter of divine law, as I see it, simply forbids making these images.
Otherwise, when the Pharisees tested the Lord about paying tribute to Caesar, mentioning that Caesar's name and image were on the coin, he wouldn't have responded: "Render to Caesar the things that are Caesar's, and to God the things that are God's." Instead, he would have corrected their misunderstanding, saying: "It is not lawful for you to make the image of Caesar on your minted gold, because such a carving is prohibited by divine law."
It would have been appropriate for him to say this if the image of Caesar, which is created not for idolatry but for the judgment of royal authority, had been shown to him on the tax coin.
This should suffice as a takeaway from the booklet of the aforementioned man.
We read in the Acts of the blessed Pope Sylvester that Emperor Constantine, not yet reborn through the font of life, recognized and immediately worshipped the faces of the holy apostles Peter and Paul.
These faces had been shown to him by the aforementioned pope on tablets where the images of both apostles had been preserved for memory since ancient times, just as they had been shown to him in a nighttime vision.
But should we, based on this authority of Constantine, worship the image of any saint?
The same emperor did this more out of the harmful custom of idolatry than from a consideration of the true reason, which he had not yet understood.
And lest we seem presumptuous in asserting this, we include the authority of the blessed Ambrose, Bishop of Milan—a man notable for his learning and holiness.
In the revelation shown to him of the holy martyrs Gervasius and Protasius, he reports that the blessed apostle Paul, speaking while those two were silent, recognized from the memory of his own image.
Yet, he does not write anywhere, not even mentioning the picture of him, nor does he say that he worshipped the apostle present and speaking with him in any way.
The blessed Paulinus also sharply rebukes a certain priest through a letter because he had requested that he send him a picture of himself and his wife, so that he might always have them present in that way, whom he loved in their absence.
It is also read that the blessed Pope Gregory rebuked the bishop of Fréjus because he had erased the images of the apostles from his basilica due to the superstition of the people who were worshipping them contrary to the rule of faith.
Rather than correcting such an error with reasonable authority, he allowed the painting to remain untouched for the memory of future generations.
But should we, by Constantine's authority, worship the image of any saint, especially when the emperor himself acted more out of a harmful habit of idolatry than from true understanding?
And to avoid seeming presumptive, we include the authority of the blessed Ambrose, bishop of Milan, a man of exceptional learning and holiness:
In his revelation of the holy martyrs Gervasius and Protasius, Ambrose reports that the blessed Apostle Paul, who spoke while the two were silent, recognized them from the memory of that painting.
Yet, he does not write anywhere about worshiping the painting or the apostle present with him in any way.
The blessed Paulinus also sharply rebuked a certain priest through a letter because the priest had asked for a painting of himself and his wife to be sent so he could always have them present, even though he loved them in their absence.
The blessed Pope Gregory is also recorded to have reproached the bishop of Frejus for erasing the images of the apostles from his basilica due to the superstition of people worshiping them against the rule of faith.
Instead of correcting the error with reasonable authority, he left the painting intact for the memory of posterity.
The blessed Augustine, in the book "City of God" (Book 10, Chapter 8), said among other things:
"We read that deadly snake bites, as a just punishment for sins, were healed by the bronze serpent lifted up on a pole and looked upon, so that the afflicted people were helped, and death was destroyed by death, symbolized by the likeness of the crucified death. This serpent, kept for the memory of that event, was later destroyed by King Hezekiah when the erring people began to worship it as an idol, earning him great praise for his piety."
About the Harmony of the Gospels, which he published against the pagans, he discusses those who claimed that the Lord Jesus Christ wrote a book in the form of a letter and handed it over to Peter and Paul, and he says:
"When they wanted to fabricate that Christ had written such a thing to his disciples, they thought it would be most credible to say he had written to those who were closest to him. They believed Peter and Paul were the most fitting recipients.
I believe they often saw them depicted together with Christ because the merits of Peter and Paul are celebrated with great solemnity in Rome, especially on the same day of their martyrdom. Thus, those who sought Christ and his apostles not in the holy scriptures, but on painted walls, completely deserved to be misled."
These are the words of Saint Augustine.
It is clearly understood that if the bronze serpent, which God commanded to be made, was smashed by the devout King Hezekiah because the erring people began to worship it as an idol, then images of saints should also be destroyed. The saints themselves would favor this, as they utterly detest being worshipped like idols, which shows contempt for divine religion. Especially since God did not command these images to be made; they were devised by human imagination.
Twenty-three.
Blessed Augustine, in the book "The City of God," Chapter 10 (Chapter 8), said among other things:
"We read that the deadly bites of serpents, as a just punishment for sins, were healed by the bronze serpent lifted up and looked upon on the wood, so that the afflicted people were helped, and death was destroyed by death, symbolizing the likeness of the crucified death. However, that same serpent, preserved to commemorate the deed, was later worshipped as an idol by the erring people and was subsequently smashed by King Hezekiah, with great praise for his piety."
Regarding the Harmony of the Gospels, written against the pagans, he addresses those who claimed that the Lord Jesus Christ wrote a book in letter form and gave it to Peter and Paul.
He says: "When they wanted to fabricate such a story, that Christ wrote to his disciples, they considered to whom it would be most credible that he wrote—those who were closest to him and to whom such a secret would be worthily entrusted.
Peter and Paul came to their minds. I believe this is because they often saw them depicted together with him, and the merits of Peter and Paul are celebrated more solemnly in Rome due to their shared day of martyrdom.
Thus, those who sought Christ and his apostles not in sacred books, but on painted walls, deservedly erred."
This is what Saint Augustine said.
From this, it is clearly understood that if the bronze serpent, which God commanded to be made, was shattered by the devout King Hezekiah because the erring people began to worship it as an idol, then the images of saints should be shattered and eradicated to dust even more devoutly by every means.
The saints themselves would favor this, as they are most indignant that they are worshipped like idols, which shows contempt for divine religion.
Especially since God did not command these images to be made; they were devised by human sense.
That God is more purely worshipped without images is also supported by Quintus Lucilius Balbus, a pagan philosopher.
As the aforementioned teacher includes him disputing in the fourth book of The City of God (Chapter 30) with these words: "Do you see how reason, derived from physical things, has been well and usefully applied to fictitious and imaginary gods?
This has led to false opinions, turbulent errors, and almost childish superstitions.
For the forms of the gods, their ages, clothing, and adornments are known to us; their types, marriages, kinships, and everything have been made to resemble human weakness.
They are also depicted with disturbed minds."
We've also accepted that the gods have desires, sicknesses, and anger.
And indeed, as the stories tell, the gods did not avoid wars and battles.
Not only, as in Homer when some gods defended opposing armies from different sides, but also when they fought their own wars against the Titans or the Giants.
These things are both said and believed most foolishly, and they are full of vanity and utmost frivolity.
Behold, meanwhile, what those who defend the gods of the nations confess.
Then, he says these things pertain to superstition, but to religion, which he himself seems to speak of according to the Stoics.
Not only the philosophers, he says, but even our ancestors separated superstition from religion.
Those who prayed and sacrificed all day long, he says, so that their children would survive them, were called superstitious.
Who does not understand he is trying, while fearing the custom of the city, to praise the religion of the ancestors and separate it from superstition, but he cannot find how to do it?
If those who prayed and sacrificed all day long were called superstitious by our ancestors, surely those who established what he criticizes, the images of the gods distinguished by different ages and clothing, the types of gods, marriages, and relationships?
When these things are blamed as superstitious, surely that blame implicates the ancestors who established and worshipped such images.
And after a few words, from Chapter 31: "The same most astute and learned author also says that only those seem to him to have understood what God is, who believed him to be a soul governing the world with motion and reason."
And thus, even though he did not yet grasp what the truth holds (for the true God is not a soul, but also the creator and founder of the soul), if he could be free from the prejudices of custom, he would confess and advocate worshipping one God, governing the world with motion and reason.
The question with him would remain about this matter, that he calls him a soul, not rather the creator of the soul.
He also mentions that the ancient Romans worshipped their gods for over 170 years without using statues.
He believes that if this practice had continued, the gods would have been revered more purely.
To support his view, he references the Jewish people.
He confidently concludes that those who first introduced statues of gods to the people removed fear from their cities and introduced error.
He wisely thought that statues could lead to disrespecting the gods.
Furthermore, Quintus Lucilius Balbus, a pagan philosopher, also argues that God is revered more purely without statues.
The previously mentioned teacher includes Balbus in his discussion in the fourth book of "The City of God" (Chapter 30), where he states:
Do you see how, from well and usefully discovered physical things, reason has been extended to fictitious and false gods?
This has led to false opinions, chaotic errors, and almost childish superstitions.
We know the forms, age, clothing, and adornments of the gods; their kinds, marriages, and relationships, all reflecting human frailty.
They are also depicted with troubled minds.
We have heard of the gods’ desires, sorrows, and anger.
The stories tell us that the gods did not avoid wars and battles.
Not only, as in Homer, did different gods defend opposite armies, but they also fought their own wars with the Titans and Giants.
These beliefs are foolish and full of vanity and extreme frivolity.
Behold, what those who defend the gods of the nations confess.
Then, when he speaks of these things as belonging to superstition, he seems to be referring to the religion which, according to the Stoics, he himself holds.
He states that not only philosophers but also our ancestors distinguished between superstition and religion.
Those who prayed and sacrificed all day, hoping their children would outlive them, were called superstitious.
Who doesn't understand that he is trying, while fearing the customs of the city, to praise the religion of the ancestors and separate it from superstition, but he can't find a way to do it?
If those who prayed and sacrificed all day were called superstitious by the ancestors, then what about those who established what he criticizes now: the diverse images of gods distinguished by age and clothing, their types, marriages, and kinships?
Surely, when these things are blamed as superstitious, it implicates the ancestors who established and worshipped such images.
And shortly after, in Chapter 31: "The same very sharp and learned author also says that only those who believed that God is a soul governing the world with motion and reason seemed to him to have understood what God is. And although he did not yet grasp the truth (for the true God is not a soul but the creator and maker of the soul too), if he could be free from the prejudices of custom, he would confess and advise that one God, governing the world with motion and reason, should be worshipped, so that the remaining dispute with him would be whether he called God a soul instead of the creator of the soul.
"
He also says that the ancient Romans worshipped gods without images for more than 170 years. If this had remained, the gods would be observed more purely.
Among other things, he would also use the Jewish people as a witness to his opinion. He does not doubt concluding that place by saying that those who first placed images of gods among the people took away fear from their cities and added error, wisely thinking that gods can easily be despised in the foolishness of images.
Blessed Augustine also says in his little book on True Religion that nothing hinders the perception of truth more than a life devoted to lust and false imaginations of sensible things, which are impressed upon us by this sensible world through the body, generating various opinions and errors.
He believed that there would be no error in religion if the soul did not worship its own soul, body, or its phantasms instead of God, which are nothing but figments drawn from the appearance of the body through bodily sense.
Therefore, let us serve the Creator rather than the creature, and not vanish in our own thoughts.
This is perfect religion.
He also says (Chapter 25): "Since the Catholic Church is spread and established throughout the entire world, those miracles were not allowed to endure in our time, lest the soul always seeks visible things, and by their familiarity, humanity grows cold, which was once set ablaze by their novelty."
Again, in Chapters 33 and 34, he mentions: "The mind judges wrongly when it is not made an eye for contemplating the highest beauty. It wants to turn the mind to bodies and the eyes to God. For it seeks to understand carnal things and to see spiritual things, which cannot be done. Therefore, this perversity must be corrected, because unless it makes what is above into below, and what is below into above, it will not be fit for the kingdom of heaven. Let us not seek the highest things in the lowest, nor cling to the lowest. Let us judge them, lest we be judged with them; that is, let us give them as much as the lowest form deserves, lest when we seek the highest in the lowest, we are numbered with the lowest among the highest."
Again, in Chapter 55, he says: "Let not our religion be the worship of dead men: for if they lived piously, they are not in such a state that they seek such honors; but they want us to worship Him, by whose illumination they rejoice that we are their companions in merit. Therefore, they should be honored for imitation, not worshiped for religion. Let not our religion be the worship of human works. For the artisans themselves, who make such things, are better, yet we should not worship them. Let not our religion be in our phantasms."
It is better to have any kind of truth than to rely on one's own judgment.
However, we should not worship the soul, even if it is true, when it imagines false things.
True straw is better than light formed by empty thoughts.
Yet, it is foolish to believe we should worship the straw that we can feel and touch.
The same idea is expressed in a letter to Consentius (Letter 85):
When carnal thoughts and vain imaginations begin to weaken reverence, with the inner help and illumination of one who does not want such idols in our heart, we should quickly break and shake these things off from our faith so that not even a trace of these phantasms remains.
Blessed Augustine also says in his book "On True Religion" that nothing hinders the perception of truth more than a life given to lust and false imaginations of sensible things, which impress various opinions and errors upon us through the body.
There would be no error in religion if the soul did not worship the soul, the body, or its own phantasms as its God, which are mere figments attracted by bodily senses. Therefore, let us serve the Creator rather than the creature, and not get lost in our thoughts. This is perfect religion.
He also says (Chapter 25):
When the Catholic Church spread and was established throughout the world, those miracles were not allowed to endure into our times.
This was so that the soul would not always seek visible things and humanity would not grow cold by their familiarity, which once burned with their novelty.
In the same place (Chapter 33, 34):
The mind judges perversely when it is not made to contemplate the highest beauty.
It wants to turn the mind to bodies and the eyes to God.
For it seeks to understand carnal things and see spiritual things, which cannot be done.
This perversity must be corrected because unless it reverses what is above and what is below, it will not be fit for the kingdom of heaven.
So let's not seek what is highest in what is lowest, nor cling to what is lowest.
Let's judge them, so we aren't judged with them; that means, let's give them only as much as their lowest form deserves.
Otherwise, when we look for what is first in what is last, we'll be counted among the last.
Similarly, he says in Chapter 55: Our religion should not be the worship of dead humans; because if they lived piously, they don't expect such honors.
Instead, they want us to worship the One who, by illuminating them, allows us to share in their joy.
Therefore, they should be honored for us to imitate, not worshipped for religion.
Our religion should not be the worship of human works.
The artisans who create such things are better than the things themselves, but we still shouldn't worship them.
Our religion should not be in our own fantasies.
Any kind of truth is better than anything that can be made up according to someone's whim.
And yet, we shouldn't worship our soul, even though it is a true soul, when it imagines falsely.
True straw is better than light formed in empty thought according to the will of the one imagining.
And yet, believing that the straw we can feel and touch should be worshipped is madness.
He says the same in his letter to Consent, Letter 85: When the composition of carnal thought and vain imagination begins to falter under reverence, with the help and enlightenment of the One who doesn't want to dwell in our hearts with such idols, we should hasten to break and remove them from our faith, not allowing even a speck of such fantasies to remain.
That he who appropriates anything divine in sacrilegious rites incurs the offense of true recklessness is testified by the same teacher in his letter to Januarius, saying in Letter 119, chapter 20:
Those who read fortunes from the pages of the Gospels, although it is preferable to consulting demons, still, I do not approve of this practice of turning divine oracles, which speak about another life, into tools for worldly business and the vanity of this life.
Blessed Jerome says something similar when discussing the Lord's words: "They enlarge their phylacteries and lengthen their tassels." He explains that they called those phylacteries of the Decalogue 'labels'; that whoever had them used them for protection and defense. They did not understand, as the Pharisees did, that these things should be carried in the heart, not on the body. Otherwise, even cupboards and chests contain books, but do not have the knowledge of God.
This is what superstitious women do among us today with small Gospels, pieces of the cross, and such things—who have zeal for God, but not according to knowledge.
The same teacher testifies in a letter to Januarius that one incurs true recklessness by using something divine in sacrilegious rites, saying this in Epistle 119, Chapter 20: "Those who read fortunes from the pages of the Gospels, although it is preferable to consulting demons, still, I do not approve of this practice of turning divine oracles, which speak about another life, into tools for worldly business and the vanity of this life."
Blessed Jerome says something similar when discussing the Lord's words: "They enlarge their phylacteries and lengthen their tassels." He explains that they called those phylacteries of the Decalogue 'labels'; that whoever had them used them for protection and defense. They did not understand, as the Pharisees did, that these things should be carried in the heart, not on the body. Otherwise, even cupboards and chests contain books, but do not have the knowledge of God.
This is how superstitious women among us still act today with small gospels, pieces of the cross, and similar items.
They have a zeal for God, but it's not based on knowledge.
Regarding such practices, as mentioned by the blessed Pope Leo, there is an impiety where some of the more foolish people worship the sun rising at the start of the day from high places.
Some Christians even believe they are being very religious by doing this.
Before they reach the basilica of the blessed Apostle Peter, dedicated to the one true and living God, they turn their bodies towards the rising sun, bow their heads in honor of the shining orb, and incline themselves.
We are greatly troubled and saddened by this, partly due to ignorance and partly due to the spirit of paganism.
Even if some worship the creator of the beautiful light rather than the light itself, which is a creature, they should still avoid the appearance of this practice.
When someone who has abandoned the worship of gods finds this habit among our people, won't they see this part of the old belief as plausible since it is common to both Christians and pagans?
Therefore, this condemnable perversity should be removed from the customs of the faithful, and the honor due to the one God should not be mixed with the rites of those who serve creatures.
For the divine Scripture says: You shall worship the Lord your God and serve him only.
And the blessed Job, a blameless man as the Lord says, keeps himself from all evil: Have I ever looked at the sun when it shone, or the moon moving brightly, and my heart was secretly enticed, and I kissed my hand in reverence, which is the greatest iniquity and a denial of the Most High God.
But what is the sun, or what is the moon, except visible elements of created and bodily light, one of greater brightness and the other of lesser light?
Just as there are different times for day and night, the Creator established distinct qualities in the lights.
Before these were made, there were days without the sun and nights without the moon.
These lights were created for the benefit of humans, so that we wouldn't be confused about the distinction of months, the recurrence of years, or the counting of time.
With clear signs of unequal hours, different delays, and various risings, the sun completes the years, and the moon renews the months.
On the fourth day, as we read, God said: Let there be lights in the firmament of heaven to give light upon the earth, to divide the day from the night, and let them be for signs and for seasons, for days and for years, and let them be lights in the firmament of heaven to give light upon the earth.
Awake, O man, and recognize the dignity of your nature.
Remember that you were made in the image of God, which, although corrupted in Adam, is restored in Christ.
Use visible creatures as they should be used, just like you use the earth, sea, sky, air, springs, and rivers.
Refer whatever is beautiful and wonderful in them to the praise and glory of the Creator.
Do not be devoted to the light that delights birds and serpents, beasts and cattle, flies and worms.
Touch physical light with your senses; but with all the affection of your mind, embrace the true light that illuminates every person coming into this world, about which the Prophet says: Approach Him, and be enlightened, and your faces shall not be ashamed.
For if we are the temple of God, and the Spirit of God dwells in us, what a faithful person has in their soul is greater than what they marvel at in the sky.
Therefore, beloved, we do not command or advise you to despise the works of God, nor to consider anything contrary to your faith in the good things that the good God has created.
Instead, use all kinds of creatures and the entire adornment of this world reasonably and temperately.
For as the Apostle says, what is seen is temporary, but what is not seen is eternal.
Since we are born for the present and reborn for the future, let us not be devoted to temporal goods but focused on eternal ones.
To better understand our hope, let us contemplate what divine grace has bestowed upon our nature in the sacrament of the Lord's birth.
Let us listen to the Apostle saying:
Colossians chapter 3, verses 3 to 4: "For you died, and your life is hidden with Christ in God. When Christ, who is your life, appears, then you also will appear with Him in glory."
Regarding such practices to quote the words of the blessed Pope Leo there arises an impiety where, at the beginning of daylight, some foolish people worship the rising sun from elevated places. Some Christians even think they are being very religious by doing this, so much so that before they reach the basilica of the blessed Apostle Peter, which is dedicated to the one true and living God, they turn their bodies towards the rising sun after climbing the steps leading to the higher altar, and bow their necks in honor of the shining orb.
We are greatly grieved and saddened by this, both because of the fault of ignorance and the spirit of paganism. Even if some might worship the creator of the beautiful light instead of the light itself, which is a creation, such practices must still be avoided. When this behavior is found among us, it will be seen as a plausible part of the old belief that is shared by both Christians and pagans.
Therefore, let the condemned perversity be cast out from the customs of the faithful, and let the honor due to the one God not be mixed with the rites of those who serve creatures. For the divine Scripture says:
Matthew chapter 4, verse 10: "You shall worship the Lord your God, and Him only shall you serve."
And the blessed Job, a blameless man as the Lord says, refrained from every evil thing:
Job chapter 31, verses 26 to 28: "Have I seen the sun shining, or the moon moving brightly, and my heart has been secretly enticed, and my hand has kissed my mouth, which is the greatest iniquity and a denial of the Most High God?"
What is the sun, or what is the moon, but visible elements of created and bodily light?
One shines brighter, and the other is dimmer.
Just as there are times for day and times for night, the Creator established different qualities in the lights.
Yet before these were made, days existed without the sun's duty, and nights without the moon's service.
These were created for the benefit of humans, so that we would not be misled in distinguishing months, the cycle of years, or the counting of time.
The sun marks the years with its varying durations, and the moon renews the months with its clear signs.
On the fourth day, as we read, God said, "Let there be lights in the firmament of the heavens, and let them shine upon the earth, and divide the day from the night, and let them be for signs and seasons, and for days and years. Let them be lights in the firmament of the heavens to give light upon the earth."
Wake up, O human, and recognize the dignity of your nature.
Remember you were made in the image of God, which, although corrupted in Adam, has been reformed in Christ.
Use the visible creations as they should be used, just as you use the earth, the sea, the sky, the air, the springs, and the rivers.
Whatever is beautiful and wondrous in them, attribute to the praise and glory of the Creator.
Do not be devoted to the light that birds and serpents, beasts and cattle, flies and worms delight in.
Touch the bodily light with bodily sense; and with all your mind's affection, embrace that true light which enlightens every person coming into this world. As the Prophet says, "Come to him, and be enlightened, and your faces will not be ashamed."
For if we are the temple of God, and the Spirit of God dwells in us, what each faithful person has in their soul is greater than what they marvel at in the sky.
So, beloved ones, we are not telling you to despise God's works or to consider anything created by the good God as contrary to your faith.
Instead, you should use all creatures and the beauty of this world reasonably and moderately.
For, as the Apostle says, "the things that are seen are temporary, but the things that are not seen are eternal."
Since we were born for the present and reborn for the future, let us not be devoted to temporary goods but focused on eternal ones. To see our hope more clearly, let us consider in the sacrament of the Lord's birth what divine grace has given to our nature. Let us hear the Apostle saying: "For you have died, and your life is hidden with Christ in God. When Christ, who is your life, appears, then you also will appear with him in glory."
In these words of the blessed Pope and orthodox doctor, we must especially consider that if the works of God's hands are not to be worshiped and honored, much less should the works of human hands be worshiped and honored, nor in honor of those whose likenesses they are said to be. For if any image were to be worshiped or honored, it should be the creator's rather than the creature's.
God made man in His own image and likeness. However, man cannot create anything that has the likeness of man's mind and reason. If he expresses some likeness of the body or its parts by carving or painting, he expresses what is least in man, not what is greatest. Surely, if men were to be worshiped, it would be the living rather than the painted ones, that is, where they have the likeness of God, not where they resemble animals or, more truly, lifeless stones or wood lacking life, sense, and reason.
Blessed Augustine says about these things in his book "On True Religion" (Chapter 5): "Just men, who have all their joy in one God, rejoice together with those who praise God through their deeds."
When they themselves are praised, as if they were the source of the praise, they correct those who are mistaken if they can.
Those whom they cannot correct, they do not encourage, and they wish to be corrected from that flaw.
If good angels and all holy ministries of God are similar or even purer and more holy, what do we fear in offending any of them if we are not superstitious, striving towards the one God with their help, and binding our souls to Him alone?
From Him, the term 'religion' is believed to be derived, and from Him, we should be free of all superstition.
Therefore, religion binds us to one omnipotent God.
Between our mind, by which we understand Him as Father and truth, that is, inner light, and Him, no creature is interposed.
In these words of the blessed pope and orthodox doctor, it is greatly emphasized that if the works of God's hands are not to be adored and worshipped, not even in honor of God, how much more should the works of human hands not be adored and worshipped, not even in honor of those whose likenesses they are said to be?
For if any image were to be adored or worshipped, it should be of the Creator rather than the creature.
Indeed, God made man in the image and likeness of God.
However, man cannot create anything that has the likeness of man in mind and reason.
If he expresses some likeness of the body or its parts by carving or painting, he indeed expresses the least part of man, not the greatest.
Surely, if men were to be adored, it would be the living more than the painted, that is, where they have the likeness of God, not where they have the likeness of beasts, or, more truly, of stones or wood, lacking life, sense, and reason.
Blessed Augustine says about these things in this way in the book "On True Religion" (Chapter 5): Just men, having all their joys in one God, when God is blessed through their deeds, they rejoice with those who praise.
But when they themselves are praised as if they were the source, they correct those who are mistaken if they can.
Those whom they cannot correct, they do not encourage, and they wish to be corrected from that flaw.
If good angels and all holy servants of God are as pure and holy as, or even purer and holier than we think, why should we fear offending them if we are not superstitious?
By focusing on the one God with their help and binding our souls to Him alone, from which the term 'religion' is believed to be derived, we would be free from all superstition.
After interjecting some thoughts:
Therefore, he says, religion binds us to the one omnipotent God.
This is because there is no creature between our mind, by which we understand Him as Father and truth, that is, the inner light, and Him.
In book 22, chapter 10 of The City of God:
Martyrs perform miracles, or rather God does so either with their cooperation or through their prayers, so that our faith may grow.
This faith helps us believe that they are not our gods, but that we have one God with us.
Pagans have erected temples to their gods, built altars, instituted priests, and made sacrifices.
However, we do not build temples for our martyrs as if they were gods, but memorials as for deceased humans whose spirits live with God.
Nor do we raise altars where we might sacrifice to the martyrs.
Instead, we sacrifice to the one God, both of the martyrs and of us.
In this sacrifice, as God's people who have conquered the world by their confession of Him, the martyrs are mentioned in their place and order.
Yet, they are not invoked by the priest who sacrifices.
The priest sacrifices to God, not to them, even though he does so in their memory; because he is a priest of God, not of them.
The sacrifice itself is the body of Christ, which is not offered to them, because they are part of it.
Thus far, blessed Augustine.
In book 22, chapter 10 of The City of God:
Martyrs perform miracles, or rather God does so either with their cooperation or through their prayers, so that our faith may grow.
This faith helps us believe that they are not our gods, but that we have one God with us.
Pagans have erected temples to their gods, built altars, instituted priests, and made sacrifices.
We don't build temples for our martyrs as if they were gods; instead, we create memorials for them as we do for deceased humans, whose spirits dwell with God.
We don't set up altars to offer sacrifices to the martyrs; we offer sacrifices to the one God, who is the God of both the martyrs and ourselves.
In this sacrifice, as people of God who have conquered the world by confessing Him, the martyrs are mentioned appropriately.
However, they are not invoked by the priest offering the sacrifice.
The priest sacrifices to God, not to them, even though he does it in their memory, because he is God's priest, not theirs.
The very sacrifice is the body of Christ, which is not offered to them, as they themselves are part of it.
Thus far, the blessed Augustine.
This is true religion, the Catholic custom, and the ancient tradition of the Fathers, as can easily be proven from the Book of Sacraments, which the Roman Church holds.
Anyone who goes beyond or abandons this way of veneration disregards the discipline of their Father and forsakes the law of their mother.
Therefore, grace will not be added to their head, nor a necklace to their neck.
Let the royal way be upheld.
This was taught by the apostles and the teachers of the Church; this was maintained by the leaders of the flock.
A sheep of God that leaves the shepherd and strays from the path led by the leader gets caught in thorns and is devoured by wolves.
Let us offer glory and honor to the Lord alone and not commit idolatry, becoming like those about whom God says: "I also shattered their heart, committing adultery and departing from me, and their eyes committing adultery through various things."
And the apostle Peter says: "Having eyes full of adultery, and insatiable sin." Jerusalem is also said to have committed adultery with the sons of the Chaldeans, seeing them depicted on the wall.
Let God be adored, worshipped, and venerated by the faithful; let sacrifices be offered to Him alone, whether in the mystery of the body and blood, by which we are redeemed, or in the sacrifice of a contrite and humbled heart. Angels and holy men are to be loved and honored with charity, not servitude. The body of Christ should not be offered to them, as they themselves are part of it.
We should not place our hope in man, but in God.
Otherwise, the prophetic words might apply to us:
"Cursed is the man who trusts in man, and makes flesh his strength, and whose heart departs from the Lord."
The Catholic doctors of the Church confirm that this applies to those who believed that the Lord Jesus Christ was merely a man and not also God, and therefore placed their trust in man, and thus were cursed.
This is sincere religion, this is the Catholic custom, this is the ancient tradition of the Fathers, as is easily proven from the Book of Sacraments, which the Roman Church holds.
Whoever exceeds or abandons this mode of veneration, scorns the discipline of their father and forsakes the law of their mother.
Therefore, neither grace will be added to their head, nor a necklace to their neck. Thus, the royal way should be followed.
This is what the apostles taught, the teachers of the Church; this is what the leaders of the flock held.
For a sheep of God that leaves its shepherd, strays from the path the ram leads, gets caught in thorns, and is devoured by wolves.
Let us offer glory and honor only to the Lord, and not engage in idolatry, becoming like those about whom God says:
"I also shattered their hearts for their idolatry and turning away from me, and their eyes for their idolatry with various things."
And the apostle Peter wrote:
"Having eyes full of adultery and that cannot cease from sin."
Jerusalem is also said to have committed idolatry with the sons of the Chaldeans, seeing them depicted on the wall.
Let God be worshiped, honored, and revered by the faithful; let sacrifices be made only to Him, whether in the mystery of His body and blood, by which we are redeemed, or in the sacrifice of a contrite and humbled heart.
Angels or holy men should be loved and honored with charity, not servitude.
The body of Christ should not be offered to them, since they themselves are a part of it.
We should not place our hope in man, but in God. Otherwise, the prophetic words might apply to us:
"Cursed is the man who trusts in man, and makes flesh his strength, and whose heart departs from the Lord."
Which Catholic teachers of the Church also confirm extended to those who believed that the Lord Jesus Christ was a mere human, not also God, and therefore were confident in man, and thus cursed.
Let no one deceive himself, let no one mislead himself, let no one cheat himself.
Whoever worships any painting, or a molded or cast statue, does not show worship to God; does not honor angels or holy men, but venerates idols.
Indeed, the cunning and crafty enemy of the human race does this, so that under the pretext of honoring the saints, he reintroduces idols, and again worships through various images; to turn us away from spiritual things, and plunge us into carnal things; and in all things we are worthy to hear from the Apostle: O foolish ones, who has bewitched you?
And: Are you so foolish, that having begun in the Spirit, you now finish in the flesh?
For Satan, as the same Apostle says, transforms himself into an angel of light.
Finally, he introduces revelries and drunkenness under the name of charity, pride and inflexible hardness he pretends to be the unshakable constancy of a steadfast mind, and calls blind fury zeal for rectitude.
Therefore, the Apostle John says: Do not believe every spirit, but test the spirits, whether they are from God.
Let us view a painting as a painting, lacking life, sense, and reason.
Let the eye be fed with this vision.
But let the soul worship God, who gives both the crown of victory to His saints, and to us the aid of their intercession.
Let no one deceive himself, let no one mislead himself, let no one cheat himself.
Whoever worships any painting, or a molded or cast statue, does not show worship to God; does not honor angels or holy men, but venerates idols.
Indeed, the cunning and crafty enemy of the human race does this, so that under the pretext of honoring the saints, he reintroduces idols, and again worships through various images; to turn us away from spiritual things, and plunge us into carnal things; and in all things we are worthy to hear from the Apostle: O foolish ones, who has bewitched you?
And: Are you so foolish, that having begun in the Spirit, you now finish in the flesh?
For Satan, as the same Apostle says, transforms himself into an angel of light.
Indeed, he introduces gluttony and drunkenness under the guise of charity, simulates inflexible arrogance as unwavering firmness of mind, and calls blind zeal righteousness.
Therefore, Apostle John says: "Do not believe every spirit, but test the spirits to see whether they are from God."
Let us view a painting as a painting - lifeless, without feeling or reason. Let the eye be fed by this vision. But let the soul worship God, who grants the crown of victory to His saints and aids us with their intercession.
For the ancients also had images of saints, either painted or sculpted, as has been shown above; but for the sake of history, to remember, not to worship. For example, the synodal acts, where Catholics supported by truth and victorious were painted, and heretics, convicted and expelled by the lies of false doctrines, were depicted to remind us of the firmness of the Catholic faith, according to the custom of wars, both external and civil, for the memory of the event. As we see in many places. But none of the ancient Catholics ever thought these images should be worshiped or adored.
Now, however, the error has grown so strong that it has become clear that worshiping figures and putting hope in them is close to or similar to the heresy of idolatry or Anthropomorphism. But what is the cause of this error?
With faith removed from the heart, all trust is placed in visible things.
Just as when we see paintings of armed men, farmers harvesting or gathering grapes, fishermen casting nets from boats, or hunters chasing deer with their dogs, we don't expect them to actually provide us with soldiers, help with our yearly work, heaps of wheat, streams of new wine, fish, deer, or pigs.
Likewise, when we see painted images of winged angels, apostles preaching, or martyrs enduring torture, we shouldn't expect any help from these images; because they can neither harm nor help us.
Therefore, to eliminate such superstition, the orthodox fathers decided that pictures should not be made in the Church:
So that what is worshipped and adored is not painted on walls.
But now the error has become so widespread and clear that worshipping figures and placing hope in them is close to or similar to the heresy of idolatry or Anthropomorphism.
And what is the cause of this error?
Faith removed from the heart, all trust placed in visible things.
Just as when we see paintings of armed men, farmers harvesting or gathering grapes, fishermen casting nets from boats, or hunters chasing deer with their dogs, we don't expect them to actually provide us with soldiers, help with our yearly work, heaps of wheat, streams of new wine, fish, deer, or pigs.
Likewise, when we see painted images of winged angels, apostles preaching, or martyrs enduring torture, we shouldn't expect any help from these images; because they can neither harm nor help us.
Therefore, to eliminate such superstition, the orthodox fathers decided that pictures should not be made in the Church:
So that what is worshipped and adored is not painted on walls.
What kind of presumption is it to celebrate Mass without a basilica, without an altar, and without the relics of saints, using such fabricated things?
The holy Fathers in the Council of Carthage declared in the Code of Canon Law of the Church of Africa, title eighty-three:
Let the altars that are randomly built in fields or by the wayside as memorials of martyrs, where no body or relics of the martyrs are proven to be buried, be destroyed by the bishops who oversee those places, if possible.
If this is not allowed due to popular unrest, the people should be advised not to frequent those places; so that those who think rightly are not held captive by any superstition; and no memory of martyrs should be accepted unless there is a body or some relics, or the origin of some dwelling, possession, or passion is faithfully handed down.
For the altars built anywhere based on dreams and futile revelations of any people should be entirely disapproved.
These rules were sufficient in those days.
For the error had not yet arisen, where now images painted with charcoal, vermilion, or red lead would be called holy images and proclaimed to be worthy of adoration.
Dreams and empty revelations that lead people to set up altars should be utterly rejected.
In those days, these statutes were enough for them because the error had not yet appeared.
Now, images made of charcoal, red lead, or cinnabar are wrongly called holy images and preached as objects of worship.
Deceitful cunning should not return, claiming it does not worship the images of saints, but the saints themselves.
For God proclaims: I will not give my glory to another, nor my praise to carved idols
The Apostle speaks about our Lord, the mediator between God and people, the man Christ Jesus: For this reason, God also exalted him and gave him the name that is above every name.
And he explains what this name is: That at the name of Jesus every knee should bend, in heaven, on earth, and under the earth, and every tongue confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.
This power, praise, dominion, this name above every name, no holy angel or human claims for themselves.
The angel who claimed it, or the human persuaded to claim it, both fell.
If any human or angel is worshipped other than him who is both God and human, called the angel of the great council as the Prophet bears witness, there is no other name above or equal to this name which is above every name.
No one is equal to God, no one else is essentially Jesus, that is, the Savior.
Let us believe the Apostle and yield to divine authority; let us bend the knee in the name of Jesus alone, which is above every name.
If we give this honor to another, we are judged as strangers to God and allowed to follow the desires of our hearts in our own inventions.
Deceitful cunning should not return, claiming it does not worship the images of saints, but the saints themselves.
For God proclaims: I will not give my glory to another, nor my praise to carved idols.
And the Apostle speaks of our Lord and mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus:
Because of this, God exalted Him and gave Him a name that is above every name.
He then explains what this name is: At the name of Jesus, every knee should bow, in heaven, on earth, and under the earth, and every tongue confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.
This power, praise, and dominion, this name that is above every name, is not claimed by any holy angel or holy man.
For the angel who claimed it, or the man who was persuaded to claim it, both fell.
If any man or angel is worshipped besides Him who is both God and man, and the angel of the great council, as the Prophet testifies, there is no other name that is or can be above this name that is above every name, or equal to it.
But because no one is equal to God, and no one else is essentially Jesus, that is, Savior, let us believe the Apostle, yield to divine authority; let us bow the knee at the name of Jesus alone, which is above every name; lest if we give this honor to another, we are judged as strangers by God and are allowed to go our own way according to the desires of our hearts.
Finished about the Pictures by Agobard the bishop.