Prolegomena (Bibliotheca Veterum Patrum Gallandi Volume Eight)
Aurelius, the foremost leader of all Africa, is celebrated among the distinguished Fathers and Teachers of the Church by Saint Fulgentius, who said:
Who would deny the blessed bishops like Innocent of Rome, Athanasius of Alexandria, Eustathius of Antioch, Gregory of Nazianzus, Basil of Caesarea, Ambrose of Milan, Hilary of Poitiers, John of Constantinople, Aurelius of Carthage, Augustine of Hippo, and others who diligently led the Churches of God?
They stood against heretics, whether new or established, with the aid of the Holy Spirit within them.
They prevented old wolves from infiltrating the Church flock and kept new ones from lurking dangerously in the Lord's fold.
Who, I ask, would deny these as vessels of mercy, prepared by God for glory?
This is what that holy bishop of Ruspe declared.
And truly, Aurelius of Carthage is deserving of such praise.
He was the first, as a learned man noted, to condemn Coelestius, who denied the sin of origin, even before Augustine spoke out.
He later excommunicated his followers through several synods.
Thus, Saint Prosper, in his poem Against the Ungrateful, spoke of those Pelagians condemned in a synod led by Aurelius:
Could a holy Council, guided by Aurelius and inspired by Augustine, have reached a different outcome?
Furthermore, he drove the Donatists out of almost all of Africa.
He transformed pagan temples for use in the Christian faith.
In seventeen plenary councils across Africa, he upheld orthodox doctrine and discipline with outstanding laws.
Regarding the time Aurelius served, it's clear he had not yet been appointed to the episcopal chair by the year 390.
In that year, at the second council of Carthage on May 19th, his predecessor Genethlius presided, who later passed away.
Thus, it was in either 391 or at the latest 392 that Aurelius took on the role of bishop, according to Tillemont.
The exact year Aurelius passed away isn't entirely clear, so nothing definitive can be said.
However, he was still alive in 427 when Saint Augustine was writing the thirty-second book of "The City of God." In it, Augustine mentions the deacons of the Church of Carthage, stating, "Among them, and indeed the only one now among the living deserving to be named with the honor due from us, is Bishop Aurelius."
This is also confirmed in Augustine's second book of "Retractations," written in the same year, where he notes, "For these reasons, the venerable old man Aurelius, bishop of the Church of this city, ordered me to write something about it, and I did."
Furthermore, Aurelius was still alive in 429 when Augustine's letter 231 was said to have been written. In this letter, Augustine advises Darius about some books sent without being requested, saying, "If you read all these while you are still in Africa, send your judgment about them, or send them to us, or send them to us through our brother Aurelius, a servant of the Lord."
Additionally, as noted by Norisius and later by Pagius and Tillemont, we learn from Marius Mercator's "Commonitorium," presented to Theodosius in 429, that Aurelius was still alive that year. When Mercator mentions Ambrose, Innocent, Zosimus, Theodore, and Praylius, he refers to them as of blessed memory, but he does not do so for Aurelius.
In fact, regarding Coelestius, who was accused in Carthage, Mercator states, "Concerning the chapters written below, he was accused before Bishop Aurelius of the mentioned city by a certain Paulinus, a deacon of the blessed memory of Ambrose, Bishop of Milan."
Therefore, Aurelius was still alive that year but likely passed away shortly thereafter, possibly in 430. Before Easter of 431, Capreolus was seated in Carthage, as we gather from his letters read at the Council of Ephesus.
After calculating the chronological details, we find that after leading Africa for nearly 40 years, the venerable old man passed away in the year 430.
This was the same year that Saint Augustine returned his spirit to God.
However, a bit earlier, on July 20th, his memory was celebrated in the oldest calendar of the Carthaginian Church, published by Mabillon, and noted with these words:
"13 days before the Kalends of August, that is, July 20, the Deposition of Saint Aurelius, Bishop."
Besides the speeches he gave to the African fathers, recorded in the Code of the African Church, our Carthaginian bishop wrote various letters, which Tillemont carefully reviewed. Among them is an encyclical addressed to all the bishops throughout the provinces of Byzacena and Arzugitana, regarding the condemnation of the heretics Pelagius and Coelestius. This was included in the ecclesiastical annals by the great Baronius from Cresconius's collection. We, however, have followed the copy enhanced with various readings and notes by the learned John Garnier from his third dissertation about Marius Mercator concerning the Imperial Constitutions published in the Pelagian case.
The subscription of the letter reads:
"Given on the Kalends of August in Carthage, during the consulship of Monaxius and Plinta," which corresponds to the year 419.
Therefore, in our edition, the letter should be moved from that year and placed later, especially if you consider what we just discussed about Aurelius's episcopal seat.
Furthermore, what greatly enhances the commendation of this letter is what the praised Garnier notes: it was indeed written to the bishops by someone who was most knowledgeable of the canons, outstanding in holiness, very mindful of episcopal dignity, very close to Augustine in affairs, and almost singular.
So that knowledge, holiness, the pursuit of dignity, and association with Augustine bestow such great authority on Aurelius in this matter, as can be the greatest, even for the example of the prelates.
So far, the learned man.
It's important to note that many letters were written to Aurelius by men renowned for their holiness and learning, including Innocent the First, his successor Zosimus, Paulinus of Nola, Augustine, Alypius, John Chrysostom, and others.
Saint Augustine also dedicated to Aurelius his significant work, On the Trinity, along with the book On the Proceedings of Pelagius, and another, On the Work of Monks, as a mark of honor.
What more can be said?
To conclude with the words of a most distinguished writer:
So much was entrusted to Aurelius alone by all the bishops of those provinces that at the Council of Carthage, held during the reign of Honorius the Seventh and Theodosius the Second, the Fathers said to him:
It has also been agreed, at the request of all, that on all letters issued by the council, only Your Holiness shall sign.
Letter to All Bishops Established Throughout the Province of Byzacena and Arzugitana by Saint Aurelius, Bishop of Carthage
Concerning the condemnation of the heretics Pelagius and Coelestius.
To my most beloved and esteemed brothers and fellow priests, Donatianus of the first seat, Januarus, Felicius, Palatinus, Primianus, Cajus, another Cajus, Januarius, Victorinus, and others across the provinces of Byzacena and Arzugitana, from Bishop Aurelius.
Regarding the condemnation of Coelestius and Pelagius and their teachings, you, my dear brothers, remember that you participated in the plenary council.
In honor of God, whose hand guides the king's heart, as stated in Proverbs chapter twenty-one, verse four, the authority of the most glorious Christian rulers, who uphold the true and catholic faith, has been added.
They wished for this to be communicated to all fellow bishops through my humble self.
Therefore, I hurried to inform your honorable fraternity by sending copies, so that nothing harmful from the deceptive persuasion of the aforementioned, now excluded from the universal Church, might creep into any part of the province.
Hence, such a necessary decree from the Christian rulers should not be hidden from you, nor the letters given to me by them.
After reading the copies, you will understand how each of you should subscribe, whether those who have already subscribed to the synodal acts or those who could not attend the plenary council of all Africa.
Since your complete subscription was in the condemnation of these heretics, nothing should remain that might reasonably suggest any suspicion of dissimulation, negligence, or hidden depravity.
And in another hand: I wish, Brothers, that you live well and remember me.
Dated on the Kalends of August, in Carthage, during the consulship of Monaxius and Plinta.
THE SYNOD OF AURELIUS, BISHOP OF CARTHAGE.
From the synodical letter, found in Labb. Councils, volume two, column 1184.
After Theodosius and Nectarius ascended to the heavens, Arcadius, son of Theodosius, took the throne, while Honorius, Arcadius's brother, succeeded Gratian.
During this period, a provincial and sacred synod convened in Carthage, attended by one hundred twenty-seven fathers.
This synod took decisive action against the idol-worshipping Donatists, other heresies, and errors in the region.
It was led by Aurelius, the bishop of Carthage.
The sacred and divine canons it issued remained effective until the time of the younger Theodosius.
Appendix
NOTICE ON THE FOLLOWING LETTER.
Baronius provides clear evidence regarding the accusation of this letter being false in the year 374, number 40, stating:
Letters are believed to have been issued in the name of Damasus to Aurelius, Bishop of Carthage, during the same consular year, as placed by Isidore Mercator at the start of his collection.
These are preceded by letters from Aurelius to Damasus, where he requested decrees from the Roman pontiffs to be sent from the apostolic see.
But why, I ask with respect, would there be a need to embellish the entrance of a grand house with falsehoods, leading to significant suspicion about the rest of the contents?
How, I wonder, could Aurelius, Bishop of Carthage, have written to Damasus, the Roman pontiff, and received a reply in that particular year, especially under those consuls?
When Saint Augustine became a Christian and returned to Africa, he found Aurelius serving as a deacon of the Church of Carthage, and later, he became a bishop of the same city.
Augustine himself testifies to this, clearly stating in his commentary on the City of God, about his return from overseas to Carthage and recounts the miracle of Innocentius being healed from an incurable disease.
And finally, he says:
"Every day he was visited by holy men, the then Bishop of Uzala of blessed memory, Saturninus, and the priest Gelosus, and the deacons of the Church of Carthage, among whom was, and from whom now alone remains in human affairs, the bishop whom we must name with due honor, Aurelius; with whom, recalling the miraculous works of God, we often discussed this matter, and we found that he remembered well what we are recounting."
Thus he himself.
You see, then, how much later we must place the bishopric of Aurelius of Carthage.
It's far from true that, as a bishop, he wrote to Damasus this year or received letters from him.
We know this because Augustine's return to Africa, after becoming a Christian, leaving Milan, and sailing from the Roman port, occurred in the year of our Lord 389.
It becomes clear that Aurelius wasn't made bishop of Carthage even fifteen years later and remained a deacon.
You see, then, how the correct timeline of events disproves the twisted fabrications of others.
So, it shouldn't surprise you that we are frequently and diligently engaged in discerning the true sequence of times.
Letter of Aurelius to Pope Damasus
To the most blessed Pope Damasus, Aurelius, Bishop of Carthage.
We humbly seek the glory of the apostolic seat and the grace of your eminence.
We kindly ask you to send us, in writing, any decrees you can find from the time of the blessed prince of the apostles, Peter, up to the beginning of your holiness, governed by the wisdom and authority of the apostolic seat.
Through the nobility and wisdom of your holiness, we hope to learn what was decreed in the holy seat during those times, and to know who acted against the apostolic canons.
Farewell, most holy Pope, and please pray for us, most loving father.
Given on the eighth day before the Kalends of March.
Read in Rome on the fifth day before the Nones of May.