Prologue
When I often discussed the Holy Scriptures with my brothers, they thought I knew something, even though I didn't.
They frequently asked me about issues that troubled them, which seemed difficult to understand or believe.
When I replied that I either didn't know or wasn't available to share the Scriptures with them, this answer wasn't satisfying for them.
Their affection led them to accuse me of pretending not to know or being too busy, because when desire is strong, patience is hard to maintain, even if delayed briefly.
As a certain pagan said, "To a desiring mind, nothing is fast enough."
So, to avoid seeming unwilling to share knowledge with those eager to learn, and to avoid their displeasure for not sharing what little I could, I decided it was better to respond to some of their questions in writing rather than speaking.
I'm not claiming to solve their questions perfectly, which would be bold to promise, but to offer whatever answers I can, which, with God's help, might be more easily fulfilled.
If what I've written reaches someone wise, I ask them not to judge me hastily as presumptuous for wanting to write down my responses. Even if it seems unnecessary to the learned, it won't be useless to me and those like me who are unlearned.
Since memory isn't a reliable keeper of useful thoughts, and many things slip away into forgetfulness, I wanted to capture some of them in writing to recall what might otherwise be forgotten.
To someone wise who knows the Holy Scriptures by heart, writings from a modest source may not seem worth much, but for the simple and less learned, they shouldn't be dismissed.
Finally, what is humbly offered to brotherly love shouldn't be seen as presumption.
That should wrap up our introduction, so let's dive into the first response.
Chapter One
You might wonder, brothers, about the fate of the first Adam.
Genesis tells us he sinned in a way that deserved damnation, yet it doesn't explicitly say he repented.
We all know he sinned, not only from what we read but also from our own experience, as we endure the consequences of his sin by living miserably in this life and leaving it even more miserably.
It's worth mentioning his state before the sin and how he was changed after, even though it's known, because it's important for what I want to discuss.
Adam was created in a unique state, unlike anyone else after him.
He was made both mortal and immortal-mortal in that he could die, and immortal in that he would not have to die.
He had the freedom to choose whether to sin or not, with each choice having its consequences: sin, and death would follow; avoid sin, and he would never die.
As it later says in Ecclesiasticus 13:19, "Every animal loves its own kind"; Adam was given a helper similar to himself, as noted in Ecclesiasticus 17:12. A woman was created not from elsewhere but from his rib while he slept, so she would be lovingly joined to him by natural affection and provide companionship.
He was placed in paradise, filled with various kinds of trees, so he could enjoy their fruit and beauty.
Among these trees were two with significant names: the tree of life and the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, named for their effects.
Adam was permitted to eat from the trees in paradise to avoid hunger and from the tree of life to avoid death and aging.
To prevent him from becoming prideful like the Angel once did in glory, a command was given to him to follow obediently. This was to ensure that while he had the dignity to rule over other creatures on earth, he remained subject only to God, humbled by the duty of obedience.
He was told he could eat from every tree in paradise, except for the fruit of the knowledge of good and evil, which he must not eat.
For if he did, he would surely die.
That tree wasn't evil, as it was created by a good God.
It was good for man, who was created, to obey the Creator, so he might learn obedience and earn heavenly glory through his own merit.
If he humbly followed what was commanded, he would be deemed worthy to join the company of angels without facing death after a deserving life.
He would cease being mortal and become immortal in a new way.
He was immortal in that he could simply not die; he would become immortal so he could not die in any way.
This impossibility wouldn't be a weakness or a defect of frailty, but a strength and pinnacle of perfection.
Therefore, it was right for a man created by such a great Creator, the giver of so many great goods, to obey.
And by loving good patience, aim for the greater rewards promised.
But who can truly express in words or even imagine how greatly he sinned when he turned away from all these things and, abandoning the Creator's command, listened to the voice of his deceived wife?
For the devil envied the great glory he enjoyed in the present and the hope of future glory.
As it is written in the Gospel of John, Chapter 8, he was a murderer from the beginning, from when man was created.
Having lost true life, which is God, he wanted to take it away from man too.
So that where he fell through pride, man would not rise by obedience.
Seeking ways to bring him down, he took the form of a cunning serpent and, hiding in it, approached the woman first, hoping she would be easier to lead into sin, knowing her to be the weaker sex.
Cleverly approaching her, he reminded her of the divine command, ensuring that when she was later accused of transgression, she couldn't claim forgetfulness as an excuse.
"Why," it asked, "did God command you not to eat from any tree in the garden?"
She replied, "We were told we could eat from every tree in the garden, except for the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, which was forbidden to us, lest we die."
To this, he responded, "You will not die at all. God knows that on the day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened, and you will be like gods, knowing good and evil."
God, who can be like you? Who in the clouds can be compared to the Lord, or who among the sons of God can be like God?"
The woman believed the deceiver, thinking that what God had said was false, and that the wicked enemy was telling the truth. But not wanting to sin alone, she went to the man and, with feminine persuasion, convinced him to eat the forbidden fruit to become like God, as the serpent claimed.
However, he knew this claim was false and that God was undoubtedly truthful in everything He said. Yet, he chose to comply with his wife rather than upset her by obeying the Creator. He couldn't bear to see her, whom he had taken as a partner by marital law, saddened, hoping he could reconcile with God through repentance.
This is what the Apostle later wrote: "Adam was not deceived, but the woman, being deceived, was in the transgression" First Timothy 2.
She was indeed deceived when she believed what God had said wasn't true; he was not deceived in that he knew the serpent's suggestion was false. Both were miserable. What could be more detestable than considering God a liar? Likewise, what could be more wicked than succumbing to feminine flattery, ignoring the one whom man knew to be the truthful God? Both sinned and ate the forbidden fruit without hesitation, and as the serpent said, their eyes were opened.
What does this mean? Did they not see before? Is it not written: "The woman saw that the tree was good for food, and pleasing to the eyes, and desirable for gaining wisdom, and she took some of its fruit and ate it, and gave some to her husband."
Genesis 3.
And it is immediately added: "He ate, and the eyes of both were opened" (Genesis 3).
Their eyes were opened, not just to see what they had seen before, but to understand what they hadn't known: the difference between the good they lost through sin and the evil they experienced.
Many people only realize how pleasant health is when they are afflicted by severe illness.
That's why the tree is called the tree of the knowledge of good and evil; tasting its fruit brought this kind of understanding.
Divine punishment, which leaves no sin unpunished, immediately struck them both, afflicting them with the itch of desire in the parts of the body considered shameful.
This happened so that those who refused to humbly obey God's law were forced to feel the law of the flesh opposing the law of the mind.
Realizing this, and stripped of the garment of immortality, they were ashamed of being naked and, wishing to hide, covered their private parts with fig leaves.
Disobedience, which is punished by more disobedience, particularly rules in the moist areas, so that because all their descendants are bound by the stain of transgression, it is most evident in the very parts where offspring are produced.
Not only did man bind himself, but he also bound all future generations with such guilt, and by deserving death through disobedience, he forced everyone else to die.
For though he was mortal before sin, if he hadn't sinned, he wouldn't have died; however, all born from him through sin were made mortal, so no matter how justly they might live afterwards, they would still necessarily die.
None of them, whether they sin like Adam or not, can escape the grip of death, since even about Christ, who did no sin, it is written:
"The exits of death belong to the Lord God" (Psalm sixty-eight, verse twenty).
If he had obeyed God's commands, neither he nor any of his descendants would have fallen into such misery; indeed, no ruin would have ever been felt, since the sole cause of this is that original disobedience.
However, God, who is rich in mercy, does not want the people He created to perish but to return.
He seeks to correct and reprimand them to bring about repentance, illustrating what He would later say: I do not desire the death of the sinner, but that they turn and live.
Ezekiel chapter eighteen.
Chapter Three
"Adam," He said, "where are you?"
Adam replied, "I was afraid because I was naked, so I hid."
The Lord asked, "Who told you that you were naked? Did you eat from the forbidden tree?"
Adam said, "The woman you gave to be with me gave me fruit from the tree, and I ate it."
(Genesis chapter 3.)
Instead of admitting his fault and seeking forgiveness, the man tried to blame the woman, who then blamed the serpent, even though being persuaded by another is never a valid excuse for sinning.
The man claimed he was influenced by the woman, and the woman said she was deceived by the serpent.
While this was true, it was not justifiable, as the sin that could be cleansed through sincere confession was unnecessarily compounded by excuses.
As a result, both received penalties: the man was to eat his bread by the sweat of his brow, and the woman was to give birth in pain.
They were expelled from paradise and barred from the tree of life, with an angel wielding a flaming sword placed at the entrance to prevent their easy return.
Yet, to ensure hope of return wasn't completely lost, the sword is described as a revolving one.
Following these events, in Genesis chapter 4, little is mentioned about Adam except that he fathered Cain, Abel, Seth, and other sons and daughters, lived for nine hundred and thirty years, and then died.
Therefore, we must diligently seek and examine, hoping that the Spirit of God, who searches everything, might help us discover something about Adam's salvation from the words of Genesis.
I wouldn't dare claim this possible without being reminded by other parts of Scripture, where clearer passages help us understand those that are obscured.
Thus, one scripture illuminates another, and as more are studied, they not only make novices wiser but also enhance the wisdom of the wise.
Because not everything is said in one place, or sometimes what is said is not entirely clear, it's necessary to read more.
This makes Solomon's saying true: A wise person will become wiser by listening.
(Proverbs 1)
Often, those things we work a little harder to understand are the sweetest.
That's why the Prophet joyfully sings to God in another translation: "How sweet are your words to my taste, sweeter than honey and the honeycomb to my mouth!" (Psalm 119)
The honey, which is plain and open, is simply called honey, while the honeycomb, hidden in the intricately crafted wax cells, requires some effort to extract.
Therefore, it's not enough to say that God's words are sweeter than honey; he adds, "and the honeycomb." By honey, he refers to the clearer parts of the holy Scriptures, and by the honeycomb, he means the more hidden elements in the Scriptures.
Now, let's briefly revisit the words of Genesis that relate to our discussion, so we may extract something from the very essence of the letters, if God allows it.
Chapter Four
God called out to Adam and said:
Adam, where are you?
And he replied:
I was afraid because I was naked, and I hid myself.
(Genesis, Chapter 3)
I wonder if in this passage, where Scripture says God called Adam, we can understand any grace, mercy from the Creator, or benefit for the sinner.
In many places in Scripture, we see God calling, and it's important to carefully consider why or for what purpose He calls.
There's a type of calling where each thing is named, either with a proper or common name, like when we say: this man is called Moses, and that one is called Aaron; or: this animal is called a horse, and that one a lion, meaning it is named.
During the creation of the world, God called the firmament sky and the dry land earth.
(Genesis, Chapter 1)
This simply means He named them.
There's another kind of calling that the prophet Haggai, or rather God through him, shows us:
And I called for a drought upon the land, and upon the grain, and upon the wine, and upon the oil, and upon whatever the ground brings forth.
(Haggai, Chapter 1)
And David says:
And he called for a famine upon the land, and broke every support of bread.
(Psalm 105)
No one, I believe, is so naive, even if not well-versed in the Scriptures, to think that famine or drought is a person that can hear someone speaking.
Hearing is something rational or at least animal creatures do, but famine and drought are not creatures; they are a kind of affliction on creatures.
However, the ancient pagans held such an error, believing these forces to be gods or humans, as some pagan said, thinking famine was one of the goddesses of the mountains obeying Ceres's command.
And he envisioned famine in a stony field.
So, when God is said to call for famine and drought upon the land, I believe it means that, due to their deserving faults, God decided to punish the inhabitants of the land and commanded famine or drought to seize it.
There's another way God is said to call people, either through a human messenger or directly, without any human involvement.
This divine calling appears in four distinct ways in the Holy Scriptures.
The first is naming or calling, the second is commanding, the third is reminding, and the fourth is transforming.
The first involves assigning names to distinguish things.
The second involves commanding people to be punished.
The third reminds people to correct themselves.
The fourth imparts grace for transformation.
Among these, the second-to-last, where humans call other humans, is quite general because it's offered to both good and bad people.
Since humans don't fully understand God's secrets, they call everyone to the kingdom indiscriminately, even though God has prepared glory for some and eternal fire for others.
I believe this is the type of calling referred to in Solomon's writings: "I called, and you refused. I will laugh at your destruction." (Proverbs 1) and in the Gospel: "Many are called, but few are chosen." (Matthew 22).
This calling, made through humans and sometimes beneficial, seems indicated by the preceding words in both books if one examines them closely.
Solomon says, "Wisdom cries out in the streets; She raises her voice in the public squares." (Proverbs 1).
A few lines later, he adds: "I called, and you refused." The Wisdom of God is the Son, Christ, who is said to preach outside and raise His voice in the squares when preachers sent by Him deliver God's word not to hearts, which only God can do, but to the ears of humans. In the broad places referred to as squares, they cry out continuously, like trumpets raising their voices, striving with the Apostle to plant and water, yet achieving nothing unless God, speaking inwardly, chooses to give growth (First Corinthians 3).
Also in Matthew, it is said: "Many are called, but few are chosen." (Matthew 22).
In the chapter mentioned earlier, it says:
"Go therefore to the highways, and as many as you find, invite to the wedding."
His servants went out into the roads and gathered everyone they found, both bad and good,
and the wedding hall was filled with guests.
Right after that, the person without a wedding garment was thrown out.
The chapter concludes with: "Many are called, but few are chosen."
In the Gospel, what is meant by roads and highways seems to be referred to by Solomon as streets.
This is similar to what's found in the book of Isaiah:
"You will all fall by the sword because I called, and you did not answer; I spoke, and you did not listen" (Isaiah chapter sixty-five).
God's final call is a unique and special one, where He reaches out directly to people without any human messenger.
Sometimes, this happens openly, like when He called Moses from the burning bush; but often, it occurs in secret, as it has with thousands throughout history.
This special call is rarely unfruitful.
In fact, it seems that the prophet Joel referred to this type of call when he said: "On Mount Zion and in Jerusalem there will be salvation, and among those whom the Lord has called." This is from Joel, Chapter 2.
He wanted us to grasp the great significance of this call, as it leads to the gift of salvation. Being called by God in this way is essentially an invitation to salvation. Therefore, it seems to me that when the divine author of history wrote, "God called Adam" from Genesis, Chapter 3, it was not meant to be taken lightly. Instead, it serves as a reminder of the loving intent of the caller and the significant journey of the one being called.
If I were to go through the divine Scriptures and highlight all the instances where God is recorded as calling directly, either openly or secretly, and discuss the importance of this call, I believe the collection would be so extensive that it would exceed the size of a typical volume. However, to ensure I'm not making claims without some evidence, I will share a few examples that come to mind, so that you can understand that this call of God holds a considerable blessing.
Chapter Six
In the Book of Exodus, it's written that while Moses was tending the sheep of his father-in-law Jethro and leading the flock to the far side of the desert, the Lord appeared to him in a flame of fire from the middle of a bush.
Seeing the bush burning but not consumed, Moses said, "I will go and see this great sight, why the bush is not burned."
When the Lord saw that he was going over to look, He called to him from the middle of the bush and said, "Moses, Moses."
And Moses replied, "Here I am."
The Lord said, "Do not come any closer. Take off your sandals, for the place where you are standing is holy ground."
And He said, "I am the God of your father, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob" from the Book of Exodus, chapter three.
In this calling where God calls Moses, a great grace is shown, as the one who came from Egypt is instructed to take off his sandals.
Sandals, made from the skins of dead animals, fittingly represent dead works, or sins, which are undoubtedly committed in Egypt, meaning in darkness: For whoever does evil hates the light from the Book of John, chapter three.
Therefore, as Moses wants to see the sight, he is rightly stopped and taught by divine order how this should be done. Namely, to hurry and cast off the old things he acquired while living in Egypt, making him worthy to see the divine vision, or rather, to know God Himself.
Thus, as he is almost barefoot, or rather ready to be barefoot, a certain knowledge of God is granted to him when it is suddenly added, "I am the God of your father, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob" from the Book of Exodus, chapter three.
Chapter Seven
In the book of Exodus, when God was speaking to Moses about making the tabernacle of the covenant and the ark of testimony, there was no craftsman available for such a significant task.
So, He said, "Look, I have called by name Bezalel, son of Uri, from the tribe of Judah, and I have filled him with the spirit of God, with wisdom, understanding, and knowledge in all work, and I have given him a partner, Oholiab." And He concludes, "They will do everything I have commanded you." The full meaning of all these tasks that Bezalel is said to accomplish is beyond what I can explain here. However, know this: the prophet particularly praises those who remember and follow God's commandments (Psalm One Hundred Three).
From this, we can understand that Bezalel is not called by the Lord without purpose.
Grace is given to him to fulfill what is commanded, especially since he is said to be called by name and filled with the spirit of God, a distinction rarely mentioned except for the righteous.
For the Lord not only knows the path of the righteous but also their names.
Hence, it is said to Moses, "I know you by name" (Exodus Thirty-Three).
And the prophet speaks about God, "He numbers the multitude of stars, and calls them all by name" (Psalm One Hundred Forty-Seven).
In the gospel parable, while the name of the unjust rich man is left unmentioned as if unknown, the beggar is called by name Lazarus (Luke Sixteen).
Chapter Eight
In the first book of Kings, we see the shift from the old priesthood to the new one being symbolically introduced.
Eli, the old priest, was rejected, while the boy Samuel was chosen.
God's call played a crucial role in this selection.
It mentions that Samuel was sleeping in the temple of the Lord, where the Ark of God was, and the Lord called out to Samuel: "Samuel, Samuel?"
Samuel responded, "Speak, Lord, for your servant is listening" (First Samuel chapter three).
This calling is filled with divine grace and is followed by immediate obedience.
Just as there's nothing more wrong than ignoring, there's nothing more perfect than quick obedience.
In Isaiah, the Father speaking to the Son is introduced, predicting future events as if they had already happened: "I," says the Lord, "called you in righteousness, took hold of your hand, preserved you, and made you a covenant for the people" (Isaiah chapter forty-two).
A little later, the Son speaks prophetically to the people who would believe from all nations, encouraging them with mercy: "Do not be afraid," he says, "for I have redeemed you and called you by your name: You are mine."
"When you walk through fire, you will not be burned, and the flame will not set you ablaze, for I am the Lord your God, the Holy One of Israel, your Savior" (Isaiah chapter forty-three).
And further down: "Listen to me, Jacob and Israel, whom I call" (Isaiah chapter forty-eight).
In the next chapter, Christ himself says: "Listen," he says, "islands, and pay attention, people from afar, the Lord called me from the womb" (Isaiah chapter forty-nine).
In Joel: "On Mount Zion there will be salvation, as the Lord has said, and among the survivors whom the Lord calls" (Joel chapter two).
And in Zechariah: "He called me and spoke to me" (Zechariah chapter six).
Chapter Nine
As we delve into the New Testament, we find that Christ's calling is anything but idle; it's incredibly fruitful, as it appears to be an infusion of spiritual grace.
When the evangelist Matthew talks about James and John, he says:
"As Jesus was walking, he saw two other brothers, James the son of Zebedee and his brother John, mending their nets, and he called them" Matthew chapter four.
The nature of this calling, the kind of grace it involved, is clarified when he adds:
"And immediately they left their nets and their father and followed him."
Just as Peter and Andrew, upon hearing "Come, follow me, and I will make you fishers of men," immediately left their nets to follow him, James and John did the same. They left their nets and their father to follow him, even though they aren't recorded to have been invited with those exact words, just called.
This same account is found in Mark, chapter three, and Luke, chapter five, who also describe their calling.
Chapter Ten
When Mark the Evangelist described the list of apostles, he said, "Jesus went up the mountain and called to himself those he wanted, and he made it so there were twelve with him, giving them the power to heal illnesses and cast out demons."
Listing them one by one, he ended with Judas Iscariot. If anyone wonders what grace Judas received from this calling, since it's known that while others were chosen, he was rejected, they should understand that he was given significant grace, as he received the power to heal illnesses and cast out demons along with the others. However, the saving grace, which I believe is given to those specifically called by God, seems not to apply to Judas as the twelfth, but rather to the number twelve itself. It is understood that the one truly called, and who pleased the caller, was another.
If I am not mistaken, the evangelist himself hints at this subtly, if one pays more than superficial attention to his words. When he said, "He called to himself those he wanted," he then added, "And he made it so there were twelve with him." Since the number twelve of the apostles was full of great mystery, it is without a doubt that this number was called and chosen. It was not diminished by Judas's fall, as another was substituted for him. He said, "He made it so there were twelve with him."
Indeed, Matthias was already with him, chosen by him in the secret of his counsel, more so than Judas Iscariot, who only appeared to walk with him for a short time. Christ wanted there to be twelve with him so much that even Judas could not reduce the number to eleven. Even as Judas fell to destruction, the perfection of the number twelve was maintained. The number eleven is accused of transgression, while the number twelve is fortified by the power of perfection. So, to ensure the saving mystery of the number was preserved, not just eleven, but twelve remained in the ministry.
If someone suggests that the term "called," as used in Mark, should be seen as "summoned" because of a linguistic figure called apheresis-which involves removing a syllable from the beginning of a word-then there would be no specific issue with Judas. Instead, it would apply to him just like it does to the others, meaning a gathering or assembly.
The terms "to summon" and "to call" don't seem to mean the same thing. Whether you interpret it this way or another, the simple term seems to shift its meaning slightly. When Christ ascends the mountain, he is said to summon, or gather, the twelve disciples, as clearly stated by other evangelists like Matthew and Luke.
Matthew says in chapter fifteen, "He called his twelve disciples to him and gave them authority over unclean spirits, to drive them out." And Luke, in chapter nine, states, "He called the twelve together and gave them power over all demons and to cure diseases."
Christ is found to summon not only Judas but also the blasphemous Jews, where no benefit to them is apparent. In the same chapter of Mark that I briefly mentioned, when the scribes who came down from Jerusalem said, "He has Beelzebub, and by the ruler of the demons, he drives out demons," he says, having called them, he spoke to them in parables: "How can Satan drive out Satan?"
In this gathering, no benefit to the blasphemers is shown, unless perhaps it is implied, as is sometimes read in John: "And many in the crowd believed in him" (John 2).
Undoubtedly, there is a different calling and a different effect of calling, as mentioned by the evangelist John when Martha says to Mary, "The Teacher is here and is calling for you" (John 11).
And later in the same book of John: "He called Lazarus and raised him from the dead" (John 11).
Chapter Eleven
At the start of his letter to the Romans, Paul affirmed his calling, which set the stage for everything he was about to share in his letters.
He introduces himself with, "Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ, called to be an apostle" Romans Chapter One, Verse One.
Paul clearly states who called him in his letter to the Galatians, saying, "An apostle not from men, nor through man, but through Jesus Christ and God the Father, who raised him from the dead" Galatians Chapter One, Verse One.
Paul describes the greatness of this calling a bit later in the same letter: "But when it pleased him who separated me from my mother's womb and called me through his grace to reveal his Son in me so that I might preach him among the Gentiles" Galatians Chapter One, Verse Fifteen.
To emphasize that this grace was not superficial or useless-since many, as Paul notes, preach Christ out of self-interest-he wrote to Timothy: "Join me in suffering for the gospel according to the power of God, who has saved us and called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace which was given to us in Christ Jesus before time began" Second Timothy Chapter One, Verses Eight to Nine.
Paul clearly mentions "and called" after "saved," to highlight how holy and beneficial this calling was, preceded by liberation.
Humanity was entangled by the first Adam's transgression, but by God's goodness, some are freed through predestination.
Those who are freed from that entanglement, already liberated in God's secret counsel, are later called with his holy calling; they are inspired, enlightened with his knowledge. Thus, from the same mass from which vessels of dishonor were made according to merit, vessels of honor were made, not by changing their nature, but by purifying it through grace.
Speaking of the riches of this gracious liberation and fruitful calling to the Romans, Paul declares: "That he might make known the riches of his glory on the vessels of mercy, which he prepared for glory, whom he also called, not only from among the Jews but also from among the Gentiles" Romans Chapter Nine, Verses Twenty-Three to Twenty-Four.
And to support what he had said with a prophetic quotation, he adds, just as it says in Hosea, chapter 2: I will call Not My People, My People, and Not Beloved, Beloved, and Not Shown Mercy, Shown Mercy.
And in the place where it was said to them, You are not my people, there they shall be called the children of God.
Chapter Twelve
In his letters, the Apostle frequently discusses this calling, but he's never clearer and more concise than in his letter to the Romans, where he outlines four stages of divine blessings.
For those whom He foreknew, He also predestined to be conformed to the image of His Son, so that He might be the firstborn among many brothers.
And those He predestined, He also called; those He called, He also justified; and those He justified, He also glorified.
Romans eight.
The first blessing is predestination, where we are preordained to eternal life.
The second is the calling, which invites and inspires us to seek eternal life.
The third is justification, where our sins are forgiven and we earn eternal life by doing good works.
The fourth is glorification, when righteousness turns into judgment and we possess peace and eternal life.
The first happens with Him, not within us;
the second comes from Him within us;
the third comes from Him, with our cooperation;
the fourth comes from Him, after we have already earned it.
First, He chooses us before we exist;
second, He advises us to be good;
third, He makes us just;
fourth, He makes us glorious and immortal.
The first is the divine truth of foreknowledge;
the second is the infusion of grace;
the third is the operation of justice;
the fourth is the reward of glory.
First, He foreknows those who will exist long after;
second, He calls the undeserving;
third, He forgives sins and grants merits;
fourth, He crowns those who have done well endlessly.
Just as none are glorified unless justified, nor justified unless called, so none are called unless predestined.
This special calling of God is attributed to Him alone;
by it, only those are called who will become saints, as the Apostle says, they were called to be saints according to His purpose.
Not according to their own merit, but according to God's purpose, because the gifts and calling of God are irrevocable.
Romans eleven.
Although the Book of Genesis doesn't specifically state that Adam was given this calling, it doesn't prevent us from interpreting it that way.
It also doesn't exclude him from salvation; in fact, its words seem to suggest his salvation.
Chapter Thirteen
God called Adam and said, "Adam, where are you?" Genesis three.
It's a great honor that the Creator seeks out His creation, not wanting it to remain hidden in the darkness of sin, but wishing it to step into the light of truth.
With this anvil and hammer of inquiry, even then, the mystery of our redemption was being forged.
The one who had sinned by wrongful consent was invited to the healing of worthy confession, so that with the same mouth by which an unjust act against salvation was committed, a true confession for salvation might be made.
"Adam," He said, "where are you?"
As if to say: It's not good for you to hide any longer; come out, step forward, confess, and admit your sins so that you may be justified.
And he replied, "I heard Your voice, and I was afraid because I was naked, so I hid myself" Genesis three.
Before sin, man could greatly boast and be considered very happy, for God had freely bestowed upon him innumerable benefits and had bound him with such a strong bond of love.
Setting aside other things previously mentioned, which would be excessive to repeat here, it was a great happiness for him to interact with angels, and indeed a great glory to visibly contemplate God, who, though invisible by nature, was visible to him through the assumed visible creation.
Indeed, man placed in paradise saw God in the way that, later on, the patriarchs and righteous men of old could see Him while still living in the flesh.
They recognized without doubt that He, appearing to them in a visible form as an angel or a man, was God.
Thus it is written about Jacob: "Behold, a man wrestled with him until daybreak" Genesis thirty-two.
And shortly after, Jacob said, "I have seen God face to face, and my life has been preserved" Genesis thirty-two.
And Joshua, when he was in the field of Jericho, said, "He saw a man standing against him, holding a drawn sword, and he approached him and asked, 'Are you for us or for our adversaries?'" Joshua five.
And shortly after it is added, "And the Lord said to Joshua."
There's no doubt that this was the one Joshua was speaking to.
Gideon was busy threshing and cleaning wheat in a winepress to hide from the Midianites when an angel of the Lord appeared to him, saying,
The Lord is with you, mighty warrior.
(Judges 6)
A bit later, the story continues:
When Gideon realized it was the angel of the Lord, he exclaimed, 'Oh no!
Lord God, I have seen the angel of the Lord face to face.
'
But the Lord said to him, 'Peace be with you; do not be afraid; you will not die.
Similarly, an angel also appeared to Manoah, about whom Scripture says:
Manoah realized that it was the angel of the Lord and said to his wife, 'We will surely die, for we have seen God.
'
But his wife replied, 'If the Lord wanted to kill us, he would not have accepted our burnt offerings and grain offerings from our hands.
(Judges 13)
Notice how Scripture refers to the same being as both a man and an angel, and also as God.
This demonstrates that when God appeared in the form of a man or angel, people recognized it as an encounter with God.
Although God is naturally invisible, He chose to appear visibly to those He wished, in the manner He desired.
Indeed, three men are said to have appeared to Abraham, and two angels to Lot, where nothing less than God was understood to be present
(Genesis 18, 19).
This is why the first humans, upon realizing their nakedness after sinning-not because they lost any clothes, as they had none before, but because they lost the holiness in which they were created-felt ashamed and feared being seen by God.
They used to see God in the way previously mentioned, and so they hid among the trees of paradise, covering their now shameful parts with fig leaves, which were perhaps the first things they found as they fled in distress.
However, even if by sinning and fleeing they could avoid seeing God, they could not hide from Him.
The eyes of the Lord observe the good and the evil
(Proverbs 15);
and the face of the Lord is against those who do evil
(Psalms 33).
He sees even those who do not see Him and follows them no matter how much they flee.
If it's true, as a certain pagan once said, that kings have long arms, then how much more should we believe that the King of Kings and Lord of Lords has arms that reach everywhere, from which no one can escape unless they choose to seek refuge in them?
Chapter Fourteen
Understanding this, Adam, when he realized he was being sought, decided not to remain silent any longer.
Instead, he chose to come forward and confess.
He said, "I heard your voice, Lord, and I was afraid because I was naked, so I hid myself" Genesis 3.
It's as if he were saying: I understand that when I was obedient, I was clothed with the robe of immortality, innocence, and holiness; I wasn't afraid to face you because I appeared holy and could witness your power and glory.
But when I crossed the line of self-restraint and fell into disobedience, I was stripped bare and felt ashamed. To find some remedy for my shame, I foolishly sought a hiding place.
In this, I sinned, and I confess that I sinned.
I admit, not only did I sin by eating, but also by hiding.
Where can I go from your spirit, and where can I flee from your presence? Psalm 139.
Indeed, I should have fled after sinning, but towards you, not away from myself.
For my soul was disturbed within me, therefore I will remember you from now on Psalm 42.
And the Lord, to add to the deserved shame and as a tool for correction, repeats the misery and the cause of the misery, so that by hearing what he has done and what he has deserved, man is further afflicted. By being afflicted, he may deserve to be purified.
"Who," he said, "told you that you were naked, except because you ate from the tree that I commanded you not to eat?" Genesis 3.
This means: Who gave you the knowledge of this nakedness, except because you didn't keep obedience?
Because you did not remain in what you had received, you feel evil and know what you did not know before.
And he said, "The woman you gave to be with me gave me some fruit, and I ate it" Genesis 3.
He explained, "Such was the perversity of my will that easy persuasion led me to sin, and feminine softness weakened a man's mind.
You gave me a woman as a companion, indeed to live together, not as a leader to sin, so that she, who was later in condition, would also be lesser in dignity, and obediently submit to my command, following me as I follow you."
In a reversed and unexpected way, I followed the one who came before me.
I listened to the persuader, accepted the offer, and failed to guide the misled; instead, I destroyed myself-not because of error, but because of love.
What she, in her misplaced trust, convinced me to do, I completed out of misguided duty as a husband, choosing not to upset her, but in doing so, I upset my God.
My sin was not any less because it was committed knowingly and deliberately.
She gave to me, and I ate.
I, who should have stopped her from eating and corrected her mistake, not only failed to prevent her but also partook myself, bound-or rather conquered-by affection, losing the strength I should have had as a husband.
If what he said, "The woman whom you gave to be with me, she gave me fruit of the tree, and I ate," seems to some like not a humble confession but an excuse, suggesting he tried to share the blame for disobedience with the woman, I can't disagree. Many saints have shared this view and expressed it in their writings.
He might have been mistaken here, not realizing how displeasing it would be to God as he blamed the woman in his response. He didn't see how serious it was to make excuses, even though he spoke the truth. So, he wasn't misled by eating, but he was misled in making excuses. He knowingly offended God by eating, but unknowingly by making excuses.
To God, the ultimate justice, even truthful excuses for sin are not pleasing. He desires not an incautious defense that worsens the fault, but a pure and simple confession to wash it away. Therefore, without excuses, the sinner should say to Him: "I have sinned, Lord, have mercy on me."
But indeed, this unprepared soul had no guidance in this matter, no example to learn from. Although he knew it was wrong to disobey God's command, he didn't understand that even truth could displease eternal truth. He knew the fallen angel disobeyed and fell, but he didn't grasp that speaking the truth could also lead to offense.
When it is said: The woman you gave me, gave me the fruit and I ate it, it can be understood in different ways.
Rightly, the woman is blamed because she offered the taste of death to the man.
By persuading and flattering him, even unknowingly, she compelled him to sin.
Chapter Fifteen
And the Lord asked the woman, "Why did you do this?"
She answered, "The serpent deceived me, and I ate." Genesis 3.
This was indeed true, though not wisely stated.
She was deceived by the serpent.
However, she shouldn't have transgressed due to deception, nor should she have added excuses for her transgression.
No one should be troubled if, after mentioning that Adam was called by the Lord, he was found to have sinned.
I didn't say this calling was given to him to prevent him from ever sinning again, but so he wouldn't stubbornly persist in sin.
Who would claim that he committed no sin after being called by God, especially since he lived for such a long time afterward?
He had already lost his state through disobedience, and if he had stayed in that state, he wouldn't have felt any sin at all.
But because he lost it, he fell into this miserable and pitiable life, where one cannot live without sin, but is delivered from it by Him who is commendably called by God through this calling.
You're surely aware that Moses, in Numbers 20, after receiving divine calling, provoked God at the waters of Meribah.
Because of that, he didn't enter the Promised Land, yet he wasn't excluded from eternal blessing.
Chapter Sixteen
And the Lord said to the serpent: Because you have done this, you are cursed above all animals and beasts of the earth.
Genesis 3.
Notice how God doesn't ask the serpent, or the devil hidden within it, where it is or why it acted as it did;
instead, because of its actions, He places a fitting curse on it.
He doesn't speak of it as a future threat but declares its curse as a present reality:
You are cursed, He says.
Since it wasn't offered hope for forgiveness or given time for repentance, it's rightly said to be cursed now, not to become cursed, having already sinned irreparably and faced eternal damnation.
It's undoubtedly cursed because it rose against God with pride, saying: I will be like the Most High.
Isaiah 14.
And because it brought down man through envy, seeing him as subordinate to the Most High.
This wickedness wasn't the beginning but an addition to the curse, further punished now after a perhaps lighter punishment earlier.
You are cursed, He says, above all animals and beasts of the earth.
Those who are animalistic and beastly, wise in earthly things, seem to incur eternal damnation, as the Apostle says: Their end is destruction, their glory is in their shame, those who focus on earthly things.
Philippians 3.
This one is declared to be cursed more than all the cursed.
Just as the Virgin Mary is proclaimed in the Gospel as blessed among women,
Luke 1.
meaning more than all women, so this one, through whose envy death entered the world,
Wisdom 2, is cursed among all, meaning more than all who are found cursed throughout the whole world from then until the end.
Chapter Seventeen
"You will crawl on your belly," it says in Genesis 3. Since he started speaking to the serpent, he keeps the metaphor going, showing how it applies spiritually to the devil. The chest is indeed where the heart and thoughts reside. So, calling the chest a dwelling for every twisted person where the devil roams freely isn't inappropriate. It's as if he walks over him, constantly oppressing him, forcing him to focus on earthly things and not allowing him to rise to heavenly ones.
The perverted person, always clinging to the earth, is no longer just called earthly but is emphatically called earth itself. This is given as food to the serpent, allowing it to absorb him completely into its belly of malice, hiding him from the light of justice and wrapping him in the shroud of eternal damnation. This is what is added: "You will eat dust all the days of your life" Genesis 3.
The days of his life are rightly seen as the entire period in which he is allowed to rage, until in the end, all his followers will be gathered and fall together into hell to face eternal death. However, so he won't boast about this temporary license or rejoice for long about deceiving the woman, the punishment is mentioned by which he is also punished now. He will always burn with the desire to harm but will sometimes lack the ability: "I will put enmity between you and the woman, and between your offspring and hers" Genesis 3.
The offspring of the devil is evil suggestion, whose fruit is eternal damnation. The offspring of the woman is the fear of God, whose ultimate benefit is the vision of God. "She," it says, "will crush your head, and you will lie in wait for her heel" Genesis 3. She will crush the scheming of your suggestions with the battering ram of divine fear, weakening your deceptions with the wisdom of her counsel, turning back the malice you gave. So, you're deceived by the one you deceived, struck down by the one you struck, and although you may lie in wait for her heel, you cannot claim victory.
After the devil is doomed to eternal damnation, humans do not receive the same curse, but instead, they endure temporary afflictions.
Since the woman was the first to incur guilt, she is the first to receive punishment.
This way, the order of receiving the sentence matches the order in which the fault was committed.
Chapter Eighteen
And God said to the woman: I will greatly increase your troubles and your pregnancies.
You will give birth to children in pain, and you will be under the authority of your husband, and he will rule over you.
Genesis chapter three.
If these words, when the historical meaning is set aside and taken only spiritually, are rightly assigned to any holy soul or to the universal Church, whose troubles and conceptions multiply, which gives birth to children in pain, that is, the fruits of good works with effort, and serves under the authority of the man, that is, Christ, and he rightly rules over her.
However, if they are understood historically, it is not unreasonable to say they specifically apply to Eve.
If this statement is thought to be general, suggesting that what was said to Eve applies to every woman, this opinion will be contradicted by the birth of the Virgin Mary, who, although she gave birth, did so without pain.
Therefore, what was said to Eve, whether understood literally or spiritually, does not apply to all women in every aspect, but some parts to some and others to others.
Whatever was said either to the woman or about the woman to the serpent by the Lord should also be believed to apply to Eve, so just as we read it was said to her: You will give birth to children in pain, and we do not doubt this to be true, so also what was said to the serpent: I will put enmity between you and the woman, and she will crush your head, we believe without doubt was said about the same woman.
Thus, by divine justice punishing her, she gave birth to children in pain, which is a punitive sentence, and by grace visiting her, she crushed the serpent's head, which is a spiritual victory.
It should be noted that what was said to the woman: I will greatly increase your troubles and your pregnancies, you will give birth to children in pain, and you will be under the authority of your husband, has both a spiritual and a literal sense, so that this woman is believed to have both experienced these things in reality and fulfilled them spiritually.
Regarding what was said to the serpent: "I will put enmity between you and the woman; she will crush your head, and you will lie in wait for her heel," this is understood not in a historical sense but in a mystical one, as a literal interpretation would seem quite pointless.
What gain would there be if the serpent's head were physically crushed, as this does not aid in the growth of the soul?
I believe this refers to the crushing mentioned by Paul to the Romans: "God will quickly crush Satan under your feet" (Romans Chapter 16).
Consequently, the same woman is later called the mother of the living, meaning good deeds, which oppose sins, often mentioned in the divine Scriptures.
This is why the Apostle, speaking to the Corinthians, says: "What will they do who are baptized for the dead, that is, for sins?" (First Corinthians Chapter 15).
And to the Hebrews: "The foundation is repentance from dead works" (Hebrews Chapter 6).
Finally, the same Apostle, when speaking to Timothy about the same woman, said: "Adam was not deceived, but the woman, being deceived, was in transgression; yet she will be saved through childbearing, if they continue in faith and love" (First Timothy Chapter 2).
He mentions she was deceived in transgression, yet suggests she will be saved through childbearing, meaning through the practice of good deeds, which are understood as children.
Thus the Psalmist says: "Look upon your servants and guide their children" (Psalm 89).
What the Apostle adds (First Timothy Chapter 2) about the children continuing in faith and love should not be seen as doubtful.
The causal conjunction "if," although sometimes used with doubt, is often used affirmatively in both divine and secular Scriptures, especially with the indicative, but occasionally with the subjunctive.
Through the prophet Malachi, God says: "If I am a father, where is my honor? If I am a master, where is my fear?" (Malachi Chapter 1).
That famous poet once said: "If there is any mercy in heaven," confidently affirming that mercy truly exists in heaven.
And the Lord in the Gospel states: "In this, all will know that you are my disciples, if you have love for one another" in John chapter thirteen, assured that they would indeed love one another.
To convey his spiritual intentions, bringing Eve to the forefront, the Apostle speaks of her, confident in the truth of his words.
Chapter Nineteen
You have heard what was said to the woman.
Now listen, if you wish, to what sentence was later passed on the man.
Genesis continues: To Adam he said, Because you listened to the voice of your wife and ate from the tree about which I commanded you not to eat, cursed is the ground because of you.
Thorns and thistles it will bring forth for you, and you shall eat the plants of the field.
By the sweat of your face you shall eat your bread, until you return to the ground from which you were taken, for you are dust, and to dust you shall return.
This is in Genesis chapter 3.
This word curse, as it seems to me, generally refers to all sin.
Specific sins are implied under this general name, so that each one can be understood by its particular name.
This is exactly what the prophet Hosea seems to do in chapter 4, where after naming the general category, he goes on to list several specific types.
He says, Cursing, lying, theft, murder, and adultery overflow, and blood touches blood.
So, when man sinned, he committed a curse worthy act.
And because sin brings a curse, a punishment must follow, so that man would not boast about going unpunished.
Therefore, it was imposed on him that his earth, that is, his mortal flesh, would be cursed, meaning it would suffer the penalty of the curse and be subjected to toil and hardship.
Using this kind of language, even Christ is said to be cursed, or rather a curse, because he bore the pains of our mortality, the pains that came from the curse placed on the first man.
The Apostle writes to the Galatians, Christ redeemed us from the curse of the law, becoming a curse for us.
And to show that what he said is true, he adds a prophetic quote, For it is written, Cursed is everyone who hangs on a tree.
That is from Deuteronomy chapter 21.
You see, then, that Christ hanging on the cross is called a curse or cursed, which simply means he was afflicted with the punishments that come from the curse.
In a similar metaphorical expression, the same Apostle calls him sin in the letter to the Corinthians: He made him who knew no sin to be sin for us.
That is from Second Corinthians chapter 5.
This is why, when God said to man, Cursed is the ground, He added, In your work, to clarify that this curse referred to the hardship of earthly labor, not eternal damnation.
It was written earlier that the Lord God took the man and placed him in the Garden of Eden to work and take care of it.
Here, it was mentioned that he should work, but this work was a source of delight, not hardship, and involved protection, not misery.
He was put in the Garden of Eden to perfectly follow divine commands, to serve God joyfully, and by remaining steadfast in His service, to continuously enjoy the given delight.
If he had maintained his dedication to divine service, he would never have experienced any trouble in all his work.
This is what was meant by saying: He placed him in the Garden of Eden to work and take care of it.
It, meaning the Garden of Eden, so that he would not lose the delightful state through negligence, which he could keep through diligence.
Don't worry if here or elsewhere in divine Scripture the garden is referred to as masculine, while modern grammarians claim it is feminine.
If grammarians prefer that it refers to the man instead of the garden, there's no need to argue, as it doesn't significantly change the meaning.
God, as it was said, placed man in the Garden of Eden to work.
The man indeed worked, undoubtedly following the command he received to obey it, and God certainly protected him as he worked in the delight where He placed him.
In some manuscripts, it is noted not as it but as that he says, to work and take care of that.
Man was placed in the Garden of Eden to work on what was commanded by God and to take care of, that is, his work, by persevering in it.
Back then, the earth of man could rightly be called blessed in its work, because his work involved no trouble, no suffering, no resistance, since there was no sin and no punishment for sin found in his work.
But now, on the contrary, it is rightly called cursed in its work, because either sin rules in it if a person lives badly, or the punishment for sin weighs it down, even if a person lives well.
Life is no longer lived without misery, though by God's mercy, this misery can now become useful for some people.
For the wicked, misery is only harmful and a form of punishment.
But for the good, it is fruitful and healing, because God transforms what is evil into good, as the Apostle says, For those who love God, all things work together for good.
That is in Romans chapter 8.
If then, in this life of misery we live well, not loving it as a comfortable bedroom but enduring it like a stable, not grumbling against God's judgment, and longing for our eternal homeland, then without a doubt, this very misery is turned into merit, and man, originally well made, is restored to something even better.
That is why the Psalmist says, You shape suffering into a commandment.
That is in Psalm 94.
God, in fact, shapes our suffering into a command for us, when he wants us not only to endure the hardships of this life but to endure them patiently.
And he counts this patience as a reward worthy act of obedience.
That is why, after it was said, Cursed is the ground because of you, it was also added, In toil you shall eat of it, meaning, you will get its fruit only through hard labor.
As another Psalm says, My tears have been my bread, which is in Psalm 42, and again, You shall eat the fruit of the labor of your hands, you shall be blessed.
That is Psalm 128.
The earth then will no longer be fruitful if it tries to be delightful without labor.
As the Apostle puts it figuratively, The widow who lives in pleasure is dead while she lives.
That is in First Timothy chapter 5.
Our flesh can fittingly be called a widow when it is not ruled rightly by the spirit as by a husband.
Instead, it breaks free from the law of the spirit and gives itself over to the brothel of its own pleasures.
So, it is alive to itself but dead to God.
The opposite is also said, You have died, and your life is hidden with Christ in God.
That is from Colossians chapter 3.
Chapter Twenty
"It will produce thorns and thistles for you" (Genesis 3).
The thorns and thistles our land produces symbolize the worries and concerns that weigh on us as we strive to either preserve ourselves from failure or nurture our prosperity.
We diligently manage the spiritual resources available to us and wisely work to acquire those we lack.
These things are essential, and without them, life cannot be fully lived, so our minds are often burdened with concern.
While we aspire to heavenly things through God's inspiration, we are often compelled by necessity to focus on temporary matters.
However, if these anxieties and concerns stay within certain limits, if heavenly matters are not neglected because of them, if they don't lead us to seek unlawful things, and if they're moderately restrained even in permissible matters, they remain manageable and tolerable.
They're like certain plants that may prick a little but don't overwhelm us, instead serving our benefit.
This is why it is said: "And you will eat the plants of the field" (Genesis 3), meaning you will engage with temporary concerns while seeking or managing fleeting things, trim them back so they do not overgrow, use them, and turn them to your advantage so they contribute to growth rather than destruction.
Then thorns and thistles are not burdensome, but instead, manageable and even useful, if temporary cares are endured not for the love of present things but in the hope of heavenly things.
Hence, the Apostle says to the Romans: "The creation was subjected to futility, not by its own will, but because of the one who subjected it, in hope that the creation itself will be liberated from its bondage to decay and brought into the freedom and glory of the children of God" (Romans 8).
Indeed, creation is unwillingly subjected to futility when a person faces temporal hardships not out of love but obedience, finding comfort in the hope of deliverance so they do not falter but rather progress.
For in passing into the freedom of the glory of the children of God, they will be freed from the bondage to decay.
Just as plants, which are the food for animals, suggest the temporary struggles where the faithful live and grow, we too, being earthly and almost like animals, need earthly nourishment.
However, once we become spiritual, if we truly do, we are rejuvenated by the sweetness of heavenly bread.
Just like animals are nourished by plants, the spiritual are nourished by bread.
This is referenced in the words given to Adam:
"By the sweat of your brow you will eat bread"
Genesis
Chapter 3.
Chapter Twenty-One
Consider this perspective: "Thorns and thistles shall it bring forth to you, and you shall eat the plants of the field." Thorns and thistles symbolize the trials and temptations of sin that arise from the earth, or our flesh, and attack the very flesh they originate from. Just like a worm that emerges from a garment or wood and consumes it, so do the suggestions of sin come from the flesh, often pricking and consuming it.
When these temptations stir the desire to sin within us, if they fail to achieve their goal because the spirit resists valiantly, they may indeed prick us but cannot overwhelm us, as long as our prudence, aided by grace, devours and crushes them like plants. We find these to be heavy and burdensome through our consent and negligence. That's why it is said: "And you shall eat the plants of the field." Our land indeed produces the bitter and harsh plants of sin, namely temptations, which we are advised to consume, so they do not grow into large thorns.
What does it mean to consume them? Through fasting and prayer. For anyone who does not strive to resist the demands of appetite and lust through prayer and fasting weakly submits to them. The fact that our enemies are weakened by such means is elegantly illustrated by Balak, son of Zippor, king of Moab, in the Book of Numbers. When he saw the people of Israel entering Moab's borders, recalling how they had defeated Sihon, king of the Amorites, and Og, king of Bashan, he was terrified and said to the elders of Midian: "This people will wipe out all those who dwell in our borders as an ox licks up the grass to the very roots." Because the ox was often sacrificed, it fittingly represents the one who says, "I discipline my body and bring it into subjection" (First Corinthians 9).
This relates to fasting.
He uproots the plants just like a holy man, driven by the impulses of his body and the desires of youth, who overcomes them through prayer to keep sin from taking control, even if it can't be completely avoided.
In this way, he's like an ox pulling up plants, who through fasting and praying suppresses rising vices, ensuring that from the muddy roots of carnality, the sapling of depravity doesn't sprout and grow wild.
Balak rightly feared that his people, the Midianites and Moabites, might be defeated, knowing how the Amalekites had been conquered.
He was aware that when the Israelites left the desert of Sin and camped in Rephidim, Amalek attacked them.
Moses, with the rod of God in his hand, went up to the top of the hill, and with Aaron and Hur supporting his hands, he continued praying until sunset.
As written in the Book of Exodus, chapter 17, Joshua defeated Amalek and his people with the sword.
Understanding the reason for this victory, Balak wisely attributed it to merits, not physical strength; to prayer and fasting, not to spear and sword.
He remembered hearing that when Moses lifted his hands in prayer, Israel prevailed, but when he lowered them slightly, Amalek gained the upper hand.
Indeed, he knew that the Israelites, though fewer in number, had overcome other peoples who were numerous, well-armed, and strongly fortified.
The Gospel seems to support this idea: "This kind," it says, "is not cast out except by prayer and fasting" (Matthew, chapter 17).
Similarly, before his passion, Christ said, "Pray that you may not enter into temptation" (Luke, chapter 22).
For those laboring and sweating in the struggle of fasting and prayer, a refreshing meal is necessary, so they are not overwhelmed by continuous effort.
Strengthened by inner refreshment and inspired with hope for heavenly things, they are also better equipped to endure temporary troubles.
Chapter Twenty-Two
So it follows: "You will eat bread by the sweat of your face" (Genesis, Chapter 3).
It doesn't specify which bread, but simply that you will eat bread by the sweat of your face.
This bread is understood, through antonomasia, to be the bread mentioned elsewhere in a mystical sense: "He gave them bread from heaven to eat" (John, Chapter 6).
This bread is undoubtedly a spiritual nourishment that renews, progresses, and invigorates our inner self, while our outer self decays and is constantly afflicted by temporal miseries.
This is the bread we refer to in the Lord's Prayer: "Give us today our daily bread" (Matthew, Chapter 6).
which is needed every day, and without it, one cannot live well or spiritually.
However, those who do not live spiritually, even if they seem to live, do not truly live.
This bread is the taste of divine sweetness, about which the Prophet says, "Taste and see that the Lord is good" (Psalm 34).
The sweetness of this delight can indeed be felt, but it cannot be expressed in words.
Remarkably, while the mind often struggles to understand, it seems unable to explain, lacking the ability to discuss it, even though the grace to feel it is present.
However, one cannot reach this ineffable sweetness without effort, nor receive the fruit of such sweetness without sweating and laboring in the struggle for holiness.
This labor includes fasting, vigil, reading, prayer, meditation, compunction, and weeping, which we must undertake in this land of the dead if we wish to eat and be nourished by the bread of angels.
But when we reach the land of the living, we will indeed eat this bread without labor and sweat, because this nourishment has a laborious beginning in this life, but a glorious completion in the next.
Therefore, it is said: "You will eat bread by the sweat of your face until you return to the ground from which you were taken." This means you must labor to eat this bread until you return to the ground from which you were taken, that is, until, with the approach of death, you become lifeless earth, just as you were initially lifeless earth before the spirit came to you.
Once your body is released, you'll stop working, having already experienced what you deserved to taste here.
You'll enjoy your rewards without struggle.
With the end of this life, your hardships will also come to an end.
It continues: And he made, etc.
Chapter Twenty-Three
God made leather tunics for Adam and his wife, dressed them, and said, "Look, Adam has become like one of us, knowing good and evil" Genesis 3.
Since skins are taken from dead animals, it's fitting that these leather tunics symbolize the mortality of the body. This mortality was imposed on them when they were stripped of the robe of immortality as a consequence of their disobedience.
This punishment of the body is marked by this very clothing, as those who were already mortal, or destined to die, were clothed in the skins of dead animals, though they had previously been naked and did not need clothes.
In this way, this kind of clothing became not only a necessary covering for their newfound shame but also a healing reminder of their weakness, reminding them where they came from and where they are going, so they wouldn't become proud again.
For this reason, I believe John the Baptist is mentioned as wearing a leather belt around his waist Matthew 3, to remind him of his descent from original sin as a mortal, and so he wouldn't become proud about being thought of as Christ.
The divine doctor applied a more biting remedy to harmful pride, for when He dressed them in leather garments, He added, "Look, Adam has become like one of us, knowing good and evil."
In saying "one of us," the Trinity is understood, where there is a plural number, including God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Spirit. Together they are not three gods, but one God.
Therefore, when He says "like one of us," it means: He became what each one of us is.
This saying seems to contain a kind of taunt at the sinner's pride, and moreover, it instills fear in those who would sin, showing that not only did man fail to gain what he wrongly desired, but he also did not keep what he had been given rightly.
He became like one of us, knowing good and evil.
It's as if to say: While he wrongly desires to be like God, behold, he has rightly been reduced to being like a horse and a mule.
And while he unjustly seeks the divinity of the Creator, he has justly been brought down to the mortality of beasts.
Now man knows good and evil, both of which I also know, but he knows by losing one and experiencing the other, which is not how I know them.
I know good by always having it, and I know evil by never experiencing it.
However, Adam, while knowing good and evil, desires to become like God.
But in knowing both, he is far from Him, as he knows one by losing it and the other by suffering it for his merits.
It can also be understood differently what is said: Behold, Adam has become like one of us, not as irony or insult, but rather considered seriously.
Behold, he says, Adam has become like one of us, that is, truly one outside of us.
Sometimes it expresses similarity, sometimes the truth of the matter.
Similarity when Peter says: Desire the pure milk like newborn infants First Peter two.
The truth of the matter when John says: And we have seen his glory, the glory as of the only begotten from the Father John one.
One of us, that is, one made outside of us, as it is said: One of the consuls, who was once a consul and is no longer, who is more clearly and commonly called an ex-consul.
Just as one who serves as consul is called a consul, so indeed one who is deprived of it is called an ex-consul; likewise, we say ex-bishops, ex-abbots, ex-lawyers, who once held this dignity and have now laid it down.
Adam, however, was made in the image of God for this purpose: to be God himself by always adhering to Him.
He who adheres, it is said, to God, is one spirit First Corinthians six.
As long as he remained obedient to the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, he was undoubtedly with them, although not substantially, but by name, not by nature, but by grace, not by his own merit of labor, but by the Creator's favor.
After eating what was forbidden and listening to his wife's voice, he was sadly cast out from their company.
He who was once one of them through righteousness became one of them through unrighteousness, meaning he was now outside of them.
By being close to God, he was like God; however, by turning away, he was no longer like God.
If language allowed, this could be more explicitly stated as "ex-God." Just as someone who was once a consul is called an "ex-consul" after leaving that position, similarly, if language permitted, one might say "ex-God," because he once was, but is no longer, a god.
Behold, he said, Adam has become like one of us; as if to say: Truly, while we remain as we are, Adam, who was also like God, has left us and become someone who knows good and evil, not in the way he knew before and as we also know, but in a way he had never known, and we certainly do not know.
Chapter Twenty-Four
To prevent him from reaching out, taking from the tree of life, eating, and living forever, the Lord God sent him out from the paradise of pleasure to work the ground from which he was taken.
He placed cherubim and a flaming sword that turned in all directions in front of the paradise to guard the way to the tree of life.
Genesis Chapter Three.
As I mentioned before, through the tree of life, Adam initially avoided death and aging.
But now, by sinning, he had earned the penalty of death.
To keep him from accessing the tree again, he was expelled from paradise, distancing him both physically and morally from his original state of immortality.
In my view, this can be seen as the divine mercy of God, who intended to nullify human sin with this punishment.
Through the death of the body, man could be purified and return to life, avoiding the misery of living and sinning forever after sin.
If, after sinning, man had remained physically immortal without death to abolish his sin, he would be like the devil, who lived immortally after sinning and never revived from the death of sin.
Therefore, it is beneficial that man is temporarily excluded from the tree of life.
A cherub, representing the fullness of knowledge, and a flaming sword, symbolizing the troubles of tribulations, are placed in between.
Through this knowledge, which signifies love, and through the pains of death, one can return to the tree of life, which is Christ.
The sword is not described as fixed and immovable; although it is flaming, it is still movable, indicating that returning to life is difficult but possible.
You have heard, brothers, what is read in Genesis first: the punishment justly inflicted for sin, and who is granted the return to life.
I wanted to remind you of this so that your love may notice that the words of Scripture do not imply his eternal destruction.
While they clearly show his sin and death, they also hint at repentance and life, albeit subtly, yet not without some indication.
I know, and it's clear that no one would doubt the things said about him after his sin truly applied to his descendants.
They were cast out of the immortality of paradise due to his sin and thrust into this world of death, facing the thorns and briars of worries and sins.
They eat their bread, both physical and spiritual, by the sweat of their brow, and return to the earth from which they were taken through death.
Finally, through love and tribulation, as if passing through the cherubim and the sword, they return to paradise to enjoy the tree of life, which is Christ, the living bread, forever.
But who would dare to complain if it's said that these descendants, as I mentioned, are appropriately assigned to this?
By sinning, they incurred death, and after sinning, through repentance, they returned to life.
The affection of piety should agree, even rejoice, with this view, as it aligns with the rule of truth.
Hence, David, after receiving the promise of divine generosity about the longevity of his descendants, entered before the Lord to humble himself and sincerely praised God for the blessings given to him, saying:
"Who am I, Lord God, and what is my house, that you have brought me this far?
But even this was seen as little in your sight, Lord God, unless you spoke about the house of your servant in the distant future" (Second Samuel, Chapter 7).
He added: "For this is the law of Adam, Lord God," as if to say:
You didn't just start showing mercy to humans recently, but you were merciful even to the first man, who lived by that law, so that when he deserved punishment, he found favor.
You didn't reject him from your grace because of his merits but called him back to serve you with benefits.
Just as today, Lord God, you grant me unearned benefits, without my deserving them beforehand.
This is the law of Adam, Lord God.
That is, you show mercy to humans undeservedly, and humans serve you out of obligation.
In Hosea, when the Lord showed His immense love for the children of Israel and brought back those who had strayed, He said:
I will draw them with ropes of humanity, with bonds of love.
This implies that just as He did not abandon Adam when he sinned but corrected him, not allowing him to wander and be lost, instead drawing him back with love; in the same way, He bound the children of Israel when they sinned and called them back.
Through the hardships and challenges of repentance, they could return to the path of salvation and avoid falling into distorted freedom that leads to servitude.
If someone believes that the references I mentioned about Adam might not specifically refer to the first man, but rather to humanity in general, as if "Adam" is used here to mean "human," they should not be criticized for this view, as they might have gathered this from their reading.
They may have read what David says in the Book of Kings:
This is the law of Adam, Lord God, which the Hebrew tradition explains as:
This is the law of man, Lord God.
Similarly, in Hosea:
I will draw them with ropes of Adam, the Septuagint and other interpreters, as Jerome notes, have translated it as:
I will draw them with ropes of men.
So, it can generally be understood here as referring to man or humans, without contradicting the idea that it could specifically refer to the first man or the first humans.
Chapter Twenty-Five
I found another testimony clearly showing the first man, even though his actual name isn't mentioned.
The book titled Wisdom, when examined closely, reveals that it speaks of the salvation of the man who was first formed.
While praising wisdom and affirming that through it, all who have pleased God from the beginning have been healed, it says:
"She protected the first-formed man by God, the father of the world, when he was created alone, and delivered him from his sin, and gave him the power to control everything" (Wisdom 10).
Blessed Augustine seems to suggest that these words best refer to Adam himself, as he included them in a letter to Evodius.
He mentioned that almost the entire Church believes Christ delivered that first man, the father of the human race, from hell, a belief worth holding onto, even if there's no explicit authority from the canonical Scriptures presented here.
What's written in the book of Wisdom: "She protected the first-formed man by God, the father of the world, when he was created alone, and delivered him from his sin, and gave him the power to control everything," seems to support this view more than any other interpretation.
Don't be disturbed if in the thirteenth book of The City of God, or perhaps elsewhere, you've read that Augustine stated Adam became disobedient until death, as if implying that Adam never repented and remained stubborn in his disobedience until death.
If that were the case, he would undoubtedly never escape eternal death.
For anyone who doesn't repent before death faces nothing but eternal punishment afterward.
However, thinking this about him is different than disagreeing with him, with whom, as Augustine said, the entire Church agreed.
When it's said that Adam's disobedience was more detestable because he became disobedient unto death, it seems to me that this doesn't refer to the length of his life, but rather highlights how grave the disobedience was, as such great disobedience deserved death.
While all disobedience is bad, some are certainly much worse, with some being the worst.
If something easy is commanded and the one giving the command threatens death for disobedience, and the servant still ignores it, then it's clear they commit a mortal sin and deserve harsher punishment, especially since it was so easy to obey.
Therefore, Adam is rightfully said to have become disobedient unto death, not because he remained unrepentant until he died, but because his sin was so severe that he deserved to die.
To sin unto death means to sin in a way that deserves death.
So, if someone commits murder, adultery, or any other grave sin, they are rightly said to sin unto death.
This doesn't exclude the possibility of repentance, but rather expresses the severity of the sin itself.
Similarly, on the other hand, Christ is described as having become obedient unto death, as stated in Philippians, chapter two, meaning he showed such great obedience to the Father that the Jews judged him deserving of death.
As he remained steadfast in fulfilling the Father's command, they shouted, "He is guilty of death," as recorded in Matthew, chapter twenty-six.
When Pilate wanted to spare him, they responded, "We have a law, and according to that law, he ought to die," which is found in John, chapter nineteen.
They didn't stay silent about the kind of death he deserved, shouting, "Crucify, crucify!" as noted in Luke, chapter twenty-three.
This is what the Apostle says: He became obedient unto death, even death on a cross, as found in Philippians, chapter two.
Although Christ remained obedient throughout his life, it can be said that He became obedient even unto death.
As mentioned earlier, it's better to understand that the Apostle wanted to emphasize not just prolonged obedience, which many weak people might have, but a perfect and strong obedience where He either disregarded or embraced death.
In this mortal life, where there are many obstacles, strength is especially valued.
If obedience persists to the point of disregarding or facing death, it is rightly considered praiseworthy.
After this life, eternal days will follow, and strength will no longer be necessary because the Lord will rule over the good servant without end, and the good servant will obey without struggle.
This long, peaceful, and glorious obedience is praised in the passage where it says: When He hands over the kingdom to God the Father, then He Himself will be subject to Him who subjected everything to Him.
First Corinthians fifteen.
Chapter Twenty-Six
The courage I mentioned as essential for this life is praised by a wise person who confidently declares:
"My soul will praise the Lord until death" (Sirach 51).
What does it mean to praise until death?
Won't the soul also praise after death?
In fact, even more so after death.
So, when the prophet encourages us and says:
"Praise the Lord, my soul" (Psalm 145),
it elegantly responds:
"I will praise the Lord in my life,"
meaning: As long as I am in this mortal life, which might be called death rather than life (where any praise given to God is insignificant compared to future praise), I cannot fully praise Him, as it is written:
"He is the God of the living, not of the dead" (Matthew 22),
but I will praise Him in the land of the living, where I will truly live, because I will live without misery.
So, when that Wise One says:
"My soul will praise the Lord until death,"
he means not a long but a strong praise, and for that, even if it can't last, he is ready to face even the dangers of death.
In contrast, Adam is said to have been disobedient until death, although he repented before death by God's mercy. Saint Augustine also notes in some writings that Adam accepted the judgment of damnation, not understanding it as eternal damnation, but as temporary suffering.
Damnation isn't always eternal, as mentioned in:
"Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire" (Matthew 25),
but often refers to physical death or any temporal affliction.
Thus, in the Second Book of Maccabees:
"Menelaus, guilty of all evil, was acquitted, but the unfortunate ones, who would have been judged innocent even among the Scythians, were condemned to death" (Second Maccabees 4).
And Origen, in his fifth homily on Luke, mentions that Zachariah, the father of John, was condemned to silence because he did not believe the angel.
So, the condemnation that Adam faced appears to be the one we mentioned earlier:
"Cursed is the ground because of you; it will produce thorns and thistles for you. By the sweat of your brow, you will eat your food."
(Genesis chapter three)
Chapter Twenty-Seven
Finally, according to the parable in the Gospel, the man who traveled from Jerusalem to Jericho and fell among robbers, as told in the Gospel of Luke chapter ten, is understood to represent Adam.
What's said about him is specifically meant to apply to him.
When a wise man interpreted this parable regarding Adam, he explained that Jerusalem symbolizes paradise, Jericho the world, the robbers opposing powers, the wounds disobedience, the priest the law, the Levite the prophets, the Samaritan Christ, the animal the body of Christ, the inn the Church, the innkeeper the head of the Church, the two coins the Father and the Son, and the return of the Samaritan symbolizes the second coming of Christ.
Origen eloquently and reasonably states all these things in his thirty-third homily on Luke, noting that these interpretations apply specifically to him.
It's important to note that the robbers did not leave him dead, but half-dead; even though they cruelly inflicted the wounds of sins, they did not take away his hope for healing.
In the sixteenth homily on Genesis, Origen states, "I will call you back from there in the end," which I believe means that his only-begotten Son descended to hell for the salvation of the world until the end of the ages, calling back the first man from there.
Therefore, this will be more truly fulfilled in him than in Jacob, as it is said, "For I will call you back from there in the end."
Augustine, in his book On the Baptism of Infants, says, "Just as those first men are believed to have been freed from eternal punishment by the Lord's blood by living justly afterward."
Pope Gregory, when speaking of Adam in the Register, said, "His soul was not so dead that it did not exist, but so dead that it was not blessed, yet Adam later returned through repentance."
Who would dare to doubt Adam's repentance when both Augustine and Gregory so openly affirm it?
Bishop John, in the sermon titled "On the Fall of the First Man," also attests to the salvation of the same man.
He says, "The Lord God both loathed the cruelty of the enemy and pitied the fall of man, being moved with fatherly compassion for the deceived man."
Finally, the Lord God said, "Where are you, Adam?" He encourages confession, desires the admission of sin, seeks to show mercy, considers forgiveness, and reproves the fault so that he can grant forgiveness, purifying those who were not willing to be shaped by instruction through confession.
And he adds: They receive garments of skin so that those who had confessed their sin might receive forgiveness through humility in appearance. The Lord indeed shows that sins can be cleansed through kindness and that forgiveness can be easily obtained through confession and humility in appearance.
These are the words of John Chrysostom about Adam. Therefore, what the church teaches, indeed what the entire Church, as Augustine says, believes about this, we should also believe, since there is no authority from the Scriptures that disagrees.
Finally, the Encratites, also known as the Tatiani of heretical depravity, as Augustine testifies, are accused of contradicting the salvation of the first man among other things they perversely think and say.
To be truthful, I have spoken longer than I intended while discussing the necessary points about Adam. Even if not perfectly, yet as best as I could, it is now time to conclude my response, since what has been said should be sufficient for the brothers' inquiry.
Thus, let this response come to an end: I will move on to another, taking a brief pause in silence.