On the Prophet Joel
by Haymo of Halberstadt
Joel's name means "beginning." He delivers a prophecy to Judea and Jerusalem.
At the start of his book, he describes sorrowful feasts and calls Jerusalem to mourning, foretelling its destruction.
Joel also prophesies the calling of the nations and the coming of the Holy Spirit upon the gathered believers.
Chapter One
The word of the Lord came to Joel, the son of Pethuel.
Joel means "the strength of God," and Pethuel means "the opening" or "the word of the Lord." The word of God, which always was with the Father, came to Joel.
Listen to this, elders, and hear, all inhabitants of the earth. Elders not by age, but by merit; and inhabitants of the earth, who are weighed down by earthly works. There is a great difference between listening and hearing. Elders, that is, the spiritual ones, listen more reverently; but those who dwell on the earth hear, but more humbly. If this has happened in your days, or in the days of your fathers, tell it to your children; and let your children tell their children, and their children another generation. What I am about to say is known by memory: a new thing desires new listeners. For new wine is put into new wineskins. In this brief sentence, he included all of humanity.
What the caterpillar left, the locust has eaten; what the locust left, the cankerworm has eaten; and what the cankerworm left, the palmerworm has eaten. For what does the caterpillar, which crawls entirely on the ground, signify if not luxury? What does the locust, which flies by leaping, signify if not vain glory? What does the cankerworm, whose whole body is almost entirely in its belly, signify if not gluttony? And what does the palmerworm, which ignites when it touches, signify if not anger? Therefore, what the caterpillar left, the locust has eaten, because often, when the vice of luxury has departed from the mind, vain glory follows, as one boasts of sanctity through chastity. Thus, while vices succeed vices, another pestilence devours the field of the mind, leaving another behind. Alternatively: The Assyrians under Shalmaneser, the Babylonians under Nebuchadnezzar, Antiochus of Syria, and the Roman Emperor Vespasian ravaged Judea. Alternatively: These four pests signify the four kinds of vices by which human souls are corrupted; for they fear, desire, grieve, and rejoice.
Wake up, drunkards, and weep, and wail, all you drinkers of wine, because it has been cut off from your mouth.
Those who are confident in the love of this world are called drunkards because they do not feel the evils they suffer.
What does it mean to say, "Wake up, drunkards, and weep," except: Shake off the dream of your insensitivity, and with lamentations, confront the devastation of the heart caused by so many vices following one after another? For a strong and countless nation has come up against my land; its teeth are like the teeth of a lion, and its molars like those of a young lion. The strong and countless nation signifies demons, which ascend not over heaven, that is, the spiritual, but over the earth, that is, the carnal.
He has made my vineyard a desert and stripped my fig tree: laying it bare, he has thrown it away, and its branches have become white. The vineyard is called the people of the Lord, and the fig tree signifies the Israelite people. The devil has stripped the fig tree because he has stripped the Jewish people of all glory. Its branches have become white because its priests and teachers appear outwardly white through hypocrisy.
Mourn like a virgin clothed in sackcloth for the husband of your youth. O wretched people, or soul, who were joined to your spouse, that is, Christ, as to a husband, and defiled by demons, you have become an adulteress. Mourn like a virgin, that is, do penance. The sacrifice and the drink offering have perished from the house of the Lord; the priests, the ministers of the Lord, mourn. The house of the Lord refers to the Jewish people or the soul, which, stripped by adversary powers, is deprived of all sacrifice of justice.
The land is desolated, the ground mourns, for the grain is destroyed, the wine is confounded, and the oil languishes. This is what David says: "There is no one who does good, not even one." Grain, wine, and oil signify the gifts of the charisms, which in the Jewish people, or in other souls, have been dissipated by the devil through a degenerate life.
The farmers are ashamed, the vine dressers wail over the wheat, the wine, and the barley, because the harvest of the field has perished.
Farmers or vine growers are like angels, or rather teachers and scholars, who lament when they see the souls entrusted to them falling to carnal passions.
The harvest signifies the human race.
The vineyard is in disarray, and the fig tree has withered; the pomegranate, the palm tree, the apple tree, and all the trees of the field have dried up because joy has disappeared from the children of men.
The vineyard or fig tree represents the Jewish people mentioned earlier.
The pomegranate and other trees signify the different gifts of grace, which are taken away from humanity by evil powers through vice.
Gird yourselves and lament, priests; wail, ministers of the altar.
Come in and lie in sackcloth, ministers of my God, because the sacrifice and libation have perished from the house of our God.
This is an exhortation to the leaders of the Church to mourn for their people, through the education of those entrusted to them.
The house of God refers to the Church, or the soul from which the gifts of God have been lost through negligence of life.
Sanctify a fast, call an assembly, gather the elders, and all the inhabitants of the land, into the house of our God, and cry out to the Lord:
Alas, alas for the day!
For the day of the Lord is near, and it will come as devastation from the Almighty.
This means: sanctify your fast, combined with other virtues.
Elders and inhabitants of the land refer to teachers and listeners gathered in the Church through faith; the day of the Lord refers to the day of judgment.
Has not the food perished before your eyes, joy and gladness from the house of your God?
For as sins and vices grow, mourning replaces joy; the house of God is understood as the Church or the soul.
The animals have rotted in their dung.
To rot in their dung means that carnal men end their lives in the stench of luxury.
The granaries are destroyed, the storehouses are broken down, because the wheat is confused.
Granaries or storehouses signify the minds of the faithful, where the grain of justice and the wine of wisdom were usually stored.
Why has the animal groaned, the herds of cattle moaned?
Because there is no pasture for them, and even the flocks of sheep have perished.
What he meant by animals and herds was that people are knowledgeable but ignorant of God's teachings.
The cattle represent the nations.
The pastures failed because the dryness of God's word has taken over everything, and with the rain stopping, everything dried up.
The flocks were scattered because there are no shepherds to teach them properly.
To you, Lord, I cry out because fire has consumed the beauty of the desert, and flames have burned all the trees of the region.
Even the wild animals look up to you as if they were a thirsty land needing rain, for the water sources have dried up, and fire has devoured the beauty of the desert.
Fire represents the devil, the desert represents this world, the beauty of the desert represents people or the glory of this age, the trees of the region represent the nations consumed by the devil, and the wild animals of the field represent the nations who, after committing evil deeds, have turned to God and seek His mercy.
The water sources symbolize the knowledge of the law, which has dried up among the Jewish people due to unbelief.
Chapter Two
Blow the trumpet in Zion, cry out on my holy mountain; let all the inhabitants of the land tremble, because the day of the Lord is coming, it is near - a day of darkness and gloom, a day of clouds and whirlwind.
The clear voice is the proclamation of the Gospel, and Zion represents the Church or the soul; the inhabitants of the land are the carnal people, whom it terrifies and calls to repentance.
The day of judgment will be like a day of darkness and gloom for those who are to suffer punishment, similar to the day of darkness and gloom due to the condemnation of the wicked.
But, because all past deeds will be revealed by the justice of the judgment, it is also compared to the light of the sun.
Like the dawn spreading over the mountains, a large and powerful people, such as has never been from the beginning, and after them, there will be none for generations and generations to come.
The large and powerful people symbolize the multitude of demons and the impious, which from the beginning, that is from Adam until the end of the world, will be destroyed in judgment and will not exist forever, because after that day of judgment, there will be no more ascension or descent, as Origen suggested.
In front of them, a consuming fire and behind them a burning flame.
Wherever they enter, the army of demons immediately makes it a desert and burns up the flowers of all virtues.
The land before them is like the Garden of Eden, and behind them, a desolate wilderness, and no one can escape them.
Before a person sins by their persuasion and is without sin, they are like the Garden of Eden; but once they are caught and led into sin, it makes them a desolate wilderness, so that there is no one, or rarely anyone, who can escape their trap.
Their appearance is like the appearance of horses, and like horsemen, they run.
The horse is the person, the horseman is the devil.
Like the appearance of horses is the appearance of the impious, through whom the devil persecutes the righteous.
The devil's chariot consists of the four passions described under the name of plagues at the beginning of this book.
Like the noise of chariots on the tops of mountains, they leap, like the noise of a flame devouring stubble, like a strong people prepared for battle.
Straw, light, and unproductive people, consumed by the devil's fire.
In his presence, nations will suffer, and all faces will turn pale.
When the nations start to be dragged with him into punishment, and the devil gains control over them, they will run like strong men, like warriors climbing a wall.
Unfortunate is that city, which represents the soul, captured by such an enemy.
When anyone enters it, running eagerly over the wall of virtues, they mock.
And when they enter the house of conscience, if they find any good there, they destroy it all.
A man will walk in his own ways and will not turn from his paths.
Each one will not constrain his brother.
Everyone will walk in their own path.
But they will also fall through windows and not be broken.
They will enter the city, run on the wall, and climb houses.
For those in whom the devil has taken power, entering through the senses of the flesh like through windows, he plunders, taking away what he finds inside.
But if anyone forbids him from entering, the building of good works will not be demolished.
They will enter through windows like a thief, meaning demons will secretly enter through our senses like thieves.
The earth trembled before him, the heavens were moved, the sun and moon were darkened, and the stars withdrew their brightness.
At the face of this demonic people, or even the Antichrist, the earth trembled, representing sinners; the heavens were moved, representing the spiritual ones.
The sun and moon were darkened because the faith of Christ and the Church will fail in the hearts of some under the Antichrist.
And the Lord gave his voice before his army because his camps are very many, and they are strong and do his word.
Divine preaching will precede the advent of the Antichrist.
The camps of demons are therefore called the camps of the Lord because in every necessity they serve his law both for the testing of the righteous and for the condemnation of the wicked.
For the day of the Lord is great and very terrible, and who can endure it?
This is understood in two ways in Scriptures: either no one or very few.
Now therefore, says the Lord: Turn to me with all your heart, with fasting, weeping, and mourning.
The Lord's call to humanity for repentance begins with fasting because fasting is the foundation of true repentance.
Accompanying fasting are weeping and mourning.
Tear your hearts, not your clothes, and turn to the Lord your God, for He is gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and rich in love, ready to relent from punishment.
This message is for those who show repentance outwardly but not in their hearts.
Let not the sinner despair because of the magnitude of their sins; the Lord's kindness and mercy promise that He does not punish immediately but gives room for repentance.
Who knows if He will turn and forgive and leave a blessing behind?
A sacrifice and drink offering to the Lord our God.
He promises forgiveness for each sin, but without certainty, so as not to encourage negligence in the penitent, and leave a blessing behind.
First, a blessing that dispels the curse, then a sacrifice and drink offering, which are good works that please God.
Blow the trumpet in Zion, declare a holy fast, call a sacred assembly, gather the people: sanctify the congregation, assemble the elders, gather the children, even nursing infants.
He repeats this again so that by frequently hearing the teaching, they may turn to God.
The gathering of the people is the assembly of the faithful in the Church through Christ; the diversity of ages signifies the distinction of merits.
Let the bridegroom leave his room and the bride her chamber.
Between the porch and the altar, let the priests, the ministers of the Lord, weep and say.
The bridegroom is Christ, coming forth from His chamber, that is, from the bosom of the Father, to the public of the human race.
The bride is His flesh, coming forth from the womb of the Virgin Mary as if from her chamber.
The bridegroom is the divine word, the bride is the faithful soul.
The priests, the ministers of the Lord, are the apostles, interceding for the people's sins.
Spare, Lord, spare your people, and do not give your heritage to reproach, that the nations should rule over them.
This means that He sent someone to deliver them, and He spared His people.
With the coming of Christ, He granted forgiveness of sins so that the nations, or demons, would not rule over them.
Therefore, among the peoples, they say: Where is their God?
The Lord was zealous for His land and spared His people.
He is said to be zealous because zeal is a sign of love.
The response of the Lord, His promise through the books of the law and the prophets: Behold, I will send you grain, wine, and oil, and you will be filled with them.
I will no longer make you a disgrace among the nations.
The grain is Christ, who in Zechariah is called the grain of the chosen ones; the wine represents the grace of the Holy Spirit; and the oil signifies the charisms, which are poured out from Christ by the gift of the Holy Spirit into the hearts of the chosen ones.
This means: by my blessing, I will wipe away the old curse.
And him who is from the north, I will cast far away from you, and I will drive him into a barren and desolate land.
The north refers to the devil; the barren and desolate land refers to all the reprobates over whom he reigns.
His face turned toward the eastern sea, and its end toward the western sea.
The devil does not face the sun of righteousness, but wherever he looks, he always sees the sea of this world.
The eastern and western seas symbolize the beginning of his downfall.
And his stench will rise up, and his corruption will rise up, because he acted arrogantly.
When this same devil is slain at the end of the world, then his stench, that is, what he truly is, will be apparent to all.
Do not be afraid, land; rejoice and be glad, because the Lord has done great things.
Do not be afraid, animals of the field, because the beautiful places of the wilderness have sprouted.
This signifies His plan for the salvation of the human race, that from their substance the Son of God would take on flesh.
What was previously cursed, He now says is restored with God's blessing.
The animals of the field are the nations to whom the word of power, that is, Christ, was brought forth through the Virgin.
Because the tree brought forth its fruit, the fig tree and the vine gave their strength.
And you, children of Zion, rejoice and be glad in the Lord your God, who has given you a teacher of righteousness, and He will make the early rain come down to you.
The tree, Christ, is truly understood as the Holy Spirit in the form of a fig tree; the vineyard is also Christ among the faithful people; the children of Zion are called the children of the Church established in the vision of faith; the teacher of righteousness, Christ, chosen by God the Father for His Church; the early and late rain, the blessing of both Testaments divinely bestowed in Christ.
And the threshing floors will be filled with grain, and the wine presses will overflow with wine and oil.
That is, in Christ, or in the beginning of the spiritual kingdom, the threshing floors of the Church are filled with the believing people, or the hearts of the chosen ones are overflowing with various virtues through the rain of the grace of the Holy Spirit.
And I will restore to you the years that the locust has eaten, the cankerworm, the caterpillar, and the palmerworm.
My great strength, which I sent among you.
These four pests signify the four disturbances through which the devil devours the human race, that is: desire and fear, joy and sorrow.
And you will eat and be satisfied, and praise the name of the Lord your God, who has done wonders with you.
For all who read the Scriptures carnally, like the Jews, and do not reach spiritual understanding, these are the ones who eat and never reach satisfaction.
And you will praise the name of the Lord your God, that is: if you have attained the mercy of God through spiritual understanding.
And my people will not be put to shame forever, and you will know that I am in the midst of Israel, that is, in the midst of those seeing God by faith.
And I am the Lord your God, and there is no other, and my people will not be put to shame forever.
I am Christ, and I am your Lord, the same Christ, and there is no one beyond Christ.
And it will come to pass afterward, that I will pour out my spirit on all flesh, and your sons and daughters will prophesy.
Your old men will dream dreams, and your young men will see visions.
The old men, He calls prophets, the young men, apostles.
But I will pour out my spirit on my servants and maidservants in those days.
This was clearly stated and fulfilled according to history.
By "my servants," he means spiritual men and teachers; by "maidservants," he refers to churches or the souls of believers.
And I will show wonders in the heavens and on the earth: blood, fire, and columns of smoke.
The wonders in the heavens refer to the saints, and on the earth, they refer to sinners, which the Lord promises to reveal. And what are these wonders but signs and the destruction of sinners, revealed with the coming of the Holy Spirit? Blood signifies the killing of souls; fire signifies the heat of the body or the anger of the heart; columns of smoke signify harmful thoughts that boil in the hearts of men.
According to history and prophecy, all these were fulfilled during the time of Christ's passion.
The sun will be turned to darkness, and the moon to blood, before the great and dreadful day of the Lord comes.
This means the brightness of some of the faithful will fail in the final tribulation and the Church will be stained with the blood of martyrs.
And it will be that everyone who calls on the name of the Lord will be saved. To call on and declare the Lord's name must be proven not only by voice but by action and result.
For on Mount Zion and in Jerusalem there will be salvation, as the Lord has said, and among the survivors whom the Lord calls. We understand Mount Zion and Jerusalem to mean the Church, in which there will be salvation, as he said.
Chapter Three
In those days and at that time, when I restore the fortunes of Judah and Jerusalem,
the first will be the holy apostles, or others who believed from among the circumcised, while the rest will come from the Gentiles.
I will gather all nations and bring them down to the Valley of Jehoshaphat, where I will judge them.
Jehoshaphat means the Judgment of the Lord.
So this is what He says: When I have shown mercy to those who confess my name, I will bring all my adversaries to the valley of judgment.
All nations could mean all unbelieving nations, or it could refer to all demons.
Against my people and my heritage Israel, whom they have scattered among the nations and divided my land.
This means, I will not oppress them on the day of judgment, but by reason of justice, or even by their own confession, they will recognize themselves as worthy of punishment.
And they cast lots for my people.
This means, they eagerly wanted to rule over each individual.
They put a boy in a brothel and sold a girl for wine to drink.
Here, He complains about their actions, that even the strongest, those who could grow into virtues, have been emasculated with injustices, and the strong souls have been subjected to lust and pleasures.
But what have you to do with me, Tyre and Sidon, and all the regions of the Philistines?
Will you repay me for something?
Tyre means trouble or distress, Sidon means hunting, that is, demons: Philistines, those who fall by drink.
All these must be understood as referring to heretics, through whom the devil has separated the people of God from the Church, and through their eloquence, like gold and silver, leading the simple ones out of the Church, selling them under sin to the sons of the Greeks, that is, the Gentiles.
And if you seek revenge against me, swiftly and quickly I will return the recompense upon your own heads.
You took my silver and gold, and brought my precious and beautiful things into your temples.
You sold the sons of Judah and Jerusalem to the sons of Greece, sending them far from their borders and leading them into sin, away from the faith of the Church.
Behold, I will raise them from the place where you sold them, and I will turn your retribution back upon your own heads.
I will restore those who were torn from the foundation of the Church to their former state of faith, and I will bring vengeance upon your heads, the heads of the heretics who led them astray.
I will sell your sons and daughters into the hands of the sons of Judah, meaning those you have taken from the Church will rise up against you.
Your sons and daughters, meaning your disciples, will be brought into subjection by the preachers of the Church.
They will sell them to the Sabeans, a distant nation, because the Lord has spoken.
Saba means conversion, while Judah means confession.
The Sabeans are called a distant nation because the saints who rule over the heretics will live forever.
Proclaim this among the nations, prepare for war, rouse the strong.
O leaders, meaning teachers, call out to those who are subject to you, for the day of judgment is coming.
Let all the warriors come and ascend.
Let the foot soldiers come, let the horsemen ascend.
The horses are the wicked men, and the horsemen are the devil or demons.
These are called warriors who usually subdue the human race through vice.
Beat your plowshares into swords, and your pruning hooks into spears; let the weak say, "I am strong."
Remove, says the Lord, O you demons, all peace into sedition, and let all rise to war.
Let the weak say, "I am strong."
To say in Scriptures means to complete by action.
And when you have done all these evils, and come with all your strength to fight against my chosen ones, then on the day of judgment, I will lay low all your strength.
Burst forth and come, all nations; gather together from all around.
There the Lord will bring down your strong ones.
This means that when the day of the Lord comes and the end of the world approaches, Satan will unleash all his power during the times of the Antichrist and will fight more fiercely to tempt and overthrow souls.
Nations will rise and go to the valley of Jehoshaphat.
But they are not judged on the mountains or plains, but in the depths below, so that the place of judgment itself becomes the place of punishment.
For there, I will sit to judge all the surrounding nations.
God's sitting signifies the habit and authority of judging.
Put in the sickles, for the harvest is ripe.
This speaks to the angels, for the reapers are the angels, and the harvest is the people.
In a way, the angels descend from their high place when they take on the roles of torturers.
Come and descend, for the winepress is full; the vats overflow because their wickedness has multiplied.
The world, or the winepress, is already overflowing with iniquities, and it can no longer contain the wickedness of the human race.
People, people in the valley of decision, for the day of the Lord is near in the valley of decision.
He did not say judgment to avoid giving the impression of doubt, but he used decision, from which nothing can be left.
The sun and the moon are darkened, and the stars have withdrawn their brightness.
The sun is Christ; the moon is the Church.
And the stars of Christ have withdrawn their brightness from those who will be tormented.
For those who go into punishment will not deserve to see the light of justice.
And the Lord will roar from Zion and give his voice from Jerusalem, and the heavens and the earth will shake, that is, from the Church of the saints or from the heavenly Jerusalem.
For just as all animals are terrified at the roar of a lion, so will all be afraid of his voice.
And the Lord is the hope of his people and the strength of the children of Israel.
And you will know that I am the Lord your God, that is, of those who believe and see God through faith.
Dwelling in Zion on my holy mountain.
The holy mountain can be understood as either the heavenly Jerusalem or certainly the Son himself.
And Jerusalem will be holy, and foreigners will no longer pass through it.
Whether it is the heavenly Jerusalem or the Church, they will no longer have power over it.
They are recognized as strangers.
On that day, the mountains will drip with sweetness, the hills will flow with milk, and water will stream through all of Judah.
The mountains and hills, representing the diversity of merits, are called holy.
The sweetness represents the words of Scripture, and the streams signify the hearts of the chosen ones.
Water symbolizes the grace of the Holy Spirit.
A fountain will emerge from the house of the Lord, watering the valley of thorns.
This fountain represents the divinity of the Son of God or the Holy Spirit, and the valley of thorns symbolizes the sins of humanity, which will be purified by their grace.
Egypt will be desolate, and Edom will become a desert of destruction because they acted unjustly against the children of Judah and shed innocent blood in their land.
Egypt represents darkness, meaning demons or sins.
Edom signifies blood or earthly pleasures, which will be desolated on the day of judgment for deceiving the children of the Church.
Judah will be inhabited forever, and Jerusalem for generations to come.
I will cleanse their blood, which I had not cleansed before, and the Lord will dwell in Zion.
Judah, meaning the house of confession, will be inhabited forever.
Even though it is not entirely innocent in this life, it is tainted with minor sins.
I will cleanse everything through my abundant mercy, which they could not achieve through their own virtues.
Zion is interpreted as a watchtower.
Therefore, the Lord will dwell on high, in the Church, where He will reign forever.