Dissertation on the Book about the Body and Blood of the Lord by James Boileau, a theologian from Paris.
The book on the Body and Blood of the Lord is attributed to Ratramnus and is defended against any suspicion of Calvinist novelty or heresy, particularly against the claims of John Hardouin, a priest from the Society of Jesus.
In 1689, a Jesuit theologian published in Paris, under the press of Francis Muguet, a letter from Saint John Chrysostom to the monk Caesarius.
This letter was accompanied by notes and a dissertation on the sacrament of the altar.
For some unknown reason, he convinced himself that Ratramnus, a priest and monk of Corbie, was not the true author of the book written 800 years ago on the Body and Blood of the Lord for Emperor Charlemagne or Charles the Bald.
He argued strongly that the book was filled with heretical errors.
However, I noticed that this dissertator was eager to refute and dismantle the arguments I used to persuade myself that Ratramnus's credibility was clear of any suspicion of heresy, and that all accusations against the book on the Body and Blood of the Lord were erased.
I published a Latin-French edition with great care in Paris, at John Boudot under the Golden Sun in 1686.
I included an apologetic preface and added further notes.
I set out to write this response, aiming to prove two things that have always seemed not only probable but certain to me: first, that Ratramnus is the true and genuine author of this book, and second, that it cannot be accused of heresy or error.
So, arise, learned reader, and, putting aside any preconceived opinions mostly formed by both uneducated and educated theological writers, judge this matter: from your judgment, I promise never to appeal.
The most reliable way to attribute a book to its author is through ancient manuscripts where the author's name is clearly stated—genuine, not fabricated or altered.
Among scholars, such titles or letters are seen as key authorities and decisive in disputes, with rights supported by these documents standing the test of time.
There's no doubt that these original manuscripts were written during Ratramnus's lifetime, marked with his name.
I published an eight-hundred-year-old copy from the Abbey of Lobbes, along with a French translation given to me by the learned Mabillon, a distinguished monk from the Order of Saint Benedict.
Mabillon is renowned for his sincerity and exceptional skill in distinguishing authentic manuscripts from forgeries.
Another seven-hundred-year-old copy from the Abbey of Salem Weiler is also mentioned in the German Journey, bearing Ratramnus's name in the same way.
Unless proven to be forged, such documents are beyond dispute.
Therefore, since the scholar does not suspect these manuscripts bearing Ratramnus's name to be false, he seems to have willingly given up any chance to contradict or refute them.
The esteemed Peter de Marca, Archbishop of Paris, whose opinion the scholar agreed with, had neither seen these manuscripts nor believed they existed.
He would not have maintained the belief that Ratramnus’s name was wrongly attributed to the work on the Body and Blood of the Lord, nor would he have credited it to John Scotus in a letter to Lord Luca Dacheriius, a learned monk from the Order of Saint Benedict, in 1659, if he had known about these manuscripts.
This is very plausible for such a great man, so learned and eager for a good reputation among scholars.
I believe he likely reverted to his previous stance, or rather defended it, as is evident from the treatise on the Eucharist.
This was made public by his companion and relative, Abbot Fagetius, and through the open confession of the aforementioned bishop to Lord Lucas Dacherius.
This happened before he wrote that famous letter to him, published in Volume 2 of the Spicilegium.
The very learned Mabillon left no room for doubt about the sincerity of this distinguished bishop in the preface to the second part of the fourth century of Benedictines, page 45, section 6.
Here, he provides undeniable testimony from this confession: Dacherius had asked what the most learned bishop thought about Ratramnus' book.
He replied that he thought highly of it, but when asked for a formal opinion, he shifted his perspective.
Furthermore, how did John Scotus depict the character and guise of Ratramnus, perhaps a living man, who was well-known among scholars and who could easily dispute and refute such boldness?
What support could he find under a hidden name with Emperor Charles the Bald openly inquiring about the learned views on the body of Christ in the Eucharist?
Why would Catholic men with differing opinions, without accusations of heresy, need to release writings under fictitious names or pseudonyms?
These issues are clearer than daylight from the second section of the book on the Body and Blood of the Lord, which shows that this entire controversy existed among faithful Catholic men.
However, two hundred years after Ratramnus' book was published, with the rise of Berengar's heresy, which gave the sect its name, they used John Scotus' book to support their cause.
They never claimed that the book on the Body and Blood was attributed to Ratramnus or Bertram instead of John Scotus.
Catholic men who opposed Berengarius did not object to changing names or titles.
In fact, some Catholic writers, for humility's sake, published their works under a pseudonym.
This was true for the author of "The Imitation of Christ," the works on the Sacraments by Saint Ambrose, the "Commonitorium" by Vincent of Lérins, and many others.
This concealment led to misattributions and speculation about the authorship of many works.
However, shortly after the invention of the printing press, the practice of using false names was uncovered, and scholars began to claim others' work as their own.
Before this, except for a few cases, pseudonymous writers were rare, although anonymous ones were not—those who hid their names and gave their works fictitious titles.
You'll hardly find this in ancient history, except for Origen's "Apology," credited to Pamphilus the martyr but believed by many to be by Eusebius of Caesarea.
It's well known that the book "On the Body and Blood of the Lord" was written at Emperor Charles the Bald's command by a learned man whose humility matched his wisdom.
The king had sought his opinion on this mystery.
Moreover, with focused intent, he refrains from speaking on his own but reflects the opinions of the Church Fathers.
So, what did he have to fear, and why attribute a false name to a work filled with the Fathers' opinions?
What benefit would there be in hiding the identity of someone writing at the emperor's behest?
These circumstances certainly don't align with John Scotus, as it would be unlikely and unbelievable to suggest he was pretending or compelled by the emperor to write the book.
No reasonable person would dare to openly claim they are writing under the orders of a great ruler on such a critical matter as religion while the king and emperor are still alive.
To do so would be to put their life and reputation at great risk, facing accusations of being a forger and crossing all bounds of decency.
It's hard to believe that Bertram's name was changed to Ratramnus by scribes or copyists in the late ninth and early tenth centuries.
During that time, the book about the Body and Blood of the Lord was widely circulated, regardless of whether it was considered heretical or catholic.
If it was catholic, why would it need to be published under a disguised name like John Scotus?
If it was seen as heretical, how could it be attributed to such a respected figure in the catholic religion, a man known for his holiness and learning, namely Ratramnus of Corbie, a monk, priest, and abbot of Orbais, as Flodoard reports?
This was someone whose help the bishops of the Gallican Church deemed necessary to defend the Western Church against the Greeks.
He had strongly defended Saint Augustine's doctrine on Predestination by the order of Charles the Bald, King of France.
Therefore, it is clear that the false attribution of Ratramnus' name to the book about the Blood of Christ's body cannot be supported except by someone making a reckless claim.
Furthermore, it follows that this work cannot be attributed to Erigena, who, because of the transformation of Bertram's name into Ratramnus, was mistakenly called the author of the book about the Body and Blood of the Lord in the eleventh century.
This doesn't appear among the true writings of Erigena, nor does any eleventh-century ecclesiastical writer, who discussed and revisited the disputes and controversies of Berengar, ever mention this book about the Body and Blood of the Lord, leaving it unmentioned and in silence.
An anonymous author, made known by Cellotius, a theologian of the Jesuit society, in the appendix to the History of Gottschalk, specifically lists Ratramnus among the opponents of Paschasius, the abbot of Corbie.
However, there's a notable difference between the anonymous author and Eriger.
Eriger, in contrast, wrote against Paschasius, as we learn from the continuation of the Chronicle of the Abbey of Lobbes, which borrowed these words from the Chronicle of Sigebert, the abbot of Gembloux:
Eriger also compiled many writings of the Catholic Fathers against Radbert about the Body and Blood of the Lord.
These writings can be found in Volume 6 of the Dacherian Spicilegium, page 591.
The confusion or mix-up of the names Bertram and Ratramnus was not a mistake for Sigebert, a twelfth-century writer, as the dissertation suggests.
Sigebert attributed the book about the Body and Blood of Christ to the true and genuine author in his Catalog of Ecclesiastical Writers, specifically naming Ratramnus, which is clearly supported by ancient manuscripts.
In fact, if some manuscripts of Sigebert show the name Bertram instead of Ratramnus, they are more recent and altered.
I don't think the dissertation writer consulted anything other than printed copies that lack the care and faithfulness to Sigebert's original manuscripts.
From this, it's easy to see how weak the dissertation writer's argument is when he imagines that Paschasius Radbert, the abbot of Corbie, meant to refer to the author of the book about the Body and Blood of the Lord with these words in a letter to Frudgard:
Although some err out of ignorance, no one yet openly contradicts that which the whole world believes and confesses.
The dissertation writer interprets these words as follows:
He undoubtedly implies, he says, that he knows of a volume whose author would not dare to confront openly, as they say, but would proceed masked.
However, Paschasius wrote this letter around the year 860.
If Paschasius truly wrote this letter to Frudgard in 860, it's unlikely he referred to Ratramnus's book on the Body and Blood of the Lord.
This is because the book was written about fifteen years later, at a time when Charles the Bald had become ruler of the Western Empire, as indicated by the preface title: "To Emperor Charles the Great," found in ancient manuscripts.
According to these manuscripts, the book was first printed in 1532.
Chronicles tell us that Charles the Bald, referred to by this title, didn't assume the empire until 875, after being crowned by Pope John the Eighth, following his victory over King Louis of Germany, who passed away in Frankfurt on August 28, 876.
It's also well known that Charles the Bald reigned for only two years, dying on October 6, 877.
It's clear how the essayist mistakenly argued that Paschasius wrote to Frudgard in 860.
This confusion arises because more years had passed since Paschasius's death than could have occurred before 853, the year Odo, abbot of Corbie, who succeeded Paschasius, signed the Second Council of Soissons.
The essayist might claim Paschasius resigned from the abbey of Corbie in 852 or 853 and hadn't yet died.
However, he won't be able to prove Paschasius lived beyond 859 or 860.
Thus, it's even clearer that Paschasius couldn't have been thinking of Ratramnus's book in his letter to Frudgard, since it was composed only during Charles the Bald's reign, to whom it was dedicated as emperor, between 875 and 877, when Charles was poisoned by his doctor Zedekiah.
These facts clearly show how the essayist is mistaken.
Hincmar, the Archbishop of Reims, mentioned a book about the Body and Blood of the Lord, which we believe was written by Ratramnus, in the year 859.
He refers to volume one of the book on Predestination, chapter 21, page 232.
There, he clearly states that not Ratramnus, but John the Scot, is widely and openly considered by everyone to be the author of the chapters that Hincmar aimed to refute.
However, the ideas that contradict the Church's faith, taken from the teachings and book of John the Scot, do not appear in the book On the Body and Blood of the Lord under Ratramnus's name.
So, what exactly are these words or the meaning behind Ratramnus's words?
First, the idea that the Deity is threefold.
Second, that angels are naturally corporeal.
That the human soul is not in the body?
Third, that the sacraments of the altar are not the true Body and Blood of the Lord, but merely a memory of His true Body and Blood.
In fact, Ratramnus states in numbers 99 and 100: that this bread and cup, which are called and exist as the body and blood of Christ, represent the memory of the Lord's passion, as He Himself said in the Gospel: "Do this in remembrance of me."
This is indeed very true and aligns most fittingly with the Catholic faith.
For Ratramnus does not claim it is not the true body, but rather that it is called and exists as the true body and blood of Christ.
Nor does he say it is only a memory, since the word "only" contains the danger of a great heresy.
Furthermore, to prevent Catholic believers from misunderstanding Ratramnus's words, he wisely avoids any trace of heresy with these words:
We should not think, because we say these things, that in the mystery of the sacrament the body or blood of the Lord is not received by the faithful, since faith accepts not what the eye sees, but what it believes.
If it is not received in the Eucharist, or if it is not believed to be received, then what the eye sees must be believed by faith to be the true body of Christ:
for as faith believes the true body of Christ to be present, it is called and exists as such.
Furthermore, during Hincmar's time, the chapters he refutes were openly attributed to John Scotus and Prudentius, the Bishop of Troyes, without any objection, but not to Ratramnus.
His virtue and faith remain untouched by any vile heresy, shining with unblemished honors.
Check out Hincmar's book on Predestination, specifically chapter 21, page 350.
In these chapters, he discusses the authors, who are often their own opponents and, in some cases, opponents of the truth, with many attributing them to Prudentius the Bishop and John Scotus.
The commentator on page 167 doesn't convincingly argue that he uncovered or removed the mask from the author of "On the Body and Blood of the Lord," which was Adrevald, a monk of Fleury during Charles the Bald's reign, in a pamphlet written against the absurdities of John Scotus, mentioned in volume 12 of the Dacherian Spicilegium.
Indeed, Adrevald's pamphlet was written either before Charles took the empire or after.
If it was before, he couldn't have uncovered the mask from a book not yet completed; but if it was after, from 875 to 877, how could he have uncovered the mask?
At that time, according to the commentator, there was no doubt in anyone's mind that the author was John Scotus.
Adrevald wrote specifically against the absurdities of John Scotus, not against Ratramnus or Bertram.
If Ratramnus had been the author of those absurdities refuted by Adrevald under John Scotus's name, such absurdities should appear in Ratramnus's book, either wholly or in part.
However, they do not catch the eye of a careful reader; therefore, Adrevald did not consider Ratramnus's book, or the book we defend, "On the Body and Blood of the Lord."
But, according to the commentator, during Berengar's time, the book "On the Body and Blood of the Lord" was known only under John Scotus's name.
The solitary Sigebert, however, attributes it to Bertram.
The straightforward answer is that Ratramnus' book on the Body and Blood of the Lord was not used by Berengarius' followers to support their error, but it was more in line with the views of John Scotus.
Moreover, the speaker continues by explaining that to prove the work often credited to John Scotus actually belongs to Ratramnus, he references a letter from the monk Ascelin to Berengarius.
This letter was included and published in the notes of Lord Lucas Dacherius on the Life of Lanfranc, Archbishop of Canterbury, on page 25, where these words defending Ratramnus' book are revealed:
"I do not regard John Scotus rashly, impiously, or disrespectfully of my priesthood: I see him striving solely to persuade me that what is consecrated on the altar is not truly the blood of Christ.
However, it is as unfair and disgraceful as possible to attribute such a statement to Ratramnus using this argument, especially since he has never spoken in this way.
Nothing seems more contrary to common sense than to imagine someone who does not believe that what is consecrated on the altar is truly the body or blood of Christ; yet, he convinces himself, without doubt, that through the mystery of the Eucharist, the bread and wine are transformed into the substance of His body and blood for the faithful to partake.
What does the faith of the Church teach us?
What do we believe and confess by that faith?
Except that through the mystery of the Eucharist, the bread and wine consecrated on the altar are truly transformed into the substance of the body and blood of Christ, to be received by the faithful, as we understand it?
Indeed, Ratramnus, also known as Bertramus, expressed these words orally and wrote them in his book on the Body and Blood of the Lord.
Then you'll understand that, contrary to what non-believers might think, my flesh isn't meant to be eaten by believers in the literal sense of being divided and torn into pieces, as previously explained in the same text.
Instead, through a mystery, the bread and wine truly become the substance of my body and blood and are to be received by the faithful.
It's incredible, inconceivable, and utterly impossible—unless all the laws of natural and reasonable fairness are violated—for someone who doesn't believe that what's consecrated on the altar is truly the body and blood of Christ, to sincerely believe that by the omnipotence of the Word, the body and blood of Christ truly exist on the altar.
These ideas seem so contradictory that they appear completely incompatible in a coherent mind.
Nevertheless, these last words thoroughly explain Ratramnus's thoughts, as they are taken from number 49 of the mentioned book.
From everything that's been said so far, it has been shown that the body and blood of Christ, which are received by the mouths of the faithful in the Church, are figures according to visible appearance.
But according to the invisible substance, that is, the divine power of the Word, the body and blood of Christ truly exist.
The same is repeated in number 99:
Let us add that this bread and cup is named and exists as the body and blood of Christ.
But to ensure nothing is lacking from our supporting arguments, I gladly ask the lecturer if they can imagine someone completely rejecting the faith of the Catholic Church, specifically believing that what is consecrated on the altar is neither truly the body nor the blood of Christ, who considers it wrong not only to deny that the body and blood of Christ are in the Eucharist but even to think it.
These ideas are no less contradictory and incompatible.
Yet, there is no room for doubt that Ratramnus, with the words in number 15, says:
They are compelled to deny that the body and blood of Christ exist, which is wrong not only to say but even to think.
Given these circumstances, it's as clear as daylight that the book mentioned by Ascelinus in his letter to Berengar should not be attributed to Ratramnus but returned to its rightful author, John Scotus Eriugena.
However, the writer argues that the passages found in John Scotus's book appear verbatim in Ratramnus’s book, number 88.
This can be easily understood from Ascelinus's letter:
"This, namely that it is neither truly the body nor the blood, he attempts to prove from the works of the holy Fathers which he expounds, among which it is enough to note this prayer of Saint Gregory:
'May your sacraments, O Lord, we beseech, accomplish in us what they contain, so that what we now perform as a symbol, we may grasp in reality.'"
In explaining this, the aforementioned John, among other things contrary to our faith, says:
"These things are performed as a symbol, not in reality;" which is not said in a Catholic manner. If I know your vigilance well, you are not unaware. The writer could easily have dismissed your objection.
Indeed, this prayer from the Sacramentary of Saint Gregory is read in the exact words by Ratramnus, but he used it to defend the Catholic sense, which is entirely opposed to John Scotus's opinion.
For John Scotus, from the words, "what we now perform as a symbol, we may grasp in reality," argued that the body of Christ exists only in figure, and by no means does its existence, reality, and substance appear in the Eucharist.
But Ratramnus interprets a completely different and opposing sense from this prayer. He believed that the body and blood truly exist under the figure, that is, under the veil and covering of an invisible form, but not in figure alone.
By these words, "we may grasp in reality," he understood the manifestation and clear declaration of the body and blood of Christ free from any figure.
Therefore, he explains Saint Gregory's prayer as follows:
"He says that in that form they are performed, not in reality, that is through likeness, not through the manifestation of the thing itself."
If John Scotus had used these words metaphorically rather than literally, Ascelinus might not have accused him of heresy.
Sometimes, truth can be ambiguous, as we mentioned in the preface of this small work by Ratramnus.
This term signifies not only the existence of something that can exist under symbols or veils but also its revelation or manifestation, which cannot be linked to any figure or metaphor.
To clarify the passage from Saint Gregory, which he aimed to defend, Ratramnus referenced another passage, number seventy-five, from the Gelasian Sacramentary, which says:
"So that what we touch in the image, we may take in the clear participation of the sacrament."
John Scotus did not present this passage because it was not beneficial, but rather inconvenient for his purposes.
Lanfranc, Archbishop of Canterbury, a strong defender of the Catholic faith against Berengar, adopted the Catholic interpretation Ratramnus attributed to this term of truth, as seen in his Dialogue against Berengar, where it states:
"The priest asks that the body of Christ, now carried under the appearance of bread and wine, may be received in clear vision as it truly is; for truth is found to mean manifestation in the holy scriptures."
Who would say that John Scotus's words appear in Lanfranc's book with the exact same syllables?
The writer overstates his case when claiming that Berengar, in a letter to Lanfranc, said John Scotus's opinion was contrary to Paschasius and differed from the views of saints like Ambrose, Jerome, and Augustine, regardless of who might oppose John Scotus.
He argues that Ratramnus's work does not differ from John Scotus's book, as Ratramnus cites the same Fathers—Augustine, Jerome, and Ambrose.
He also notes that Ratramnus lists Erigena among Paschasius's opponents, but what does that signify?
There's nothing stopping John Scotus's opinion from opposing Paschasius, nor Ratramnus from aligning with him.
In fact, it's highly likely that this is the case.
Moreover, if citing Augustine, Ambrose, and Jerome means Ratramnus doesn't differ from John Scotus, then by that logic, Lanfranc could agree with Berengar, Sanctesius with Calvin, and Perronius with Plesseus Morneio.
Is it really acceptable to misuse reason and sense so recklessly?
This kind of reasoning might hold if Ratramnus only presented Augustine, Jerome, and Ambrose, but he also cited St.
Isidore of Seville, numbers 40, 45, and 47; St.
Fulgentius, number 89; the Sacramentary of St.
Gregory, number 88; and the Missal of Gelasius, number 85, none of which, except for St.
Gregory’s Sacramentary, are mentioned by John Scotus.
Moreover, Erigena didn't claim that Ratramnus opposed Paschasius; an anonymous writer from Cellot did, and it's wrong to confuse him with Erigena.
Even if, in some manuscript possibly five hundred years old, an anonymous booklet bears the name of Erigena, a stronger argument is needed to attribute such a trivial work to a wise man respected by the Church.
Finally, the dissertator mentions on page 168 that Berengar, in a letter to Richard, noted in volume 2 of the Dacherian Spicilegium, says John Scotus wrote at the suggestion and request of Charles the Bald, under whose command many believe Ratramnus also wrote in 855, the same year the Annals of St.
Bertin reported many things counter to the Catholic faith in Charles's kingdom, with his knowledge.
These matters are easy to address.
Since there's a big difference between requests and commands, there must also be a significant difference between the work of John Scotus and that of Ratramnus; for John Scotus wrote at the suggestion and request of Charles, while Ratramnus wrote by command.
Ratramnus's book begins with the words: "You commanded, glorious prince," and from Berengar’s letter, we understand that John Scotus wrote at the suggestion and request.
Ratramnus, a humble monk secluded in his cloister, follows the orders of the emperor and king, stepping into the light.
John Scotus, buoyed by his scholarly pride, responds to the prince's warnings and requests.
The heresies that unsettled the state in 855, as noted in the Annals of Saint Bertin, could not have originated from Ratramnus's book.
Although dedicated to Emperor Charles the Bald, the book was intended for Emperor Charlemagne.
It couldn't have been completed and published before the period between 875 and 877, when Charles the Bald's reign ended, as this title is taken from ancient manuscripts addressed to Charles the Bald.
However, the commentator on the same page repeatedly mentions that the book on the Body and Blood of the Lord was condemned at the councils of Vercelli and Paris in 1050, and later burned at the council in Rome under Pope Nicholas the Second in 1059, with John Scotus's name attached, because by then the true author had been identified and recognized.
This is why very few copies exist under the name Ratramnus or Bertram, since during those councils, the assumed name was acknowledged.
He adds that for this reason, it wasn't seen under Ratramnus's name before 1526, up to which point there had been complete silence about this book.
Now, if this is the case, let the commentator explain how it happened that so many councils and distinguished figures like Lanfranc, Ascelin, and Durandus failed to notice this pseudonym.
They neither objected to the insolent usurpation of the name by John Scotus nor defended the memory of Ratramnus, a learned and pious man, well-deserving of the Gallican Church in countless ways, from such heretical disgrace and insult.
I must admit, I don't quite understand how the lecturer concluded that copies of the book "On the Body and Blood of the Lord," which weren't seen before 1525 under the name Bertram or Ratramnus, were burned.
Sigebert, in the twelfth century, specifically forty years after the Roman council, lists the book "On the Body and Blood of the Lord" under the name Ratramnus among Catholic and orthodox writings. Trithemius, the abbot of Spanheim, in the fifteenth century, does the same in the "Catalog of Ecclesiastical Writers," and repeats Sigebert's findings. Previously, the Anonymous of Cellot, or as the lecturer believes, Eriger, pointed to Ratramnus as the author of this book. Even John Fisher, Bishop of Rochester, mentioned it in 1526.
So, nothing could be further from the truth than the lecturer's claim that there was complete silence about this book under Ratramnus's name until 1526. If anyone reads John Scotus's books on Predestination or "On the Division of Natures" carefully, they'll notice such a difference in style and so many Greek mystical and ascetic Fathers cited—whose traces can't be found in Ratramnus's books—that attributing "On the Body and Blood of the Lord" to John Scotus seems presumptuous and unnecessary.
However, I must mention one decisive point in this dispute. It's known that John Scotus believed that Christ's body after the resurrection was neither tangible nor fleshly, as explained in book five of "On the Division of Nature," page 293, number 37: Whoever examines the statements of Saint Ambrose and Gregory the Theologian will find not a transformation of the earthly body into a heavenly body, but a complete transition into the spirit itself—not into what we call ether, but into what we call intellect.
Ambrose indeed removes all composition, suggesting that after the resurrection, body, soul, and intellect become one simple entity, rather than being three separate parts.
What seems like three here becomes one intellect there.
Similarly, Gregory confidently asserts that at the time of resurrection, the body transforms into the soul, the soul into the intellect, and the intellect into God.
Thus, God will be all in all, much like air turns into light.
In the same book, number 38: If the flesh of Christ is transformed into the power of God and the incorruption of the spirit, then surely that flesh itself is power and incorruptible spirit.
And if the spirit is the power of God, it exists everywhere, not only above places and times but also above everything that exists.
There's no doubt that the flesh, transformed into power and spirit, is contained nowhere and is unchanged by time.
Like the power and spirit of God, namely the Word, it surpasses all places and times, going beyond all boundaries.
Now indeed, who would attribute such opinions to the author of the book on the Body and Blood of the Lord?
This author teaches ideas that are entirely contrary and opposed, especially in number 30, where these words are introduced from the mouth of Christ: When after the resurrection you will see me ascending to the heavens, with the fullness of my whole body and blood.
And in number 99: Truly, the body in which Christ suffered and rose is his own body, taken from the body of the Virgin Mary, tangible and visible even after the resurrection, as he himself said to the disciples: Touch and see, for a spirit does not have flesh and bones as you see I have.
Therefore, there's no need to dwell further on these matters.
It's helpful to proceed calmly and gently to defend and uphold the faith and orthodoxy of this book.
However, the dissertator says on page 166 and 288 of this book, in the inner column of the new edition of Amsterdam, number.
.
I am really surprised that, even now, some people support the work attributed to Ratramnus, especially after it was recently criticized by the censors of the Council of Trent and the highest popes.
If the speaker is amazed that certain theologians accepted the book by
Ratramnus on the Body and Blood of the Lord, despite it being censured and placed on the index of prohibited books by the examiners of the Council of Trent and the Roman pontiffs, then they will be even more intrigued by the ancient Latin Mass that
Matthias Flacius Illyricus had printed in Strasbourg in the past century.
Indeed, this Mass, much like the book by
Ratramnus, first emerged with the help of a heretic and was similarly placed on the index of prohibited books by the Council of Trent's examiners, as noted in the second appendix of the index.
However, today this Mass by Illyricus is regarded as Catholic and orthodox by all learned Church writers and is rejected by Protestants for strongly opposing their doctrines.
Its credibility and orthodoxy were defended by the eminent Cardinal Bona in his book on Liturgical Matters, Book 1, Chapter 12, and a new edition was included in the Appendix to that book.
P.
Cointius, a priest of the Oratory of Jesus, ensured a more accurate and refined version in the Ecclesiastical Annals of the Franks, just as we produced a more precise version of
Ratramnus's book on the Body and Blood of the Lord from an ancient manuscript with care and faith.
This same Latin Mass was censured by the Spanish inquisitors during the reign of Philip II, prompted by
Fernando Álvarez de Toledo, Duke of Alba, a man known for his fervent and zealous commitment to the Catholic faith, whom the Jesuit
Famianus Strada described as being propelled from the cannons of war in Antwerp and returned to the same war cannons.
Indeed, it is not surprising if the judgments and condemnations by such tribunals, which were not granted infallibility from heaven, require assistance and defenders.
Among the works of the distinguished Claude Espence, a theology doctor from Paris who might have become a cardinal if not for some misguided decisions, as noted by Jacques-Auguste de Thou and Espence himself, his commentaries on the Epistle to Titus and his treatise on Continence stand out.
These writings are not only rich in erudition but are also crafted with wisdom and courage, challenging the widespread abuses and vices of the time.
Unfortunately, the works of such a great man were included in the index of examined works by the Council of Trent, alongside Ratramnus and the Latin Mass of Illyricus, though they deserve high esteem among scholars.
There's no doubt that our speaker would consider Espence among the Catholic doctors fully approved in matters of doctrine and faith.
I would be curious to ask the speaker if he believes the articles of the Gallican clergy on ecclesiastical power, presented to the most Christian king in 1682 and condemned by Pope Innocent the Eleventh, could be defended.
Would he be upset or indifferent to the criticism directed at the censures by the Faculty of Paris against Vernant or Amadeus Guymen, and would he admire someone who defends such censures?
It's well known that these were not only placed in the index of prohibited books but were also banned and proscribed by Pope Alexander the Seventh, with an official bull issued in Rome, imposing excommunication to be incurred immediately on June 25, 1665, in the eleventh year of his papacy.
No author's works have faced more censure than those of Origen Adamantius; repeatedly, popes and even general councils have proscribed Origen's teachings.
Nevertheless, the Jesuit Petrus Halloix of Liège, with not-so-humble intent, defended Origen in a large folio volume, as thick as larger books, and made his case to the Supreme Pontiff Innocent the Tenth.
The defense of Origen was approved by four notable Jesuits, known for their piety and knowledge.
They reviewed it under the orders of Reverend Father Carafa, the general prefect of the entire society, at the Roman College in 1646.
This defense of Origen was then made publicly available with the permission of the visitor of the provinces of Flanders, England, and French-Belgium in Liège in 1648.
However, Origen, once defended, entered the path of universal inquiry in Rome and earned a prominent place in the index of prohibited books, although it was more honored in Jesuit libraries, as it is nowhere found in the list of prohibited books.
Moreover, the famous book by Jesuit Luis de Molina on the Concord of Grace and Free Will, condemned by the University of Salamanca on July 22, 1595, and declared dangerous and erroneous by the bishops of Spain, is defended daily by Jesuits and several theologians of considerable note.
Just as the books on the Roman Pontiff by Cardinal Bellarmine are, as reported by James Fuligati, another Jesuit, in the Life of Robert Bellarmine, chapter eleven.
Given this, there's no doubt that books marked with censure and judged matters are subject to review and can be referred to a renewed judgment.
Thus, causes that have fallen into decay can be restored to the status of judicial procedure.
This is of no concern to the Church or religion: it has always been permissible and will always be permissible to defend some authors from the accusation of violated faith.
Indeed, nothing prevents the letters of Pope Honorius the First from being cleared of the reproach of the Monothelite heresy.
With this right, Facundus, the Bishop of Hermiane in Africa, strongly and vigorously defended the three chapters in favor of Ibas of Edessa, Theodore of Mopsuestia, and Theodoret, Bishop of Cyrus, by which we also receive the doctrine of Ratramnus as worthy of defense.
Molina and Bellarmine, once placed in the indices of prohibited books, easily obtained their removal from them.
If we bolster our arguments to counter the slander tarnishing his reputation and name with credible and convincing evidence,
it's more surprising to encounter judges unjust to Ratramnus than to find advocates in his favor.
It will soon be noted that he was condemned and committed to the fire by plenary synods and the entire Church long ago.
Recently, in the previous era, the most illustrious and learned bishops, Sanctesius of Evreux and Cardinal Perronius, Archbishop of Sens, found him to be openly teaching heresy.
Indeed, we acknowledge that the book titled "On the Body and Blood of the Lord" was condemned at the Council of Vercelli under Pope Leo the Ninth and burned in Rome under Pope Nicholas the Second in the year 1055.
However, we completely deny that Ratramnus or Paschasius authored this book.
It's well known that this book was presented under the name of John Scotus, without objection, and under that name, it was used by the followers of Berengar to support their errors.
Furthermore, Cardinal Perron and Sanctesius followed the common opinion of the writers of their time, who, influenced by the Protestant rhetoric, rashly convinced themselves that this book favored Calvinist errors.
Nevertheless, these points do not hinder the rightful defense and support of the book.
The writer himself views the letter of Saint John Chrysostom to the monk Caesarius as worthy of defense, while Cardinal Perron considers it a forgery by Peter Martyr Vermigli, a Florentine heretic, to favor Calvinism.
Just as Perron and Sixtus of Siena believed the book of Ratramnus was a fiction by Oecolampadius. This is evident from Perron's treatise on the Eucharist, pages 381 to 383, and the Library of Sixtus of Siena.
Additionally, it's important to note that the writer differs from the defenders of Ratramnus as he was the first in the Christian world to defend the doctrine of this letter to the monk Caesarius.
Among all the scholars who suspected it of being illegitimate, he claims authenticity for Saint John Chrysostom, stating it in Latin, not Greek, and assigns it to him despite significant opposition.
On the other hand, several church writers, well-respected for their knowledge and piety, have supported the orthodoxy of Ratramnus's book "On the Body and Blood of the Lord" both before and after Cardinal Perron.
These include John Fisher, the most illustrious martyr of Christ, and Sigebert, abbot of Gembloux in the twelfth century.
Trithemius Spanhemiensis 15; the doctors of Louvain after the Council of Trent; Jacobus Gretzerus; Antonius Possevinus; Gilbertus Mauguinus; Godefridus Hermannus, a doctor and fellow of the Sorbonne under the name Hieronymus from Angelo Fortis; Jacobus Samboevius, royal professor of sacred theology at the Sorbonne; Dom Joannes Mabillon, the very learned Benedictine monk, and countless other Parisian theologians who, in their theses, provided strong support for the innocence and integrity of Ratramnus before and after the Latin-French edition with the preface and notes that we arranged in the year 1686.
Among them, I must honorably mention the distinguished Peter Berthe, a fellow of the Sorbonne.
He was already a highly skilled librarian of our Sorbonne and the esteemed rector of the University of Paris.
In that thesis, which our elders called the lesser ordinary, dedicated and inscribed in the name of Louis the Great of the University of Paris; presided over and signed by the most illustrious and reverend Franciscus de Harlay, Archbishop of Paris, commander of the royal orders, supervisor of the Sorbonne, director and superior of the Royal College of Navarre, on the 20th of September, in the year 1685, these words are written in column 6:
Hence, neither Anastasius the Sinaite nor Damascenus among the Greeks, nor Paschasius, or his direct opponent, in his existing work, Ratramnus among the Latins, altered anything.
They defended their faith strongly and maintained it completely untarnished.
So, what remains except that I compare the disputant with himself, and either adapt or restrain his admiration.
Indeed, since he considers it necessary to readily obey the authority of Cardinal Perron regarding the book of Ratramnus, he vehemently opposes and contradicts him concerning the heresy of the Stercoranists, and fully embraces our view on the fabrication of this heresy, setting aside the reputation and eminence of Perron, on page 171 of his dissertation.
What we've discussed so far concerns Ratramnus and the author of the book On the Body and Blood of the Lord in general terms.
Now, it's our responsibility to examine the teachings of this book, clear it of any suspicion of heresy, and defend it from any criticism.
Ratramnus, as noted by the writer on page 174 of the first edition, line 8, indicates both in the preface and at the end of his book that he is sharing not what the Church teaches, but what he personally believes.
When the emperor requested his opinion on the body and blood of the Lord in the Eucharist, he clearly stated that he didn't want to assert anything from his own perspective, but rather, he wished to follow the teachings of the holy Fathers.
He remained true to the paths laid out by the ancients or elders, as described in paragraph five, which require neither commentary nor further explanation.
I will try to express my thoughts on this matter, not by relying on my own skills, but by following in the footsteps of the Fathers.
And in paragraph one hundred and two, at the end:
In my desire to follow your greatness's command, I, though humble, have taken the liberty to discuss significant matters, not out of my own presumption, but guided by the authority of the elders.
In paragraph thirty, Ratramnus acknowledges that he opposed many, which the writer argues indicates he was disputing against the Church's doctrine.
Ratramnus may acknowledge this, but a group of opponents emerged, defending the idea that there's no symbolism, and everything is openly revealed in the Eucharist.
This opinion is completely erroneous, opposing both Paschasius and Ratramnus equally, and contradicting all the ancient Church teachers.
This is abundantly clear from these words in section 32:
Here arises the question many propose, speaking not in a figure, but in truth, that is, openly.
Those who say this are proven to contradict the writings of the holy Fathers.
But what then?
Doesn't Paschasius confess that he has many adversaries, just like Ratramnus?
We gather this from these words of the letter to Frudgard on page one thousand six hundred twenty-five:
However, I have stirred many towards understanding this mystery; and at the beginning of this letter, page one thousand six hundred nineteen:
For you ask about a matter concerning which many doubt.
In the same letter, Paschasius agrees with Ratramnus in clear terms, specifically on page one thousand six hundred twenty, letter E, where he seems to have copied a text from Ratramnus from this section 32:
And therefore if anyone says that this flesh and this blood are without mystery and sacrament, not to be taken in part as a figure, as those then carnally wise, he destroys everything.
Thus, it's difficult to understand what is beneficial for the writer from this section 52, to demonstrate that Ratramnus is an adversary of the Catholic Church.
For this reason, the writer continues in a connected discourse, page one hundred seventy-five:
Therefore, he says about Ratramnus, section 8, he distinguishes a figure from reality to the extent that in a figure something else is understood than is said.
Therefore, neither is Christ the vine nor the apostles the branches, although they have that name in sacred writings.
And when Christ is said to be born or to have suffered, he is understood to have truly suffered and truly been born.
This, he says, is the truth in narration, that is, the bare and open meaning of the words.
The text claims that what is on the altar is truly the body of Christ.
However, it specifies that this is only in the symbolic figure of a mystery.
It argues against the idea that the phrase "body of Christ" has a straightforward meaning.
Additionally, it rejects the interpretation of it as simply the visible body being represented.
There's no need for such a lengthy explanation, nor is it necessary to delve deeply to understand what Ratramnus means by figure and truth.
He explains his thoughts clearly in numbers seven and eight:
A figure, he says, is like a shadow showing something through certain coverings; for instance, when we want to express something, we might call it bread, just as in the Lord's Prayer we ask for our daily bread.
Truth, on the other hand, is the clear demonstration of something, not hidden by any images of darkness, but indicated by pure and open meanings, such as when we say Christ was born of a Virgin, suffered, was crucified, died, and was buried.
So, as he mentions in number thirty-two and elsewhere, some need to believe that the body of Christ is in the Eucharist, not in figure, but in truth.
These are the ones who believed there was no shadow, no veil, no figure in the Eucharist, but that everything was open and clear.
The question Ratramnus was addressing wasn't whether the body of Christ truly or really existed in the Eucharist, or only figuratively; this dogma was unquestioned by anyone.
Instead, it was asked whether it was manifest and clearly visible to the eyes, divided without a veil, without a trope, without a figure, without shadow, or whether it was hidden and concealed, existing as the true body under shadows or figures.
We understand that Charles the Bald posed this question to Ratramnus for examination from number five:
What your greatness asks is whether the body and blood of Christ, received by the faithful in the Church, is done in mystery or in truth, meaning whether it contains something secret revealed only to the eyes of faith and whether this view of the body outwardly, which the mind’s vision sees inwardly, should be clear in the light of manifestation.
So, when Ratramnus consistently denies that Christ's body is truly in the Eucharist, he isn't denying the real presence, but rather the visible presence that appeals to our senses.
This is a clear and transparent presence, not hidden by any coverings, veils, or figures.
In this regard, he aligns with the thoughts and opinions of Saint Paschasius.
Indeed, as Ratramnus states in number 49:
According to the invisible substance, that is, the divine power of the Word, the body and blood of Christ truly exist.
In number 77, he writes:
Therefore, what appears externally is not the thing itself but the image of the thing; in the mind, what is felt and understood is the truth of the thing.
Number 15 reads:
It is not right to deny that the body is Christ's, not only to say it but also to think it.
And in number 30:
Then you will understand that, not as the unbelievers think, my flesh is to be eaten by believers, but truly through the mystery, bread and wine are transformed into the substance of my body and blood, to be taken by believers.
Thus, Paschasius teaches in this sacrament that both the figure and the truth remain in almost the same words in the book "On the Body and Blood of the Lord," chapter 4, page 1564:
Therefore, the truth is when the body of Christ is made by the power of the Spirit in his word from the substance of bread and wine.
The figure is when the priest, performing something externally for the remembrance of the sacred passion, daily sacrifices the Lamb at the altar, which was done once.
But if we truly look, it is rightly called both truth and figure: so that what is externally perceived is the figure or character of the truth; the truth, however, is whatever about this mystery is rightly understood or believed internally.
Therefore, Paschasius and Ratramnus did not hold different or opposing views, nor did they argue with each other. Even though Paschasius believed there was some figure in the Eucharist, he was still Catholic. Indeed, it's not doubtful that Ratramnus was as well; for he never stated that Christ's body was only a figure in the Eucharist, as has been attributed to him.
One hundred seventy-five; this term was solely invented by the scholar, and it does not appear in the detailed and scholarly sections written by Ratramnus.
Therefore, he denies that it can truly be said that what you see on the altar of God is the actual body of Christ, born of the Virgin; a point he explicitly refutes in numbers fifty, fifty-nine, and one hundred one.
According to Ratramnus in paragraph 16, even if the Eucharist consists of a single substance, it doesn't mean there are two different existing things.
However, it's important to note that the body of Christ in the Eucharist cannot be seen or perceived by sight.
This is acknowledged by Paschasius and all Catholics.
So, even if Ratramnus were to deny that the body of Christ can be seen in the Eucharist, he wouldn't face any criticism.
Indeed, what we see in the Eucharist is visible, but the true body of Christ, which is genuinely present under these visible forms, is not itself visible.
Therefore, what is visible in the Eucharist isn't the body of Christ but rather a veil, shadow, or figure that conceals and hides it.
It's well understood that the body of Christ in the sacrament goes beyond the perception of the senses and eyes because it is a spiritual and entirely spiritual body, as Paschasius states.
Only the dimensions, whiteness, taste, and smell are perceived by the senses, unless we consider the views of some recent philosophers.
R.
Father Magnan of the Order of Minims of Saint Francis of Paola has elaborated extensively on this topic.
He believed that God, through the action He provided to the bread before consecration, creates the same effect on the eyes after consecration as the bread and wine did before.
The renowned Cartesian philosopher D.
Rohault, in a book written in the vernacular, explains that since the body of Christ occupies the entire space the bread did, surrounded by the same surface or boundary, it must affect the eyes in exactly the same way as the bread before consecration.
If things were as they seem, undoubtedly, the whiteness and roundness we see would be the body of Christ appearing before our eyes.
However, the speaker seems to have a different view, possibly preferring some scholarly subtlety.
He believes that the true body of Christ is hidden and concealed in the sacrament; it is the very substance of Christ's body, just as what appears is the body itself of Christ.
Yet, it is easy to say that the substance of Christ's body is indeed present in the Eucharist, but it does not become visible to our eyes and senses.
In a miraculous way that surpasses nature's powers, it remains hidden and cannot be perceived by the senses.
Moreover, it needs to be examined why Ratramnus explicitly denied in passages fifty, fifty-two, and one hundred one that the body on the altar is the same body born of the Virgin.
I completely deny that Ratramnus ever denied in these passages that the body hidden in the Eucharist is the body born of the Virgin, suffered, and was buried.
However, we must clearly acknowledge the significant difference, considering the distinct nature between the body celebrated in the Church through the mystery, and the actual body with its physical properties that was born of the Virgin Mary, crucified, buried, miraculously resurrected, and ascended into heaven.
This understanding is not difficult to grasp from passage eighty-eight, where he states: Therefore, the body and blood celebrated in the Church differ from that body and blood recognized as glorified in Christ’s body; this body is a pledge and appearance, while that is the truth itself.
In passage eighty-nine: We see, therefore, that the mystery of Christ's body and blood, now consumed by the faithful in the Church, is separated by many differences from that which was born of Mary the Virgin, which suffered, was buried, resurrected, ascended into heaven, and sits at the right hand of the Father.
It's been clearly shown that the bread referred to as the body of Christ and the cup called the blood of Christ are symbolic, as they represent a mystery.
There's a significant distinction between the body present through the mystery and the body that suffered, was buried, and rose again.
The writer should have included excerpts from Ratramnus's writings with some logical reasoning.
This way, they could have demonstrated, without violating dialectical reasoning, that Ratramnus did not believe the body celebrated in the Church is the same as the one formed in the womb of the Virgin, crucified, and later resurrected.
Therefore, it's beneficial for us to introduce this idea to the writer and to help them understand the difference of the same body.
This is while maintaining the true presence of the body and blood of Christ in the Eucharist of the Catholic Church as complete and inviolate.
There's no reason to doubt that Lanfranc, Archbishop of Canterbury, was a strong opponent of Berengar.
It was through Berengar's actions that he was led to renounce his errors and burn his books in front of Pope Nicholas the Second in 1059.
Lanfranc was a true and great defender of the Catholic faith, so much so that he was beyond any suspicion.
Yet, in the Dialogue against Berengar about the Eucharist, he states:
It can truly be said to be the same body taken from the Virgin, yet not the same in terms of essence and the true nature's properties and power, but not if you consider the appearance of bread and wine.
If such words were found in Ratramnus, they would provoke the writer to break arguments.
It's enough for Ratramnus to have introduced some distinction between body and body; he never said it wasn't the same body taken from Mary.
However, the blessed Algerus, a distinguished defender of the faith against Berengar, seems to speak even more in line with Ratramnus's thinking in Book One on the Eucharist, chapter.
The blood and flesh of Christ, he explains, can be understood in two ways: either as the spiritual and divine nature, as he himself said, My flesh is true food, and my blood is true drink, or as the flesh that was crucified and the blood that was shed by the soldier's spear.
This is not about his dual substance but rather the dual form of his substance, which is now seen in the form of bread and wine.
A bit further in the same chapter: The appearances and likenesses of those things are the names used before, namely bread and wine, not the body of Christ.
The body and blood of Christ are referred to by name in the way we often name the sign by the thing it signifies.
And in chapter 18: Regarding the sacrament of bread and wine, which signifies and is nominally the body of Christ, it was mentioned earlier.
But the true body of Christ, invisible after the resurrection, is the sacrament of the visible body of Christ in his passion, as Augustine testifies in the book Sentences: His flesh is what we receive in the sacrament, covered by the form of bread, and his blood is what we drink under the appearance and taste of wine, the sacrament of flesh of flesh and blood of blood.
Therefore, it does not follow that Ratramnus was not convinced that the body taken from the Virgin is absent in the Eucharist, even though he distinguishes between the body taken from Mary and that which is celebrated in the Church; for he clearly teaches that the substance of bread and wine is transformed into the body and blood of Christ.
It is wrong not only to deny but even to think that it is not the body of Christ; and he states that it is named and exists, as we showed earlier.
The same ideas are found in Yvo of Chartres in a letter to Finarus, and previously in Rabanus Maurus in a letter to Heribaldus of Auxerre, which the learned Baluzius made public, strongly defending it from any suspicion of heresy or error.
Father Christian Lupus of the Order of Saint Augustine was a professor of sacred Theology at the University of Leuven.
In a dissertation, he explained certain testimonies of the Holy Fathers related to the heresy of Berengar.
This work is found in volume five of his notes on the Councils, page three hundred and seventeen, printed in Brussels in the year of Christ sixteen seventy-two.
Verse number ten:
The dissertator states, "It is clear that the bread and wine figuratively become the body and blood of Christ."
Who can doubt that, in certain ways of speaking and writing, bread and wine symbolically represent the body and blood of Christ?
Paschasius, Lanfranc, Guitmond, and both ancient and modern Catholic scholars freely acknowledge this, as long as it is understood that the true body of Christ is genuinely present within and beneath these symbols.
Ratramnus clearly explains this in section nine:
Outwardly, the bread maintains its original form, its color is visible, and its taste is detected:
but inwardly, something far more profound, much more precious, and exceedingly excellent is signified.
And in section ten:
The wine, consecrated by the priest to become the blood of Christ, outwardly appears as one sacrament but contains something entirely different within.
In section nineteen, on page two ninety-one of the Amsterdam edition, line eighteen, in the outer column, the writer states:
They are not the same as they are believed to be.
While this sentence might have a reasonable interpretation on its own, when expressed with the intent to contradict the Catholic assertion that "What is seen on the altar is the body of Christ," it becomes a dangerous heresy.
Where did the writer get the idea, and from which words of Ratramnus did he understand that Ratramnus wrote with the intention that what is seen and what is believed are not the same, opposing this Catholic statement: What is seen on the altar is the body of Christ?
Ratramnus means nothing other than that the body of Christ, which truly lies hidden under these appearances and exists on the altar, does not come into view or is not visible to the sense of sight.
This is plainly acknowledged by all theologians and indeed by all people who are not impaired in mind or sight, except for some recent philosophers.
But this matter can be easily settled with an example.
For instance, if instead of saying "are not the same as what is seen and what is believed," Ratramnus had said "are not the same as what is corrupted and what is believed," or "are not the same as what is cast aside and what is believed," or "are not the same as what is broken and what is believed," the writer would not dare object to these propositions.
Even if they could have an understandable meaning when considered precisely and alone, if they were proposed with the intention to oppose these Catholic statements: What is broken on the altar is the body of Christ; what is cast aside is the body of Christ.
What is corrupted on the altar is a deadly heresy because the body of Christ cannot be corrupted, cast aside, or broken.
But indeed, Ratramnus means nothing other than that the body of Christ, which is truly believed to be in the Eucharist, is not seen.
Like the appearances that are broken, corrupted, and cast aside, are not the same as the body of Christ, which is believed to lie hidden and exist under these appearances.
From this, it's clear how unnecessary it is to complicate things with so many clouds of subtleties and ambiguities to establish this Catholic proposition:
What appears on the altar is the body of Christ, and anything contrary is clearly heretical.
Essentially, this proposition means that what is broken on the altar is the body of Christ.
In this context, the word "this" does not refer to the proper and natural body of Christ hidden under appearances, but to a nominal body, as Blessed Algerus describes.
It's a body in figure that conceals its true and natural self, which has become invisible to our eyes.
Moreover, section 15 clearly teaches that it is not truly the same thing according to its proper essence.
This thinker's idea couldn't be more wrong; these words don't mean that something doesn't truly exist in its essence.
Instead, it's important to recognize that the change in the Eucharist isn't in what's outwardly visible, but in what's hidden and not perceived by our external senses.
Ratramnus argues that there's a difference between what we see and what we believe, suggesting that something different exists internally than what's visibly apparent.
He asserts that the change pertains to something other than the body, meaning it's not what truly appears, but something else that isn't perceived according to its own essence.
From this, we understand that Ratramnus didn't reject transubstantiation.
He concludes that those who refuse to acknowledge the change in the Eucharist, which doesn't affect outward appearances, are forced to deny that the body of Christ exists in the sacrament.
This is something that cannot be said or thought without blame.
If they refuse to admit it, they are compelled to deny that the body is the blood of Christ, which is wrong not only to say but even to think.
I gladly confess that I have never understood anything more fitting to the Catholic faith than the necessity of acknowledging the change in the sacrament of the Eucharist, which doesn't appeal to human senses, or denying that the body of Christ truly exists in this sacrament, which is wrong not only to say but even to think.
Thus, in number 18, he contrasts the mystery with the property, meaning the true essence of things.
Therefore, when he denies that the body of Christ is truly present on the Lord's table, he denies that it exists in its own essence.
It doesn't oppose the nature of the mystery at that point.
In fact, it shows and confirms that these are compatible with the example of baptism.
In baptism, water, while keeping its natural properties, inwardly conceals the power of holiness and immortality.
This argument indeed proves that the Eucharistic elements, while maintaining their natural properties like coverings and dishes, conceal the holy and immortal body of Christ.
Therefore, as Ratramnus says, in its corruptible nature, there is the property of moisture, but in the mystery, there is the saving power.
The debater drew an unnecessary conclusion from that point.
When he denies, he says, therefore the body of Christ exists on the Lord's table in truth, he denies that it exists in its own essence.
Because he understands by truth the manifestation of the thing alone or its external revelation, which eliminates all association with a figure or shadow, but not the proper essence of things, which does not reject the association of figures.
That being the case, even if I were to concede, though I would never agree, that Ratramnus denies the Body of Christ is in the Eucharist in truth, he would deny nothing other than that the said body is not palpable or entirely without any figure and shadow.
It's unthinkable to say he wanted to claim the body does not exist, about which he says in paragraph ninety-six, in clear words, that the body of Christ is named and exists.
He admits that an internal change occurs which the external senses do not perceive, and the existence of the body in the Eucharist cannot be denied without great offense.
Page of the Amsterdam edition two hundred ninety-one; of the first Parisian edition page one hundred seventy-five.
Every sensible person will understand that this single interpretation of the expression "in truth" pleased John Scotus, that is, Ratramnus, and indeed all Catholics.
They remember that Berengar was condemned for similarly asserting that everything occurs in a figure and in the sacrament but nothing in truth.
Especially since John Scotus was almost Berengar's adopted and favored student.
To illustrate this point, the writer shared a piece by Walter, the prior of Saint Victor,
which can be found in volume three of the Sacred Analects by the esteemed scholar Mabillon, on page 450.
Berengarius was rightly and wisely condemned because he understood the phrase IN TRUTH to mean the actual nature or essence of the thing itself.
He believed that in the sacrament, everything was symbolic, with nothing being in the reality and essence of the body of Christ.
However, it's absurd to consider Berengarius as an interpreter of Ratramnus, who had died two hundred years earlier.
Ratramnus himself clearly indicates that by the phrase IN TRUTH, he means the external manifestation of the thing, essentially a revelation, empty of and completely opposed to all figures and shadows.
As we have proven earlier, from number five.
Ratramnus then states that the substance of the wine is seen, according to number ten, as the author notes on page one hundred seventy-six of the first edition published in Paris by Claudius Muguet in 1699.
Or on page two hundred ninety-one, number one hundred seventy-six, section eleven, of the Amsterdam edition of 1709, by de Lorme.
At a time when Catholics openly professed that the substance of bread is converted into the substance of the body of Christ, as Haymo of Halberstadt mentioned earlier on page ninety-nine.
They said what we see on the altar is not the substance of bread, but the body itself, born of the Virgin.
Ratramnus does not claim that the substance of wine is visible.
If he only stated this, it might suggest a change in the wine's substance after consecration.
Instead, he clarifies that nothing else is visible except the substance of wine: What else is seen on the surface but the substance of wine?
He explains that through consecration, the wine becomes the sacrament of Christ's blood, displaying one thing outwardly while containing something else inwardly.
The sacrament of Christ's blood, created through priestly consecration, shows one thing on the surface and contains something else inside.
To clarify that he refers to more than just the wine's substance and outward appearance, he uses precise language to say that what appears is the form of bread that was there before (and thus is no longer).
The color is seen, the taste is perceived, but inside there is something much more precious and excellent because it is divine.
He emphasizes that it is not merely a sanctifying power, but the very body of the Lord Christ, which cannot be perceived by sight, taste, or any sense, but is seen and consumed by the faithful mind.
Outwardly, he states, it appears as bread as it did before (therefore, after consecration, it is no longer the same).
The form is shown, the color is apparent, the taste is accepted, but inwardly something far more precious and much more excellent is indicated because it is heavenly, because it is divine, meaning the body of Christ.
This is revealed not to the senses of the flesh, but to the gaze or consumption of the faithful soul.
These ideas are supported by what is mentioned in section 30: But truly through the mystery, bread and wine are transformed into the substance of my body and blood for believers to receive.
I truly do not know how else the faith and persuasion of the Church can be expressed unless it is clearly understood from these words.
Furthermore, Haymo of Halberstadt clarifies that what we believe on the altar is the body itself born of the Virgin, not what we see on the altar.
It was understood that what we see is visible, unlike the true body of Christ, which is hidden in the Eucharist.
Haymo clearly explains this in volume twelve of the Dacherian Collection:
The invisible priest transforms his visible creations into the substance of his flesh through secret power.
In this body and blood of Christ, due to the reluctance of the recipients, the taste of bread and wine remains, and the appearance is transformed into the substance, nature into the body and blood of Christ: yet, the sense of the flesh suggests one thing, while the faith of the mind suggests another.
Furthermore, these ideas align with what Anastasius Sinaita states in book twelve of the Anagogical Contemplations on the Hexameron:
"He does not speak about his visible flesh and blood";
and before him, Saint Dionysius in chapter three of the Hierarchy, page two hundred eighty-six, whom we reference in the preface:
"But, most divine and sacred ceremony, having revealed to us the symbolic coverings of enigmas placed around you, manifest to us clearly, and fill our mental visions with a unified and unveiled light."
But you, most divine sacrament, revealing the symbolic coverings of enigmas around you, manifest clearly to us, and fulfill our minds with unique and open light.
Eleven. (page two hundred ninety-one, section three, under number one hundred seventy-six, Amsterdam edition, seventeen hundred nine.)
However, to prove no change of substance is made, in number twelve, he calls upon the judgment of the eyes and senses, saying the appearance of the creature remains; and in number fourteen, that the appearance and form have not changed in themselves, meaning their proper essence: or, if preferred, the external form, which that nation believed to be inseparable from the substance.
I wish the writer hadn't omitted any of Ratramnus' words.
From section twelve, it's clear that Ratramnus himself established the transformation of the bread's substance into the substance of Christ's body.
He doesn't just say that the appearance of the creature remains.
He states that outwardly, the appearance of the creature, which was there before, remains recognizable.
According to the truth, the outward manifestation—the appearance of the creature, which was there before—is still recognized as remaining.
This aligns perfectly with Catholic teaching: without a doubt, the appearances of the bread and wine, which were there before, remain even after consecration.
Therefore, no change can be seen or recognized by the power and ministry of the senses.
This transition isn't recognized to have happened here either.
As he mentions in section twelve, in this sacrament, if considered in the simplicity of truth (that is, what appears outwardly and is perceived by the senses), and nothing else is believed than what is seen, no change is recognized as having occurred.
He doesn't say "No change is proven or demonstrated," but "no change is recognized," meaning it is perceived by the senses and eyes.
But if something else is believed beyond what is seen by the senses, a change has occurred, as he states in section thirty: "But truly through the mystery, the bread and wine are transformed into the substance of my body and blood, to be taken by believers."
Furthermore, even the words from section fourteen, brought up by the writer, stating that the appearance and form have nothing changed in them, are truncated and distorted.
Because with these, Ratramnus seems to indicate that by appearance, he means the material and substantial form of the bread and wine sustain no change.
Whereas on the contrary, if these words are presented whole and sincerely, they convey the opposite: namely, according to the appearance and form of the creature or visible things outwardly and what falls under the senses, the bread and wine, which were before, have nothing changed in them: which is very true.
Based on the appearance and form of the elements, both the bread and wine haven't changed in themselves.
If there's been no change, they remain just as they were before.
However, with a firm conviction, it's essential to acknowledge that a true internal transformation has occurred, one that's not visible or perceptible to our senses.
Physically, nothing appears to have changed; indeed, it's rightly observed that nothing noticeable to the senses has altered.
Otherwise, one would be forced to deny that it's the body of Christ, which is not only forbidden to say but even to contemplate.
Or if they refuse to profess it, they must deny that it is the body and blood of Christ, which is forbidden not just to say but also to consider.
Blessed Alger, a devout Catholic and strong opponent of Berengar, expressed similar thoughts in his time, as we learn from chapter 17 of the first book on the Sacrament of the Eucharist.
He noted this duality, not of substance but of form, whenever the saints spoke of the body of Christ, saying it was not the same, as it is the same in substance but not in form.
In chapter 18, just as the imaginary sacrifice is figuratively called death, the crucifixion of Christ, the form of bread and wine is also figuratively called the body of Christ.
Similarly, the sacrament of faith, namely baptism, is figuratively referred to as faith.
It's important to note that in one of these parallels, he stated that the heavenly bread, which is truly the flesh of Christ, is uniquely called the body of Christ, because that body is not physical but spiritual and divine above all else.
In the other instance, however, the sacrament of the body of Christ, meaning the form of bread, was completely called the body of Christ in a specific way, as he observed that by the common representation of non-existing things, it's called the body of Christ.
But when he mentioned that the invisible body of Christ is the sacrament of the visible body of Christ, it should be understood intellectually through some external action, not taken literally by the senses.
In what sense did Ratramnus express this, number 56?
Understand that the body and blood of Christ are present not in form, but in power.
This is the stance of Catholics opposing those who claim that what is seen is truly the body of Christ.
According to Catholic teachings, it's important to clarify that the substance of Christ's body is not perceived by the senses; this is clearly false.
Instead, what we see and perceive are the veils and shadows that cover the true body of Christ.
So, the meaning of this statement is: What is seen is the body of Christ, meaning the substance that truly exists invisibly beneath these perceptible veils is the true body of Christ itself.
Therefore, Ratramnus rightly explains that the body and blood of Christ exist not in appearance, but in power.
We truly believe that the body of Christ is present, and because we believe, we do not see.
If we were to see, we would claim we see rather than say we believe it to be the true body and blood of Christ.
Indeed, you faithfully believe in the body and blood of Christ, but if you were to see, you would say, "I see the body and blood of Christ," not "I believe."
From this power with which Christ is endowed in this mystery, it is argued that this power is to be revered, as it allows Him to create whatever He wills, transforming what was not before into what He wishes and when He wishes.
Therefore, it is said that the order of nature should not be considered here; instead, Christ’s power should be revered, which creates what was not and transforms the created into what was not before.
Thirteen. Catholics, as noted by the dissertator on page 291, section 176, of the Amsterdam edition, and on page 176, section 4, of the Parisian edition, did not desire that faith, which lies inwardly in the soul, operates in the mystery.
They claimed that what appeared on God's altar was the body of Christ, that the substance of the creatures remained unchanged, with the appearance preserved as mentioned in chapter four, and that after consecration, they were no longer symbols of what they were before.
Indeed, a transformation occurs internally, but in the symbols beforehand, in the minds of believers. Ratramnus presents these particularly opposing views in this one place, namely, number.
Those who refuse to accept anything beyond the visible and prefer to judge by appearances might ask what kind of change has occurred here.
In terms of substance, these elements remain what they were before consecration.
Bread and wine existed before, and they appear to remain in that form even after being consecrated.
However, through the powerful strength of the Holy Spirit, they are inwardly transformed, which faith perceives, nourishing the soul and providing the essence of eternal life.
From Ratramnus's words, we can't derive five propositions that oppose the writer's original five.
Indeed, the Catholics didn't want anything about faith, which resides within the soul, to be active in the mystery.
Ratramnus asks, "Shouldn't the faith, hidden within the soul, play a role in the mystery?"
He suggests the opposite of the fifth point: an internal change does occur, but not in the symbols until it happens in the souls. Instead, he demonstrates throughout his work that this change is a matter of faith, meant to be transformed beforehand.
In essence, he states in number eleven: "If, according to some, nothing is symbolic and everything is literal, then faith accomplishes nothing here."
This means nothing should be considered faith if nothing is hidden; everything external and internal should be revealed, and one should say "I see" instead of "I believe," as Ratramnus notes in number fifty-four.
If you truly saw, you would say "I see," rather than "I believe the body and blood are of Christ."
What in these words suggests heresy? What appears contrary to the Catholic faith?
What does it mean for the faith hidden internally to act in this mystery, unless it means engaging with the essence of the mystery?
Certainly, faith fulfills its role by contemplating this mystery under the forms of bread and wine, believing and asserting that the true body and blood of Christ are hidden and concealed through the miraculous transformation of the bread and wine's substance, as we see Ratramnus teaching from numbers forty-nine and thirty.
But truly, through the invisible nature, that is, the divine power of the word, the body and blood of Christ exist...
and through the mystery, the bread and wine are transformed into the substance of the body and blood, to be received by the faithful.
In any case, Ratramnus never claimed that the faith hidden internally acts within this mystery; rather, he said faith accomplishes nothing if, according to some, nothing here is symbolic but everything is literal.
What is truly and clearly Catholic is that the Eucharist embodies both a symbol and reality.
It's incorrect to say that it is purely symbolic or not symbolic at all.
Let's explore what Ratramnus means by these words:
For, according to the substance of creatures, what they were before consecration, they remain afterward.
Bread and wine existed before and seem to remain in the same form, but I argue that by the substance of creatures, he does not mean an entity that exists independently, as the Peripatetics speak, but rather the external qualities and attributes of the substance.
These were present before and now are not, yet they appear neither to survive nor remain, as these words signify:
Bread and wine existed before and seem to remain in the same form.
For Ratramnus, the word "form" does not refer to the thing itself but to its appearance, shadow, and likeness, as Horace, Book 2, Satire 2, puts it:
"It is the appearance that leads you, I see."
Moreover, setting aside examples that could prove ancient ecclesiastical writers referred to substance as the attributes and qualities of things, not the things themselves—a sample of which is in the preface to the Latin edition of Ratramnus you have at hand—there's no doubt that Ratramnus meant to signify such affections of the soul, not the soul itself, with these words:
Therefore, what is inwardly transformed by the mighty power of the Holy Spirit, what faith perceives, nourishes the soul, and provides the substance of eternal life.
The substance of eternal life is not the soul itself existing independently, but rather bliss itself, or the complete and perfect possession of unchangeable life.
Romans, Chapter 14, Verse 4, compares the Eucharist with baptism.
Numbers, Chapters 17, 18, and 19, page 292, Amsterdam and Paris edition, page 176, year 1699, mentions that in baptism, there are two aspects: the element that washes outwardly and the power of sanctification or the faith of the one who is washed, which cleanses inwardly.
Therefore, in form or property, there is nothing but water; in mystery or in the believer's understanding, there is healing power.
I openly admit that Ratramnus compares the Eucharist with baptism; but by the Eucharist, he not only means the bread and wine, but also the entire Eucharist itself, specifically the true body and true blood of Christ, under the appearances of bread and wine.
This must be Ratramnus's understanding: since he recognizes a true change of substance, he does not assert two existences, and he considers it a great wrong to think that the body of Christ, which is named and exists, is not there.
Now, if he compares the Eucharist understood in this way with baptism, what false accusation can be made against him?
For just as the power of sanctification is added to the element of water in baptism, much more does the power of immortality and sanctification approach the true body of Christ hidden under the appearances, which administers to us the substance of immortality and eternal life.
Indeed, unless we approach this mystery with faith and love, the hidden flesh of Christ is of no use: it is the spirit that gives life.
Just as water is of no use if it lacks the power of sanctification, that is, unless the adult initiated by the sacred baptism believes and persuades himself that eternal life can be acquired by this power of sanctification.
Therefore, it is not only marvelous that the body of Christ exists in the Eucharist, but that it exists there for our sanctification.
It remains equally in the mouth of the wicked and the good.
But against the wicked, it is food of death, and for the good, it is food of life—life for the good and death for the wicked.
Moreover, such a comparison is neither new nor unusual; it has been used by the strongest defenders of the presence of the body and transubstantiation, as we understand from the letter of Paschasius to Frudgard.
The blessed Algerus also made the same comparison, in chapter 10, book II, and 8, book III, and he considers that what seems to have a physical appearance is understood to have spiritual fruit, just as Ratramnus does in number 19.
What we see nourishes the corruptible body with temporary things, but what we believe nourishes the soul with eternal things, as the soul will live forever.
(Page 292 Amsterdam edition; Paris edition, page 177, line 2).
Let's look at numbers 4 and 19.
In baptism, according to Ratramnus, whether from the old covenant or the new, there are two components: the water, which is visible, and the spiritual power, which is believed internally.
A mystery forms from both when one comprehends what the symbol represents.
He explains that the Eucharist becomes a mystery, much like the cleansing water of salvation, because the mind perceives something different than what the symbol shows.
From this understanding of faith, the mystery is named and realized.
He further extends this understanding to the sacraments of the new law, equating them with those of the old covenant.
He reaffirms this in number 91, comparing old sacrifices with new ones, stating that just as the former represented things to come, this sacrifice symbolizes past events.
Ratramnus doesn't discuss the Eucharist in section twenty-one, nor does he mention the concept of faith as the mystery of the day and its occurrence in the following sections.
Instead, he focuses on the mystery that emerges from the body and blood of Christ, enveloped in the appearances of bread and wine, with the added power of sanctification, to be received worthily by believers as an object of faith.
This principle applies not only to the Eucharist but also to all the sacraments of both the Old and New Testaments.
It's not unique to the Eucharist that the power of sanctification is combined with the bread and wine, as it is also with the water in baptism, but this power is added when it is joined to the true body of Christ, hidden and concealed under these appearances or figures.
There's no doubt that this is Ratramnus's view, as he states in section twenty-four that the blood drunk by the Jewish people in the desert was a symbol of the blood taken from the Virgin's womb and shed on the cross, not only for our redemption but also for us to partake in:
"So that we may understand," he says, "that in the desert, the spiritual rock stood and provided its stream of blood to the people, who later took a body from the Virgin and was hung on the cross for the salvation of believers, presenting to our times, and from it poured out a stream of blood by which we are not only redeemed but also drink."
However things may be, if the blood shed by Christ from the wood of the cross for our redemption is truly the blood taken from the Virgin mother, then that blood given to us and similarly poured out for our drinking must be true and the same by which we are not only redeemed but also partake.
It's easy to confirm and indeed demonstrate Ratramnus's orthodoxy in this section.
If we ask all the ministers of Calvinist superstition whether the blood shed on the cross for our redemption is not the true blood taken from the Virgin Mary, they would undoubtedly affirm that it is indeed true and proper blood.
If the question is raised about the blood shed by Christ for us to drink, some might say it only represents the true blood symbolically, or that it's offered symbolically according to a heretical view.
However, if we asked Ratramnus, he would provide a Catholic perspective.
Christ, standing as a spiritual rock in the desert, provided a stream of his blood to the people, which, taken from the body born of the Virgin and hung on the cross for our salvation, is present today.
From it, he poured out a stream of blood by which we are not only redeemed but also nourished.
According to Ratramnus, just as we are redeemed by the true blood of Christ from the Virgin-born body, we are truly nourished by the same blood.
He would also say that we are redeemed and nourished by the blood symbolized in manna, the Red Sea, and the rock in the desert.
Although now concealed under the appearances of wine and bread, it truly exists there, becoming the focus of our faith and spiritual understanding.
In the remarkable union of truth and symbol, it was also a symbol of the manna, the Red Sea, and the rock in the desert of the past, just as they were symbols of the future.
As he notes in number 91, just as those things symbolized the future, this sacrifice symbolizes the past.
(Page 292, number 177.)
Therefore, Ratramnus in number 30 says, do not think that my flesh or my blood is to be consumed physically or divided among you, since after the resurrection, you will see me ascend to the heavens with my body and blood whole and intact.
Indeed, which Catholic ever thought of Christ's flesh being torn into pieces?
Clearly, no one.
It's quite plausible and likely that Ratramnus's opponents were Catholics.
This is especially true since he refers to them as faithful in section eleven, clearly indicating they were free from any suspicion of heresy.
While some of the faithful claim that the body and blood of Christ, celebrated daily in the Church, are without any figure or revelation, who would believe that some faithful individuals were tainted with heresy?
However, those opponents truly believed that the real body of Christ was seen or perceived in the Eucharist in its true form, not hidden in any figures or shadows of mystery.
These opponents rejected and defended themselves against the offensive notion that they were convinced to believe the body of Christ was corrupted and acted like food due to natural heat and spirit.
They held that, even when soaked with fluids and dissolved in the chest and stomach of the recipients, they did not doubt the true body and blood of Christ.
Abbot Abbaudus, an author of uncertain age, shared the same opinion about the breaking of the body of Christ.
He was followed by Walter, prior of Saint Victor in Paris, whose fragments were published by the very learned Mabillon in the fourth volume of Sacred Analects.
Many Catholic writers, both before and after the age or retraction of Berengar, as Mabillon notes in his comments on Abbaudus's Treatise on the breaking of the body of Christ, also shared this view.
No matter the circumstances, there was no group of people who believed that the flesh of Christ and God could ever be discarded.
Nor had the Christian people forgotten what is reported in Exodus chapter thirty-two, verse twenty.
When Moses, seizing the calf that the Israelites had made, burned and crushed it into powder, scattered it in the water, and made the sons of Israel drink it.
An ancient writer named Peter of Rheims, also known as Peter of Riga, wrote something noteworthy in his poem within the work Aurora.
John Selden confirms this in the Cottonian Library in his work De Diis Syris, Section Two, regarding the golden calf, and I've seen it myself in the library of the metropolitan church chapter of Rheims.
"He crushed it, mixed it with water, and gave it as a drink to the Hebrews so that God might pass through the foul places."
Exodus Seventeen, page 292.
The insightful one wanted to convey that Christ's body is neither seen at the altar, nor eaten, nor broken, and with the body taken up to heaven, it no longer exists here on earth.
If Ratramnus had truly believed that Christ's body didn't remain on earth after ascending into heaven, he wouldn't have written in section ninety-nine: This bread and cup, which is called and exists as the body of Christ.
Nor would he have mentioned in section twenty-four the blood shed on the cross, by which we are not only redeemed but also nourished.
His readers wouldn't have been confused or misled by preconceived ideas about his actual words.
Nor would he have advised in section one hundred one: We shouldn't think, because we say these things, that the faithful don't receive the body or blood of the Lord in the sacrament's mystery, as faith perceives not what the eye sees, but what it believes.
Faith believes that the true body is hidden in the Eucharist, not just a figure, and thus perceives no false or figurative presence.
Nor would he have stated in section ten: The wine, through priestly consecration, becomes the sacrament of Christ's blood, showing one thing outwardly but containing another inwardly.
What else does it contain inwardly besides Christ's blood replacing the wine?
Moreover, why mention in section thirty that through the mystery, the bread and wine are taken by the faithful as the transformed substance of the body and blood, if he had dismissed the Catholic Church's doctrine of transubstantiation?
It shouldn't be confused with the phrase "through the mystery," which signifies the true body and blood of Christ hidden under the appearances of bread and wine.
In truth, Ratramnus means nothing different in that context than what he stated in section twenty-eight, that Christ, before suffering, could transform the substance of bread and wine into his own body and blood.
Section eighteen.
The writer notes, on page one seventy-seven of the Paris edition and two ninety-two of the Amsterdam edition, that it is not present unless it is tangible, which is repeated in section eighty-nine, and concludes in section seventeen that where the body is not seen or evident, it is not present at all.
These ideas are not found anywhere in Ratramnus' writings, nor is it credible that a person of sound mind would be so contradictory.
He consistently states, or implies, that the body of Christ, in which he suffered death, is present in the Eucharist, as we have already demonstrated in many instances, making repetition unnecessary.
In sections 89 and 97, he does not argue that where the body of Christ is not visible to the eyes, it is absent.
He merely points out the distinction between the mystery of the body celebrated in the Church and the actual body of Christ in which he suffered and died.
The difference is that in the mystery, the body is veiled under the forms and not touchable, whereas the body that suffered and was buried is visible and touchable.
Furthermore, he does not claim there are two separate existences; instead, he explicitly teaches that it is not about two different existences, namely body and spirit.
Rather, it is one and the same thing, which in one aspect consists of the appearance of bread and wine; in another, it is the body and blood of Christ.
Number 16.
Nineteen.
Page 292, Amsterdam.
He interprets the Lord's saying, "It is the Spirit who gives life," in number 31 as referring to the spiritual work of believers, that is, faith, which gives life and creates the mystery.
Without this faith and work, the mysteries merely nourish the body and are not even mysteries, but simply the substance of bread and wine.
Ratramnus strongly emphasizes that those who partake in the Eucharist must have faith.
Furthermore, Paschasius and all Catholic believers insist, following Saint Paul's guidance: "Let a man examine himself, and so eat of that bread and drink of that cup.
For whoever eats and drinks unworthily is guilty of the body and blood, not discerning the Lord's body" First Corinthians 11:29.
Ratramnus does not differ in meaning when, in explaining number 31, he states: "It is the Spirit that gives life."
In this mystery of the body and blood, there is a spiritual operation that grants life, without which the mysteries are of no benefit.
Indeed, these mysteries not only fail to benefit but actually cause harm and death if received without faith and charity.
Theologians teach with the intention that the Eucharist is a sacrament of the living, not of the dead.
However, this does not imply that only the spiritual work brings life or completes the mystery.
Ratramnus never expressed it like this in number 31; instead, he taught the opposite by saying: "The flesh profits nothing" as unbelievers understand; otherwise, it provides life, as received by the faithful through the mystery.
And why is this?
He explains it by saying: "It is the Spirit that gives life."
In this mystery of the body and blood, there is a spiritual operation that grants life, without which those mysteries are of no benefit, because they can indeed nourish the body, but they cannot nourish the soul.
Who, then, would understand from this that only the recipient's faith operates the mystery, and not recognize the Christian and Catholic truth, namely, that the flesh and blood of Christ in the Eucharist grant life to the soul, that is, grace, to those who receive this sacrament worthily, to those properly prepared, ready, and suitable, adorned with faith, charity, and the virtue of repentance?
20.
Ratramnus says, as the essayist notes, on page 292 of the Amsterdam edition.
The spiritual action occurs because it's driven by the spirit of faith.
Faith nurtures, brings joy, and gives life to our inner selves, while what is external sustains the body.
This is the clear and pure prayer of the Sacramentarians.
I would like to ask the speaker how he convinces himself that the mystery can occur in any way other than spiritually.
This suggests that the mysteries happen through the act of faith, not by the power of the Holy Spirit, which is what makes the mysteries the objects of our faith.
Paschasius aligns with Ratramnus in chapter five of the book on the Body and Blood of the Lord:
Therefore, Christ is the food of angels, and this sacrament is truly his flesh and blood, which a person eats and drinks spiritually.
Thus, what sustains the angels also sustains humans, because everything a person receives is spiritual and divine.
And at the end of the same chapter:
We also consume the spiritual flesh of Christ spiritually, in which eternal life is believed to exist.
Otherwise, thinking according to the flesh leads to death, but truly perceiving the flesh of Christ spiritually leads to eternal life.
He notes in a continuous discourse, chapter six, that this spiritual flesh of Christ is recognized by the good, but not at all by the bad:
Behold, he says, everyone indiscriminately receives the sacraments of the altar often, but some eat the flesh of Christ spiritually and drink the blood, while others do not; even though it seems they receive it from the priest’s hand.
So, what do they receive, when there is one consecration, if they do not receive the body and blood?
Truly, because they receive unworthily, as the Apostle Paul says: He eats and drinks judgment on himself, not discerning the body of the Lord.
First Corinthians 11:29.
Behold what the sinner eats and drinks.
Certainly not the flesh and blood for his benefit, but judgment.
And why?
Because he does not examine himself, nor does he discern the body of the Lord.
The unbeliever thinks he can partake in what is worthy and holy while being unworthy, noticing nothing beyond what he sees, nor understanding beyond what he feels.
On the same matter, Ratramnus says after Saint Isidore of Seville:
This same teacher also says: A sacrament takes place in some celebration when the deed is done in such a way that it is understood to signify something, which must be received reverently.
In defining the sacrament, it aligns with Paschasius in chapter three of the book on the Body and Blood of the Lord:
"A sacrament is whatever is presented to us in any divine celebration as a pledge of salvation, where a visible act performs something quite different invisibly inside, which must be received reverently."
Blessed Algerus, a strong opponent of Berengar, follows in the footsteps of Ratramnus and Paschasius in book two on the Eucharist, chapter one:
"Christ is in that sacrament because it is the body of Christ; it is not, therefore, physical food, but spiritual. If it is spiritual and not physical, how can it be subject to physical separation?"
In the same chapter, he argues that fasting, which is physical, is not broken by the spiritual food of the Eucharist:
"But let it be far from the hearts of the faithful to believe that fasting is broken on days of fasting, no matter the hour the Mass is celebrated; because since it is not physical, but spiritual food, physical abstinence is not broken by spiritual food."
Therefore, there is no room for doubt that the mystery is spiritual. Ratramnus, nevertheless, means in his mind what the speaker expresses, because the spirit of faith accomplishes it:
"Faith nourishes, delights, and enlivens inwardly, while what it is nourishes the flesh."
For faith does not do everything internally, as it rather accepts it as the object of its belief. This is the singular mindset of Ratramnus and all Catholics.
He clearly denies in number 52 that what is taken by the mouth at the altar can grant eternity, for the life contained in the mystery comes from the invisible power of the Word, which works faith in us; in this faith lies the efficacy and virtue of the body of the Lord.
It's clear that these three points are missing in Ratramnus's section 52.
He openly acknowledges, when explaining the words of Saint Ambrose, that the bread of life, which came down from heaven, is received by us at the altar.
He speaks clearly about the spiritual nourishment by which the faithful are nurtured in the Church, the food that believers receive, and he teaches that the bread and wine not only can, but actually do, give us eternal life.
This living bread that came down from heaven provides the substance of eternal life.
He states that in the Eucharist, what is perceptible to the senses or tangible can only nourish the body, but not the soul in any way.
This is so true that among all Catholics, it is beyond any shadow of a doubt.
This reasoning strongly proves that those who believed there was no symbolism in the Eucharist, thinking everything was open and clear manifestation, are greatly mistaken.
Ratramnus never said that the life contained in the mystery comes from the invisible power of the word, which produces faith.
The speaker forgot that Ratramnus criticized the notion of the mystery being enacted spiritually because the spirit of faith accomplishes it.
Indeed, if Ratramnus said that faith makes the mystery, by what right can one claim that the life within the mystery creates or produces faith?
Whichever way the speaker turns, it's not easy to escape this dilemma.
For if Ratramnus's intention is that faith makes the mystery, it's wrongly accused of making the mystery produce faith.
However, he was far from such subtleties, as he fully acknowledges that the mystery of the Eucharist is accomplished by the power of the Spirit of God, which is the credible object of our faith or Christian persuasion.
Nothing wiser or more orthodox than this doctrine of Ratramnus can be proposed.
Consequently, it is necessary not to have taught in this faith the efficacy and power of the body of Christ.
On the other hand, it's argued that this bread contains a life not visible to the eyes, but recognized only through faith.
This bread has come down from heaven, and it is said that whoever eats of this bread will become immortal.
Therefore, within this bread lies a life that isn't seen by the physical eyes but is perceived through faith.
This is the living bread that descended from heaven, and it is truly said: Whoever eats this will never die; it is the body of Christ.
Who would be convinced that these words imply the efficiency and power of the body of Christ are understood within this faith?
Just as eyes are said to see colors and light, without containing their effectiveness: saying that faith perceives or believes in the mystery of the body of Christ, viewed through the eyes of faith, is not to claim that the efficiency and power of the body of Christ lie in this faith.
However, I fear that in this discussion, it might be too contentious to claim complete victory.
Socrates, Ecclesiastical History, Book 3, Chapter 18, Page 633.
When he denies that Christ is physically on the altar (as noted by the commentator on page 178 of the Paris edition, and page 292, number 178, of the Amsterdam edition, and page 178, first Paris edition), and insists it should be understood spiritually, he reveals in number 76:
Just as in the mystery, that bread is taken as the body, so too in the mystery, the members of the people believing in Christ are represented.
And just as that bread is called the body of believers not physically, but spiritually, so it is necessary to understand the body of Christ not physically, but spiritually.
Ratramnus aimed to demonstrate that there is a symbolic aspect to the Eucharist.
His best argument draws from the symbolism of the body and blood of the faithful.
This is represented by the mixing of water with wine in the chalice.
Just as the people are symbolically united with Christ through the mixing of water, representing the blood of the people, so too are the forms of bread and wine symbolic of the body and blood of Christ.
These elements serve as veils or coverings of Christ's body and are seen as representations or shadows.
Through them, the true body is present but not perceived by the eyes and senses of those who observe.
While sight, touch, and taste are deceived, it is through hearing alone that belief is safely held.
Alger refers to these forms as the body of Christ because they conceal and encompass the true body of Christ.
With these ideas in place, it's clear that comparing the body of the people with the body of Christ in the Eucharist is easily grasped by all.
Ratramnus wants the body of Christ to be seen as the symbolic figure of the people's body and blood.
However, this doesn't contradict the belief that the true body is hidden within these forms.
Though the body and blood of the people are only understood symbolically, Paschasius, a strong advocate for the presence and transubstantiation of Christ's true body in the Church, made the same comparison.
He stated that the body of the people is figuratively present in the Eucharist, just as Christ's body is.
He never doubted that the real presence of Christ's body is truly hidden beneath these forms.
He expresses this in chapter 11 of the book On the Body and Blood of the Lord:
"And therefore, it was rightly provided that, because water flowed together with blood, in this mystery of true blood, water is mixed, so that we may also be in it, so that through this sacrament of salvation, we may be mystically united and offered to divine eyes."
If wine is offered without water, the blood of Christ seems to be without us; conversely, if only water is offered, the people seem to be without Christ.
When both are mixed and joined together, the mystery of the Church is rightly and spiritually fulfilled.
Further down in the same chapter, the faithful are encouraged to rejoice, understanding themselves to be united with Christ in such a profound unity through grace and advanced to a fervor of love.
Therefore, it is fitting in this mystery that our image is represented by water, so that each person may understand they are received into the blood of Christ and transformed for the better.
Although mystically wine and water are first mixed, after consecration only blood is consumed, because we initially receive it from the water of baptism and drink it again through daily hunger and thirst.
For this reason, it is not inappropriate that water is also consecrated, not because the water remains, but because it is turned into blood to signify what faith perceives.
This makes it easy to see how unnecessary the conclusion drawn by the dissertation writer from Ratramnus's words is.
The dissertation writer asserts that it is clearly stated, without ambiguity, that the body is not physically present in the consecrated bread, that is, according to substance, but only in the understanding of spiritual faith.
Indeed, such a conclusion cannot be drawn from Paschasius's similar words, if not the same ones.
Why then deduce it from Ratramnus, who had the intelligence to prevent such a misunderstanding, so that a fabrication from Calvin's mind would not be attributed to him over time, as is evident in number 101?
Nor should it be thought that because we say these things, the body of the Lord or his blood is not received by the faithful in the mystery of the sacrament, when faith receives not what the eye sees, but what it believes.
The dissertation writer did not more effectively present the passage from Ratramnus in number 75 with these words:
But we see nothing is changed in the water; consequently, therefore, nothing is shown physically in the wine.
Whatever is signified in the water from the body of the people is accepted spiritually, and it is therefore necessary to accept spiritually whatever is intimated in the wine about the blood of Christ.
Essentially, this means that when we see wine, our senses don't perceive the blood of Christ, and these appearances are spiritually and figuratively the body of Christ.
Similarly, when water is mixed, we don't perceive the blood of people; the water is only figuratively and spiritually considered as such.
This doesn't prevent the true body of Christ from being present in the Eucharist, while the body of the people is only represented symbolically.
The comparison doesn't need to be perfect to support what Ratramnus primarily argues—that there is a symbolic aspect to the Eucharist, and not everything needs to be clearly revealed.
So far, we've adequately addressed the points that the critic in the book accuses of deviating from Catholic faith and labels as heretical.
Now, let's examine what the critic describes as more obscure and disguised, and let's pursue defending the innocent and untainted Ratramnus as legal experts would.
The critic argues, on page 292, theme 179, number 1, first edition Paris, page 179, that Ratramnus or the author of the book on the Body and Blood of the Lord complicates the issue so much that even experts struggle to understand.
As stated in number 5: What is received in the Church by the faithful as the body and blood, whether it occurs in mystery or truth, contains something secret revealed only to faith's eyes.
Or whether without any mystery, it's perceived externally by sight, while internally it’s understood by the mind’s eye, so that everything is clarified in the light of revelation.
And whether it's the same body that was born of Mary, suffered, died, was buried, and then rose and ascended to heaven, sitting at the Father's right hand.
Understanding this question can be challenging, especially since, during Ratramnus's time, there were believers who felt that everything about the Eucharist was straightforward.
They believed that the body and blood of Christ were not hidden under any form or symbolism.
We can see this in section 11 of the book On the Body and Blood of the Lord:
Some believers argue that the sacrament of the body and blood of Christ, celebrated in the Church, is presented without any form or symbolism, in a clear revelation of truth,
while others contend that these are presented as a mystery, with what is perceived by the senses differing from what faith understands.
There is a significant difference between these views.
Moreover, Ratramnus cannot be blamed for the confusion surrounding this question.
He wasn't the one who raised it; it was Emperor Charles the Bald who ordered the investigation and discussion of the matter, as we learn from section 5, which the writer deliberately omitted.
Ratramnus didn't pose the question as: "Is the body and blood of Christ, consumed by the faithful in the Church, taken in mystery or in truth, etc.?" Instead, he stated: "Your Majesty's Excellence asks whether the body and blood of Christ, consumed by the faithful in the Church, is taken in mystery or in truth."
Therefore, Ratramnus shouldn't be held responsible for the complexity of the question. This critique should be directed at the emperor himself.
With these words, your greatness seeks to understand something the author of this question also does not fully grasp—the secret within the soul of every faithful person: the mystery's covering, a symbol that each person contemplates and believes within themselves about the Word of God regarding the body of Christ.
The author is not questioning whether it is just a figure and sign that, when combined with the faith of the believer, is called the name of the mystery.
Nor are they asking if the bread is the body of Christ only in thought or truly in reality.
The real question is whether it can be said that, even before the operation of faith and mind, what is seen can truly be the body born of the Virgin.
Indeed, Ratramnus only explored and questioned whether this sacrament was devoid of all figure and empty.
He demonstrated that there is indeed some figure united with truth, according to Paschasius's view.
He always considered the inner and secret aspect of the Eucharist to be deceptive to human eyes, not merely the result of faith's perspective.
It seemed unthinkable to him that the body of Christ could be regarded as a mere figment of reason.
Rather, he did not doubt that it exists on its own, truly existing as an object around which reason, faith, and intellect revolve.
Nowhere does Ratramnus suggest that the mystery consists of two things: symbols as signs and the faith of the believer, which completes the mystery when believed, contrary to what the disputant claimed on page 179 of the Paris edition, 292 of the Amsterdam edition, number 179, omitting the place because there is none from which it was copied.
Nevertheless, he continues in an unbroken discourse, theme 11, 24.
It is similarly misleading what Ratramnus says in number 9: A mystery cannot be called such if nothing is hidden, nothing is removed from bodily senses, nothing is covered with a veil.
But that bread, which through the ministry of the priest becomes the body of Christ, presents something outwardly different to human senses and proclaims something different inwardly to the minds of the faithful.
.
because it is heavenly, because it is divine, that is, the body of Christ is shown, which is perceived, received, or granted not by the senses of the flesh, but by the contemplation of a faithful soul.
These words INTERIOR and EXTERIOR have misled even the most educated people.
The term interior, which appears in Numbers Ten and Twenty-One and in other places, is not understood by this author to mean anything different in the symbols themselves.
Instead, he believes that the mystery happens in the minds of believers, and he argues that it can't be called a mystery unless, when the mind is prompted by the symbols, it believes something beyond what the eye sees.
For the mystery is created from both the symbol and the believer's faith.
It's not easy to detect any deceit or cunning in Ratramnus's words.
If he truly explains clearly and openly, without any ambiguity, what he understands both internally and externally from these words, and sincerely indicates what is within or outside the mystery of our faith, without influencing the readers' minds to believe that such a mystery is created in the souls of believers, then it's very likely that his words are free from deceit or fraud.
Furthermore, from the words in paragraph nine, we can easily understand and grasp his meaning, which the writer did not hesitate to omit or, dare I say, erase.
Externally, the form of bread that was there before is presented, its color is shown, and its taste is received.
But internally, something entirely different, much more precious and excellent, is revealed, because it is heavenly and divine; that is, the body of Christ is shown, which is not perceived by the senses of the flesh.
Who in their right mind would persuade themselves or understand from such speech that faith operates the body of Christ and exists only through the power of the mind's thought in the Eucharist?
What deceit or fraud could there be in the construction and coherence of such words, and what could Ratramnus mean except that sight, touch, and taste are deceived in this mystery, but it is safely believed by hearing alone?
If there is any cunning, it's the writer's, who cleverly omitted these words; but the strength of a lion, or Ratramnus, clearly and vigorously expresses his mind about the Catholic faith.
Foxes are indeed cautious, but those who catch foxes are more cautious.
Ratramnus does not say, internally, as the writer claims, that the symbols are changed, but rather that internally, to the innermost mind, the body of the Lord is intimated or signified by the symbols, where the faithful mind sees, receives, and accepts.
When he cleverly discusses this, he denies that it can be said that the sight of the body looks at Christ or that the mouth eats Christ.
There are three clear and obvious falsehoods in these statements.
First, it's incorrect to claim that Ratramnus doesn't mention the internal change of the symbols.
He explicitly states in section nine: THE BREAD WHICH WAS BEFORE.
If it truly was bread before, it is no longer so, indicating an internal change, as no external change is visible.
Furthermore, Ratramnus clearly states in section thirty: Truly, through the mystery, the bread and wine are changed into the substance of the body and blood of Christ, to be received by the believers.
Second, Ratramnus doesn't claim that the body is merely signified by the symbols to the innermost mind.
He clearly states that the bread and wine have changed into something different than they were before.
This is undeniable, as he further argues that the change is not visible to our eyes nor apparent externally.
The bread and wine appear to be something other than their outward form suggests.
It's a misconception, which cannot be conceived without error, that according to Ratramnus's view in section fifteen, the body and blood of Christ are present in the Eucharist.
Therefore, they must admit that a transformation has occurred in a way other than physically, or acknowledge that they are not truly what they appear to be, but something else in their essence.
If they refuse to acknowledge this, they are forced to deny the presence of the body and blood of Christ, which is wrong to assert or even think.
Third, the dissertator wrongly attributes to Ratramnus the clever denial that the sight perceives the body of Christ and that the mouth eats Christ.
He wisely and plainly denies that the sacred body of Christ, celebrated in the Church, is visible or tangible to the senses, or that it is divided and consumed like ordinary food.
However, alongside Paschasius, he openly acknowledges that the substance of the body and blood of Christ, not directly visible, is truly hidden and enveloped within the appearances of bread and wine, existing invisibly and not subject to the senses.
In truth, to affirm what Catholics have willingly accepted, none of this satisfies the pseudo-Ratramnus, according to the dissertator.
The Paris edition, numbered 180, and the Amsterdam edition, numbered 293, present evidence with five formulated propositions.
These propositions argue that the proper works oppose Ratramnus and greatly displease him.
First, the consecrated bread is truly the body of Christ that was born of the Virgin.
According to the perspective of the pseudo-Ratramnus, there is no figurative meaning in the phrase "body of Christ."
It is not to be understood metaphorically; rather, everything is perceived in truth.
As stated in number 14, one should willingly confess to seeing it in the simplicity of truth and think of everything corporeally.
Second, the Catholics indeed freely said, "What we see is truly the body of Christ."
Third, anathema to him who says that faith performs the mystery.
The commentator notes that before faith, through the consecration by the mouth of the priest of God, God Himself performs the mystery in the symbols.
Fourth, nothing spiritual is conducted in that mystery, nothing hidden, nothing secret.
Fifth, we do not accept that faith creates, but rather, what is created by the word of God and the mouth of the priest, faith considers and believes.
The first proposition does not contradict Ratramnus at all.
He, along with Paschasius and all Catholics, affirmed that both the symbol and the truth are present in the Eucharist.
He denied that the symbolic body, or the visible appearances of bread and wine, was born of the Virgin Mary.
However, he never doubted that the true body, hidden under these appearances and veils, was indeed formed from the purest blood of Mary.
In the first part of the book, he demonstrated that the body of Christ is present in the Eucharist with a symbol beneath the veils and appearances of bread and wine.
In the second part, he shows that these appearances, which should be called the symbolic body of Christ and serve as a veil for the true hidden body, are not the body born, dead, and buried from the Virgin Mary, but rather differ from the true body of Christ.
His adversaries, convinced by their reasoning, argued that there was no symbol or veil in the Eucharist, but that the actual body of Christ, born from Mary, was openly seen and defended.
Such were some modern philosophers, as well as Abbo the Abbot and Walter, prior of Saint Victor in Paris, and many others, perhaps misled by interpreting Berengar's retraction too literally.
The second proposition also seems to easily align with Ratramnus's thought if we understand from these words that what we see is truly the body of Christ, meaning the substance under the Eucharistic veils or visible appearances is the true hidden body of Christ.
This is indeed the true opinion of Ratramnus, Paschasius, Lanfranc, and the Catholic Church.
But if we understand this hidden substance to be tangible and perceivable by the senses, it is contrary to Ratramnus and aligns with the opinion of the adversaries, which he thoroughly countered and refuted in the work we defend.
Ratramnus does not refuse to subscribe to the anathema of the third proposition, since the body of Christ present in the Eucharist is regarded as an object of faith, not as an effect, as we have observed above.
It broadly acknowledges that faith plays a role in number eleven.
However, when it claims that faith works or contributes to the body of Christ, it's like an artisan who doesn't create the material but works with it.
Similarly, faith doesn't create the Trinity, the incarnation, or the Eucharist, but engages with these mysteries by believing in them, giving assent, or understanding them through obedience to faith, not by forming them through belief.
All the faithful completely reject the fourth proposition.
Ratramnus rightly states that nothing will be achieved by faith if there's nothing secret and hidden in this mystery.
Indeed, nothing would be left to believe if everything were revealed and made known.
Paschasius goes further than Ratramnus, strongly asserting in his letter to Frudgardus that it is entirely spiritual.
However, if by these words the writer means spiritual, hidden, and secret, intending to signify something that relies on understanding the mystery, it cannot be more different from Ratramnus's sense.
We are confident that no passage expressed and explained in these words will be produced by him.
The fifth proposition clearly explains Ratramnus's perspective.
What is achieved by the word of God, if not by the power and force of the divine word?
As mentioned in number forty-nine, the body and blood of Christ, received by the faithful in the Church, are figures according to visible appearance.
But truly, according to the invisible substance, that is, the divine power of the Word, they genuinely exist as the body and blood of Christ.
Can a figure be more clearly recognized with the truth, and the existence of the body of Christ in the Eucharist be more strongly demonstrated by the power of the word?
However, nothing stops this passage from being enriched by adding another.
From number forty-four: We confess that in the sacrament of the body and blood of the Lord, whatever is outwardly taken is meant for the refreshment of the body.
But the Word of God, which is the invisible bread invisibly present in that sacrament, invisibly nourishes the minds of the faithful through its participation.
But it seems to deny, says the writer, on page one hundred eighty, only in number.
In what we observe, the appearance of flesh is recognized in that bread.
But who would be so foolish as to think or believe that?
Ratramnus understood that no one could deny the mind's power.
He argued that it is essential to acknowledge a symbolic aspect in the mystery of the Eucharist.
Numbers ten:
Because of this undeniable fact, it's evident that the bread and wine symbolically represent the body and blood of Christ.
Yet, who doubts that Ratramnus wrote against those who supported and defended this opinion?
As shown by the frequently mentioned number five, who would believe that most Catholic opponents of Berengar were even more against this view?
Who can deny that Abbot Abbaudus or Walter, the prior of Saint Victor of Paris, supported the defense of this opinion?
Who isn't aware that more recent philosophers, particularly Father Magnan, a distinguished theologian from the Minim order in the Toulouse province, who was never criticized by the Catholic Church, deliberately wrote an appendix to sacred philosophy against Theophilus Rainaud the Jesuit?
The aim was to demonstrate that God, through His involvement, creates the same perception in our eyes and senses with the absence of the bread's substance after consecration as the bread and wine did before.
Thus, the body of Christ can be perceived in the form of bread without any symbol or shadow.
On page 293, number 180, from the Amsterdam edition, the writer noted:
"But in that, Ratramnus was in heresy, where there is no appearance of flesh, there is no flesh."
Paschasius addressed this error in a letter to Frudgard.
How is it possible that someone, accused of heresy for not believing in the flesh of Christ when it doesn't appear as flesh, can so eloquently explain what's inside and outside the Eucharist?
This person teaches that apart from the appearances of bread and wine, nothing is perceived by the senses, yet inside, the actual body and blood of Christ truly exist.
Who wouldn't understand these words from Ratramnus, number 10:
What else is visible on the surface than the substance of wine?
But if you look inside, it is not the liquid of wine anymore, but the liquid of the blood of Christ?
From these words, I strongly argue that Paschasius did not write against Ratramnus when he addressed those who believed no flesh could exist without the appearances and manifestations of flesh.
The essayist notes on page 181 of the Paris edition, 293 in Amsterdam:
In this clear understanding, pseudo-Ratramnus (thus it pleases to distort the truth) number 88:
In appearance, he says, these things happen, not in truth; that is, by likeness, not by the manifestation of the actual thing.
He assumes as certain and proven what is most false, that Christ's body cannot exist anywhere except in one of two ways: either through a visible manifestation or merely through likeness or figure; because when appearance is opposed to truth, mere likeness or figure is understood.
Ratramnus doesn't argue that this form is not true, meaning it isn't just a likeness or a representation of the thing itself.
Instead, he indicates that this idea is expressed and signified through this prayer of the Church:
"May your sacraments, Lord, we ask, accomplish in us what they contain, so that what we now perform in form, we may understand in the truth of things."
Indeed, this is quite appropriate.
For in this prayer, form and figure do not contradict or oppose the truth of Christ's body itself, or the true substance of the body, but rather reveal it clearly and openly, without any coverings or hindrance.
Therefore, while explaining this phrase, Ratramnus wisely states not in truth, meaning not through the manifestation of the thing itself.
He does not claim with certainty that the body of Christ cannot exist except through clear manifestation or through likeness or figure.
On the contrary, from this prayer of the Church, he argues that the body of Christ in the Eucharist is hidden under forms and shadows, specifically, the appearances of bread and wine.
Since in that prayer, it is requested that the body of Christ, which is performed under the appearance of bread and wine, may be seen in clear vision just as it truly is in heaven.
Blessed Alger, a well-known opponent of Berengar, used the same prayer to defend the views of Ratramnus in the first book on the Eucharist, chapter 5, in the middle of the Antwerp edition of 1536.
Indeed, the priest asks, he says, that the body of Christ, which is now performed under the appearance of bread and wine, may eventually be understood in clear vision as it truly is.
Now, who but someone wishing to differ with the common understanding would attribute to Blessed Alger the claim that it is known for certain that the body of Christ cannot be present in any way other than through clear manifestation, or merely through likeness or figure.
After the dissertator, on page 181 of the Paris edition and 293 of the Amsterdam edition, did not doubt that Ratramnus taught the change of bread and wine in number.
He makes a strong effort to prove that Ratramnus spoke falsely and insincerely, suggesting that the body in the Eucharist was merely symbolic, existing only as a thought of the mind.
He references words from Numbers, chapter 16: They acknowledge that the body and blood of God could not exist without a change for the better, and that this change was made not physically, but spiritually.
So, it must be said that this was done figuratively, as under the appearance of physical bread and wine lies the spiritual body and blood of Christ.
From this, we understand that Ratramnus demonstrated a change in form occurred, not physically or in a way perceptible to human senses.
But who would then convince themselves that Ratramnus believed Christ's body existed only in form?
The reason he acknowledges a form in this mystery is compelling and accepted by all Catholic believers.
Namely, under the appearance of physical bread and wine lies the spiritual body and blood of Christ.
However, this does not mean that the body and blood of Christ exist in the sacrament merely through solitary mental thought stimulated by symbols.
When Paschasius says in the letter to Frudgard, "and it is all spiritual," the deceitful and treacherous will interpret it this way.
The same critique applies to the blessed Alger, as he speaks in Book One on the Eucharist, Chapter Five, according to Ratramnus's perspective: What is seen has a physical appearance; what is understood has a spiritual benefit.
Therefore, what is physically seen is different from what is spiritually understood, so the sacrament differs from the essence of the sacrament.
And in Book Two, Chapter Thirty: What is seen has a physical appearance; what is understood has a spiritual benefit.
The dissertation writer acknowledges on pages one hundred eighty-one and one hundred eighty-two, section six, of the Paris edition, and the Amsterdam edition, page two hundred ninety-three, section six, or number six, that Ratramnus used the term "conversion" in numbers twenty-four, twenty-five, and twenty-seven.
But to accuse him of dissimulation and deceit, he cites the comparison Ratramnus made in those numbers, between manna and the Eucharist.
He proves there that Ratramnus suggested the conversion of manna into the body of Christ occurred in the same way bread and wine are transformed into flesh and blood.
But since this opinion, which supports the presence of body and blood in manna, is false, insolent, and abandoned by all, the dissertation writer argues that Ratramnus's opinion on the presence of Christ's body and blood in the Eucharist should face the same rejection.
Among the Fathers and doctors of the Church, the comparison between manna and the Eucharist is both common and widely recognized.
This similarity is quite fair and justified.
Just as manna was a symbol representing the future Eucharist, the Eucharist also reflects the past manna.
However, this does not mean that the Fathers saw the Eucharist as merely symbolic or that they didn't believe in the real presence of Christ's body in the sacrament.
The author, a teacher in Israel, knows how easily I could prove the faith of the Fathers if he were to criticize them more aggressively over this comparison, as some have done with Ratramnus or the author of "On the Body and Blood of the Lord."
He would realize that, as they have taught in countless instances, the true presence of Christ's body in the sacrament is not diminished by this comparison. But I would gladly ask him why he treats Ratramnus unfairly and doesn't uphold this standard of fairness, especially since Ratramnus has expressed his faith in this presence in many previously cited places, particularly in section 24, where he mentions Christ, saying:
"He later presented the body taken from the Virgin and hung on the cross for the salvation of believers in our times and poured out through the wave of blood, by which we are not only redeemed but also nourished."
Therefore, it is beyond all doubt and dispute that Ratramnus believed that people were equally redeemed and nourished by the true blood of Christ that was poured out. He wisely avoided ever expressing words that would separate them from his writings as if they were mere tales and always omitted them.
Consider the fact that he explicitly denies in section 62: "This manna," says Ratramnus, "which they ate and the water they drank, no one doubts was physical." Here, as with the Eucharist, he argues that what is consumed is as physical as the manna was.
I now ask the writer if he imagines that something can be eaten physically, slowly, and with sensation while receiving the sacrament with a physical mouth, except for what is suited to and subject to the senses?
Does he want us to believe that the true body of Christ is consumed like ordinary food, being torn to pieces with teeth and swallowed bit by bit?
No one can strictly hold or accurately defend this opinion.
So, what troubles him in these words of Ratramnus?
Is it not the sacramental appearances alone that are eaten physically, chewed by the teeth, and slowly and with sensation lowered into the chest through the throat, like manna?
Do Paschasius, Alger, and all Christian and Catholic men generally explain a different doctrine?
In section number 26, the writer states on page 293 of the Amsterdam edition that in both symbols, it is taught that only Christ is indicated, who feeds the souls of believers.
He subtly avoids or rather precisely denies with that clever word that in one symbol Christ is only indicated, while in the other he is also contained; of which there is no faint trace in the whole work.
He also denies that the wicked partake with their teeth, since he only feeds the souls of the good.
Ratramnus does not claim in section twenty-six that Christ is merely hinted at in both creeds.
In reality, he states that Christ is indicated in both.
The words "merely" and "only" are inventions of the writer, clouded by preconceived opinions against Ratramnus, and they don't appear in Ratramnus's work.
If he had used them, he would contradict himself.
For example, in section nine, he says:
"Outwardly, the bread appears as it was before; its form, color, and taste are perceived. However, inwardly, something far different, much more precious and excellent is indicated, because it is heavenly and divine, that is, the body of Christ, which is shown not to the senses of the flesh but to the vision of the faithful soul, where it is seen, received, and eaten."
And in section ten:
"The wine, through priestly consecration, becomes the blood of Christ, presenting one thing on the surface, but containing something else inwardly."
Who could possibly think that these words deny Christ in either case?
Just as he writes:
"But if you consider inwardly, it is no longer the liquid of wine but the liquid of the blood of Christ to the minds of believers... it tastes when it is tasted."
And in section forty-three:
"Hence, the blood and body of Christ are said to exist because they are made by the divine Spirit and are received not as they outwardly appear but because they exist by an invisible power far different from what they visibly appear."
What could align more with the Catholic faith?
The writer asks, where in the work can even the slightest trace of this be found?
On what basis does he imagine Ratramnus denies that the body of Christ is affected by the teeth of the wicked, when it nourishes only the souls of the good?
Is he suggesting it nourishes both the good and the wicked equally, thereby tainting the faith with heresy?
Does he not understand that the body of the Lord is to be judged, received as holy, and is life to the good and death to the wicked?
And whoever receives it unworthily is guilty of the body and blood of the Lord?
Why is it important to prepare so thoroughly and approach the altar of God with such grace and readiness when receiving the Eucharist, if it nourishes the souls of both the good and the evil equally?
Is it truly to deny that the body of Christ is received in substance by the wicked, when it is said to be nourishment and life for the good but death and destruction for the wicked?
In number 28, there seems to be a similar deceit and cunning.
It uses Catholic words as if to inspire faith, yet by comparing it to manna and water, it undermines the true meaning of those words.
Just as, he says, a little before he suffered, he was able to transform the substance of bread and the creation of wine into his own body, which was to suffer, and into his own blood, which was to be shed:
so also in the desert, he was able to transform manna and water from the rock into his flesh and blood.
Would Calvin not willingly agree with this statement?
Ratramnus didn't set out to prove the real presence of Christ’s body in the Eucharist, as no one at that time questioned it.
Instead, he sought to show that there was a symbolic representation within it.
This was in contrast to those who believed everything was outwardly revealed without any figure or shadow.
It's not surprising that Ratramnus used the true and unique symbolic conversion of the Eucharist to support his argument.
This was his intention and spirit, and I doubt Calvin would have agreed with it.
Indeed, in any situation, he used this reasoning:
Clearly, when there is no doubt that Christ the Lord could transform the substance of bread into His own body and the substance of wine into His blood, which was to be shed for humanity's salvation, he could also have symbolically transformed manna in the desert into His body and the water from the rock into blood.
But who would think that Calvin would favor this view?
However, while I don't find the opinion that Christ’s body and blood were really present in the manna and rock in the desert to be true, it’s not so unbelievable that it appealed to Ratramnus.
Indeed, John Duns Scotus, in Book Four, Distinction Ten, Question Four, adds two corollaries that aren't entirely opposed to this view:
In the first, he argues that before the incarnation of the divine Word, the Eucharist could have existed as it does now, both in its meaning and in what it signifies and contains.
In the second, he teaches that after the incarnation, Christ’s body could cease to be naturally present, yet the Eucharist would truly remain, both in the truth of the sign and in the truth of what is signified and contained.
Certainly, since existence in the natural mode is not part of the essence of existence in the sacramental mode, nor is it its cause, the latter does not depend on the former.
Nothing depends on something that is neither its essence nor its cause.
Indeed, if such views of Duns Scotus are considered orthodox and acceptable in the Catholic Church, what is so strange or unusual about what Ratramnus said in section 28?
Consider these words: Just as shortly before he suffered, he could transform the substance of bread and the creature of wine into his own body, which was to suffer, and into his own blood, which was to be shed.
So also in the desert, he was able to transform manna and water from the rock into his own blood.
For if, as the writer Harduin suggests, Calvin would not refuse to agree with Ratramnus's opinions, by what right would he refuse to assent to the ideas of Duns Scotus?
And if indeed the school of the Scotists accepts the truth to be defended in this matter, who will accuse Ratramnus of falsehood or lying?
Indeed, who among these does not understand, as I noted, that nothing in the mystery of transubstantiation seemed false or impossible to Ratramnus?
He believed that in the manna and water from the rock of the desert, the incarnation, just as Duns Scotus believed in the Eucharist, could consist in both the signification and the thing signified and contained.
Some from the school of the Scotists might find it unnecessary to bring this against the minister of Calvinist superstition, who usually call the opinions of John Duns Scotus the subtleties of Scotus alongside Francis Rabelais.
But let the reader remember that I am writing against the Jesuit Harduin, for whom the Scotist school always seemed rational and theological, striving to establish and build the Molinist foundation from their very origins.
But in section 30, the writer states on page 293 of the Paris edition, and page 293 of the Amsterdam edition, section 7, that truly through the mystery, the bread and wine are transformed into the substance of the body and blood, to be received by believers.
What an ingenious heresy to deceive the minds of mortals!
So, why did he go out of his way to avoid saying that the substance of Christ's body is consumed by mouth?
Why did he choose the words "to be taken" instead of "not to be taken," unless he believed that the bread or wine wasn't physically transformed?
It's challenging to grasp the cunning nature of a clever heresy designed to mislead people with words like these:
"Truly, through the mystery, bread and wine are transformed into the substance of body and blood."
If Ratramnus had only said "transformed through the mystery," there might be room for doubt.
But when he says that the transformation truly occurs through the mystery, what doubt or complication could such a statement face?
What does the doctrine of the Catholic Church present in the mystery of transubstantiation, other than that truly, through the mystery, bread and wine are converted into the flesh and blood of Christ, not just figuratively, as the defenders of Calvinist superstition stubbornly claim?
Paschasius expressed Ratramnus's thought in words, whose faith the writer does not question, in the book "On the Body and Blood of Christ," chapter 4:
"Thus, by the same, from the substance of bread and wine, mystically the same body and blood of Christ is consecrated."
And in chapter 11: "Who does not know truly that it is the body and blood of the Lord in truth, even if it is received in the sacrament by faith?"
Secondly, by what right does the writer so insistently question why Ratramnus carefully avoided saying that the substance of Christ's body is consumed with the mouth?
Does he not acknowledge in number 5 that the entire question and debate were about this body, specifically the body of Christ that the faithful receive with their mouths?
Charles the Bald sought Ratramnus's advice and opinion on this matter:
"What in the Church is taken with the mouth of the faithful, the body and blood of Christ, your great excellence asks whether it happens in mystery or in truth."
What protection could Ratramnus gain from a cleverly hidden word that was necessarily part of explaining the proposed question?
I also don't see why it matters if Ratramnus said "to be taken" or "to be received," since they ultimately mean the same thing.
The Lobbes manuscript has "to be taken," while other similar or equal ones have "to be received."
Let's find out if the speaker can explain the many benefits they gain from engaging in these intricate and subtle arguments.
In section 36, the concept of TRANSPOSITION is credited to him in number 42.
He states,
"The bread that is offered becomes the body of Christ when it is sanctified; similarly, the wine, after flowing from the vine, through the divine sanctification of the mystery, becomes the blood of Christ—not visible, but invisibly—by the working of the Spirit of God, certainly in the souls of the priest or the congregation, where faith contemplates and realizes the mystery."
While it seems he denies that this occurs visibly, the trick of an unprincipled person is to argue that the body cannot exist—as we heard earlier from Paschasius—unless it is tangible and visible, and therefore, where it is not, it doesn't exist at all.
Here's what the speaker needs to prove: that Ratramnus convinced himself the transformation occurs solely in the believer's mind and is not the result of faith, but rather its effect.
However, this is completely impossible.
The same misconception could be attributed to Paschasius, who states in chapter three of the book On the Body and Blood of the Lord, page 1560, that a tangible thing is transformed into His flesh and blood intelligibly, by God's power through the Word of Christ.
To be transferred and to be transformed are synonymous and mean exactly the same thing.
It's also unnecessary to claim that Ratramnus falsely denies this transformation happens in a way perceivable to the senses.
He denies that the body can be anything other than what is tangible and visible.
Paschasius said exactly the same thing in chapter five of the book On the Body and Blood of the Lord: Therefore, Christ is the food of angels, and this sacrament is truly His flesh and blood, which a person eats and drinks spiritually.
By this, from what the angels live, the person will live, because everything spiritual and divine is in what the person perceives.
And at the end of the same chapter: We also drink and eat spiritually the spiritual flesh of Christ, in which eternal life is believed to be; otherwise, understanding according to the flesh is death, yet truly perceiving the flesh of Christ spiritually is eternal life.
He continues with the same error, number 42: From where, he says, the blood and body of Christ are spoken of, because they are not what they outwardly appear to be, but what they have become inwardly in the souls of believers, through the operation of the divine Spirit and faith, are received.
And because by invisible power they exist far differently than they visibly appear, it is by the power of the Word, which surely creates and generates faith in our souls.
This Word, when believed, has the power of the body and blood of Christ to nourish and give life to the soul.
The interpretations and meanings the writer assigns to Ratramnus's words lack only a strong argument to defend and support them.
This would be much easier if these words, which believers and those with faith attach to Ratramnus's text, were actually found in the original manuscript, rather than just in the writer's imagination.
However, since these interpretations were created in the writer's own mind, he might as well insert them into Paschasius's text, claiming the right of a forger, and accuse Paschasius of Ratramnus's heresies and arguments.
The reader can see this from the following words of Paschasius, taken from chapter four of the book On the Body and Blood of the Lord.
It is not appropriate to consume Christ with teeth; rather, he intended for this bread and wine to truly become his flesh and blood through the consecration by the spirit of faith in the minds of believers.
Can an egg be more like an egg?
In section forty-two, page two hundred ninety-four of the Amsterdam edition, Paris edition page one hundred eighty-four, we learn that the body and blood of the Lord are called mysteries because they possess a secret and hidden nature.
They are different from what they outwardly appear to be and achieve something different than what they visibly suggest.
The writer takes this from Ratramnus to suggest that he believes the mysteries are internally formed through faith, invisibly working in the minds of believers.
The writer must prove his point, but he struggles even with this simple task.
Why attribute to Ratramnus what can't be applied to Paschasius, when Paschasius expresses the same ideas in his own words?
Paschasius states in his book "On the Body and Blood of the Lord," chapter three:
"It's called a mystery because it contains a hidden and secret arrangement within itself.
A sacrament occurs whenever the Holy Spirit, through the divine Scriptures, works effectively by speaking inwardly.
Through the sacrament of the Scriptures, we are spiritually nourished from within and, once nourished, we are guided in the work and discipline of Christ."
At the end of this chapter, he adds:
"Therefore, it's not surprising if the Holy Spirit, who created the man Christ in the womb of the Virgin without seed, also daily transforms the substance of bread and wine into the flesh and blood of Christ by the invisible power of His sacrament, even though it is not perceived externally by sight or taste.
But because they are spiritual, they are fully received by faith and understanding, as the Truth predicted."
If Ratramnus expressed these ideas, because the body and blood of Christ are spiritual and received by faith and understanding, the writer wouldn't hesitate to challenge them, but would completely refute them.
Deceptions, says the writer Hardouin in the same place, first Paris edition, page one hundred eighty-four, and second Amsterdam edition, page two hundred ninety-four, number one hundred eighty-four, section eight.
Let's consider the rest of the man's claims in number fifty-six:
Now, because faith comprehends everything that appears to be everything, and nothing is grasped by the eyes of the flesh: understand that the body and blood of Christ exist not in form but in power, which are believed.
Hence, Ambrose said the natural order should not be observed here, but the power of Christ should be revered:
who does whatever He wants, however He wants, in whatever way He wants, creating what did not exist, and transforming what was created into what it was before.
However, since transubstantiation cannot be more clearly explained through the words of Ratramnus, the writer decided to include words from Saint Ambrose's "On the Mysteries," along with additional commentary.
Specifically, in the minds of believers, the power of the Divine Word creates faith in the body and blood of Christ through the strength of the Holy Spirit, as mentioned in number 54.
This is how it is understood.
No one can say that what we see on the altar is the true body of Christ.
It is said that the body is not present in form or property, meaning not in its essence, but in power; something Paschasius rightly addresses in chapter 26 of the Gospel of Matthew.
Hence, he wonders what stops someone from saying that the truth of the flesh and blood of Christ is not in the substance itself, but in the sacrament: a certain power of the flesh, not flesh itself; a power of the blood, not blood itself; a figure, not the truth; a shadow, not the body.
This power is merely a sign, because symbols represent the body and blood to the mind.
The writer draws terrifying conclusions from these texts, and indeed, there's no room for doubt.
If the explanations, which align well and are trustworthy, are strictly derived from sound reasoning, then Ratramnus, or the author of the book on the Body and Blood of the Lord, whom we wrote this study to defend, firmly holds the Calvinist heresy.
Indeed, this heresy cannot be expressed or stated more chastely or elegantly than with these words: Understand that the body and blood of Christ exist not in form, but in power, which are believed.
For in any case, if the body and blood believed in the Eucharist exist in power and not in form, taking the name for essence and the property of nature, behold, we recognize pure Calvinistic heresy.
However, the writer somehow unfortunately blinds himself to this reality, which he applies to number fifty-six, where these words which are believed do not appear, but instead, these which are seen, which convey a very different and Catholic meaning.
Indeed, what is seen in the Eucharist is whiteness, roundness, and finally, extension—visible objects easily perceived by human senses, which indeed are not the forms and appearances of the body and blood of Christ, but of the bread and wine that were there before, and which God transformed into His body and blood.
As Ratramnus cites from Saint Ambrose's book On the Mysteries, Chapter Nine: He changes what is created into what it was not before.
However, I do not wish to accuse the writer, a man otherwise pious and not lacking in intellect, of such foul interpolation or corruption as to unjustly consign the unfortunate Ratramnus among the crafty heretics.
Among those who warmly welcomed him, Peter Allix, a minister of Calvinist beliefs in the Charenton temple of France, chose not to resort to crude methods.
This is evident from the Latin-French edition he carefully prepared in Rouen in 1672 at LUCAS, and the English-Latin edition produced by another person in London in 1686.
Despite the ministers being adamant defenders of their beliefs, they did not dare to replace the word CERNUNTUR with CREDUNTUR.
The unnecessary and disgraceful nature of altering Ratramnus's text with such interpolations is clearly demonstrated by the doctrines throughout this book: Thus, what is seen is not the same as what is believed.
What is seen feeds the corruptible body, being itself corruptible, but what is believed nourishes the soul, which is immortal.
Therefore, let the reader approach Ratramnus with an open mind and observe in section 56 that it reads CERNUNTUR and not CREDUNTUR.
Then, let them witness the defense crumbling and the flawed interpretations and assumptions derived from this passage falling apart.
Given these points, it cannot be true that the transformation occurring in the Eucharist exists solely in the souls of believers, where the power of the divine word instills faith in the body and blood of Christ through the Holy Spirit's strength.
Such a creation of faith is not found in Ratramnus's work.
Additionally, in that passage, Ratramnus does not oppose "not in appearance but in power" to the essence or nature of the body of Christ, but only to the external appearance, which neither appears in the Eucharist nor is visible. Instead, he agrees with Paschasius in number...
The body and blood of Christ, which the faithful receive in the Church, are symbols in their visible form.
However, in reality, according to the invisible essence—the divine power of the Word—they truly are the body and blood of Christ.
Who, in their right mind, would doubt the sincerity of Ratramnus' faith from these words?
It's easy to understand that by "appearance," he didn't mean nature or property, but the outward appearance and manifestation.
Thus, there's no need to assume that Paschasius wrote against Ratramnus in his commentary on the Gospel according to Matthew, chapter 26, or that Ratramnus meant something different by "appearance" than outward manifestation, when he says:
Not the flesh by appearance, but by sacrament; this indeed, which now contains the likeness of it in the mystery, is not flesh by appearance, but by sacrament.
He clearly explains his meaning and abundantly shows that by "appearance," he meant the outward revelation of bread and wine under which, in the sacrament, the true body and blood of Christ exist.
For, he states, in the appearance of bread, the true body of Christ is present in the sacrament, as He Himself declares: This is my body.
Furthermore, considering Ratramnus' stance, how mistakenly does the commentator claim that Ratramnus is wrestling with illusions, asking, Who declared that Christ's body is visible on the altar?
Was that notion to be refuted by the testimonies of the Fathers?
One could easily respond that he himself agreed with this opinion, since he repeatedly states in numerous places that what is seen as the body of Christ, is indeed visible.
Can something be seen if it is not visible, and can the invisible be made visible?
Even if this reasoning, challenged by its own senses, doubts this idea, there's no question that Ratramnus convinced his opponents that there's no symbol or shadow in the Eucharist; everything is clear and open.
These views were supported by Abbot Abbaudus, Walter, the prior of Saint Victor in Paris, and more recent philosophers of our time.
All of them professed the Catholic faith and religion but were somewhat less inclined towards Aristotelian philosophy, and did not consider the concept of accidents without a subject.
Why does it say in Numbers, chapter five, verses forty-nine and ninety-six, and elsewhere, that what is placed on the Lord's table, celebrated and kept on the altar, and consumed by the faithful, is the true body of Christ only in mystery or symbol?
Ratramnus never claimed in Numbers five, forty-nine, ninety-six, or anywhere else, that the body of Jesus Christ, received by the faithful, is the true body of Christ only in mystery or symbol.
As the schools would argue, this proposition is contradictory: It's unthinkable for the true body to be only in symbol and mystery, because it would imply that the body is both true and not true.
In fact, Erigerus, or the Anonymous Cellotian, stated that there were only two factions; similarly, Paschasius and Ratramnus mentioned: Some people, he said, claim that what is received from the altar is the same as what was born of the Virgin, while others deny this and say it is different.
From the words of the Anonymous Cellotian, I assert that everyone should understand that the differing opinions among faithful people regarding the cause of the Eucharist should not be seen as factions.
That is, different sides opposing the truth of the faith.
Ratramnus points out in section eleven that this entire debate has emerged among the faithful.
Yet, since the Anonymous Cellotian is a writer of very humble talent and little merit, whose solitary testimony supports the belief that Ratramnus and Paschasius were in conflict, this whole controversy can be easily resolved by carefully reading the works of Ratramnus, Paschasius, and the Anonymous Cellotian.
From these, a reader will understand that this Anonymous neither grasped the mind of Ratramnus nor of Paschasius.
Indeed, the Anonymous failed to notice that Ratramnus never denies the body born of the Virgin Mary is present in the Eucharist, but only states that it differs from the body celebrated in the Church, which is a nominal body under which the true body is hidden and concealed.
And since Ratramnus only denies that this nominal body is the one born of Mary, the Anonymous mistakenly believed that Paschasius, who claims that the true body born of Mary is in the Eucharist, and Ratramnus, who denies the nominal body is born of Mary, are opposed to each other.
In fact, considering the distinction between the nominal body and the true body, or the true body hidden under the figurative body, they can easily be reconciled and brought to agreement.
The debater Ratramnus supposedly referred to the supporters of both viewpoints as "patrons" to equally please the faithful—those who assert that everything is open and clear, and those who believe there is a symbolic aspect in the sacrament of the body consumed by the faithful in the Church.
This seems far from common sense, as he was required to respond to the emperor who sought his counsel, and to identify as heretics those who, by the consensus of all Catholics, must be considered heretics if they truly denied the true and real presence of Christ's body in the Eucharist.
The first issue is his improper use of the term "mystery": in sections seventy-three, seventy-four, and ninety-eight, he teaches that the consecrated bread is a mystery, both of the body in which Christ was born and of the body of the Church, which we have proven through many documents to be far from the truth.
Ratramnus does not teach that the consecrated bread is a mystery, but rather a symbol and a veil that covers and conceals the body of Christ.
Paschasius expressed the same idea in many places, especially in chapter four of the book "On the Body and Blood of the Lord" by Halmo of Halberstadt. The dissertator presents this against Ratramnus's passage, without contradicting it.
In fact, he supports this view in the treatise on the Body and Blood of the Lord, which the learned monk Dom Lucas d'Acherius published in volume twelve of the "Spicilegium," page twenty-eight, where these words that beautifully clarify Ratramnus' meaning can be found.
In the body and blood of Christ, due to the reverence of those partaking, the taste of bread and wine remains, along with the symbol, while the nature of the substances is completely transformed into the body and blood of Christ.
The senses of the body report one thing, while the faith of the mind reports another: the senses of the body can only report what they perceive, but the understanding of the mind and faith declare and affirm the true flesh and blood of Christ.
Forty-three. Furthermore, the two ecclesiastical prayers he references in numbers eighty-five and eighty-eight do not support the error of pseudo-Ratramnus.
Earlier, we talked about the Church's prayers in relation to Ascelin's letter to Berengar.
Ratramnus presented these prayers to challenge those who believed that everything in the Eucharist could be fully understood through the senses, without any mystery.
These prayers ask God that what we perceive symbolically, we might truly partake of through a deeper understanding of the sacrament.
This means that what we perform symbolically now, we may eventually comprehend in its true reality.
The term "manifestation" in Ratramnus's writings signifies the revelation of truth, as we've discussed before and in the preface.
Blessed Algerus also used this term to mean revelation in Book 1 on the Eucharist, Chapter 5.
Thus, at the end of a certain mass, it is prayed:
"May your sacraments achieve in us, Lord, what they signify, so that what we perform symbolically now, we may fully understand in truth."
Indeed, the priest prays that the body of Christ, now symbolized by bread and wine, may one day be seen clearly as it truly is.
About this vision, the Gospel of John teaches: "Whoever loves me will be loved by my Father, and I will love them and reveal myself to them."
In the passion of blessed Dionysius, it is said that while he was celebrating the sacred mystery in prison, the Lord appeared to him and, offering the holy gifts, said:
"Receive this, my dear, which I will soon complete for you along with my Father."
This implies, "What I give you is sustenance for the journey; I will not change it into something else but will fulfill it by revealing myself."
In the preface, I mentioned that these prayers were translated from Greek to Latin, as we understand from the words of Saint Dionysius, which we discussed earlier in response to objection 10.
However, prayers explained in this manner cannot support any error, so we must acknowledge Ratramnus as free from all heresy.
The lecturer makes an effort to argue that this was misunderstood by referencing Saint Augustine.
In his twenty-seventh treatise on John, Augustine interprets participation up to the participation of the spirit.
But what does that mean?
These prayers were clearly written long after Saint Augustine, during the time of Gelasius or Saint Gregory the Great, as they appear in their sacramentary books but not in Augustine's works.
These arguments are so weak that they don't even require a response.
The lecturer doesn't achieve a more convincing outcome with his interpretation of this other prayer.
We ask you, Lord, that your sacraments may fulfill in us what they signify, so that what we now perform outwardly, we may understand in truth.
He insists confidently that this prayer's meaning aligns with another prayer from Paschasius's time: Pour the spirit of your charity into us, so that those satisfied with the Paschal sacraments may be unified by your kindness.
It would be just as challenging to prove that the hymn "Te Deum Laudamus" shares the same meaning as Psalm 130, "Out of the Depths," Psalm 109, verse 44.
See dissertation page 295, Amsterdam edition, and page 188, Paris edition.
This misinterpretation of the mystery leads Pseudo-Ratramnus to frequently claim that the body of Christ on the altar is vastly different from the one in which Christ was born, as distinct as the difference between a sign and the thing it signifies.
Ratramnus doesn't bring a false or twisted interpretation to the mystery:
He clearly explains his view in section nine, where altering anything is considered terrible and to be feared.
If the mystery is performed without any symbol, then it isn't rightly called a mystery.
Because it can't be called a mystery if nothing is hidden, nothing is beyond bodily senses, and nothing is covered by a veil.
Who doesn't see the clear traces of truth in these matters?
Who doubts that these ideas apply to the Eucharist?
In the Eucharist, faith and understanding focus on the hidden body and blood of Christ, while the senses only perceive the appearances of bread and wine, as Ratramnus states in section nine.
Beyond this, nothing stops the laws of reason or Christian religion from recognizing the difference between the veiled body of Christ and the same body revealed and manifest, as philosophers say, and the same body placed spiritually and definitively.
This difference doesn't concern the substance of the body, but rather the different modes of existence.
What prevents us from acknowledging a significant difference between our living bodies and the same bodies revived after resurrection?
Didn't the apostles recognize a significant difference between the glorious and splendid body of Christ during the transfiguration and the same body during his death, torn and mutilated?
Therefore, nothing stops us from admitting the distinction and the great interval between the body of Christ born of the Virgin, suffered and crucified, shown to the world, and the same body veiled, hidden, wrapped in symbols and shadows in the Eucharist, intangible and beyond senses.
Blessed Alger, the adversary of Berengar, said this body is THE SAME AND NOT THE SAME:
The same was said by Lanfranc, Archbishop of Canterbury.
Furthermore, we must not overlook, according to Alger, that there are two kinds of the body of Christ in the sacrament of the Eucharist.
The first is the symbolic one, represented by the forms of bread and wine through shadows and figures.
The other is the true and proper body, taken from the Virgin Mary, hidden and concealed under the symbolic, deceiving the eyes and senses of people.
Ratramnus explains that there are not two separate existences; rather, clearly and truthfully, as he teaches in number 30, the bread and wine are transformed into the substance of the body and blood of Christ.
He states in number 28: We do not believe any of the faithful doubt that the bread has become the body of Christ, which, when given to the disciples, he says: This is my body which is given for you; nor do they doubt the cup contains the blood of Christ about which he says: This is the cup, etc.
The writer might argue that all these do not signify the body born of the Virgin Mary, dead and buried.
But such an objection is not difficult to counter, since Ratramnus himself says the blood shed for salvation is drunk by the faithful, by which not only are we redeemed, but also nourished, as we observed earlier from number 24.
Page 295, Amsterdam edition, and 198 Paris edition.
However, Pseudo-Ratramnus distinguishes and separates the body that exists through the mystery, which exists in the understanding of faith after the reminder of the figure, symbol, or mystery.
He wrongly considers it to be the divine and spiritual and invisible body indicated by Jerome.
This, I say, he rightly distinguishes from the corporeal and proper or human body of Christ, but he impiously denies that there is a place for the proper body on the altar.
Ratramnus certainly did not imagine that the body of Christ is present in the Eucharist through mere thought or intellect.
Such a notion or product of reason never crossed his mind; therefore, he does not differentiate or separate the true and natural body from a fictional one, but rather from a nominal body, as Algerus states, which conceals and covers the true and proper one.
Ratramnus does not deny that the true and proper body of Christ exists in the Eucharist.
He explains in number 49: The body and blood of Christ, received by the faithful in the Church, are symbols in visible appearance; but in invisible essence, which is the divine power of the Word, they truly exist as the body and blood of Christ.
And if they truly exist, they do not exist merely in the mind.
To exist only in the mind is to exist fictitiously and artificially; much like "The beautiful woman turns into a fish below."
Furthermore, Ratramnus does not impiously deny, as his critic claims, that the proper body is present on the altar. He clearly states in number 24 that the body taken from the Virgin and crucified for the salvation of believers was presented in our times, and from it, he poured out a stream of blood, by which we are not only redeemed but also nourished.
Truly, since we are not redeemed by fictional or imaginary blood, but by real blood, we are also not nourished by fictional or imaginary blood, but by real blood—the same blood shed for the redemption of humankind.
If by "proper body" we mean a body with physical properties, weight, dimensions, tangible sensations, and perceptible to the senses, then such a body indeed does not have a place on the altar. But if by "proper" we mean true, spiritual, and beyond the grasp of the senses, Ratramnus believed as much in the true body of Christ, born of the Virgin and present in the Eucharist, as all the faithful believe that the bodies we have now will be the same, revived, glorious, and spiritual after the resurrection.
In number 46, the critic states that Ratramnus errs, page 187 of the Paris edition, 295 of the...
Amsterdam views the sacrament as a complete symbol, unchanged and unaltered.
It represents the very body in which Christ was born.
Ratramnus explains that there is no visible change in the external appearance of the Eucharistic elements, meaning the symbols of bread and wine, and rightly so.
However, he clearly teaches that the substance of the bread and wine is transformed into the body and blood of Jesus Christ.
In sections 15 and 30, he states, "The bread and wine, transformed into the substance of the body and blood, are to be taken by believers," as even the Magdeburg Centuriators acknowledged.
Similarly, when saying that the reality of the sacrament is the very body in which Christ was born, the blessed Algerus conveyed the same idea.
In Book 4 of "The Eucharist," Chapter 5, he says, "The sacrifice is made up of two things, the sacrament and the reality of the sacrament, that is, the body of Christ."
Furthermore, "Therefore, the sacrament is one thing, and the reality of the sacrament, that is, the body of Christ, is another."
Who would say Algerus is mistaken in this?
On page 295 of the Amsterdam edition, and 189 of the Paris edition, there's a related error suggesting the entire mystery is completed by faith.
As mentioned earlier, the bread, which is figuratively and mysteriously called the body of Christ, is taken by the mouth of the faithful as a mystery.
In other words, faith understands this sign to be the body of Christ.
He never believed that every mystery is achieved by faith alone, nor can such a distorted view be interpreted from his writings.
According to Ratramnus, a mystery is the object of our faith because it contains something beyond the reach of our external senses.
He never stated that the body is figuratively received as a mystery.
To demonstrate this, only a contemptuous opponent would be provoked by selectively quoting words from Ratramnus's work.
In number 44, he explains that the sacrament or mystery consists of two elements: the visible bread and the word of God.
Concerning the body of Christ signified by that bread, it is believed through understanding, thus the mystery is fulfilled by understanding and faith.
To challenge the speaker's point, we need to write out the words from number forty-four, which clearly convey the opposite message.
We acknowledge that in the sacrament of the Lord's body and blood, whatever is physically consumed is intended for the nourishment of the body.
However, the Word of God, who is the invisible bread present in that sacrament, nourishes and gives life to the minds of the faithful in an unseen manner.
Isn't it clear from this that the Word of God, Christ the Lord, is the invisible bread received by the faithful in the sacrament of the Eucharist?
Paschasius made this very clear in the book "On the Body and Blood of the Lord," chapter eight.
O man, learn to appreciate something beyond what is sensed by the mouth of flesh; learn to see something beyond what is shown to these physical eyes. Understand that God is spirit and is present everywhere without being confined to a place. Understand that these spiritual truths are not presented physically or carnally before the divine majesty.
And earlier in chapter five: We also drink spiritually and eat the spiritual flesh of Christ, in which eternal life is believed to be.
And in chapter six: Furthermore, that sacrament of faith is rightly called truth.
Therefore, it is truth when the body and blood of Christ are made from the substance of bread and wine by the power of the Spirit and His Word. It is symbolic when the priest, as if performing something else outwardly, daily sacrifices the Lamb at the altar in remembrance of the sacred passion, which was done once.
You will find the same explanation in Algerus at the beginning of the book on the Eucharist.
Number forty-nine: The sacrament holds a secret: there is a difference between what is visibly seen and what must be received invisibly.
This means its purpose is not in the sanctified bread that is seen, but in the spirit of the believers in faith that is hidden.
This conclusion—that a sacrament contains something secret, with one aspect visible and another that must be received invisibly—is considered both orthodox and catholic.
It is derived from Saint Isidore, Bishop of Seville, in Book Six, Chapter Nineteen of the Etymologies, where it is written:
"A sacrament is in some celebration when an act is performed in such a way that it is understood to signify something that must be received reverently."
Paschasius offers a similar definition of sacrament at the beginning of Chapter Three of his book On the Body and Blood of the Lord:
"A sacrament, therefore, is anything in any divine celebration that is given to us as a pledge of salvation, when the visible act performs something else invisible that must be received reverently."
This definition is explained according to, and from, the perspective of Ratramnus throughout Chapter Three, which doesn't need to be repeated here. Attributing to Ratramnus the belief that the body of Christ in the Eucharist exists solely through intellect is as misguided and unnecessary as attributing it to Paschasius.
Likewise, in number forty-nine, the disputant states on page one hundred ninety of the Paris edition, Amsterdam two hundred ninety-five:
"The body and blood of Christ, which are so called and are figurative," he says, "those taken by the mouths of the faithful, are figures according to their visible appearance: but truly according to their invisible substance; that is, by the divine power of the Word, they truly exist as the body and blood of Christ."
The invisible substance is the power of the divine Word in which the mind believes. Thus, Ratramnus was misleading to the French interpreters with his use of Catholic terms like the invisible substance, which he twisted and misused. They translated this passage as "BY THE POWER OF THE DIVINE WORD," whereas he actually said "according to the power of the Word."
Among all the French interpreters of this treatise by Ratramnus, I am the only Catholic who translated these words as "the power of the Word."
Peter Allix, minister of the Calvinist faith at the Charenton temple, translated it according to the author's intent in the edition made in Rouen in 1672.
Before that, Augustin Marlorat had translated it in 1561 as "according to the power."
Since a faithful translator should focus more on conveying the meaning rather than a word-for-word translation, and I aimed for an accurate and revised translation rather than a commentary or interlinear version, there's no doubt that with the words "according to the power," he meant "by the power."
He uses this expression in number 443: and because they exist quite differently by invisible power than they appear visibly; to indicate what he intended to say in number 49, namely, that according to the invisible substance, the divine power of the Word, the true body and blood of Christ exist.
The substance of the bread is transformed into the substance of the Lord's body by faith.
This is false and fabricated. Our Ratramnus never spoke in such a way.
We have clearly demonstrated that he always viewed the body and blood of Christ in the mystery of the Eucharist as an object, not merely as an effect of faith.
Therefore, the presence of the body in the Eucharist comes before the operation of faith.
Similarly, on page 296 of both the Amsterdam and Paris editions in 190, in number 68, he states that the bread of the body of Christ includes two things:
that which becomes the body and that which is the bread of eternal life, namely the Word of God.
When it is believed, the soul is nourished and refreshed by the body of Christ.
We all know that the nourishment of the soul occurs through the communion of the body, not by transforming the body into the substance of the soul.
However, it's incorrect to claim that Ratramnus sees the body of Christ merely as something tangible that is consumed physically, or as just the Word of God in which one believes.
In fact, in section 68, he points out that Saint Ambrose, whose words he references, speaks of the bread that is the body of Christ and sustains the essence of our soul—not because it enters the body, but because it is the bread of eternal life.
Thus, it's clear, he states, which bread he refers to: the bread of the body of Christ, which nourishes our soul not by entering the body, but because it represents the bread of eternal life.
This view is very Catholic and orthodox.
It doesn't imply that the body of Christ is merely the Word of God, in which the soul is nourished and fulfilled, although it's essential to have faith in the Word of God and to love God wholeheartedly to truly receive the body of Christ.
In section 72, page 296 of the Amsterdam edition, he explains that the flesh of Christ is spiritually composed of two elements: the outward form it presents and the spiritual power of the divine Word—the invisible influence and divine strength of the Word of God in which one believes.
All these things are fabricated:
Here, he doesn't focus on the composition of the spiritual flesh of Christ, but rather explains the different and distinct ways the body of Christ is understood to exist, such as in the womb of the Blessed Virgin and on the cross.
Then he discusses what is known as the Eucharistic body.
In his writing, he demonstrates that the spiritual flesh of Christ, whether taken from the glorious Virgin, which grants the soul immortal life, results from the spiritual power, invisible effectiveness, and strength of God.
This differs from what is perceived by the senses compared to what is believed and understood by faith.
For whatever offers life substance within it possesses spiritual power and invisible effectiveness and divine strength.
It is vastly different from what is outwardly seen and what is believed in as a mystery.
Paschasius states, along with all defenders of the Catholic faith in chapter 11, concerning the body and blood of the Lord:
He will provide for the priest who considers the sanctity of the mystical sacrifice and its effectiveness, showing how the tangible is intelligibly transformed by the power of God through the word of Christ and his flesh and blood.
And in chapter 4:
It seems to be a figure when it is broken, when something different is understood in its visible appearance than what is perceived by sight and taste, and when the blood is mixed with water in the cup.
Moreover, that sacrament of faith is rightly called the truth.
Therefore, it is the truth when the body and blood of Christ are created by the Spirit's power in his words from the substance of bread and wine.
(Page 296, Amsterdam Edition, 191 Paris.)
Number 77 of Ratramnus:
He describes it as the true body, which the mind perceives through thought:
it exists in the understanding of faith, indeed invisible and spiritual, yet the mind itself recognizes it.
Observe how the body of Christ exists in the mystery within the minds of believers in the Word of God; outside the mind, it is not present on the altar.
All that's needed is to transcribe the ideas from number seventy-eight to show how unnecessary it is to attribute such an opinion to Ratramnus, particularly the suggestion that the body of Christ is not present on the altar outside the mind.
He states: what happens outwardly is one thing, and what is believed through faith is another.
Isn't it true that outwardly we see only the appearances of bread and wine, while inwardly we truly believe in the existence of the body of Christ?
What pertains to the body's senses is perishable, but what faith truly believes is imperishable.
Is there anything fictional or false about this?
While the appearances decay daily, the body of Christ, which is the object of faith, remains untouched by any corruption.
What appears outwardly is not the thing itself.
Whiteness, roundness, the taste of bread, the smell of wine—are these the body of Christ?
But isn't the image of the thing truly an image, a figure, a veil, a cover that deceives human eyes?
Truly, what is perceived by the mind is the truth of the thing, because the thing itself is the body of Christ; the truth of the thing is the truth of the body of Christ.
And since it is truth, not a mere illusion or a construct of reason, does it exist only in the mind's thought and not as a true and solid object for the mind itself?
Amsterdam Edition, page two hundred ninety-six, Paris.
191.
Numbers eighty-nine and ninety-four.
Ratramnus says that the soul is spiritually nourished by faith, without considering what feeds the body, which is pressed by the tooth and divided into parts, but focuses on what is received spiritually in faith.
This undoubtedly implies that outside of faith, there is nothing but what feeds the body, pressed by the tooth.
Nor can it be refuted what the Church of God professes with Paul and Augustine, indeed with Christ the Lord.
What you see is my body.
We've already mentioned that the nourishment of the soul, provided by the flesh and blood of Christ, doesn't happen like natural nourishment—it's not about the flesh itself becoming part of the soul's substance.
Instead, it's about the infusion of grace through faith, hope, and charity.
However, this doesn't mean it's not the true body of Christ.
Through its reception, we gain spiritual nourishment via the power and virtue of the Spirit of God.
Given this, it's important to point out how mistaken the author is when he claims that Ratramnus suggested the Eucharist offers nothing but bodily nourishment apart from faith.
Ratramnus doesn't say this; he states that what is received spiritually with faith nourishes the soul.
There's a significant difference between faith and what is perceived through faith, just like there is between sight and what is seen.
Ratramnus aligns wonderfully with Paschasius in making the distinction between those who approach the sacred communion of Christ's body worthily and those who don't.
Everyone receives the sacraments of the altar indiscriminately, but one person eats the flesh of Christ spiritually and drinks the blood, while another does not, even if they both appear to receive the morsel from the priest's hand.
Regarding the author's claim that Ratramnus teaches something contrary to what the Church of God professes with Paul, Augustine, and Christ the Lord—"This which is seen is my body"—we've explained this many times. We can't respond better than with the words of the blessed Alger in Book 1 on the Eucharist, chapter 11.
Similarly, Augustine to Irenaeus says: "Not what you see is what you will eat; it is indeed and not itself, itself invisibly and not itself visibly."
Therefore, "If it must be celebrated visibly, it must be understood invisibly."
Thus, since the body of the Lord is not physical food but spiritual, it must be understood invisibly.
Thus speaks the strongest defender of the Catholic faith against Berengarius, fittingly supporting the thoughts and opinions of our Ratramnus, whom no Catholic could accuse of error or heresy for his words.
What you see in the Eucharist is not the physical body of Christ, as it is neither visible nor tangible.
Instead, it is truly what is hidden and concealed beneath the visible appearances of bread and wine, which were once and are now transformed into the substance of the body and blood of Christ, meant to be received by the faithful.
For this reason, in number 15, he denies that the body of bread is changed.
Why?
Because, he says, physically, nothing appears to be altered in them.
Indeed, but it is still believed.
In number fifteen, he doesn't deny that the substance of the bread changes.
Instead, he uses the numbers to show that this change isn't detectable by human senses, which no one doubts.
Physically, he notes that nothing seems to change.
Therefore, they have to admit that the change is beyond the physical body.
At the end of this section, after proving that some change must occur in the Eucharist, he states: If they wish to argue otherwise, they are forced to deny that it is the body and blood of Christ, which is not only wrong to say but even to think.
What could more strongly support the doctrine of the Catholic Church than these words?
I'm amazed that the lecturer never considered these with focused attention.
In the same place, and in number sixteen, he mentions that the change is figurative and spiritual, as we've noted, which happens through the understanding of faith.
This is false; Ratramnus never spoke in such a manner, nor did he claim that this change occurs through the understanding of faith.
On the contrary, he asserts that a transformation should occur from bread and wine into the body and blood of Christ.
As he mentions in passage thirty, bread and wine are transformed into the substance of the body and blood by the power and might of the Divine Word.
Indeed, he teaches that such a change does not occur in a physical or tangible way, but spiritually and beyond the senses, as Paschasius, Alger, Lanfranc, and all Catholic writers have stated.
Therefore, Ratramnus states in passage sixteen, that under the appearance of corporeal bread and wine, the spiritual body and blood of Christ exist.
Although the body is real, it is beyond the comprehension of the mind, yet it is spiritual and glorious, like our bodies will be after they are resurrected.
They will indeed be the same as they are today, living on earth, but revived in heaven and glory, differing from their current state of mortality by the substance of immortality.
What Ratramnus stated in his continuous speech confirms the sincerity of his faith so clearly that nothing can weaken it.
It's not that there are two separate existences, namely body and spirit, but rather one and the same thing.
In one aspect, it appears as bread and wine, but in another, it is the body and blood of Christ.
Nothing more fitting can be said for the Catholic faith, nor can I understand why the disturbed speaker might interpret these words as indicating that only the substance of bread is present on the altar, by whose reminder the body of Christ, which is believed, enlivens the minds of believers.
And that what is perceived is called the spiritual body of Christ.
On the contrary, since he acknowledges the transformation of bread and wine into the body and blood of Christ, and that the physical and sensible appearances do not differ from Christ's spiritual or glorious body, it is manifestly consistent.
Ratramnus found it difficult to grasp that, in this mystery, the substance remains bread, which, when contemplated, nourishes and invigorates the soul with the body that is believed.
This is what is understood as a spiritual body.
Page 276, Amsterdam edition and 191, Paris edition.
From this, we must conclude what he states freely and openly in number 40.
The Lord's body and blood are referred to as symbols because they derive their name from the true body and blood in which Christ was born.
They are a sacrament that inspires memory and faith.
The symbols aren't just called the body of Christ because they remind us of it or awaken faith in it, but because sacraments and mysteries are named after what they contain.
That's why Blessed Algerus refers to the Eucharist as the nominative body of Jesus Christ, as it represents and covers it.
These appearances and representations resemble the body of Christ and present its image, not simply because they bring back its memory, but because they nourish the body.
Just like the Word of God, which is the living bread from heaven, nourishes and refreshes the souls of the faithful who partake in it.
Just as the substance of this visible bread and wine nourishes and intoxicates the outer person, so the Word of God, which is the living bread, refreshes the minds of the faithful through participation.
Moreover, we shouldn't overlook that Pseudo-Ratramnus, with notable audacity, has corrupted the testimonies of the Fathers he abuses, especially those of Ambrose and Augustine.
The illustrious bishop Peter de Marca has already warned us about Ambrose, in the testimony that the impostor recites in number fifty-nine, that these words were removed: "What we make is the body from the Virgin."
Ratramnus did not alter or corrupt Saint Ambrose when he quoted from his book, "On the Mysteries," chapter nine.
Nor did the esteemed and knowledgeable Peter de Marca ever accuse him of such corruption.
This is clear from his letter to Lord Lucas d'Achery, found in volume five of the "Spicilegium."
He simply notes that Ratramnus could have wisely and skillfully used these words from the same chapter of Saint Ambrose:
"This which we make is the body from the Virgin," which appear earlier in the chapter, separated by fifty lines.
Paschasius could have used the same words, yet he wouldn't be called a corrupter of Ambrose for that reason.
But if we act in good faith, can an ecclesiastical writer justly be accused of distortion and corruption, and be charged as an eraser or imposter for omitting certain words that are fifty lines apart from the cited location?
Certainly not.
If I were to ask all the scholarly Fathers what it means to corrupt an author's text, they would unanimously say that it is to remove words from the text and use it to introduce a heretical meaning as Catholic and attribute it to the author.
The reader will find ample examples of such crimes in the "Critical Colloquy on the Errors of Illustrious Men in Literature," compiled in the works of Marcellus of Ancyra.
Meanwhile, note the audacity of the dissertation on page 184, where it takes these words of Ratramnus from number 56:
"Understand that the body and blood of Christ exist not in appearance, but in truth, which are seen," which provide a completely Catholic and orthodox sense.
The dissertator removed the word "seen" and wrote in Ratramnus's text "believed," to convict Ratramnus of the crime of Calvinist heresy, as we have already observed in response to objection 39, which it seems tedious and unnecessary to repeat here.
(Page 193 Paris, and 296 Amsterdam.)
Even in Augustine’s words, it is not much lighter.
During the sermon to the infants, when the holy doctor mentioned: Pseudo-Ratramnus read, "You receive the mystery of the Lord."
Every edition of his book has included this phrase since the first publication in 1522, with the exception of the last edition in 1686.
He deliberately did not change this passage from Augustine.
The intention was to demonstrate that the consecrated bread is referred to as a mystery in the same way that it is our mystery; meaning, it is merely a symbol of the Lord's body just as it is merely a symbol of the faithful.
It's easy to address this: the 1686 edition of Ratramnus, which I played a major role in editing, should be preferred over others.
This edition was meticulously copied from an 800-year-old manuscript of the Abbey of Lobbes with exceptional precision and fidelity.
However, if Ratramnus is criticized for interpolation due to the phrase "you receive the mystery of the Lord" instead of "you receive your mystery," then the same critique would apply to the sermon of Saint Fulgentius. This sermon appears at the end of the letter to Deacon Ferrandus with the wording "you receive the mystery of the Lord."
This can easily be verified from the edition of Saint Fulgentius's works produced in Lyon by the Sebusians, with the dedication and effort of Father Theophilus Rainaud, a knowledgeable and capable Jesuit.
Regardless of the situation, if there's room for conjecture among scholars beyond the authority of the ancient manuscript of Lobbes, I believe it should rather read "you receive your mystery" than "you receive the mystery of the Lord." This is because Ratramnus himself states in the previous line, "your mystery is placed on the Lord's table."
Therefore, it seems more just and fair to judge the faith of Ratramnus based on the ancient 800-year-old manuscript rather than the more recent corrupted and altered versions by heretical editors. Moreover, the conjecture of the dissertator is so misleading that it's clear he was overly zealous against Ratramnus.
Similarly, in number 33, when Augustine, whom we cited, said, "the mystery of the passion should be sweetly and usefully stored in memory," the dissertator, after removing and omitting the first two words, presented it as "should be faithfully stored."
This interpolation, although it might seem minor elsewhere, was used with the intent of suggesting that the mysteries are performed by the faithful through their faith, not by God Himself in the sanctified symbols.
It is the debater's responsibility to prove that Ratramnus altered Augustine's writings with this intention.
However, this interpolation is so minor and trivial that the Calvinists dismissed it entirely, believing it didn't support their cause at all.
In the editions of Ratramnus they oversaw, they used "pleasantly and usefully" instead of "faithfully." This is particularly evident in the most recent edition made in London in 1681 and in Mr. Peter Allix's edition, minister of the Charenton temple, in 1672, as well as in all other editions published by Protestant scholars since 1532.
Furthermore, if the debater wants to stubbornly defend such a slight and trivial conjecture, I appeal to the common sense of learned individuals.
Who can truly believe that it's possible to remember the flesh of Christ on the cross for mankind's salvation pleasantly and usefully?
If not faithfully, then how faithfully?
If not pleasantly and usefully, what is the debater trying to achieve other than extracting water from a pumice stone through some peculiar effort?