Two Privileges of Pope Anastasius the Third
Privilege for the Church of Vercelli. (Year 912.)
ANASTASIUS, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to the most reverent and holy RAGEMBERTO, bishop of the holy Church of Vercelli, for the days of his life only.
Just as shepherds of sheep brave the cold and heat to protect their flock day and night, ensuring none are lost or taken by wild beasts, they remain ever watchful.
How much more effort and care should we, as shepherds of souls, dedicate to being vigilant and attentive, fulfilling our duty to protect the Lord's flock?
So that on the day of divine judgment, we are not punished for negligence before the supreme Shepherd due to our carelessness, which now brings us honor and elevation among others!
We grant your holiness the pallium to celebrate the solemnities of the masses, which we bestow upon you without altering the privileges of your Church.
Use it only on the day of the holy venerable Resurrection of our Lord Jesus Christ, on the birthdays of the holy apostles, on Saint John, on the Assumption of the blessed mother of God Mary, on the day of the birth of our Lord, on the solemnity of your Church, and on the anniversary of your ordination, as was done by our predecessor, Lord Gregory, the presiding bishop of this blessed see.
In the private chamber, your brotherhood should put on the pallium, then proceed to the solemnity of the masses.
Do not arrogate anything more to yourself with reckless presumption, for if something is improperly assumed in appearance, even those things that could have been done properly may be lost.
As the honor of this garment is to be preserved through modest actions, we encourage you to ensure that all ornaments are fitting, so that, with God as your guide, you may rightly and everywhere be notable.
Let your life be a guide for your children.
If they find any strength within themselves, let them channel it by watching and imitating you, always striving to improve by following your example.
After God, let your goodness be reflected in how they live.
Don't let temporary prosperity lift your heart too high, nor let adversity bring it down.
Whatever happens, face it with the virtue of patience.
Avoid hatred or indiscriminate favor.
Let the guilty recognize your strictness, and don't let false suggestions make you see the innocent as guilty.
Don't let grace excuse the guilty; avoid showing leniency to wrongdoers, so nothing goes unpunished.
Embody the sweetness of the good shepherd and the firmness of a true judge.
Support those who live innocently, and correct those who are restless.
Sometimes, the zeal of those in charge can turn correction into cruelty in an attempt to be strict.
Manage your anger with judgment, and use discipline to address faults without withdrawing your love from those you correct.
Show mercy to the poor as much as you can, defend the oppressed, and stand firm against those with different intentions.
Do not favor anyone over justice, and do not dismiss those seeking fairness.
Strive to uphold fairness, so the wealthy don't sway us from the right path, nor should the humility of the poor lead them to despair.
With God's mercy, aim to be the person sacred scripture instructs, saying: "A bishop must be blameless" (First Timothy 3:2).
You can use all these principles beneficially if love is your guide, ensuring you never stray from the path.
Behold, dearest, among many other things, these are the duties of a priest.
If you carefully maintain your cloaks and show that you've received them externally, you'll keep them internally as well.
May the Holy Trinity envelop you with its protective grace and guide you along the path of reverence, so that after the hardships of this life, we can together reach eternal joy.
This was written by John, secretary of the Holy Roman Church, in February during the fifteenth indiction.
Farewell.
Issued on February tenth by Theophylact, treasurer of the Holy Apostolic See, in the year of the pontificate of Lord Anastasius, the supreme pontiff, with God's favor, and of Scili Junior, Pope, from the most sacred seat of the blessed Peter the apostle, in the fifteenth indiction.
Privilege for the Church of Hamburg. (Year 912.)
Anastasius, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to the beloved brother Hoger, the venerable archbishop of the Church of Hamburg, eternal greetings.
It is fitting for the apostolic authority to assist those who excel in pious devotion with benevolent compassion and to eagerly support those who ask for help.
For from this, we undoubtedly earn the greatest reward from God when places of reverence, properly managed, are brought by us to a better state.
Therefore, because you asked us to confirm the entire archbishopric of Hamburg for you and your successors, as it was decreed by our predecessors Gregory and Nicholas of this apostolic see, we, moved by your prayers, grant and confirm by apostolic authority, with all things generally and specifically pertaining to that same mentioned archbishopric.
Namely, all things that your predecessors acquired through their efforts, or even those granted there by faithful Christians for the love of the eternal homeland, or that are still being granted.
Also, with those who at this time have been converted to the faith of Christ, encouraged and protected by the grace of God, namely bishops among all the peoples of the Swedes, Danes, Norwegians, Icelanders, Greenlanders, and all northern nations.
As well as in those parts of the Slavs, which are from the river Peene to the river Eider, so that they remain under the authority of you and your successors, archbishops of the Church of Hamburg.
Or whatever can be acquired by you, with the favor of divine grace, from the error of unbelief, whether of people or places, to the Christian religion.
We also send you the pallium, and we decree that its use be held perpetually and inviolably by you and your successors.
Furthermore, we have decreed that no archbishop, whether of Cologne or any other, should claim any authority in your diocese, and so forth.
We also allow your head to be adorned with a miter, a symbol of the Romans.
If anyone tries to oppose or violate this privilege of our authority in any way, let them be cursed.
But whoever observes it faithfully will receive grace and blessings from our Lord Jesus.
Issued by the hand of Adrian, secretary of the holy Roman Church, in the month of January, in the 8th indiction.