On the Birth of the Virgin
by Paschasius Radbertus, the Abbot of Corbie
Admonition
This small work on the Virgin Birth, whether it was by Ildephonsus of Toledo, Archbishop, or Paschasius Radbertus, Abbot of Corbie, had long been in doubt when I first published the first volume of Spicilegium.
However, our John Mabillon, with very certain arguments, proved it to be by Paschasius Radbertus.
It seemed right to include those very arguments here, by which the aforementioned small work, now presented by me in full, is attributed to Radbertus.
Francis Feuardent, a theologian from Paris, published some small works of Ildephonsus in the Library of the Fathers.
Among them is the book on the Virginity of Saint Mary against three unbelievers, whose Prologue begins: "God, true light, who enlightens every man," etc., and starts with: "O my lady and my mistress," etc.
He added another book attributed to Ildephonsus on the perpetual virginity of Saint Mary and her childbirth, with this beginning: "Although the virginity of the blessed and glorious Mother of God Mary is the honor of all Churches," etc.
We discovered with very certain arguments that the first book is by Ildephonsus, but the latter is by Radbertus, Abbot of Corbie.
Ildephonsus published the book on Virginity, full of testimonies from the Old and New Testaments, says Zixilanes.
This way of speaking clearly appears in the first book, but not in the latter.
Furthermore, Ildephonsus, according to Julian, wrote the book on Virginity against three unbelievers, specifically against Jovinian, Helvidius, and the Jews, as is evident from the letter of Quiricius, which is prefixed to Ildephonsus' works in a manuscript.
Ildephonsus openly addresses and criticizes these same unbelievers by name in this first book.
In the latter book, however, the status of the question is completely different: the testimonies of the Fathers are everywhere brought in for confirmation.
Among these are praised and cited Gregory the Great's Moralia, Augustine, Jerome, Cyril of Alexandria, Peter of Ravenna, and others, whom Ildephonsus does not even mention in his work.
Lastly, there is a great difference in style between the two works.
Hildefonsus, by compiling synonyms, challenges his adversaries; Radbertus, on the other hand, proceeds with greater gravity, which befitted his elder status in the latter book.
He dedicates his work to the abbess and nuns of Saint Mary at Soissons, where he was educated, as will be evident from the title of the work mentioned later.
Thus, he often calls them dear mothers and matrons.
Therefore, it is Radbertus, not Hildefonsus, who should be considered the author of this latter book.
During his time, a controversy arose among Catholics about how Saint Mary gave birth to Christ.
Some asserted he was born in the natural and common way of other men, while others, including Radbertus, opposed this view.
This question emerged in Germany, as taught by Ratramnus, a monk from Corbie, who opposed Radbertus' view in a booklet he composed on this topic and addressed to someone unknown to him (not, therefore, to Radbertus, the abbot of his monastery).
Radbertus seems to respond to Ratramnus, calling the adversaries brothers with these words:
But because the rashness of some brothers now again labors indecently by questioning, I have decided to write to you, matrons of Christ, about these things, which they themselves try to explore more curiously against her chastity than religiously.
To understand the state of the controversy: I do not say, he states, that they claim she lost her virginity, who, not knowing a man, conceived as a virgin, gave birth as a virgin, and remained a virgin; but because they deny the very thing they confess, while they say she gave birth to a son according to the common law of nature.
Hence, the great difference between the work of Hildefonsus and Radbertus becomes apparent.
Hildefonsus argues against three infidels; Radbertus against brothers.
Hildefonsus argues against Helvidius and the Jews, who deny the virginity of the Mother of God.
Radbertus argues against Catholic theologians, who admit the same virginity of the Mother of God but do not explain it correctly: like those who said Mary gave birth to Christ with her virginal gates expanded; which certainly Jovinian, whom Hildefonsus opposes, had already intended.
Radbert divided his work into two books, dedicated to the nuns of Soissons, with this inscription found in the Corbie manuscripts:
"To the venerable matron of Christ along with the holy virgins living a monastic life in Soissons, Paschasius Radbertus, the least of all monks, etc."
If Fevardentius had seen this inscription, he would have undoubtedly attributed it to Radbert as his own genuine work.
The book begins with: "Since all the Churches, etc.," as found in the Library of the Fathers up to the middle of the booklet.
From the place where this note is read, something is missing here, and the handwritten manuscripts differ entirely from the printed versions. They substitute part of the sermon attributed to Hildefonsus, which is titled among the printed works concerning the Purification of Saint Mary.
The second book of Radbert is the same homily that follows the aforementioned sermon in the printed versions, beginning with: "Among the words of the holy Scriptures, etc."
Mabillon noted this, but Acherius, who was copying it, forgot to mention that Radbert's work was copied from an old Corbie manuscript and compared with another from the same monastery.
Both believe that these two books were sent to the virgins living in Soissons, which we will reconsider immediately.
Book One
Preface
To the venerable matron of Christ, along with the holy virgins living monastically in Vesona from PASCHASIUS RADBERTUS, the humblest of all monks.
Dearest ones, I have decided to address the question recently brought to me about the birth of the blessed Virgin Mary; because I know you value this topic greatly.
I want you to understand how much I, who have been away from you since childhood and am now advanced in years, have considered it.
Although the virginity of the blessed and glorious Mother of God, Mary, is an honor, glory, and model of virtue for all churches, it is especially so for the holy virgins, whose chastity is deeply illuminated by her virtues, guided by her examples, and strengthened by her merits.
Therefore, venerating and recounting her most sacred childbirth with a devoted mind and heart is truly a grace of divine gift.
To combat and overcome heretical depravity requires the work of the Holy Spirit and the power of the Most High, who overshadowed her; allowing her to give birth to the Lord and man without male union and without any corruption, and always remain a virgin.
For this, we read that the blessed Jerome wrote long ago against the heretic Helvidius and his accomplices; he defeated and overcame them so thoroughly that no relapse of error against her has arisen up to the present.
But now, because the reckless boldness of some brothers is once again raising questions, I have decided to write to you, matron of Christ, about these matters.
These brothers attempt to investigate more curiously than religiously against her purity; by exploring her virgin birth and the purity of her womb, the most skilled physiologists cunningly introduce a mix of vices through their arguments, leading to many dangers of error.
They claim that the blessed Virgin Mary could not have given birth in any other way, nor should she have, than by the common law of nature, and as is the custom of all women, for the true birth of Christ to be acknowledged.
Otherwise, they argue, if He was not born as other infants are, it is not a true birth.
And therefore, lest it be thought a fantasy, or just as water flows through a channel, he might be believed to have been born through the womb of the Virgin without the process of birth, it is pious to believe that he was born according to the law of nature, just as other infants are born, and that she gave birth just as other women do.
O blind piety, which thinks so impiously of the Virgin Mary, and blind presumption, which speaks so impiously of Christ.
I am not saying that they claim she lost her virginity, who conceived as a Virgin without knowing a man, gave birth as a Virgin, and remained a Virgin; but because they deny what they confess, by saying she brought forth a son according to the common law of nature.
If it is as they assert and affirm, which heaven forbid, then Mary is no longer a virgin, Christ was born under a curse, a child of wrath from sinful flesh, and she, who is proclaimed blessed by the angel, remains under a curse and gave birth under a curse.
Otherwise, what is it that they require the law of nature in Mary, where everything in her was possessed by the Holy Spirit?
Which the power of the Most High overshadowed?
If the power of the Most High overshadowed her from all the heat of sin, in conception and in birth, just as she was free from all the heat of lust, so she was also free from all pressure of the curse, not of herself, but by the power of the Most High, she was immune and separate.
Therefore, let them consider the laws of divine things, because divine laws do not depend on the nature of things, but the laws of the nature of things are proven to flow from divine laws.
Therefore, it is presumptuous to assert about Christ that he was born according to the common law of nature, who was not conceived in the womb according to the use of nature, from the flesh of the Virgin.
For even the law of nature, under which women now conceive and give birth, if I may say so, is not truly the law of nature in a way, but of curse and fault; because if Adam and Eve had not first sinned in paradise, no one would be born under the guilt of sin.
And therefore, this common law of birth is not of nature, but of corruption and fault.
Mary, because she was blessed and had no stain of corruption, gave birth to Christ without pain and without corruption.
If Christ had been born from corruption or with pain, He would have been born under a curse.
Genesis attests to this curse when the Lord said to Eve: "I will greatly multiply your pain and your conception" Genesis 3:16. Symmachus translated this as "your afflictions." Origen, Theodotion, and the Septuagint translated it as "your sufferings and groans." Both Theodotion and Symmachus used "afflictions" for "groans."
All these translations do not refer to the law of nature, as some unlearned natural philosophers claim, but to the law of vengeance, which multiplies and increases the cause of sin: labor in childbirth, afflictions, sufferings, and groans. In Hebrew, it is written: Shevil. Therefore, all who give birth do so not according to the original nature, but because of the fault and curse of just divine retribution.
But the blessed and most glorious Virgin Mary did not give birth according to the common law of nature, nor according to the original nature. She bore a son not from the seed of a man, but divinely conceived by the Holy Spirit from her own flesh, without any taint of sin, both God and man. Therefore, her childbirth should not be treated like others because, as the distinguished doctor Athanasius said in his little book of Faith, written in the form of a dialogue: "The Incarnate and Only Begotten, in His mysterious secret that He alone knows." He continues: "It is ours to believe, and His to know."
Therefore, let them hear that it is only His to know how He was conceived, how He lived in the womb, how the Word, God and man, was born from the virgin as one Christ. As he said, "God the Word fully took on what is human to become human, and the assumed human fully took on what is divine to be God." If this is so, as he confessed, or rather because it is so, where, I ask, is the common law in birth, where is the taint of sin?
For Christ, who is God and has always existed, from the moment He became man and united in one person, has always remained and continues to be true God and true man.
Not two separate beings-one being God and the other being man-but one and the same being, both God and man.
Although there is a distinction by which He is God and a distinction by which He is man, in both respects He is one God and one man.
He was never conceived or born as a mere man without God.
Because He was conceived by the Holy Spirit from a virgin's flesh and truly born as a man, from His very conception, through an ineffable birth, He emerged as true God and was born as man.
How then can that which is ineffable be commonly spoken of?
Or how is Christ not always entirely true God, if He was never conceived or born without being true God?
Therefore, just as it is rightly believed that He was conceived with closed bodily organs, so it is entirely believed that He was born with a closed womb.
He did not lack any human capability in being born from a virgin, just as He never ceased to be God and one Christ.
He willed to be born in the unity of true God and man, so that everything about His birth would be true, ineffable in how He was born, and entirely credible that He was born from a virgin without the stain of sin, just as He was free from any contagion of the original sin.
Therefore, let the reckless investigators of such a great mystery listen and understand that these are not the rights of humanity in being born, nor the law of, I do not say, a condemned nature, but even not the law of the first origin before sin.
God and man, from a virgin, thus Christ was born.
As blessed Cyril says in the Letter to Nestorius, a common man was not born from the holy Virgin.
In the very womb of the virgin, as he himself confesses, the Word united with flesh and endured a carnal generation.
He made his own birth of the flesh, and he who made man in the form of God, was made man in the form of a servant.
Both God from the power of the one receiving, and both man from the humility of the one received.
Therefore, such a birth is not common by the law of nature, but as he was miraculously conceived, so miraculously God and man were born.
It was not adoption like the others that made him the Son of God, but the nature of divinity exalted him into the proper Son of God, and gave him the name that is above every name Philippians 2, so that he was entirely the Son of God, man and Word.
He was never not the Son of God, who remains the only begotten of the only begetter forever.
Therefore, he was never conceived or born as a mere human like other infants are born, such that the title of son would be granted to him by the grace of adoption or by the merit of virtues.
The Word of God, because it became flesh, assumed man into himself without the person of man, so that the whole Christ would be proper, not by the gift of grace being reborn like others, but preserving the property of both natures.
Indeed, he did not assume the person of man, but only man, because he himself, as the third person with the Father and the Spirit, has always been one God in the Trinity.
Therefore, in accordance with his eternal right, he did not assume a person but a man in time, whom he did not have before, so that he who assumed and what was assumed, as the blessed Augustine says in his book on Predestination, would be one person in the Trinity.
As Augustine says elsewhere, the Word of God was born of the Father, and the Word made flesh was born of the mother.
The same one and only Son of God was born before the ages and born in the age.
Both births are of one Son of God.
Therefore, the Virgin Mary is rightly called the Mother of God because she gave birth to God and man.
The Word made flesh, not in the way other infants are born, or as men are made by the gift of grace, but, as the blessed Gregory says in his Morals, he assumed man into his person while preserving the property of both natures essentially.
Through this miraculous sacrament, he was both eternal from the Father and temporal from the mother, one and the same true Son of God and man.
As Gregory says in the same Morals, it is one thing for men to be born to receive the grace of adoption through him, and another for one singularly to come forth as God from conception by the power of divinity.
Therefore, I ask, let these people stop saying that he was born like others are born.
For the virgin Mother of God did not give birth to him from the origin of the first transgression so that he should be reborn, but from the Holy Spirit so that he might be believed to be God, without pain and without groaning, without distress and hardship, without sorrow and affliction, for all these are just retributions and punishments of damned flesh from the first origin.
But the blessed Mary, although she was born and conceived from sinful flesh, was already, when the grace of the Holy Spirit came upon her, called blessed among all women by the angel.
The Holy Spirit, he said, will come upon you, and the power of the Most High will overshadow you.
Luke chapter 1, verse 35.
Otherwise, if she was not sanctified and cleansed by the same Holy Spirit, how could her flesh not have been sinful flesh?
And if His flesh came from the mass of the first transgression, how was Christ, the Word made flesh, without sin, who took flesh from sinful flesh, unless the Word that became flesh first overshadowed it?
The Holy Spirit came and the power of the Most High completely filled it.
Therefore, truly the flesh was no longer sinful flesh.
In this, God completely poured Himself, and the Word that became flesh came to us without sin.
He not only did not inherit the law of corrupted nature at birth, but also did not inherit the law of the first origin that women would have had if the mother of all, Eve, had kept the commandment in paradise.
Otherwise, how was she filled with the Holy Spirit and without original sin, whose glorious birth is declared happy and blessed in every Church of Christ by all?
For if she were not blessed and glorious, her feast would not be celebrated everywhere by everyone.
But because it is so solemnly observed, it is established by the authority of the Church that she was subject to no sins when she was born, nor did she contract original sin in the womb where she was sanctified.
Hence, although the days of Jeremiah and Job are pronounced cursed-the day of their birth-yet the day when the happy birth of Mary began is pronounced blessed and is observed with sufficient piety.
If she were in sin, she would rightly be called cursed and mournful rather than blessed when it was announced to her father that she was born into the world.
But now, because the blessed Virgin Mary illuminates the entire Church with her blessing, is she not deservedly venerated, sanctified in the Holy Spirit?
Therefore, no one's birth is celebrated in the world except Christ's, His, and the blessed John's.
Thus, if the blessed Virgin Mary had not been sanctified in her mother's womb, her birth would not be celebrated.
But now, because she is venerated by the authority of the whole Church, it is established that she was free from all original sin, through whom not only was the curse of the mother Eve lifted, but also a blessing is granted to all.
If the renowned and most sacred Virgin's birth is universally celebrated and honored as holy and glorious, how much more should she be honored when, already full of grace, she is greeted by the angel with respect?
For when he says to her (Luke 1:28), "Hail," he offers her heavenly reverence. When he says, "Full of grace," he shows that anger is completely driven out and grace is restored. When he says, "Blessed are you," he demonstrates the fruit of blessing. Because when the Holy Spirit came upon her, he purified the Virgin from all impurities and refined her, making her holier than the stars of heaven. Moreover, when the power of the Most High overshadowed her, the Word, which was eternal with the Father from the beginning, immediately came into her womb to become flesh in time and dwell among us.
Therefore, let the new debaters and investigators of the new and unheard-of birth listen and understand first, as they are men, how they might properly debate the nature and sex of women. Then, as they seek to understand nature and the common law of birth, let them consider what divine power accomplishes: "Who shall declare His generation?" (Isaiah 53:8).
For "who" here is taken as impossible, because no saint, not to mention divinity, can fully describe His human generation, though all should believe in both.
From this, it follows that their hesitation and needless debate are superstitious, as they claim He opened the womb's gates and brought forth the impurities of blood like all others, and carried the defilements of the fertile, in which groans and pain are multiplied, and sorrow and hardships are increased, so no one gives birth to a son without these. But let it be far from the hearts of the faithful to suspect such a thing of the Virgin Mary, who brought blessing to the world instead of the curse of the first origin.
Therefore, as I mentioned, she is proclaimed blessed among women by the angel and greeted most graciously as the glorious mother of the Lord above all others.
Elizabeth, in the spirit of prophecy, also declares her blessed, and the fruit of her womb is revered as blessed.
So, it is believed that her childbirth was not subject to the usual pains and groans of women, since such a great blessing and grace flowed through her.
Because the blessed Mother of God was free from sorrows and sufferings, she was untouched by any curse, filled with the Holy Spirit, and wholly dedicated to the Lord.
The power of the Most High overshadowed her, and from the sanctified flesh of the virgin, the Word took flesh and united it in the unity of person.
This is what is meant by "The Word became flesh," not by a mixing of natures, but by unity of person. So, regarding this birth, we rightly believe it is said: "Who shall declare his generation?" For this wondrous birth of the flesh is ineffable, surpassing the common laws of nature, and is understood through the sacrament of grace.
The fact that God is born as a man from a Virgin is not a customary event, but a mystery; not natural, but powerful and dignified; not an ordinary birth, but one of divine authority. Therefore, human wisdom should only seek to understand that the Word became flesh and was born as he wished, when and how he wished.
Otherwise, who can grasp what is unheard of and ineffable? What can human intelligence rightly seek in this divine and incomprehensible narrative? As the Evangelist says: "The birth of Christ was like this" (Matthew 1:18).
Indeed, this carnal generation was unique.
The Evangelist did not say "it was made thus," but "it was thus," indicating that the generation of Christ with the Father is ineffable. Through this previously mentioned and ineffable manner, he was born of a mother. Therefore, what he was, he always was. And what always existed from eternity could be made in time; whatever was made in him is not surprising.
They are greatly mistaken who claim that someone born under the common law of nature was not conceived according to that law.
The law of birth, now called the law of nature, originates from the fault of the first condemnation.
The Apostle says: "We were all once children of wrath, just like the others" Ephesians 2:3. However, the faithful should never believe that Christ was born a child of wrath, as others are born into the flaw of corruption, resulting in pain and groaning.
According to the flesh, there is neither groaning nor pain without the corruption of the womb, nor corruption without pain and groaning. Groaning and corruption in childbirth come from the fault and curse of the first origin.
Therefore, let us question the followers of the heretic Helvidius, who, although they do not deny that Mary remained a virgin, defile her purity and the grace she is proclaimed to be full of by saying she gave birth according to the common law of corrupted nature.
If she had given birth this way, she would still be subject to the curse of the first condemnation, contradicting the angel's word and the Word of the Father. It is far from the truth that the Word of the Father would have assumed human flesh from sinful flesh.
Since it is contrary to the Catholic faith to think this way, the Blessed Virgin, full of grace, neither felt pain nor suffered the corruption of her womb. She was free from fault, with the Holy Spirit cooperating in her and the power of the Most High overshadowing her. She was thus free from the curse of the first condemnation and the groaning and pains that afflict all daughters of Eve during childbirth.
Therefore, the Prophet, speaking for Christ, says to the Father: "You are the one who brought me out of the womb; you made me trust at my mother's breasts" Psalm 22:10. When he says, "you are the one who brought me out," he declares his unique birth, sweetness from the womb.
Otherwise, everyone who comes into the world from their mother's womb is brought forth by the will and operation of God. However, Christ, conceived in a special and ineffable way from the Virgin, entered the world without his mother suffering.
Therefore, it is right to believe that God and man were born into the world in a new and marvelous way, unlike any other.
Consequently, Jeremiah testifies: "The Lord will create a new thing on the earth; a woman will encompass a man" (Jeremiah 31:22).
It was indeed new and marvelous that a virgin conceived without seed and without any corruption by a man, making the birth entirely unique.
Thus, it is equally believable that, in a similar new and marvelous way, He was born into the world without pain, groaning, or any corruption of the flesh.
This is why it is specially mentioned in the psalm that is entirely about Him.
To the Father, He said, "You are the one who brought me out of the womb," as if to say: "You brought me out not in the usual manner, causing great distress to the mother, but with a new exit that preserved her modesty. Indeed, You brought me out of my mother's womb without disrupting the integrity of her body."
To clarify that it was not a mere illusion, as some heretics claimed, He added: "My hope from my mother's breasts." Therefore, by mentioning the mother and breasts, the truth of His flesh and not a phantom is affirmed.
Although He was born from a closed womb, which He Himself made passable while keeping the seal of modesty intact, He was created from the flesh of the Virgin and thus rightly remembered as having been suckled by her breasts.
All of this happened so that a new thing was made on the earth when the Word became flesh, and He was called Emmanuel, which means "God with us" (Matthew 1:23).
This is the enclosed garden in the Song of Songs, the sealed fountain (Song of Songs 4).
The garden was enclosed when God entered and found her incorrupt; the fountain remained sealed when God and man were born from her, without violating the integrity of her modesty or blood.
For the blood and fountain of modesty, which were not corrupted in the conception of the offspring by the union of a man, should not be corrupted in the birth, which would have involved the mother's torment and the contamination of her chastity.
This is certainly why the Church, based on the authority of the holy Fathers, sings about her birth: "And the mother has joy," it says, "along with the virginity of modesty." This was corrected by other distinguished men to say, "along with the virginity of honor." The greatest honor of virginity is if a virgin gives birth to both God and man, and yet, despite being born of a human, she is not afflicted by any sufferings that would mar the seal of modesty.
In Greek, sufferings are called "kakia," which severely afflict both body and soul. But blessed Mary endured none of these; she had joy in the fruit and honor in giving birth. Hence, it is also said that the Virgin conceived, gave birth, and remained a virgin. Therefore, it is said that she conceived and gave birth while remaining in an equal condition. Indeed, women in childbirth do not usually come together with men, so a virgin cannot be said to have lost her virginity when there is no desire or possibility of union, but the integrity of the virgin and the honor and incorruptibility of the flesh are upheld.
Otherwise, since we men do not know the nature of that sex, let us ask virgins, let us equally ask married women. Virgins, so that we may know what the integrity of flesh and blood is; married women, to know if there is any corruption or pain in childbirth, unless it involves contamination of blood and the receipt of semen. We do not gladly impose embarrassment on you, dearest, as we speak about these matters not without great shame. But it is an honor of exceptional piety and a virtue for you to proclaim the chastity of the blessed Virgin as uncorrupted and uncontaminated, and to confess that she is free from all taint of original sin.
If we ask virgins about this, they know the grace of incorruption but do not know the fruitfulness of offspring. If, however, we inquire of those dedicated to marriage, they indeed know the pressures and groans of Eve's curse, they know the fruitfulness of semen amid hardships and sorrows, but they do not know the integrity of virginity, neither in conception nor in childbirth.
Blessed indeed is the Mother of the Lord, who remained a virgin in both conception and birth.
That is, a mother in conception and a virgin in childbirth, because in neither of these was she tainted by the example of other women.
She neither admitted Adam to herself nor conceived a son through Eve's corruption, nor did she give birth to the Lord under the curse with pains and distress.
Hence, it is clear that just as she conceived with a closed womb, she also gave birth with a closed womb, not by the common law of corrupted and cursed nature, but by the grace of the Holy Spirit and the power of the Most High, by which it is said she was overshadowed.
But some people, striving as much as they can, try to claim that the Virgin gave birth in sin and bring insults to her chastity.
They take from the Gospel: quote "When the days of her purification were completed, they brought Jesus to Jerusalem to present him to the Lord, as it is written in the law of the Lord: Every male that opens the womb shall be called holy to the Lord" end quote (Luke 2:22-23).
They say, look, when it says the days of her purification were completed, the evangelist shows she was subject to the law of nature and was defiled by impurities, and that Jesus opened his mother's womb.
These reckless assertors, in thinking this way, completely misunderstand and destroy the sound doctrine that the churches have been taught about Christ, that the grace of the Holy Spirit proclaimed in mystery.
For it is not said that the days of her purification were completed as if the blessed Virgin needed purification for any sin, because she gave birth to the Lord Jesus Christ conceived by the Holy Spirit, but because she was under the law.
The Lord Jesus Christ, made under the law, born of a woman, observed the laws and precepts of the ancients in him by right for a time, until the law ceased and grace succeeded.
And this is the completion of the days according to the custom of the law and not according to the necessity of purification, because the blessed and undefiled virginity remained immaculate and uncorrupted, tainted by no impurities, troubled by no pains of Eve.
According to the angel's voice that brings joy to everyone, it cannot be that Christ Himself caused His mother suffering at His birth.
Among the angels' watches and praises, I do not believe He brought His mother the groans, pains, and sorrows of Eve.
Therefore, there was a different purification for those women in which not only were the sins of the soul purified, but also the faults of the body.
A different purification for Mary, in which the custom of the law was observed only for the sake of the mystery, because she who bore God incarnate, the purifier of all, needed no purifications.
Moreover, the completion of her days of purification was for no other reason than the fulfillment and custom of the law.
The purification and separation of other women are for many reasons, where the faults of the soul and the body are purified.
Hence, seven days are designated as unclean, during which a woman is commanded to sit in unclean blood, most unclean according to the days of her separation, and thirty-three days to sit in pure blood.
Yet, during all these days, the woman was unclean and filthy from many faults until the whole state of the body was restored, the bodies healed, and the blood ceased from its corrupted flow.
Thus, with the filth cleansed, the woman would be purified with divine sacrifices and offerings.
But blessed Mary needed no such sacrifices, as she bore the holy sacrifice from herself, through whom the world was purified.
For what the evangelist says, "Every male that opens the womb shall be called holy to the Lord," does not mean we are compelled to believe Christ opened His mother's womb as others did, but to teach that they presented Him to the Lord to do according to the custom of the law for Him. Because every male that opens the womb shall be called holy to the Lord, in the mystery of the law and the sacrament of sacred transgression.
For the evangelist did not bring this testimony from the law to show that Christ opened the virgin's womb like other firstborns, but to show that He was made under the law and came forth from the virgin's womb, not to be called holy, but to be essentially holy, to whom every closed thing is rightfully open.
The blessed Ambrose, explaining this passage in the Gospel, says in his commentary on Luke (book 2, chapter 2):
"It was not through a man's involvement that the secrets of the Virgin's womb were revealed, but the Holy Spirit infused an immaculate seed into her untouched womb.
This seed, as the aforementioned doctor explains, did not come from outside but from the flesh and blood of the Virgin herself.
We should not believe that the Holy Spirit provided the seed for the flesh, as Irenaeus suggests, but rather, this highlights the operation of the Holy Spirit."
Then he added: "For the holy Lord Jesus, alone among all born of women, did not experience earthly corruption because of the newness of his immaculate birth and repelled it with heavenly majesty."
And shortly after: "He then said, 'He alone opened the womb for himself; and it is no wonder.
For he who said to the prophet, 'Before I formed you in the womb, I knew you, and in your mother's womb I sanctified you' (Jeremiah 1:5), he who sanctified another's womb so that a prophet might be born, is the same one who opened his mother's womb so that he might emerge immaculate.
"
With these words, it certainly does not seem to me that he contradicts himself or other holy doctors, because he says that he alone opened the womb for himself.
He indeed opened it wonderfully by his own power, making the way passable while the Virgin's womb remained closed, just as the doors were closed when he entered through them to the disciples, and just as the sealed and closed tomb when he rose and went out through it."
Hence elsewhere he also says: "The gate of Christ becomes passable, filled with grace, and the king passes through and it remains closed."
He does not say this to suggest he contradicts himself, but so that you might fully understand that he was born from the womb and through the Virgin's womb, which he made passable for himself, thus opening the womb for himself.
Indeed, for himself, because although the Virgin's womb remained closed, it was passable to him; however, when he came into the world, he left it closed and sealed with the seal of chastity."
Absolutely, because nothing is difficult for God.
As someone once said, all nature obeys His commands.
Therefore, it is clear without a doubt that He was born in such a way that the secret womb of His mother remained intact and closed, which He Himself opened by His own power.
Moreover, He alone opened the womb of virginity of the holy Church, which He dedicated to Himself as a bride to generate people.
From this womb, the Prophet David sings, saying: "Sinners are estranged from the womb; they go astray from birth, speaking lies" (Psalm 57:4).
This describes the nature of heretics, who are estranged from the womb of the Church's integrity.
The Apostle earnestly endeavored to keep it immaculate and guard it as a virgin when he says: "For I am jealous for you with a godly jealousy. I promised you to one husband, to Christ, so that I might present you as a pure virgin to him" (Second Corinthians 11:2).
He then opened its secret womb when He granted the grace of being reborn through water and the Holy Spirit.
To this, the prophet says: "Rejoice, barren woman who does not bear. Break forth and shout, you who are not in labor, because more are the children of the desolate woman than of her who has a husband" (Isaiah 54:1).
Hence, also, Hannah in her song says: "Until the barren woman has borne many; and she who has many children has become feeble" (First Samuel 2:5).
Therefore, He alone is essentially holy, not by whom the mother is corrupted, but by whom the womb of the Church is opened, the firstborn among many brothers.
This was symbolically indicated through the divine law by prescribing the sanctification of the firstborn.
Not that they were truly holy, but because they were called so by the mystery of the law.
Otherwise, if we follow the letter, how could every male who opens the womb be holy, since it is well known that many were exceedingly wicked?
Was Ahab holy, or Joram, or others?
Were the false prophets whom the fire from heaven consumed at Elijah's prayer holy?
Certainly not.
But in the sacrament of future prefiguration, they were called holy when they were not, until Christ, who is essentially holy, came, who opened the womb of His bride and restored the fertility of bearing children.
He himself was deemed worthy of the Lord's presence; no one doubts that all others were merely symbols of what was to come, according to the law.
This is why they present him to the Lord, for he is the purification through the resurrection on the eighth day in Jerusalem, so that in him, all the adoption of the sons of God may be granted and offered.
For the law says, "Every male that opens the womb shall be called holy to the Lord," a promise of the Virgin's truly holy birth. He was pure, opening the womb of the Church so that all other things may be sanctified in him and be the firstborn.
Thus, the angel distinctly said to Mary, "And that which will be born of you will be called holy, the Son of God" (Luke 2:53).
Not that he corrupted his mother by being born; he left her intact and inviolate.
Because God made man was born from her, he opened the womb of the Church and made a path for himself in his flesh, keeping the chamber of the Virgin closed.
This showed that he took a Virgin as his mother and bride, demonstrating that she would remain a virgin and immaculate by such a great and noble birth.
Hence, it is clear that he was offered according to the law, just as he was circumcised.
He bore no original sin to be erased unless Christ himself were circumcised.
Yet, he was circumcised because he wished to be under the law to redeem those under the law, just as he was offered, so that he might offer us who were guilty as a sacrifice to God the Father in himself.
If he himself, heaven forbid, were impure to defile his mother, how would he cleanse us in his offering and make a sacrifice to God with a pleasing aroma?
Therefore, although he bore our pains and carried our illnesses, heaven forbid that he caused any injury or distress to his mother's honor.
Heaven forbid that she, through whom all the curse of Eve was lifted, should herself be subject to the curses of the first condemnation in childbirth.
Where virtue is born, it is hard to believe that such a great flood of vices exists there.
Where the joy of all is proclaimed, it's surprising that such sadness and groaning have intervened.
Among the company of angels, it's unexpected that an impure woman sat in unclean blood for seven days.
If this were the case, then the shepherds would not be permitted to enter in the morning according to the law.
But now, since an angel invites them to proclaim the good news, they come and see, find and understand the Word that had been foretold to them.
Therefore, it should not be believed that they found Mary in such filth, alone and distressed, as typically happens to new mothers.
At whose birth a multitude of angels sings: Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace among people of good will Luke 2:14
Therefore, where and by whom such peace is proclaimed, I do not believe that those disgraces or physical pains happened to the immaculate mother.
Also, the Magi then enter the house reverently and find what the shepherds found: Mary, Joseph, and the child.
They find her not tormented by pains, but attending to the child.
Then they bow down and worship, offering gifts to the one they find with his mother.
They worship, I say, her firstborn.
However, firstborn does not mean one followed by brothers, but one preceded by none.
Although some have preferred to say he should be called only-begotten rather than firstborn, the language of Scriptures states that whatever first opens the womb is called firstborn and sanctified to the Lord.
The Evangelist preferred to call him firstborn according to this custom rather than only-begotten.
Not because he opened the womb by the law of nature, as is the custom with other women, but because he was born of her as both firstborn and only-begotten, made under the law by divine law, so that through him the entire law might be fulfilled in spirit and letter.
For he is also called the firstborn from the resurrection among many brothers.
Therefore, since a species can be derived from a genus, although the only-begotten could be said by nature, it is more appropriate to call him the firstborn here, to indicate that many other brothers were already being gathered in him and through him as children of the Church by grace, whose womb he opened.
In the Old Testament, the firstborn were often given to those who were pre-chosen by God's grace, whose dignity was not from nature but from grace.
Thus, we also say that the firstborn is more significant than the only-begotten, so that through him, all who are gathered by grace may be united with him in the heavenly realms.
This was the figure represented by all those firstborn consecrated to the Lord under the law.
Therefore, it was fitting that from all these firstborn who opened the womb to the Lord, the Lord should be legally offered among them, whose form they all prefigured, so that he would be the firstborn holding primacy in all things.
Not one who tormented his mother's womb, but who opened the Church's womb.
I have said this so that the wise reader may understand that it is not the following brothers who make the firstborn, but Christ is certainly called the firstborn because everyone who is only-begotten, as he was his mother's only-begotten, may be called firstborn, but not all firstborn can rightfully be called only-begotten.
From this, it is understood that he should be called the firstborn, before whom there was no one and after whom there is no one, and not just the one whom brothers follow.
Therefore, Christ is rightfully called the firstborn from the virgin, not because he tormented the virgin's womb and unlocked the hall of modesty, but because he who was the firstborn of all creation from the beginning was born from her as both the only-begotten and the firstborn in the manner he willed, without the groaning and pain of childbirth.
For he is also rightly called the firstborn of baptism, who is said to have risen as the firstborn in the resurrection.
In both natures and births, although he is called the firstborn, he is rightfully believed to be the only-begotten, because he is the same Son of man and God; not different, but one and the same in both.
According to the principles of Catholic truth, it's clear that only a heretic would claim that Christ was born in the same way as other infants, following the common law of nature.
Although the renowned doctor, Jerome, in his work against Helvidius, seems to have conceded this point, he was actually challenging the heretic's disrespectful proposal.
Helvidius suggested that it was unworthy of divine majesty for Christ to be carried in the Virgin's womb or born in a humble manner, but Jerome argued otherwise.
By opposing these claims, Jerome did not concede but rather highlighted the dignity of God's glorious humility.
He argued that the more humble and dishonorable the circumstances that divine majesty endured for us, the more dearly He redeemed us and the more He is to be honored.
In his response to the heretic, Jerome made it clear that he did not bring any infamy or sin upon the Blessed Virgin.
Instead, he praised the divine condescension and immense self-emptying in the form of a servant, demonstrating the mercy of the Creator even to such heretics.
Therefore, Jerome did not yield to those who erred with Helvidius but corrected them, teaching them not to defame the Virgin or detract from God's humility.
He maintained that her chastity was never harmed and fought tirelessly with the word of God to defend her.
God granted him the grace and strength to resist his enemies and overcome them, ensuring that no one dared to rise against him.
I pray, most holy virgins of Christ, through your merits, that He who granted such eloquence and strength to vanquish adversaries may also grant me the grace of speaking and reveal what is worthy of this mystery in the Spirit of truth.
So that through you, O matrons of Christ, I, who have no merits of my own, may be found worthy to adequately defend the chastity of the mother of my Lord, and reveal the truth to those who do not believe, so they may repent and cease to speak falsehoods.
They claim that Christ could not be born differently from others, as if all births are described similarly in the divine Scriptures.
However, this birth is far different from those born under the curse, and different if Eve had not sinned.
This one is under the curse and suffering, but that one would have brought forth fruit in the bloom of blessing without groaning and pain.
Therefore, I ask, let them at least concede that type of birth to Christ from the Virgin Mary, by which all would have been born by common law if Eve had not sinned, a birth now known only to God and perhaps unknown to humans.
Let them not attribute to Him curses, groans, and sufferings, as He brings joy to His mother.
The more the Virgin was free from the corruption of passion, the pain of the flesh, and the filth of disgrace, the more she was full of grace and incorrupt, dedicated to the Holy Spirit and overshadowed by divine power.
The Holy Spirit has His own ways, described in sacred Scriptures and hidden by eternal laws.
There is one birth of flesh from flesh, another of God from God, and countless others.
Yet, not one mode of being born is the same for all, nor is their order of existence the same.
Although birth is equally attributed to each, Christ is rightly believed to be born of the Virgin Mary because He assumed flesh from her.
The birth itself, however, how it came to us, whether in the condition that Eve would have given birth if she had not sinned, or gloriously, because she gave birth to God and man and remained a virgin, is unnecessarily questioned.
In this matter, none of the saints wanted to doubt.
All proclaim with Catholic faith that she neither conceived in sin nor gave birth in sin and pain, nor did Christ draw any sin from her.
He did not draw sin from her, nor committed any, because he did not trouble his mother's modesty with any pains in being born, nor in any way stained her virginity.
So we do not say, as some claim, that he was born monstrously.
Instead, as foretold long ago by the prophets and handed down to us by the holy Fathers, she is the gate shown to Ezekiel, of which he says: "I saw a gate in the house of the Lord, and it was closed; and no man shall pass through it; because the Lord God of hosts has entered through it" (Ezekiel 44:2).
About this gate, blessed Ambrose, in that same hymn which I mentioned, composed in honor of the most holy Virgin, says: "The gate of Christ becomes passable, filled with grace, and the King passes through and remains closed, as it was, through the ages."
Therefore, when he says it becomes passable, he explains himself and shows the transition of his birth; when he says it remains closed, he shows the fulfillment of what was in the prophets. It would not be called closed if her integrity had been harmed in any way. But because the virginal modesty was in no way violated, nor was the font opened, the meaning is undoubtedly clear, because he came to us with the womb closed, just as he entered to the disciples with the doors closed.
Indeed, the sight of the disciples then proved both, namely that the doors were closed, and that the Lord, entering through the same, stood present before them. Thus our faith holds with certainty both about Christ: that her integrity was passable in his birth from her, and yet the womb was not opened. Otherwise, how can it be said to have remained closed if it was violated?
How could a woman in labor give birth without pain and without groaning if she followed the usual course of other women and delivered her child with distressed insides?
And if it was like that, as they say, how did she remain as closed as she was before giving birth?
For those doors were no more penetrable when closed than the untouched womb of the Virgin.
Therefore, it is not unreasonable to believe that the Lord came to us in this way, so that the birth of Christ from the flesh of the Virgin would be proven, and the Virgin would not be tormented by any pains.
They might say that the body, already incorruptible and immortal, would pass through more easily wherever it wanted than it did before it was resurrected.
But certainly, no one who thinks sensibly would say this, because from the moment He was conceived as a man, He was always the same who was previously God.
Hence, when He walked on the waves of the sea before His passion, He was no less a man than God.
If you consider the nature of things, either He carried the body without weight, or He confirmed the waves with His power so that they could sustain the heavier weight of the body.
Therefore, as the blessed Gregory says in his homilies, the works of our Redeemer, which cannot be comprehended by themselves, must be weighed by His other works, so that more miraculous deeds may support faith in miraculous things.
For, he says, the body of the Lord entered to the disciples through closed doors, just as it exited the closed womb of the Virgin at His birth.
Then he adds: What then is the wonder if, after His resurrection, He entered through closed doors, destined to live forever, who, coming to die, exited not through an opened womb of the Virgin?
Behold, such a great and high-ranking teacher and supreme pontiff has expressed his opinion on this matter, having read all the distinguished Latin and Greek writers before him.
Behold, from this one thing, which he believed to be beyond doubt, he proves what might have been doubted.
Therefore, no one who thinks sensibly tries to affirm something uncertain about a matter that is very doubtful.
While those observing the visible body doubted when they saw the closed doors, the teacher of truth removed all doubt by commanding them to touch and see his hands and side.
Likewise, this distinguished author asserted and confirmed something very difficult to believe: that the Lord's body, after the resurrection, entered through closed doors and was both incorruptible and tangible.
The Gospel proves this entry through closed doors when he appeared to the disciples with the doors shut, just as he was born from the closed womb of the virgin.
If it cannot be rightly said that he was born through the womb, then neither can it be said that he entered through the doors.
Nevertheless, he is proven to have entered when it is read that he stood in their midst.
Just as he exited the tomb, shown when the angel rolled back the stone and revealed the empty tomb.
Therefore, it is clear that the stone door was passable and penetrable for him, and could not hold the living one whom it had previously sealed as dead.
Similarly, the closed and sealed womb of the virgin could not hinder the birth of the whole body, nor did it need to be opened, because it was not fitting for there to be torment for the one who was the honor and joy of the mother.
For to God, everything closed was passable in her, and the honor was that everything born was divine.
I plainly confess that there is not as much material for disputing why he exited the sealed tomb or why he entered to the disciples through closed doors as there is for why he exited the closed womb of the Virgin Mary.
In the former, divine majesty is manifested; in the latter, divine condescension is shown, and due honor and reverence for the mother and her modesty are demonstrated.
Here, the blessed Ambrose also testifies in hymnic praises.
In a hymn about the birth of the Lord, he celebrates that the enclosure of modesty remained, and the banners of virtues shone in her, in whom the entirety of the Majesty of the Deity dwelt, until the time arrived for giving birth.
Therefore, in whom the enclosure of modesty remained intact, there was no disruption, no affliction of the flesh, no foulness of a dire condition.
And in whom the banners of virtues sparkled, no sin of original origin flourished to torment her.
The banners of virtues shone in that sacred childbirth when the virgin conceived without seed, the virgin gave birth without pain and sorrow, and remained a virgin with fruitful offspring.
This is indeed the enclosure of modesty remaining, with the genital secret that was opened to her being violated in no way.
Not in conception, not in birth, not in any confusion of childbirth.
For the entire Church of Christ, both Roman and Greek, confidently sings with its own and divine authority that the Virgin gave birth without pain, that she remained inviolate, because the Holy Spirit preserved her unblemished in all things, so that the virgin had a son, and the honor worthy of such a gift was preserved for her, as the womb was dedicated to God with such sanctification.
The first volume on the Birth of the Virgin Mary concludes here, dedicated together with the sacred virgins.
Book Two
In the words of the Holy Scriptures, we must always avoid vain and superstitious interpretations.
As it is written in Proverbs, "the wayward are hard to correct; and the number of fools is infinite" (Sirach 1:15).
Therefore, the recklessness of certain brothers, since they began to defile the sacraments of the divine gift with insolent debate and to scrutinize the mystery of the sacred birth with unnecessary inquiry, prefer to err with heretics rather than to correct their wrong beliefs with the Catholics.
Because they find cracks in their vain disputations, they introduce the foul bilge of perverse contamination for the destruction of souls.
They falsely claim that the Virgin Mary gave birth to the Lord by natural law like other women and that she was only incorrupt in childbirth because she did not conceive from a man's union.
Regarding her incorruption, I believe I have already spoken sufficiently in the previous volume.
But because they do not yield to our statements, they stubbornly assert that virginity can only be corrupted by a man's union.
They claim that Mary should not be called corrupt, even though she gave birth according to the law of all women.
They argue that even if her womb or genital secret was open like other women's during the birth of Christ, virginity could not be corrupted.
Therefore, the Mother of God was the only virgin who was incorrupt after birth.
While they spread such vain babblings and nonsense, they use the authority of the holy Fathers and defile the Catholic faith.
Hence, I beg, because they disdain to hear us, let them hear the blessed Augustine, whom it is not permissible to contradict, discussing this matter in the book "Handbook" (chapter 34) among other things.
For he says: "It is not permissible to say that anything was lacking in human nature in that assumption."
Not like those born of both sexes through the desire of the flesh with the obligation of sin, whose guilt is washed away through rebirth, but as one who had to be born of a virgin, whom the faith of the mother, not lust, conceived.
Because if even through birth his integrity were corrupted, he would no longer be born of a virgin, and falsely, which is unthinkable, the entire Church would confess him as born of the Virgin Mary.
The Church, imitating his mother, daily gives birth to his members and is a virgin.
About this, in fact, an elegant work was written to Volusianus, to which we are also referred for reading on this matter.
But those who neither want to read that book nor this passage are deceived by their own recklessness.
Otherwise, as this distinguished teacher admits, if even through birth the virgin's integrity were corrupted, it would not be right to call her a virgin, as her virginity would have been corrupted by the birth.
And if she were corrupted even through birth, how could she be a whole and unharmed virgin?
Therefore, let these idle talkers listen to this great teacher and come to their senses, so they do not introduce Christ as conceived in sins and born in iniquities through their false assertion.
Because if he was not born of a virgin, then what the Church confesses is false, as he says here; and also false is what all the Scriptures of the New and Old Testaments testify about her.
But since she remained entirely a virgin, she was not burdened with any pains, she was not corrupted in any way; therefore, she did not take on any impurities of childbirth, did not emit any flow of blood, nor did she endure any corruption of her internal organs.
If a woman in labor suffered such and similar torments, without a doubt, she would not be a virgin, because her virginal integrity would have been violated.
Hence, Sedulius, a rhetorician of the Roman Church, says in his Paschal work (chapter 3, beginning): "For indeed, the small and great infant, small in limbs, lofty in divinity, flowing through the pure chastity of the hospitable temple, did not harm the body when leaving, which he had not harmed when he came." Therefore, if this is so, indeed because it is so, he was not born as others are born with a corrupted body, but God and man were born with unharmed internal organs.
Even now, the divine mystery of the virgin birth is evident.
She was conceived and brought forth while maintaining her maternal modesty, with her womb remaining closed.
The holy teachers clearly state that the Virgin remained whole and closed, just as she was before giving birth.
This wouldn't be possible if, like other women, she experienced corruption during birth.
No virgin of this kind succumbs to such passions; hence, she is rightly called a true virgin because she remains whole and incorrupt.
The blessed Mother of God is believed to be a true virgin while giving birth, maintaining her purity and integrity.
If she were not uncontaminated like other virgins, she would not be considered a true virgin.
To illustrate this, the prophet David, using an apt example, says: "He shall come down like rain upon the fleece, and like drops dripping upon the earth" Psalm 72:6
Cassiodorus, a senator, interprets this verse in his Exposition of the Psalms, referring to the most holy Virgin Mary, who is likened to the fleece. He compares the divinity of the Word to rain, which silently falls on the fleece, filling and permeating the virgin body and mind.
He uses this comparison to prophesize the coming of Christ into the virgin's womb. Just as rain pervades the fleece without harming it, the divinity of the Word preserved the virgin's purity.
Christ found her whole and incorrupt when He descended like rain upon the fleece and entered the virgin's womb, just as drops drip upon the earth. Through these prophetic words, the perfect incarnation of Christ is made clear.
We see the earth sprout with drops of rain, which nourish and bring forth every plant and all the greenery of the field.
Just as the divinity of the Word descended into Mary like raindrops onto the ground, it made her bring forth the seed of life-not from anywhere else but from herself, from the flesh of the virgin through the infusion of divine majesty.
Therefore, what was born from her was both divine and human, so that from Mary, neither the divinity of the Word was born without a human, nor the human without the Word, because the Word was made flesh, and thus God and man are one in Christ.
Furthermore, the rain that descended on the fleece did not express the nature of germination from the fleece, but the manner of birth from the virgin.
For rain during clear weather, when it drenches the fleece, equally preserves its integrity upon entry and exit, because the integrity of the fleece is in no way violated by the rain.
Thus, that heavenly speaker felt about the Virgin Mary and confessed that neither upon the entry of the Son of God was she corrupted nor upon His exit violated, but in all things full of grace, intact and unharmed she was preserved; neither when He enters are the womb or the internal organs corrupted, nor when He is delivered are they opened.
The generative secret remains closed and immaculate; the womb is emptied, like the fleece from the rain, but the internal organs are not disturbed.
Therefore, with these two statements, as the aforementioned doctor suggests, the Holy Spirit wanted to declare what Isaiah finally testifies about Christ, saying: "As the rain and snow come down from heaven and do not return there, but water the earth and make it bring forth and sprout; so shall my word be that goes out from my mouth. It shall not return to me empty, but it shall accomplish what I desire and achieve the purpose for which I sent it."
Behold what David wanted to signify through the rain and the raindrops, certainly the infusion of the Holy Spirit and the divinity of the Word.