Prologue by the Author
John acknowledges those who encouraged his work.
To the lords and brothers in Christ of Salerno, I, a servant of Christ Jesus, brother John, greet you.
At your request, I did not find it burdensome to write about the life and virtues of the blessed hermit fathers, as recorded by the learned Palladius during the time of Emperor Theodosius.
I immediately set to work, with body supported and knees bent, believing that I was doing something beneficial for you.
However, as I was eager to complete the task, I began to suffer from severe stomach pain.
One day, while enduring this illness, I was visited by our fellow brother, Lord Adhelrad, and John, the steward of the sacred Salernitan palace.
Seeing my perseverance, they began to reminisce about the pious and remarkable memory of our most holy father, Lord Odo.
They knew how much I cherished sharing stories about him or contributing something worthwhile to his legacy.
Remembering the scripture, "The people tell of the wisdom of the saints, and the Church announces their praise," I began to recount his origins as they requested.
Upon hearing this, they suggested that if my affection for him was true, I should promptly document the benefits of his good heritage for future generations.
Reflecting deeply on the wishes of these devoted men, I initially remained silent, as monks often do.
I feared that by recounting the life of such a great man, I might not do it justice and inadvertently dishonor it.
My speech lacked the beauty of grammatical skill, and I doubted my worthiness to narrate the life of this most holy man, even if I had the ability to speak eloquently.
The author presents witnesses, sharing what he has seen and heard.
But why does he remain silent about the names of many?
As I began this work, I invoked the Creator and the Son with heartfelt tears, like those of a virgin, along with the Holy Spirit-equal, giver of languages, and distributor of words-who opens the mouths of the mute and makes infants articulate.
I hoped that He, who once inspired me to turn away from the world and be enflamed with love for such a Father, would grant me eloquence through His breath, as I am without any help from letters.
Therefore, dear friends, encouraged by you, I have boldly taken on this work.
Please support me with your prayers so that I may complete it.
If anyone reads this or hears it read, I ask that they do not shudder, laugh, or speak falsely, as if the world, abandoned by God until now, could not produce such a man for the Church, to whom Christ promised long ago, "I am with you always, to the end of the world."
I testify to Jesus, knowing that there are many things beyond what I narrate that my teacher Arnulf used to recount under oath, having witnessed them himself. Likewise, Hucbert, bishop of the Tiberine Church, and one of our brothers named Landricus. I chose not to write about these events, not because they lacked importance, but because they did not follow His way eagerly, and I did not want to rely on their testimony. If I were to describe it, I believe it would be enough to praise any ancient father and apostolic man.
I was truly pleased to write about those things which, as if told by another, I heard directly from him and committed to memory. Moreover, what Lord Hildebrand, a truthful man and prior of the monastery at Cluny, taught me and many others.
Meanwhile, I ask you, my dearest, not to request the names of your ancestors and other Gauls you grew up with.
I have neither seen them nor had the chance to do so.
At that time, I was bound by strict rules, which didn't even allow me to inquire, especially since I was born on Italian soil and raised within the Church.
Book One
Odo, a truly blessed man, was born from the lineage of the Franks.
He grew up in the household of William, the powerful Duke of Aquitaine.
At the age of nineteen, he was tonsured at Saint Martin of Tours.
There, he was educated in the liberal arts, focusing on grammar.
He then went to Paris, where he studied dialectics and music under Remigius, a very learned man.
When he was thirty, he traveled to Burgundy and lived a monastic life for fifteen years under Abbot Berno.
Eventually, he was ordained as an abbot and became a beloved leader and father to the monasteries in the regions of France, Aquitaine, Italy, and the city of Rome.
The author's fortune.
In the year 939 AD, during his sixtieth year and his thirtieth year as a monk, he traveled to Rome.
He found me, caught up in worldly matters, and mercifully brought me to the monastery of Saint Peter in Ticino.
There, under the brief custody of King Hugh, he entrusted me to Lord Hildebrannus for education in monastic disciplines.
Soon after, when we arrived in Rome, he deemed it fitting to take me, despite my unhappiness, as his companion.
He had taken me from my parents as a canon and later returned me as a monk.
During those times, while we traveled and talked, I boldly began to speak, setting aside any embarrassment.
Feeling far from the monastic path, I dared to ask him about his life and upbringing.
I urged him to kindly share his story with me.
As was his custom, he remained silent for a while.
Then, wiping the redness from his face and sighing deeply, he began to tell me about his origins.
His words were filled with tears and groans.
Odo shares with John about his father's religious beliefs and the early days of his own life.
"My father," he said, "was named Abbo, and he seemed to be of a different character and behavior than people of today.
He memorized stories of the ancients and the Novella of Justinian.
At his table, the words of the Gospel were always heard.
If any dispute arose, people trusted his judgment so much that everyone would come to him for resolution.
That's why he was beloved by all, especially William, the most powerful count, who ruled over Aquitaine and Gascony at the time.
He was dedicated to keeping the vigils of the saints.
On the night when peace was given to angels and men, and Christ the Lord visited the world, emerging from the virgin womb like a bridegroom from his chamber, he spent it in silence with tears and prayers.
While observing these vigils, he thought to ask the Lord for a son because of the virgin birth.
With such fervent prayers, he was blessed to revive the womb that had ceased to bear.
My father often shared with some the story of my birth."
"During my infancy, he once entered the room where I lay alone in the cradle, without a guardian.
Seeing no one around, he lifted me up with his own hands, and with a heartfelt look upward, he said, 'Receive, Martin, jewel of priests, this child,' and placing me back on the bed, he left; but he chose not to reveal what he had done to anyone."
"After I was weaned, he entrusted me to one of his priests, living in a more remote place, to be raised and instructed in the study of letters.
The priest later confessed that during those days, he had a vision.
'I saw, and behold, the leaders of the churches began urgently asking me for the boy.'"
When I asked what they planned to do with him, whether they intended to return him to his father's house, they told me they hadn't come for that purpose.
Instead, they intended to take him to the regions of the East.
However, the priest didn't want to let him go and couldn't resist them.
Not knowing what else to do, he lay prostrate on the ground, turning to prayer and pleading that they punish him first before taking the boy.
He said he was suffering from the father's vengeance, and his parents accused him of betraying the boy.
To this, one of them reportedly responded, "Lest the boy's father should take revenge on the priest, let us release him for a time."
Learning of this revelation, the priest returned me to my parents.
All these things you're asking me, oh son, I heard from my father.
But when I grew up, now as you see me old and worn, they praised me as a vigorous and remarkable young man.
Over time, my father began to withdraw me from the ecclesiastical order and involved me in military exercises. For this reason, he entrusted me to serve the count in the house of William.
Eventually, leaving my studies behind, I started serving in tasks related to hunting and bird-catching.
But Almighty God, who grants salvation to the unwilling and calls things that are not as though they were, began to frighten me in dreams and show me how my life was inclined towards evil. Moreover, He turned all my hunting experiences into exhaustion.
The more I involved myself in these pursuits, the more I returned sorrowful, worn out, and drained of all energy.
During these times, my father advised me to hold the famous vigils, which he was accustomed to celebrating.
After several years passed, I prepared to celebrate the Christmas Eve vigil. Having spent part of the night awake, it suddenly pleased my mind to beseech the Mother of the Lord Jesus for my life.
Then, indeed, praying, I began to say, "O Lady, Mother of Mercy, on this night you gave the Savior to the world; be graciously my intercessor."
I turn to your glorious and unique child, most loving one, and ask you to listen to my prayers with compassion.
I am deeply worried that my life might displease your Son.
And because, dear lady, He revealed Himself to the world through you, I beg you to have mercy on me without delay.
Amidst these prayers and morning praises, and during the solemn celebration of the Masses, the next day dawned.
As usual, the white-robed choir of canons was present.
While the singing of such a grand celebration was performed with various voices, as an impatient youth, I rushed into their midst and began to join them in praising the King of the world.
I know and admit that I acted improperly, but I still held onto that saying of David in my heart, which is written: Praise the Lord, all you nations, and praise Him, all you peoples.
Soon after, I was seized by a terrible headache that overwhelmed me briefly before subsiding.
After the Gospel reading, the same headache returned, and if I hadn't leaned on the church's railings, I would have collapsed as if lifeless.
The pain was so intense that when it struck, I felt no hope of life.
This happened to me when I was sixteen, and for three years after, I suffered from this affliction.
Because of this, I was taken back to my parents' home, and for two years, they tried every possible treatment.
The more varied and extensive the medicines I took, the further away health seemed to be.
During those times, with deep sorrow and heavy sighs, my father explained that this was my fate, adding: Behold, blessed Martin, what I offered gratefully, you demand fully.
Truly, you are rightly honored in a vow, but it comes at a cost.
Finally, despairing of finding a remedy for my health, I thought I would find solace by eagerly turning to him.
Indeed, to whom I was entrusted without knowing, I would serve again, with my hair cut, knowing this was the path I had taken.
Here, my dear children, is the story of my birth and the beginning of my life.
You'll notice that I haven't accomplished anything good by my own will.
However, judge my humble ways as you see fit, while you continue to proclaim and glorify the mercy that watches over me.
Odo, who was dedicated to Saint Martin, wrote hymns in his honor.
He held such deep devotion for the blessed Martin that he cherished him above all other saints, entrusting himself to his protection every day.
He kept Martin in his heart no matter where he was, spoke of him often, and followed his example in deeds.
Not more than six years had passed when, during the church's vigils before Martin's body, Odo happened to be present.
Since the antiphons for that service were brief and the nights were long, they extended the service by repeating each antiphon throughout the psalms.
This became quite a challenging task for them.
Eventually, they approached him and pleaded with one voice: "Father, we've waited a long time for your arrival to relieve us from this great effort. Now that you're here, we ask you to compose more antiphons about the life of your lord Martin, with enough length to alleviate the monotony of these very short ones."
However, he replied that not only could he not create these, but even if someone else had, his age would prevent him from learning them.
He also praised the brevity of the current ones and dismissed the longer ones they were requesting.
But they insisted that if he refused, it would offend Martin, suggesting that such an excuse showed hidden pride.
Persuaded by their words and prayers, Odo soon committed himself to this great task with effort.
He composed three hymns in Martin's praise, and I've decided to include just one example here.
"Christ the King, glory of Martin; this is your praise, you are his; grant us to worship you in him, and him in you."
In addition, he composed twelve antiphons, each with three different parts, whose words and harmonious sound are so well-tuned that nothing sweeter seems to be found in meaning or in musical harmony.
They are currently staying in Benevento.
His memory was never absent from his heart and mouth, whether morning or evening.
He always cherished in his heart the one he spoke of with his mouth.
"O Martin, O holy one, how blessed it is to rejoice in you, O Martin," and so on.
For now, since the place has fittingly provided the opportunity for this narrative, with the Lord's help, when I begin to fully explain his life, I will recount what the blessed Martin wished to accomplish through him.
For now, let's return to where we left off.
When he was nineteen, he became a cleric.
The most blessed man, Odo, in his nineteenth year, sought refuge with the blessed Martin and took on the duties of a cleric.
I'd rather stay silent than talk about the gathering of nobles and the grand display, so as not to seem like I'm insulting the poverty he later embraced.
Among them was Count Fulco, who had raised him.
He immediately granted him a cell near the church of Saint Martin and provided him with daily sustenance from the same church, which he accepted.
Yet, the most blessed man, a lover of poverty, having scorned worldly glory, sought only to please God.
So, during the day, he devoted himself to reading, and at night he dedicated himself to prayer, knowing it is written:
"If anyone does not know, they will not be known" First Corinthians 14.
Virgil is devoted and becomes frightened.
In those days, our most skilled sailor, who guided us through the whirlpools of this world, swam across the vast sea of Priscian.
As he was eager to read Virgil's poems, he had a vision of a certain vessel.
It appeared beautiful on the outside, but inside, it was filled with serpents that surrounded him without biting.
Upon waking, he realized that the serpents symbolized the teachings of the poets, the vessel represented Virgil's book, and the path he walked on, while very thirsty, symbolized Christ.
He dedicated himself to the Holy Scriptures.
Meanwhile, I'll briefly explain how the power of patience started to show in him later on.
Leaving behind the poets' verses, guided by a higher spirit of wisdom, he fully turned to the interpreters of the Gospels and the prophets.
During this time, almost all the clergy began to rage against him with furious outcries.
"What are you trying to do?" they asked. "Why are you attempting to take over someone else's work? You neglected this task during your youth. Spare yourself and leave these complex writings behind, and turn to the psalms."
However, the same spirit that once taught him to remain silent about good things now taught him to stay quiet about negative things. With his head bowed, ears closed, and eyes on the ground, he pondered David's words in his heart:
"I said, 'I will guard my ways that I may not sin with my tongue; I will keep a guard on my mouth.'" (Psalm 39).
Yet, he did not forget the promise of the Lord:
"By your endurance, you will gain your souls." (Luke 21).
With the Lord's help, I will describe what remains to be said about his patience in the following.
He becomes famous for his virtues.
He visits the tomb of Saint Martin at night, carrying tablets.
He is frightened by demons.
Now, let's quickly move on to the contempt of material things.
Let those who wish, praise the expellers of demons, healers of the dead, and others renowned for their virtues.
Among all of them, I, being insignificant, will first praise my Odo's patience, then his disdain for material things, his efforts in gaining souls, restoring monasteries, providing clothing and food for monks, ensuring peace for the Churches, promoting harmony among kings and princes, protecting all roads, diligently following commandments, persevering in vigils and prayers, caring for the poor, correcting the young, honoring the old, improving morals, loving virgins, comforting those who abstain, showing mercy to the miserable, strictly observing the rules, and finally, setting an example of all virtues.
At that time, good Jesus was planting a paradise of monks from various backgrounds in a small cell, from which he would nurture the hearts of the faithful.
Finally content with a tiny cell, away from everyone's sight, he hurried to please God alone.
Having given away to the poor all he had brought for temporal use, in accordance with the gospel command, he worried not about tomorrow.
Indeed, at night he secluded himself from human sight and went alone to the tomb of the blessed Martin to pray, which was nearly two miles away from his cell:
not relying on a companion by his side, nor supported by a staff, but only carrying two tablets in his hand, perfect for writing, designed to be opened but not separated, as students typically use on their right thigh.
But the enemy of good began to instill such terrors upon him.
Foxes emerged from both sides of the road, initially watching his back as they pursued him, then boldly throwing themselves in front of him.
Yet, when they realized they couldn't deter him from his passionate and determined journey, they gave a yelp and rushed at him with open mouths, threatening to strangle him.
But he neither fled nor gave up; instead, with his legs folded and his neck stiffened, he defended himself using only his shoulders and arms.
Finally, offering his entire body to their teeth, he managed to avoid the lethal bite to his throat.
And suddenly, behold, a wolf came rushing in at full speed, rescuing him from their attacks, and from then on became his companion and domesticated friend.
If anyone finds this too honorable or burdensome, let them read the life of Saint Paul as described by Saint Jerome; there, they will discover that the same man's tomb was prepared by lions.
If that example doesn't seem sufficient, move on to the life of Saint Ammon, where you'll find that his cell was guarded from robbers by two dragons.
Then, returning to the aforementioned Jerome, look into the life of Florentius of Nursia, set forth in dialogue by blessed Pope Gregory: there you will find that Jerome deserved to have a lion as a guardian for the donkeys, and Florentius a fierce bear for the protection of livestock.
From then on, he traveled more securely, always keeping in his heart the testimonies of good Jesus and singing aloud, saying:
"Truly, you are faithful, Lord, in your words, and holy in all your works. You lift up all who fall and raise up all who are crushed."
The wolf protected him from being eaten, which it once used to eat, and frightened the foxes, which it used to be frightened by.
Therefore, regarding any invisible temptations the devil might have used against him, I beg no one to ask of me.
However, as proof of the truth, I believe the described visible battle should be sufficient for all readers.
At night, when he went out for prayer from the cell where he stayed, he didn't close its little door behind him, because he feared losing nothing, being content with just a mat on the bare ground and the clothes he wore.
He regularly read the Rule of Saint Benedict.
While going through various books, he came across this rule.
As he skimmed through it, he stumbled upon the passage that commands monks to sleep fully clothed.
Rule of Saint Benedict, chapter twenty-two
Not fully understanding its meaning, he lay clothed for three years.
Although he wasn't yet a monk, he embraced the gentle yoke of monastic life.
He was diligent in following the saint's commandments and aspired to imitate another's way of life.
At that time, the Lord Jesus was planting simple seeds in barren land, foreseeing a hundredfold harvest.
Saint Odo was physically vigorous.
This is remarkable because despite lying on the ground in darkness, the brightness of his body remained unchanged,
and his spirit's strength was not diminished even after long periods of fasting.
Over the past two years, when we often visited the holy places in and around Rome for prayer, our youth couldn't surpass, or even keep up with, his venerable age of sixty.
When we, exhausted, asked him to spare himself and us, he would say:
"Surely you see that I have lost all strength.
Long old age has made me a weak old man.
Look, it has been thirty years since I was as you now see me."
In this way, he would lament his weakness to us:
yet we marveled at his strength with great astonishment, and not without reason:
as someone who was not overcome by decay, he was not to be overthrown by corruption.
Indeed, he made little of whatever strength he saw in himself:
he considered it significant if he could see any strength in another.
During his childhood, he was sustained by half a loaf of bread and a handful of beans, and (which is against the nature of the Franks) very little drink.
Having laid aside all corruptible burdens, he, as a naked soldier of Christ, girded himself and bore arms.
He was seen by all as a young recruit leading the ranks of the old, and trusting in Christ, he eagerly sought to bring back glorious spoils from the enemy.
All these things happened at the church of Saint Martin in Tours.
That place is rich in virtues, remarkable for miracles, abundant in wealth, and shining with all kinds of religious devotion.
It is fitting that it should be remarkable, having deserved to have such a resident.
Not only a great martyr or confessor, but a light of the world and a jewel of priests:
kings hasten there, and leaders of various nations frequently visit with gifts and vows.
He offers advice to everyone.
Many people visit him-some familiar faces coming back, others new, seeking to know him.
Like an overflowing fountain, he offers the most desired wisdom to everyone, providing fitting examples as if from an open library:
Instructing one in chastity, encouraging sobriety in another; teaching one to disdain worldly desires, advising another not to covet what others have.
He generously provides each person with what they need, lamenting this miserable world and acknowledging its impending downfall with its admirers.
Thus, he urges everyone to live simply and avoid ill-gotten desires, to control their appetites, saying:
"He who stuffs his stomach nourishes lust."
To those driven by lust, he recounts the downfall of the dragon, saying:
"Alas for those wretched ones, for the dragon drags a third of the stars behind him."
To the drunkards and gluttons, he warns:
"Nebuzaradan, the captain of the guard, destroyed the walls of Jerusalem."
To the effeminate and those who lie with men, he contrasts Herod's murder and the scribe's exile.
"The soul is greater than the body," he said, "and worse is he who does such things than Herod. Herod killed bodies, sending souls to heaven; this one separates bodies from God, slaying souls with eternal death. The scribe who tested the recruits was captured and taken to Egypt: for he, after death, will be led to hell."
The teacher mourned the downfall and said:
"Look, Lord, at the city that was made desolate, full of riches," and again he lamented:
"Woe to you, Behemoth. You never cease, alas, to lay gold like dust, with the rays of the sun beneath you" (Job 41).
Those who heard these words were either terrified, aware of their sins, or delighted, comforted by his words, as if different people took various foods from the same pantry.
I testify to Jesus, for I have never heard such sweet speech from any man.
It was fulfilled in him, as the Lord says in the Gospel:
"The kingdom of heaven is like a householder who brings out of his treasure what is new and what is old" (Matthew 13).
So, everyone, enriched with divine wisdom and fulfilled by heavenly nourishment,
gave thanks and returned to their homes.
He refused the gifts.
They offered him many presents, but he didn't want to accept any, because he had been very generous in giving away his own belongings and didn't feel right receiving gifts from others.
However, there was a time when his lord persuaded him, and despite his reluctance, he accepted one hundred coins that were sent to him.
But as a true soldier of Christ, he didn't keep them for even a moment and immediately gave them away to those in need.
Meanwhile, the student began to surpass his teachers and became a role model for those who followed.
He studies in Paris.
During this time, he went to Paris, where he thoroughly read the dialectic works of Saint Augustine that were sent to his son, Deodatus.
He often read Martianus on the liberal arts.
Throughout all of this, his teacher was Remigius.
After finishing this, he returned to Tours.
Gregory's Moralia is summarized, inspired by a vision Gregory had to undertake this task.
At that time, the brothers who cared for him requested that he condense the moral teachings of the blessed Pope Gregory into a single volume for them.
However, he said he couldn't do this, adding that even if he could, he shouldn't, so as not to alter or diminish the work of such a great man and its significant value.
Conversely, they argued that it would be better to abandon it altogether and move on to other Scriptures than to be overwhelmed by such a great task.
This matter was debated among them daily.
I know many will be upset about this, and to appease them, I wanted to include this explanation.
This was not done out of arrogance, but by the Lord's arrangement, so the light placed on a mountain, which had been hidden under a bushel, would shine.
However, the following event will make what we have said clearer.
While they persisted in their request, one night, Lord Odo was praying as usual in the church of Saint Martin, and he suddenly fell asleep.
In his vision, he saw a choir of saints descending into the church.
First, they blessed the Lord; then they sat in order on the benches, and after a while, one of them stood up and said, "Why do we linger here?"
The others replied that they were waiting for Pope Gregory.
Hearing this, our father Odo, eager to see, began to look around to find from which direction he might see him coming.
Then, lifting his eyes upward, he saw the blessed Gregory coming as if sent from heaven, more splendid and adorned in face and character than all who had come before him.
As soon as he arrived, everyone stood and bowed their heads to ask for a blessing.
He didn't go down among them but stood at the church's pulpit and called to the blessed Odo, who was lying on the ground, saying,
"Rise, brother Odo, do not be afraid."
When he got up, he saw something resembling a pen sticking out above his ear, sharpened as if by a teacher's skill and firmly set at the top.
Taking it, the blessed one handed it to him and said,
"Go ahead confidently and complete the work assigned to you. The book you write will not be erased, but mine will stand forever."
Immediately upon waking, he understood what he had seen.
Then, taking that large volume, he carefully read through it and combined the healthier parts he had foreseen into one volume, and in this way, he quelled the murmuring.
Fulco, the count, recovered his health and was inspired to turn away from worldly pursuits.
Later, Count Fulco, for some unknown reason, took two small gold vessels from the treasures of Saint Martin.
However, driven by greed, he refused to return them and faced severe consequences.
Nearing death, he ordered himself to be taken to the tomb of Saint Martin.
There, despite promising many gifts, he did not regain his health.
Moreover, he became so worn out over time that he awaited death.
When Lord Odo visited him out of concern, he said, "Return the vessels of Saint Martin that you took, and you will be saved immediately."
Fulco promised to return them and even give more if the truth was proven.
Immediately, lifted by the hands of our father and those assisting him, he was brought to the body of Saint Martin and fell to the ground.
He couldn't delay receiving the promised help; having regained the use of his limbs, he began to walk on his own as if he had come on a stretcher.
Indeed, he was so corrected that he would not commit such acts again and faithfully fulfilled what he had promised.
Meanwhile, Father Odo began to advise him to leave the world behind and strive solely to please God.
Fulco replied, "You cannot persuade me to do this right now.
However, I have a beloved knight named Adhegrin, who is brave in arms and wise in counsel.
If he listens to you, he will immediately obey your wishes," which indeed happened later on.
Within a few days, having fully regained his strength, he returned home.
People from all around gathered to congratulate him on his recovery.
Taking up the conversation, he began to explain to those around him what he had gone through and added how quickly he discovered the power in Lord Odo's words.
Adhegrinus draws close to himself.
He seeks Balmam, where Euticius's rule was strong.
Among those helping and listening closely was Adhegrinus, who, deeply moved, quickly returned after arranging all his possessions.
He cut his hair and left secular life, becoming a champion of Christ from then on.
Our father took everything he brought for his temporary use and distributed it to the poor, just as he had done with his own belongings before.
The palace soldiers were content in a small hut.
Seeing the world full of evil and its followers on a ruinous path, they hurried daily to ascend the heights of monastic life.
Meanwhile, there was no place within France's borders with a monastery that they didn't visit or send scouts to.
Not finding a place of religion where they could rest, they returned to the hut with great sorrow.
For this reason, Adhegrinus decided to go to Rome.
Starting his journey, he reached the borders of Burgundy and arrived at a village called Balma.
There, he found a monastery recently built by Abbot Bermon.
He turned aside and was warmly welcomed by him, according to the rule of Saint Benedict, in the guest house.
He wished to stay for a while as a guest, not because he needed anything, but to learn the customs and habits of the locals.
The founders of that place were followers of a certain father Euticus.
I chose not to include details of his life's merit or conduct here; however, I want to remind you of the kind of death he deserved.
Euticius Odo returned to the same place and was appointed to lead the school there.
He lived during the reign of King Louis the Great, and he was cherished by the king and beloved by all.
Though he was a layman educated in foreign studies, he set aside the usual pride of human frailty and dedicated himself entirely to the rules and teachings of the blessed Fathers.
He compiled various customs from these authorities into a single volume.
Soon after, he became a monk.
He was held in such high esteem by the king that a monastery was constructed for him within the palace grounds.
After completing his life's journey, with brothers gathered around, he suddenly passed away.
However, as preparations for the devout father's funeral were underway, behold, he who had died returned to life.
Amidst their astonishment and amazement, Father Euticius said:
"Thanks be to God, know that in these forty years, I do not recall taking food on a single day without first weeping.
Today, the Lord has comforted me by removing my sorrow and has granted me a place of rest among the choirs of angels."
Having said this, he rested forever.
Father Euticius was indeed the creator of these customs still observed in our monasteries.
The venerable Adhegrinus witnessed this and quickly informed our father Odo about it.
So Odo, taking one hundred volumes of books with him, soon moved to the same monastery.
He, who had once been a follower, later became a leader.
Lord Adhegrinus confined himself to a small cell and, with Abbot Berno's permission, stayed there for three years.
Since Father Odo was a scholarly man, he was entrusted with the demanding duty of teaching at the school.
He was thirty years old at the time.
I confess, I thought I would quickly and simply pass over the life of our most holy father, but my mind, like a restless opponent, wants to recount the men who were his companions here along with his life.
So, I encourage you, just as I am willing to work hard, it shouldn't feel burdensome or difficult for you to accept this.
It feels right and pleasing to God to share the stories of those whose lives are eloquently described and whom He has guided from this journey to their eternal home.
The life of Adhegrinus in the wilderness. 25.
The venerable Adhegrinus, whom we mentioned earlier, was later granted permission to retreat to the wilderness, where he confined himself in a small cave.
One day, overwhelmed with severe distress and with no one around to offer words of comfort or examples from any father, as Wisdom says:
"Woe to the one who is alone, for if he falls, he has no one to help him up" (Ecclesiastes 4).
He was on the brink of despair, feeling as if he were caught in a sinking whirlpool.
Then, suddenly, a very splendid man appeared and kindly asked him what was troubling him or why he seemed so close to despair.
Adhegrinus replied:
"Since I began serving the Lord tirelessly, I haven't received any consolation from Him in any way; because of this, I am greatly distressed, as I do not know if my service is pleasing to Him, or if I will ever deserve any reward for my labor."
Immediately, the man embraced him, kissed him, and said, "Believe, because you will never be unworthy of the Lord's goodness."
With those words, he consoled him and then left.
26. Another incident occurred when the tempter lured him outside the cell where he was staying and suddenly attacked him, taking him to the edge of a very steep cliff, trying with all his might to throw him off.
But what could the soldier of Christ do, unable to stand steadily there?
He didn't know how to resist at all.
However, at the brink of death, blessed Martin suddenly appeared, took his hand, and asked, "What is this, and how did you get here?"
Adhegrinus replied, "I don't know, lord."
Then, comforting him, Martin returned him to his place.
27.
About five years ago, when Father Odo was on his way to Rome to rebuild the monastery within the church of the blessed Apostle Paul, as it had been in the past, he felt compelled by the Lord Pope and all the orders of the Holy See to visit a particular man first and consult with him on this matter.
This was in line with the saying: "Do everything with counsel, and after it is done, you will not regret it" (Ecclesiasticus chapter thirty-two).
As they were discussing the matter and engaging in a lengthy conversation about spiritual things, Father Odo asked him to share any divine revelations he might have had at that time.
Recalling their old friendship and filled with love, Lord Adhegrinus responded:
"On that day, at that hour, after we completed the psalmody, the blessed Martin suddenly appeared to me. His distinguished face and almost familiar presence, following a blessing, immediately gave me permission to speak.
After exchanging a few words, I asked him where he was going or coming from."
He answered, saying: "I am coming from Rome and heading to France. I turned aside to visit you on my way."
Then, grateful, I implored him, since he considered a sinner worthy of a visit, to also deem it worthy to rest under his shelter, even briefly.
But he replied: "Today is the ordination of Louis, king of the Franks, and I must hurry to attend his anointing; therefore, I cannot delay."
To this, I said: "If you must leave, I ask that you first bless me."
But he answered: "You don't need my blessing. Long ago, the one who blessed me also blessed you."
When I kept urging him to bless me, he insisted that I should bless him as well, saying he wouldn't agree with me unless I returned the blessing.
This led to a friendly disagreement between us, as he refused to bless me and I felt unworthy to presume."
After exchanging blessings, he soon departed, leaving me with great sorrow.
To confirm the truth of this event, Father Odo, a most trustworthy witness, was present.
He ordered the day and hour to be recorded and later, upon careful investigation, found everything had happened as he predicted.
Over 30 years have passed, if I am not mistaken, since he has been living in the same hermitage.
He only comes down to the monastery of Saint Peter, known as Cluny and about 2,000 yards away, on Sundays and major feast days.
He takes a small amount of flour to make bread for himself and a few beans, then immediately returns to the hermitage.
He never uses wine, and his food is not seasoned with fat or oil.
He endures both cold and heat at all times: heat between his shoulders, cold between his hands and arms.
However, as we continue to describe this man's life, let us quickly return to the topic from which we have strayed far.
I remember promising first to explain Father Odo's patience, which is the foundation of all virtues, and then, as time allows, to carefully narrate his other virtues.
Therefore, with the Lord's help, as far as my strength allows, I will hasten to fulfill my promise.
False brothers test Odo.
In the same monastery mentioned before, there were some brothers whose lives and behaviors you will learn about in the following story.
When they heard that Lord Odo had come for spiritual devotion, they approached him, pretending to ask why he had come.
When they received his answer, they said:
"We are all trying to escape this congregation to save our souls, and you, on the other hand, have come here to lose yours?"
When he asked why they said this, they added:
"Do you know the custom of Abbot Berno?"
He replied, "Not at all."
And they said: "Oh, if only you knew how harshly he treats a monk.
His corrections are followed by beatings; he ties up those he beats with shackles, subdues them with imprisonment, afflicts them with fasting, and after enduring all this, the poor soul still cannot gain his favor."
Hearing this, Lord Odo began to hesitate about entering gradually.
Seeing this, Adhegrinus quickly intervened and said:
"Father Odo, do not be afraid; these words are not from a servant, but from a tempter.
Notice that through their mouths, the devil speaks."
Immediately, those brothers retreated in confusion.
For Father Odo, along with his colleague Adhegrinus, submitted their necks to Christ's sweetest yoke.
Because of this, blessed Benedict, who knew future events, commanded in his monastic rules, Rule, chapter fifty-three, that no one should speak with a guest unless permitted by the prior.
How many have been deceived in such a way from the beginning of holy devotion, turning back and returning from the warmth of inner desire to the coldness of wrongful will?
And although Scripture says: "Test the spirits to see if they are from God" (First John chapter four, verse one), the testing of the faithful and those seeking the Lord should not be like this, especially since the Lord commands through the prophet to those who are ignited by the warmth of the Holy Spirit: "You who are in the south, hurry to those who come from the north with bread."
The soldier of Christ, just as he didn't embrace flattery, wasn't shaken by fears either.
Regarding these matters, the blessed Job rightly says:
Let those who curse the day curse it, those who are ready to rouse Leviathan.
(Job chapter 3).
The Cluniac rituals are emphasized.
Meanwhile, I'd like to pause the story of our father Odo to explain the customs of this place, which will make the following reading clearer.
The custom was that the schoolmaster would never be alone with a single boy, not even for a short break, nor would the boy speak with him in private.
For good measure, another boy or one of the brothers would always accompany them during conversations.
If it was nighttime and a boy needed to leave, he wouldn't dare step out of the dormitory without the light of a lamp and the company of another brother.
During meals, there was always reading at the table.
Each person would carefully gather the crumbs from cutting the bread before the reading ended and consume them with gratitude.
Once the reading was finished, no one dared eat those or any other food beyond that.
They believed these crumbs to be more sacred than other foods.
They said a miracle had been revealed regarding them in those years.
There was a certain brother in the monastery who was very capable and beloved by all.
When he was near death, with the brothers gathered around praying to commend his spirit to the Lord, he suddenly cried out, saying:
Help me, I beg you, for God's sake;
he said, now I am being taken to judgment, where the devil, the accuser of humanity, presented a full bag of bread crumbs against me as testimony, which I refused to eat according to custom, having fallen from the table.
After a brief moment, he cried out again terribly and said:
Look, the devil I mentioned is here, carrying the bag.
As the frightened brothers stood amazed, he added:
He is there in that place, do you not see him?
Then he fortified himself with the sign of the cross and, amidst words of prayer, surrendered his spirit.
From that day on, the crumbs were collected with all diligence.
There is also another practice of silence among them.
During the designated times, no one within the monastery's cloister dares to speak or interact with another brother.
However, when twelve readings are celebrated, no one in the cloister speaks the following day, except at the chapter meeting.
On the eighth day of Christmas and Easter, complete silence is observed both day and night.
This brief silence is said to signify eternal silence.
Whenever there was a need to request something, they communicated through various gestures, which scholars might call the signs of fingers and eyes.
This system was so developed among them that, even without speaking, the signs alone would suffice to convey all necessary things.
But on ordinary days and during other saints' octaves, they maintained such discretion.
Indeed, on ordinary days, throughout the cycle of day and night, they sang 138 psalms, from which we deducted 14 for those with weaker spirits, excluding the special prayers frequently used by our brothers, which seem to go beyond the usual form of the psaltery.
Similarly, they repeated two Masses and litanies.
During each canonical hour, they bent their knees twice.
On the octaves we mentioned, they sang only 75 psalms during the prescribed cycles, bent their knees once, and ate twice.
There are indeed many other things, which I think I should not include here for the sake of impatient readers.
Odo's Patience Tested. Thirty-three.
When Odo took on the role of teacher, he soon found an opportunity to test his patience.
One night, a boy asked to be excused for a natural need.
The location was so close to the dormitory that the lamp, which was kept burning by rule, lit it completely.
So Father Odo got up, woke one of the boys, and, satisfied with just that light, accompanied him.
The next day, as usual, the brothers gathered in the chapter, and after the reading from the martyrology and the Rule, they began to scold him harshly for going out after the boy at night without a candle.
But since no one dares to present their case before asking for pardon, nor defend their opinion after asking, he immediately fell to the ground and asked for pardon, saying the dormitory light was sufficient for him.
However, they not only did not listen to him, but instead judged him guilty of a serious offense.
This blessed man, who followed the narrow path, sought to emulate Him who, when suffering, did not threaten, nor get angry or complain, but instead sought temporary places, prostrated on the ground, and asked for pardon.
His abbot, wishing to test his patience, pretended to be angry and pronounced a sentence connected with excommunication, instructing him not to ask for pardon again that day.
But he reflected on the words of David in his heart, I was like a beast before you, and I am always with you Psalm Seventy-three, and again, You have put burdens on our backs, and laid people over our heads Psalm Sixty-six.
He went and, throwing himself at the brothers' feet, asked them to go and ask pardon from the abbot on his behalf, which they did.
Finally, Abbot Berno, amazed by such patience in a young man, soon called him and, following the rule, healed the disturbance with a blessing.
From then on, Odo became dearer to him.
Thirty-four.
There were also brothers in that same congregation, young in mind and action, whom we mentioned earlier.
They, instead of progressing, were heading toward destruction.
Whenever they found an opportunity, they would hurl various insults and false accusations at him.
But the peaceful man, Odo, would take them aside and, though innocent, humbly throw himself at their feet, asking for forgiveness-not out of fear, but out of brotherly love-hoping to correct them with patience, as he saw they were inviting divine retribution.
Eventually, they were sometimes subdued by his patience, but like flowing water, they would soon return to their old vices.
Instead of following his example, they pursued him.
The leader of this trouble was called Guido.
Often, when one would urge another to insult him, the one sent would say, "What is the point of doing this every day when we can neither drive him away nor provoke him to anger? You know he is wiser than us. Up to now, whatever I wanted to learn from him, he has generously shared. I fear that one day, overwhelmed by such injuries, he might begin to withhold what he now freely gives."
But the other would respond, "It's not as you claim. Brother Odo is such a person that he would endure not only these things or similar ones but even worse, and after this, he would generously provide whatever you want."
Indeed, after a short time, they were struck by divine retribution through God's just judgment because brotherly correction could not restrain them. After Berno, the father of that monastery, passed away, they soon abandoned their religious way of life and returned to the secular world, eventually earning a very grim death.
The Miracle of the Crumbs. Conversion of Parents.
Our father often shares the story of this miracle that happened back then.
There was a brother in the community with a particular habit; when he sat at the table, he would fully immerse himself in reading.
One day, as usual, he gathered crumbs, but before he could eat them, the abbot finished reading.
The brother was unsure of what to do, as he didn't dare eat the crumbs after the reading was done, nor did he want to discard them for fear of waste.
So, he clenched his fist, deciding to save them for the father of the monastery when they returned after the verse.
Upon returning from the oratory, he immediately prostrated himself at the father's feet.
When asked why he sought pardon, he opened his hand to show what had happened, and all the crumbs had turned into pearls.
Everyone was wondrously amazed and glorified the Lord.
Then, by the father's command, the pearls were woven into a special ornament for the church.
The brother, as if talking about someone else, would often recount this event.
From that moment, he felt an inner urge to rescue his parents from the ties of this world.
As a result, not long after, he received permission to visit his father, brought him to the monastery, and made him a monk.
He also had his mother take the sacred veil.
If her life had been written about, it would have seemed more like a history than a simple note.
Odo persuades the betrothed to remain a virgin.
During that time, one evening, he stopped at the home of a certain nobleman to rest while the masters of the house were away.
Their daughter, a grown-up virgin, was staying there with the household.
She was very curious and spent the entire evening observing his actions and lifestyle.
Feeling moved, she secretly approached him through a back door and, falling at his feet, confessed that she was soon to be married.
She pleaded with him, for the sake of God, whom she acknowledged he served, to free her that night.
Hearing this, the soldier of Christ was unsure of what to do or how to fulfill the desire of such a virgin.
He struggled intensely within himself, considering his devotion to God and the tears of the virgin.
He contemplated God's judgment, the potential loss of her soul, and the scandal that might arise among her parents and the community, questioning why a monk would dare to take such actions.
But, moved by the love of God and the sobs of the virgin, he eventually agreed to rescue her.
That night, while all the household servants were asleep, he and the brother who was with him rode ahead on horses.
By his command, the servants who accompanied him followed, taking the virgin with them.
The next day, they arrived at the monastery.
Near the monastery, there was a chapel built where noblewomen were received for prayer.
He arranged for her to stay there and then proceeded to the monastery.
The following day, as was customary, he made an effort to report everything he had done to the abbot.
When the abbot heard about what had been done with the virgin, he looked troubled and began to reprimand him severely for acting without permission.
Immediately, he fell to the ground and, prostrated at the abbot's feet, begged for forgiveness.
After this, at the father's command, he was lifted from the ground, and after being questioned again, he responded by saying:
"Lord Father, since you have deigned to take me in my miserable state, as far as I have been able to observe, you have never been concerned with anything else except saving souls."
Most abbots focus on how they can succeed materially and gain people's favor.
But you, relying on piety and mercy, aim to please God alone for the purpose of saving souls.
This inspired me to follow your example, and I wanted to win this virgin for the glory of your name.
Although her tears eventually moved me, I remembered your warning, knowing I couldn't ignore it.
I preferred to be corrected by a kind father rather than be responsible for her soul.
If only I could have saved all the women in this province bound by earthly ties, and you would have had to kindly correct me for each one.
With these words, he calmed the father's anger, but still, he was given this instruction:
Go, and just as you knew how to rescue her from the world, ensure you nourish her daily with holy teachings, so she never regrets her decision and is tempted back by the devil.
Father Odo then began bringing her food each day and teaching her with the examples of the fathers before him, until, within a few days, he led her to a monastery and joined her with the sacred virgins.
All this was done for the good testimony of the brothers present.
Not long after, she passed away in the Lord.
The sisters gathered around her to protect her spirit with prayers, and when they nearly held her as if she were already gone, she suddenly said with all the strength she had:
Help me, please, to rise.
When they asked why she said this, she replied,
Behold, I see the most blessed Paul the Apostle coming, and I want to meet him.
She hadn't finished her words and, stretching her arms as if to rise quickly, she repeated them.
The others thought she was delirious.
Meanwhile, as much as she could, she lifted herself onto her knees, and with her head bowed, she asked for a blessing from the one approaching, saying:
Bless me, and immediately she rested forever.
From this, no one doubted she was received by the one who had visited her.
Father Bernus, foreseeing that he would become a very honorable man, promoted him and, without his consent, called upon a bishop to ordain him as a priest.
According to Father Odo, this bishop would bless food that no dog would dare eat; and if a dog did eat it by chance, it would immediately die, as if it had consumed something poisonous.
I hope no one criticizes me for mentioning that he was ordained without his consent, as doing so might suggest one belongs to those who would buy or sell the gift of the Holy Spirit without fear.
On the night before his ordination, when he awoke, he didn't remember his consecration and found the stole given to him by the bishop around his neck, as per custom.
He immediately began to lament as if something grave had happened to him.
For a long time afterward, out of great shame, he didn't know how to show his face outside the monastery.
Subsequently, Father Bernus sent him to the same bishop on a certain occasion.
When the bishop gave a lengthy speech to console him about the dignity of the priesthood, they ended up discussing the state of the church.
Father Odo then explained a sorrowful speech about priests from the prophecy of Jeremiah.
Once he finished, the bishop asked him to write it down and compose it as a book.
In response, Father Odo mentioned that a monk isn't allowed to do anything without the prior's permission.
Because of this, the bishop went to the monastery.
Being a close friend of the aforementioned father, he quickly obtained what he wanted.
By his order, Father Odo composed three books from the prophecy of Jeremiah, which have since been translated into different churches.
Odo was reluctantly chosen as abbot.
During that time, Father Bernus began suffering from a deadly illness.
He soon called the nearby bishops and resigned from all his duties.
With a tearful voice, he declared himself guilty and unworthy of such a ministry.
Meanwhile, he asked the brothers to choose whoever they wanted as their father.
Then, the brothers seized our father and, as if forcibly constrained, brought him before the abbot, with everyone demanding that he be ordained.
Since he still did not want to yield and take on the role of pastor, he was eventually overcome by the bishops' excommunication.
Thus ordained, Father Bernus soon thereafter passed away to the Lord.
Book Two
Saint Odo is troubled by the disturbances caused by certain brothers.
Due to many hardships and frequent illnesses, I have only been able to recount a few things about our father Odo, specifically those he accomplished under his abbot.
However, your diligence can easily understand from these accounts how great a perfection he began with.
But since the beginning of a blessed life brings difficulties and labors, while the end of struggles brings glory and praise, I will quickly guide you through his blessed and peaceful life, as if along a straight path, to his death.
So, Father Odo was chosen and ordained as abbot, and immediately, the aforementioned old persecutors rose against him.
However, preferring peace and rest over living in strife, he left that monastery, along with what had been prepared there by Lord Berno and handed down to him in a fatherly manner, and went to Cluny, completing the monastery that had been started earlier.
The elders of that place followed him.
Saint Martin is known to be a helper.
At that time, all the funds he had brought with him to build the monastery workshop were used up.
These events took place around the feast day of Saint Martin.
Our tradition is to celebrate it over eight days.
After finishing the morning celebration on the eighth day, and before dawn, everyone returned to their beds, more to rest than to sleep.
Our father mentioned that an elderly woman had a vision revealed to her.
She saw a venerable man with white hair, dressed in a splendid robe, wearing a rain cloak, and carrying a bishop's staff.
He approached and began to inspect the monastery's structure.
When asked who he was and why he was looking around, he replied, "I am the one whose feast the brothers celebrate on the eighth day; I have come to visit them.
Tell them not to lose heart, but to continue the work they have started."
He also mentioned that all the funds he had brought were exhausted.
And he said, "Do not be afraid.
Look, I am now coming from Rome and heading to Tours.
I will travel through Gaul and Aquitaine, and from these regions, I will send them such support that they will have plenty now, and it will last long after."
The brothers, happy and reassured by the promise of such a great man, began to give thanks to God with joy.
As for who this person was, I do not dare to declare, because it was our father's way to never attribute anything directly to himself.
But if he saw something great or small, he would describe it like this.
One of our brothers, or an elderly woman, saw this or that.
Every time he told me this, he also mentioned that within a few days after this revelation, more than three thousand gold coins were brought from the borders of Gaul.
He used to tell me such great and wonderful stories about what happened at the monastery of Saint Benedict, known as Fleury, and also at Cluny.
If I dared to write it all out in detail, the book would become too long for the writer to handle.
As we more clearly narrate the very faithful promise of blessed Martin being fulfilled, I'm suddenly reminded of the significant aid from wild animals.
This might make some readers laugh, but since we have become a spectacle to angels and humans, those who refuse to imitate us, or cannot, may at least be moved by us.
Seeing us progress from good to better things, and finally leaving behind a sorrowful life, may they follow with all joy into eternal happiness.
The dedication of the Cluniac church.
After the oratory of the monastery was built, the brothers invited the bishop, as is customary, to consecrate the place.
However, looking down on the poverty of the monks, he arrived on the appointed day with his entourage and assistants.
When the brothers learned of their arrival, they felt greatly embarrassed, as they didn't have a setup worthy of receiving them honorably.
But that morning, at dawn, a huge wild boar emerged from the forest and hurried toward the monastery.
The church guardian saw it and, being outside the monastery while contemplating the decoration of the place, fled into the church and locked the doors against it.
However, the boar, setting aside its wild nature, as if seeking entry, persistently knocked on the doors and smeared them with foam from its mouth wherever it could reach.
Since no one dared to open the door out of fear, it stayed there until the bishop arrived with his people.
The boar willingly offered itself to be killed, fulfilling the words of the psalmist who says:
"Those who fear the Lord will lack no good thing" (Psalm 34:10); and again: "They will not be ashamed in the evil time, and in the days of famine they will be satisfied" (Psalm 37:19).
Odo's compassion for the poor was truly remarkable.
Father Odo once admitted that he always had enough to support the brothers and give generously to those in need.
No poor person ever left his caring presence without receiving help.
Whenever I accompanied him, he always carefully inquired whether we had sufficient resources to aid the poor.
If everything necessary was available, he would proceed confidently, without hesitation, giving to everyone who asked.
By God's will, everything he needed was provided to him.
He always kept the instruction from the Book of Tobit in mind: "Do not turn your face away from anyone in need, and give to everyone who asks you" (Tobit 4).
If someone brought him a gift and appeared to be poor, he would immediately ask what they wanted or if they needed anything.
If they requested something, he would quickly assess the value of the gift and ensure that double the value was given back to them.
I often witnessed him doing this in many situations.
I must admit, I often felt troubled by such actions.
As a leader, I would express concern about the poverty of our community and the needs of the brothers, arguing under the guise of scarcity that it was wrong to give away everything so freely.
I thought I was being wise, but in reality, I was blinded by ignorance and caught in the grip of stinginess.
However, because he was a very skilled healer of souls, he would gently address my errors with discretion and heal the wound in my mind with his example.
He would say to me, "Be quiet, you speak out of your own misfortune."
There was a young man dedicated to his studies, who one winter night, while hurrying to attend Matins early with his fellow students, saw a half-naked poor man lying in the church courtyard. Moved by compassion, he took off his cloak and placed it over the poor man as he passed by. Realizing what he had done, he dismissed any fear of the cold. After completing the morning praise, he returned to his cell, now completely chilled.
When he tried to warm his frozen limbs by laying on the bed, he discovered a pound of gold there.
From that moment, he had enough to use for himself and to share with others.
However, I'm not sure what she was referring to.
With these and similar stories, she eased the pain of my shortcomings.
I want to move on to other topics, but his countless acts of kindness compel me to speak more about his generosity.
I know this might make me feel embarrassed.
Still, I will write and confront myself with criticism, exposing my faults to everyone.
If I can't confess these things to him now, since he's passed away, perhaps you can act as intermediaries with him.
On his travels, whenever he encountered children by the roadside, he would encourage them to sing.
As a reward for their play, he would give them something from his belongings.
He believed they deserved a significant reward.
He would often say such things to bring us joy with his cheerfulness and to renew them with his compassionate heart.
His words were full of joy, and his speech, due to his great happiness, made us laugh.
But he, keeping moderation in mind, would soon present a chapter of the Rule to us, saying:
Rule of Saint Benedict, Chapter Four, Seven: "Do not love excessive or loud laughter."
And again: "A monk should not be easily or readily given to laughter, for it is written: A fool raises his voice in laughter."
Sirach Twenty-one.
Indeed, he would curb our laughter in this way and others like it, yet his spiritual cheerfulness filled our hearts with inner joy.
But who am I, unworthy as I am, to say anything worthy about him, or to recount such great joy?
Truly, when we couldn't satisfy our minds otherwise, we would secretly kiss his garments.
But what is surprising about us who were always close to him?
Indeed, whenever he entered the church of Saint Peter, the servants of God and those who came to pray would rush behind him, and, grasping the edge of his cloak, they would kiss it.
He walked quickly, almost as if he were trying to escape, and they followed him like they were chasing him.
He was like a cornerstone, both angelic and human, generous and pleasing, so much so that every day he seemed to fulfill what is written in the Psalm:
"Happy is the man who is merciful and lends" Psalm One Hundred and Twelve, verse Five,
and again, as the Apostle Paul says:
"God loves a cheerful giver" Second Corinthians Nine, verse Seven.
He believed that the blind and the lame would be the gatekeepers of paradise, so no one should turn them away from his house, or they might close the gates of paradise to them in the future. If any of our servants, unable to tolerate their rudeness, responded harshly or didn't immediately offer the usual benefits, or refused them entry to our guest house, he would scold them severely with threats; then, while he stood by, he would call the poor person and instruct them, saying:
"When this man comes to the gate of paradise, repay him in kind."
He would say this to scare them, so they wouldn't act that way again, and to teach them with love.
If he found an elderly or weak person along the way, which often happened, he would immediately get off his horse and have that person sit on it, telling those ahead to continue on and directing one of the servants to stay close to the person to prevent them from falling. He himself would walk on foot among us riders, always singing psalms and encouraging us to join in. If anyone, out of respect or fear of him, wanted to dismount, he would immediately tell them to stay seated, understanding they did so out of respect for him, not for the sake of the poor person; for I often saw him do this.
Odo's Journey to Rome.
When we crossed the Cottian Alps with Gerald, the bishop of the church of Riez, we arrived in Rome together.
I recall him helping a possessed woman who was immediately healed and traveled with us to Siena, where she remained due to weakness from dysentery.
Later, we saw her again in Rome at Saint Paul's, where he promptly gave her a coin as a sign.
She sat there, embarrassed, with her head down and her eyes on the ground, so I asked who she was.
He answered, "She is such and such."
He gave me signs to help me recognize her more easily.
During the journey, there was an old and frail man crossing the Alps with us.
He was carrying a bag full of bread, garlic, onions, and leeks, which had an unbearable smell.
Yet the kind father, upon seeing him, had him sit on his horse and took the smelly bag upon himself.
Unable to stand the odor, I distanced myself from the person I was traveling with.
After making it through the narrow alpine paths and beginning our descent, I saw him in the distance, urging his horse to carry the poor man.
He didn't return the bag to the poor man but hung it on the saddle instead.
I hurried to catch up with him, and when I did, he said, "Come closer, for there are psalms we must sing."
When I mentioned that I couldn't bear the smell of the bag, he quickly rebuked me, saying, "Alas! The poor man can eat what smells bad to you, and you can't bear the odor! The poor man can carry it, and you say you can't even look at him!"
He said this about himself, a true follower of Christ.
With these words, he rebuked me and cured my sense of smell so that I never smelled that odor again.
Another journey of Odo to Rome for peace.
This took place during January and February.
Around that time, we were sent to Italy by Pope Leo to act as envoys of peace between Hugh, King of the Lombards, and Alberic, Prince of the Roman city.
After facing some difficulties, we finally arrived in Siena.
However, the city was experiencing a food shortage.
We had nearly 30 silver coins to support us on this perilous journey, most of which had already been spent.
Remembering Odo's habit of not keeping anything for himself or us, I feared that we and our companions might suffer from hunger without funds to buy food.
So, I took the remaining coins and secretly left, crossing the city without his knowledge.
When he entered the city, the needy approached him, asking for the usual help.
But when he looked around and didn't see me, he immediately realized what I had done.
He knew that even though I wasn't in sight, I couldn't be far away.
So, he signaled everyone to follow him, which they did.
While crossing the city square, he noticed three men who, despite their dignified appearance, were in need.
He offered them the chance to share in his blessing.
In front of their house were baskets full of laurel berries.
He immediately asked one of them the price of the laurel berries.
The man mentioned a low price, to which Odo replied, "Be quiet, don't say that price, but say this many coins."
The man complied, and immediately received that many coins, allowing Odo to bless them with his generosity under the guise of a purchase.
Meanwhile, as I watched for his exit, I saw him approaching from afar, walking like a soldier ready for battle, surrounded by groups of the poor.
He was so filled with joy that when I greeted him in our usual manner, he could barely bless me back.
Then, I pretended to ask who those people were walking around him and what they were seeking.
He replied, "These are the servants of God and our workers. So hurry up and give them their reward."
After this, I asked him again why he needed such a large quantity of bayberries or where he had gotten them from.
He started speaking to us with words so profound and powerful that I had never heard anything like it since my early years, nor do I expect to hear anything like it again.
He made everyone so happy that, out of sheer joy, none of us could hold back our tears, nor could we speak to one another.
The tears of such great joy had not yet been wiped away when, considering his fatherly kindness, I began to ask him not to burden us with the load of those berries, but to return them to the sellers.
But he said, "No, I won't do it because I fear they might return the payment after us."
I could hardly convince him to do this by showing him the seclusion of the place and the length of the journey we had already completed.
On that very day, he predicted to me that the former would become the future, along with many other things that happened to me later.
Then he began to instruct me on how I should acquire patience among other virtues; starting with himself, he explained how much and what kinds of things he had endured from his brothers during his time of ordination.
Of course, it's not appropriate to write about this now because of their most holy conduct afterward.
Before we completed the journey, and before all our money was completely spent, we encountered our brother Peter, a priest, who was then coming to Rome for his lifestyle.
From his resources, our poverty was enriched because we received what we needed from him to complete our journey.
This happened over two months, namely in January and February.
Our journey was through the Ammiates Alps.
Such a great flood of snow poured out in those days that it took away our recognition of the path we once knew, and it filled all the hollows so much that with our limbs freezing, we even lost the ability to speak.
When I saw his frail body wasting away, I made him a warm tunic to protect and comfort him.
After completing the mission, our people forced us to return along the coastal borders.
Upon reaching the place commonly known as Burrianum, with the sun already setting over the ocean, we encountered a poor man, half-naked.
I couldn't clearly see his appearance then and couldn't recall it later.
However, I remember he was barefoot, his sides exposed, yet he walked fearlessly over the vast snow.
When our father approached him, he stopped, made us go ahead, and immediately stripped himself to cover the poor man, instructing me to give him enough money for his journey.
I paused briefly and asked him where he was headed, knowing there was nowhere to turn in the vast wilderness.
He said he could reach a shepherd's camp by the end of the day.
From his words, I realized he was not just an ordinary man, because the distance he promised to cover in one hour took us nearly the entire day.
This event had been shown to me in a terrifying vision the night before, in the same sequence.
His compassion was so profound that he not only helped the faithful but also extended his hands to his persecutors.
On this subject, I'll recount an example witnessed by Brother Firmus, the brother of Lord Baldwin, the abbot.
Odo's dedication to peace was clear through his kindness to a hostile peasant.
Previously, when King Hugh was besieging Rome due to his conflict with the late Prince Alberic, Odo moved around both inside and outside the city.
He spread messages of peace and harmony, hoping to calm the king's anger and protect the city from the siege.
One day, as he walked near the monastery of the blessed Apostle Andrew, located on the slope of Scaurus, a peasant attempted to kill him over a small flask of water.
As Scripture says: "The one who walks with integrity walks securely" (Proverbs 10:9).
He walked with his head bowed, harming no one and suspecting nothing.
This habit was so ingrained in him, according to the Rule of Saint Benedict, Chapter Seven, that whether standing, walking, or sitting, he always kept his head bowed and eyes fixed on the ground.
Because of this, some jokingly called him "the Digger" during conversations.
When the peasant tried to strike his head, everyone on the road shouted and restrained the attacker's hands.
Then the gentle father said: "I do not know how many coins he borrowed," and he returned good for evil and let him go unharmed.
However, when the prince heard about this, he wanted to cut off the peasant's hands.
Upon hearing this, Lord Abbot Odo earnestly pleaded for mercy, ensuring the peasant was freed unharmed and uninjured.
Let's talk about the thief and the importance of silence.
Many of you have probably heard the story of what our father once did for a thief while traveling to Rome.
I'd like to share it with you so it isn't forgotten.
While he was in the city for prayer, it was decided that our brother, Lord Godfrey, should go to the field to watch over the horses.
One night, as the shepherds fell asleep and he was praying, a thief came, took a horse, and rode off.
Our brother chose to lose the horse rather than break the silence.
If he had spoken, the thief would have likely abandoned the horse.
Instead, he quietly woke a shepherd and signaled what had happened.
When morning came, they saw the thief at a distance, sitting still on the horse.
They caught him and brought him to our father, who ordered that five silver coins be given to him, saying it was unfair to let him go without compensation for his night's efforts.
After I was drawn to monastic life and later became the prior, our brothers often reminded me of that thief.
Since he was the miller's son, whenever his father opposed the brothers' wishes, they urged me to ask for those coins back.
On the topic of silence, which is essential for a monk's life, we should delve deeper into it.
A monk's life is truly meaningful only when pursued in silence.
Without it, any good or honorable actions, no matter how well-intentioned, amount to nothing.
An impressive example.
During a time when the fierce Northmen were ravaging the lands of the Poitevins and the Touraine with their bloody swords, two venerable men from the same congregation were sent to Touraine for reasons unknown.
One of them was named Archembald, whom I knew well.
The other, whom I did not know, was called Adalasius.
These men were highly regarded and have since become father figures to many monks.
While on their journey, they stopped at a certain place to rest.
That night, they were captured by the Northmen.
Nearby, there was a town that the Northmen attacked and seized during the night.
Another group of Northmen, who had gone ahead, arrived at the place where the brothers were and managed to capture them, binding their hands, yet they could not make them speak.
In the morning, they reached the designated meeting place.
The brothers separated slightly and, while still bound, lay face down on the ground, intending to break their silence only after finishing the recitation of the psalms.
Before their prayer was completed, another group arrived with much plunder.
Their leader, upon finding the brothers on the ground, inquired about their identities.
The captors explained everything, noting that they couldn't get the brothers to speak.
Driven by barbaric brutality and excessive pride, the leader charged at them on his ornamented horse, as if to strike them with a spear, trying to instill the fear of death to see if they would react.
Meanwhile, the crowd gathered for this spectacle was shouting barbarically and clapping their hands.
But the brothers remained steadfast in spirit and unmoved in body.
This was not done in jest, but in strict adherence to the holy rule under which they wished to live and die, never departing from it.
But the Almighty's hand quickly turned their joyful scene into mourning.
As soon as the barbarian approached, the horse he was riding suddenly veered, throwing him to the ground and injuring him.
This fall was immediately followed by a deadly fever.
Everyone fell silent and, in amazement, began to ask each other what they should do.
Eventually, they decided, according to their barbaric customs, that one of them should be killed for the life of their leader.
So, they began to draw lots to decide who among them should be sacrificed.
However, the lot never fell on the virtuous men who were followers of Christ.
They were astonished and admired these men, saying they must be beyond human, as the lot couldn't fall upon them.
Indeed, they had previously killed one of their servants in this manner.
The other servant, who survived, knew the enemy's language well and secretly informed them in Latin of everything that was being said.
We believe this man was saved by the Comforter of men because of these revelations.
Then, approaching them, they quickly untied their hands and, through an interpreter, earnestly pleaded with them for their leader's life.
Consequently, they never dared to bind them again.
It was also remarkable that one of the brothers wore a golden cross around his neck, and when they found it, they dared not take it away.
They used the food and drink they wanted while they were among them; thus, they experienced that well-tested joy that produces patience, about which the Apostle says:
"Not only that, but we also glory in tribulations, knowing that tribulation produces patience; and patience, hope. And hope does not disappoint, because the love of God has been poured out in our hearts"
Romans Five.
And now, therefore, all of you who wear monastic garments, I beseech you to contemplate these men's examples with me and give some effort to silence. For about this good silence, Isaiah says:
"In quietness shall be your strength"
Isaiah.
Jeremiah says: "It is good to wait quietly for the Lord"
Lamentations Chapter One.
And again: "It is good for a person to bear the yoke in their youth, to sit alone in silence because He has laid it on them"
Lamentations Chapter Three, Verse Twenty-Seven.
Similarly, David speaks of this, saying: "I said, 'I will watch my ways and keep my tongue from sin; I will put a muzzle on my mouth'"
Psalm Thirty-Eight.
And the Apostle Paul: "We command and urge those of you who lead such lives to settle down and earn the bread they eat"
Second Thessalonians Chapter Three.
We mention these ancient prophets so that no one thinks this practice of silence was invented in modern times, as some mistakenly believe.
Notably, the Fathers of the New Testament-Paul, Anthony, Hilarion, John, and finally the blessed Father Benedict-imitated this, along with many others whom we do not list by name to avoid tiresome repetition.
If anyone wants to diligently explore this silence, they can find it abundantly in their records.
Therefore, to prevent anyone from accusing us of neglecting the quiet life led in solitude, let us turn our focus entirely to the teachings of the evangelists and begin with the works of the Lord Jesus.
Our first testimony is from Matthew: Jesus told his disciples to get into the boat and go ahead of him to the other side of the lake while he dismissed the crowd.
After sending them away, he went up on a mountainside by himself to pray
Matthew Chapter Fourteen.
The second is in Mark: Jesus made his disciples get into the boat and go on ahead of him to Bethsaida while he dismissed the crowd.
After leaving them, he went up on a mountainside to pray
Mark Chapter Six.
The third is in Luke, stating: During those days, Jesus went out to a mountainside to pray and spent the night praying to God
Luke Chapter Six.
Again in the same book: "Be always on the watch, and pray that you may be able to escape all that is about to happen and that you may be able to stand before the Son of Man."
During the day, he was teaching at the temple, but at night he went out to stay on the Mount of Olives
Luke.
Section twenty-one.
The fourth testimony in the Gospel of John concludes with: Jesus went up to the Mount of Olives, and early in the morning, he returned to the temple.
John eight.
If the Word of God, the Creator of flesh, while living among humans and preaching the Gospel of life, remained silent for a time, it becomes clear what we should do.
Since death and life are in the power of the tongue,
Proverbs eighteen,
and Scripture tells us: In many words, you will not escape sin,
Proverbs ten,
and: A talkative man will not be established on the earth,
Psalm one hundred thirty-nine.
If those brothers, when beaten and threatened while bound, did not break their silence, imitating him of whom it is written: Like a sheep led to slaughter, and like a lamb silent before its shearer, so he did not open his mouth,
Isaiah fifty-three,
but those who suffer no force, nor are compelled by anyone, willingly break the rules, what will they say when judged?
Since the cause of both will be examined in the sight of God and angels.
Regarding this examination, the holy Church cries out in terror through blessed Job, saying: You renew your witnesses against me,
Job ten seventeen.
In these matters, the most severe punishment is for those convicted by witnesses.
Those who receive the curse of the law are those who know the law's teachings and still recklessly turn away from its commands.
The Psalmist says of them: Cursed are those who stray from your commands,
Psalm one hundred nineteen.
The brothers who were sick reluctantly accepted medicine.
There were two brothers in our group, whose names I won't mention here, who, due to their severe illness, often asked him for medicine, hoping to recover.
Initially, he resisted their persistence, but eventually agreed to their request and allowed them to seek treatment.
First, he gathered them and shared a story as an example.
He said, "I once saw a brother with a wound like yours, and he passed away before regaining his health."
But they, unaware of their own situation, brought in a doctor, yet despite the treatments, they never fully recovered.
I also know another brother who, at the time of his conversion, tried to wash away past sins with tears. He gave up other pursuits and devoted himself day and night to prayer, remorse, and lamentation.
When the most experienced father asked why he wasn't with others for teaching or learning, he explained truthfully and revealed the secrets of his heart.
He asked for permission to continue, knowing that according to the Rule, chapter 49, anything a monk does without his spiritual father's permission is presumptuous and vain glory, not a reward.
Our father said to him, "The time will come when this spirit will leave you, and your mind will be troubled by the stings of vain glory."
Soon, that brother lost his sense of remorse, and only after six months did he manage to regain it by pleading with our father.
His words were full of profound seriousness; as a holy man filled with the holy spirit, he never spoke in vain.
John is foretold of the bishopric. Fifteen.
Recently, in the presence of our brothers and others with us, Lord John, the bishop of the Church of Nola, shared that three years ago he had traveled to Rome twice but couldn't receive the blessing of the said bishopric due to opposing enemies.
Meanwhile, Lord Odo was on his way to Gargano for prayer.
Seeing John's sadness, he asked what was troubling him.
After John explained his concerns and expressed his reluctance to return to Rome a third time for the papal order, Odo blessed him and said, "Go again without worry, and know that God has fulfilled your wish."
Then, he let him go.
Following the blessing, John departed, and within fifteen days, just as our father had predicted, it happened for him.
This is why we confidently assert that this man truly possessed the spirit of prophecy, as his words are confirmed with such authority.
The grandson receives baptism.
I want you to remember, brothers, that last year a traveler claiming to be from our father's family, who was in a hurry to go to Jerusalem, spoke to you several times about our father.
He mentioned that during the years when the Norman people were ravaging the lands of Tours, they captured Lord Odo's grandson, who hadn't been baptized yet, along with his nurse.
This father hailed from Tours.
When he heard about this, he immediately turned to prayer, pleading with the Lord until he knew the boy was freed.
While he was concerned for all the captives, he was especially worried about the boy's soul, fearing the child might be lost to hell without the cleansing of baptism.
However, among other things, we shouldn't overlook what the boy's nurse narrated.
She said the captives were taken to a place beyond a river so deep that it could only be crossed by boat or swimming.
This place was an eight-day journey from Tours.
By then, hopes of seeing the boy again were fading.
At that dangerous moment, the woman was suddenly inspired by the breath of God to take the boy and leave, and that's exactly what she did.
She passed through the enemy ranks so securely that not only was she not stopped, but she wasn't even questioned.
She crossed the deep river on dry feet and completed the long journey in just three days without suffering from hunger, thirst, or fatigue until she reached Tours.
The merit of this deed became immediately clear because as soon as the boy was brought to our father, he had him baptized.
Then, looking up to heaven, he prayed to die, and after three days, he returned his spirit to heaven.
His father became a monk.
The blessed father himself explained what followed, not as if these things were done by or for him, but he recounted how the Lord had delivered him from dangers.
He survives a shipwreck.
While crossing the Rhone River by boat with the local nobles, an incident occurred where one horse attempted to kick another.
The kick hit a plank of the boat, exactly at a spot where a branch had been removed during its construction.
As soon as the plank broke, water rushed in through the hole, quickly filling the boat to the surface.
Yet, guided by divine intervention, the boat reached the other bank fully loaded.
Father Odo remained inside until everyone else had disembarked.
Finally, after he got off, the ship sank into the depths.
This situation clearly shows the remarkable nature of this man, who, through his prayers, achieved what was once granted to Peter and Paul, and then to our father Benedict.
At the same time, he had the opportunity to travel to Rome for prayer.
However, not long after, while returning to his homeland, his journey was obstructed by the vast amount of snow in the Alps of the Bordons, a place that is never free from snow.
Near this area lives a group of people called the Marrones, believed to have gotten their name from the province of Marronea.
These people, for a fee, guided him as they usually do for others, because otherwise, no one can cross these mountains in winter.
Before the sun could set, the remaining daylight turned to darkness due to a snowstorm.
As they were trying to pass through this treacherous and dangerous place, suddenly, the horse that our father was riding slipped sideways, and both of them fell into a precipice.
Then, Father Odo, releasing the reins, raised both his hands to heaven as he fell and immediately found a tree branch with his arms, hanging onto it until those who had gone ahead heard his cries and returned to rescue him.
Curiously, that branch was never seen again, as no tree is ever seen or grows there, and the horse was never found again.
Also, robbers. Nineteen.
Indeed, because he was driven by a passionate love for the peace of kings and princes, as well as the reform of monasteries, he traveled frequently.
As a result, robbers often set traps for him.
One day, forty robbers attacked him.
When one of them, more notable than the others, named Aimon, saw him and the brothers accompanying him constantly singing psalms while continuing their journey, he was deeply moved.
He said to his companions, "I have never seen such men before, nor do I think they exist anywhere else; let us leave them alone."
"There is also an arms-bearer with them, a brave man indeed, and we cannot harm them without risking our safety."
They responded, "Let us take down that arms-bearer with our spear, and let the others go after stripping them."
He replied, "Turn your weapons on me first, because as long as I live, you can do nothing to them."
Thus, they were divided among themselves and returned to their places.
The robber we mentioned earlier followed our father, repented of his crime, and ceased his wicked ways of robbery from then on.
We believe this did not happen without reason.
The grace of the spirit that filled him was such that his joy not only delighted the joyful but also transformed the sorrowful into true happiness, making them participants in eternal rejoicing.
For his tongue, as Scripture says, was a tree of life and a soothing tongue, with the sweetness of honeycomb dripping from his lips, and the law of wisdom in his words.
The thief was accepted into monastic life, and as he lived a religious life, he was called to heaven by blessed Mary.
One day, while traveling near the bandits' borders, a young thief noticed the kindness in his face.
Immediately, the young man felt remorse and fell at his feet, humbly begging for mercy.
When asked what he wanted, the young man pleaded for monastic compassion.
Then, our father asked if anyone from the same parish knew him.
The young man replied, "Everyone."
Our father said, "Go today, and tomorrow bring one of the elders from that place with you when you come to me."
Hearing this, the young man went and did as he was told.
The next day, when both of them appeared before him, Father Odo began to inquire from the elder about the life and conduct of this thief.
The elder said, "This young man, father, is a notorious thief."
Upon hearing this, the wise father told the thief, "Go and first correct your ways, and then seek monastic discipleship."
But the thief replied, "If you reject me today, I will go to ruin, and God will hold you accountable for my soul."
Moved by compassion, the kind father instructed him to take the path to the monastery and go ahead of him, which he did.
After spending some time under regular examination, he finally became a monk and was assigned to obey the cellarer brother.
Even though he was uneducated, he was given the yoke of obedience and the task of learning, which he undertook devoutly.
He offered one hand to obedience while carrying the Psalter in the other, imitating the Israelites who, when rebuilding Jerusalem, held a sword in one hand to ward off enemies and used the other for building.
Thus, this brother lived his life, and after a short time in exile, he reached the end of his life.
As he struggled at the point of death, he called upon the kind father, asking for a private conversation.
When he sought forgiveness, the father asked if he had fallen into any error after becoming a monk.
But he said, "When a certain naked person asked, I gave them our tunic out of guilt and took a rope made of hair from the storeroom."
When asked what he did with it, he said, "To restrain the gluttony I had developed over time, I tied it around my stomach."
The holy father was astonished at what had happened.
And when he wanted to remove it from his body, the skin that had adhered to it came off along with the pus.
He added, "Last night, father, I was lifted to the heavens through a vision."
"I encountered a most glorious and powerful woman who approached me and asked, 'Do you recognize me?'"
And I replied, "Not at all, my lady."
She said, "I am the mother of mercy."
So I asked, "What do you command me to do, my lady?"
And she told me, "In three days, you will come here at this hour."
And so it happened.
On the third day, at the hour she mentioned, he passed away.
This clearly showed that what he saw was true because he departed from this world at the time she predicted.
From then on, our father kept the custom of calling the blessed Mary the mother of mercy.
John's mission to Naples. Odo's revelation about the struggle of two brothers.
21. Around this time, due to the needs of our monastery, I was sent to Naples.
Once all the necessary preparations were finally made, I had the chance to return to Rome by sea.
When I arrived in the city of Portus, I was welcomed by noblemen who had also come from Rome the day before.
When I asked about our father, they happily shared, as if speaking to a new friend, what he had done during my absence.
Last August, on the day of the Assumption of the Blessed Mary, our father was at the monastery on the Aventine.
Lord Baldwin, the abbot, asked him to celebrate mass there that day in honor of Saint Mary and to personally give them communion, the body and blood of the Lord.
Initially, he declined, but after they insisted, he reluctantly agreed.
He went into the church, and after a brief prayer, he began to leave.
Those trying to hold him back heard him say, "Please, let me go, because two of our brothers are at the end of their lives, and I must hurry to them so they do not pass away in my absence." Then he added, "Look, at the door of the monastery stands someone compelling me to go."
He had barely finished speaking when the messenger arrived, just as he had predicted. When he reached Saint Paul, he immediately went and celebrated mass for Brother Benedict, giving him the body and blood of the Lord as his last rites. Thus, Brother Benedict surrendered his spirit to the Lord. The other brother, named Gislebert, who was my cousin, followed on the eighth day.
Now, let us return to earlier times as if in a circle, and briefly consider greater examples.
In Rome, they annotated and clarified the Life of Saint Martin with small notes.
Remarkably, the manuscript was unharmed by the rain.
Three years ago, while we were at the blessed Paul's in Rome, Lord Abbot Baldwin requested the correction and annotation of the book about the life of the revered Bishop Martin, which Gallus and Postumianus had composed in dialogue form.
He eagerly agreed and enlisted Brother Othegarius to assist with the corrections.
As they were working, the bell rang for evening prayer.
Following the rule, they immediately left their work and went to the church, leaving the manuscript open where they had been sitting.
Engrossed in the evening prayers, they forgot about the manuscript.
It was winter, and that night a heavy downpour filled all the workshops of our monastery.
The spot where the book had been left was positioned such that water from its roof and three other roofs above it cascaded down like a torrent in that one spot.
The book remained open and stayed there until morning, with torrents of water pouring around it.
The margins of the book were washed on all sides, yet the writing was untouched.
In the morning, the book was presented to the brothers.
As we all stood in astonishment, the wise father remarked:
"Why are you amazed, brothers? Know that the water dared not touch the Life of the blessed Martin." And he said this with some joy.
One of our brothers, quick to speak, picked up the book and added:
"Look and see, for this book is old, eaten by worms, and once washed by water, so much so that it is now discolored. See the signs, and our father says that the book, once washed, feared to be touched by water now? One thing is different from another."
Then the modest father said:
"Be quiet, do not say such things. There is no one like Martin who can have praise among all nations."
Therefore, the actions that the Lord took because of him became a source of praise for Martin.
The monks had their unrestrained speech brought under control.
During that time, our father's name began to shine brightly across the land, like a brilliant star.
He became known to kings, well-acquainted with bishops, and cherished by nobles.
The monasteries established in their territories were entrusted to our father's authority, allowing him to correct and organize them according to our customs.
Meanwhile, he visited a certain monastery with a few brothers, one of whom we recognized as Adolf, who passed away to the Lord two years ago.
After that week concluded, as Saturday evening approached, our brothers began preparing according to the rule's command in the usual manner.
At that moment, one of the monks happened to pass by where these preparations were taking place.
When he saw our aforementioned brother washing his sandals in our customary way, he was moved to anger, broke the silence, and began to say:
"Tell me, where did Saint Benedict command monks to wash their sandals?"
Our brother signaled to him in our manner to remain silent, as it was not an appropriate time.
He did not recall what Wisdom says through Solomon: Whoever corrects a mocker invites insult to themselves (Proverbs 9:7); and again: Do not rebuke mockers or they will hate you (Proverbs 9:8).
Seeing he received no response, he grew very angry, and inflamed with a fiery rage, he started spewing these words:
"Oh, you who used to travel the provinces of the world for business, now you come to preach the rule to us and correct the lives of your betters.
By swearing and perjuring, like a hawk, you were accustomed to taking people's possessions, and now you shamelessly desire to be blessed by us, as if we are unaware of your actions.
For God did not make me a serpent to hiss like you, nor a cow to moo; but he made me a human and gave me the language to speak."
As he continued to bark these and similar things, the aforementioned brother quickly walked away from him.
The next day, when all these events were recounted at the chapter meeting, that unfortunate man not only refused to ask for forgiveness, but he also insisted that he had acted correctly.
He added that it wasn't appropriate for someone like him to be reprimanded by his superior.
Our father, angered by his arrogance, said: "Today is Sunday, so no one should be upset. Therefore, this discussion will be postponed until tomorrow."
And so it was, and shortly after, everyone rose from the meeting.
However, he suddenly became mute and died three days later without the absolution of his words.
Behold the danger of arrogance.
Indeed, many monks have had their lives harmed by this weapon up to now; because while they think they know what they do not know, they become fools by their own ideas, according to the Apostle, as the Scripture says:
"Whoever does not want to be a disciple of truth will be a teacher of error."
About these, the Lord also speaks through Amos:
"They have turned back to be without a yoke and have become a deceitful bow" (Amos 7).
Surely, they seem to reflect those who strive to be called teachers before they become students and seek to ascend to the height of authority before they learn to submit.
Indeed, the untrained youth claim the prize of victory, and with uneducated hands, they do not hesitate to take up the armor of a mighty soldier, neglecting what Scripture says:
"Whoever is not regularly subject should not preside over others."
But because they do not want to live lawfully, they do not fear to turn the face of their heart from the law's command.
Regarding these, the Lord speaks through the prophet:
"They have turned their backs to me and not their faces" (Jeremiah 2).
And Nicodemus, a teacher of the law, came to Jesus at night because he wanted to be instructed first, in order to teach others afterward.
This illness presents two major issues:
First, it subtly drives its creator to ascend to a position of teaching authority under the pretense of holiness.
Second, the misguided individual attempts to teach others based on these mistaken beliefs.
And, painfully, these misguided people try to pull down some who were steadfast in their beliefs.
Regarding such individuals, the Lord says in the Gospel:
"They are blind leaders of the blind.
If a blind person leads another blind person, both will fall into a pit."
Matthew 15.
Their gathering is more like an inn than a congregation, as everyone does as they please and ignores what they don't want to do.
About such people, Solomon says:
"A heap of stubble is the assembly of sinners."
Ecclesiasticus 21.
Blessed Benedict refers to this type of monk as the most disgraceful.
(Rule, Chapter 1).
He describes their way of life as so wretched and miserable that he believes it's better to remain silent about it than to speak.
So, moving on from that, let's revisit the complaint of the aforementioned monk and see what Blessed Benedict advises about the monastery's possessions.
He says, "Let them regard all the monastery's vessels and all its property as if they were sacred altar vessels."
And again, "If anyone handles the monastery's property carelessly or negligently, let them be corrected."
(Rule of St. Benedict, Chapters 31, 32).
After all, what are the brothers' shoes and clothes if not the monastery's property?
If elsewhere he instructs the weekly servants to return the ministry's vessels clean and intact to the cellarer, vessels which are indeed earthen and cheap and assigned to kitchen duties, what should be thought about the shoes, which are valuable and meant to adhere to the church floor?
But just as it seems a serious fault for monks to be overly concerned with providing for others, it is much more serious to neglect their own.
If a wealthy person is criticized for indulging in lavish feasts daily, then certainly, a servant of God faces severe criticism if they wish to celebrate every day.
This is especially true because in the sixth degree of humility, the blessed Benedict advises that a monk should be content with humility and simplicity.
As a result, someone careless might neglect to clean their shoes, tossing them aside where they become ruined and unusable.
Such shoes are of no benefit to themselves or the poor, even though the aforementioned father instructs that all old items should be given to those in need.
We mention this not to suggest that they should appear shabby or ostentatious like hypocrites, but to emphasize that they should keep all their clothing clean and washed, as a certain wise person once said:
If you wish to be good and seek an honest life, cherish cleanliness of body and soul.
The commandments of the Fathers serve as boundaries for those who follow them.
Regarding this, the Lord speaks through Moses: Cursed is anyone who moves their neighbor's boundary stone (Deuteronomy 27:17).
This boundary of the commandment, which the aforementioned monk dared to transgress, rightly resulted in the sentence of a curse where he crossed the line.
This is why the rich man, said to be buried in hell, admits he suffers more from the fire on his tongue than on any other part of his body.
Hence, it is said by a wise person: By what sins, a person is also tormented.
The Apostle James also remarks: The tongue, he says, is a fire, a world of iniquity.
The tongue is placed among our members, it stains the whole body, and sets on fire the wheel of our birth.
The tongue is a restless evil full of deadly poison (James 3:6, 8).
The psalmist also says about it: The Lord will destroy all deceitful lips and the boastful tongue (Psalm 12:3).
Similarly, Ezekiel states: I will make your tongue stick to the roof of your mouth, and you will be mute (Ezekiel 3:26).
And if only the tongue were silent and not separated from the company of the faithful.
What, I ask, is excommunication if not separation from the good?
Among his other instructions, Saint Benedict strictly enforced the rule of silence, imposing the penalty of excommunication without leaving it to any superior's discretion.
Therefore, anyone aspiring to the heights of monastic life should be mindful of their actions and strive to avoid this severe penalty.
Always remember what happened to those two virgins who carelessly ignored Saint Benedict's instruction, as mentioned by Saint Gregory in his Dialogues.
But we've discussed this enough, so let's move on to other matters.
Book Three
The Death of the Monks of Saint Martin.
During the time when our father was teaching us the monastic disciplines, he often shared stories about not just the deaths, but also the tragic downfalls of many monks.
He used these stories diligently to curb our youthful impulses and guide us towards the joys of paradise, much like a shepherd using the rod of fear.
One day, as he was explaining these matters to us, I, guided by his fatherly wisdom, asked him whether the decline of the monastic order was limited to Italy or if it had similarly collapsed across Europe, and how, in what manner, or when this had occurred.
He then began to explain these things to us:
Years ago, while the monastic community flourished at the church of Saint Martin in Tours, they started to abandon their ways and customs, spoiling their life and purpose with their own desires.
They discarded their traditional clothing in favor of dyed and loose mantles and tunics adorned with cloaks.
Their shoes were so colored and polished that they seemed almost glass-like.
To avoid stumbling during the nocturnal praises, they would rise with the daylight.
These actions, and many others like them, went against the rules.
When God decided to bring an end to these matters, one night, while everyone was resting, one monk stayed awake and saw two men enter the dormitory.
One held a sword, and the other instructed him to strike them individually with the words: "Strike this one and that one." When the attacker turned to strike the witness, the observer cried out, saying: "I adjure you by the living God, do not kill me." Instantly, the attacker withdrew the sword, and he alone was spared among them all.
Let's talk about how serious it is to change monastic clothing.
I asked him again what fault it was for a monk who, with a pure mind, used any kind of clothing.
He immediately gave me this example:
During the time when the Normans were ravaging our lands, many from our order left their monasteries, using the enemy as an excuse, and pursued all the worldly pleasures they had previously renounced.
Instead of the company of brothers, they preferred being with family and friends, and instead of the monastery's possessions, they sought to enrich themselves with their own wealth.
Once their clothing, which they had left the monastery with, wore out, they didn't wear similar ones but opted for colored ones, commonly called blue.
During this time, a certain brother, fleeing from this trouble, sought refuge in our monastery, pleading with us to accept him.
Agreeing to his request, he immediately renounced everything he had acquired and gave it to the monastery.
When the brothers instructed him to go and bring everything he had collected to the monastery, he replied:
"I am the one who has subjected everything I had up to now to your authority, and it is in your power to demand or release it.
Therefore, I will not leave the monastery alone, but if it pleases you, command one of the brothers to go.
However, obeying your will, I will go with him and follow his instructions as best I know how.
But whether I stay here or go there, from now on, I will be stripped of all things."
Indeed, at the insistence of the brothers, he went with the brother assigned to this task of obedience.
It happened that when they arrived at the place where the aforementioned brother had lived before, he was suddenly struck by illness and died there.
As he lay on his deathbed, the brother who had gone with him prayed more fervently for his soul to God the closer he saw him approach death.
And so it happened that both of them saw this vision: There was a throne set high up, upon which Saint Benedict appeared to be sitting.
Before him stood an innumerable army of monks.
The steps leading up to this throne seemed to be covered with cloaks, and on the lowest step, as if asking for forgiveness, lay that sick brother.
On either side of him sat the aforementioned army of monks.
However, there was an open path between them for those ascending.
After the brother had been lying prostrate for a long time, one of those standing by approached Blessed Benedict, pleading for the brother, saying he was worthy to be lifted by his vision so he could express his wishes.
To whom he seemed to respond that he saw a man but did not recognize the habit, and therefore should not discuss or judge the cause or life of a man of another order.
Hearing this, our brother of the order removed his clothes and dressed the sick brother in them, urging him to ask for forgiveness again in the same vision.
Once this was done, a voice from above commanded him to rise and go up.
Then, waking from sleep, our brother immediately acted on what he believed he was doing in the dream.
As if now assured of his brother's soul's departure, he protected it by praying as much as he could and fortified it with holy communion.
Therefore, consider, my son, the apostle's statement saying: "Faith without works is dead." James chapter two, verse twenty-six. And as it is written elsewhere: "Whoever says he knows Christ must walk as He did." First John, chapter two, verses four and six. Similarly, whoever professes to be a monk must imitate Father Benedict in action and mind, because it is written: "Not the hearers of the law are righteous before God, but the doers." Romans chapter two, verse thirteen.
For it is not enough for a monk to have purity of mind alone if the signs or evidence of other works are lacking, of which the Lord says: "Let your light shine before others, that they may see your good works and glorify your Father who is in heaven." Matthew chapter five, verse sixteen.
On this topic, the blessed Gregory elaborates more in the first part of Ezekiel.
We'll share an excerpt from his sermons.
Just as there are two ways to stray from God, people can become apostates in two ways.
Each person either turns away from their Creator in faith or through their actions.
So, just as someone who abandons their faith is considered an apostate, someone who returns to their former deeds is also viewed as an apostate from Almighty God, even if they seem to maintain their faith.
One without the other is ineffective, just as faith is powerless without deeds, and deeds are meaningless without faith.
Therefore, no one should be troubled by our previous statement about the brother not being able to receive forgiveness or ascend before changing his garments.
It's clear that the Law specified what kind and quality of garments the sons of Levi should wear, without which they couldn't enter the sanctuary.
Who would dare suggest using the rational in place of the shoulder piece, or wearing a linen ephod instead of a byssus tunic?
Each has its own distinct color, craftsmanship, and variety.
Even Jesus, the great priest, was opposed by the devil until an angel clothed him in different garments.
And David, when he wanted to confront the Amalekites, consulted God twice and wasn't granted permission.
It was only the third time, after he was clothed with the Ephod, that he heard the command.
"Do you want me to show you more examples of how a small thing can greatly disgrace and corrupt?"
When I eagerly responded that I did want to know, and he saw my enthusiasm for his teachings, he explained these examples to me in a brief account.
Recently, two brothers died very suddenly, though not in the same place or on the same day.
One of them went to his sister's house, claiming he was extremely hungry and asked for food.
His sister immediately replied that she had plenty of fish for him to eat at any time he wished.
However, he seemed annoyed and said he was tired of fish, having eaten it continuously for many years, and that he couldn't bear the sight of it anymore.
His sister responded: "Look, we have some meat available, so eat whatever you like."
He then ordered a piece of meat to be roasted for him.
Unable to wait for it to cook, he cut a small piece and threw it into the coals.
Then he ordered wine to be brought and eagerly took a bite of the meat; but the morsel he swallowed did not go down his throat, nor could he spit it out, and he died with the food.
The other brother, arriving early in the morning at a relative's house, immediately asked if they had something for him to eat.
When they replied that it wasn't yet time to eat, he indignantly said: "Alas, I've been riding all night, working under my given orders without rest, and now you expect me to fast?"
"So, bring me something if you have it."
When they said they had fish, he became more indignant and, filled with arrogant pride, began to look around.
A flock of birds, which we call hens, was walking around his feet.
Then, as if mad, he grabbed a stick and struck one that pleased him, angrily saying: "This will be my fish today."
Those standing around him, with some embarrassment, started to say: "Perhaps it is permissible for you to eat meat, Father?"
The bird, he said, is not meat, for birds and fish share the same origin and creation, as our hymn tells us.
At his words, everyone fell silent.
Meanwhile, the chicken he had killed was placed in front of him, now roasted.
He took a morsel and bit into it.
This bite he could neither vomit nor swallow, and it took his life.
He received blows and beatings in disgrace as a reward for his wickedness before he died.
If your mind is troubled over the death of these two brothers, remember how we showed you before with the example of one; they would have been worthy of the death they met.
For a few lentil grains, Esau lost his birthright.
The people of Israel, while being fed with manna, turned their hearts back to Egypt, longing for the pots of meat they recently ate under harsh slavery.
The apostle Paul speaks of these, saying: "Let us not be desirous of evil things, as they also desired."
First Corinthians 10:6.
These people said they were tired of fish; others murmured, saying, "Our eyes see nothing but manna."
We say this not to blame the food, but those who misuse it.
Hence, Paul also says: "Make no provision for the flesh, to gratify its desires."
Romans 13:14.
For what he denies in desires, he grants in necessities.
Three young men sent into the Babylonian fiery furnace, rejecting royal foods, escaped unharmed from such a great fire.
The same fire burned and killed everyone it found from Chaldea.
Therefore, Nabuzardan, the captain of the guard, destroyed the walls of Jerusalem.
So let no one be disturbed that Elijah was fed with meat in the time of famine, morning and evening, but let whoever seeks food consider the provider.
Often demons take on the form of such creatures.
Such food from ravens was suitable for his service, and his fullness in the evening and morning deserved hunger.
But truly, when he ate bread, he had an angel as a messenger, and he was strengthened so much that he did not need food for forty days.
We've explained all this to make it clear that the problem lies not with the food itself, but with the desire for it.
Interestingly, the downfall of many has led to a correction in morals.
Because of this, the order of monks among us declined.
However, it has been corrected, and often is, by many miracles, so that with God as our guide, it endures.
While we intended to delve deeper into the life and teachings of our father, we somewhat unintentionally veered off into these excesses.
Due to this, we've strayed far from our original purpose, which we should quickly return to.
Here's a warning about someone whose vein was cut.
Our brothers, who came before us, often share that there was a brother from our father's congregation who, at the right time, underwent a bloodletting treatment.
This action troubled his spirit because, even though necessity forced him, he shouldn't have done it without permission.
Soon after, the vein from which the blood flowed burst, and until his last breath, no remedy could stop it.
They also mentioned that whether he predicted good or bad for someone, it was unavoidable.
I wish some of us hadn't experienced this ourselves.
Blessed are those who were fortunate enough to witness his presence while he was alive.
Unlucky me, who didn't deserve to serve him for even two whole years.
Odo's fear of faults in the abbot.
As the time approached for us to part ways, according to God's plan, the thought of his absence stirred a deeper love in my heart.
One day, seeing how sad I was, he gently tried to comfort me as he usually did.
But when he realized that his usual ways weren't enough to ease my troubled mind, he began, like the patriarch Jacob, to recount past events and predict the future for me with prophetic insight.
Dearest son, listen to what I have to say.
I thank God, because for all the sins I committed from my youth, I've already faced punishment in this life, except for those against my abbot.
I always hoped that day wouldn't come, praying to God that He wouldn't hold those sins against me in the future.
Now I believe my prayers have been answered, because what I did to him, I have now received back from you.
But understand, they are not returned to you simply, but tenfold.
Be strong and patient, so you can endure them quietly with perseverance.
He said this with tears, then kissed my head and commended me to the Lord.
But You, Almighty Lord, mercifully spare me from what is returned to me by Caesarius the priest, a hundredfold and more burdensome, and if any of my sorrows remain, kindly turn them away.
The monks' craving for meat.
At the same time, Prince Alberic granted us the monastery of Saint Elias, known as Subpentonia, mentioned by blessed Gregory in the book of Dialogues.
However, as blessed Gregory says, it's hard to teach new things to an old mind.
We couldn't stop the monks we found there from eating meat.
Our father appointed one of our brothers, named Theodard, as the superior of that monastery.
Seeing that he couldn't restrain them from this vice through virtue or holiness, he began buying fish from neighboring regions to satisfy their desires.
This effort wore out the horses left to him by our father, as they were constantly running back and forth.
This brother often tried to inform our father of their stubbornness and his own struggles.
Meanwhile, as he prayed to the Lord, the valley where the monastery stands, surrounded by nearby hills, enclosed itself, blocking the stream that flowed through it.
Then, as a mass of water gathered, it formed a lake, relieving the brother of his burden since he no longer needed to buy fish.
But some did not understand the significance of this event, as they did not publicly see how it happened and did not hear our father's prayer.
This is the way of hypocrites, not the faithful, who do not understand what the psalmist sings:
"The Lord has heard the desire of the humble; Your ear has heard their heart's desires" Psalm 10:17;
and again: "He will fulfill the will of those who fear Him; He will hear their prayers" Psalm 145:19.
Similarly, He did this before when he was in France at the monastery of blessed Benedict:
we can speak of this matter more confidently as we have the same father as a trustworthy witness.
But first, a faithful account must be given of how the aforementioned monastery was received, so that our writing may reach what follows as if along a straight line.
The monastery of Saint Benedict of Fleury underwent a reformation.
After the persecution under Normund, the cruel king of the Normans, came to an end in Gaul, the Lord fulfilled His promise through Isaiah:
"For a brief moment I have left you, but with great compassion, I will gather you. In a moment of anger, I hid my face from you for a little while, but with everlasting kindness, I will have mercy on you" (Isaiah 54:7-8).
The brothers, who had been scattered out of fear, returned to the monastery of Saint Benedict, reclaiming their sacred space.
However, while they were united physically, their minds remained divided in that holy place.
Let's move past this sorrowful situation to focus on how Odo, the most blessed father, was called and chosen, even preordained, by Saint Benedict.
One day, as the brothers were in the cloister, one brother, returning from an errand, met Benedict at the monastery gates.
Benedict instructed him:
"Go," he said, "tell these brothers that because they do not let me rest, I am leaving this place. Let them know that I will not return here until I bring from the borders of Aquitaine such a man who is according to my heart."
When the brother hesitated, wanting to ask for the name, Benedict replied:
"Know, brother, I am Benedict."
He then began to leave.
The brother reported what he had been told; however, the unfortunate ones, deprived of such a father, did not turn to tears and prayers, which often pacify the Lord's threats. Instead, they mounted horses and rode out to find him, intending to bring him back either by force or persuasion. Yet, when they found no one, they began to mock the brother incessantly.
During that time, a man named Elisiard, who was once a distinguished count and now lives as a monk, heard about the disgrace of these monks.
He asked for and received the aforementioned abbey from King Rodulf of the Franks and passed it on to our father.
Then, accompanied by two other counts and bishops, he set out with our father, Odo.
When the brothers heard of their arrival, some took up swords and climbed to the rooftops of the buildings, preparing to hurl stones and missiles at their enemies.
Others, armed with shields and swords, guarded the monastery entrance, declaring they would rather die than let them in or accept an abbot from another order.
Meanwhile, they reflected and said, "Look, we see what blessed Benedict recently warned us about. Alas, why didn't we believe our brother? Everything he told us has come true. Isn't this Odo the Aquitanian, the one we often suspected blessed Benedict spoke of? Alas, why didn't we send for him sooner and invite him willingly?"
Meanwhile, they wondered how they could drive them away, considering different options. Among them was a brother named Vulfaldus, a young man of good character. As he moved among them, they sent him certain royal decrees, which stated that no one from another congregation could ever assume the priorate of that place. To him, our father said, "I come in peace, harming and injuring no one, but to correct those who are not following the rules."
With these and similar words, even through messengers, he continually soothed their minds. But when they saw that their efforts were of no use, they turned to other arguments, sometimes calling the king, sometimes threatening to kill him. This went on for three days.
But afterward, Father Odo, unbeknownst to all, mounted a donkey and quickly headed to the aforementioned monastery. Meanwhile, the bishops and the counts who were with him ran after him, shouting, "Where are you going, father? Are you perhaps seeking death?"
Do you see that they are ready to kill you?
At whatever hour you approach them, you will surely die.
Do you want to give them joy from your death and cause us deadly grief?
They shouted these and similar words after him.
But, as Scripture says:
"The righteous are as bold as a lion and will be without fear" (Proverbs 28:1);
they could not in any way deter him from his path.
I'm about to say something amazing.
However, as he approached and was recognized by those who previously knew him, those who were resisting him at that time were immediately moved and changed, so that I can undoubtedly say:
"This is the change wrought by the right hand of the Most High" (Psalms 77:10).
Indeed, they immediately threw down their weapons, went to meet him, and embraced his footsteps.
Truly, a great joy was experienced by everyone that day.
Therefore, they welcomed Father Odo back into the monastery, and everyone else returned to their places.
The consumption of meat and personal ownership was hardly given up.
Bishops gathered around Odo.
During this time, he began to persuade them to stop eating meat, live frugally, and possess nothing as their own.
Whatever they secretly held, they should openly renounce in front of everyone, just like the apostles.
But since they did not hold the monastery's property in common, and instead divided it among themselves according to their ability and desire, when they realized that what was once allowed was no longer permitted, they preferred to unjustly give away their possessions to their supporters, or rather their oppressors, than to properly and regularly renounce them.
They planned to consume by eating what they had formally renounced, along with what our father had brought with him, hoping that once everything was consumed, they would be granted meat even against their will.
Because of this, they incessantly requested fish.
On the other hand, the compassionate father provided them with everything they needed to restrain them from one thing.
Thus, by his giving and their consuming, nearly everything was used up.
Indeed, our father stood firm, confident in faith, secure in hope, and fortified by love, knowing the gospel promise that he would not be abandoned.
Luke twelve, verse twenty-two: "Do not worry about what you will eat, or what you will drink, or what you will wear."
Meanwhile, during these events, Saint Benedict appeared in a vision to a certain brother and commanded him to tell our father not to fear for lack of money and not to worry about acquiring things.
He added, "Tomorrow, I will send one hundred coins, and in the following week, I will provide such a variety of resources that they will suffice for the brothers' needs many times over"; which indeed came to pass.
Furthermore, many people from the surrounding regions began to flock to the feet of the blessed man, taking up the path of pleasing obedience under his teaching, so that they might later be worthy to ascend to the seats of heaven.
His holiness became so renowned that not only laypeople and canons were drawn to him, but even some bishops would leave their positions to join his community.
Meanwhile, you could see that place, like land cleared of thorns, sprouting new growth, as if producing a fresh harvest.
It was like a threshing floor, delivering grain, separated from the chaff of vices, to the Lord's granary through frequent words.
This story takes place on the feast of Saint Benedict.
As the feast day of Blessed Benedict approached, our father decided to travel from the monastery where he was staying to another monastery, so he could devoutly keep vigil by the body of the blessed man at night.
And that's exactly what he did.
On the night before the solemn day, the morning Praise was celebrated before dawn.
One of the brothers, exhausted from the night vigil, fell asleep again.
In his dreams, Blessed Benedict appeared to him.
Once the brother recognized him, Benedict said, "Tell the brothers that although I couldn't be with them last night, I will certainly be here today."
The brother asked, "And where were you, Lord?" Blessed Benedict replied, "In the island of Britain."
Curious, the brother asked, "What did you do there?" Benedict answered, "Brother Leutfred, who, due to his pride, left this place and crossed the sea, died last night and was seized by demons. I struggled against them and freed him from their power."
Hearing this, the brother was astonished at what had happened. The holy father spoke again, "If you marvel at this event, listen further. Know for certain that from the day this monastery was built, all the brothers who have passed away here have been received into eternal rest."
The brother then asked, "Since, Lord, you said you would be with us today, who will let us know the hour of your arrival so we can meet you?"
Benedict replied, "No one, but I will show such a sign to everyone that no one will doubt my presence."
The brother asked, "And how should we prepare to receive such a father, or with what services shall we stand by him?"
Blessed Benedict replied, "If you are concerned about more exquisite foods, you have fish in abundance."
The brother answered, "Not at all, Lord." The saint said, "Let it be ordered that the fishermen do not go to fish in the Loire River, but in this pond, which flows near the monastery."
Upon hearing this, the brother awoke from his sleep.
Eager to share, he told the other brothers everything he had been instructed.
Knowing about their father's arrival and the advice from Father Odo, each brother worked to offer spiritual gifts from their hearts to their spiritual father.
They spent the day immersed in spiritual hymns and prayers.
Meanwhile, the monastery's servants, who were supposed to fish at the marsh, instead went to the Loire River, where fishing was forbidden.
They returned to the monastery by 9 AM, tired but empty-handed.
When asked why they returned empty-handed, they were too ashamed to admit their disobedience, but their silence was betrayed by their flushed faces.
The steward told them, "I know of your presumption. Since you ignored the orders, now go back to the marsh for fishing."
And so they did.
On this fishing trip, they unexpectedly caught so many fish that no one doubted the same power that fed people in the wilderness was directing the fish into the marsh.
The fish were so plentiful that they never ran out.
Thus, the marsh, once known for its croaking frogs, became abundant with fish.
This miracle was clearly documented by our father in the book he wrote about the arrival of Saint Benedict's body in Orleans, with the same meaning but in different words than others.
Consequently, a large crowd gathered for the celebration from nearby regions, including many who were blind, lame, paralyzed, or suffering from various ailments, all awaiting a time of refreshment.
Father Odo commanded that they should not be given food before the Mass.
When the time came, they all entered for Mass.
The church was so large that no one had to stand outside.
Indeed, when they began to sing the angelic hymn, Glory to God in the highest, the doors of the church suddenly shook and opened with a great noise.
Everyone turned around, struck with a certain fear.
In that very noise, all the sick present were restored to their previous health.
The blind received sight, the deaf gained hearing, and the lame walked.
Amazingly, all the church lamps were lit.
Then everyone understood that the blessed Benedict had arrived, just as foretold.
Such spiritual devotion filled their hearts that they couldn't hold back their tears of immense joy.
However, the names of the brothers who witnessed this weren't disclosed to me by Father Odo.
Because of this, it's uncertain whether he or someone else was the one who saw these things.
While in Rome and gravely ill, Saint Odo receives a reprieve from death.
He then travels to Tours during the festival of Saint Martin.
He passes away on the eighth day after the festival of Saint Martin, November 18.
As he neared the end of his life, his virtuous deeds promised him a blessed reward from Christ.
In Rome, he suffers from a severe and persistent fever.
His body is wracked with pain, as a chilling fire consumes his bones and flesh, bringing various forms of suffering upon him.
It truly seemed as though the Lord was already calling him, stripping away his earthly existence.
What could this holy man do?
As a devoted follower and representative of the apostle, he longed to be freed and live with Christ in his heart's deepest desires.
He had completed his holy labors and finished an exemplary course of virtue.
Through divine grace, he was confident, with complete certainty, that the crown of righteousness awaited him in heaven.
However, while he was uncertain about his calling, he wished to first return to his beloved Martin.
It was with Martin, whom he cherished deeply, that he wanted to offer his prayers and entrust his final breath, along with his earthly remains.
Indeed, the mercy of Almighty God is always pleased to accompany pious wishes, and it was immediately present in our Odo, whom He had set apart from birth as a chosen vessel for Himself.
During the following night, beloved by God, Odo sees a vision of a man of striking appearance and grace, who says to him:
"O holy and God-beloved soul, your calling and the final release of your body are indeed near; but Martin delays this with his prayers, granting you a return to your homeland and strength.
When you arrive there, life will be given to you instead of death, and the blessed company of the chosen will be rewarded to you by Christ for your pious labor."
Soon, signs restore faith in the vision: the body's illness subsides for a while, and health quickly returns.
He embarks on the journey with difficulty, not considering his old and frail limbs.
Driven by his great passion for Martin, he overcomes the hard labor.
The more devoted he is in spiritual service, the more confident he becomes about the reward.
After completing the arduous journey, he arrives at Tours, with the celebration of the blessed bishop approaching, a time during which the victorious spirit departed from the body.
Then there is a double joy in the city, as Martin's annual celebration is renewed and the long-desired presence of Odo, a fellow citizen, is reverently embraced by everyone.
During this holy festival, the holy man is so devout, offering prayers mixed with tears to Martin and the sacrifices of a contrite heart on that saving altar.
It is as if he were a living sacrifice, beyond our ability to recount, as our minds are weighed down by dullness and our speech by rusticity.
Concerned about his calling, his mind is fixed on God.
Forgetting earthly things, with a pure gaze of the mind, he contemplates only heavenly things, more attentively as a true servant of Martin.
Thus, he remains in a state of suspense during the entire celebration of the blessed bishop.
However, contrary to his hope, he anxiously groans as the promised gifts are delayed for three days.
But on the fourth day after the festival, the fever returns.
Cold blood creeps into his heart, and his strength is consumed by a bitter wound.
Then, having achieved his desire and being certain of God's mercy, his spirit indeed grows weary in the sick body.
But his joyful mind sees God, sighs, and breathes, with his last voice echoing, "You, Christ, spare the redeemed."
He calls out to Martin repeatedly, looks up to Martin, and prays. He instructs the monks who are coming from everywhere and lamenting his irremediable calling, entrusts them to God with fatherly prayers, protects them with blessings, and bids farewell with pious sobs.
The fourteenth day before December has arrived, marking the eighth day of Martin's celebration.
On this day, the blessed spirit, renewed by divine nourishment and strengthened by the life-giving cup, ascends freely to the heavens, released from mortal flesh.
Guided by Martin, he faithfully presents the abundant fruits of the talents entrusted to him.
In return for his pious efforts, he receives a worthy reward and joins the assembly of saints, shining with the brightness of blessed immortality, through Christ our Lord, who lives and reigns forever and ever.
Amen.