The Life of Saint Goar
by Wandalbert of Prum
In the name of Christ, the Prologue of Wandalbert the Deacon on the Life, Deeds, and Miracles of Blessed Goar, written for the illustrious Marcuvard, Abbot of the Monastery of Prum, begins happily.
The miracles of divine works must always be regarded with unwavering faith and narrated with devoted glorification for humanity, as the Holy Scripture reminds us and the angel commands Saint Tobias.
However, many of these miracles, which Christ's power accomplishes either by Himself or through holy men set forth as examples to the world, are sometimes less known and clear in our time.
This is because we either focus too little and lightly on these due to our preoccupation with fleeting things, or even those that deeply move us with their greatness, we neglect to pass on to future generations in writing, not due to ignorance of the events, but due to the laziness of our minds.
In this matter, our fault is both more evident and less excusable than that of our ancestors.
Indeed, for many years in Gaul, the study of literature has languished, and it is not easy to find many who have performed the duties of the liberal arts in past ages.
Those who, by the generosity of princes and the diligence of the best men, have advanced the studies of the disciplines to our time, now rightly compel us to bear the shame of the crime if we allow the deeds of holy men, which could have reached our knowledge, to perish from the knowledge of posterity.
Moreover, we should not listen to those who attribute so much value to past ages that they deny that things worthy of being recorded can still happen now with absolute judgment.
Divine Providence always orders things that are suitable for humanity in every age, so that we should neither long for the happiness of people of the past, nor is it believable that they would have condemned the state of our times if they could have foreseen how it is now.
Even today in the Church, there are many people living lives of exceptional virtue.
In the holy places of the Churches, amazing miracles often occur, revealing the merits of the saints.
These miracles have become so frequent that few, if any, are astonished by them anymore, as they have become commonplace to the hardened hearts of people.
Therefore, since you, holy and most beloved Father Marchuard, have asked me to undertake a new work, I will explain more accurately the Acts of the holy confessor of Christ, Goar.
Until now, these Acts have been heard in a rather lowly style and language that offends many listeners.
I will add new miracles that are faithfully reported by many in his memory.
For those who might be moved by my writings, I assure you that I do not presumptuously assume the authority to correct the work of our elders, nor do I arrogantly seek to compose a new writing.
I simply fulfill the duty of obedience I mentioned at the beginning, considering it glorious according to Scripture to recount the works of God and record the deeds of the saints for the benefit of future generations.
Proverbs 25:2.
In undertaking this work, I greatly trust in the merits of the holy man and your command, to which I owe all that I can.
I am not easily influenced by rumors or prejudices, having the support of benevolent people.
If the matter turns out well, it will be an absolute testimony of truth and faith.
The Prologue concludes in the name of Christ.
Here begins the booklet on the Life and Deeds of Saint Goar, whose feast is celebrated on the day before the Nones of July.
Goar's homeland, parents, and virtues.
Goar was a native of the province of Aquitaine, which makes up almost a third of Gaul.
He came from a distinguished family, with a father named George and a mother named Valeria.
He lived during the reign of Childebert, king of the Franks, who was descended from the renowned King Louis.
Blessed Remigius, bishop of Reims, converted Louis and his army to the Christian faith through preaching.
Goar lived until the time of King Sigebert, whose kingdom was centered in the city of Metz.
Throughout his life, Goar was virtuous and noble, known for his distinguished deeds, dignified appearance, pleasant demeanor, humble mind, chaste body, faithful beliefs, and notable works.
From an early age, he dedicated himself to religious and pious acts, quickly reaching a peak of holiness that allowed him to perform miraculous deeds and understand heavenly secrets.
As his love and longing for the heavenly homeland grew daily and the fruits of his good works flourished, his life became an example for others to follow.
Many, inspired by both his preaching and his example, turned from wickedness to a better life and more righteous actions; those who had once served the devil began to serve Christ.
After becoming a priest, he retreated to Germany and established a church.
Like a city on a hill that can't be hidden, his fame and the impact of his holy life grew.
He advanced to the rank of priesthood, becoming a steward of Christ's mysteries and a dispenser of the divine word to the people.
As his desire for heavenly things increased, he began to despise all visible things and longed for the invisible.
He left his homeland and parents, becoming a pilgrim in the world and a citizen of the heavenly homeland.
He journeyed to the farthest regions of Gaul.
He arrived in the province along the banks of the Rhine River, called Tricoria, which is part of the diocese of Trier within the boundaries of Wasalia.
There, he chose to serve God freely.
In a certain place on a stream now called Wocara, with the permission and support of the bishop of Trier, named Felix, he built a church using his own resources.
He placed many relics of saints in it, including those of the Holy Mother of God, Saint John the Baptist, and other saints that I didn't think necessary to list.
He excels in hospitality.
In this place, he served God for many years, dedicating himself day and night to vigils, prayers, and fasting.
He strived for patience and, above all, hospitality, which he practiced whenever he could.
While he excelled in all virtues of the soul, hospitality was considered his own special and unique virtue.
He brings pagans to the faith.
Meanwhile, he began to share the word of salvation with the gentiles around him, who were devoted to idol worship and deceived by vain superstitions.
As a dedicated evangelist who had given up everything for Christ, he became a teacher, guiding many to the knowledge of eternal life.
As a result, many nearby pagans, who had been in error until then, were moved by his words and inspired by his example to reject their false beliefs and turn to Christ, the way of life.
To ensure the authority of his preaching, he began performing miracles to help the sick and those with weakened limbs.
These miracles were done in the power of Christ's name, so that unbelieving minds, which couldn't be convinced by reason, might be moved to believe through these miraculous acts.
This is something we still witness today.
He continues to multiply his merits to those who seek them in various ways.
At his memory, we see the blind regain sight, the lame walk, the possessed gain mental health, and those suffering from other ailments receive healing.
This is confirmed in the holy man's life, as reflected in the Psalmist's words:
"Your friends are greatly honored, O God, their leadership is greatly strengthened" (Psalm 138:17).
In his prayers, he was persistent and showed charity to the poor.
Every day, during the solemnities of the Mass, he had a dedicated custom of offering the sacrifice of the body and blood of Christ for the state of the Church.
He would complete the entire psalter with intense prayer.
Afterward, he would share food out of charity with pilgrims and the poor, whom he was almost never without.
He would commend them to God in prayer while also providing them with physical nourishment.
Thus, any traveler who arrived would receive both the word of salvation and the aid of intercession, along with food for the body.
He did this, mindful of the apostolic teaching that God loves a cheerful giver Second Corinthians Chapter Nine, and desiring to receive Christ in the poor and pilgrims, so that he might be worthy of hearing from Him: "What you did for one of the least of these my brothers and sisters, you did for me" Matthew Chapter Twenty-Five.
The devil stirs up envy.
The ancient enemy, always envious of the progress of the chosen ones, strives in many ways to oppose their efforts.
All who desire to live piously in Christ suffer persecution.
The devil was deeply grieved by the works of charity and preaching done by this holy man.
He began to set traps of temptation for him, sometimes secretly, sometimes openly, working in various ways to turn him away from his purpose.
Nevertheless, he endured all these things with equanimity, knowing that it is necessary to enter the kingdom of God through many tribulations.
Therefore, he could not be restrained from preaching, always dedicating himself to winning souls for God.
Nor was he hindered in any way from works of charity, which he knew were very pleasing to God.
So much so, that daily many people came to him, either fleeing from pagan vanity to the sincerity of faith, or desiring by his example to offer voluntary servitude to Christ.
The vexations of rivals are endured.
Just as good people congratulate others for actions they see as worthy of praise and use them for their own improvement, the minds of the wicked always try to obscure the righteous works of the chosen ones.
What they do not want or cannot imitate, they maliciously criticize and tear down.
Therefore, it happened that at a certain time, two clients of the bishop who was then presiding over the Church of Trier, named Rusticus, came to blessed Goar under the false pretense of piety.
One was called Albuinus, and the other Adalwinus.
They claimed they had come to seek what was necessary for the church lights of Saint Peter in the aforementioned city.
While they were supposedly looking for supplies for physical light, they could not hide the darkness of their malicious intentions.
Accused before the bishop.
These people observed what the servant of Christ was doing.
He preached the word of God to those who came to him, praised Christ through psalmody every morning, and then celebrated masses.
Afterward, he had lunch with the pilgrims and the poor who visited him, driven by a zeal for charity and an unwavering practice of kindness, not by any fault of intemperance.
As the virtuous life of a good person is hard for the wicked to bear, they thought they had found a way to accuse the servant of God and tarnish his reputation.
They returned to their patron and began to spread lies, claiming they had seen reprehensible and harmful behaviors in him.
They said he was more of a glutton and a wine drinker than a priest of God.
They accused him of eating and drinking in the morning, unable to follow the usual and proper times and manners of taking food like others.
They also claimed that he preached to cover up his vices with words and did many other things that, unless restrained by pontifical authority, would bring insult and reproach to the bishop himself.
They implied that the bishop allowed these actions to happen in his diocese by a foreign and insane man.
They argued that Goar should be brought before the Church's public judgments to account for his actions, lest this insolence spread among others, thereby weakening the authority of the bishop.
These accusations were made, but while they were plotting against the servant of Christ, divine judgment revealed the true nature of the holy man to others, and exposed the accusers for their own condemnable behavior.
An appeal is made to the bishop's judgment.
The bishop of Trier, hearing these things about the man of God from his people, responds as many prelates do.
Especially those who are worldly, engaged in various occupations, and distracted by many matters, they often struggle to address each issue and cannot easily discern the truth behind what many people say.
Influenced by his people's words, the bishop ordered them to return to the blessed Goar quickly, instructing them to bring him back as soon as possible for questioning about his actions.
The messengers quickly returned to the holy man as commanded.
Wanting to hide their deceit and accusations under a guise of politeness, they greeted him in the name of their bishop, requesting and ordering him to come swiftly.
Hearing this, the man, with a simple heart towards everyone, felt great joy and thanked God, grateful and saying he had been deemed worthy to receive the visit and the command to go to his bishop: "May the Lord make it so, may He make it so that I can, because obedience must be shown without delay."
Even though he could have suspected the bishop's command and the reason for his summons might not have been hidden, he still considered the Lord's authority given to the apostles, saying: He who rejects you rejects me, and he who listens to you listens to me (Luke 10).
And from the apostle Peter: Be subject to every human institution for the Lord's sake (First Peter 2).
The bishop kept the messengers overnight.
Since it was late in the day and they couldn't leave immediately, he detained them and treated them with his usual kindness.
He prepared a meal to refresh them from their journey.
As he often did, he spent the night in hymns and praises to God.
At first light, as he did every day, he began with prayers and psalms to God.
After that, he conducted the solemn Mass.
He then told his disciple to prepare a meal for his messengers and himself.
"Son," he said, "prepare a feast for us from our provisions, so that the bishop's messengers can dine with us. Perhaps God will send a poor person to share the meal and drink with us in Christ's love."
When the corrupt and evil-minded men heard this, they could no longer hide their wickedness. Acting as if they were rightly reprimanding someone, they said, "You are not acting properly, disregarding the legitimate and canonical time for eating. We prefer to wait for the proper time of day to eat."
As if the Kingdom of God were about food and drink and not righteousness, peace, and love; or that delaying a meal was more important than moderation and self-control. They implied the holy man acted for the sake of his stomach, not out of kindness. However, he ordered the food so those who wished to leave early could be refreshed and not sent away hungry, rejoicing to have received Christ in his guests.
When he saw they resisted him obstinately, he calmly said, "It is a bad house where the Lord is not feared. If you truly feared God, you would not refuse charity." While he was speaking, his boy came and announced that a traveler was at the door. Hearing this, he rejoiced, and upon receiving the traveler, he said...
How good and pleasant it is when brothers live together in unity!
When the table was set, he shared a meal with the traveler.
His rivals supplied Goar with provisions.
The executors, seeing this, quickly prepared their horses with enthusiasm, declaring they had found a reason to accuse Goar and charge him with a clear crime to the one who had sent them.
However, they requested that he provide them with some food and drink for their journey.
Always full of charity and eager to do good, even to the ungrateful, he gladly accepted their request and ordered the provisions to be placed in containers.
Then, calling his usual traveling companion, he set out with them on a journey to the city of Trier.
They are tormented by hunger and thirst through divine intervention.
By midday, as they were traveling, the sun had reached its highest point.
Suddenly, in revenge for His servant, divine justice appeared.
Those who had earlier rejected the food and drink offered to them out of love began to feel intense hunger and thirst.
They also experienced a fatigue greater than anything they had felt before.
Meanwhile, the holy man was meditating on divine praise and Psalms, following the Apostle's teaching: Pray without ceasing, give thanks in all circumstances (First Thessalonians 5).
When they had completed six miles of their journey and arrived at a place called Paul's Field, Albuinus said to his colleague Adalwinus:
I am extremely hungry and thirsty.
To which he replied:
And unless I drink quickly, I will die on the spot.
So they stopped by a stream they knew was nearby, intending to drink from it and eat by its banks.
But when they reached it, they found no water at all, because the stream had dried up by the will of the Creator due to their wickedness.
They then reached into their bags to take the food they remembered being given by the holy man, but they found the bags empty.
And rightly so, for those who were empty of love, which is the fullness of all good things, found the bags empty in which they had received nourishment from the man full of love.
Saint Goar miraculously feeds them.
Disturbed by this, and not yet fully understanding their fault, they continued their journey on horseback, wondering what was happening around them.
Their fatigue grew so much that Albuinus fell from his horse as if lifeless, and Adalwin went to the man of God, fervently begging for mercy for himself and his companion.
Then, recalling Romans twelve, verse twenty: "If your enemy is hungry, feed him; if he is thirsty, give him something to drink; for in doing this, you will heap burning coals on his head."
And considering the Lord's command: First John three, verse eighteen: "Love your enemies, do good to those who hate you."
He responded to the one who was asking:
"Son, it is necessary to remember that God is love, and whoever abides in love abides in God, and God in him.
Therefore, when you saw me offering food to you out of love for Christ and receiving it myself, you should not have refused the duty of charity.
Now, however, God is working this for your correction, so that, corrected by His admonition, you may learn to embrace the love which is the bond of perfection."
While he was speaking, he saw three large deer in the distance, as if signifying the mystery of the Trinity by their number.
Immediately invoking the power of the Trinity, he commanded the deer to stay as long as he wished.
They obeyed at once, and although they were senseless animals, they yielded to the divine name, silently accusing the hardness and disobedience of humans.
He took a vessel and, approaching the deer, milked their udders.
Then, allowing them to leave, he used the milk he had collected to rub the limbs of those who lay as if lifeless, immediately restoring them to their former strength and health.
He then instructed them to return to the stream, draw water, and take food from their bags to refresh their fasting bodies.
Thus it happened that those who had previously found empty vessels and a dry stream due to their offense against the holy man, afterward, having received his pardon, found sufficient water in the stream and the food they had placed in their vessels.
It proves that we must obey our leaders.
While they were eating and marveling at what had happened to them, the blessed Goar began to ask why the bishop had summoned him.
It seemed strange to him what business the bishop might have with him.
For we, he said, must show obedience to our leaders, and it is not without reason that divine power today has deigned to show through wild beasts, but to reveal how it cares for its servants and does not abandon those who trust in it.
The Lord is capable of preparing a table in the desert, and how magnificent are your works, O Lord.
At this, those men, overwhelmed with fear and dread, said nothing in response, thinking they would suddenly perish, seeing such great power in the servant of Christ, whom they had dared to offend.
After this, as they were traveling, they arrived in Trier after many days.
When they arrived, the holy man, as was his constant habit, entered the church to commend himself and his cause to the Lord.
He is seized by the bishop under accusation.
Those who had brought him quickly approached the bishop and reported everything that had happened on the journey and what they had observed in the man of God.
Instead of being amazed by the divine works and praising God in His saint, the bishop, consumed with fury, began to tell those around him that the things Goar had done were not by divine power, but by magical arts and sorcery.
He insisted there was no sign of true virtue in him, claiming he was a slave to the flesh and stomach, eating and drinking in the morning, and unable to endure fasting and abstinence.
He claimed that the holy and righteous of old pleased God through fasting, abstinence, and almsgiving.
These things were being proclaimed as if one could be holy through abstinence alone, and not through charity and sincere love for God.
He hung his cloak on a sunbeam.
While this was happening with the bishop, in the presence of the church clergy, a venerable priest entered the house where the bishop was sitting with his countrymen.
He began to look around to see where his disciple, with whom he had come, might sit, or where he could hang his cowl.
Then he saw in the corner of the house what looked like a wooden beam attached to the wall-it was actually a sunbeam coming through a small window.
Approaching it, thinking it was a beam, he hung his cloak on it and instructed his disciple to stand nearby.
It is not surprising that a sunbeam took on the hardness of wood to serve a holy man, since all creation is subject to the will of the Creator who is devoutly served.
He defends himself against the accusation of practicing magic.
When the bishop saw this, he began to question why Goar was hanging his clothes on a sunbeam:
that it was not a divine miracle for a weak man to presume so much; rather, that he did these things out of boasting and tricks of magical arts, not by virtue.
Therefore, he should come closer and give an account of his deeds:
it seemed strange to him that someone with no outstanding sanctity should milk wild animals and use a sunbeam instead of wood.
While these questions were being asked of the holy man, and accusations were being prepared against the simple and pure conscience of a man of God, the holy man, who was well aware of his own innocence, simply replied:
"I have never learned any evil arts: God, the righteous judge, strong and patient, the searcher of hearts and inspector of secrets, knows that I have never known or practiced any magic arts at all, nor do I wish to give any consent to the opposing party in any way.
As for milking wild animals, I did not do it through any incantations, of which I know none at all, but through divine compassion granted and ordained for the health of those who accompanied me; nor do I know anything about hanging my clothes on a sunbeam, as it is said, but rather on an oak stick.
As for being said to eat and drink in the morning, let Him who sees all and judges discern whether I acted out of gluttony or the duty of charity."
The custom of the people of Trier regarding abandoned infants.
As he was saying this, a boy from the church clergy named Leobgisus came in carrying an infant in his arms.
The infant was thought to be only three nights old, and his parents were unknown.
At that time, it was the custom in Trier that if a woman gave birth to an infant whose parents she did not want to be known, or whom she could not feed due to poverty, she would place the newborn in a specific marble basin designated for this purpose.
This basin, now in the monastery of Prum, was donated by the illustrious King Pepin.
It supplies water to the brothers before the refectory, so that when an abandoned infant was found, someone moved by compassion would take and raise the child.
Whenever this happened, the guardians or caretakers of the church would take the child and ask the people if anyone was willing to raise the child as their own.
If someone offered to do this, the abandoned infant was brought to the bishop, and by his authority, the person who took the infant from the caretakers was granted the right to raise and keep the child.
The infant's speech defends Goar's innocence.
Here's what happened: the infant was found in a shell by the cleric mentioned earlier and brought before the bishop and the church.
Seeing this, the bishop addressed his people, saying, "Now, we can easily determine whether Goar's works are from God or from the adversary.
Let it be revealed to us who the parents of this child are; and if he is relying on divine power, let the three-day-old infant speak, against the natural order, and tell us the names of his parents."
The man of God is put to the test; the bishop orders him to prove his innocence and the holiness of his simple soul by performing this miracle.
He must do something to strengthen the faith of those who doubt him, making them listen and follow him.
If he either does not want to do this or cannot do it, his past actions and claims of innocence and purity will not be believed.
Everything he has done so far would be attributed entirely to witchcraft: therefore, a capital punishment, as for a sorcerer and magician, would be imposed on him.
Then the most blessed man began to be deeply distressed and afflicted, because such commands from his bishop put him in a difficult position:
his own conscience and the testimony of divine judgment were always enough for him. It should not be demanded of him, knowing himself to be a sinner, but these miracles are meant for the saints."
Since he couldn't resist the bishop's commands and feared that those who usually listened to him might misunderstand his intentions, he turned to prayer, extending his hands to God, and said:
Christ, who emptied yourself for the redemption of mankind and took the form of a servant, show mercy to me, though I am an unworthy servant of yours.
Display the power of your virtue in this need.
Let the present bishop and his people know that I love you, worship you, and genuinely wish to serve you, Creator and Redeemer of all.
After saying this, he approached the person carrying the infant and asked how many nights the child had been alive since birth.
When he was told that the child was born three nights ago, the man of God added:
Holy Trinity, I invoke you, and I adjure you, infant, in the name of the Trinity, to clearly name your parents.
Then the infant, extending his hand towards the bishop, responded in the clearest speech:
This is my father, Bishop Rusticus, and my mother is called Flavia.
Thus, by the most just judgment of God, while the bishop was making slanders against the servant of the Lord and trying to obscure with malicious deceit the works he should have admired, it was clearly revealed to all what his deeds were and what kind of person he was in his private life, even as he judged others publicly.
The bishop is encouraged to do penance; a sevenfold penance is promised for him.
When the bishop realized he had been exposed and saw that what he believed could be hidden had been revealed to everyone, he fell at the feet of the blessed man.
He confessed without a doubt that he recognized Goar as holy and acceptable to God.
Through Goar's virtue, or rather divine retribution on his behalf, the crime that he thought only he, the woman he had illicitly been with, and one small child knew about, had been uncovered through an innocent and not yet speaking infant.
The holy man, considering what had happened, stood astonished and perplexed, drawing deep sighs from the bottom of his heart.
Turning to the bishop, he began to lament that the bishop seemed to have been publicly exposed through him.
He said it would have been better to make a voluntary and secret confession, that the bishop should have cleansed the guilt of his conscience through voluntary correction and appropriate satisfaction before being publicly known.
For it is true and firm: "Nothing is covered up that will not be revealed, or hidden that will not be known" (Matthew 10).
Therefore, he advised the bishop to accept wholesome advice and undertake severe and prolonged penance for his guilt, as judged by the priests.
This penance should not consist only of words but come from the depths of the heart, with true tears and the contrition of the spirit, to satisfy God, who desires the life of all.
He should work diligently so that, as he has brought gain and joy to the devil by committing such a great crime, he should now bring sorrow and confusion to the devil by doing worthy penance.
No one, not even the bishop himself, should despair of forgiveness since the Lord Himself cries out through the prophet: "I do not desire the death of the sinner, but that he turn back and live, and on whatever day the sinner turns back, I will forget all his iniquities" (Ezekiel 18).
And Jesus Himself says in the Gospel: "I have not come to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance" (Luke 5).
Since heavenly mercy is prepared to forgive, it's necessary for people to be ready to repent.
He himself is in a state of mind where, according to his abilities, he is willing to undertake and complete seven years of penance for his sin.
With constant prayers and laments, he wishes to beg God for mercy on his behalf.
Although he knows there will be many good and better men who will mourn his fall and support him with their prayers, he recalls the words of the Apostle James: "Pray for one another, that you may be saved" (James, Chapter Five).
With these and similar words, he urged the bishop towards penance and satisfaction.
With the love he had for everyone, he sympathized with his situation and asked the Lord to forgive him, remembering the apostolic saying: "Whoever brings back a sinner from the error of his way will save his soul from death" (James, Chapter Five, Verse Twenty).
Modestly, he responds to Sigibert about himself and the bishop's accusation.
After these events, news quickly reached King Sigibert, who immediately sent messengers to summon the blessed Goar.
Once Goar arrived, the king questioned him about the reports he had heard, including the bishop's messengers, the tamed wild animals, the bishop himself, and the child who spoke beyond his years.
Since Goar did not respond, to avoid appearing boastful, the king, moved by the obedience owed to kings, princes, and priests, ordered him to explain in detail what he was being questioned about.
Compelled by necessity, Goar asked the king what he wanted to hear from him.
The king replied that he was inquiring about the messengers, the animals, and the bishop.
The holy man then asked the king to recount the events as he had heard them.
After the king explained the events in detail, the blessed Goar added:
I must not neglect obedience, but you will hear nothing else from me than what you have already said, for it happened as it was reported.
He refuses the bishopric.
Then the king, filled with admiration, began to openly share what he had learned about the acts of the holy man.
As he spoke, everyone started to shout that Goar deserved to become the bishop of Trier after Rusticus was expelled, believing this was divinely ordained.
They thought the one who could adorn the pastoral office with signs, virtues, and a meritorious life should lead the Church.
The king, with a joyful and eager spirit, wanted to fulfill their wishes.
Therefore, with the support of the priests and nobles present, he ordered that Goar should accept the bishopric of the Church.
However, Goar, who did not seek his own benefit but that of others, and who remembered the wise man's advice, "The greater you are, the more humble yourself in all things" (Ecclesiasticus 3), and the Lord's saying, "When you have done all that you were commanded to do, say, 'We are unworthy servants; we have only done our duty'" (Luke 17), began to feel sad and distressed, taking the king's command seriously.
He said it would be better for him to die than to take up the bishop's seat.
He advised the king to consider divine wisdom in the priest, as it is said: "The disciple is not above the master, nor the servant above his lord" (Matthew 10); and: "If they have called the master of the house Beelzebub, how much more will they call those of his household?" (Matthew 10).
He argued that a place of repentance should not be denied to a bishop, that the King of all in heaven judges each person, and that just as the king wishes to have his sins forgiven, he should also allow Rusticus to seek forgiveness for his actions.
He said it is not easy to depose a priest from his office, given that all mortals are fragile and prone to sin due to the weakness of the flesh.
The king, under pressure, asked for a truce.
In response to what had been seen, the king replied that he would neither deny the bishop penance nor refuse to follow the advice of the one through whom such miracles were performed.
However, he couldn't go against the judgment of the priests and the will of the people, and thus agreed to promote the bishop to the episcopate as requested.
Then the very holy man, seeing the king stubbornly resisting him, humbly and tearfully asked to return to his cell so he could think freely for a while and respond appropriately.
The king immediately allowed this and ordered him to return to the city of Mediomatricum, now called Metz, within twenty days.
He withdrew to his cell, planning in the meantime to find a way to avoid the king's proposition.
Once he reached his cell, he prostrated himself in prayer and earnestly implored the Lord to mercifully deliver him from the heavy burden of pastoral care.
He believed it was enough to serve his remaining days in secret and in the hidden depths of his conscience, and felt he couldn't bear the burden the king wished to impose.
Persisting in these prayers and afflicting himself, he was struck with a severe fever and began to suffer from a long illness.
What more can be said?
The situation unfolded in such a way that the king, who expected to see him after twenty days, did not see him even in the span of seven years.
Thus, Divine Providence acted towards His servant, allowing him to avoid the king's insistence on promoting him to the episcopate.
He fulfilled his promise to the bishop of praying for him for seven years, albeit in infirmity.
During his whole life, especially in those seven years, he devoted himself to prayer, praying as the Apostle instructs for all people, for kings, and for all those in high positions, so that they may lead a quiet and tranquil life in all godliness and dignity, as it is written in First Timothy chapter 2.
After those same seven years had passed, she continuously shed tears without stopping and constantly prayed to the Lord, remembering this verse:
"Those who sow in tears will reap with joy"
Psalm one twenty-six;
knowing that the end of her life was not far off, and desiring to depart and be with Christ
Philippians one twenty-three.
Sigibert couldn't visit because of his illness.
So, after seven years had passed, King Sigibert remembered the decision he, the people, and the nobles of the palace had made about Saint Goar.
He immediately sent messengers to ask him to come.
But Saint Goar, filled with the Spirit of God and aware that his death was near, responded prophetically:
"Tell your lord, my children, that he will not see my face in this life unless he comes to my cell himself, because I am gravely ill and cannot move. Although these divine punishments are much lighter than I deserve."
When the messengers reported this to the king, he sadly remarked that he was not worthy to have such a teacher, nor did the people deserve such a bishop. Nevertheless, he sent other messengers, earnestly pleading for the holy man to come and not deny himself to a prince who greatly desired to see him. When they arrived, they found the servant of Christ suffering from a much stronger fever and illness, yet constantly praising God.
With them nearby, the holy man said: "Do not tire yourselves or your king any further, my children, because I am certain and trust in divine mercy that I will not leave this place anymore, except for my own burial."
Thus, remaining firm in his purpose, he continued steadfastly in praising God and praying.
He asks the king for a place for his burial and attendants.
Then those who had been sent to him inquired what he wished to obtain from the king through them.
He replied:
My only request is this: if it pleases him, he may gain from this place an increase in merits and a cause for eternal reward in the kingdom of heaven.
And when my last day in this life and my due end comes, by his authority and command, he may have Agrippinus and Eusebius, the priests, come to me, who should commit my body to burial.
Having received this response, those who had been sent returned to the king, reporting the words and prayers of the priest in order.
When the king learned of this, he was deeply moved, groaned, and his face changed, for he saw that he was about to lose such a great man soon.
Immediately, summoning the aforementioned priests to him, he ordered them to proceed to his cell according to the will of the holy man, commanding them to carry out with all diligence and care whatever he instructed.
He died and was buried.
After those seven years we mentioned earlier, he spent three years and three months in illness, praising God.
This blessed man, full of days and good deeds, and known for his acts of justice, passed away in his cell where he had served God for many years.
He was surrounded by the priests we mentioned and many other good and honest men.
He died on the fourth day before the Nones of July, leaving behind the world and its pleasures and desires, which he had long forsaken for the love of the heavenly homeland.
He reached Christ the King and the happiness of eternal life, where he will forever possess eternal goods.
He did not want to possess the so-called goods of this present time when he could have, and now he will have an eternal, God-made home in the heavens with Christ.
He often made his poor and earthly home a refuge for Christ in his members.
Agrippinus, Eusebius, and other priests and noble men who were present, took care of his lifeless body with the utmost honor and reverence, and buried it in the same place and church which he had built.
Here's what I have to share about the life of the holy man Goar.
I've based this on ancient and very old sources, aiming to follow the truth faithfully in recounting these events.
I've made an effort to refine the simplicity of the speech, which might have offended the learned, as per your wishes, most distinguished and revered father.
I hope that both I and everyone who reads this will always be helped by the intercession and merits of this great man before the divine mercy.
We, who daily falter against divine laws due to human weakness and mortal life, may, through the intervention of the one who faithfully served the law of Christ, be relieved of our sins and deserve assistance in living well, by the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ.
To whom, with the Father and the Holy Spirit, is honor and glory forever and ever, Amen.
The booklet detailing the life and deeds of the holy and blessed confessor, Goar, written by the deacon Wandalbert, concludes happily.
Here begins another booklet on the miracles that took place at the Memorial of Saint Goar, from the time his church began to be built successfully.
Author's Prologue. The Authority of This Writing.
Now that I have found and corrected, as best as I could, the writings about the Life and Deeds of Blessed Goar handed down by our predecessors, and with your encouragement, dear father, which I gratefully embrace in all things, I see that I must undertake a new work.
Just as I promised in the preface of the previous book, I must write down for future generations the miracles that have been divinely performed in the most sacred memory of the aforementioned confessor, as I have learned them from the faithful.
These miracles are so clear that, except for a few who were present or heard from those who were, they have remained completely unknown to others.
I would consider it a great fault if not for the lack of written records and the neglect that has crept in due to the laziness and indifference of some, which has led us to regard divine works and the benefits granted to us in our times as trivial and insignificant.
In describing these events, I will fully follow the accounts of those who reported them to me, including only what they confirmed they saw themselves or heard from those who witnessed it.
However, there are so many and they are so significant that if I wished to record them all, I would exceed the scope of a reasonable volume.
From this, we can easily estimate how many great things must have been performed by the merits and virtue of this man over the long span of past times, given the vast number of events known to have occurred and reached our knowledge within approximately the last seventy-seven years.
It is not credible that the merits of this holy man in performing miracles began to shine only in our days, and not also in earlier times, conferring the same benefits to believers and the devout through him, even if the records were not handed down to posterity.
I want everyone to know that I didn't trust just anyone with these claims, but rather credible men.
And you, venerable father, have judged the truth of their accounts.
Especially Herirad, a monk and priest of your congregation, and Theodrad, a cleric of Saint Goar's cell, who were both older and had lived near that place since childhood.
On the translation of the body of Saint Goar.
The chamber of Saint Goar was granted to Abbot Asuerus of Prum by Pippin.
The church was restored, not without a miracle.
To get to the story, many years after Saint Goar's death, when clerics performing divine services were already supported by the church's stipends and the crowd of people increased daily, the chamber of Saint Goar was entrusted to the venerable Asuerus by the pious Frankish prince Pippin, father of the emperor Charles of august memory.
Asuerus was the first to head the monastery at Prum, which you now manage as the third, dearest father.
He aimed to improve the place and instruct the clerics in the practice and study of religion.
To enhance and ennoble his task, he began building a basilica over the body of the holy man, ample enough to accommodate the people and suitably decorated to honor the blessed confessor.
There were previously two churches not far apart from each other.
The smaller one was believed to contain the venerable body in the earth, but the exact location of the sepulchre was unknown.
Leaving that church intact, Asuerus laid the foundations around it and constructed the basilica that remains to this day.
The earlier church was not destroyed until the entire construction of the present building was completed.
During this time, those who knew well testified to a remarkable event: until the basilica was entirely built, no rainwater, despite the heaviest downpours, fell on the entire site.
When it rained, it fell around the middle of the Rhine and the top of the mountain, leaving the intervening space completely dry.
This divine miracle made it clear how pleasing the building's work was to the heavenly regard, as the rain showers were somehow prevented from hindering its progress.
The church was dedicated.
When the basilica was completed, and the time came for it to be consecrated to the divine name, messengers were sent by the most excellent prince Charles.
The Archbishop of Mainz, a commendable man of character and life from the English people, and Basinus of Speyer-which is now called Speyer-along with Megingoz of the city across the Rhine, known locally as Wurzburg, were all bishops ordained by Saint Boniface, bishop and martyr.
Through them, the church was consecrated, and the body of the most blessed man was moved to its current resting place.
The remains of Saint Goar are sought through three days of fasting and prayer.
Once found, they heal a cleric with a disabled hand.
They arrived at the location, and after consecrating the house, preparations began for the translation of the body.
Abbot Asuerus was present with some monks, and an immense crowd had gathered from everywhere.
The bishops decided to first seek the Lord's will through three days of fasting before proceeding with lifting the relics.
After this was devoutly carried out by all, Archbishop Lul commanded his men to dig in the old church, so the venerable relics could be lifted and transported.
But when all the ground underneath was dug up and examined, and no sign of the sought-after treasure was found, the bishop, troubled, asked the abbot if there were any clerics serving God in the place.
The abbot replied that there were only six.
The bishop called them to him and urged them to pray for divine mercy to find the body of their patron.
He commanded the others present to withdraw for a time, and he himself departed to dine with the abbot and the co-bishops.
Then the clerics who remained diligently prayed to Christ to help them find where the venerable relics were hidden.
Among them was a cleric named Madalbertus, who had a disabled right hand and a limp.
He grabbed a spade and said, "Now, if God wills, it will be clear where my lord is buried." He immediately went outside the old church's area and, not far from its eastern wall, struck the ground with the spade, lifting a brick with the blow. With the brick lifted and a small hole exposed, he used his disabled hand to pull out the silk cloth covering the sarcophagus enclosed within the brick wall. His hand, previously disabled, was immediately restored to health.
Thus, with the sarcophagus quickly uncovered, and with the bishops and people summoned by the excitement of the new miracle, everyone present gave thanks and praises to God. The body of the holy man was found inside a leaden coffin within the sarcophagus.
The body was immediately lifted and placed on a bier, then taken to the oratory of Saint Mary, which had been nearby for a long time.
It was to be transferred shortly afterward to a prepared spot in the new church, with the people watching.
The relics, initially immobile, were carried to the new church.
The bishops decided that, due to the narrowness of the place-bordered on one side by the Rhine River and on the other by a very high mountain-the crowd could not gather in one spot.
Therefore, they instructed that the crowd spread out along the base of the mountain.
Because of the multitude's desire and presence, the revered relics were to be carried a bit farther along the upper path that leads around the base of the mountain and then brought back to the new church.
Upon announcing this plan, when the bishops tried to lift the bier, it was so heavy that it could not be moved at all.
With everyone puzzled and waiting for a long time, the archbishop, inspired by God as it later became clear, addressed the people.
He said that Saint Goar, during his life, had scorned worldly glory, human applause, and favor, considering them fragile and perishable, out of love for eternal goods; he continued to scorn them even after death.
Therefore, the body should be lifted simply and with humble devotion and carried directly from the church to the new house, without being paraded around to please the crowd as had been planned.
Barely had the bishop finished speaking when the bier was lifted with such ease as if it had never been heavy.
The venerable relics were then brought to the new church by the bishops and the abbot and placed with the highest honor and reverence in the spot where they are now venerated.
Finally, the cloth found on the sarcophagus, as mentioned above, remains incorrupt above the church altar even today.
Thus, the garment has remained intact through the ages, a testament to Saint Goar's enduring merits before God.
The basilica was completed, honoring the memory of the holy man as it deserved.
Miracles and divine favors began to occur there continuously.
I will briefly recount some of these, mentioning what happened under each abbot, in order.
Miracles Performed During the Time of Abbot Asueri.
About the wine that increased in the cask.
Asuerus, the first abbot of the monastery of Prum, often faced challenges due to the infertility of the land, which sometimes resulted in a smaller quantity of wine being produced in the regions of Gaul.
As the time for the new vintage approached, the clerics living in the holy man's cellar had only one cask of wine left.
When they began using it, and every day both the clerics and the numerous guests were given cups from it, after eight or nine days, they thought the wine had dwindled to barely half or a third of the cask.
But suddenly, they found it had increased to the brim, so much that the floor beneath was soaked with the overflowing wine.
This miracle occurred because the blessed man always practiced hospitality properly and sincerely.
As a result, neither the servants nor the guests who arrived ever lacked wine to be served.
On the wine that stayed in the open barrel.
Here's another miraculous tale:
One evening, as night approached, Horduinus, the cellarer, drew some wine from a barrel.
Lost in thought, he didn't secure the barrel properly and left it slightly open.
The next day, when he returned to the barrel, he found the opening still open, with a spider's web spun across it.
Remarkably, not a single drop of wine had spilled onto the floor.
About the slave of a nobleman named Wido, who was lame and then healed.
Around the same time, a slave of a nobleman named Wido, who was limping, came to the place and was healed through the merits of the holy man.
With his master's permission, he dedicated himself to church service and, before long, became a priest.
When these events were recorded, he was still alive.
About a certain Freculfus who lost his mind.
During the reign of Asuero, a chief of the royal estate named Freculfus, from a place not far called Wasalia, lost his mind.
When his people took him to the venerable memorial, he regained his sanity.
About Waltarius, a nobleman possessed by a demon.
Waltarius, a man noble by worldly standards, is still alive today and was suffering from a very severe affliction, undoubtedly possessed by a demonic spirit.
He was sewn into a hide and taken to the venerable tomb, where he lay for a while.
With his hands outstretched, he dedicated himself and all his possessions to Saint Goar with a loud declaration and even gave a very fine vineyard, which remains in the possession of the same Cell to this day.
Immediately, he was freed from the madness he had suffered for so long.
Although he remains free and is sometimes accused by many of being driven by greed and stealing others' property, he still freely declares himself to be a servant of Saint Goar and testifies that he was healed by him.
Reginarius, the uncle of Waltarius, was punished for his arrogance.
Despite being a nobleman, Reginarius was known for his cruelty and greed.
He despised holy places and harbored a deep-seated hatred for people of the Roman nation and language, to the point where he couldn't even stand to see them.
If he captured anyone from this group, he would sometimes treat them cruelly.
With the same foolish hatred and barbaric mindset, he detested the venerable Asuerus and some of his monks.
One day, as the abbot was residing in his cell, Reginarius had to pass by due to his journey.
As he neared the church, he asked his servant to guide him in a way that would avoid the sight of the basilica of Goar and the presence of the Romans, including Abbot Asuerus and his companions.
So strong was his foolishness and innate savagery that he couldn't even bear to look at noble Roman men in passing.
The servant promised to fulfill this request.
After traveling a bit and arriving at the monastery and basilica, the servant advised his master to cover his head with a cloak for a short time if he wanted to avoid seeing those he dreaded.
Reginarius did as advised and moved past the place.
The servant then said, "Now, be careful not to look back, for you will see no one you wished to avoid."
However, as soon as the servant finished speaking, Reginarius was struck by a severe bowel movement, and shortly after, he died.
Thus, the one who foolishly and arrogantly shunned the sight of the venerable place and good men was, by God's just judgment, deprived of both the light of day and his life.
About the miraculous fish given on the feast of Saint Goar.
One year, when Asuerus, the abbot, came from the Prum Monastery for the feast of Saint Goar, along with some monks, the Rhine River was flooded, and there were no fish available to serve the abbot and the brothers.
On the day of the celebration, a few of the brothers were sitting in front of the church in the morning.
A monk named Ansegilus, known for his good life, joked while sitting with them:
"O blessed Goar, see how good you are at rewarding us. We serve you and labor in vigils and psalm-singing for your feast; today, you do not even provide us with a single little fish to refresh ourselves."
He had scarcely finished these words when, not long after, in some willow baskets prepared for fishing, which had been suspended from a tree by a fisherman on the riverbank and left in the water as the river rose, two sizable fish, commonly called catfish, were found and brought to where the brothers were sitting.
However, the abbot did not use this fish due to illness. Then the monk who had spoken before said:
"For us, you have done well, providing fish for our refreshment, but you should not neglect that old abbot of yours; he will not be able to use it."
After a short time, when the miller was bringing flour by boat, a fish, which we call a pike, jumped into the boat and was caught by the miller, who brought it to the gathering of monks (for they had not yet risen from the place).
"Now," said the monk, "blessed Goar, you have fulfilled your complete gift, since you have provided appropriate food for both us and your old abbot."
It is remarkable that such playful words were so easily heard! But these events are not unlike the merits of the blessed confessor: for when he was living, he used to give his possessions to the needy for Christ's sake and always offered hospitality and refreshment. Rightly, after his death, he could provide such things for those serving him.
The virtue of hospitality holds great merit in divine judgment, especially as it was a quality the blessed man notably practiced during his life.
The reverence due to the place where his sacred remains rest is affirmed by those who frequently visit and receive divine favor.
Conversely, those who neglect or pass it by with indifference still face divine judgment.
The following examples will illustrate this more clearly.
About Count Heriwin Warned by Divine Scourge.
A certain count named Heriwin was traveling through an area and decided to stop.
Although his men advised him to pray, he postponed it due to the urgency of the journey.
Not long after, he fell from his horse and was seriously injured.
His men carried him back to the church.
While lying there briefly, he received a blessing of health at the revered memorial.
About Eufimia the Abbess, similarly corrected.
In the same way, Eufimia, the noble abbess from the city of Metz, while traveling there, did not dismount to pray as everyone usually did.
Shortly after, she fell from her horse and broke her leg.
She was reluctantly carried to the church, and she regained her health through the merit of the blessed man.
About Emperor Charles and the Peril He Faced Due to His Ignorance.
His authority in punishing and advising even kings was unmatched.
Charles, the emperor of most excellent memory, was sailing from his palace at Ingelheim on the banks of the Rhine River.
He was heading to a castle at the confluence of the Moselle and Rhine rivers, intending to stay there for the night.
His sons, Charles and Pippin, were following him in separate boats.
When the emperor reached the monastery of the holy confessor by boat, Abbot Asuerus met him and asked him to visit Saint Goar and offer charity in his cell.
The emperor declined and signaled his son, also named Charles, to leave the boat and pray in the church, while he continued his journey.
When his son disembarked, Pippin, who was following in another boat, mistook the docked boat for his father's.
He also disembarked and joined his brother in the church.
There, inspired by divine mercy and the merit of the holy confessor, they reconciled their serious disputes and hostilities, entering into brotherly harmony and a pact of friendship.
After eating and drinking, they happily rejoined their father at the intended location, with all their people safe.
However, the emperor, who had remained alone in the boat with his men after his sons disembarked, aimed to continue to the mentioned place.
Suddenly, a dense cloud arose, followed by dark fogs, causing them to wander in the river.
Neither the emperor, his companions, nor the ship's pilot could determine their direction or where they were steering the boat.
Thus, throughout the rest of the day, exhausted at sea, just after the emperor recognized his fault and began to pray to Blessed Goar, they landed on the shore late in the day with night approaching.
However, they disembarked about three miles, or perhaps a little more, from the place where they intended to land, and the emperor had to stay that night without necessary supplies.
The next day, he publicly testified that it was his own sin and fault that caused him to be in danger on the river, far from the convenience of travel and royal accommodations.
He stated that these events did not happen to him without reason, but that Blessed Goar rightfully demanded punishment for the emperor's disrespect, and he had deservedly suffered.
He vowed and firmly promised never to bypass the place of the holy man, no matter how urgent his journey might be, if he came near it again, having experienced such inconvenience as proof that the saint could impose any retribution he wished on those who thought they could neglect him.
With these vows, he sent twenty pounds of silver and two silk vestments to the abbey.
From then on, for the rest of his life, he never neglected his vow for any reason.
Finally, the person who was then the pilot of the royal ship and is still alive today bears undeniable witness to the event.
And it is not without reason that kings' faith and devotion lie with him, who for Christ not only scorned great and desirable, but all worldly honors and fleeting dignities; and though he could have been made a bishop, he chose to remain in a humble position rather than be burdened by the weight of honors.
Among Christian princes, this devotion to the servants of God is so spontaneous and devout, as they know they will be more pleasing to God the more they humble themselves before the servants of Christ, who could have been elevated by the swell of royal majesty, but chose instead to humble themselves.
About Queen Fastrada being healed there.
The same prince's wife, Fastrada, was suffering from a very severe toothache.
She came to the place to pray for relief from her pain.
As soon as she prayed humbly, she was freed from her discomfort.
Because of this, the emperor gave a villa called Nasonia, and it remains under the jurisdiction of that place to this day.
On the story of a man who risked his life walking on ice and was miraculously saved.
Around the same time, the Rhine River froze due to extreme cold, making it strong enough to support the weight of animals and vehicles.
There was a tenant of the royal estate, known as Wasalia, whose vineyard was near the monastery's vineyards of Saint Goar.
Occasionally, he would steal parts of those vineyards and cunningly add them to his own.
One day, while walking on the river's ice and nearly reaching the middle, the ice suddenly broke into many pieces across the wide expanse of the river.
He found himself standing on broken ice, being carried along the river, trembling and anxious.
It was an extremely dangerous and desperate situation, being carried on a fragment of thin ice on the widest and fastest river, with no way for human help to reach him.
With no hope or plan of escape, he began to pray for divine mercy and invoked the merits of Saint Goar for his liberation, loudly pleading for forgiveness and help.
When he had entirely lost hope, he took off his sleeve, threw it from his hand, looked towards the basilica, and offered his vineyard to the dominion of the holy man.
Immediately, by divine power, the ice carried the man to the shore like a small boat and set him safely on land.
He then transferred ownership of the vineyard to the church, where it remains to this day.
Thus, the merit of the blessed confessor both appropriately punished the man for his fault and miraculously rescued him from danger.
On the story about Isanhard, the steward of a royal estate, who was struck down and later healed.
Isanhard, who was the steward of the royal estate, was acting unjustly towards the household of Saint Goar.
One night, he was visited by Saint Goar in a dream and, after a severe reprimand, was struck down so badly that the next day he couldn't walk and had to be taken to the church by boat.
After lying down for a while at the church, he regained his health, except for a heaviness in his genitals, which is believed to have been left as a sign for his salvation.
These events took place during the time of Abbot Asuerus, due to the divine power present and the merit of the blessed confessor.
However, during the tenure of Tancred, who succeeded Asuerus in managing the monastery of Prum and the cell of Saint Goar after Asuerus passed away, the events I am about to share, granted by divine mercy, occurred.
Those who reported these events to me, and whom I consulted for information, witnessed them firsthand.
Miracles Performed During the Time of Abbot Tancred
About the excessive flooding of the stream and the miraculous preservation of the tower.
Once, after a sudden abundance of rain, the stream we mentioned in the previous book, called Woccar, rose dramatically.
Swelling into a massive torrent, it uprooted everything in its path, causing danger and damage to many.
When it first began to overflow, it was unclear what was blocking its course.
But as waters descended from the mountains, it grew so much that, finally breaking through its barriers, it swept away even large and very strong houses from their foundations into the Rhine.
At that time, something miraculous occurred:
In one of the houses that was uprooted, there stood a small tower with signs hanging from it, which remains on the roof of the church to this day.
Although the tower was much weaker in construction than the house it stood in, and despite facing the full force of the waters, it remained completely unharmed.
Even more miraculously, the house, with its walls intact and joined together, was uprooted, yet it couldn't drag the tower with it.
No one has ever discovered how the tower remained or by what separation it passed through the house.
Finally, after the torrent of water had passed, two flasks of oil were found at the base of the tower, and no one has ever known who placed them there or where they came from.
On the story of a Scottish woman who was healed there.
A Scottish woman named Brigida, who had difficulty walking, was left there by her parents and fellow citizens who were returning from the city.
After spending some time there, on the day of the annual celebration, in front of a large crowd, she was healed and stood up.
On the slave girl of a certain Hadebald who was healed twice.
The slave girl of a well-known man named Hadebald, who was both blind and mute, was healed in front of the people at the revered memorial.
When this became known, her master, who had sent the sick girl, brought her back to his service now healthy.
Soon after, her previous infirmity returned.
Compelled by the evident miracle, her master sent her back to the place where she had been healed.
Not long after, the health that had been granted to her was restored once the master had repented for his recklessness.
She spent the rest of her life in that same place.
Finally, her sister still lives there and is a very reliable witness to the event.
Speaking of another blind woman.
Around the same time, another blind woman regained her sight in the presence of Abbot Tancred, and she continued to live there for many more years.
On the story about a servant's young child who was born blind and mute.
One day, while the abbot was with the congregation, a servant woman brought her young son, who had been blind and mute since birth, to the church.
As soon as the boy entered with his mother, he began to speak and point at the church's paintings with his finger.
The mother was amazed by this miracle, but due to the suddenness of it, she didn't dare to publicly confess what she had witnessed.
When she returned home with the boy, his previous disabilities immediately returned, making it clear she should not have kept silent about the divine favor.
Realizing her mistake, she quickly took her son back to the church and told the abbot and the congregation everything.
The blessing, which had been delayed by the mother's timidity, was quickly restored; as soon as she finished explaining, the boy immediately regained his health.
On the story of a lame woman from the city of Mainz.
She came to the festival of Blessed Goar.
Placed before Abbot Tancred, she was healed while the clergy completed the evening psalms.
But now, let me recount those events to show clearly how those who dared to disrespect the merit and reverence of the blessed man were either corrected or punished.
Once, when some potters were transporting pots for sale on a small boat along the Rhine River, a certain faithful woman and her young son happened to be traveling upstream as well.
When they reached the monastery, the woman asked her companions to either go to the church to pray or, if they didn't want to, to dock the boat and wait for her on the shore until she returned from her prayers.
She went alone to pray, leaving her very young son on the boat with her companions.
They moved the boat to an upper place and waited for her for a while.
Growing impatient with her delay, they continued their journey.
However, divine retribution soon followed, making it clear that they should not have neglected the opportunity to pray or disrespected the short wait, especially since she had only briefly delayed them.
When they came to a place on the river where hidden underwater rocks and the collision of waves create very dangerous conditions for navigators, about 100 steps or a little further from the church of Saint Goar, the boat was seized and sunk, and they perished.
But the devoted woman's prayer could not be in vain; although her companions were submerged by the water, her son, saved by divine power and protected by the saint's merit, was not lost.
As she came back from her prayer and saw the pots floating on the water, she realized what had happened-that her companions and the boat had perished.
Worried about her son, whom she feared had also been lost, she looked around with great tears.
Suddenly, she saw her little boy being lifted by the waves and brought near the riverbank.
The miracle was so astounding that when the mother took the baby, she found him floating on the water up to his waist.
He had reached the shore-something no person could ever achieve with swimming skills and physical strength.
On the child who was safely carried across the Rhine on a horse.
Around the same time, another miracle occurred, which I've included here due to the similarity of the events.
The mother of a nearly five-year-old child was traveling on a boat with the child's godfather.
The parents had placed the boy on a horse, as he had requested from his mother and godfather, while they walked along the shore.
Suddenly, the horse, without a rider, passed the boaters and went into the river with the boy on its back.
No one could call it back.
Everyone feared for the child's safety as they watched him being carried into the fast, deep, and wide river on the uncontrollable horse, so they prayed earnestly for Goar's assistance.
The horse swam across the river with the boy unharmed and emerged on the opposite shore.
This event was undoubtedly miraculous, as the horse managed to cross such a large, difficult, and dangerous river without a rider, and the child, who couldn't even sit on the horse on dry land, escaped without any harm.
On Willigelmus, who was given over to a certain demon and later rescued.
To continue with the story, a man named Willigelmus, who is still alive, took a vineyard that his mother had given from the rightful possession of the Church of Saint Goar.
He was then possessed by a fierce demon.
Tormented by it, he eventually returned the vineyard and was immediately cured.
This example serves as a warning to others that it is not right for heirs, the children, to take away property dedicated to the church by their parents' vow.
On a certain priest named Wolvo.
Wolvo, who was raised by his mother from a young age, became a priest later in life.
For a long time, he deceitfully took the tithes that rightfully belonged to the church of Blessed Goar for his own use.
Not long after, he became blind and mute.
His people brought him to the basilica of the most holy man.
There, he handed over his property along with the restored tithes.
After appeasing the one he had offended, he regained his health.
On the merchant named Badoard who died because of a killed slave.
A merchant named Badoard was about to board a ship on the Rhine.
One of his slaves, who had accidentally offended him and feared punishment, jumped off the ship and quickly ran to a church for sanctuary.
Badoard chased after the runaway and began to drag him out of the church.
A monk named Herirad, who was present by chance, tried to stop him and pleaded with Badoard in the name of Goar, both requesting and threatening him.
I learned this from Herirad himself.
However, the merchant, driven by rage, ignored the monk's pleas and threats.
He dragged the slave from the altar and struck him right outside the church as an additional sign of contempt.
Not long after, the merchant realized whom he had obeyed and whom he had scorned.
Possessed by an evil spirit, he soon died after suffering extreme agony.
On the miraculous release of a certain Humphrey's servant from chains.
A servant of Humphrey, a cleric of the church, was being dragged with his arms tied behind his back for an offense against his master.
Terrified by the punishment he faced, he looked towards the church and silently prayed, as he had no other way to escape.
What a remarkable event!
Immediately, the chains binding him loosened and fell off faster than you could say.
Freed from the chains, the servant rushed to the church.
His master did not pursue him, allowing him to avoid the punishment for his offense.
Such was the power of the silent prayer offered by the holy man to almighty God.
Christ did not allow him to remain bound, as he sought refuge at the holy altar out of necessity and faith.
This event also demonstrated the strength of the holy man's intercession in freeing souls from their bonds, as his prayer so effortlessly released the physical chains.
On Abbot Maximinus, who was in danger due to negligence but was saved.
At a certain time, when Abbot Tancred was in his cell, Maximinus, the abbot of the monastery of Saint Gereon, near the city of Agrippina, now called Cologne, was returning from the province of Vangiones with a boat full of wine and many companions after the grape harvest.
As they approached the monastery of Saint Goar, his companions suggested docking the boat to pray to Saint Goar.
Maximinus dismissed this, saying that such delays were unnecessary and there would be a better time for praying later.
Discouraging his companions, he continued the journey, but divine retribution did not allow him to proceed unscathed.
As soon as the boat came into view of the cell, it suddenly began to sink from one side, causing the vessels it carried to fall into the water, instilling fear of immediate loss and danger in everyone.
They all cried out and tearfully begged for help.
The abbot confessed his fault, and they invoked the merit of Goar.
Abbot Tancred, observing the situation from a higher place and realizing the great peril they were in, immediately sent his men to help those in distress.
Boats were quickly brought down, and assistance was provided in every possible way.
Thus, with the help of the abbots and the efforts of many, but especially through the support of Blessed Goar, the boat was recovered, the vessels and goods were retrieved, and the abbot reached the shore unharmed.
He hurried off the boat to pray, firmly convinced that one should never easily pass by a place so distinguished by the merits of such a great man without offering a prayer.
On a certain Frisian who was similarly endangered.
A merchant from the Frisian people was sailing his ship near the farther shore and did not intend to approach the shore where the monastery is located.
However, the ship came near those rocks we mentioned earlier.
Suddenly, it was seized and dragged by the force of the waves into a whirlpool, putting everyone in immediate danger.
But when the master of the ship repeatedly called upon the name and merit of Saint Goar for help, the ship was immediately carried safely into the harbor.
As soon as he reached the land, he went to pray and, in gratitude for their safety, gave a silk garment in memory of the venerable saint.
This garment was later brought to Prum Monastery by Theodradus, the cleric who told me this story.
On the merchant's servant miraculously rescued from the danger of water.
I am going to tell a story somewhat similar to the previous ones, but one that contains an even greater miracle, and has almost as many trustworthy witnesses as there are inhabitants of the place where it happened.
A merchant from the aforementioned Frisians was sailing a ship through the Rhine River.
As is customary when navigating against the current, he had his men pull the ship along the shore with a rope.
As he approached the vicinity of the cell, his men and others on the riverbank advised him to disembark from the ship to pray.
He said he could not do so at the moment, as the delay would hinder their planned course, and he could only reach a suitable resting place by continuing the voyage.
With this resolve, he steered the ship himself, staying at the helm with one of his servants, while the others pulled the ship along the shore.
One of them, leading the group, held the end of the rope wrapped around his back and waist.
They reached the treacherous rapid we mentioned earlier when suddenly the ship was seized by violent waves.
With the helmsman unable to help, the ship was pulled far from the shore.
Those pulling the rope along the shore could no longer withstand the force and let go; but the one who had been leading, unable to free himself from the rope quickly enough, was dragged into the whirlpool with the ship.
The master of the ship, struggling at the stern, did not notice this; the others who had let go of the rope called out loudly to the ship and to the companion being dragged underwater, asking for divine help and the merits of Saint Goar.
The force and whirlpool of the water were so great that the ship could not be steered back on course until it was swept far to the opposite shore, causing great fear and horror among many.
When the merchant reached land, he ordered his servant to collect the rope, which had been pulled through the water attached to the ship.
When the servant collected it, he found the other servant entangled at the very end of it, just as he had been wrapped in it.
After being carefully examined and tested in various ways, he was found to be nothing but dead.
Finally, with a lot of straw and fire applied all around, he felt no heat and showed no sign of life.
What happened next?
He was carried back to the nearer shore, where his lord and companions prepared for his burial.
The church's caretaker was asked to provide a burial place.
Once the grave was obtained, his seemingly lifeless body was placed in the caretaker's house for an hour while they opened the grave.
Then, after a short time, he began to warm up, gradually opened his mouth, and started to breathe.
He then completely raised himself up, spat out a little blood from his mouth, and immediately stood up healthy.
After everyone prayed and gave thanks, he hurried to take the ship with his companions as before.
When the merchant saw this, he felt greatly improved and thankful for the correction of his fault.
He paid a pound of silver to the sacred altar and, continuing his journey, left with all his companions safe.
Let others think what they will about this matter.
I confidently say that the merits of the blessed man are all the clearer after his death, as he diligently avoided human praise and boasting while he lived.
He does not seem inferior to any of the saints in showing such signs and miracles, except only the apostles and the most renowned martyrs of the Church.
In loving God and his neighbor, he is not easily judged inferior to any of them.
Although he did not shine with many miracles known to men in his life, he stood out for his charity, which is greater than all miracles.
Therefore, after his death, he shines daily in the faith of the living with so many great virtues.
On the divine light kindled in the church lamps.
Furthermore, Heriradus the monk, who, as often mentioned, was the most reliable and truthful narrator of these miracles for me, asserts twice that, without any external warning, the lamp which hangs before the venerable memory shone with divine light.
He confirms that this happened both in the current year when we wrote this and the previous year, as witnessed by those present.
But that will be discussed in its own place.
So far, I have described the events reported to have occurred while Abbot Tancrad was still alive.
Now, with Christ's help, I will proceed, as I proposed, to the times of the most illustrious Father Marcuvardus, who assigned me this very task.
Miracles performed during the time of Abbot Marcuvardus.
About Emperor Louis being relieved from foot pain there.
To give you a clearer sequence of events, even if it means starting a bit out of order:
The most pious and merciful Emperor Louis, who is deeply devoted to the Christian faith and still holds the highest position thanks to divine mercy, was suffering from intense foot pain, a condition that often afflicted him, though not continuously.
While struggling with this pain, he left his palace, called Ingelheim, located on the banks of the Rhine River, and traveled by boat to pray at Saint Goar.
He could hardly walk due to the severe pain and relied more on the support of others than on his own steps.
When he arrived at the church, he humbly and devoutly prostrated himself before the revered memorial and prayed for a long time while lying on the ground.
When he rose, he turned to the abbot and distinguished man Gerung, formerly the steward of the palace and now a monk, and said,
"Thank God, now I feel relief given to me by the merits of Saint Goar, and I am no longer suffering from the pain with which I came here."
He returned from the memorial happy and cheerful and spent the whole day in this state.
I learned these details from the abbot himself, who was present, although I was not far off myself, as I had seen the emperor suffering greatly from the said pain in the palace the day before.
A Scottish woman was healed from lameness there.
To give some background, citizens returning from the city left behind this Scottish woman who was sick and unable to walk properly.
After spending six months in that place, on the day of the annual festival held on July 6, she regained her ability to walk during the evening Psalms.
On the demonic child at the memory of Saint Goar, promised by the father with a gift of bees.
Thirty-eight.
The previous year, after the events we recounted about the emperor, a certain peasant brought his young son, who was possessed by a demon, to the church with tears and supplication.
When he laid him down in front of the memorial, crying out in front of many people, he said,
"Saint Goar, now give me back my son and drive out the demon that torments him; I will immediately bring you a gift of a swarm of bees
(for this is what the peasants call a swarm of bees).
"
This simple request of the peasant was not in vain: the father, happy and rejoicing, took his completely healed child back home.
Indeed, he brought the promised swarm of bees, which still remains in the gardens of the Church to this day.
I learned this from Theodradus, who often told the story, and from Ekkibald, the scholarly and truthful head of that place.
On the light twice kindled in the lamp by divine intervention.
To elaborate on what I briefly mentioned earlier, last year on Easter, when Provost Ekkibaldus wanted to perform Mass at dawn, and again this year during Lent, the same man was performing Masses, and the light in the church was missing.
The custodian, after putting down the lamp and finding it without fire, hurried to bring it.
Suddenly, in the sight of many, the light spontaneously shone in the lamp, which many faithful men who were present frequently testify to have happened.
On a lame and deaf boy and a blind girl healed there. 40.
To conclude this account of recent miracles, while I was writing this and before the book was published, a large crowd of people gathered for the annual celebration of the blessed deposition, as usual.
A well-known woman from a nearby area arrived with her nearly seven-year-old son, who had been lame, mute, and deaf from birth, causing his unfortunate mother daily grief and sorrow.
With devoted faith, the mother brought him before the venerable tomb during the nighttime vigils.
Near the end of the morning Psalms, while the clergy of the church were singing the Gospel canticle, the little boy suddenly stood up, making a slow effort, and for the first time ever, stood on his feet, calling out loudly to his mother.
The mother, crying with joy, immediately rushed over and found her son, who she had left weighed down by so many troubles, now walking, speaking, and hearing.
It was not difficult for Christ, in honor of His worthy confessor, to grant the boy the ability to speak and the knowledge that others gain only through hearing, for He is the wisdom of God who opens the mouths of the mute and makes the tongues of children articulate.
The minds of all present were filled with awe at this great miracle.
The whole church praised Christ, and the miraculous healing of one little boy ignited the faith of many hearts.
41.
On the same day, while the people were witnessing the solemn mass and the priest was performing the divine mysteries, a girl of about the same age as the aforementioned boy, who had been brought faithfully by her parents, received her lost sight.
Thus, with two miracles on a single day, the merit of the holy man became evident to all, and the faith of those present recognized that Christ's mercy is always present for those who call upon Him.
I've summarized, as clearly and briefly as possible, the miracles performed by Blessed Goar, bringing the narration up to the year 839 of the Lord's Incarnation.
I've only included the accounts I learned from trustworthy sources, as I mentioned at the beginning of this small book.
These stories are well-known not just to those who reported them, but to almost everyone who visits the place.
I didn't record everything I heard from reliable witnesses, as including everything would have either exceeded the scope of this work or been too lengthy for the listeners.
My intent wasn't to prevent others from writing about these events.
Those who wish can explain them more thoroughly or describe similar miracles that may happen in the future, following the example set by you, esteemed Father Marcuvard, and myself.
If divine works are to be glorified, it's fitting that the effort to document them continues as long as we benefit from divine virtue.
As long as there are people capable of doing so, let extraordinary events be recorded in writing.
That's why I decided to include blank parchments in this little book, so that future wise individuals can conveniently add anything they think should be included once this work is published.
The commemoration begins joyfully here, discussing how and by whom Saint Goar's cell was incorporated into the monastery of Prum.
Having now completed my account of the holy man's miracles, I find it necessary to briefly explain, as an addition to the two previously published booklets, how and why Blessed Goar's cell became part of the monastery of Prum.
This way, it should always remain under the governance and authority of the abbot, who, by God's grace, leads that monastery.
Prum Monastery Beginnings.
The illustrious King of the Franks, Pepin, father of Emperor Charlemagne, motivated by love for Christ and at the request of his wife, the saintly Bertrada, built this monastery.
He established monks there to serve God under a regular order and appointed the venerable Asuerus as the head.
Asuerus successfully governed the monastery for forty-five years.
Due to his meritorious life, Asuerus was granted the authority to take what was necessary for his travels under royal jurisdiction.
Once, while traveling to the province of the Vangiones, he stopped at Saint Goar, overseen by a man named Erpingus, but couldn't obtain necessary supplies.
He later reported this to the prince, lamenting the lack of hospitality where it once thrived.
The king promised to address this issue when possible.
Not long after, at the palace of Attigny, the prince reminded Abbot Asuerus of the situation with Saint Goar and entrusted its governance to him, urging him to restore proper hospitality.
The dispute over the cell of Saint Goar was settled by Charlemagne.
This was the first connection of the cell with the monastery of Prum, established by the command and will of King Pepin.
Initially, it was not directly subject to the monastery or the monks, but was entrusted to the abbot to manage as a benefice.
However, after King Pepin's death, when Charlemagne reigned, a dispute arose between the bishop of Trier, Weomad, and Abbot Asuerus over the cell.
The bishop claimed it fell under his church's jurisdiction, while the abbot argued it was a hereditary possession according to the king's law.
The church could claim nothing, as it had been entrusted to the abbot by King Pepin and passed into Charlemagne's dominion by right of succession.
As the argument persisted and often led to controversy, the king sent very faithful and truthful envoys multiple times to diligently investigate and resolve the dispute.
Upon examination, they found that the abbot's claims were correct: the possession of the cell was royal rather than ecclesiastical jurisdiction.
But this was not enough for the bishop.
The renowned prince, holding a general assembly in Saxony at the spring called Lippe, in the presence of almost all the leading men of the kingdom and distinguished men of both orders, took it upon himself to examine the matter.
By the judgment of everyone present, an oath condition was established for the advocate of the monastery, Rabert, which he later confirmed with twelve others, that the possession of the cell belonged not to the Church of Trier, but to the royal dominion.
So, after defining the matter and with the bishop finally agreeing, the famous king, with the consent of his people, handed over the cell of the holy man to the monastery of Prum.
He issued a charter confirming this handover, stating that he was giving this cell to the monastery out of love for Christ and in honor of his parents, King Pippin and Queen Bertrada.
This was under the condition that the abbots of the monastery would hold it forever, using its resources freely for the needs of their brothers who serve God, and arranging what was necessary for the common benefit without any opposition.
This agreement covered not only the possessions the cell held at that time but also those it would acquire in the future.
Anyone who wishes to know more about how these matters were enacted and established can refer to the privilege that remains intact in the archives of the monastery to this day.
For now, it is enough to briefly recall the matter to provide useful understanding and avoid being accused of neglecting our duty concerning Saint Goar.
Finally, when we were writing this, Tancradus and then Marcuvardus had succeeded in the administration of the monastery of Prum and the possession of Saint Goar's cell by vicariate change.
Regarding Abbot Asuerus and the cell of the holy man, what we first mentioned happened as stated, as some senior figure, not unworthy of trust, testified that he had heard from the same abbot.