Theodulf, Bishop of Orleans, gives instructions to the priests of his parish.
One On the duty to care for the progress of the subordinate people, and on the dignity of priests.
I urge you, dearest brothers, to diligently work for the progress and improvement of the subordinate people.
By guiding them towards salvation and teaching them with both words and actions, you can help their growth and ours, with the aid of our Lord Jesus Christ.
I also encourage you to continuously read these chapters, which I have briefly compiled for the betterment of life.
Memorize them, shape your habits through these readings and the Holy Scriptures, improve your life, and strive to lead the subordinate people, with the Lord's help, to the heavenly kingdoms.
Remember that we, who are entrusted with the care of souls, will have to account for those who perish due to our negligence.
However, for those we have guided through words and examples, we will receive the reward of eternal life.
For the Lord said to us, "You are the salt of the earth" (Matthew 5:13).
If the faithful people are the food of God, we are the seasoning of that food.
Understand that your rank is closely connected to ours.
Just as bishops hold the place of the Apostles in the Church, priests hold the place of the other disciples of the Lord.
They hold the rank of the high priest Aaron, while you hold the rank of his sons.
Therefore, always remember your great dignity, your consecration, and the sacred anointing you received in your hands.
Do not fall from that dignity, nullify your consecration, or pollute your hands anointed with holy oil by sinning.
By maintaining purity of heart and body, and setting a good example for the people, you can guide those you lead to the heavenly kingdoms.
Two
That reading and praying should be done constantly.
You should dedicate yourselves continuously to both reading and praying, because the life of a righteous person is guided, adorned, and protected from sin by reading regularly.
According to the one who said:
"I have hidden your word in my heart, that I might not sin against you" (Psalm 119:11).
For these are the weapons, namely reading and praying, by which the devil is defeated.
These are the tools by which eternal happiness is obtained.
With these weapons, vices are suppressed.
With this nourishment, virtues are nurtured.
Three Action should follow reading.
Even if there's a break from reading, manual labor should come next because idleness is the enemy of the soul.
The ancient foe easily leads anyone into sin if they're idle from reading or prayer.
By reading, you'll learn how to live and teach others.
By praying, you'll benefit both yourself and those you love.
Through manual labor and mortification of the body, you'll deny nourishment to vices, support your own needs, and have something to offer those in need.
Four What preparations should be made before coming to the synod.
When you gather for the synod, as usual, bring the vestments, books, and holy vessels that you use for your ministry and duties.
Also, bring two or three clerics with whom you celebrate the solemnities of the masses, to show how diligently and earnestly you conduct the service to God.
Five The care that should be taken with the bread, wine, and water in celebrating Masses.
The loaves you offer to God as a sacrifice, whether made by you or by your children in your presence, should be prepared cleanly and carefully.
Ensure that the bread, wine, and water, essential for celebrating Masses, are handled with the utmost cleanliness and care.
Nothing in them should be impure; everything should be of proven quality, in line with what Scripture says:
"Let the fear of the Lord be upon you, and do everything with diligence"
2 Chronicles 19:9.
Six Women should not approach the altar while Mass is being celebrated.
Women should not come near the altar during Mass when the priest is celebrating.
They should remain in their places, and the priest will take their offerings to present to God.
Women should be mindful of their perceived weakness and the frailty of their sex, and thus should refrain from touching anything sacred in the service of the Church.
Men who are not clergy should also be cautious, recalling the story of Uzzah, who was struck down by the Lord when he tried to touch the Ark of the Lord without permission.
Second Samuel chapter 6.
Seven That the priest should not celebrate Mass alone.
The priest should never celebrate Mass alone because the Mass requires the priest's greeting and the people's response.
It involves the priest's admonition and, again, the people's response.
Therefore, it should never be celebrated by one person alone.
There must be those present who stand around him, whom he greets, and from whom he receives a response.
This brings to mind the Lord's saying:
"Where two or three are gathered in my name, I am there among them" (Matthew 18:20).
Eight That in churches, besides sacred things, nothing else should be stored.
We often see churches being filled with harvests and hay.
Therefore, we strictly want this to be observed: that nothing should be stored in the church besides church vestments, holy vessels, and books.
If other activities are conducted there that shouldn't be, we might hear from the Lord:
"My house shall be called a house of prayer; but you have made it a den of thieves"
(Matthew 21:13).
Nine From now on, only a select few who are deserving should be buried in the church.
It was an ancient practice in these regions to bury the dead in churches.
Often, places meant for worship and sacrifices to God became cemeteries or mass graves.
Therefore, we're decreeing that this practice must stop.
No one should be buried in the church unless they are a priest or a righteous person who has earned such an honor through their life's merit.
The bodies already buried in churches should not be exhumed.
Instead, visible tombs should be buried deeper, with new pavement laid over them so no trace of the tombs remains, thus preserving the church's reverence.
If there are too many bodies to do this, then that place should be considered a cemetery.
The altar should be removed, and a new one constructed in a place where sacrifices can be offered to God in a pure and reverent manner.
Ten To prohibit idle talk and profane actions in the church.
You should come to church solely to praise the Lord and to perform His service.
Arguments, disturbances, idle talk, and similar actions should be completely banned from this holy place.
Where the name of God is invoked, a sacrifice to God is offered, and the presence of angels is undoubted, it is dangerous to say or do anything inappropriate for that place.
If the Lord drove out of the temple those who were buying and selling sacrifices to be offered to Him, how much more will He angrily cast out those who defile the place dedicated to divine worship with lies, idle talk, laughter, and other such nonsense?
(Matthew chapter 21, verse 12)
Eleven Masses should only be celebrated in a church.
The solemnities of the masses must be held exclusively in a church, not in any houses or common places, but in the place the Lord has chosen.
As it is written:
"Be careful not to offer your burnt offerings in just any place you see, but in the place which the Lord chooses to put his name."
Deuteronomy 12:13.
Twelve Women should not live with a priest.
No woman should live in the same house as a priest.
Although the canons allow his mother, sister, and similar individuals without suspicion to live with him,
we completely prohibit this because other women, who are not related to him, may come to serve or visit and tempt him to sin.
Thirteen Priests Should Avoid Drunkenness and Taverns, and Not Socialize Recklessly
You must ensure that you avoid drunkenness.
Additionally, you should preach that the people under your care abstain from it.
Do not visit taverns for drinking or eating, and do not wander through houses or neighborhoods out of curiosity.
Do not hold gatherings with women or with any impure persons.
However, if a head of a household invites you to his home with his wife and children to share in spiritual joy, and to receive spiritual nourishment from your words, and to offer you physical nourishment as an act of charity, it is proper that if any of the faithful provides you with a meal, they should be spiritually nourished by you in return.
Fourteen Priests should not try to draw the faithful from other churches to their own.
No priest should persuade members of God's Holy Church from another priest's parish to leave their church and give their tithes to him.
Each should be content with his own church and congregation, and follow the principle:
"Whatever you want people to do to you, do the same to them" (Matthew 7:12)
Anyone who goes against these rules or resists these warnings should know that they risk losing their position or being detained in prison for a long time.
Fifteen. Do not entice other clergy members.
We strictly forbid anyone from enticing or accepting another's clergy member.
The sacred canons impose severe punishment for this offense.
Sixteen. Regarding those who try to bribe their way into other people's churches.
If a priest is found to have given or is giving gifts to any clergy member or layperson in order to take over another priest's church, he should know that for this theft and cruel greed, he will either lose his position or be detained in prison for a long time doing penance.
Seventeen Do not refuse baptism to sick children from other parishes.
If a sick child is brought to any priest for baptism, regardless of their parish, the sacrament should not be refused.
If anyone denies this request and the child dies without being baptized, the person who refused will be held accountable for the child's soul.
Eighteen Sacred vessels should not be used for other purposes.
No priest or layperson should use a chalice, paten, or any sacred vessel dedicated to divine worship for anything else.
Anyone who drinks from a consecrated chalice anything other than the blood of Christ, received in the sacrament, or uses the paten for anything other than the ministry of the altar, should heed the example of Belshazzar.
When he took the Lord's vessels for common use, he lost his life and his kingdom.
Daniel 5.
Nineteen Which schools can they send their relatives to, if they want?
If any of the priests wishes to send his nephew or any relative to a school, whether it be in the church of the Holy Cross, the monastery of Saint Anianus, Saint Benedict, Saint Lifardus, or any of the other monasteries granted to us to manage, we grant him permission to do so.
Twenty They themselves have schools where they educate the children of the faithful for free.
Priests should establish schools in towns and villages.
If any of the faithful wish to entrust their children to them to learn letters, they should not refuse to receive and teach them.
They should teach them with the utmost charity, keeping in mind what is written:
"And those who are wise shall shine like the brightness of the sky; and those who lead many to righteousness, like the stars forever and ever" Daniel 12:3.
Therefore, when they teach them, they should not demand any payment for this, nor accept anything from them except what the parents, out of a spirit of charity, willingly offer.
Twenty-One A Brief Guide to the Christian Life
Since the pages of Holy Scripture are filled with tools for good works, and within them, we can find weapons to suppress vices and nurture virtues, we decided to include a saying from a certain Father about these tools.
It briefly outlines what should be done and what should be avoided.
First, love the Lord your God with all your heart, all your soul, and all your strength; then, love your neighbor as yourself.
Next, do not kill, do not commit adultery, do not steal, do not covet, do not give false testimony.
Honor all people, and do not do to others what you do not want done to yourself.
Deny yourself to follow Christ.
Discipline your body, avoid indulgence, love fasting, help the poor, clothe the naked, visit the sick, bury the dead, assist those in trouble, and console the grieving.
Distance yourself from worldly affairs.
Prioritize nothing over the love of Christ.
Do not give in to anger, do not hold on to anger, do not harbor deceit in your heart, offer genuine peace, and do not abandon charity.
Avoid swearing oaths to prevent perjury.
Speak the truth from your heart and mouth, do not repay evil with evil, do no harm, but patiently endure any harm done to you.
Love your enemies, do not curse those who curse you, but bless them instead.
Endure persecution for the sake of justice.
Do not be proud, do not be a drunkard, do not be gluttonous, do not be lazy, do not be sleepy, do not be slothful, do not complain, and do not slander.
Place your hope in God.
When you see something good in yourself, attribute it to God, not to yourself; but always acknowledge that any evil comes from you and take responsibility for it.
Fear the day of judgment, dread hell, desire eternal life with all spiritual longing, and keep the prospect of death daily before your eyes.
Guard your life's actions at all times.
In every place, know for certain that God sees you.
Quickly bring any bad thoughts that come to your heart to Christ, and share them with your spiritual elder.
Guard your mouth from evil or wrong speech.
Avoid talking too much.
Refrain from speaking empty or frivolous words.
Do not indulge in excessive or disruptive laughter.
Willingly listen to holy readings.
Frequently devote yourself to prayer.
Each day, confess your past wrongdoings to God with tears or sighs in prayer.
Strive to amend those wrongs from now on.
Do not fulfill the desires of the flesh.
Hate your own will.
Obey the commandments of the priest and teacher in everything, even if they, which may God forbid, act otherwise, remembering the Lord's command: Do what they say, but do not do what they do Matthew 23:3.
Do not seek to be called holy before you truly are, but first strive to be what is truly said.
Fulfill God's commandments daily through actions.
Love chastity.
Hate no one.
Harbor no jealousy or envy.
Avoid contention.
Shun pride.
Respect your elders.
Love the younger ones.
In the love of Christ, pray for your enemies.
Make peace with those you are in conflict with before sunset, and never despair of God's mercy.
Behold, these are the tools of the spiritual craft.
When we have unceasingly fulfilled them day and night, and present them on the day of judgment, the Lord will grant us the reward He promised: What no eye has seen, nor ear heard, nor the heart of man imagined, what God has prepared for those who love Him Isaiah 64:4; First Corinthians 2:9.
Twenty-Two
All the faithful should learn the Lord's Prayer and the Creed.
Everyone, from the youngest to the oldest, must learn the Lord's Prayer and the Creed.
They need to understand that these two statements form the entire foundation of the Christian faith.
If someone doesn't memorize, believe, and frequently recite these, they cannot be considered Catholic.
It is decreed that no one shall be anointed with chrism, baptized, received from the baptismal font, or presented for confirmation before the bishop unless they have memorized the Creed and the Lord's Prayer, except for those too young to speak.
Twenty-Three Everyone should pray to God at least twice daily, in the morning and in the evening.
Tell them that if they can't do more, they should at least pray twice—once in the morning and once in the evening.
They can say the Creed, the Lord's Prayer, or simply: "You who formed me, have mercy on me," or "God, be merciful to me, a sinner."
Give thanks to God for the daily provisions and for creating us in His own image, setting us apart from the animals.
After doing this and worshipping God alone, they should ask the saints to intercede for them before the divine majesty.
If there's a church nearby, they should go there; but if they are traveling or find themselves in the woods or fields, they should pray wherever they are when morning or evening comes, knowing that God is present everywhere, as the Psalmist says:
"In every place of His dominion" (Psalm 103:22); and, "If I ascend into heaven, You are there" (Psalm 139:8), etc.
Twenty-Four On Observing the Lord's Day.
The Lord's Day is significant because it is the day God created light, manna rained in the desert, the Redeemer of mankind rose from the dead for our salvation, and the Holy Spirit was poured out upon the disciples.
It must be observed with such reverence that, aside from prayers, the solemnities of the Mass, and those activities related to eating, nothing else should be done.
If there is a necessity for sailing or traveling, it is allowed, provided that Mass and prayers are not omitted due to these activities.
On Saturday, every Christian should gather with lights at the church and attend vigils or the morning office.
They should also bring offerings for the solemnities of the Mass.
When gathering at the church, no cause should be spoken or heard, and no quarrels should take place.
Only God should be attended to, through the celebration of sacred offices, the giving of alms, and praising God with friends, neighbors, and spiritual guests.
Twenty-Five Everyone should love and offer hospitality freely.
They should be reminded to love hospitality and not refuse lodging to anyone.
If they do provide lodging, they should not accept any payment unless the guest willingly offers something.
They should be reminded how many have pleased God through hospitality, as the Apostle says, "For by doing so, some have entertained angels without knowing it" (Hebrews 13:2).
And again, "Be hospitable to one another without grumbling" (First Peter 4:9).
And the Lord Himself will say at the judgment, "I was a stranger, and you invited Me in" (Matthew 25:35).
Indeed, let those who love hospitality know that they are receiving Christ in their guests.
Demanding payment before accepting a guest is not only inhumane but also cruel.
It turns what the Lord commanded to be done for the sake of receiving the kingdom of heaven into a means for acquiring earthly possessions.
Twenty-Six The faithful should avoid the crime of perjury.
It must be preached that the faithful should avoid perjury entirely, recognizing it as a great crime.
It is forbidden in the law, the prophets, and the Gospel.
Matthew 5:33 says:
Some people take this crime lightly and impose only minor penance for perjury.
They should know that the penance for perjury should be the same as for adultery, fornication, murder, and other serious crimes.
If anyone, after committing perjury or any other serious sin, refuses to come to confession because they fear the long hardship of penance, they should be expelled from the church and from the communion and fellowship of the faithful.
No one should eat or drink with them, pray with them, or receive them into their home.
Twenty-Seven They must be told to abstain from false testimony, understanding that this is a very serious crime, expressly forbidden by the Lord Himself on Mount Sinai.
The Lord said, "You shall not bear false witness" (Exodus 20:15) and "A false witness will not go unpunished" (Proverbs 19:5)
Anyone who has committed this sin must be purified through penance, as previously mentioned regarding perjury, or face condemnation and excommunication.
They should also be warned that it is not just foolishness, but wickedness, to commit such a grave crime for silver, gold, clothing, or any other reason, including drunkenness.
This can lead to enduring seven years of severe hardship or expulsion from the church.
The Lord said, "What good will it be for someone to gain the whole world, yet forfeit their soul?" (Matthew 16:26)
While they may appear pious to others, they are being cruel to themselves.
Twenty-Eight That priests be ready to teach the people.
We urge you to be prepared to teach the people.
If you know the Scriptures, preach the Scriptures.
If you don't, at least share this well-known saying:
Turn away from evil and do good (Psalm Thirty-Four, Fifteen); seek peace and pursue it, because the eyes of the Lord are on the righteous, and His ears are attentive to their prayers, etc.
No one can excuse themselves by claiming they lack the words to build someone up.
As soon as you see someone going astray, do your best to either argue, plead, or rebuke them, leading them away from error and encouraging them to do good works.
And when we gather in a council with the Lord's help, let everyone share how much they have labored with the Lord's assistance, or what fruits they have acquired.
If anyone needs our help, let them inform us kindly, and we will not hesitate to assist to the best of our ability with equal kindness.
Twenty-Nine How the faithful should pray.
Remind the faithful to be diligent and devoted in their prayers.
Here’s how they should pray:
First, after reciting the Creed, which is the foundation of their faith, each person should say three times: "You who formed me, have mercy on me," and three times: "God, be merciful to me, a sinner," and then complete the Lord's Prayer.
If the place or time requires, they should ask the holy apostles and martyrs to intercede for them.
With the sign of the cross on their forehead, they should lift their hearts, hands, and eyes to give thanks to God.
If there isn't enough time to do all these things, it's sufficient to say: "You who formed me, have mercy on me," and "God, be merciful to me, a sinner," and just the Lord's Prayer, with sighs and heartfelt repentance.
Thirty On the Daily Confession of Sins to God.
Every day, in our prayers to God, whether once, twice, or as many times as we can, we should confess our sins.
As the Prophet says, "I acknowledged my sin to you, and I did not conceal my iniquity. I said, 'I will confess my transgressions to the Lord,' and you forgave the guilt of my sin"
(Psalm 32:5).
After making our confession with groaning and tears to the Lord in prayer, we should recite Psalm 51, or Psalm 32, or Psalm 25, along with other relevant psalms, and thus complete our prayer.
The confession we make to priests also helps us because, by receiving their saving advice and through the most beneficial observances of penance or mutual prayers, we wash away the stains of our sins.
But the confession we make to God alone helps us because the more we remember our sins, the more the Lord forgets them; conversely, the more we forget our sins, the more the Lord remembers them.
As the Prophet says, "I will remember their sins no more"
(Jeremiah 31:34).
Remember what the Prophet David testified about himself when he said, "For I know my transgressions, and my sin is always before me"
(Psalm 51:3).
Thirty-One Those who come to confession must confess everything and be examined thoroughly.
Confessions should cover all sins, whether committed in action or in thought.
There are eight principal vices that almost everyone struggles with.
They are gluttony, or excessive eating; fornication; sloth or sadness; greed; vain glory; envy; anger; and pride.
Therefore, when someone comes to confession, they should be carefully questioned about the circumstances under which they committed the sin they are confessing.
Based on the nature of the act, appropriate penance should be assigned.
They should also be encouraged to confess their perverse thoughts and be guided to confess their struggles with the eight principal vices.
The priest should name each vice and listen to their confession about it.
Thirty-Two
Each person should spiritually perform the acts of mercy they carry out for others on themselves.
The hungry must be fed, the thirsty given drink, the naked clothed, the sick and those in prison visited, and strangers welcomed.
As the Lord said, "For I was hungry and you gave me food, I was thirsty and you gave me drink" (Matthew 25:35).
All these things should be done spiritually for oneself and physically for others, because these acts are of little use for attaining eternal life if one lives in luxury, pride, envy, and, to avoid listing them all, in vice and disorder, neglecting other good works.
Therefore, if someone sees they do not have Christ, who said, "I am the living bread that came down from heaven" (John 6:41), and does not have charity, which is the nourishment of the soul, they are indeed hungry.
But if through good works they join themselves to Christ and are filled with the sweetness of charity, they have certainly fed themselves as a hungry person.
Someone who lacks the teachings of the Holy Spirit and the streams of Holy Scripture is thirsty.
But if they water themselves with the flowing word of God and intoxicate their mind with the sweetness of the spiritual drink, they have given drink to their thirsty self.
Someone who sees themselves stripped of righteousness or other exhibitions of good works, and clothes themselves with righteousness or other virtues, has undoubtedly clothed their naked self.
If they lie in the bed of their vices and suffer from the disease of their iniquity, bound by the chains of their sins, and surrounded by the wall of their vices in the darkness of their iniquity, they are indeed sick.
But if they escape the mire of their vices through confession and are freed from the chains of their sins by the lamentations of penance, and emerge into the light of good works, they have certainly visited their sick and imprisoned self.
If on this life's journey, you find yourself working hard and being disturbed by the storm of vices like bad weather, and you don't have a place for good deeds,
know that you are on a journey and need a place to stay.
But if you lead yourself to the house of virtues and take shelter in their protection,
you indeed receive a guest.
When you offer all these things to yourself spiritually,
you feed, give drink to, clothe, visit, and receive Christ in yourself, of whom you are a member.
Thirty-Three Believers of the holy Church of God need to be reminded to teach their sons and daughters to show obedience to their parents, as the Lord says, "My child, honor your father"
Likewise, parents should act modestly toward their sons and daughters, as the Apostle says, "And you, parents, do not provoke your children to anger."
It should also be mentioned to them that if they wish to spare their children in a parental way, the Lord does not let these injuries go unpunished unless proper repentance is shown.
It is easier for children to endure any punishment from their parents than to incur the wrath of God.
Thirty-Four What True Love Is.
People should be reminded that true love means loving God more than oneself, loving your neighbor as yourself, and not doing to others what you wouldn't want done to you.
There are many other aspects to consider, but listing them all would take too long.
If anyone thinks love is only about food, drink, and exchanging gifts, they are greatly mistaken.
As the Apostle says, "The kingdom of God is not a matter of eating and drinking" (Romans 14:17).
When these actions are done with love, they are good and should be considered among the virtues.
Thirty-Five Those involved in business and trade should be cautious not to value earthly profits more than eternal life.
Anyone who focuses more on worldly matters than on their soul's salvation is straying from the path of truth.
A wise person once said that in their life, they have lost their innermost self.
In this matter, as in others, we should follow apostolic teachings, which say, "And that no one should take advantage of or defraud their brother in this matter" for God is the avenger of all these things.
Just as those working in fields and other laborious tasks to earn food, clothing, and other necessities are required to give tithes and alms, those engaged in business for their own needs should do the same.
God has given each person a skill by which they are sustained, and everyone should use their skills to provide for the body and the soul, which is even more necessary.
Thirty-Six One week before the beginning of Lent, confessions should be made to priests, penance should be accepted, those in discord should be reconciled, and all quarrels should be settled.
They should forgive each other's debts from their hearts so they can more freely say, "Forgive us our debts, as we forgive our debtors."
Thus, entering the blessed time of Lent with clean and purified minds, they approach Holy Easter and renew themselves through penance, which is the second baptism.
Just as baptism washes away sins, so does penance cleanse.
And because a sinner cannot be baptized again after baptism, the Lord has given the remedy of penance so that sins committed after baptism can be washed away by it in place of baptism.
The Holy Scriptures show that sins are forgiven in seven ways.
First, in baptism, which is given for the remission of sins.
Second, through martyrdom, according to what the Psalmist says, "Blessed is the one whose sin the Lord does not count against them" (Psalm 31:2)
Because, according to David's judgment, "Blessed are those whose iniquities are forgiven, and whose sins are covered" (Psalm 31:1).
Sins are forgiven through baptism, covered through penance, and not counted through martyrdom.
Third, through almsgiving, according to Daniel, who said to the profane king Nebuchadnezzar, "Redeem your sins with alms and your iniquities with acts of mercy to the poor" (Daniel 4:24)
And "Water extinguishes a blazing fire, and almsgiving atones for sin" (Sirach 3:30)
And the Lord in the Gospel says, "But give alms of such things as you have, and behold, all things are clean unto you" (Luke 11:41)
Fourth, if someone forgives those who sin against them, according to this: "Forgive, and you will be forgiven; give, and it will be given to you" (Mark 11:25)
And, "So your Father will also forgive you your sins, if you forgive each one from your hearts" (Mark 11:25)
If someone, through their preaching and good deeds, converts others from their error, they are fulfilling what the Apostle says: "If someone turns a sinner from the error of their way, they will save their soul from death and cover a multitude of sins" (James 5:19)
Through love, as it is written: "Love covers a multitude of sins through Jesus Christ our Lord" (First Peter 4:8)
Through repentance, as David says: "I turned in my suffering, while the thorn was fixed" (Psalm 31:4)
Thirty-Seven The Lenten season must be observed with the utmost care, so that the fast during this time, except on Sundays—which are exempt from abstinence—is not broken in any way.
These days are the tithes of our year, which we must spend with all devotion and holiness.
There should be no occasion to break the fast during these days, because at other times fasting is often broken for the sake of charity, but during this time it should not be broken at all.
At other times, fasting is a matter of personal choice and discretion, but not fasting during Lent is a transgression of God's command.
Fasting at other times earns a reward for abstinence, but during this time, anyone who does not fast, except for the sick and children, brings punishment upon themselves.
This is because the Lord consecrated these days to sacred fasting through Moses, Elijah, and Himself.
Thirty-Eight Almsgiving should be combined with fasting.
On fasting days, the food or drink you would have consumed should be given to the poor.
Simply saving your lunch for dinner is not a sacrifice; it's just an increase in food.
Thirty-Nine
Fasting should not be broken before the evening service.
Many people who think they are fasting start eating as soon as they hear the signal for the ninth hour.
These people should not be considered truly fasting if they eat before the evening service has been celebrated.
One should attend Mass, and after hearing the solemnities of the Mass or evening services and giving alms, then one should go to eat.
However, if someone is unable to attend Mass due to necessity, they should estimate the evening hour and, after completing their prayer, break their fast.
Forty From whom to refrain while fasting.
During these days of fasting, one should abstain from all indulgences and live a sober and chaste life.
If someone can avoid consuming eggs, cheese, fish, and wine, it shows great virtue.
However, if someone cannot abstain from these due to illness or work, they may use them.
Just ensure to observe the fast solemnly until evening, and consume wine only for the refreshment of the body, not to drunkenness.
Abstaining from cheese, milk, butter, and eggs without fasting is foolish and unreasonable.
Drunkenness and indulgence in wine are prohibited, not milk and eggs.
The Apostle doesn't say: Do not eat milk and eggs, but rather, Do not get drunk on wine, which leads to debauchery (Ephesians 5:18).
Forty-One
Which days during Lent should the faithful receive Communion, and how to celebrate Easter week?
On each Sunday in Lent, except for those who are excommunicated, the sacraments of the body and blood of Christ should be received.
On Holy Thursday, Good Friday, the Easter Vigil, and Easter Sunday, everyone should fully partake in Communion.
All the days of Easter week should be celebrated with equal reverence.
Forty-Two
During these days of fasting, we should avoid disputes and quarrels, focusing instead on praising God and doing necessary work.
The Lord admonishes those who argue and fight during Lent, as well as those who pressure debtors for repayment.
Through the prophet, He says:
"Look, on the day of your fast you pursue your own interests and oppress all your workers.
Look, you fast only to quarrel and to fight and to strike with a wicked fist" (Isaiah fifty-eight, verse three).
Forty-Three
During these sacred days, spouses should abstain and live chastely and devoutly.
This way, with a sanctified heart and body, these holy days are observed, allowing us to reach the holy day of Easter.
Fasting is almost worthless if it is tainted by marital acts and is not complemented by prayers, vigils, and alms.
Forty-Four On Holy Communion: how and how often it should be taken.
People should be advised not to approach the sacred sacrament of the body and blood of the Lord carelessly, nor to abstain from it too much.
They should carefully choose a time when they can abstain from marital relations for a while, cleanse themselves of vices, adorn themselves with virtues, be dedicated to charity and prayers, and then approach such a great sacrament.
Just as it is dangerous for anyone impure to approach such a great sacrament, it is also dangerous to abstain from it for a long time.
This is with consideration for those who are excommunicated, who do not take communion whenever they want, but at certain times, and for any religious people living holy lives, who do it almost every day.
Forty-Five On Sundays, people should not be distracted from public worship by special masses.
Special masses conducted by priests on Sundays should not be held in such a way that they distract people from the solemn public masses, which are canonically held at 9 AM.
It is unfortunate that some, on Sundays or other festive days, upon hearing that a mass is being celebrated, even if it is for the deceased, leave immediately.
They spend the whole day from early morning in drunkenness and feasting rather than serving God.
Forty-Six
Everyone should gather at the mother church to hear the solemn Mass and the preacher, and not eat food before the service is completed.
People should be reminded not to eat before the public service is completed, and everyone should gather at the holy mother church to hear the solemn Mass and the preaching.
Priests should celebrate Mass in the oratories no earlier than the second hour, so the people are not distracted from the public solemnities.
Both the priests in the city or nearby, and the people, as mentioned before, should come together for the public celebration of Mass, except for the consecrated women who customarily stay within the monastery's cloisters.
Dearest brothers, most holy fellow priests, and helpers of our ministry, I beseech you with a humble heart in the presence of our Lord Jesus Christ and His saints, to serve God worthily in all religious devotion of love and chastity, and to be teachers and guides to the people of God in all good examples.
So that the people of God may be taught both by your holy conduct and devoted preaching, to the praise and glory of the holy name of our Lord Jesus Christ, and for the eternal salvation of your souls.
Conduct yourselves before God and all the people in chastity of body and humility of soul, showing holy love to all, doing nothing that would make your holy priesthood blameworthy, nor allowing anything in your life that could justly be criticized by anyone.
Let your conduct be free from evil, greed, avarice, gluttony, and drunkenness, as is fitting for the holy priests of God, who must lead the people of God and govern the churches of Christ.
Learn the Catholic faith, preach it diligently, and share it with the people.
Each of you, in your own church, should perform your duties in honor of Almighty God at the appointed times, so that Almighty God may be honored, and His holy name praised by all who see you fulfilling your priesthood and service honorably.
Preach worthily to the people, so they may confess their sins and receive penance in such a way that they cannot receive forgiveness from God for their sins unless they make a pure confession and just penance.
They should also abstain from the sins they committed before, for this is true penance and the most certain indulgence, ensuring that a person does not commit again the same sins for which they have sought pardon.
They should abstain from fornication, and those who have wives should use them legitimately at the appointed times, honor their wives, and thus keep the faith of chastity with their wives, just as they wish their wives to keep it with them.
The sons and daughters they have should be raised in the fear of God and in His holiness, so that they are not thieves, robbers, fornicators, nor commit any other impurities in their bodies to satisfy lust.
They should be obedient to their parents in all good things, so that they are worthy to receive a blessing from the Lord.
Preach to everyone to love the truth, to be kind to the poor, travelers, and the miserable, from the substance that God has given them.
They should not only refrain from taking others' belongings but also generously give their own.
If they wish to have God's blessing, they should not bear false witness nor commit perjury, for God condemns false and perverse witnesses eternally.
Remind them to faithfully do whatever they owe their masters in all labor and work assigned to them.
They should come to churches often, especially on feast days, for prayer, to hear the word of God, and not remain there with idle words during prayer.
They should have pure and holy humility among themselves, and patience and charity, which is the head and foundation of all good.
Preach to them that there is one Almighty God, creator of heaven and earth, who redeemed the world through His Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, and opened the kingdom of heaven to all the faithful, where He will judge the world.
Preach to them about the future judgment and the eternal punishments of the wicked.
Urge them to confess and repent from their sins or to abandon those same sins.
Name those sins which the blessed Paul, teacher of the Gentiles, enumerated, saying:
Do you not know that the unjust will not inherit the kingdom of God?
Do not be deceived; neither the sexually immoral, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor men who practice homosexuality, nor thieves, nor the greedy, nor drunkards, nor slanderers, nor swindlers will inherit the kingdom of God.
Those who do these things or similar things, if they neglect to confess and repent, will be condemned to eternal torment and flames with the devil.
Those who wish to enter the kingdom of God should practice justice, mercy, truth, kindness, and obedience.
They should also give alms according to their ability, practice fasting and prayers, love Almighty God, and do good to all people as much as they can.
Live in chastity and piety, in humility and obedience, and in good faith, trusting in God’s mercy, so that He may forgive all their sins and grant them eternal joy with His saints.
These things, most holy priests of Christ, preach to the people for eternal life with the holy bishops and apostles.
Make yourselves worthy in all religion and chastity in the sight of Almighty God, so that He may grant you, with the abundant fruit of your labor, to receive the glory of eternal happiness.
May Almighty God make you progress in good works, most beloved brothers.