On the Prophet Habakkuk
by Haymo of Halberstadt
The prophet Habakkuk, known as Chabacuk in Hebrew, prophesied after Judah, which is the two tribes, had been taken into captivity by Nebuchadnezzar.
We know this from the Book of Daniel, who was one of the captives from Judah.
When Daniel was placed in the pit, an angel brought this prophet with a meal from Judea.
The name Chabacuk means "embracing" or "embrace," because he was beloved by the Lord, or because he wrestled with the Lord and embraced Him in a kind of struggle.
For none of the prophets dared to challenge the Lord to a debate so boldly and say: "How long, Lord, shall I cry for help," etc.
Chapter One
The burden which Habakkuk the prophet saw.
Whenever a burden is mentioned in the prophets, it signifies the weight of miseries and affliction.
We should pay attention to what follows:
Which Habakkuk the prophet saw.
He saw, that is, he understood what he was saying, unlike the heretic Montanus, who claimed that prophets spoke without understanding, like madmen making meaningless sounds.
How long, Lord, shall I cry for help, and you do not listen?
I call out to you because of violence, and you do not save?
The prophet speaks full of sorrow and complains to the Lord, asking why He has allowed the temple consecrated to Him and the city of Jerusalem, once specially called the city of God, to be destroyed by the Chaldeans.
Why does He not listen to the people crying out to Him and does not save them from the violence of their enemies?
Why do you make me see wrongdoing and look at trouble, seeing plunder and injustice against me?
Why, he asks, have I lived to this time, to witness wrongdoing and trouble, the affliction I endure from enemies?
The prophet said this, troubled by the anguish of his mind, and as if doubting that nothing happens without God's providence, seemingly unaware that saints are tested and make progress through tribulations, just as gold is refined to brilliance in the fire.
But this can also be said, that the prophet speaks such things not from his own perspective, but from that of the imperfect, who, ignorant of God's hidden judgments, dare to complain against the Lord when they see the wicked prosper and the good oppressed, though He knows what, to whom, and when is fitting.
The Psalmist laments something similar, saying: Behold, these are the wicked; always at ease, they increase in riches.
Psalm 73:12
Job also, after listing the happiness of the wicked in the world, concludes: They spend their days in prosperity, and in peace they go down to Sheol.
Job 21:13
And judgment and strife became more powerful.
Because of this, the law is torn apart, and justice does not reach its end, because the wicked prevail against the righteous, therefore perverted judgment emerges.
The prophet, or the people he speaks for, laments because they have been judged not by truth but by power.
They have endured everything not according to the law but through force, making the judgment never-ending.
For the purpose of judgment is to judge justly.
He then explains why he says this by adding: Because the wicked one, that is Nebuchadnezzar, prevails against the just, that is Judah.
Necho, the wicked king of Egypt, prevailed against the holy Josiah.
Daniel and the three martyr boys serve the most wicked king, Nebuchadnezzar.
This can also refer to the saints who complain about why their persecutors prevail against them, why the most wicked judge, after accepting bribes, condemns the innocent and absolves the guilty.
Look among the nations, and see, be amazed and astounded, for a work is being done in your days that you would not believe if told.
The voice of the Lord responds to what the prophet had accused, that the innocent people were overpowered by the wicked.
He (the Lord) says: This injustice, which you think has happened only to Israel, see it happening among other nations as well.
For not only Judah and Jerusalem were given into the hands of the Chaldeans, but all the surrounding nations were too.
He also says that Nebuchadnezzar will have such power and might that if someone describes it, it would seem incredible due to its magnitude.
And what that work is, he shows when he says: For behold, I am raising up the Chaldeans, a bitter and hasty nation, who march through the breadth of the earth to seize dwellings not their own.
They are dreadful and terrible.
The Chaldeans were known to be very warlike and strong, as testified by Trogus and Pompeius, and others who wrote barbarian histories.
Not content with their own borders, they wandered here and there over the heights of the earth, living by plunder and the sword, and possessing cities not their own.
From themselves will come their judgment and their burden.
Their horses are swifter than leopards, fiercer than evening wolves, and their horsemen spread out.
Their horsemen come from afar; they fly like an eagle hastening to devour.
They all come for violence.
This means he will appoint leaders and judges from his own people, and he will not have bodyguards from other nations.
His judgment will come from himself, so just as he acted, he will be treated; and just as he devastated others, he will be devastated.
His horses are faster-swifter than leopards, which are the fastest animals and marked with beautiful variety.
He also compares their horses to evening wolves, because they are said to be fiercer at night, driven to madness by daytime hunger.
They are also compared to eagles, which rush very swiftly to devour.
It follows: Their faces are like a scorching wind, and he will gather captives like sand; he will triumph over kings, and tyrants will be his ridicule.
He will laugh at every fortress, build a mound, and capture it.
Then his spirit will change, and he will pass through and fall.
Just as the breath of a scorching wind withers all green things, so at their sight everything will be devastated, with the number of spoils and captives being so great it could be compared to the sand of the sea, though this is an exaggeration.
Nebuchadnezzar will triumph over the kings of other nations.
Tyrants will be his ridicule, as he makes them precede his chariot in triumph, and his pride will be so great that he will strive to surpass nature.
Finally, Nebuchadnezzar, wanting to capture the city of Tyre situated in the middle of the sea, threw immense mounds into the sea, building such a great mound that he almost turned the sea into an island, establishing a pedestrian path in the waters.
He will laugh at every fortress as if it could be easily captured, and he will build a mound of stones and earth to capture it.
Then his spirit will change, meaning he will be raised in pride, believing himself to be a god.
He even erected a golden statue for himself and commanded all nations to worship it.
After this, he will lose human sense, be cast out from among men, and eventually fall, ceasing to exist.
This is the strength of his god.
This should be read with irony, to make the meaning clear.
This is the strength given to him by his god Bel.
His strength was like that of Bel.
Tropologically, the Chaldeans (interpreted as demons) represent those through whom God exercises vengeance.
God sends indignation, wrath, and tribulation through bad angels.
They are a bitter nation because they spare no one.
Swift in the subtlety of spiritual nature, they walk across the breadth of the earth, which means through the wide ways of the world.
His judgment comes from himself because he is handed over to punishment according to his deeds, and the wicked are allowed under his power.
Just as Philetus and Hermogenes, whom the Apostle handed over to Satan so that they might learn not to blaspheme.
Are You not from the beginning, Lord my God, my Holy One, and we will not die?
The prophet understands from the Lord's response that Nebuchadnezzar received power against Judah, or the devil against the righteous, by a just judgment: but that we live and are not killed by him is due to Your mercy.
Lord, You have appointed him, that is Nebuchadnezzar, for judgment, and by his power, You judge and correct sinners justly.
This follows: You have established him strong to correct, meaning You have given him great and solid strength so that through him You might correct offenders.
These things, literally said about the Chaldeans and their king, can also refer to the devil, whom God has appointed in judgment, as a very strong executioner, so that through him He might afflict the wicked with punishments and test the afflicted good.
Your eyes are pure, so as not to see evil, and You cannot look upon iniquity.
I know, Lord, that You do not willingly look upon evil and injustice, nor can anyone doubt Your justice.
However, why do You allow the Babylonians to act so, and the just Israel to be oppressed by the impious Nebuchadnezzar?
Why do You not regard those acting unjustly and remain silent while the impious devours one more righteous than himself?
We call Israel just, not because he is perfectly just, but because he seems just in comparison to the oppressing impious one.
People are like fish in the sea, and like creatures that have no leader.
Just as fish and other irrational animals are without a leader, the weaker are devoured by the stronger, and those with power rule over others.
Among humans, reason seems worthless, and everything happens by strength.
And although everything is governed by your providence, I cannot understand why the wicked prosper and the righteous are defeated.
He says this, not because he believes it, but to express human impatience.
He will lift it up with a hook, drag it in his net, and gather it in his fishing net.
Because of this, he will rejoice and be glad.
Therefore, he will offer sacrifices to his fishing net and make offerings to his net, because through them his portion is increased.
Since he said people will be like fish of the sea, he continues the fish metaphor.
Just as a fisherman uses a hook, net, and fishing net to catch fish, so too what he cannot catch with a hook, he catches with the net, and what escapes the net is surrounded by larger nets.
In the same way, the king of Babylon, after laying waste to everything and capturing all nations through war and deceit, will rejoice and offer sacrifices to his fishing net and his net, meaning the idol Bel or the golden statue he set up in the plain of Dura in Babylon.
He will offer the fattest victims, namely all the nations he has conquered, compelling them to worship it.
His portion is increased through these idols, and through them he believes he possesses all riches.
For this reason, he spreads out his fishing net and continually kills nations, that is, princes and kings, whom he has caught like great fish and subjected to his empire.
Therefore, he does not stop attacking and slaughtering all nations.
According to the allegory, the devil, whom the king of Babylon represents, cast a hook and first drew man from paradise, surrounded him with nets and multiple deceptions, and through him made all men sinners.
And his chosen food-because he scorns to tempt the lowly and worldly-he even attacks the holy and perfect, never stopping in his pursuit to deceive the human race.
Chapter Two
I will stand at my watchpost and fix my position on the fortress.
I will look to see what will be said to me and what I will answer to my accuser.
The prophet had first complained, and the Lord answered him, saying: Look at the nations, etc.
In response, the prophet moderated his question, as if repenting for what he had previously said, and he says flatteringly: My God, my Holy One, we will not die.
Nevertheless, he asked the same thing, though with a certain reverence: Your eyes are pure so that they do not see evil.
Why do you not look upon those who act unjustly, etc.
Now he says that he is waiting to see what the Lord will answer, so that what was said before may be told to everyone.
I will stand at my watchpost, that is, in the height and elevation of my prophecy, to see what will follow after the destruction of the temple and the city, and the captivity of the people.
And the Lord answered me and said: Write the vision and make it plain on tablets so that whoever reads it may run, because the vision is still for the future, and it will appear at the end, and it will not lie.
As the Lord had said through Isaiah: While you are still speaking, I will say, here I am.
Now the Lord responds and commands the prophet to write the vision, that is, the prophecy, and make it plain, that is, to write it diligently and clearly on the tablets of the heart.
According to the Apostle, who speaks to the Corinthians: You are our letter, written on our hearts.
And this is because the vision is still far off, in the appointed time, and when the end of things comes, it will be proven true.
Clearly, this prophecy is about the coming of Christ, and that question which the prophet had asked, why the wicked would rule, is resolved, because iniquity would reign in the world for so long, and the spiritual Nebuchadnezzar would capture people like fish, until he comes through the incarnation.
If he delays, wait for him, because he will surely come and will not be late.
If, in your eagerness for the fulfillment of the vision, he seems to delay to you, do not despair, but wait patiently, because he will surely come and will not be late.
Behold, anyone who is faithless will not have a righteous soul within themselves.
But the righteous will live by their faith.
If anyone doubts this promise and wavers, thinking that what they see delayed will not come, their soul will not be righteous but will be corrupted by their unfaithfulness.
Another translation says: "My soul will not be pleased," meaning it will displease me. So, if someone who does not believe displeases me, then the righteous who believe in my promise will live by their faith.
Just as wine deceives the drinker, so will the proud man be. He will not be honored, and he will enlarge his soul like hell, never satisfied like death. He will gather all nations to himself and heap all peoples to himself. Will not all these take up a parable against him, and a taunting riddle against him? And it will be said, woe to him who multiplies what is not his.
Here, the destruction of Nebuchadnezzar is clearly pronounced. Just as wine makes the drinker drunk so that neither foot nor mind can perform its duty, so the proud man, whether generally all the proud or specifically Nebuchadnezzar, will not be honored, nor will he achieve his will. Like death and hell, they are never satisfied with the slain and always seizing, setting no limit to their greed.
How long will they keep piling up thick clay against themselves? This word is directed specifically against Nebuchadnezzar and generally against all the greedy. Every greedy person multiplies what is not theirs because the wealth they gather, whether rightfully or wrongfully, cannot stay with them but passes to other owners.
He beautifully called excessive wealth thick clay, because it confounds the purity of the soul and weighs down the mind with the heavy burden of iniquity. Will not those who bite you suddenly rise up, and those who tear you apart be awakened? You will be plundered by them because you have plundered many nations. All the remaining people will plunder you because of the blood of men and the violence of the land, the city, and all its inhabitants.
He refers to the Medes and Persians, who, rising against the kingdom of the Babylonians, first stripped them of their luxury, then tore and scattered them, killing Belshazzar and dispersing all the princes of the kingdom.
Then the devastator of the whole world was plundered by them, and he was spoiled by all the peoples who could escape his cruelty.
This, he says, will come because of the blood of man, referring to Judah, and the iniquity of the land, implying the city of Israel, that is, Jerusalem, and all its inhabitants, encompassing all the people.
The phrase "how long" is either the voice of one rebuking or refers to the prophet's desire for the swift destruction of wickedness and pride.
Woe to him who gathers evil greed for his house, to set his nest on high, and thinks he will be freed from the hand of evil. He speaks against the wicked king, who gathers evil greed for his house, not understanding that riches acquired through evil are the cause of his downfall. At the same time, he is reproved for his pride, for he has set his nest on high like birds, thinking he could be freed from the hand of evil, that is, never coming into the power of enemies.
He calls the greed for money and riches evil because there is also good greed, that is, the desire for the spiritual riches of the wisdom and knowledge of God, although it is rarely or never read that the name of greed is placed in a good sense.
You have devised shame for your house. While you set your nest on high, you have done nothing but devised shame for yourself and your posterity, because this concern will end in disgrace. You have cut down many peoples, and your soul has sinned.
Because the stone will cry out from the wall, and the wood that is between the joints of the buildings will answer. In this, he says, that you have killed many, you have raged against your own soul, and you have burned with such cruelty that the stones of the destroyed cities and the wood of the overturned and burned walls would cry out against your cruelty.
The wood between the joints historically signifies the wood placed in the middle of a structure to hold the walls together.
In the seventy interpreters, it's written, "The beetle will cry out from the wood," literally referring to a fly that hides in the joints of walls during winter or a storm. So, the meaning is: Even flies hidden in the holes of the wood will cry out against your pride and greed.
Woe to him who builds a city with bloodshed and establishes a town by injustice.
This message is directed against Nebuchadnezzar, saying: Woe to him who built Babylon with bloodshed and death, and constructed its walls with injustice.
Are these not the words from the Lord of hosts? He says, do not disregard the speaker, so that the usefulness of the person is not seen as a reason to dismiss the message. For the words spoken by the prophets are the words of the Lord.
People will labor in much fire, and nations will exhaust themselves in vain. When Babylon burns, they will labor in vain to extinguish the fire and strive to no avail. The Chaldean people will fail and grow weary, unable to put out the fire once it is lit. For the earth will be filled with the knowledge of the glory of the Lord, as waters cover the sea. When Babylon is overthrown, the power of God will be manifest to all, and just as waters cover the seabed, the whole earth will be filled with the glory of the Lord.
In some manuscripts, it is written negatively, "These things are not from the Lord of hosts"; meaning: Such a building, made with bloodshed and injustice, is not from the Lord.
Woe to him who gives drink to his neighbor, adding poison and making him drunk, so he can gaze on his nakedness.
The Hebrews tell a story here that is more fantastical than true:
They say King Zedekiah was captured by Nebuchadnezzar in Riblah, which is Antioch, and after his eyes were gouged out, he was taken to Babylon.
There, during a royal feast, Zedekiah was given a drink that caused his stomach to release its contents, humiliating him in front of the guests as he soiled himself.
This is what is meant by the phrase: "Woe to him who gives drink to his neighbor," etc., highlighting that a once-powerful king was brought to such disgrace.
God threatens that he too will drink such a potion.
However, it is better understood not as a literal purgative, but as the suffering Nebuchadnezzar was to endure.
In Scriptures, a cup or drink often symbolizes suffering or affliction.
The prophet condemns the wicked king for forgetting his own humanity and, as if he were immune to suffering, making others drink the bitterness of their troubles to expose their shame and amplify his power.
This metaphor of a drunk man, stripped and shamed, is used to describe how Nebuchadnezzar made everyone drink the cup of fury, leaving them stripped and enslaved.
This means the friend is filled with shame instead of glory.
"Drink and be exposed; the cup in the Lord's right hand will come around to you, and disgrace will cover your glory."
Because you have made many drunk, you too will drink from the Lord's cup.
You will be filled with the Lord's punishments, and everything you consumed will be expelled, bringing you from great glory to extreme misfortune.
The iniquity of Lebanon will cover you.
Lebanon here refers to the temple built from Lebanese wood.
Another prophet says: "Open your doors, Lebanon."
Thus, the iniquity of Lebanon, meaning the destruction of the temple and sanctuary, will devastate and ruin him.
However, he maintains the metaphor, using Lebanon to represent the temple and referring to animals for sacrifices and offerings, saying:
The devastation of animals, meaning the destruction of the sacrifices offered in the temple, will terrify the Babylonians because the harm to the temple and the cessation of sacrifices frightened and destroyed them.
This is due to the blood of men, meaning the killing of men and the wickedness within the promised land and the city of Jerusalem, affecting all those living in it.
In a moral interpretation, heretics were reprimanded for intoxicating everyone with bitter and twisted doctrines, giving a drink to a friend, meaning a fellow believer, not from the fountain of Siloam, which symbolizes Christ sent by God the Father, but from the stream of Egypt, representing darkness and sorrow.
Hence, that stream is rightly called Sior, meaning turbulent and muddy.
It is said that they too will be filled with shame instead of glory when their perverse doctrine is revealed and condemned by the Church's judgment.
The devastation of Lebanon will cover them.
Lebanon indeed means incense in Greek, symbolizing the purity of prayer.
Therefore, the devastation of Lebanon will cover them because their prayer, which is a special sacrifice to God, will turn into their condemnation, as the Psalmist said about Judas: Let his prayer be counted as sin.
What profit is there in an idol, created by its maker, a cast image, and a false image, because its maker trusted in his creation to make mute idols?
The prophet marvels at the foolishness of King Nebuchadnezzar, who commanded a golden statue to be made, trusting in the idol he had fashioned, even though it could not benefit him at all.
The difference between a carved image and a cast image is this: a carved image is made of wood or marble, while a cast image is made of metals that can be melted and cast.
This applies not only to idolaters but also to heretics, whose carved images are their twisted doctrines, which they invent and venerate as truth, worshipping falsehood.
Woe to him who says to wood: Awake; to silent stone: Arise.
Can he teach? This question is often posed to those who worship idols.
Woe to anyone who worships objects made of wood, stone, or metal and calls out, "Wake up," to something that is just an inanimate form.
In Greek, "eidos" or "idea" means form; hence, the word "idolum" refers to a form.
Can the stone you invoke teach you or foretell the future?
Look, this one is covered with gold and silver. This suggests: Look, this stone you worship, oh idolater, is overlaid with gold.
And every spirit, the breath of life, is not within it; the idol or stone lacks life.
But the Lord, whom true worshipers worship, resides in His holy temple.
Let all the earth be silent before Him. Not in a man-made temple, but either in the heavens or within each of the saints, as the Apostle says: Do you not know that you are the temple of God and that the Spirit of God dwells in you?
Either the Lord is in His holy temple, meaning the Son is in the Father, or He is in His temple, which is the entire world, containing and ruling all things.
For in Him we live, move, and have our being.
Therefore, God is in the world, not confined to one place, but filling all things with His majesty, permeating all, encompassing everything.
The prayer of the prophet Habakkuk for ignorance.
Previously, he had rashly complained to the Lord, saying: How long, Lord, will I cry out and You will not hear?
And shortly after, Why do You not look upon those who act wickedly?
He also heard the Lord responding and learned that Nebuchadnezzar or even the devil were placed to judge and punish sinners.
Now he repents and laments that he spoke rashly, asking for pardon for his ignorance, which is why it is written in the title, "For ignorance."
David also asks the Lord, Do not remember the sins of my youth and my ignorances.
Some believe that "For ignorance" shows that the prophet prays to God for human errors and ignorance, so that with the darkness of error removed, the true light may be revealed.
Chapter Three
Lord, I have heard your message, and I was afraid.
The "message" refers to the voice he heard inwardly in his mind.
This is similar to what Isaiah said: "Lord, who has believed our message?" and elsewhere, "The Lord God has opened my ear."
Lord, I have heard your message.
I heard with the ear of the mind the punishments you have prepared for Nebuchadnezzar or the devil and his followers, and you have threatened them with eternal woes five times.
And I was afraid of your most secret judgments.
Lord, your work, I understood, I have heard; that is, the mystery of your incarnation.
For the work of God, as the blessed Augustine says, is: "The Word became flesh."
This can also be understood about his resurrection.
I heard your work, that you who chose to die for us, will rise from the dead.
In the midst of the years, revive it, that is, in the fullness of time fulfill what you have promised.
For you said: "Still, a vision awaits its time; it will speak at the end."
So when that appointed time comes, revive your work so that your word does not die but is fulfilled in action.
In the midst of the years, you will make it known.
When the time comes, and you have completed the promised works, then you will show that what you promised is true.
When you are angry, you will remember mercy, not that God in human fashion forgets in anger and remembers mercy afterward, but that to us, in our suffering, it seems he forgets when he does not quickly help those in distress, as the Psalmist says in tribulation: "How long, Lord, will you forget me forever?"
At the same time, consider God's clemency.
He does not say, "After you have inflicted punishments," but "When you are angry, you will remember mercy."
For he does not always strike when he is angry, but only threatens.
This is also like what the Apostle says: "The wrath of God is revealed against all the ungodliness of men."
He said "is revealed," not "is inflicted"; it is revealed to instill fear and to spare those who correct themselves.
Another translation says: "In the midst of two living beings, you will be known."
These two living beings, we recognize as the Son of God and the Holy Spirit.
The creatures are thought to be the two cherubim, facing each other with the oracle or mercy seat between them.
Some believe the creatures represent the two thieves between whom the Lord was crucified.
Others say the creatures symbolize the two Testaments, Old and New, with Christ recognized between them.
Many interpret them as Moses and Elijah, between whom the Lord appeared transfigured on the mountain.
God will come from the south.
Some interpret "God will come from the south" to mean Bethlehem, located in the southern region where Christ was born. And the holy one from Mount Paran. Mount Paran is near Mount Sinai, where the law was given. It is said that the Holy One will come from there because through the law comes the knowledge of God. This is the literal interpretation.
Or "God will come from the south," meaning from midday, from those who are the children of light and day. Therefore, the Lord will come from the south and is expected by those fervent in love and faith. Hence, in the Song of Songs, the bride asks, "Tell me whom my soul loves, where you graze, where you rest at midday." And the holy one from Mount Paran. Paran means "the mouth of the seer," and indeed, from the mouth, that is, the speech of an educated and insightful person, comes the knowledge of God. (Diapsalma.)
His glory covered the heavens.
At the birth of the Lord, the heavens were filled and covered with glory, as the angels proclaimed, "Glory to God in the highest." And the earth is full of his praise because his advent brought peace to the earth, as the angels sang, "And on earth peace to people of good will." It should be noted that when it says, "His glory covered the heavens," it shows that what is covered is less than what covers. Therefore, the glory is greater than the heavens that are covered. We can also understand the heavens to mean the saints, who bear the image of the heavenly and declare the glory of God. These heavens are covered, meaning illuminated, by the glory and majesty of God.
The earth is full of His praise, for as the Psalmist says, His name is wonderful throughout the earth.
His splendor will be like light because the brilliance of His miracles shines with a manifest glow.
Let's not be troubled by the passage of time.
In the past, it was said: His glory covered the heavens.
Now, the earth is full of His praise.
And in the future, His splendor will be like light.
Indeed, Divine Scripture is not confined by time, as it transcends all time.
Horns are in His hands, representing the banners and trophies of the cross.
Note that even though the Lord's hands are fixed to the horns of the cross, it does not say: The hands of the Lord are on the horns, but rather, Horns are in His hands.
He had power over the cross itself, indeed over death itself, as He says: I have the power to lay down my life.
There, His strength is hidden.
There, in the horns, His strength is hidden, as well as the power of His divinity.
Though He was in the form of God and equal to God, He humbled Himself, taking the form of a servant and submitting to the Father unto death, even death on a cross.
Therefore, on the cross, His strength was hidden, when He said: My soul is sorrowful unto death.
We can also interpret royal power from the horns.
It is customary in Scripture to use a horn to symbolize strength and power, as the Psalmist says: In You, we will gore our enemies with a horn.
And the mother of holy Samuel says: He will give power to His king and exalt the horn of His anointed.
Therefore, horns were in His hands, because although He suffered for us, He did not lose His royal power; rather, through the cross, He expanded His kingdom.
Death will go before His face.
Death, the devil, the author of death, of whom John says: And his name is Death.
Therefore, death went before His feet, because as soon as He was baptized in the Jordan, it confronted Him, tempting Him after forty days of fasting, before He either preached or revealed Himself as God through miracles.
Hence it follows: The devil will go out before His feet, because he confronted Him as He came out of the waters.
Another translation says: Resheph will go out before His feet.
The Hebrews say that Resheph is the name of a demon who holds a high rank among others, similar to Beelzebub.
They say he entered the serpent in paradise and deceived the first human through it.
From the curse by which he was condemned by the Lord, he received his name.
Resheph means "crawling on the belly."
It had been said to the serpent, or rather to the devil who was in the serpent: "You will crawl on your belly."
So the devil came before the feet of the Lord, because as soon as he was baptized and the voice of the Father thundered over him at the descent of the dove, the devil, disturbed by this, came to tempt him, wanting to test whether he was the Son of God.
He stood and measured the earth.
Standing is a divine attribute, while moving is a human one.
The Lord stood and measured the earth, because by the power of his divinity, arranging all things, he measured the earth, that is, the hearts of earthly men, discerning and foreseeing who would be worthy to be chosen and who would be rejected by just judgment.
He looked and scattered the nations.
The look of the Lord is the vision of divine majesty, by which he foresees everything, arranging each thing in its place and time.
He looked and scattered the nations, meaning he dispersed them so they would no longer be nations, but reborn through faith and baptism, becoming children of God.
And the mountains of the world were crushed.
With the nations of the world scattered, the mountains were crushed, meaning all the power of the demons was broken, which he calls the mountains of the world because of their pride and arrogance.
Or he calls the mountains of the world the princes and powerful ones of this world, who were broken from their hardness of pride upon seeing the clarity of Christ's miracles.
But he calls them the mountains of the world because there are other mountains that are not of the world, namely the holy apostles and apostolic men, of whom the Psalmist says: "I lift my eyes to the mountains," etc.
These are not the mountains of the world, but the mountains of God, the mountains full of curdled milk, meaning filled with spiritual grace.
The hills of the world bowed down from his eternal paths.
Those who are the mountains are also the hills, meaning the powerful and their peers, whose pride no one could humble before the coming of Christ.
We are broken and bent down by the journeys of His eternity, that is, of God, because the eternity of His divinity has deigned to come to us.
His journeys are from heaven into the womb of the virgin, from the womb to the manger, from the manger to baptism, from baptism to the cross, from the cross to the tomb, and from the tomb back to heaven.
The stronger demons can also be understood as the mountains, found in heretics and apostates, who rise against the knowledge of God.
The hills, on the other hand, represent demons of lesser power, who are in secular people boasting of riches, strength, beauty, nobility, and other worldly goods.
These mountains and hills were broken and bent down at the coming of Christ.
When such people converted and followed Christ's example of humility, the demons within them were confounded, and their opposing strength was reduced to nothing.
For iniquity, I saw the tents of Ethiopia.
Ethiopians are the most dreadful people, said to eat the flesh of dragons, symbolizing demons dreadful in their wickedness, whose sweetest drink is men with the mind of serpents, always ready to harm.
The tents of the Ethiopians are the people themselves, who by working to acquire riches, become their tents.
As the prophet expressed in one word, iniquity: For every rich man is either wicked himself or the heir of a wicked man.
Therefore, the prophet says, I saw men made the tents of Ethiopia for iniquity, that is, greed, which never ceases to gather riches.
When they acquire riches, they indulge in luxury, pleasures, and all iniquity, thus becoming a dwelling place for demons, who should instead be the temple of God.
The skins of the land of Midian will be troubled.
What he called tents above, he now calls skins; and what he called Ethiopians, he now calls the land of Midian.
Midian is a region near Ethiopia.
Midian is interpreted from judgment, meaning condemnation.
The people of Midian will be troubled.
Those who have made their lives dwellings for demons by acquiring wealth and worldly honors through injustice and wickedness will be troubled.
Terrified by the guilt of their sins and the fear of eternal punishment, they will live in constant dread and, after death, will endure severe torments.
Were you angry with the rivers, Lord?
Was your wrath against the rivers, or your indignation against the sea?
The prophet asks the Lord as if in doubt: O Lord, when you made the Jordan River turn back and divided the sea to make a path for your people, were you angry with the rivers or indignant with the sea?
The insensible elements had done nothing to deserve your indignation.
Just as you fought for your people then, now you ascend your horses and draw your bow to give salvation to your people.
It should be known that there are good rivers and bad ones, and the sea can be both good and sweet or very bad and bitter.
A river is used in a good sense when the Psalmist says: The rush of the river makes the city of God glad.
But in an evil sense, as Pharaoh speaks in Ezekiel: The rivers are mine, and I made them.
The sea is also used in a good sense where it is said in the Psalm: The earth and the world belong to the Lord.
He established it upon the seas.
Bad rivers are the doctrines of heretics, which run like rivers with foaming eloquence and flow against the truth.
The Lord is angry with these, and his wrath is upon them.
The sea represents those who are carried about by every wind of doctrine and are always at the bottom.
The Lord's indignation is upon them because they favor perverse teachers, but his wrath has not yet fully flared up, as they are awaited to repent from their errors.
You who ascend on your horses, your chariots bring salvation.
The horses of God are the souls of the saints upon which the Lord ascends to possess and guide them from the paths of error to the way of truth.
From these horses came the one who said: I have become like a beast before you.
The prophet Elisha was surrounded by these horses and chariots, which he showed to his fearful servant.
For the Scripture in the Book of Kings says: When he looked, behold, the mountain was full of fiery horses and fiery chariots all around Elisha.
And it should be noted that among the many thousands of horses and chariots, no rider is seen.
For He was the charioteer and driver to whom the Psalmist sings: You who sit upon the cherubim, reveal yourself.
God ascends upon horses like these, and His chariots are salvation; or, as another translation says, Your cavalry is health.
The cavalry of God is the multitude of all the righteous, the salvation of the entire human race, because riding on the saints, He surveyed and saved the whole world.
You will rouse your bow; that is, what you promised in the Old Testament, you will fulfill in the New.
For by the bow, which is stretched by two ends, the two Testaments are understood.
Hence it follows and shows what the bow is: Oaths to the tribes which you spoke.
You will rouse (he says) the bow, fulfilling the oaths that you spoke to the tribes of Israel about the coming of your Son.
(Diapsalma.)
You will split the rivers of the earth; the mountains saw you and trembled.
The rivers of the earth are the hearts of earthly men, which were split and opened through repentance by the preaching of the apostles, so that they would receive the seed of the word of God.
For even at the passion of the Lord, the rocks were split, to signify that the hard hearts of the nations would be split through faith.
The mountains saw this, that is, the opposing forces, and trembled, envying the salvation of the nations.
Or the mountains are the high kingdoms of the earth, and the lofty powers of the world.
They saw the growth and spread of the faith of Christ, and trembled, and stirred up the gravest persecution against the saints.
Hence it follows: the torrent of waters passed by.
The torrent of waters, a strong storm of persecution, passed by, that is, it ceased, after the mountains, that is, the powers of the world, recognized Christ.
Or in another sense: the torrent of waters, that is, the preaching of the apostles, passed by, announced to all the ends of the world.
The deep gave its voice: this means the profound preaching of the apostles resounded throughout the world.
The height will raise its hands; that is, divine power revealed itself through miraculous works.
Raising hands means performing miracles.
Alternatively: The deep gave its voice; this means the underworld, conquered by Christ, praised the conqueror of death.
The height raised its hand; that is, the angelic height, as if with a certain applause, praised Christ.
The sun and moon stood still in their dwelling.
According to Isidore, after the day of judgment, the sun will not set and the moon will not descend below the earth, but will always appear above the earth; the sun indeed in the east, the moon in the west, visible to the whole world, and they will not descend below the earth, so as not to show their light to the underworld.
In a higher sense: the sun and moon stood still in their dwelling because Christ, who is the true sun, rising from the dead, ascended to the dwelling of heaven; the moon, that is, the Church, remained devoutly and unwaveringly in the faith it received.
As another translation says more clearly: The sun was raised in its rising, and the moon stood in its order.
In the light of your arrows they will go, in the brightness of your flashing spear.
The order of the words is: Your arrows and your spear will go in the light and in the brightness of the flashing.
The arrows and spears of God are the apostles, because just as arrows and spears shine and wound, so the apostles shone with miracles, wounding with their preaching, and announcing eternal punishments to sinners.
Alternatively: The sun and moon stood still in their dwelling.
O God!
The sun and moon, and all the splendor of the signs, with which you once illuminated your people, were now covered by the weight of evils and a certain horror of darkness; but with your appearance, they stood in their dwelling, that is, they regained their splendor and power.
Therefore, without a doubt, the faithful people will go in the light of your arrows, and in the brightness of your flashing spear; this means, they will walk through the path of this life in the light of your commandments, which, like arrows or spears, wound for salvation, and terrify to correct.
You will trample the earth in fury.
In the powerful preaching of the apostles, you will tread upon the earth; that is, you will touch the hearts of worldly people.
And with fury, by the threat of judgment, you will astonish the nations, the earthly kingdoms, and make all the powers of the world marvel.
Because you went out, O God the Father, for the salvation of your people, for salvation with your Christ, that is, with your Son, whom you anointed with the unique chrism of grace above all the saints.
As the Apostle says: God was in Christ, reconciling the world to himself.
You struck the head from the house of the wicked one.
The head means the prince of this world; the house means the world or the soul of the sinner, in which he rests as in his own inn.
Therefore, the head is struck from the house of the wicked one, so that when it is struck, the house becomes the house of God and a dwelling place of justice.
You laid bare the foundation up to the neck.
You revealed all the cunning and secret plans of that wicked one to the faithful up to the neck, that is, up to the very one who is the head and prince of spiritual wickedness, namely, the Antichrist.
Because just as the neck is joined to the head, so he is similar to the malice of the devil, and almost like the administrator of deception.
Hence the Apostle says: So that we would not be outwitted by Satan, for we are not ignorant of his designs.
(Diapsalma.)
You cursed his scepters.
The scepter is a symbol of royal authority, and thus through the scepter royal power is implied.
God cursed his scepters, that is, the kingdom and power of the wicked one.
The wicked one, according to the previous prophecy, can be taken as Nebuchadnezzar, any enemy of the people of God, or even the devil himself.
Of whom it further follows: The head of his warriors, you understand, you cursed.
Not only his scepters, but also the very head that you struck, you cursed.
The head of the warriors is the devil, the persecutors of the Church, such as Nero, Domitian, and others who declared public persecution of the Church.
Those coming, like a whirlwind, like a storm with immense terror, to scatter me, that is, the unity of the holy Church.
Their joy, meaning the persecutors' joy, is like that of someone who secretly preys on a poor person.
Just as a thief is happy when he robs a poor person without anyone noticing or helping, so the persecutors of the saints rejoiced, thinking that God did not see or know whom they were oppressing.
This also applies to any wrongdoer who takes pleasure in sinning without consequence, believing he can hide from God and that God is unaware of his actions.
You made a way in the sea for your horses.
The horses of God are the apostles and other preachers, for whom God made a path in the sea, which represents the world, so they could travel far and wide.
They could not have reached so many fierce nations by preaching through their own strength, unless God had made a way, uniting the diverse nations under one Roman Empire.
In the mire of many waters; that is, in the idolatry of many nations, you made a way for your preachers so that they would despise it and trample it like mud.
I heard not with the ear of the body, but with the understanding of the mind.
And what did he hear?
He heard the things that were said by the Father to the Son about His birth and suffering, by which He was to redeem the world.
And my belly was troubled; that is, my understanding was troubled, questioning why I dared to criticize God's judgments, since even the Son of God, who had no sin, endured such great and undeserved suffering from the unworthy.
At the sound of this hearing, my lips trembled so that I no longer dared to speak or complain about why the righteous are afflicted in the world.
Let rot enter my bones and spring up beneath me.
The prophet, now certain that the saints are tested by adversities in this life to be led to true rest in the next, says he willingly wants to suffer all contrary things; he wishes to be tested and afflicted by bodily infirmity like Job, saying: Let rot enter my bones, so that not only the flesh but even the marrow of the bones decays.
And let it spring up beneath me, that is, let it bubble up with a multitude of worms.
By this, he shows himself ready to endure all the gravest and most extreme punishments.
And why is this?
So that I may rest in the day of trouble; that is, on the day of judgment, when there will be such tribulation as never before.
And so I may join the prepared people.
The command is to join those who are ready and prepared to resist spiritual enemies.
For the fig tree will not blossom.
The fig tree represents the Jewish people, to whom the Lord came seeking the fruit of righteousness, but did not find it.
He immediately cursed it, saying: No fruit shall ever come from you again.
Foreseeing, therefore, that the Jews would persist in their unbelief, the prophet, full of sorrow, says: The fig tree will not blossom.
This means the synagogue of unfaithful Jews will not bring forth the flower of faith and the fruit of good works.
This is not about all, but about those who were blinded, most of whom perished.
When the fullness of the Gentiles comes in, then this fig tree will blossom, and all Israel will be saved.
And there will be no fruit in the vineyards.
We learn from many places in Holy Scripture that the people are called the vineyard, one of which is: You brought a vine out of Egypt.
This vineyard, planted among the patriarchs and cultivated nobly among the prophets, brought forth fruit most pleasing to God.
But when the Lord appeared, it degenerated: And when it should have produced grapes, it produced wild grapes; that is, when it should have believed in Christ, who was promised and sent to them, it instead denied Him, and asked for His death, saying, We have no king but Caesar, and, Crucify Him, crucify Him.
Foreseeing this, the holy prophet laments, saying: There will be no fruit in the vineyards; that is, the root of good works in the Jews.
The work of the olive will lie.
The olive represents the synagogue, as recognized by those who have read the apostle Paul discussing the broken branches of the olive tree and the wild olive grafted into the good olive.
The work of this olive tree was anointing, because in the Old Testament, kings and prophets were anointed with visible oil.
The prophet foretells that this anointing will cease with the coming of Christ, just as Daniel says: When the Holy One comes, anointing will cease.
The olive tree will fail, meaning the Jewish people will fail, who promised to fulfill everything that the Lord commanded, saying: "We will do everything that the Lord our God commands, and we will obey Him."
And the fields will not yield food. Jerusalem, the earthly city, is designated by the name of fields, that is, plains. For although it was situated on mountains and it had been said about it: "Its foundations are on the holy mountains," after it refused to receive the Son of God, it is called lowly and flat, fallen from the height of virtues. Therefore, the fields will not yield food, because the Jewish people now produce no fruit of faith or good deeds.
The flock will be cut off from the fold; that is, from Jerusalem, where the people lived like sheep in a fold. The mixed multitude of people will be cut off, destroyed by Titus and Vespasian with the sword, famine, and captivity. And there will be no cattle in the stalls, meaning the priests, scribes, and other leaders, who, like fat bulls, ruled over the people as their herds, and delighted in full stalls. Therefore, there will be no cattle in the stalls, because with Jerusalem overthrown, all the dignity of its leaders was nullified, and what the Lord had said was fulfilled: "Your house will be left to you desolate."
But I will rejoice in the Lord, and I will exult in God my Savior. With the predicted destruction of the people and leaders and the entire city, the prophet speaks from his own perspective and that of the apostles and all the saints. "I," he says, "will rejoice in the Lord, not in riches, not in the glory of this world, and I will exult in God Jesus my Savior." For Jesus means savior or salvation, but the interpreter preferred to use the Hebrew word itself because the name Jesus is always sweet and full of joy to hear.
God the Lord is my strength. All my strength, all my justice is Christ, who is my God. And He will make my feet like those of deer. The nature of deer is to abandon flat and low places and ascend steep mountains, even killing snakes drawn out of their caves by their breath.
Thus, the saints leave behind earthly and lowly things and strive for heavenly ones.
Through their preaching, they drive out the malice of the ancient serpent from people's hearts.
Therefore, the prophet says, "The Lord God will set my feet," meaning my actions, "like those of deer," making me, by His grace, despise fleeting things and desire eternal ones.
And He will lead me over my heights, singing victoriously in psalms. He will lead me over my heights, meaning to that heavenly homeland, because it has been prepared for me and all the saints before the ages. Therefore, I confidently say: Over my heights. Yet, He will lead, because this is not by my strength, but by His grace.
He will lead me singing to the victor, that is, to Christ, the conqueror of death and the devil. Therefore, He will lead me over my heights, to the blessed company of the heavenly city, which consists of angels and holy people. Mingled and united with them, I may sing to the victor with the angels, "Glory to God in the highest."
And I will sing in the psalms of praise, harmonizing with the psalmist David: "O Lord, in Your strength the king will be glad."