Historical Note.
According to Mansi, in The Most Comprehensive Collection of Councils, volume 18, column 447, John, son of Alberic, who ruled the city, assumed the papal seat in the year 965, during the reign of Emperor Constantine the Eighth.
Even though he didn't meet the necessary age and other requirements to be a legitimate pope, the entire clergy eventually agreed that it was better to tolerate him than to risk a schism that could divide the Church.
The whole Catholic Church understood it was less damaging to have a leader, despite his flaws, than to split the Church into two separate entities, each with its own leader.
Thus, he was recognized as the true and legitimate pope worldwide.
He was the first to change his name from Octavian to John, not abandoning but merely altering his leadership style.
His father, Alberic, had named him Octavian for temporal rule over the city, but upon taking the papal role and spiritual leadership over the world, he chose to be called John.
With youthful zeal for threats and violence, he gathered an army with support from the Duchy of Spoleto and waged war against the Prince of Capua, named Pandulf.
When Pandulf fiercely resisted with aid from the people of Salerno, John had to retreat and seek peace through negotiations.
During his time, Berengar, freed from the fear of the deceased Liudolf, son of Otto, who had been sent to Italy to curb Berengar's tyranny, roamed Italy unchecked, devastating both sacred and secular places indiscriminately.
Unable to tolerate the tyranny any longer, Pope John sent a delegation to Otto, the king of Germany.
With the help of Liutprand, he pleaded with the king through letters and signs to, for the love of God and the holy apostles Peter and Paul-whom he hoped would forgive his sins- rescue him and the holy Roman Church from their enemies, and restore them to safety and freedom.
At the same time, guided by God, the people of Milan made a similar request through an appointed delegation.
Before leaving Germany, Otto held an assembly at Worms, where he appointed his son Otto, born of Adelaide, as king, and entrusted him to the care of Archbishop Wilhelm of Mainz, his son from another wife.
After pledging loyalty and security to the apostolic see through an oath, Otto received a promise regarding future succession in the Roman Empire and its rights and titles.
With these preparations complete, the pious king, as Liutprand noted, gathered his troops and swiftly went to Italy, expelling Berengar and Adalbert, clearly having the most holy apostles Peter and Paul as his allies.
Once he had restored what had been taken to their rightful lords, in the year 962 of Christ the Redeemer, the seventh year of John's pontificate, he arrived in Rome.
There, he was received with great honor, wonderful splendor, and ceremony by the pope, with applause from all the people, and was called and ordained as Emperor and Augustus, receiving the anointing of the empire.
What he lawfully returned to Pope John and the gifts he added to the Roman Church are detailed in an authentic donation document inscribed in gold letters, preserved in Rome at the Castel Sant'Angelo.
In gratitude, the pope and all the leaders of the city swore over the body of Saint Peter never to support Berengar and Adalbert, and so the emperor departed Rome and went to Pavia.
Meanwhile, Pope John, persuaded to defect, forgot his sworn oath and joined with Adalbert.
When the emperor received reports from returning messengers confirming the truth, Luitprand writes that he remarked:
"He is a boy; he will easily change through the example of good men. I hope that with honest reproach and liberal persuasion, he will easily emerge from those evils."
Consequently, when the emperor returned to Rome, both the pope and Adelbert fled. Luitprand notes that the citizens welcomed the holy emperor and his entourage into the city, promising loyalty and firmly swearing that they would never elect or appoint a pope without the consent and election of Lord Emperor Otto Caesar Augustus and his son, King Otto.
Three days after his arrival in Rome, a pseudo-synod was convened under Otto's authority, where John was removed from his position, and the pseudo-pope Leo the Eighth was appointed.
After Otto's death, when he returned to the city, he deposed him as an adulterer and usurper of the seat, annulling all the acts of that council, which had been conducted without adhering to any lawful or traditional order, where Pope John had been replaced.
Regarding the unfortunate end of Pope John, the author, believed to be Luitprand, writes:
One night outside Rome, while entertaining himself with another man's wife, he was struck in the groin by the devil so severely that he died within eight days from the wound, not because, as he claimed, he was justly condemned and justly received his fate, but because, despite being warned by God through many great trials, he did not abstain from his habitual sins.
Although these accounts by Luitprand may reflect the views of an adversary of the man and are heavily attributed to Otto, I do not contest their truth, as they do not harm the Catholic faith. We unanimously profess that Peter and his successors, after receiving Christ's promise, can fail in morals but not in faith.
Regino's chronicle asserts that Pope John's death occurred in the year nine sixty-four, on the day before the Ides of May.
Pope John the Twelfth: Epistles and Privileges
One Letter from Pope John the Twelfth to Archbishop Wilhelm of Mainz.
Year Nine Fifty-Five.
He mentions that the letters addressed to Agapetus were given to him and expresses sorrow for his troubles.
John, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to the most reverent and beloved brother Wilhelm, archbishop of the holy Church of Mainz.
Know that we have received the letters your brotherhood sent to Pope Agapetus of blessed memory, whom the divine power arranging all things appointed to the apostolic seat upon his death, not by our merits, but by his mercy preceding us, from whom are all things that exist.
We believe nothing happens in the world unless it is done by his will or consent.
Indeed, we are saddened by the losses, miseries, and the plots of wicked men who disturb the holy Churches of God and all order and state, as the apostolic judgment decreed, to rejoice with those who rejoice and to weep with those who weep.
For we have become the head of all Christianity after the Lord, not by any human privilege, but by the voice of the Lord himself to the blessed apostle Peter, as you know well, saying: You are Peter, and on this rock, I will build my Church, etc.
Therefore, if we know that any member of our body is unjustly suffering tribulations or troubles, either by letters or in any other way, we sympathize and are distressed.
With you, we oppose their plots and injustices with apostolic authority as much as we can.
In the meantime, we urge your community to stand firmly against those who choose to live rebelliously and unjustly, and who strive to destroy the churches of the Lord.
If they refuse to obey our pious commands and your warnings, do everything you can to resist them and guide them towards the path of peace, truth, and justice.
This way, we ensure that we are not found guilty before the righteous judge due to their growing wickedness.
For those whom you recognize as persisting in evil deeds and who refuse to be corrected by your instructions, send them to this our apostolic seat, as was the ancient custom.
Alongside them, send your trusted believers who can faithfully and orderly report to us about their cases and everything happening in the regions of Gaul and Germany.
This matter is close to our hearts, and we strongly desire that peace and honor remain in all churches and among all Christian people.
Any traces of evil that may have existed should be completely removed.
SECOND PRIVILEGE OF POPE JOHN THE TWELFTH FOR THE MONASTERY OF SAINT MARY HUMOLARIENSI.
Year 956.
JOHN, bishop and servant of the servants of God, to the venerable abbot BERNER of the Church of the blessed Virgin Mary, Mother of God, and through him to the entire congregation forever.
If we give our consent to the rightful requests of the pious, we believe we are serving the will of the Lord.
Therefore, let it be known to all the children of the Holy Mother Church, both present and future, that our son, the noble young king Lothair of the Franks, has humbly petitioned us to support with our authority a certain cell located in the district of Vermandois, built in honor of the blessed Virgin Mary, Mother of God, and Saint Hunegundis the Virgin.
Influenced by his father, King Louis, Count Adalbert, and the worthy man Gilbert, who holds the same abbey by right of benefice, he seeks to elevate it for the revered practice of sacred religion and aims to fortify it with the royal authority's decree.
We rejoice at his request, and with the strength of ecclesiastical authority, we exercise our power and command by the apostolic authority with which we are supported, that no secular person shall ever possess the aforesaid abbey, nor shall anyone usurp anything from the property of that cell, not the king, nor the count, nor the bishop, nor any prince endowed with any power, except perhaps for the purpose of protection and defense, and this only with the permission of the regular abbot of the same place.
If anyone gives or promises money or any gift to the king or any prince to acquire this, they will be subject to the curse to be imposed.
Therefore, let an abbot according to the rule of Saint Benedict be appointed for the same cell, and monks subject to regular discipline, whom we strictly prohibit from suffering any loss from the property of the same cell.
However, the property of this same church includes the villa of Humolarias, where the cell is built, along with all the associated dwellings; Merulficurtis and its surroundings; Eudoldicurtis and its appendages; Caviniacus with its dwellings; and in the villa called Frisia on the river Somme, there are 12 dwellings, which the church is allowed to keep perpetually for the convenience of fishing.
Therefore, these properties, along with any others the church may acquire with the Lord's help, will be possessed freely and without any opposition, supported by apostolic authority.
This was written by Leo, from the sacred repository of the holy apostolic see, in the month of January, during the 14th indiction.
It was given on January 2nd, by George, the second bishop of the holy apostolic see, in the first year of the pontificate of our Lord John, sovereign pontiff and universal pope, with the Lord's favor.
Three Letter from Pope John the Twelfth to Berenger, Bishop of Verdun. Year 956.
Confirms the privileges and possessions of the Monastery of Saint Viton.
John, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to Berenger, our brother, bishop of the Church of Verdun, with all those entrusted to him by God, may you receive the reward of eternal recompense.
It is fitting for apostolic governance to support those who excel in pious religion with benevolent charity and to provide eager approval to those who ask.
For in doing so, we will undoubtedly earn the greatest reward from the Lord, the creator of all, if we improve venerable places of saints through our authority.
Therefore, dear brother, we have found among your other acts of holy conduct, that you have built a monastery in your bishopric near the city of Verdun, specifically in the church of the blessed Peter, for the love of God, where the bodies of the holy confessors rest.
And of the aforementioned church of Saint Mary, once bishops Vitonus, Pulchronius, Possessor, and Firminus, you have supported it with prudent consideration using the resources of your church.
So that if at any time the children of your Church, moved by divine love, seek to pursue the perfection of a contemplative life, they would not be seen as completely separated from your Church, but would find a refuge of solace in the monastery, which is a part of the same Church, under the habit of religion, and serve the Lord in peaceful tranquility there.
Let it be known to the diligence of all the faithful, both present and future, that we wish the same monastery built by your ordinance, with all matters and royal decrees established with your counsel, to remain unshaken forever.
Namely, the estate above Scantia, with its appurtenances; Flavigny, with its adjuncts; and the abbey of Saint Amantius, with whatever pertains to it.
To Neuville, along with its locations; to the court of Mantion, as it pertains to you; Parry, with its surroundings; the church of Marculfi-Court, with its surroundings; Arbord-Villa, with its belongings; the church of Castonis-Court, with its associated items; the church of Marleio, with its surroundings; the church of Amonzei-Villa, with its lands, vineyards, mills, servants, and maidservants; the abbey of Peter, and the church of Maroa; to Limacum, whatever pertains to that place; to Neuville in the county of Barr, whatever pertains to that place.
All these aforementioned places, with all their general and specific belongings, and whatever by the grace of God and the vow of the faithful has been granted to this monastery, we confirm eternally through this our apostolic privilege; both to you and your successors, and further, to be strengthened by the privilege of our authority, so that the same Verdun Church, which until now was deprived of those children exposed in its care from infancy, while they sought external monasteries, may henceforth and in the future take pride in their holy devotion in a community subject to it, with the guidance of its bishop and the leadership of the glorious abbot Humbert.
However, if anyone, with reckless daring, whether of great or small status, of any order or power, dares to go against this our apostolic command, let them know that by the authority of the blessed Peter, prince of the apostles, they are excommunicated, bound by the chain of anathema, and alienated from the kingdom of God, condemned with all the wicked to eternal fire and punishment.
But whoever observes this our command, may they deserve to obtain grace, mercy, and eternal life from our most merciful Lord God.
Written by the hand of Leo, the notary of the holy apostolic see, in the month of January, in the fourteenth indiction.
Farewell.
Issued on January 9 by Martin, bishop and librarian of the holy apostolic see.
In the seventh year of the pontificate of Lord John, the Supreme Pontiff and Universal Pope, the twelfth, at the most sacred seat of the blessed Apostle Peter.
In the first month, during the fourteenth indiction.
Letter Four: Epistle of Pope John Twelve to Landulph, Bishop of Benevento (Year Nine Hundred Fifty-Six)
John, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to the most reverend and holy Landulph, bishop of the holy church of Benevento, and to your successors forever.
Since the summit of the highest and apostolic dignity shines with the brilliance of divine progress and strives earnestly to offer praises to God, we are compelled by our apostolic pastoral duty to promote stability in pious places and confirm them with the decree of apostolic institution.
Therefore, as you have requested that the holy church of Benevento, under your leadership by God's favor, be adorned with the privileges of the holy apostolic see, and that we confirm the ancient boundaries granted by our predecessor pontiffs, we grant this with our authority, supporting your pious desires.
We grant to you and your holy church of Benevento whatever it has historically and rightfully possessed, from the time of your predecessors, including Bivinum, Asculum, Larinum, Sipontum, and the church of Saint Michael the Archangel on Mount Gargano, with all their appurtenances, estates, churches, families of both sexes, and properties.
We grant to your religion and your successors the right to govern and legally manage all places within the ancient jurisdiction of your parish, with all their appurtenances, whether they are cities or any castles long held by your predecessor bishops.
We decree with apostolic authority, under the solemn witness of divine judgment and with strong prohibitions of anathema, that no person, regardless of their office or status, whether high or low, or Greek, should ever harm or take anything from the Church of Saint Benevento, or reduce its boundaries in any way.
No one should cause any trouble or malice, nor should anyone be allowed to remove anything from it or from what belongs to it, regardless of their status.
This is to ensure that the venerable Church of Saint Benevento, adorned with apostolic decrees and privileges, remains unshaken and endowed.
If anyone, which we do not desire, with wicked boldness, attempts to oppose or transgress what we have decreed for the praise of God and the stability of the Church of Benevento, whether Greek or any other person seeking power or primacy, by themselves or through another, in these churches without the will and command of the Bishop of Benevento, and those who might presume to receive them, all shall remain under the same apostolic and strict unbreakable anathema and shall not enter any church or perform any ecclesiastical office.
But whoever observes and keeps all of this decree of ours for the worship of God shall abundantly receive the grace of blessing from our most merciful Lord God, and may they be deemed worthy to partake in eternal life.
Written by the hand of Leo, the secretary of the Holy Roman Church, in the month of December, in the fifteenth indiction.
Farewell.
Given on the eighteenth day before the Kalends.
In January, with the help of Bishop Marinus and the librarian of the highest apostolic see, and with the Lord's favor, during the pontificate of our lord John, the supreme pontiff and universal pope, in the most sacred seat of the blessed Apostle Peter, in the eleventh month and the fifteenth indiction mentioned above.
Five LETTER OF JOHN THE TWELFTH TO ARCHBISHOP HENRY OF TRIER. Fragment.
- Year 957. He grants the use of the pallium.
JOHN, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to the most reverent and beloved brother HENRY, Archbishop of the Holy Church of Trier, for your life only.
Given the day before the Ides of February by the hand of John, the librarian of the holy apostolic see, in the year of our Lord, during the pontificate of the lord John, supreme pontiff and twelfth universal pope, seated in the most sacred chair of the blessed Apostle Peter, with the most pious lord Augustus Otto, crowned by God, great emperor, in his first year, in the month of February, in the fifth indiction.
Six Brief Recollection.
In 958, Pope John the Twelfth compelled the residents of Subiaco, who were defiant toward the abbot of the Subiaco monastery and had seized many of its properties, to restore everything.
This occurred perhaps in the third year of Pope John the Twelfth's papacy, in May, during the first indiction.
Since the human mind is always busy with various tasks and concerns, unable to express everything in words or remember the future, the gift of writing was discovered by wise men through God's will, allowing us to inscribe what we can't keep in mind.
Therefore, I, Leo, abbot of Saint Benedict of Subiaco, recount how the Lord Pope visited our monastery for prayer and how we protested about the issues at Subiaco and other regions, regarding the constant persecutions and afflictions inflicted upon our monastery.
Moved by compassion and mercy for this venerable place and our entire congregation, the Lord Pope began to sympathize with the injustices we had suffered since Lord Alberic of blessed memory passed away.
While the supreme pontiff stayed at the monastery with honorable bishops like Marinus of the Church of Polimartium, Constantine, bishop of Portus, John, humble bishop of Tivoli, and Roman judges like George, second secretary of the Holy Roman Church, Leo, chief secretary of the Holy Apostolic See, and many others, he commanded all adversaries to come before him.
When they appeared before the Lord Pope with us, they were greatly restrained; he ordered that all properties, dwellings, and lands, mentioned individually, be returned to the monastery.
He instructed the abbot to create a brief recollection of this affair, having it signed by the aforementioned men and other worthy individuals for the everlasting memory of the matter.
Seven Bull of Pope John the Twelfth to Abbot Leo. Year Nine Thirty-Eight.
Confirms the goods and rights of the Subiaco monastery.
John, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to the venerable priest, monk, and abbot Leo of the esteemed monastery of Saint Benedict and Saint Scholastica, located in Subiaco, and to your holy congregation and successors forever.
The desire for pious will and commendable devotion should always be supported by apostolic help for those who need it, ensuring that what is legally established remains firm through justice, undisturbed by any opposition, and maintains unbreakable right and authority.
For this reason, the laws declared by apostolic authority require that each rightful possession be confirmed.
Therefore, since it is known that your holiness has acquired many sacred places, all belonging to the honor and benefit of your esteemed monastery by right and authority, you seem to possess various fields along with castles and assets, as well as a multitude of servants.
All these places, fields, lands, and possessions, with all the original servants residing there, including male and female colonists and everything associated with them, you have requested to be confirmed by the privileges of the apostolic see to be held under the authority of your reverence, your holy congregation, and your successors, the servants of the Lord, forever.
Of course, the entire castle, known as Sublaco or by any of its other names, along with all its boundaries, borders, and limits, including lands, houses, vineyards, fields, meadows, pastures, forests, willow groves, and various fruit-bearing trees, as well as wells, springs, and streams of permanent water, building ruins, and surrounding, adjoining, and neighboring areas-whether cultivated or uncultivated, empty or full-together with its male and female settlers, and all dues related to acorns, grass, or any other rights that belong to the castle and are customarily paid to our holy Roman Church.
We fully confirm these to you, with all their belongings and adjacent areas, for the perpetual use and benefit of the monastery of Saint Benedict.
We firmly establish this for holding without any dues, including the river, starting from Petra Imperatoris straight to the bridge Terraneo.
It proceeds through channels to the lake below the monastery with its watermills, and then straight to Silicella and Saliceto, passing through the place called Mandra, with watermills there, and then descending through the bridge at Saint Angelo, likewise at Saint Peter, and then to the meadows of Ajano.
Similarly, another water source, called Cona, located in the same river, and the water called Flumicello, together with Augusta, Bullica, and Timida, all flowing into the aforementioned river, and up to the territory of Saint Cosmas; with all the banks and shores previously mentioned belonging entirely to both sides; along with all the waters of the place itself where watermills are made or can be made, or wherever fish can be caught in all the aforementioned waters.
Additionally, we grant you and your successors the church of Saint Felicitas, without any dues, to hold perpetually for the use and salary of your aforementioned venerable monastery.
The estate known as Lubenzana and Intermarana includes everything: farms, canals, and all its villages, no matter where they belong.
This includes the Canterano farm, Marano, Seminarum, Oricula, Arsula, Bulsinianum, Toccanellum, Marcatellum, the Paternum farm, the Aprunio farm, the Arpellum farm, the Lenanu farm, the Tessine farm, the mountains known as Gemini, descending into Trellano, Mount Gordiano, the Sassa farm, and the hill of Ferrari.
It also includes a small monastery, another small monastery, Piscano, and the Colony near Saint Valerius on both sides, and half of the ibex.
Additionally, it includes the Miniano farm, the Castaniola farm, Lorilliano, Saint Cecilia, the Boberanum farm, and the farm called Valle, with the church of Saint Eleutherius, as well as the farm called Capramolente with the church of Saint Anastasius.
The estate called Ampolloni, with the church of Saint Martin, is also part of it.
This includes the Paternum farm, known as Pentima, the Bruvano farm, the Saint Pamphili farm, the Danieli farm, the Merulana farm, the Paccano farm, and the Tospoliano farm with the church of Saint Mary and Saint Lucentius.
The Saint Cirici farm, the Cispa farm, and the Romani farm with the church of Saint Angel and Saint Felix are also included.
These are bordered on one side by the Tivertino River, on the second side by Papi, and on the third side by the Arco Fulgurati, descending on the mountain where there are cypresses, leading to the mountain called Bulturella, and straight through Saint Mary descending into Piscano.
Everything related to the aforementioned estate in its entirety is included, as well as the Caliscano farm in its entirety with the church of Saint Peter.
Furthermore, there's the monastery of Saint Barbara and Saint Anastasius, with two small enclosures-one in front and one behind-along with houses, lands, and farmsteads, including everything that belongs to them, located in the city of Tivoli.
Also, half of the church of Saint Mary in the same area, with houses, vineyards, lands, and all their belongings across the Tiber near the Marble Bridge, and a complete enclosure over the vineyard called Valle Arcese, and another over the vineyard with olive trees.
Then there's the church of Saint Sebastian, a small vineyard in front with an olive grove, and an enclosure of the vineyard located beneath the small gate of Tiburtina near the road called Quarrati.
Similarly, there's a complete enclosure over the vineyard known as Ortu Magno.
The land of Casaperta includes a small enclosure of the vineyard called Asorbo, and a portion in the greater Meadow, which originally belonged to Bishop Calvo.
The lands of Stafilanum, Romaniano, Patelini, Ozano, Criptule, Panzi, Diruti, Agnaniole, Macroniano, Semissano, Paternum, Vallelonga, Saint Mary in Pesile, Donabelli, Factoro, Lucu, Catacumba with the church of Saint Lawrence, and Afri-all these lands, completely located in the territories of Palestrina and Tivoli.
Additionally, the complete enclosure of the vineyard called Ancarano with the aforementioned trees; the land and vineyard called Pentuma, which belonged to Priest Tetualdo.
There are also two pieces of vineyard at Saint Lawrence in two locations; similarly, the land of Porclanicum completely with all its belongings; the lands of Otorano, Arcerano, Palasano, Cesuline, Olebano, Campelione, Ojano and Priano, Cammerano, Collemundum, Catilano, Cocubalo, Pacurano; and the church of Saint Michael with all its belongings, located in the smaller territory of Ferentinello; all these are in the territory of Campanino.
Furthermore, the Falconiano estate with the church of Saint Nicholas, the Fontiniano estate, Colle de Morelli, the Toccanellum estate, the Capla estate, the Oraro estate, the Gratuliano estate, the Cerviano estate, the Labezano estate, the Casanico estate, and the Domum estate with the church of Saint Peter; the Ponzia estate, and the Pozzorosano estate with a vineyard enclosure located next to Caranico, along with a valley of four bushels with its chestnut grove near Saint Peter, including lands, vineyards, houses, and forests spread across various locations in the territory of Aquila.
Similarly, in the territory of Albanense, there's the Sorano estate with vineyards, lands, crypts, and the church of the Four Saints; the Silva Majore estate; the portion that belonged to Bishop Floro; a piece of vineyard in Zizinni; and the complete enclosure of a vineyard located in the Cerasano estate.
Also, there are two small houses at the Salarum bridge, and a portion of Palmi with lands and gardens.
Two meadows near Porta Maggiore, along with two small houses, one in Pedica, called Burdunaria, and another in Campo Maggiore.
Similarly, there are complete houses with yards and gardens, and the church of Saint Theodore, located within the city of Rome near Porta Maggiore, just as they belonged to Bishop Floro.
Likewise, houses that belonged to John and Stephen of Griphi, with a yard, a pergola, and a small garden near the Claudia aqueduct.
And a completely enclosed vineyard with fruit trees, and crypts near the road leading to Jerusalem.
Similarly, a complete house with a yard, a small garden, and a vineyard, with everything associated with it, located in Rome, in the Seventh Region, where the church of Saint Vitus is situated.
Also, a vineyard or land near Jerusalem.
Additionally, the complete enclosure of a vineyard in Albano in the Zizinni estate, comprising six pieces; and a complete house with a small garden, located near Saint Martin.
Similarly, there's a house with a yard located in Sibura.
Likewise, the monastery of Saint Erasmus with all its surroundings or belongings, as contained in your command; also, two pieces of vineyard Inosti, one in the Mauri estate, and another in Calabriceto.
Next, let's discuss the cultivated and uncultivated meadow on the land of Aguzanu.
The properties mentioned above, along with all lands, hamlets, estates, churches, monasteries, houses, gardens, vineyards, male and female servants, tenants, and tenant women, rivers and water mills, fisheries, whether mentioned earlier or located in other regions or cities-wherever your venerable monastery holds and possesses them through any document of records, be it a decree, privilege, exchange, or donation, and everything that faithful Christians have given to your holy congregation for forgiveness of their sins-wherever you hold them in your monastery through records, both old and new, we firmly confirm to you and your successors through this apostolic decree to hold perpetually and eternally.
Moreover, we confirm to you one entire hamlet, called.
.
near Quartum, with its meadow within these boundaries: on the first side, the hamlet called Barbilianum, on the other side, the land of Munitula, extending from that meadow through its boundaries to the deserted walls beyond Formam, reaching the Public road, and on the third side, the same Public road; on the fourth side, the land called Decorita, with water flowing through its boundaries into the shape of Jovia, exiting through the shape, and returning through the boundary alongside the water, up to the aforementioned land of Barbilianum.
In addition, we confirm the entire land Sexto with its meadow near the stream within these boundaries: on one side, the road leading to the bridge of Adenona, and on the other side, the public road, and any other boundaries that may exist.
All places belonging to you and to our holy Roman Church, which we serve by the Lord's authority, are granted and confirmed to you and your successors through this apostolic privilege.
This includes all immovable locations with all their belongings, as previously mentioned, from the present first indiction and forever, for the use and benefit of that venerable monastery.
However, the priests and monks of that monastery must pray every day in the same church for the salvation of our soul and the souls of our successors, reciting one hundred "Lord, have mercy" and one hundred "Christ, have mercy."
The priests must offer sacred oblations during the solemnities of Mass three times each week for the forgiveness of our soul and the souls of our succeeding pontiffs to Almighty God.
We declare with apostolic authority, under divine judgment and anathema, that no one, whether any of our succeeding pontiffs or any other person, great or small, may dare or presume to act against, alienate, or remove any of the aforementioned immovable places with all their belongings and adjacencies, as previously mentioned, contrary to this our pontifical privilege.
Instead, we decree that it must remain firm and stable through perpetual and everlasting times, as we have established.
If anyone (which we do not wish) attempts to oppose this apostolic privilege and wishes to contradict or transgress it, let them know that by the authority of Almighty God and our Lord, the prince of the apostles, Peter, in whose role we serve, though undeserving, by the Lord's grace, they are bound by the chain of anathema and alienated from the kingdom of God.
But those who, with pious intent, act as true guardians and observers of this our apostolic privilege may deserve to obtain the rewards and grace of blessing and mercy from the righteous judge, our Lord God, and eternal life through the merits and prayers of blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, and Saint Benedict in the heavenly courts.
Written by Leo, secretary and notary of the holy supreme apostolic see, in the month of May, in the first indiction already mentioned.
Farewell well.
Given on May 10th by Marinus, bishop and librarian of the holy Polimartian Church of the supreme apostolic see, in the third year of the pontificate of our Lord John, the tenth supreme and universal Pope, at the most sacred seat of the blessed Apostle Peter, in the aforementioned first month and indiction.
Let the noble diploma, which is also kept in its archive, be added to enhance the greater ornament of the Sublacensian monastery.
Letter Eight: Rescript of Pope John XII for the Excommunication of Artaldus of Reims and Amblardus of Lyon, Archbishops, etc.
, for the Invasion of the Possessions of St.
Symphorian.
(Year Nine Hundred Fifty-Eight)
In the year 959 AD, during the third indiction, Emperor Michael ruled in Constantinople, Lord John held apostolic authority in Rome, and Lothair was King of the Franks.
During this time, an excommunication was sent to the archbishops of France and Burgundy.
It was addressed to Artald, Archbishop of the Church of Reims, and the bishops under his authority; to Amblard, Archbishop of the Church of Lyon; to Rodmund, Bishop of the Church of Autun; to Achard, Bishop of the see of Langres; to Frotgar, Bishop of the Church of Chalon; to Natran, Bishop of Nevers; and to Richard, Bishop of Auxerre.
This message concerns the land and property of Saint Faustus, Saint Augusta, and Saint Symphorian, located in the region of Provence, within the area known as Magna, which is held by Isuard and his associates through authority.
Excommunication.
By the authority of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, and by the order of all the saints, we hereby excommunicate and anathematize Isuard and all his companions who hold the land of Saint Symphorian.
After hearing this, let none of them enter the church, listen to Mass, make peace with a Christian, eat, drink, or sleep.
If they fall ill, they should not be visited; and if they die, they should not be buried or prayed for, unless they seek amendment and satisfaction.
Regarding the lands of Saint Symphorian located in the counties of Avignon and Cavaillon, Isuard eventually made amends to Girard, Bishop of Autun, on Tuesday, July 16, in the year of our Lord 972, during the fifteenth indiction, in the reign of King Conrad.
The restitution of matters situated in the bishopric of Cavaillon, made to Hugo, dean of the church of Saint Symphorian of Cavaillon and his clerics, was confirmed by Desiderius, Bishop of Cavaillon.
Letter Nine: Letter of Pope John Twelve to Saint Dunstan, Archbishop of Canterbury (Year Nine Hundred Sixty)
John, bishop and servant of the servants of God, sends his greetings to his fellow brother Dunstan, archbishop of the Church of Canterbury.
May you have enduring salvation in Christ for eternal life.
If shepherds are willing to face the sun and frost day and night to protect their flock, keeping a watchful eye so that none of the sheep go astray or fall prey to thieves, how much more should we, as spiritual shepherds, be vigilant for the salvation of souls?
Let us be diligent in our duty to guard the Lord's flock, ensuring that we do not flee in fear when danger comes, and so that on the day of divine judgment, we will not be found negligent, having been judged with honor above others.
Therefore, we fully affirm your primacy, expecting you to carry out the duties of the apostolic see as your predecessors did, just as it is recognized that the blessed Augustine and his successors, bishops of the aforementioned Church, have done.
We present the pallium to you, according to tradition, for celebrating the solemnities of the Mass.
You are permitted to use it as our predecessors decreed, with the privileges of your church remaining intact.
Your wisdom is well aware of this, and everyone knows how much the honor of the garment inspires awe through the moderation of actions.
These ornaments reflect your moral character, so that, with God as your guide, you may stand out and make your life a model for your followers.
In this way, they will be inspired to imitate what they see.
May the Holy Trinity surround your fraternity with its grace and guide you in the path of its fear, so that after the challenges of this life, we may together be deemed worthy to reach eternal sweetness.
This was written by the hand of Leo, the scribe of the apostolic see, in the month of October, in the fourth indiction, on the first day of the Kalends of October.
In the twelfth year of the supreme pontiff John.
Ten Privilege of Pope John the Twelfth for the Monastery of Saint Salvator of Fulda.
(Year Nine Sixty-One.)
John, bishop, servant of the servants of God, sends greetings to his beloved son Hatto, the venerable abbot of the esteemed monastery of our Lord Jesus Christ and Saint Boniface, martyr of Christ, located at Boconia on the bank of the Fulda River.
This message is for you and your successors, the abbots, forever.
Since it's always important to fulfill reasonable desires, it's only right that the devotion of someone who founds a pious establishment should be granted authority in giving privileges.
Therefore, because you have requested that the aforementioned monastery of Saint Salvator be granted the privileges of the apostolic seat, ensuring it remains under the jurisdiction of our Church, which we serve by the grace of God, and not under any other church's authority; we are pleased to grant this request by our authority.
Consequently, we forbid any priest from any other church to have authority or jurisdiction in the mentioned monastery, except for the apostolic seat.
No one should presume to celebrate the solemnity of masses there unless invited by the abbot of the monastery.
Also, to ensure that what is under the apostolic seat remains firmly established in both places and matters, whether currently held or to be acquired in the future through divine mercy, this venerable monastery shall continue to possess these rights through the gifts, offerings, and tithes of the faithful, without opposition from anyone, with perpetual firmness.
We hereby declare through this decree that anyone-whether a bishop of any Church or a person of any rank-who attempts to violate this charter, which we confirm by the authority of the chief of the apostles, shall be cursed and incur God's wrath, becoming an outcast from the company of all the saints.
Nevertheless, the dignity of the aforementioned monastery, granted by us, shall remain perpetually intact, supported by apostolic authority.
This was written by the hand of Leo, notary of the apostolic see, in the month of December, during the fifth indiction.
Issued on December 10th by the hand of John, bishop and librarian of the holy apostolic see, in the year of our Lord during the pontificate of the lord John, supreme pontiff and universal pope twelve, at the most holy seat of blessed Peter the apostle, in the sixth month of the fifth indiction.
Letter Eleven: Privilege of Pope John Twelve for the Church of Salzburg (Year Nine Hundred Sixty-Two)
This document confirms the privileges and possessions of the Church of Salzburg.
It grants the pallium to Archbishop Frederick at the request of Emperor Otto.
It also declares that Archbishop Herold, who has been blinded and deposed, will be excommunicated if he continues to perform sacred duties.
If priests, etc.
This was given on February 7th, through the hand of Andrew, treasurer of the holy apostolic seat, etc.
Letter 12: A letter from Pope John XII to the Archbishops, Bishops, Abbots, Clergy, and People of Gaul, Germany, and Bavaria in the year 962.
At the request of Emperor Otto I, he decrees that the monastery of Magdeburg should be elevated to an archbishopric, and the monastery of Merseburg should become a suffragan bishopric of the Church of Magdeburg.
John, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to the most reverent brothers, archbishops, bishops, abbots, monks, leaders, all clergy, and people in Gaul, Germany, and Bavaria.
Whenever the privilege of concession and confirmation is requested from the Holy Roman Church, which we serve by God's authority, for the advancement of new Christianity, we have deemed it worthwhile to grant it with all diligence and love.
Lest what ought to be generously granted towards pious desires is taken away by the deceitful enemy due to neglect.
Therefore, dearest brothers, we must strive with all our strength to ensure that Christianity, which Almighty God daily extends and advances through His servants with heavenly victory, is also strengthened and sustained by our assistance through Him.
Now, by the grace of God, our most beloved and Christian son Otto, having defeated barbarian peoples, namely the Avars and many others, approached the highest and universal seat, over which we preside by God's authority, to receive from us a triumphant crown of victory for the defense of the Holy Church of God, from blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles.
We welcomed him with paternal affection and anointed him as emperor with the blessing of blessed Peter for the defense of the Holy Church of God.
And when we were discussing in the church of blessed Peter the apostle concerning the state and governance of all Christianity, considering what is useful according to God, the aforementioned most pious Emperor Otto informed our paternity how he had newly established in the Catholic faith the Slavs, whom he had conquered, earnestly pleading and requesting that the sheep he had acquired in Christ might not be dominated by the cunning of the ancient serpent due to the absence of a shepherd.
In response to this request, dear brothers, we have given our approval as is only right.
With all our hearts, let's ensure this new foundation is built on the rock, Christ, at the mountaintop.
He who desires no one to perish will provide strength.
With His gracious consent, we wish and thus decree, through this document of privilege, that the monastery of Magdeburg in the Saxon kingdom, near the Elbe, which the most holy emperor established for new Christianity due to its proximity to the people of those regions, be elevated to an archiepiscopal seat, capable of guiding and governing the entire flock of God through subordinate suffragans.
We wish and through this document of privilege, we command that the monastery of Merseburg, which the pious emperor dedicated to God after defeating the Hungarians, be raised to an episcopal seat, subordinate to the seat of Magdeburg, because so many people cannot be governed by a single shepherd.
We wish and by the privilege of our authority, decree that the tribute and tithing of all the peoples, whom the pious emperor baptized or will be baptized by him, his son the king, and their successors with God's blessing, be allocated and subjected to Magdeburg, Merseburg, or any future seat they choose, by them and their successors.
We also wish, dear brothers, and by the command of the blessed Apostle Peter, we order that the archbishops of Mainz, Trier, Cologne, Salzburg, and Hamburg, be steadfast supporters with all their heart and strength for the elevation of the Magdeburg monastery to an archiepiscopal seat and the Merseburg monastery to an episcopal seat.
When Almighty God, through His servant, the most invincible emperor, his son the king, and their successors, led the neighboring Slavic people to embrace the Christian faith, we aimed to establish bishoprics in suitable locations as opportunities arose.
We seek to have bishops consecrated by the Archbishop of Magdeburg as suffragans, with the consent of the aforementioned individuals, their archbishops, and successors.
However, if the sons of our most pious emperor, and the successors of his son the king, attempt to break these statutes, or if the bishops of the mentioned churches, along with others and their successors, do not support or agree with the Archbishop of Magdeburg, his successors, and their suffragans, may they be struck with the sword of excommunication and face eternal damnation from the supreme judge.
Therefore, may Almighty God grant our most serene emperor Otto and his son, the king, who is spiritually our son, a long life, so that living peacefully in this world, they may receive the palm of unfading glory in the next.
Written by the hand of Leo, notary of the Holy Apostolic See, in the month of February, in the 5th indiction.
Given on February 12th by the hand of George, deputy notary of the Holy Apostolic See, in the year of our Lord's favor during the pontificate of our lord John, the seventh supreme pontiff and universal pope, in the 1st year of the reign of our most pious lord Augustus Otto, crowned by God, the great emperor, in the aforementioned month and indiction.
Letter 13.
This is a letter from Pope John the Twelfth to Henry, the Archbishop of Trier.
It's a fragment from the year 962.
The Pope reinstates the use of the pallium to him.
John, servant of the servants of God, addresses the most beloved and most reverend Henry, Archbishop of the holy Church of Trier, granting this privilege only during the days of his life.
Issued on the eighth of January, delivered by Leo, the official of the holy apostolic seat, during the pontificate of Lord John, the supreme pontiff and universal pope, the twelfth.
This occurred at the most sacred seat of the blessed Peter the apostle, on the second day of January, in the fifteenth indiction, in the year of our Lord's incarnation nine hundred fifty-seven.
Letter Fourteen The Privilege of Pope John the Twelfth for the Monastery of Saints Stephen, Dionysius, and Sylvester in Rome, Year Nine Hundred Sixty-Two.
John, bishop, servant of the servants of God, extends greetings to our beloved son in the Lord, the appointed abbot Theofilact, and to the venerable monastery of Dionysius and Sylvester, known as Cata Pauli, and to your successors as abbots forever.
It is fitting for apostolic leadership to support those who excel in pious religion with kind compassion and to eagerly grant approval to those who seek it.
By doing so, we earn a reward from the Creator of all, the Lord, or receive pardon if venerable places of saints are undoubtedly improved.
Therefore, since your devotion humbly requested from the apostolate that we grant and confirm to you the aforementioned monastery with all its churches, buildings, and appurtenances, both within and around it.
This includes the entire mountain called Augusto, with the church of Saint Michael at the summit, along with the vineyards and lands surrounding the same mountain, and the entire church of Saint Nicholas with all its appurtenances.
The boundaries are as follows: on one side, the public road leading under the arch and the aqueduct called Virginis; on the second side, the same aqueduct and the mountain called Pinei; on the third side, the walls of the city of Rome and the gate of Saint Valentine; and on the fourth side, the city wall extending to the ancient Posterula once known as Saint Agatha's.
And the road from the same Posterula, which goes next to the aforementioned church, and the public road leading under the arch located in the fifth region of Rome.
Also, beyond the mentioned aqueduct and lands with their buildings, as they appear to be held by the same monastery, with the land within Archiones beneath the vineyard of John, formerly a great bishop.
There's a grand marble column named Antoninus, beautifully adorned, with the Church of Saint Andrew at its base.
The surrounding land is encircled by a public road within the city of Rome.
Similarly, there are two churches, one larger and one smaller, named Saint Mary, situated in front of the gate of the mentioned monastery.
The Church of Saint Hippolytus, along with its belongings, is located outside this area, as is the Church of Saint Anastasius, which has a well behind it and its belongings.
Additionally, there's the Church of Saint Stephen, known as "of the Field," and the Church of Saint Mary, located in the area called Arciones.
The Church of Saint John is located in Pinea with its belongings.
We also affirm the entire monastery of Saint Valentine, including all its buildings and nearby properties, which are all situated outside the gate also named Saint Valentine, under the authority of the aforementioned venerable monastery.
Moreover, we confirm the entire Milvian Bridge, with all its entrances and exits, donations, or tributes.
Similarly, the sowing land located outside the gate of Saint Valentine, next to the walls of Rome, is on the left side between the boundary of the first side of the ditch, which is a coal pit between the wall and the land, extending to the Tiber River.
On the second side is the river itself, on the third side is the public road leading to and from Saint Valentine, and on the fourth side... under the jurisdiction of the Holy Roman Church.
On the hill, there's another sowing land with its gardens at the entrance, along with everything related to it.
In that place, with their own right hand, they approach Saint Valentine, where the large arch lies beneath the land known as Passaranum, along with the complete fish pond.
This pond is bordered on the first side by the public road previously mentioned, and on the second side by the communal fresh water spring, situated between the aforementioned monastery and Gregory Mansonario of the school of confession of the blessed apostle Peter.
From there, it directly leads up to the beginning of the ancient wall, bordered on the third side by the land of the venerable monastery of Saint Cyriacus, located on the Via Lata, and continues through the boundary, upwards through the Plain of the Hill called Bossetulo, exiting onto the Via Flaminia.
We indeed confirm for you the entire estate known as Girulo, with its various trees and everything it encompasses, as it appears to belong to you according to the series of documents located outside the gate of Saint Valentine, about 1 mile from the city of Rome.
This estate is bordered on one side by the public road, the ancient stone road that descends to Sanguinaria, and on the second side by the Formello of fresh water, which exits under the hill of this Girulo or the meadow of the aforementioned Saint Cyriacus.
On the third side, it is bordered by the mentioned Monastery of Saint Valentine, or the sowing land of your monastery's right, which the heirs of Roman from the Field of Mars hold on the fourth side.
Similarly, we confirm for you an entire estate called Pelajolo, complete with its arable lands, fields, meadows, pastures, and mountains, which includes the church of Saint Sylvester located in the wilderness, along with everything generally associated with it.
This estate was once part of the aforementioned venerable monastery, given in exchange through the charter of exchange by Alberic, a former Roman senator, in which he and his brothers, namely Constantius, a noble man, and Sergius, bishop of the holy Nepesinae Church, signed with their own hands, along with Berta and another Berta, concerning the valley of Saint Vitus, located in the venerable monastery outside the Salarian gate at a distance of .
.
Along the Tiber River, on one side, sits the estate of Gorgini, surrounded by relatives.
On the second side is the Tiber River itself, where vineyards now flourish, and a meadow belonging to the venerable monastery of Saint Basil.
Nearby, there's another land with a meadow also belonging to Saint Basil's monastery.
The land and its meadow from Gregory at Capo Marzo lie here.
On the third side, there's the estate with five columns, known as Molario.
On the fourth side, we confirm the entire estate called Gallorum, Balleolum, and Pacianum, or whatever other names they originally had.
Once, through a donation deed to your aforementioned monastery, it included arable lands, sand caves, fields, pastures, meadows, buildings, ruins, adjacent mountains, plains, wells, springs, both cultivated and uncultivated, and all that belongs to it, located outside.
.
about one from the bridge.
Among relatives on one side is an estate that once belonged to Rose, now occupied.
On the second side, there's an old wall, and land that once belonged to Azzon's chapel, now held by Elpizo, a nobleman.
On the third side is the land of Stephen from Theodore.
Nearby is the cave called Serpentarico, with another vacant land next to it belonging to the monastery of Saint Vitus.
Indeed, there are also two complete pieces of arable land next to that estate above the cave, belonging to the monastery of Saint Vitus.
Similarly, outside.
.
Nument.
there is a complete estate called Lampati with everything that belongs to it.
We also confirm to you one complete estate called Aguziano, located outside the Matra bridge.
Furthermore, we confirm to you three complete estates, including one called the bridge of Ninth, with various arable lands, trees, or sand caves, deserted ruins covered with Sinino work, cultivated and uncultivated, along with everything that belongs to it, located at the aforementioned bridge.
John, known as the Latin Way, is about 9 miles from the city of Rome.
On the first side, it is bordered by the Claudia aqueduct and the bridge called Nono.
The second side features the structure known as Ebeberatorium, the third side includes the estate of Morene, and the fourth side is adjacent to the crypt called Ardenda, under the jurisdiction of the Holy Roman Church.
Additionally, there's another estate called Dominicalia, which includes a deserted church with its gardens and ruins, both cultivated and uncultivated, along with everything associated with it.
It's located on the Latin Way next to the Ponte de Nono estate.
On one side, it's bordered by the estate itself, on the second side by a stream called Papati, on the third side by a public road with ancient paving stones, and on the fourth side by the major structure and an estate called Seven Vats.
This includes another complete estate with various places and names, such as the valley Manciaria, the precious house, the hill called Paulelli, and the field known as Albanensis, all with their lands, crops, forests, various trees, and water mills.
There's a deserted church named Saint Peter located on the Latin Way about 10 miles from the city of Rome.
On one side, there's arable land where meadows once known as Pauli existed, the second side borders the Civitella estate, the third side is alongside the public road leading to a place called Saint Peter's Cell, and the fourth side features a deserted church named Saint Mary in the Diaconia.
From there, it descends through the trench to the major structure, or by whatever other names they may be known, under the jurisdiction of the venerable monastery of the holy apostles Andrew and Bartholomew, known as Honorius.
Indeed, there's a complete church called Saint Angel with vineyards and lands around it located in the Albanensi territory, approximately.
.
miles from the city of Rome.
On Crescentuli Hill, including all the vineyards with their entrance and path to the winepress, located in the Alban territory at a place known as Cassa Nova.
Additionally, there are four complete sections of vineyards with their path, winepress, and entrance in the same territory at a place called Jusi, and also a vineyard with its path, winepress, and entrance from the Ariccia territory, located at Cucurti.
We also grant you the estate known as Zinziomi, which includes the church of Saint Mary, vineyards, lands, a water mill, and cellars, as you currently possess them in the Alban territory, situated about 13 miles from Rome.
Furthermore, there are two sections of vineyards in a place called Honorii, within the Ariccia territory.
Moreover, in the mentioned Ariccia territory, at a location known as Cosmedi, at the base of the main road, which belongs to the venerable diaconate of Saint Mary.
Similarly, we grant and confirm to you half of a salt pan in a place called Fossatum Major, as it was given to you through various documents from the heirs of the former lord known as Cacoinbucte.
Likewise, there is another complete salt pan called Saint Sylvester located at Campo Major, belonging to the same aforementioned monastery.
We also confirm to you two entire mills on the Tiber River, near the School of the Frisians, as this water mill was once given to you by Alto Amaro, along with another complete mill with its equipment, entrance, and all fittings, as you currently hold it, or as it was from our predecessor, the most holy Pope Agapitus.
By the authority of this privilege, we have granted and confirmed to you the rights over the Tiber River mentioned earlier, before the dam, along with the water behind it for building another water mill.
This is located between the adjacent properties:
On one side, the water mill of Saint Mary on the Capitol and the water mill of Leo the protoseminarist;
On the second side, half of the river itself;
On the third side, the water mill of Theophylactus, known as Numenculario, and the water mill from the monastery of Saint Cyriacus on the Via Lata;
And on the fourth side, the public road, which falls under the jurisdiction of the monastery called Saint Terentianus in its entirety, along with all its listed cells, namely those of Saint Stephen and Saint Mary, as well as the cell of Saint Benedict, Saint Sylvester, and Saint Val.
Along with all their properties located in the territory of Polimarciense, under the jurisdiction of the venerable monastery of Saint Lawrence, the martyr of Christ.
Especially when the intercessions of the saints strengthen the work of Christ during the night.
Therefore, since your holiness has asked us to confirm to you, in honor of God and our Savior Jesus Christ, the properties of Curilianus with all their belongings, we return to the aforementioned monastery the estate called Ortana, or by whatever other name it is known, which we acknowledge was taken from our monastery for two years.
Considering the mercy and needs of the venerable monastery, motivated by love for Almighty God and for the salvation of our souls, as well as for the support of the brother monks, we return and confirm to you and your successors forever the aforementioned estate in its entirety, together with its hamlets, namely Mojana, Tojana, Occiana, Antiquina, Suranco, Betruano, the hamlet of Pingiano, Terenzano, Centum Cellae, Coriliano (or Catiliano or Camilliano), Pozanelle, Genbriano, Collicello, Julianello, Sepuliano, the well, the hamlet of Fuficanum with streams and waters, and with houses, vineyards, lands, and forests, fields.
.
Pastures, willow groves, both fruit-bearing and non-fruit-bearing trees, wells, springs, streams of perpetual water, ancient buildings, and ruins with their surroundings, cultivated or uncultivated lands with their watermills, along with male and female tenants, and everything that belongs entirely to the estate called Ortana, or by any other name they might be known.
We also grant and confirm to you a church named after Saint Juvenalis, along with its lands, woods, olive groves, and all trees, whether cultivated or not, all located in the previously mentioned territory of Ortana, approximately 50 miles from the city of Rome.
Furthermore, we establish for you the city of Ortana with houses belonging to the aforementioned church of Saint Juvenalis, and all immovable properties that fall under the jurisdiction of the venerable monastery, both within the city of Ortana and throughout its surrounding territory.
We also confirm to you the entire property of Paternum with all its assets, including houses, vineyards, lands, woods, meadows, willow groves, and everything that wholly belongs to it, both within and beyond, located in the aforementioned territory of Ortana.
Its borders are defined on one side by small houses, on the second side by a flowing river, on the third side by Coreliano, and on the fourth side by the property of the Pinatori and Septiniano.
Furthermore, we establish for you all immovable properties under the jurisdiction of your aforementioned monastery, within the city of Gallesana, and throughout its territory, or in these three estates called Cazanum, Pusiniam, and Cesa Narniense.
Indeed, we also grant you the estate called Preciliano with everything that generally belongs to it, located in the territory of Savinensi, under the jurisdiction of the Holy Roman Church, bordered on one side by the estate called Paura, on the second side by the stream of Utriculo known as Butino, on the third side by the property of the monastery of Saint Mary, and on the fourth side by the property of the monastery of Saint Salvator.
Indeed, we also confirm the matters of jurisdiction and those rightfully belonging to your monastery in the Nepetino territory, including Casa Mala, which is on the land known as Casa Nova and Bobarica, as well as Boltejano.
This includes the servants and maidservants residing there, who already belong to your monastery.
Furthermore, we confirm the assets that rightfully belonged to you through the documents of the same monastery in the Alto territory, once belonging to Amaro.
Likewise, we confirm the entire estate called Paccianum, with all its appurtenances, located in the Sutrino territory, including the cell of Saint George and its appurtenances in the aforementioned Sutrino territory.
Similarly, we confirm all matters that pertain to the rights of your aforementioned monastery in the Collinense territory, in the place called Vallis and Tintorissi, on the mountain called Arca, as well as in Saint Cassano and in Curte, and in Baccaricio.
This includes vineyards and arable lands, forests with its large marsh, along with houses and tenants and tenant women residing anywhere belonging to your aforementioned monastery.
All of the above-mentioned immovable properties are under the jurisdiction of our holy Roman Church and the aforementioned monastery or other pious places of any kind.
Inclined by your prayers, for the salvation of souls through intercession, we confirm the inviolable stability of the aforementioned monastery.
Through this perpetual decree, we affirm the aforementioned estate called Ortana, with its vineyards and lands, small farms and mills, and all the tenants, tenant women, their sons and daughters residing there, along with the complete church of Saint Juvenalis located nearby, as well as the aforementioned Paterno in its entirety with all its appurtenances as read above from the present fifth indiction in perpetuity.
We grant and confirm to you, and to your mentioned monastery, the right to maintain and protect everything that needs improvement or defense without any disturbance.
Make sure it is managed so that no count, steward, or anyone else, regardless of rank, can diminish, alienate, or present any document for legal action against the monastery regarding any part of the land, church property, or the families living there.
If anyone under our apostolic authority tries to litigate against the monastery concerning the mentioned land or church, we declare it null and void because it is unjust and against the law.
By apostolic authority and under divine judgment, we decree, with the interdict of Saint Peter the Apostle, that none of our successors or any other person of great status may dare to impose upon the named land, church, vineyards, lands, or all its belongings.
Instead, it should remain for the benefit and use of the monastery, supporting and sustaining the monks residing there for all time.
If anyone presumptuously ignores this apostolic confirmation issued by us, let them know they are bound by the anathema of our Lord's apostle Peter, alienated from the kingdom of God, and condemned to eternal fire with the devil and his most terrible followers, as well as with Judas, the betrayer of Jesus Christ, and cast into the abyss of hell with the wicked.
But whoever, with pious intent, acts as a guardian, obedient and observant of this saving decree of our confirmation, may they be worthy of receiving the blessing and grace of heavenly reward and eternal joy under our just judge, the Lord our God.
Written by Leo, a notary of the Holy Roman Church, in March during the fifth indiction.
Farewell.
Issued on the eighth day of March by John, bishop and librarian of the holy apostolic see, in the seventh year of the pontificate of our Lord John, the supreme pontiff and universal pope, twelfth in the sacred see of the blessed apostle Peter.
I, Cirinus, notary of the Holy Roman Church, found in the parchment privilege of Bishop John, neither added nor removed anything.
I wrote and faithfully copied it: Thanks be to God.
I, John, son of Lawrence Angel of the City, notary by the authority of the Holy Roman prefecture, at the request of the religious and honorable Lady Jacoba de Comite, abbess of the monastery of Saint Sylvester of the Head, found in the document or written copy by Cirinus, formerly a notary of the Holy Roman Church.
This was faithfully taken from the parchment privilege, as I was able to perceive, faithfully copied, and rendered into public form from that copy, which appears in the Limentana Letter, also known as the Beneventan Letter.
With the learned men, especially the venerable Lord John, bishop of Nepi, vicar general of the lord pope in the City, and in the presence of John of All Saints, John son of Lawrence, Peter son of Lawrence, James son of Nicholas, All Saints, and Francis son of Lawrence Mancini, notaries as requested witnesses.
Unless by chance a letter or syllable by error not .
.
which could change the truth of the said instrument, it was faithfully rendered into public form, as requested, in the year of our Lord 1318, under the pontificate of Lord John, the twenty-second pope, first indiction, on the 26th day of April.
Fifteen Privilege of Pope John the Twelfth for the Monastery of Saint Peter in Bivore, Year Nine Sixty-Three.
The monastery of Saints Peter, John, Vitus, Stephen, and Agatha in Bivore, founded by Count Billingo, is placed under the jurisdiction of the one apostolic seat.
Its properties are confirmed with the condition that a reasonable payment of one pound of silver is offered on the altar of Saint Peter by him and his successors every fifteen years.
With the highest apostolic authority.
The sixteenth letter of Pope John the Twelfth to the bishops of the Roman Synod, from the year 963.
We have heard that you wish to appoint another pope.
If you proceed with this, I excommunicate you by the power of Almighty God, preventing you from ordaining anyone or celebrating Mass.
Doubts
Letter Seventeen: Letter of Pope John the Twelfth to John the Archpriest, John the Second, and John the Third, Priests (Year Nine Hundred Fifty-Seven)
John, Bishop, servant of the servants of God, to the beloved sons in Christ: the devoted Archpriest John, and the devoted priests John the Second and John the Third, along with their brothers and your successors forever.
Apostolic guidance should support those who excel in pious devotion with compassionate kindness and grant the desired agreement to those who seek it.
This is particularly important because a reward is kept with God, the creator of all things, when venerable places are properly organized and undoubtedly improved.
Since you have asked us to grant and confirm to you and your successors that the church of Saint Tryphon, martyr of Christ, be protected and free from all conditions with all its belongings, which has been newly built by Crescentius, the noble prefect of Rome, or by the other neighbors of the church.
Indeed, through the intervention of our esteemed prefect, Crescentius, we confirm this church to you and your successors with this privilege of our authority, so that you may remain there perpetually and continually offer praises to the eternal God.
From the present fifth indiction, we grant it to you and your successors to hold.
On the day of the sacred dedication of this church, when we placed the most holy body of the blessed Tryphon, martyr, there with our own hands, we declared that just as other Catholic churches within Rome are honorable, so is this one.
It is fitting that we serve Saint Tryphon, martyr, with utmost devotion, and that the church under his name, dedicated by us and our successors to Almighty God, should receive due honor.
At the appointed procession or station, the choir of our sacred palace should gather there.
The excellent martyr offered his body to God through various punishments, earning the crown of the heavenly kingdom.
If he sees us devoted in his service, through his intervention, we will be able to escape the punishment of hell.
Such a noble task is not reserved for him alone, especially since his sanctuary, which has existed for a short time, is built on a distinguished foundation, raised in height, and extended in width.
What previously seemed narrow and unsightly now, with divine grace leading, appears bright and beautiful.
Just as this sanctuary was completed to honor Almighty God and the most precious martyr Tryphon, so will all who helped in its construction find splendid and well-decorated homes in the heavenly homeland.
The eminent martyr himself rejoices with Christ, and all his servants who offer him grateful services will also rejoice.
As the benefits of our Redeemer increase daily within us, many services should be performed by us for his church.
May God be glorified through us, his servants, so that the holy martyr, for whose love it was constructed, may lead his devoted servants to eternal glory.
We also affirm for you and your Church of Saint Tryphon the oratory built in honor of Saint Stephen the first martyr, along with the books and decorations of this oratory, the portico next to it, and the vacant land around it for burial.
We confirm for you the entire area called "a Pila," with the pila itself located within the Tiber River in that area, including water for building a water mill and the bank of that area.
May you receive from there the bank tax from the area of Saint Lucia to the area of Saint Martin, along with all things pertaining to this oratory.
The property in the Campomartis region is situated next to the gate and is bordered on one side by a marker and relatives.
The second side is next to the riverbed, the third side is adjacent to the city wall and John the caretaker's house, and the fourth side is along the public road.
The noble Crescentius, the esteemed prefect of the city, donated and granted the oratory of Saint Stephen the Proto-Martyr to you and your church through a deed of donation.
We hereby grant and confirm this to you and your church forever, free and secure from any conditions imposed by other churches, whether temporal or spiritual, along with all its parish, holdings, and appurtenances, as previously stated.
We also wish and, by apostolic authority, command that none of our successors, who may serve in the place of Blessed Peter, the Prince of the Apostles, shall alter or violate this privilege of our concession and confirmation under any pretext or deceit.
If anyone, though we do not foresee it, should rashly attempt to oppose this apostolic privilege or presume to break it in any way, and does not adhere to the terms outlined above, let them be aware that, unless they repent, they are bound by the authority of Almighty God and of Blessed Peter and Paul, and by our authority as their vicar, to be tied with the chain of excommunication and alienated from the kingdom of God, to be burned with the devil and his dreadful hordes, along with Judas, the betrayer of our Lord Jesus Christ, in the fire of eternal punishment.
But whoever, with pious intentions, acts as a guardian and observer of this apostolic constitution of privilege, may they be worthy of obtaining the grace of blessing from the just judge, our Lord God and Savior Jesus Christ, and from His holy mother, the Virgin Mary, and eternal life with all the saints and chosen of God, forever and ever.
Amen.
Letter Eighteen: Bull of Pope John Twelve for the Monastery of Volturno St.
Vincent. Year Nine Hundred Sixty-Two.
John, bishop and servant of the servants of God, sends greetings to the venerable Abbot Paul and the monastery of Saint Vincent, martyr of Christ, located above the source of the Volturno River in Samnium, within the territory of Benevento.
This message is also for your successors who will be regularly appointed in the same venerable monastery, forever.
We are deeply committed to ensuring that all churches of God and holy places do not suffer from any lack of necessities, but instead thrive with their own resources.
Therefore, it is our duty to ensure the stability and integrity of these venerable places with complete pastoral dedication and to provide them with support for their benefit.
What is offered to these venerable places in honor of His holy name, for the praise and glory of His divine majesty, is acceptable to us and deserving of full mercy in His presence.
Such a pious work may receive a reward in heavenly actions.
Therefore, because you have asked us to protect the monastery of the blessed Vincent, the martyr, situated above the Volturno River in the Benevento territory, in the parts of Samnium, along with its dependencies and monasteries, namely the monastery of the blessed Peter the Apostle located near the Sabbato River, in the aforementioned Benevento territory.
Also included are the monastery of the Holy Mother of God, Mary, in the place called Sano; the monastery of the Savior, our Lord Jesus Christ, located in Alife; and the monastery in honor of Saint Mary, built in the territory of Marsi, in the place called Apinianici.
Furthermore, we grant you and your successors, the future abbots, the monastery of Saint Maurus within the county of Atina, along with another monastery dedicated to Saint Mary, the Mother of God, located in the territory of Penne in a place called Marano.
Additionally, another monastery in honor of Saint Mary, the Mother of God, at a place known as Two Basilicas, along with other monasteries, cells, estates, and houses, as well as the men and women servants residing there, with all their belongings, are granted to you and your successors.
These are to be held under the jurisdiction of our holy church, which we serve with God's help, and not to fall under the jurisdiction of any other church.
Therefore, in support of these pious desires, we grant by our authority what you request.
Thus, we grant you and your successors, the abbots, the permission from our apostolic seat to have the power to invite any bishop you choose into the mentioned venerable monastery for the needs of Christians, to consecrate churches, and to perform ordinations of subdeacons and deacons over time, fulfilling every ecclesiastical rank there as needed.
We also declare that no bishop should summon a subdeacon to his synod unless it is his own wish, nor should he judge or excommunicate an abbot or monk in any manner.
We also wish to impose apostolic authority on you and your successors, the abbots who will be ordained over time, that if priests or clerics from any church come to join the brotherhood, or if they choose to adopt the monastic habit, they should be immediately accepted.
You are always allowed to obtain chrism and confirmation from any bishop you wish, as we have stated, under our apostolic authority.
We prohibit any priest from any church from having jurisdiction or authority over the aforementioned venerable monastery, except for the apostolic seat, unless invited by the monastery's abbot.
No one should presume to celebrate masses there without such an invitation.
We further decree, under apostolic censure and the threat of divine judgment, as well as severe and formidable anathemas, that no one of any rank should presume to take authority over the venerable monastery or its matters, or to take or alienate its properties, possessions, or churches, or anything belonging to them, in any way.
Nor should anyone inflict any harm or inconvenience during times of peace or barbarian invasions, since we have decreed that the monastery should remain under the firm stability of our holy church's jurisdiction during both peace and barbarian times, as stated.
We also declare, by the authority of the blessed apostles, in front of God and His terrifying future judgment, through this page of our apostolic privilege and decree, that the places exchanged or granted by any abbots to you in the venerable monastery of Saint Vincent, martyr of Christ, as well as other possessions granted or offered by kings, dukes, or any Christians, or those granted there in the future, should remain under the firm stability of the jurisdiction of the aforementioned monastery and remain perpetually.
No one should have the permission, as stated, to cause any trouble or take away what was given to it from the monastery's properties.
These should remain inviolate according to the apostolic institutions and privileges associated with these venerable places.
The monks of the congregation should always have the right to elect their abbot.
The abbot himself should have the authority to judge his monks, whether they're from a male monastery or even a female one under his jurisdiction.
However, if anyone dares to boldly oppose what we've established for the glory of God and the stability of this revered monastery, or if they wish to transgress in any way, let them be bound by excommunication and consigned to eternal fire with the devil, his most atrocious followers, and Judas, the betrayer of our Lord Jesus Christ.
But truly, whoever faithfully observes all these things with a pious intent, keeping our apostolic decree aimed at the worship of God, may they receive an abundance of blessings from our most merciful Lord God and be deemed worthy to share in eternal life.
Farewell.
Written by the hand of Benedict, scribe of the holy Roman Church, in the month of July, in the fifth indiction, at the most sacred site of the blessed apostle Peter, in the eighth year of the pontificate of Lord John.
LETTER FROM POPE JOHN TO KING AEDRED OF THE ENGLISH (Year 955-63).
This letter encourages the protection of the privileges of the oldest monastery of Saints Peter and Paul in Canterbury.
JOHN, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to AEDRED, most excellent king, and to all bishops, dukes, counts, abbots, and the entire faithful people of the English nation, dearest greetings and apostolic blessing.
With a zeal for promoting divine worship, we are always focused on the stability of venerable places.
Our hope is that through the devoted efforts of souls dedicated to Christ, who have chosen to serve there during their lives, they can continue undisturbed under regular rule.
We want the structures built for God's praise and religious worship to remain steadfast.
Therefore, I urge you, illustrious king and dearest son, along with all our spiritual sons of the mentioned people, to carefully regard the monastery established among you in honor of the blessed apostles, the prince Peter and the teacher of nations Paul.
Ensure that no one, regardless of status, faces disturbances.
And that the abbot and monks serving God there may have your full support and freely possess whatever belongs to their rights.
This will help them lead their lives more effectively in holy conduct.
When the time comes that the abbot passes away, someone from the same community, chosen with common counsel, should be appointed and consecrated there to take charge.
No bishop should seize any authority there, nor presume to celebrate their Mass unless invited by the abbot.
This is in line with what our predecessors, worthy of God, have granted to the same Church in their apostolic rights and privileges.
To prevent anyone from opposing with reckless actions, we have also taken care to add our writings, backed by apostolic authority.
This monastery was the first to be graced with the presence of holy monks from the very start of your Church's rise.
It was built from the ground up by Aethelbert, the most Christian king, who was brought to the faith of Christ by blessed Augustine, a disciple of the revered Gregory, through the encouragement of the same Father, your apostle Augustine.
He appointed Peter, a monk sent from this apostolic seat, to be the abbot over monks who feared the Lord.
There, following Gregory's command, Father Augustine chose a place for the king himself, his successors, and archbishops, where their remains would await the day of resurrection.
If anyone tries to defile or destroy this holy purpose, let them know they are bound by apostolic authority with the chain of anathema and will suffer eternal fire alongside Judas, the traitor of the Lord.
Therefore, we command the canons of the monastery of St.
Savior who reside there not to disturb this holy commitment in any way.
If they do, let them face the same anathema.
In Christ, may you, my lord son, be well with all of yours.
Given on the tenth day before the Kalends of May, in the eleventh year of the reign of our most pious lord, Emperor Otto, in the eleventh indiction.
Twenty To the clergy of England.
(Years 955-63.)
He confirms the privileges of the monastery of Saints Peter and Paul.
John, bishop, servant of the servants of God, sends greetings and apostolic blessings to Eadred, most excellent king of the English, and to our beloved son Odo, archbishop of the Church of Canterbury, along with all the bishops, dukes, counts, abbots, and faithful people of the English nation.
Among your sacred faith's illustrious virtues, which you, most excellent son, and the kings under you, with your nobles and people, have embraced in submitting to the Christian religion, we especially cherish this warmth of your charity.
This seeks to confirm through us the ancient dignity and freedom of the monastery in the suburbs of Canterbury, dedicated to the chief apostles Peter and Paul by Augustine, the first teacher and apostle of the English, and founded by Aethelberht, the first Christian king of the English, beloved by God.
It is where, by apostolic authority, the bodies of the kings and archbishops of Canterbury will be buried in perpetuity.
Your royal eminence requests that we confirm this as it was sanctioned by your predecessors, the kings, and our predecessors, the pontiffs, with the privileges described by the apostles.
Therefore, we gratefully decree that this apostolic Church, considered by you as the first-born in the grace of the chief apostles, shall be the primary mother among all other monasteries in your kingdom that exist now or will arise in future generations.
By royal and apostolic confirmation, it will be free from all secular servitude, ensuring that no bishop or successor of your kings will harm or disturb it in any way.
No occasion for servitude shall ever be demanded from any of its properties, even in the slightest way, so that under its king, as a defender, not a tyrant, it may serve Christ alone freely.
To our beloved son and fellow priest of the Church of Canterbury, Odo, we instruct, in the name of the blessed apostles and the chief Peter, that he should not use the pride of leadership but instead offer the service of love where it is needed.
He should regard the abbot as a Roman legate and fellow minister of the Gospel of peace, considering him a brotherly companion, not a subordinate, in all things, just as the holy and God-beloved sons of the apostolic see, Archbishop Theodore and Abbot Adrian, did.
Let no one seize control of this Church, nor should anyone assume any role (except for the ordination of the abbot) without his approval and that of the brothers.
No one should take or do anything from its closest and specific places, parishes, or in any privilege of its right without the abbot's consent, so that no abuse may disturb the peace of the Lord's flock.
Those who cause such scandal would be better off sunk with a millstone in the depths.
The abbot should also be considered the first among the rest, so that he may lead his brothers affectionately rather than imperiously, as the firstborn and in the place of Rome, towards the unity of holy faith, love, and harmony.
Therefore, we affirm that these and other matters, whether by you or your predecessors, or by you, or your successors, or by any persons, will be observed by all the kings, princes, and people of Britain according to your request until the end.
Let no one who acts against this (God forbid) be cut off by the sword of excommunication of Saint Peter, the chief of the apostles, and perish, but rather let those who support the Church be admitted by its key and rejoice in the kingdom.