Commentary on the Revelation of Saint John
by Primasius of Hadrumetum
Book Two
The solemnity of the sealed book with seven seals, its acceptance, and the vision of its revelation are recalled.
The inspection of the white horse is narrated with the opening of the first seal.
The red horse with the second seal, and the black horse with the third seal, are mentioned.
The pale horse with the fourth seal.
With the fifth seal, the souls of the martyrs are found under the altar of God.
An earthquake, the darkening of the sun, the moon turning to blood, and the falling stars.
Four angels are described as holding the four corners of the earth.
The number of those marked from each tribe is mentioned.
An innumerable multitude from all nations is foretold.
The Lamb in the midst of the throne will rule them.
The law of God can be understood in three ways, or even more, but it must be known through correct exposition, as taught by the testimonies themselves.
As we read in Solomon (Proverbs 7): "Write them on the tablet of your heart;" similarly, remember it is written in the book of Job (Chapter 11): "Oh, that God would speak with you and show you the secrets of wisdom, which are manifold!"
But because things approved by the same spirit cannot contradict each other, it is easily demonstrated by sound reasoning that both are consistent.
It is of utmost importance to apply interpretations to the sacred scriptures that do not deviate from the truth of those texts.
Instead, by soberly understanding the author's intent, they should be elucidated beneficially and should always correspond with the rules of faith and truth.
For it should not be considered contradictory that when the Spirit of God is described as unique or simple (Wisdom 7), it is also immediately described as manifold or varied, as the diversity of translations shows.
It is certainly simple in the singular nature of its property, yet manifold in the distributions of grace;
or it is celebrated in three ways for the remission of sins: by baptism, penance, and martyrdom, as the psalmist sings (Psalms).
Blessed are those whose iniquities are forgiven, and whose sins are covered.
Blessed is the man to whom the Lord does not impute sin.
It is believed that sins are forgiven through baptism, covered through penance, and not imputed through martyrdom.
However, other Fathers said that sins are forgiven in seven ways, adding almsgiving to the acquisition of debt remission, restraining a neighbor from error, and the abundance of charity, through which we read that the abundance of sins is covered.
Proverbs chapter ten.
These seven ways can also be comprehended within those three ways, which are more clearly expounded.
The reason for this preface will soon be explained in the following reading.
As we hasten to explain difficult passages, we do not want to be marked by rash advancement or judged by anyone as forgetful of paternal tradition.
Chapter Five
I saw a book in the right hand of God, who was sitting on the throne.
It was written inside and outside and sealed with seven seals.
In the right hand, in Christ, he says, for he is the arm of God, the right hand of the Father, or in supreme happiness.
The book written inside and outside represents both Testaments.
The outside refers to the Old Testament, which was seen; the inside refers to the New Testament, which was hidden within the Old.
Hence, the Apostle addresses the Hebrews, saying, Hebrews 12:
"For you have not come to what can be touched, a blazing fire, darkness, gloom, a tempest, the sound of a trumpet, and a voice whose words made the hearers beg that no further messages be spoken to them; for they could not endure the order that was given."
Now, comparing spiritual things with spiritual, we do not look at what is seen, but at what is not seen. For what is seen is temporary, but what is not seen is eternal.
Therefore, it is called one book because neither the New Testament without the Old, nor the Old without the New, is complete.
The Old Testament is the herald and veil of the New, and the New is the fulfillment and revelation of the Old.
Although the Old was outside, it did not all appear; it was not all hidden.
To express it more clearly, all the dispensation of the Savior under the name of the book is often read, whether promised or completed in both Testaments.
Sealed with seven seals, it is covered with the multifaceted fullness of hidden mysteries, hence also from the shadowy and dense mountain.
Although the number seven embraces universality, I think that seven modes, like seven signs in the divine Scriptures, should be openly sought in exercises and necessarily found.
Not only of the sayings, which even worldly authors, by God's revelation, could regularly observe in their writings, but also of saving understanding, which is said to have remained reserved specially for Christ to reveal.
For as long as the same Lord turned water into wine in those six jars, as in six ages, understanding the Old Testament spiritually, the law could not intoxicate anyone with the fervor of the spirit.
Those signs had remained closed until now.
After carefully examining the sacred pages, we can see that speech can be understood in seven ways: indicative, declarative, imperative, optative, conjunctive, infinitive, and impersonal.
For example, the indicative is found in Micah 6:
"I will show you, man, what is good, and what the Lord requires of you: to love justice, to show mercy, and to walk humbly with your God."
And in Isaiah 48:
"I am the Lord your God, who teaches you what is good, who leads you in the way you should go."
Also, when asked in Isaiah 63:
"Who is this coming from Edom, with dyed garments from Bozrah?"
it is answered indicatively:
"I who speak righteousness, mighty to save."
Declarative:
"Listen to me, Jacob, and Israel, whom I called; I am the first, and I am the last, and besides me, there is no God" (Isaiah 48).
Also in Isaiah 40:
"Why do you say, Jacob, and speak, Israel: 'My way is hidden from the Lord, and my judgment is passed over by my God'? Do you not know, have you not heard: the everlasting God, the Lord, the Creator of the ends of the earth, does not faint or grow weary; his understanding is unsearchable. He gives strength to the weary."
And in Jeremiah 21:
"Behold, the days are coming, says the Lord, when I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel and the house of Judah."
Imperative:
"You shall not take the name of the Lord your God in vain"; and, "You shall have no other gods before me" (Exodus 20).
And in Isaiah 58:
"Cry aloud, do not hold back, lift up your voice like a trumpet."
Optative:
"Oh, that you had paid attention to my commandments! Then your peace would have been like a river, and your righteousness like the waves of the sea" (Isaiah 48);
And in Psalm 119:
"Oh that my ways may be steadfast in keeping your statutes!"
And in Psalm 55:
"Oh, that I had wings like a dove! I would fly away and be at rest."
Conjunctive:
"If you listen to my voice and keep my covenant, you will be my treasured possession among all peoples; for all the earth is mine, and you will be to me a kingdom of priests and a holy nation" (Exodus 19).
Elsewhere also:
"I will dwell in them and walk among them, and I will be their God, and they shall be My people"
Leviticus 26.
Or,
"If they had stood in My counsel, surely I would have turned them from their evil thoughts"
Jeremiah 23.
Furthermore, the infinitive mood, which is also the sixth in order:
"To know and understand the Lord, and to do judgment and justice in the midst of the earth"
Jeremiah 9.
Likewise,
"To refrain from evil, is understanding"
Micah 6.
Impersonal,
"Who has helped the Spirit of the Lord? With whom did He take counsel, and who instructed Him, and taught Him the path of justice, and showed Him the way of prudence"
Job 28?
Or in what is written:
"Who among you will give ear to this, pay attention and listen for the future"
Isaiah 40?
And,
"Who is the man who fears the Lord? He will instruct him in the way he should choose"
Psalm 25?
Or,
"To understand the law is the best sense; and, Who can speak of the mighty acts of the Lord"
Psalm 105?
And other similar things, which can be more suitably applied to each of the modes. These, I say, we easily find in words; but now, just order demands that we fit the regular forms of intelligence to the very things themselves as by seven signs with suitable testimonies, or rather that we prove the testimonies themselves to serve the same rules.
For although the previously mentioned modes of speech seem somewhat appropriate, they are deemed insufficient for what we are seeking. Therefore, the book is said to be sealed with seven seals, because a higher secret mode, which had previously been hidden there but is asserted to have been revealed by the dispensation of Christ, should be pointed out.
For those of us studying the Scriptures, the first layer we encounter is the historical narrative, followed by the allegorical meaning.
The third layer recognizes both aspects, while the fourth concerns the unchanging essence of the Divine Trinity, whether it is properly or figuratively suggested in the sacred texts.
The fifth layer relates to parables, crafted through narrative and action, so that when something is said or written, it may hold a different meaning, uplifting the mind to spiritual understanding.
The sixth layer pertains to the dual advent of the Savior, or matters related to it, ensuring that the first is not confused with the second, and vice versa.
A great deal of discernment is required here.
This is why the minds of the Jews were clouded when the Lord came, and they still suffer from the same blindness.
Sometimes prophecy concerning human sins and transgressions foretells future deeds or the hidden senses of spiritual matters.
The seventh layer instructs us with divine precepts, establishing a clear form of living and making a symbolic representation of living known.
We must carefully consider what is written externally and what is internal.
Now, it is fitting to teach these layers with examples.
The historical layer, which is the first, tells us in this way that there is one God: Hear, O Israel, the Lord your God is one Lord (Deuteronomy 6:4), and that everything was made by Him, and similar things.
The second allegorical layer is like this: Abraham obtains an oath from his servant in a new and unusual manner, saying: Put your hand under my thigh and swear by the Lord, the God of heaven (Genesis 24:2-3).
This is recognized as symbolic because it is not a common practice generally, except for Abraham and Jacob, the special prophetic patriarchs, from whose lineage Christ was expected to be born physically.
For instance, from all the faithful in Israel, a girl is sought for King David and found to be so fervent that she could warm the old king's cold limbs with suitable heat (First Kings 1:1-4).
Indeed, so pure that even when heated, it did not incite lust; or that the people in the wilderness, scourged by fiery serpents, were freed from the serpent's bite by looking at a bronze serpent.
Numbers 21
Typically, David changed his appearance before Abimelech, and he let him go and left.
Although in the book of First Samuel, it is said that David changed his appearance before Achish, king of Gath, when he was acting like a madman at the city gates, letting his saliva run down his beard, carrying his own body with his hands, and performing other acts like a madman, thus symbolizing the Lord's passion.
Therefore, when the name Abimelech is substituted for Achish, it alerts the reader to uncover the deeper hidden mystery from the meanings of these names.
Abimelech indeed means "my father's kingdom."
So then, the Son of God, Jesus Christ, before the kingdom of his Father, that is, before the Jews, changed his appearance when he came in the humble form of a servant and became obedient unto death on the cross.
Philippians 2
This is specifically symbolized by the timbrel; having been rejected by the Jews due to their disbelief, he wished to preach the Gospel to the Gentiles, from whom he established the Church.
This is: He let him go and left, which the apostle Paul explicitly says in the book of Acts: "The word of God was indeed sent to you, but since you rejected it and judged yourselves unworthy of eternal life, behold, we turn to the Gentiles."
Acts 13
Or that in the parable of the vineyard, "He will miserably destroy those wicked men and lease his vineyard to other tenants."
Matthew 21
From this principle, I think the expression also descends, where we read: "The mountains skipped like rams, and the hills like lambs."
Psalm 114
And, "The rivers clap their hands."
Psalm 98
Likewise, "The trees once went forth to anoint a king over them."
Judges
However, these expressions do not indicate that such events actually happened, since it is naturally impossible, but something is described metaphorically through fitting symbolism.
In these ways, I also think that parables of things are distinguished from verbal parables.
The sixth way to recognize the advent of Christ is by discerning what pertains to his first coming and what pertains to his second coming.
The first coming is associated with places of humility, as Moses says in Deuteronomy 18: "The Lord your God will raise up for you a prophet like me from among your brothers; you shall listen to him."
Also, "Afterward, you appeared on earth and lived among men" (Baruch).
And again, "He had no beauty or majesty to attract us to him, nothing in his appearance that we should desire him. He was despised and rejected by mankind, a man of suffering" (Isaiah 53).
And a little later, "Surely he took up our pain" (same book).
And again, "He was led like a lamb to the slaughter, and as a sheep before its shearers is silent, so he did not open his mouth" (same book).
About the second coming, we read: "Our God will come and will not be silent" (Psalm 50).
And, "They will look on the one they have pierced" (Zechariah 12).
Malachi also says: "I will come to put you on trial. I will be quick to testify against sorcerers, adulterers, and perjurers, against those who defraud laborers of their wages" (Malachi 3), etc.
What we have said about the sins of certain men often symbolizes something prophetic, where signs of inner and outer indications seem to shine forth.
The public sin of David in Second Samuel 11 and 12 concerning the wife of Uriah the Hittite was evident, but the prophecy from his evil deed figured something good for us.
Bathsheba indeed means "well of satisfaction" or "seventh well," which specifically signifies the Church. Christ, having separated her and killed the devil, to whose illegitimate company she was bound, joined her to himself from the nations.
We also read about this in the Song of Songs (Song of Solomon 4): "A well of living water"; this number is joined because of the sevenfold operation of the Holy Spirit.
For even in the name of Uriah the Hittite, the person of the devil is clearly signified.
Uriah, whose name means "My light is of God," was a Hittite, which means "cut off." This could be because he did not stand in truth and was cut off from his heavenly light due to his pride or because, having lost his true strength by falling, he transforms himself as an angel of light Second Corinthians 11, still daring to say: "My light is of God."
King David, a strong man, saw a woman bathing on the roof of her house. With a lustful eye, he desired her and took her Second Samuel 11. Christ, the King of kings, saw the Church, cleansed by washing and the word, treading on earthly things, longing for heavenly things, and predestined her. The provident groom loved her when she was called, so that he might join her, justified, to himself in a legitimate spiritual marriage, just as Moses Exodus 2 in the person of Christ was taken from the water, struck down the Egyptian who was plotting against the Hebrew, that is, the devil hostile to the Israelites, with a blow of his foot, and covered the slain under the sand.
For all of you, says the Apostle Galatians 3, who were baptized into Christ have clothed yourselves with Christ. In Him, we will do mighty deeds, so that we can confidently say: "I will extend my shoe over Edom; foreigners are subject to me" Psalm 60. He who crushes Satan under our feet allows his corpse to lie in those whom he recognizes as unstable, truly comparing them to the shifting sand.
We also know this happened to Tamar, Judah's daughter-in-law Genesis 38, and many others, so that when they fell into sin, God, who knows how to use even our evils well, might enact another mystery through them.
For the Apostle teaches First Corinthians 10 that all things that happened to that people at that time were prophecies of things to come. And although they might have paid the purgatorial penalties for their sins or obtained pardon through the remedies of repentance, divine mercy has prepared the effect of Christ's dispensation for us. Therefore, sins appeared outwardly, but mysteries were hidden within.
For this reason, I preferred to pass over the story of Judah's daughter-in-law, so that I might not extend this work with much more lengthy discourse.
Regarding the actions of Lot and his wife Genesis 19, what Blessed Augustine said while arguing against Faustus the Manichaean, for a general understanding of similar passages, I thought should be included in this work.
He says:
Just as another type of people is represented in his wife, namely those who, called by the grace of God, look back, unlike Paul, who forgets what is behind and reaches forward to what is ahead Philippians 3.
Hence, the Lord himself says: No one who puts a hand to the plow and looks back is fit for the kingdom of heaven Luke 9.
Nor did he neglect that example by which he seasoned us with salt, so that we would not foolishly ignore but prudently avoid this evil Luke 17.
Thus, she was turned into a pillar of salt to remind us of this Genesis 1:9.
Similarly, in Lot himself, when his daughters slept with him, something else was symbolized; it was not just about him being rescued from Sodom.
At that time, Lot seemed to embody the future law: some of those born from him and placed under the law, by misunderstanding it and misusing it, produce works of unbelief, as if intoxicated by water.
For the law is good, says the Apostle First Timothy 1, if one uses it lawfully.
However, we do not justify the actions of Lot or his daughters because they symbolized something that foretold the future perversion of some people: those women intended one thing by their actions, while God, who allowed it to happen, aimed to demonstrate something else, maintaining righteous judgment over the sins of those present at the time and his vigilant providence for the significance of future events.
Therefore, one thing is an event when narrated in holy Scripture as prophecy, and another when considered in the lives of those who committed it, as a crime.
And this is how Saint Augustine prefaced his interpretation so that we should consider the same about Judah's daughter-in-law or similar cases.
The seventh mode, which retains the dual nature of commandments, is the way of living, for example: "You shall love your neighbor as yourself" Leviticus
For the one who loves his neighbor has fulfilled the law, as the Apostle explains more fully in Romans 15.
This also relates to the life of figurative circumcision, the Sabbath, and animal sacrifices.
This method seems similar to the second one; however, it is distinguished by this reasoning: it pertains only to morals, while the other also refers to faith.
Therefore, the Apostle James distinguishes both, saying in James 2, "Faith, if it does not have works, is dead in itself."
In the circumcision of the flesh, the cutting away of vices is understood, and by the Sabbath, the rest of souls is understood, as it is said in Psalm 46, "Be still and know that I am the Lord."
And by sacrifices, it means we should present our bodies as a living sacrifice, holy and pleasing to God, as mentioned in Romans 12.
Other commandments in the Old Testament were to be fulfilled in acts of life, while some were represented by signs of life.
Christ extends his grace to fulfill these commandments, and by removing the signs, he declared his presence in his own time.
For the law was given through Moses, as stated in John 1, as an external part outwardly, like "You shall not covet," as in Exodus 20, or "Do not follow your desires," as in Sirach 18.
But grace and truth came through Jesus Christ, also found in John 1, as an internal part hidden, revealed with the fullness of time.
Although the explicit form of the mutable command remained, the people, weak and laboring under the burden of the law, needed grace.
In those figurative animal sacrifices to be offered, they expected the Lamb who was to come, to whom it was truly foretold they were reserved.
When he came, in whom all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge are hidden, as stated in Colossians 2, the commandments of life to be lived would be completed by grace, and the figures, as shadows mentioned in Hebrews 8, would be immediately dispelled when the truth was revealed.
It was different in the Old Testament, commanded by the letter that kills, so that by the Spirit that gives life, it could be fulfilled, as it says, "Do not follow your desires," as stated in Sirach 18.
Hence, Paul says in Romans 4: "For the law brings wrath; but where there is no law, there is no transgression." Although it clearly appeared to those who heard it without a covering, human weakness was not able to fulfill it by its own strength. Another matter, which was covered with a mystical veil, awaited the coming of the Lord, to whom the example and shadows serve as stated in Hebrews 8. For in Him the form of heavenly life exists for us, from whose faith the righteous shall live, as mentioned in Habakkuk 2. When these were revealed, the law convicted the guilty, Romans 1, and exposed the weak, so that salvation might be sought. By signifying these things, as if bringing forth Christ within the veil, who was to come, when He came, the celebration of figures, which was a shadow of things to come, ceased. And there is no need to seek further, since the truth of His living body has clearly manifested, Hebrews 8. For Christ is the end of the law for righteousness to everyone who believes, Romans 10.
I think this pertains to the twofold distribution of those precepts, about which the Apostle speaks, and he says, listing them clearly, First Timothy 1: The law is good, if one uses it lawfully. For he had said, First Timothy 1: The goal of the commandment is love from a pure heart, a good conscience, and sincere faith. By saying this, he clearly insinuates the law of faith, and immediately follows it by expressing the law of deeds, saying: The law is not made for a righteous person, but for the lawless and rebellious, for the ungodly and sinners, and all other things contrary to sound doctrine. Hence, it can be asked, since the law is not made for a righteous person, how a righteous person is said to use it lawfully, because we do not need the terror of the punishments of the commandments, who now freely enjoy the perfection of virtues through grace. Indeed, faith has already obtained for him, which no one could attribute to their own strength, as the Apostle says, Romans 3: For all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God. Indeed, a firm will is first shown in us through the law, but grace has healed the will, and the will has fulfilled the law. Therefore, the law is imposed on the unwilling wicked, so that they are not allowed to sin with impunity. But it is not imposed on the righteous, because by the love of the Holy Spirit's commandments, they are no longer allowed to sin.
They use the law of the righteous to either teach others with the instructions of the commandments or to guide them by the example of virtuous behavior.
Thus, the Apostle distinguishes both when he says in Romans chapter 8:
"For you have received the spirit of adoption as children, by whom we cry, Abba, Father."
Delighted by this advice of the Apostle in prayer, he also says, putting aside those things, we loved the better ones.
Hence the same Apostle says in First Corinthians chapter 7:
"About virgins, I have no command from the Lord, but I give my counsel, urging by exhortation, not compelling with a command, following the Master's instruction, who said in Matthew chapter 19:
'He who can accept this, let him accept it.'"
Therefore, because he is now a worker, his intention does not allow him to handle the work he has taken up.
It is enough for us to say that this kind of thing is concluded in this manner, written inside and out.
Further inquiry is made about these seven ways we mentioned, which should be considered internal and which external.
The first is historical, external.
The second is allegorical, entirely internal.
The third retains a dual form of both, so that it appropriately fulfills the duty of the present time and figuratively represents something of the future.
The fourth concerns God, with whom there is no change or shadow of turning, received with faith and piety.
Both senses must be taken internally, for they cannot be comprehended by intellect.
For the peace of God, says the Apostle in Philippians chapter 4, surpasses all understanding because both its essence exceeds the limits of our capacity, and no one can adequately grasp its mercy, of which many things are told metaphorically.
The fifth, where something different than what is read is found, often diffused in parables, is so obscure with certain ambiguity that it must be considered entirely internal in all ways.
The sixth concerning the dual coming of Christ is evident with certain testimonies, placed openly externally, but hidden internally with certain secrets, so that the open removes doubt, the hidden exercises faith, and removes weariness.
The seventh in the commandments of living life, as we have already mentioned, appears externally, but in the commandments for shaping life lies hidden internally.
Hence we also read it was said to Daniel in Daniel...
Chapter 12: Seal the words and the book until the appointed time.
Many will travel back and forth, and knowledge will increase.
Sealed with seven seals.
The seven stages of inner human renewal, through the grace of God's Spirit of the mind, observed by our fathers.
Blessed Augustine speaks of these in the book On True Religion as follows:
The first stage is in the nurturing breasts of useful history, which nourishes with examples.
According to Jacob, forgetting the human and aspiring to the divine, it is not contained by human authority but relies on the highest and unchangeable law through steps of reason.
The third stage, already more confident and uniting the carnal appetite with the strength of reason, rejoices inwardly in a certain marital sweetness.
When the soul is united with the mind and is veiled by modesty, it is no longer compelled to live rightly: even if all permit, it is not allowed to sin.
The fourth stage, already doing much more firmly and orderly by that very fact, shines forth into a perfect man, and is apt and suitable for enduring and breaking all persecutions and the storms and waves of the world.
The fifth stage, living peacefully and entirely tranquil in every respect, experiences the abundance of the unchangeable kingdom of the highest and ineffable wisdom.
The sixth stage, in every way transforming into eternal life, passes into the complete forgetting of temporal life, in the perfect form that was made in the image and likeness of God.
The seventh stage is eternal rest and undistinguished by any ages, perpetual blessedness.
For as the end of the old man is death, so the end of the new man is eternal life.
For the former is the man of sin, the latter of righteousness.
These seven stages of progress, by which we are said to advance, the same most illustrious teacher Augustine frequently mentions.
Writing to Maximus, he says: Thus you confirm your life and conduct with the precepts of God, which we have received to act well, beginning with religious fear.
For the beginning of wisdom is the fear of the Lord (Psalm 111:10).
Firstly, when human pride is broken and weakened, approach the holy scriptures with pious gentleness and meekness.
Do not argue in your mind or with contention, even about things you do not yet understand and which may seem absurd or contradictory to the unlearned.
Instead, yield and gently defer your understanding, rather than harshly accusing their secrets.
Thirdly, when human weakness begins to reveal itself to you, and you recognize where you fall short and how you drag with you the painful bonds of mortality inherited from Adam, you realize how far you wander from the Lord.
You see another law in your members opposing the law of your mind, leading you captive in the law of sin which is in your members.
You cry out Romans chapter 7: 'Wretched man that I am!
Who will deliver me from this body of death?
' so that the grace of God through Jesus Christ our Lord, promising liberation, may console you in your lament.
Fourthly, you now desire to fulfill righteousness much more vehemently and fervently than wicked men desire the pleasures of the flesh, except that it is in the hope of divine assistance.
In this desire, there is a calm ardor and a more secure flame.
In this fourth stage of life, prayers are persistently pressed, so that the satisfaction of righteousness may be granted to those who hunger and thirst.
This makes it not only not burdensome but also delightful to abstain from all corrupt pleasures, whether one's own or another's, or by resisting, which is easily granted by divine means.
Fifthly, the counsel of showing mercy is joined, so that in what you can do, you help the needy, because in what you cannot yet do, you desire to be helped by the Almighty.
The gift of mercy is twofold: when forgiveness is granted, and when humanity is shown.
The Lord briefly summed up these two in Luke chapter 6: 'Forgive, and you will be forgiven; give, and it will be given to you; This work also contributes to the purification of the heart, so that as much as possible in this life, we may be able to see the unchangeable substance of God with pure understanding.
There is something against us that must be released so that our vision can break forth into light, from where the Lord Himself said: Give alms, and behold, all things are clean for you.
Luke chapter 11.
The sixth beatitude follows the purification of the heart itself.
To direct one's sight straight and pure into the true light, neither what we do well and commendably, nor what we cautiously and wisely despise, should be aimed at pleasing people or meeting bodily needs.
For God wants to be worshiped freely, because there is nothing other than Himself that should be desired.
When we come to this purity of understanding through the steps of a good life, whether more slowly or more quickly, we may dare to say that we can somewhat grasp with our mind the unity of the supreme and ineffable Trinity, where there will be supreme peace, beyond which nothing more can be expected, when the sons of God, reformed to the image of their kind, enjoy the unchanging fatherly nature.
First, Blessed are the poor in spirit, where the fear of God is; Matthew chapter 5.
Then, Blessed are the meek, where teachable piety is; third, Blessed are those who mourn, where knowledge of one's own weakness is; fourth, Blessed are those who hunger and thirst for righteousness, where the strength to strive to control desires is; fifth, Blessed are the merciful, for they shall obtain mercy from God, where there is the advice to help so that you may deserve to be helped; then we reach the sixth step, where it is said: Blessed are the pure in heart, for they shall see God, where the intellect is pure and able to understand.
We cannot keep even a part of the Trinity unless we do not seek human praise, even though we do praiseworthy things.
John chapter 14.
Therefore, we reach the tranquility of that peace in the seventh step, which the world cannot give, for even those four virtues I mentioned earlier, philosophers could judge by effort, namely prudence, courage, temperance, and justice.
If we add these three to the perfect practice of religion, that is faith, hope, and love, we find the number seven.
Indeed, these three things are essential, without which no one can worship God or please Him.
Given this, either the saving knowledge and secret mysteries in the sacred scriptures, hidden in those seven ways like seven signs, are more obscurely shaded, or the total sum and perfection of virtues, by which a person grows internally, are specially ordered step by step, rather than being confused.
The promised help of eternal salvation, with Christ the Lord mercifully suffering, truly rising, wonderfully ascending, and always working in each person, can be revealed, known, obtained, and perfected.
Those signs revealed and perfected in Him and through Him are truly proclaimed.
I believe this must be taught with testimonies.
For among other things, the Apostle says this in 1 Corinthians chapter 1: "The mystery which has been hidden from ages and generations, but now has been revealed to His saints, to whom God willed to make known the riches of the glory of this mystery among the Gentiles, which is Christ in you, the hope of glory."
We proclaim Him, admonishing every man and teaching every man with all wisdom, so that we may present every man perfect in Christ.
For this purpose I also labor, striving according to His power, which works mightily within me.
In the Old Testament, it says: "The Lord created me at the beginning of His way" (Proverbs chapter 8).
Since He is principally the way in which we must walk for our salvation, we know that from Him the way, that is, the progress, steps, and established ways of living, and the secrets of the legal mysteries, are revealed and conferred.
And I saw a mighty angel proclaiming with a loud voice, "Who is worthy to open the book and break its seven seals?"
The mighty angel refers to the proclamation of the law, since we remember that the same law was given in the words of angels, as Stephen explained, and received, yet not kept by all the people.
Now, the herald rightfully demanding its observance testifies that he found no one worthy to open it.
When the first seals are broken and the book is opened, the usual order is reversed with purpose, because Christ opened the book after completing the work of his voluntary suffering.
By breaking down the enmity in his flesh and nullifying the law of commandments in decrees, as mentioned in Ephesians chapter 2,
he proved that he fulfilled the prophecies of both Testaments in himself, and the veil of the temple was torn by his suffering.
As if by removing the veil of the legal figures, he revealed the seven seals, which represent all the profound mysteries of divine law.
No one was found worthy to open the book, neither in heaven, implying it was beyond the capacity of angels.
Not because angels were unaware of the mystery of the Lord's incarnation and dispensation, but because it was not meant to be fulfilled through an angelic being.
For the Son of God, intending to redeem mankind, assumed true humanity and wished to fulfill everything himself.
Hence Isaiah says, according to the Septuagint,
"Not an angel," he says, "not a messenger, but the Lord himself saved them," neither on earth, meaning no one among the perfectly righteous living in this life.
For man needed the aid of his Creator alone for restoration, and not under the earth. No saint among the dead was found worthy to open the book or to look upon it.
To look upon it means to comprehend it. Thus, Paul says in Ephesians chapter 3 that he preaches the incomprehensible riches of Christ to the Gentiles, of which the Lord says, meaning the love of the New Testament, because it was hidden in the law and Christ reserved it for his presence.
No one could see it clearly enough to perform it, for Christ alone was able to fulfill it by his dispensation; it could only be foreseen, not perfected.
And I wept much because no one was found worthy to open the book or to break its seals.
The Church in John wept, burdened by the works of sin, imploring its redemption, which it showed to be in the opening of that book.
And one of the elders said to me: Do not weep; behold, the lion of the tribe of Judah, the root of David, has conquered to open the book and to break its seven seals.
One of the elders, representing the entire body of the prophets, whose sure prophecies consoled the Church, speaks of Christ from the tribe of Judah, who redeemed the world by his blood.
We read the prophecy in Genesis 49: Judah is a lion's cub; from the prey, my son, you have gone up.
He crouches, he lies down like a lion and like a lioness; who will rouse him?
The same one is called both a lamb and a lion, who innocently accepted a devoted death, and overcame the power he accepted.
He had previously and justly threatened, saying through Hosea in Hosea 13: I will be your death, O death; I will be your sting, O hell.
And Isaiah in Isaiah 11: Behold, the root of Jesse will stand as a banner for the peoples; the nations will seek him, and his resting place will be glorious.
For each believer, when we strive to weep for our sins and remember the promised redemption through the consolation of the Scriptures, we know we have eternal salvation, affirmed by a response similar to one of the elders.
Therefore, he promised both past and future, because the Spirit subtly refers to the past and demonstrates the future as described in Romans 15.
And I saw, and behold, in the midst of the throne and the four living creatures and in the midst of the elders,
The throne, the living creatures, and the elders represent the Church.
In the midst of the Church, a lamb standing as though it had been slain.
For as often as Christ, having been slain, is preached in the midst of the Church, the same Lamb is seen as if sacrificed for the sins of the world.
These things, unknown to the unlearned, are revealed, and the Son is sculpted in the memory of a devoted worshipper.
When the Church, which Christ clothes, mortifies itself to the world to live to God, the Lamb is said to be sacrificed for the body, the head.
Finally, it follows, having seven horns and seven eyes, which are the seven spirits of God sent out into all the earth.
The variety of expressions has taught us to present one understanding, signifying the most excellent gifts of the Holy Spirit with horns, through which Christ reigns in His Church across the world.
It continues, "Who are the seven spirits of God." For nothing justly rules throughout the earth and is especially enlarged by the gift of the Holy Spirit except the Church of Christ.
Remember, the number seven is often used to represent the whole. But because the horns are above the head, the unique exaltation of the Church over Christ is rightly placed. Hence, "On this rock," He says, "I will build my Church" (Matthew 16), as if to say, "I will build you upon me" (Wisdom 1).
Moreover, "The Spirit of the Lord has filled the world" (Psalm 74).
To make this happen, the horns of sinners are broken, and the horns of the righteous are said to be exalted.
About this, Isaiah had predicted (Isaiah 24): "We have heard songs of praise from the ends of the earth declaring the glory of the righteous."
Therefore, having seven horns is understood to mean possessing the whole world, in which the sevenfold grace of the Spirit rules, due to His notable sevenfold operation, which He mentions here for the enlightenment of the eyes, about which I think Zechariah has said (Zechariah 4): "These seven are the eyes of the Lord, which roam throughout the earth."
But also the dignity of His excellence is fittingly expressed by the horns. For natural horns grow as if by breaking the confines of the place, not content with the level of the flesh, but seeking higher and higher as they grow. For the spiritual person judges all things, but is judged by no one (First Corinthians 2).
Nor could anyone judge, unless, no longer being carnal in the body, they are elevated to a superior watchtower, presiding over others.
Thus, the Apostle (Romans 8): "You," he says, "are not in the flesh, but in the spirit."
And He came and took the book from the right hand of God who was seated on the throne. The book from the right hand of God is said to be the dispensation arranged by the Father and Himself, which the Son of Man received, because both dwell with their spirit on the throne.
We should understand the right hand here as a symbol of blessed victory.
It shouldn't be interpreted literally, as if the Son is receiving a book from the Father's right hand, since the Son himself is the right hand of the Father.
As he always triumphs in his own, who says John 16: "Rejoice, because I have overcome the world," and has made his Church victorious, it is declared that he receives the book about this.
And when he had taken the book, the four living creatures and the twenty-four elders fell down before the Lamb, each having golden harps and golden bowls full of incense, which are the prayers of the saints. The living creatures and the elders, representing the whole Church, fall before the Lamb, not without acknowledging the virtues performed. Therefore, each having golden harps and golden bowls, with strings stretched over wood, represents the passion of Christ, which the Church continually imitates to fulfill what is lacking in the sufferings of Christ in their flesh, according to the Apostle Colossians 1.
The bowls symbolize a pious confession accepted by God, where nothing is hidden with a double heart, but is openly revealed by action. These are also the golden vessels in the great house Second Timothy 2, exuding the sweet fragrance of the good odor of Christ. Moreover, the prayers of the saints are thanksgivings from those celebrating the salvation of the world, and intercessions for the stability of the little ones.
Christ, he says, suffered for us, leaving us an example that we should follow in his steps First Peter 2. Therefore, when those who are Christ's crucify their flesh with its passions and desires Galatians 5, they play harps to Christ, so that as he did for them, they do for him, looking to Jesus, the author and finisher of their faith Hebrews 12.
When he wished to reveal himself with seven notable titles, he is shown to have performed seven secret signs: teaching that he is co-eternal with the Father as God, was born of a virgin, lived as a man, suffered, rose again, ascended into heaven, sent the Holy Spirit, acquired the Church from the Gentiles, and announced himself as the future judge.
Let's hear what Isaiah says to the Jews: Isaiah 29, according to the Septuagint:
All these words will be to you like the words of a sealed book.
Both the learned and the unlearned are deprived of understanding.
The learned are prevented by the seals from accessing the inner secrets, and the unlearned are hindered by ignorance.
The Lord rebukes the leaders of the Jews for taking away this key of knowledge, as stated in Matthew chapter 23:
Woe to you, teachers of the law, who have taken away the key of knowledge; you yourselves have not entered, and you hinder those who are entering.
By denying Christ, whose coming is prophesied, they were taking away the key of knowledge.
Indeed, denying the faith blocks the knowledge of the law that contains Christ.
And singing a new song.
Christ brings forth a new song in harmony with the truth of both Testaments.
Remaining the same Word from the beginning, He was born anew through a virgin, clothed as a man-God, handed over to death by His own authority, miraculously raised from the dead, elevated to the heavens, acquiring the nations with the Holy Spirit, and leaving a new song for the Church to continually sing.
With this new song, the Church confidently hopes for the coming Judge, so that we may walk in newness of life, as stated in Romans chapter 6:
If anyone wants to be my disciple, let him deny himself, take up his cross, and follow me, as it says in Luke chapter 9.
You are worthy, Lord, to take the book and to open its seals, for you were slain, and with your blood you redeemed us for God, from every tribe and language and people and nation.
You made us a kingdom and priests to our God, and we reigned on earth.
They praise this very dispensation of Christ, designated by the name of the book, which they confess belongs to Christ alone.
It is further declared that the creatures and elders represent the Church when they say: You redeemed us with your blood.
For it is only fitting for the Church to say this.
It also shows in which heaven the animals and elders are when they say: we are a kingdom and priests for our God, and we have reigned over the earth.
And now, if the intelligence of the higher realms remains, some virtues in heaven are also believed to rejoice in this way.
It also shows the Church receiving the book in Christ, when those redeemed from every people, tribe, nation, and language confess that they have received power and a kingdom.
For he who is joined to God is one spirit.
They will be, he says, two in one flesh.
1 Corinthians 6:16.
But I say in Christ and in the Church.
Ephesians 5:32.
Therefore, he received in it what he gave; he is crowned with what he crowns.
That is why Isaiah says: He has adorned me with a crown like a bridegroom and adorned me with jewels like a bride.
And I saw and heard the voice of many angels around the throne, and around the animals and elders.
He showed what the throne, animals, and elders are, in whose midst he heard the voice.
For if the righteous are called the sons of God, why are they not called angels?
Both, however, by grace, not by nature, although the heavenly militia of angels can also unite with the animals and elders in a common praise, rejoicing over such a great gift of our redemption.
And their number was thousands upon thousands, indeed innumerable, saying with a loud voice: Worthy is the Lamb who was slain to receive power and wealth, and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing, and every creature that is in heaven, and on earth, and under the earth, and in the sea, and all that are in them.
Although these things rightly belong to Christ, our head, they can also be understood in relation to his Church, provided that what belongs to the head alone, some things also belong to the body.
Colossians 2:19.
Worthy is the Lamb who was slain to receive power and wealth, etc.
For he is the treasure of all good things and the wisdom of God.
He indeed makes all nations to rule, saying: Foreigners submit to me; and, You have put all things under his feet.
Psalm 59:9 and 8:6.
And I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven.
Matthew
sixteen
He then moves on to the head, saying:
And every creature that is in heaven and on earth and under the earth, and in the sea, and everything in them.
It should not be difficult to accept that the Church received this with Him, with whom it rose again, just as a member has a head.
Nor is it unjust to say the Church is worthy of every creature.
Although each member judges itself unworthy with religious humility, we say the whole body shares in its head, of which we read:
He gave us everything with Him.
Likewise,
He made us sit in the heavenly places.
We often know that "creature" signifies men, as the Apostle says:
For the creation itself will be liberated from the bondage of corruption into the freedom of the glory of the children of God.
Romans
eight
And the Lord:
Preach the Gospel to every creature.
Mark
sixteen
For everything that pertains to all creatures is found in man: to be, to live, to move, to feel, to understand.
Therefore, here he refers to every creature as every human being, that is, the whole world.
Hence, he himself says:
All authority in heaven and on earth has been given to me.
Matthew
twenty-eight
He did not receive his authority in time, but wanted to signify the dignity of the Church in men.
He, who teaches that he is equal to the Father in all things, so that what he says, who is in heaven, the very human nature in Christ is preferred to the angels, should rule in heaven: preached to men, reigning should rule on earth: who, prevailing, is taught to have ruled and under the earth, with the groans of the underworld loosened.
I heard all saying:
To him who sits on the throne and to the Lamb, that is, to the Father and the Son, blessing and honor and glory and power forever and ever.
And the four living creatures said: Amen.
The Church indeed says: Amen, that is, truly, faithfully.
And the twenty-four elders fell on their faces and worshipped the living one forever and ever.
The same living creatures are the elders, who bore witness, saying: Amen.
The Church was described, along with its duties and commendable works.
It was essential to proceed in this manner so that, by revealing each of the signs, their meanings would become clear.
Indeed, nothing could be omitted from these seven signs.
In their mystery, through affection, understanding, and action, all forms of perfection were shown to be present.
He describes, at times, starting from the end and going back to the beginning.
He discusses both Christ's triumph and the future challenges the Church will face, reviewing the contents of each sign in his unique way.
This approach provides both consolation from the victory's prosperity and concern for the upcoming battles, ultimately announcing the remarkable judgment.
Chapter Six
When the Lamb opened one of the seven seals, it revealed the sacrament.
However, there are many sacraments, and they are not all the same.
As the Apostle Paul says in the book of Hebrews:
"In many ways and at many times in the past, God spoke to our ancestors through the prophets, but in these last days, He has spoken to us through His Son."
Discussing the variety of sacraments, which prepared the future dispensation of Christ and the salvation of the Church, is a lengthy topic.
In the three ways we mentioned earlier-speech, understanding, and action-all things can be briefly summarized. Speech encompasses all the precepts of the heavenly oracle.
Therefore, "In many ways," he says, "and at many times He spoke," suggesting the forms of applying understanding regularly.
In the Gospel, after the resurrection, the Lord is said (Luke 24) to have opened the minds of the disciples so they could understand the Scriptures and to have kindled their hearts so they would preach what was revealed to others.
They fulfilled what was lacking in Christ's afflictions in their own flesh (Colossians 1), and truthfully said: "We have become examples to all who believe" (First Thessalonians 1).
Likewise, "So that we might give ourselves as an example to you to imitate us" (Second Thessalonians 3).
If they had not done this, they would sing the Scriptures retained in memory in vain, unable to penetrate with understanding or perfect in action.
Since we've discussed the hidden ways of speech and understanding of salvation, let's now focus on those hidden in action with the opening of each seal.
If the opening of the seal is the revelation of the sacrament, and its mystery consists of speech, understanding, and action, let's see how these three can be reasonably found, said, understood, and performed.
For example, "Behold, I come" (Psalm 40), it is written about me in the scroll; by saying "I come," he foretells himself as yet to come.
When asked who this is, he is understood as the desired one of all nations, Christ.
This is especially true because he is mentioned at the beginning of the book of Psalms and Genesis: In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth.
In Psalm 104, it says, "In wisdom, you have made them all." To those who asked who he was, he answered that he is the beginning, as stated in the Gospel of John, Chapter 8.
When asked why he came, it follows: "To do your will, my God, I desired," from Psalm 40. He says the same in the Gospel of John, Chapter 4: "My food is to do the will of him who sent me."
We understand this from his expression around the hour of his passion in John, Chapter 14: "So that the world may know that I do the will of my Father, get up, let us go from here."
Therefore, the deeds of this sealed book are known to have been revealed when he taught that he remains one with the Father from the beginning, and being born of a virgin, he lived as a true man.
For the salvation of the world, he took on suffering undeservedly, rose again with a triumphant death, opened the tomb, and broke hell. When he ascended to heaven, he sent the promised Holy Spirit to the disciples, filling the world, acquiring a multitude of nations, and teaching that he is the judge to be hoped for in the future.
When he opened one of the seven seals, I heard one of the four living creatures saying with a voice like thunder: "Come and see." And behold, a white horse, and the one who sat on it held a bow, and a crown was given to him, and he went out conquering and to conquer.
First, as we have mentioned before, in speech he varies, to which understanding is joined, immediately filling the innermost parts of action, and what proceeds in action agrees with the word, and by the relation of understanding, which I want the attentive reader to observe in the other signs.
He said: "I heard one of the four living creatures saying: 'Come and see.'" What is one creature is the whole Church, which proclaims with a great voice of preaching, inviting the succeeding Church to faith: "Come and see," as stated in John, Chapter 1. "If anyone is thirsty, let him come and drink," from John, Chapter 7. "Approach him and be enlightened," from Psalm 34.
Wake up, you who sleep, rise from the dead, and Christ will shine on you.
(Ephesians 5)
Behold, a white horse, and the one who sat on it held a bow.
A crown was given to him, and he went out to conquer, and he went out as a conqueror.
This horse can be understood as the apostles and preachers of the truth of the Church, whitened by grace (Psalm 50), whose rider is Christ.
Therefore, through the prophet it is said (Habakkuk 3): Because you rode on your horses, and your chariots brought salvation.
He is also said to hold a bow, which is more aptly compared to the preaching of the word of God, by which the inner parts of people can be pierced to bring forth the fruit of faith.
Hence we read (Psalm 45): Your arrows are sharp; mighty peoples will fall under you.
A crown is rightly signified to be due to preachers.
And when he opened the second seal, I heard the second living creature saying: Come and see.
The same words of exhortation to come and see are repeated in a different context, when the white horse signifies good, but the red horse is set in evil.
I believe that just as good promises joy for the Church's victory, so evil warns of caution from the foreknowledge of future events.
For it follows, another red horse came out, and to him who sat on it was given the power to take peace from the earth, and for people to kill each other, and a great sword was given to him.
This red horse, as if stained with the blood of others, not its own, is said to oppose the victorious Church, when peace, which surpasses all understanding, is suggested to be taken from the earth, which is taught both by action and by the sword.
And when he opened the third seal, I heard the third living creature saying: Come and see.
And I saw a black horse, and the one who sat on it had a scale in his hand.
In this scale, the measures of a feigned examination are signified, by which the merits of each are weighed.
For whatever befits a just judge, transgressors usurp.
Hence it is said: I will set my throne in the north (Isaiah 14).
And because they could prevail temporarily with God's permission, it teaches in this way: Do not harm the wine and the oil.
And I heard a voice from the midst of the four living creatures, saying: "A pound of wheat for one denarius, and three pounds of barley for one denarius, and do not harm the wine and the oil."
In wheat and barley, the Church speaks, whether through the great and the small, or the leaders and the people. However, one pound is not less than three. Indeed, the same perfection exists in singularity and in the Trinity. Thus, the Lord, in Matthew Chapter 13 and Luke Chapter 13, speaks of leaven hidden in three measures of flour, showing that wisdom and teaching from a small amount sanctify all the people in the mystical number of the indivisible Trinity.
He also teaches that the price of wheat and barley is the same, even if one surpasses the other in merit; both are redeemed with the same price. Otherwise, due to the diversity of professions, I think the different numbers of one and three are set. In the denarius, eternal life is signified, which among many dwellings is common to all. So, even if through differences in merit one may be higher than another with a greater reward, no one will be older compared to another; there will be one immortality for each individual, and a common eternity remains for all.
In the wine and oil, therefore, the power of the sacraments is forbidden to be violated, such as the anointing and the precious blood. Hence, we read in Zechariah Chapter 9, "What is His goodness, and what is His beauty, but the wheat of the chosen and the wine that brings forth virgins?" And in the Psalm: "Wine gladdens the heart of man, and the face is made cheerful with oil" (Psalm 104).
And when he opened the fourth seal, I heard the fourth living creature, saying: "Come and see." And I saw a pale horse, and the name of the one who sat on it was Death, and Hades followed him. Power was given to them over a fourth of the earth, to kill with the sword, with hunger, with death, and with the beasts of the earth.
There are two parts in the world, one of God and the other of the devil. But the devil's part is subdivided into three parts: paganism, false brothers, and those separated by open error or schism. Thus, there are three parts that fight against one. In this context, he now predicted power would be given to the fourth.
This church, he says, will be tested by various swords of evil.
This is also reflected in the number of angels, where against one good, he opposed three evils.
With the sword - a red one; the second - a black one with scales; and the third - a pale one marked by death.
The red sword signifies war, the black one famine, and the pale one announces death.
While assigning each plague, he also foretells future plagues by numbering them, including the names of the beasts.
Since it may be unclear whether the speech is literal or figurative - because the sword can be both physical and spiritual - the same applies to famine, whether it refers to the word of the Lord or physical hunger, and to death, whether eternal for souls or temporary for bodies.
He clarifies that the fourth good one will be tested by these visible, temporal persecutions, to which three evil ones are opposed.
For those who are called according to God's will (from the Letter to the Ephesians), will remain in the fullness of the chosen ones, especially those whom he wished the sacraments of wine and oil to be kept unharmed, saying: "Do not harm the wine and oil." In the wine, he signifies the price of redemption, and in the oil, the chrism of baptism.
By mentioning barley and wheat, he shows that the church, up to the end of the world, cannot be destroyed by any persecution of evil, because he counts these species not insignificantly, but with a sacred number and quantity of value. What those exercise for their own malevolent punishment, God, supremely good, turns to the benefit of his own, providing us with opportunities for spiritual triumphs.
Then follows: "And when he had opened the fifth seal, I saw under the altar of God the souls of those who had been slain for the word of God and their testimony; and they cried out with a loud voice, saying: 'How long, O Lord, holy and true, will you not judge and avenge our blood on those who dwell on the earth?' And white robes were given to each of them."
Of course, regarding those others whom God, even amid adversities, keeps safe through the secret work of His counsel, it is said that He has seen the relics of the martyrs-that is, their souls-not in a cheap or random place, but under the altar of God.
This means that whether they remain in the unity of the Church or valiantly fight under the testimony of Christ's name, they do so as if under the altar of God until death.
As was said about the Maccabees, under the covenant of God: Blessed are the dead who die in the Lord.
Much more so for those who, knowing they have a home not made by hands, eternal in the heavens, desire their heavenly dwelling (Second Corinthians 5), they are therefore said to intercede.
We conjecture in this way: after the Lord's passion has freed the groans of hell, we do not believe that the souls of the saints go to hell anymore.
I think this is more aptly signified here, similar to the Old Testament, where the golden altar was described inside.
Here, through the term of the memorable altar, the intellectual secret is known, like the inner Holy of Holies, where pilgrims, having received the pledge of salvation, sigh, having hope as an anchor for the soul, safe and firm, and going beyond the veil, where Jesus, the forerunner, has entered for us, according to the Apostle's saying (Hebrews 6), who thus indicated the presence of Christ by intention, to explain the figures.
How long, O holy and true Lord, will You not judge and avenge our blood on those who dwell on the earth?
This should not be believed in a carnal sense, that they are inflamed with a desire for vengeance, since we know that even here, those placed by them, through the abundance of charity, also love their enemies (Mark 5).
But it is clear that they prayed against the kingdom of sin, and asked for such things out of desire for that kingdom, of which we say: Thy kingdom come (Matthew 6).
And we understand this to be revealed to them by the presence of divine wisdom, that the wicked are inevitably to be punished with eternal punishment, and that until the end of the age, with the fountain of heavenly grace flowing, many are still to be joined to the fellowship of holy martyrs.
Upon receiving this response, they are filled with indescribable joy, which we believe is symbolized by white robes.
Each one receives a white robe, meaning that through the perfection of love, which is infused into the hearts of believers by the Holy Spirit, they are content with this consolation and prefer to delay for the sake of increasing the number of their brothers.
What they carry in their prayers, inspired by divine benevolence, is said to be immediately informed by a response.
It is not right to believe that they desire anything against God's will, since their desires depend on His will.
And I saw, and when he opened the sixth seal, there was a great earthquake, and the sun became black as sackcloth made of goat hair.
The sixth seal represents the sixth age of the world, during the end of which the final persecution is announced, shaking the whole world with its violent impact like an earthquake.
The sun and the moon, Christ and the Church, are said to be darkened because many will deny Christ during the final persecution.
As it is said in Second Corinthians, chapter 4, "If our gospel is veiled, it is veiled to those who are perishing, in whom the god of this age has blinded the minds of the unbelieving, that the light of the gospel of the glory of Christ, who is the image of God, should not shine on them."
Hence it is said in Matthew, chapter 24, "So as to mislead, if possible, even the elect."
In this way, the sun is said to become black, as if Christ's works, power, or teachings are temporarily obscured, or His defense delayed, when the wicked are allowed to attack the saints.
Hence the prophet Habakkuk, chapter 1, says, "Will you remain silent when the wicked swallow up those more righteous than themselves?"
Concerning Christ Himself, we read in Luke, chapter 2, "Behold, this child is appointed for the fall and rise of many in Israel, and for a sign to be opposed."
Through Him, some achieve certain progress, while others turn away and fall.
The moon turning to blood signifies that the Church will shed blood for Christ more than usual, with a great clamor of persecutions looming.
Thus, it will shed its own blood, not the blood of others, unlike that red horse, which is described as red with the blood of others.
The stars fell to the earth like a fig tree shaken by a strong wind, losing its unripe fruit.
These stars represent those in the Church who, though considered among the elect, seem to shine temporarily.
When the rage of persecution intensifies, they fall from their high status as if from heaven.
This is foretold by the Lord in the Gospel, saying:
Matthew 24: There will be a tribulation such as has never been nor ever will be.
And unless those days were shortened, no flesh would be saved, but for the sake of the elect, those days will be shortened.
The Church is likened to a tree; the unripe fruits, which another translation calls large, are people.
The shaking of the wind represents the agitation of persecution, through which people are torn away from the Church.
They are compared to unripe fruits either because of their faithlessness, as those who turn back to a crooked bow (Psalm 78), preferring to return to unbelief after leaving the faith; or because of the immaturity of time, where the Church, seeking to bring forth their happy birth, suffers the sorrowful misfortune of their unhappy end.
And the sky receded like a scroll being rolled up.
Rightly, the sky (that is, the Church) is indicated to recede like an open book, not a closed one.
For whatever is closed cannot be recognized by anyone.
What is unrolled is immediately revealed.
Thus, when this persecution is clearly discerned, it avoids and withdraws so that it is not seen by strangers.
It is known only to those it can trust through the unity of the spirit, protecting itself from unknown and foreign people, hiding by the spirit of discretion so it is not betrayed when understood.
Hence John says:
Do not believe every spirit, but test the spirits to see if they are from God (First John 4).
And every mountain and island was moved from its place, and the kings of the earth, officials, commanders, the rich, the mighty, and every slave and free person.
The Church is also symbolized by mountains and islands.
For it is the city set on a mountain (Matthew 5).
Therefore, we read (Psalm...
Mountains surround it, and in Isaiah chapter 24, it says, "In the islands of the sea, the name of the Lord God of Israel." This predicts being moved from place to place due to persecution. The good move by taking precautions and fleeing, while the wicked, driven by treacherous will, are moved to worse, as it says in Revelation chapter 2, "I will move your lampstand from its place."
We consider the kings of the earth to be powerful, capable of standing firm in judgment by their own discretion. Magistrates, tribunes, the wealthy, and the strong-all these are understood in terms of their different roles and the quality of their strength. None are predicted to be free from the troubles of persecution, though no one doubts that the number of the chosen will be saved.
Every servant and free person: the free are those not bound by marital ties, while the servant is recognized as being bound by marriage. They hid in caves and among the rocks of the mountains, saying to the mountains and rocks, "Fall on us" (Luke chapter 23), "and hide us from the face of him who sits on the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb, for the great day of his wrath has come. And who can stand before it?"
We understand the caves and rocks of the mountains as fitting refuges of the Christian faith. For it is written in Proverbs chapter 30, "The weak people make their home in the rock:" to which sentiment the Psalm also agrees, saying in Psalm 104, "The high mountains are for the deer, the rock is a refuge for the hedgehogs and hares." Here we also recognize those exalted in the Church being referred to as mountains, due to their eminent love of Christ's knowledge (Philippians chapter 3).
The small ones, driven by the noise of persecution, seek the remedies of protection, said to seek the refuge of the firm rock; for wherever they flee among such mountains, they are said to flee to the rock dwelling within them.
But the rock, as it says in First Corinthians chapter 10, was Christ.
So when they are fortified by the counsel of those mountains, being covered by salutary advice and protective counsel, they pray that the mountains themselves fall upon them out of compassion.
For each one is covered under the shade of that which encourages them with exhortation.
Hence Isaiah.
And then he said, "Go into the rock, hide in the hole in the ground from the face of the terror of God and from the face of His fury, when He rises to strike the earth."
He says this to those driven by severe persecution, encouraging them to seek refuge. The prophet seems to suggest that even in such unparalleled persecution, we should seek Christ and the refuge of the Church, the invincible head and glorious body.
What he says about the face of the Lamb sitting on the throne is to ensure that when He comes, He may find them steadfast in faith, not as reprobates.
Furthermore, we must pay attention to the type of expression that the Holy Spirit has wrapped in this book.
Up to the sixth seal, He kept the order. Pausing briefly on the seventh, He recapitulates the same; intertwining two narratives, and as if following an order, He concludes with the seventh.
But this recapitulation must be understood in context.
Sometimes He recapitulates from the origin of Christ's dispensation, sometimes from the Passion, sometimes from the middle time, sometimes about the persecution itself, or just before it.
Now, after describing the sixth, He returns to the origin, intending to describe it briefly and differently.
Chapter Seven
After this, he said, I saw four angels standing at the four corners of the earth, holding back the four winds, so they would not blow on the earth, the sea, or any tree.
In these four corners, the Church in John sees the four kingdoms represented: the Assyrians, the Medes, the Persians, and the Romans.
These kingdoms, with their power, suppressed everything, allowing nothing to breathe freely according to their own law.
Therefore, he said, so they would not blow on the earth, meaning those inhabiting the earth, the sea, or any tree.
The number four is used because of the four most well-known parts of the world, which are the four corners, symbolizing the four winds, according to Daniel, Chapter 7: Behold, the four winds of heaven were stirring up the great sea, and four great beasts came up from the sea, each different from the other.
The Church is seen to be intermingled with the kingdoms of the world across all four corners and is known to have foreigners within itself and among foreigners.
On the land, this diversity is seen in the provinces; on the sea, the islands; and on the trees, symbolizing a kind of forest, signifying various roles and qualities of people.
Then I saw an angel ascending from the rising sun, holding the seal of the living God.
This first coming of our Lord Jesus Christ is declared here, who is elsewhere called the Angel of Great Counsel, as mentioned in Isaiah, Chapter 9.
Therefore, from the rising sun, according to Zechariah, Chapter 6: Behold, the man whose name is the Branch.
And he cried out with a loud voice to the four angels, to whom it was given to harm the earth and the sea, saying: Do not harm the earth, the sea, or any tree, until we have sealed the servants of our God on their foreheads.
He is said to cry out because by the power of his beneficial preaching, he restrained the opposing powers, so they would not oppress the world with their usual cruelty of unjust domination.
In these kingdoms, where fervent idolatry reigned, even the power of the four harmful angels is thwarted, as if they were mere servants, by that voice:
"Repent, for the kingdom of heaven is near"
(Matthew 3).
This is also acknowledged by some of the demons, who said to the Lord
(Matthew 8):
"Have you come here to torture us before the appointed time?"
About this coming, Daniel says
(Chapter 2):
"A stone was cut out of the mountain without hands, which struck the statue that was revealed to him, whose head was gold, chest and arms were silver, belly and thighs were bronze, and legs were iron."
In this statue, four kingdoms are designated:
in the gold, the Assyrians; in the silver, the Medes; in the bronze, the Persians; and in the iron, the Romans.
As Daniel narrated with the angel explaining
(Chapter 2), he continues:
"In the days of those kings, the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed, and this kingdom will not be given to another people; it will crush and consume all these kingdoms, and it will stand forever."
The stone, having struck the four kingdoms, grew like the destruction of the unjust tyranny and became a great mountain, filling the whole earth.
Therefore, these four angels are now said to be restrained by power, so that the mentioned kingdoms would not be allowed to harm with their usual ventures, until the number of the elect known to God is marked with an inviolable sign; about whom the Apostle says
(Ephesians 1):
"He chose us before the creation of the world to be holy and blameless in his sight, predestining us for adoption to sonship through Jesus Christ."
Now indicating this multitude of the sacrament with an appropriate number, it follows:
"And I heard the number of those who were sealed, one hundred forty-four thousand sealed from every tribe of the sons of Israel."
This number signifies the entire Church, for the trinity is a quadruple ratio, as three times four, ten plus two times ten plus twelve times twelve makes one hundred forty-four.
The city itself is described as being twelve stadia in every direction, with a perimeter of one hundred forty-four cubits in total.
This mystical number signifies the innumerable multitude of the elect, symbolizing an infinite number with a finite one.
Next, we see the designation of the number of the sealed, mentioning each tribe individually.
From the tribe of Judah, twelve thousand were sealed.
From the tribe of Reuben, twelve thousand.
From the tribe of Gad, twelve thousand.
From the tribe of Asher, twelve thousand.
From the tribe of Naphtali, twelve thousand.
From the tribe of Manasseh, twelve thousand.
From the tribe of Simeon, twelve thousand.
From the tribe of Levi, twelve thousand.
From the tribe of Issachar, twelve thousand.
From the tribe of Zebulun, twelve thousand.
From the tribe of Joseph, twelve thousand.
From the tribe of Benjamin, twelve thousand.
It's not surprising that, when listing all the tribe names, he started with Judah and repeated the same names.
The Lord Jesus Christ wanted to be born from the tribe of Judah.
Here, the order of earthly generations is not followed, presenting Judah, who is fourth, before the eldest.
This signifies the fullness of the elect with the determined number of the redeemed, directing our attention to this intention.
In naming the other brothers, he did not follow the order of birth, placing those younger than Reuben before him.
This can be seen in the comparison of the books of Genesis and Exodus.
Judah, when interpreted, means praise or confession, as taught in the paternal blessing: Judah, your brothers will praise you.
Reuben, seeing the son, or seeing the son.
Simeon, heard sorrow, or name of dwelling.
Levi, added.
Issachar, there is reward.
Zebulun, dwelling of strength.
Benjamin, son of the right hand.
Dan means judgment or judging of the Hebrews passing through.
Naphtali means breadth. Gad means trial, girded, or a bandit.
Asher means blessed.
Joseph means increase.
Manasseh means forgotten or necessity.
We know that various virtues are present in each of the faithful.
For example, one person might stand out for their fullness of saving knowledge, while another excels in gentleness.
These twelve names are arranged according to the order and ranks of the gifts and the progress of souls, not by their birth order or their names when they entered Egypt.
That's because the focus there is on the origin of earthly generation and their dwelling in Egypt during the Exodus.
I made sure to add the order of their birth, along with the interpretations of each name, to show that this change wasn't made in vain.
We also want to caution the young ones not to think this number refers to the deaths of the infants murdered by Herod (Matthew 2), as some misinformed people believe.
To be brief, Herod is known to have killed infants from only one tribe, Judah, where he acted within his jurisdiction as a tetrarch.
However, here all the tribes are mentioned.
We will connect the meanings of their names to their tribes and fit them into the number to clarify the previously mentioned meaning of the fullness of the chosen, if we explore the secrets of this place.
In Judah, both the confession of sins and the praise of virtues are clear, which suits the number of those sealed from the same tribe.
In sacred writings, confession is not only related to sins but often understood as praise.
Hence the psalm of the dedication of the house of David, which is the twenty-ninth:
"Sing to you my glory, and I will not be saddened; Lord my God, I will give thanks to you forever, and the Lord having no sin at all. I give thanks to you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth."
Reuben means seeing the son.
We know that works are often signified in the sons.
To the children of light walking in the light, it is said: "You will see your children's children; peace be upon Israel" (Psalm 127), whose children are now spiritually taken up in discussion.
And the Apostle also says (Galatians 6): "Peace upon the Israel of God."
Therefore, from the name of the tribe, the number of those sealed is used, who rightly see the Son. To such as these, the Lord says (Matthew 5): "Let your good deeds shine before others, that they may see your good works and glorify your Father in heaven."
Simeon means "he heard sadness" or "name of the dwelling." I think those are designated here, about whom the Lord says: "Blessed are those who mourn, for they will be comforted" (Matthew 5).
For they hear sadness in such a way that they prefer to have it devoutly accepted here, sowing in tears so that they may reap in joy (Psalm 126).
They do not place their intention on their dwelling here, but lift their hearts up where Christ is seated at the right hand of God (Colossians 3), desiring to be clothed with our dwelling which is from heaven, like Abel, who was waiting for the city that remains in heaven, whose architect and builder is God.
Therefore, the name of the dwelling of Simeon is interpreted so that he hears both what is to be had here and what is to be expected by the faithful; because now is the time for mourning and longing for a better dwelling.
Hence, the Lord was saying to the disciples: "You will weep and lament, but the world will rejoice. You will grieve, but your grief will turn to joy" (John 16).
Levi means "added." This fits with what we read in Solomon (Ecclesiasticus 26): "The number of his days will be doubled," those who use the goods of this present life in such a way that they purchase eternal things with temporal ones, lest they be hindered by earthly things and deprived of heavenly ones.
We know that Job provided a praiseworthy example to them (Job 42), who rightly despised the temporal things he had long possessed, so that the number of his years and the amount of his substance were doubled for him, remaining added.
Hence Isaiah (Isaiah 61): "In their land, they will possess a double portion, and everlasting joy will be theirs."
Issachar means "reward"; hence Jeremiah: "Let it rest," he says
Hold back your voice from crying and your eyes from tears, because there is a reward for your works.
Listen to the Apostle, like a spiritual athlete, not fighting aimlessly, who says:
Galatians Chapter 6: Brothers, let us not grow weary, for in due time we will reap.
And hear the Lord Himself say:
Matthew Chapter 6: Store up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither rust nor moth destroys.
We surely know that there is a reward for the faithful.
This number is known even for this tribe, and by the judgment of the chosen and the sacrament of their calling, it is especially said to them:
Rejoice and be glad, for your reward is great in heaven.
Matthew Chapter 5
Zebulun, a dwelling place of strength.
Here, I believe, signifies the militia of those who, fighting spiritually in martyrdom, also with their bodies as a dwelling of strength, overcome the rage of the enemy.
Divinely aided, recovering from weakness according to the Apostle:
First Corinthians Chapter 12, they become strong in battle.
Therefore, celebrated for the title of their name and the effect of glorious virtue, they acquire the titles of glory as victors.
Benjamin (Genesis Chapter 35), son of the right hand.
It is not difficult to recognize those sons of the right hand, whom Truth, in the Gospel, figured by the name of lambs, saying:
Matthew Chapter 25: The lambs to the right, so that those strengthened by His right hand in this world may enjoy happiness in the future.
Dan, judgment or judging of the Hebrews passing through.
I think the judgment of those is meant here, who discern spiritually between the times of the New and Old Testament, so that they neither think the Gentiles should Judaize, nor believe anything should be mutilated to condemn the Old Testament.
On this question, indeed, there was not only a dispute among the apostles themselves, as blessed Paul mentions to the Galatians:
Galatians Chapter 2, but also among spiritual men afterward, such a question arose, which, as we are known by this great name interposed, would have needed to be referred for judgment.
Quocirca Dan, the judgment of the Hebrews passing by, signifies either a time or a type, symbolizing the actions of the Jews passing by, which prefigures the coming of Christ and the Church.
Their actions are not to be referred to themselves but to something greater.
As the Apostle says in First Corinthians 10, all these things happened to them as a figure.
And in Second Corinthians 5, the old things have passed away, behold, all things have become new.
This is in line with the earlier discussion about the same ceremonies, and all things should not be repeated unless necessary for explanation.
Naphtali means breadth, as we read in the blessings of Shem and Japheth in Genesis 9: May God enlarge Japheth, and may he dwell in the tents of Shem, which means named.
This is understood as referring to Christ, who is named throughout the world, so that at his name every knee should bow, in heaven, on earth, and under the earth.
We also read that his name is poured out like ointment in Song of Songs 1, which commands that his name be proclaimed continuously and not kept in silence.
Thus, we see the breadth of the fruitful Church in the children of adoption, whom we rejoice to see expanded by good works.
Gad means temptation, girded, or warrior.
As we read in Job 7, according to the Septuagint, this life is a temptation.
It is fitting for the soldiers of Christ to fulfill his commands and continually fight against all temptations.
He says in Luke 12: Let your loins be girded, and your lamps burning, so that we may restrain illicit desires and shine through good works, as he also says: Let your light so shine before men in Matthew 5.
We must direct the end of good works to God, not to human praise.
For this reason, his name is interpreted as warrior, acquiring the goods of the heart secretly and offering them to God for approval, not for human recognition.
As he promised in Matthew 6, your Father, who sees in secret, will reward you openly.
Therefore, a thief is called so because he hides from sight. Asher means blessed.
I believe the blessedness mentioned here is the one the Lord speaks about in the Gospel, saying, Matthew 5: "Blessed are you when people insult you, persecute you, and falsely say all kinds of evil against you because of me," to designate the sacred number among the chosen.
Joseph means increase. The increase referred to here should be applied to the leaders and various members within the unity of the Church, especially those whom the Lord says, Matthew 25, will gain double from the talent of spiritual substance entrusted to them.
This applies to those who fulfill the vow of virginity or the promise of celibacy, which is not required but brings a reward when faithfully kept because they choose what is better by forgoing what is permissible. Hence the Apostle, First Corinthians 7, says: "I have no command from the Lord about virgins," or like Zacchaeus saying, Luke 19: "I give half of my possessions to the poor, and if I have cheated anybody out of anything, I will pay back four times the amount."
In the Church, if some emerge who act out of love for eternal life, driven by great devotion, they could rightly be associated with this name. Either because leaders with diligent effort double the money the Lord commanded to be given to the bankers, Matthew 25, so that upon His return He might collect it with interest; or when celibates, foreseen by divine grace, conquer the temptations of the flesh with the abundance of the spirit; or those who, from their own resources, offer more than just tithes according to the command, but a greater part.
Motivated by increased virtue and devotion, they strive not only to obey the command but also to commend themselves to God with superior acts of virtue, not to avoid punishment but to gain a reward.
His name, Joseph, which means "increase," seems appropriate: Joseph was elevated among foreigners and known to have prospered successfully. He had a son named Manasseh, which means "forgotten" or "necessity," as he forgot the very harsh servitude and captivity.
Now, if we look at the order of their birth according to the meanings of their names, we don't find the outcome of the previous explanation. For instance, if we start with the firstborn, Reuben, which means "seeing a son" or "they see a son," and place Judah, who is fourth in birth order, it completely contradicts a sound understanding. No one achieves the peak of good works before beginning with confession because unless we renounce evil deeds through confession, we are not shaped by what is right and pleasing.
Therefore, to show that their order of names was not changed in vain but to signify and recognize the great difference between the rise of a blameworthy nature and the orders of saving grace, we follow the order of this book and briefly connect the meanings we have derived from the interpretations of the names, like this:
The perfection of our works of confession and divine praise follows naturally, as Judah follows Reuben, so that it is neither desirable to repeat things to be repented of nor reluctant to fulfill praiseworthy deeds where God is praised. Therefore, Reuben is added in this order, so that he who works may rejoice in hope, and those who see may attribute the worker to the praise of God.
Yet, because the body that is corrupted still burdens the soul (Wisdom chapter 9, verse 15), and we groan while burdened (Second Corinthians chapter 5, verse 4), and as long as we are in the body, we are away from the Lord (Second Corinthians chapter 5, verse 6), and through many tribulations, we must enter the kingdom of God (Acts chapter 14, verse 22).
As it is written, Gad follows, which means temptation.
I say, it follows not by the order of birth, but by the course of spiritual combat.
Even such people do not lack the temptations of this present life, through which they are exercised in struggle and girded with a spiritual belt.
They are not allowed to wither in idleness; for although temptation can come in both good and evil forms, it is proposed here to be understood in a way that it may be turned into virtue through good use.
Therefore, to be recognized as one armed and fighting spiritually: "You have girded me," he says, "with strength for the battle" Psalm 18. Hence, we read in James 1: "Blessed is the man who endures temptation, for when he has been approved, he will receive the crown of life," just as Abraham shone when he was tempted. For although temptation is indeed evil, we rightly call those blessed who overcome it or emerge victorious from it.
Therefore, after Gad, Asher follows, which means blessed, according to the rule of truth received from the Lord who says in Matthew 5: "Blessed are you when people hate you, and persecute you, and say all kinds of evil against you falsely, for my sake." Secure in the faithful promise of this blessedness, they are not distressed but say with the Apostle in Second Corinthians 6: "Our heart is enlarged." And they sing in the psalm, Psalm 119: "I ran in the way of your commandments, when you enlarged my heart."
Therefore, Naphtali follows, which means breadth, so that not only do we not fail, but also, forgetting what is behind, we stretch forward to what is ahead, according to the Apostle. So that, bound only by the necessity of human condition, we do not make provision for the flesh in its desires. For our way of life, he says in Romans 13, is in heaven, and although there is a desire to depart and be with Christ, Philippians 3, we still carry this treasure in earthen vessels, Second Corinthians 4.
Therefore, after Naphtali, Manasseh follows, which means forgetfulness or necessity. About this necessity, the Apostle says in Romans...
XIII) Do not cater to the desires of the flesh,
as you should not serve lusts, but attend to necessities.
The prophet, longing for better things, prayed about this, saying Psalm 24:
"Deliver me from my necessities."
This applies to Simeon,
which means "I have heard" or "the name of a dwelling place,"
to make it clearer what should be expected here
and what should be awaited for salvation.
The joy of the heavenly dwelling will be given
to those whose spirit is sorrowful with fruitful repentance,
to whom it is also said: "Your sorrow will turn into joy" (John 16).
Therefore, Levi is added,
meaning "added,"
in which we understand either those who exchange temporal things for eternal ones, as Solomon says (Proverbs 13):
"The ransom of a man's life is his wealth;"
or those who follow the counsel of the Lord (Matthew 19),
receiving a hundredfold in this age and eternal life in the age to come.
This also fits with what is written,
that he who adds knowledge adds labor.
Even the holy Job had tribulations added to him,
so that, once tested, he might receive a greater reward.
And not without reason does Issachar follow in order,
which means "reward,"
because, as the Apostle teaches (Romans 8):
"The sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory that will be revealed in us."
It is more fruitful to fight where a reward is promised.
These things God works and perfects in the dwelling place of strength, which is called Zebulun,
when strength is made perfect in weakness (Second Corinthians 12),
so that the body, considered weak by enemies,
and through whose substance they try to bring ruin to the spirit, is found invincible with God's strength,
succeeded by the increase of the unfortunate, that is,
Joseph, which means "increase,"
and in this context signifies the increase of graces, whether you understand it as the double return of talents,
the increase of spiritual benefit,
or in the things offered by the faithful with religious devotion to God the Redeemer.
To help you understand, all these individuals are placed here with significant order and interpretation of their names.
They are set to be on the right hand of Christ, the eternal King, in the future judgment.
Benjamin is placed last, representing the "son of the right hand," symbolizing the ultimate happiness promised as the perfect reward.
At that time, the last enemy to be destroyed is death, as mentioned in 1 Corinthians 15. Thus, each of the faithful may rightly be called a "son of the right hand," or it could refer to the entire Church, about which we sing: "The queen stands at your right hand in gold from Ophir, adorned with many colors," as noted in Psalm 45.
It's important to note that in the Apocalypse, Manasseh, who is not a son of Jacob but a grandson, is placed in the sixth position despite being adopted among the sons. Meanwhile, Dan, who is indeed a son and counted among the brothers in both Genesis and Exodus, is completely omitted here. This suggests that the Church, adopted from the Gentiles, rejects the faithlessness of the Jews in the sixth age of the world.
Manasseh, born among foreigners in Egypt, is placed in the sixth position due to the merit of adoption, highlighting its significance. Dan, however, is given no place, clearly showing that everything here is based on significance, not just transient relations. Dan's omission indicates the passing away of the time of the Hebrews, as the ceremonial laws of circumcision and fleshly sacrifices are no longer necessary. This is taught by the Apostle in 2 Corinthians 7: "The old things have passed away, behold, all things have become new," and similarly in Hebrews 7: "The former commandment is set aside because of its weakness and uselessness."
Given these facts, I assert that I do not oppose the words of the Lord, who showed that three parables of profession imply thirtyfold fruit for the married, sixtyfold for widows and the continent, and a hundredfold (Matthew 13; Mark 4; Luke 8) for virgins, or even martyrs.
While in the field, the active service of the clergy, the contemplative leisure of the monks, and the wanderings of the laity symbolized different things, it seems they do not exceed the same number.
However, all these modes can be understood in the same three, proven by sound doctrine and clear experience.
From the number of monks, the order of the clergy, and the ranks of the married, many often exist who, by their confession, are praiseworthy like Judah, effective in their works like Reuben, strong in the trials of temptation like Gad, blessed like Asher, generous in works of mercy like Naphtali, forgetful of past wrongs like Manasseh, sorrowful like Simeon in the valley of tears yet always rejoicing.
They long for the name of the dwelling in heavenly Jerusalem; and in Levi, who rejoice in the promise of present and future life, founded on eternal good with added temporal goods; and in Issachar, strengthened by the contemplation of future reward; and in Zebulun, who fight for Christ and lay down their lives; and in Joseph, who strive for the increase of spiritual substance and offer more than God's commandments either in virginity or from their own resources; and in Benjamin, who receive the right hand of eternal happiness.
So, with the last enemy, death, destroyed (First Corinthians 15), God may be all in all, to the extent that the Lord Himself does not contradict His words when, elsewhere, remembering the eight beatitudes, He describes them with an admirable arrangement.
He did not separate them from those three professions but taught that they can be found in them and shine forth from their members.
In this, we can observe the understanding derived from the names of these patriarchs and appropriately align the names to the same ranks, not by the equality of number, since these are eight and those are twelve, but by the quality of understanding related and arranged opposite to each other.
For the first blessing, Jesus called the poor in spirit, meaning the humble, who, filled with the fear of God, are saved by confessing their weaknesses.
To them, it is said:
"Do not be proud, but be afraid"
(Romans 11).
Therefore, it is fitting to understand the poor in spirit as those in Judah, through praiseworthy and truthful confession.
Hence, Isaiah also says:
"On whom does my spirit rest, except on the humble and quiet and those who tremble at my words?"
The second blessing is assigned to the meek. The meek are those who, obedient to sacred teachings, believe without resistance what they hear and accept without criticism what they see handed down in the Church. They are fittingly symbolized in Reuben, which means
"seeing a son" or "those seeing a son."
The third is:
"Blessed are those who mourn, for they will be comforted"
(Matthew 5).
This corresponds to Gad, which means "temptation" or "armed," placed third according to the previous explanation.
The fourth is:
"Blessed are those who hunger and thirst for righteousness,"
to which Asher, which means "blessed," is also compared in the same order.
Indeed, no better blessedness can be found than for a lover of true righteousness to be satisfied by its author, who replenishes without depletion, is sufficient for each, and remains whole for all.
In the fifth place:
"Blessed are the merciful"; Nephthali, truly meaning "width," is associated in the fifth order.
This signifies exercising works of piety in such a way that, with narrow greed removed, it always expands joyfully with generous liberality.
In the sixth place, it is said:
"Blessed are the pure in heart, for they will see God."
Manasseh, in his sixth order, which means "forgotten" or "necessity," also occurs here.
Manasseh, who was adopted from a grandson into a son, also represents the Church, to whom it is said:
"Listen, daughter, and see, and incline your ear, forget your people and your father's house"
(Psalm 45).
Such people are also fit to see God with a pure heart, who, having forgotten what is behind and reaching out to what is ahead
(Philippians 3), say:
"With my mind I serve the law of God, but with my flesh the law of sin"
(Romans 7).
Is this relevant to me?
It seems to me that the cluster of grapes brought from the promised land by two men (Numbers 13) symbolizes two groups of people: the Jews, who had the cluster (meaning Christ) behind them, and the Gentiles, who always had Christ in front of their eyes.
In the seventh place, it is said: Blessed are the peacemakers, for they will be called children of God.
Simeon is matched to this, meaning he heard sadness or the name of the dwelling.
Such people, already enriched by the abundance of wisdom, say: With those who hate peace, I was peaceful (Psalms 120:7).
They are grieved with the same zeal as the prophet who said: I saw the foolish and was distressed (Psalms 119:158); and My soul was grieved because of the sinners who abandoned your law (Psalms 119:136).
In the eighth place, it is said: Blessed are those who are persecuted for righteousness' sake (Matthew 5:10).
To this beatitude, Levi is assigned in terms of order, but I think Zebulun for the meaning of the word, which is the dwelling of strength, where the martyrs of truth are designed to conquer the devil, naturally stronger.
Even though the sense of Levi is not far off if the honor of martyrdom added to baptism is acknowledged.
However, lest someone thinks these merits were given by human strength, it should be proven that they are by the gift of the one who divides his own to each as he wills (First Corinthians 12:11).
The sevenfold operation of the Holy Spirit seems to be in harmony with each beatitude or name, as long as those desiring to reach the harbor of wisdom know to start from fear.
The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom (Psalms 111:10).
Thus, the prophet starts with fear when listing, and anyone striving for perfection will begin there.
Fear is therefore in Judah, to whom the poor in spirit are compared; piety in Reuben, to whom the meek are assigned; knowledge in Gad, meaning temptation or girded, to whom the mourners are connected in the third order.
Fortitude is the fourth, Asher, to whom those who hunger and thirst for righteousness are suited.
Counsel is assigned to Naphtali, to whom the merciful in the fifth beatitude rightly belong.
Certainly, it is a guiding principle that whoever wants to be helped by a superior should first hurry to help those below them as much as they can.
The understanding of Manasseh involves forgetting earthly things and focusing on divine matters with a pure heart, which aligns with the sixth beatitude of seeing God.
Wisdom, however, is embodied in Levi, who is particularly suited to bear the "logium," the rational word, because solid food is for the mature. As it is said, we speak wisdom among the mature, which is perfected in the soul of one capable of divine contemplation, making it effective. It is as if an action added by God:
For whether we are out of our mind, it is for God; or whether we are in our right mind, it is for you.
This especially suits those from whose tribe priests were commanded to be legally appointed to the altar. These priests clung to God in such a way that they also considered their sacred duties for their neighbor, or rather, for the people.
For the Lord was born from both the priestly and royal tribes, Levi and Judah, reconciling earthly things with heavenly things. As stated in Ephesians chapter 2, He is our peace, teaching that He is both the true king and priest. Hence, Elizabeth, Mary's relative, is mentioned in the Gospel of Luke chapter 1.
Indeed, because Christ the Lord acquired the Church for Himself from both the circumcised and the uncircumcised, Jews and Gentiles, when He grafted the Gentiles as a wild olive shoot into the richness of the olive tree of the Israelite people, as stated in Romans chapter 11, the redemption of both peoples is clearly shown in the named and numbered tribes. Especially to remember the salvation of the Gentiles, it says:
After this, I saw a great multitude which no one could count, from every nation and all tribes and peoples and languages.
Those whom he had previously named individually, he now unites in unity, standing before the throne and in the sight of the Lamb. They were clothed in white robes, with palm branches in their hands, and they cried out with a loud voice:
Salvation to our God who sits on the throne, and to the Lamb.
In their robes, baptism, and with palms, the triumph of the cross is hinted at, suggesting that they would conquer the world through Christ.
The love given through the Holy Spirit, as signified by the robes, is also referenced in Romans 8.
This multitude of the chosen, whom God foreknew and predestined to be conformed to the image of His Son, is foretold by the sign of the sacred number.
Those who come from the nations also become Israel, just as the children of Abraham are called, not by flesh, but by faith, in that seed, which is Christ the cornerstone.
The Apostle says in Ephesians 2: He himself is our peace, who made both one and broke down the dividing wall of hostility, in his flesh, abolishing the law of commandments expressed in ordinances, that he might create in himself one new man out of the two, making peace, and might reconcile both to God in one body through the cross.
As for the palms carried in their hands, this signifies either the perseverance of good works in their hands, as we read: The Lord confirmed his arms in good work (Psalm 76), and, With my hands in the night before him, and I was not deceived; or it signifies the power in their hands, which they received to become children of God by adoption, as it is said of Joseph (Genesis 41): And the Lord had given everything into his hand, that is, into his power.
And with a loud voice they were saying: Salvation to our God who sits on the throne, and to the Lamb.
With great devotion and unceasing praise, they proclaimed that the Father and the Son reign on the throne, that is, in the Church, with the Holy Spirit reigning together with them.
The order of these words is as follows: Salvation to our God and to the Lamb who sits on the throne, as we read in a similar expression in the Gospel of John 17: That they may know you, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom you have sent; as if to say, That they may know you and Jesus Christ whom you have sent, the only true God.
There is only one throne and one nature's power.
The name of the lamb designates both the Father and the Son, just as when the Holy Spirit is named, both the Father and the Son are implied.
In the book of Acts, we read: "Take heed to all the flock, in which the Holy Spirit has made you overseers, to shepherd the Church of God, which He purchased with His own blood." We know that only Christ shed His blood for us, making it clear that even when one is named, the entire Trinity is understood.
All the angels stood around the throne, along with the elders and the four living creatures. He explained what this multitude was by naming them, distinguishing the whole Church. He said, "All who are around Him will bring gifts," and they immediately fell on their faces before the throne and worshiped God, saying, "Amen." To show that the countless crowd standing before the throne was known to him, he identified them as the angels who fell on their faces and worshiped.
He did not mention the multitude, the living creatures, or the elders worshiping there, but only the angels. They are the multitude, the elders, and the living creatures; they fell and worshiped God, saying, "Amen." Therefore, we also read in Romans chapter fifteen: "Rejoice, O Gentiles, with His people, and let all the angels of God worship Him."
Therefore, blessing, glory, wisdom, grace, honor, power, and strength belong to our God forever and ever. By enumerating these seven virtues, we are reminded to seek understanding, as God wanted His Church to share in these virtues. When these praises are given to God, each individual acknowledges receiving them from Him. We must consider that what is named here is not exclusively divine attributes but also those God deems worthy to grant to the faithful.
Blessing and glory, wisdom and grace, honor, power, and strength-all of these are shared by the Church of Christ, and we rejoice in them.
While omnipotence, majesty, and eternity are attributes that only God has always possessed, these seven virtues are granted to all the faithful by Him, who gives them the power to become children of God.
Therefore, if we acquire any good, we should truly recognize that we have it through God's generosity.
It is fitting to prove this abundantly from other sources.
For blessing especially suits the Church, as we read in Psalm 3: "Your blessing is upon Your people." He will indeed give blessing to those to whom He also gives law and glory, about which we sing in Psalm 89: "Let the favor of the Lord our God be upon us," so that with unveiled faces reflecting the glory of the Lord, we are transformed into the same image from glory to glory, as stated in Second Corinthians, chapter 3, being called by the name of light.
And wisdom, not the uncreated, co-eternal with God the Father, but the wisdom created in us and the angels, which, as the law distinguished, says in Ecclesiasticus 1: "Wisdom is from God, and was with Him always, and is before time;" and it adds about the created wisdom: "Wisdom was created before all things, and the understanding of prudence from everlasting."
And grace, about which it is said, "By grace you have been saved through faith" (Ephesians 2); and honor, about which we read: "Glory, honor, and peace to everyone who does good" (Romans 2); and strength, which Isaiah mentions: "He gives power to the faint, and to those who have no might He increases strength" (Isaiah 40).
And one of the elders answered, saying to me: "Who are these clothed in white robes, and where did they come from?" And I said to him: "Sir, you know." And he said to me: "These are the ones who came out of the great tribulation, and washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb."
One of the elders or prophets represents the body, or the Church, as if the leaders were speaking to the lower members about the reward to be hoped for the laborers in the future, as the Apostle speaks about the Gospel in Romans.
The justice of God, he says, is revealed in it from faith to faith, meaning from the faith of those preaching to the faith of those listening.
And when the number of the faithful is said to come from great tribulation, it demonstrates what we read in Acts chapter fourteen:
"We must enter the kingdom of God through many tribulations."
Therefore, the Apostle also says in Galatians chapter one:
"Brothers, let us not grow weary, for in due time we will reap."
The number of the faithful is refined through the trials and pressures, just as oil is carefully produced by applying the weight of the press. Through the threshing of the tribulum, the threshed grain is gathered for storage.
That they are said to have washed their robes in the blood of the Lamb shows the reward of their efforts, so the labor of the mentioned struggle is endured equitably.
He rightly added:
"And they made them white in the blood of the Lamb."
As if to say: The robes that others stained through neglect, ignorance, or contempt after the grace of baptism, these made white in the blood of the Lamb, that is, in the grace of Christ, or even through the acceptance of martyrdom.
This merit should be specially assigned to those in the Church who shed their blood for Christ, making the robe of baptism clearer through the better honor of the Lamb's blood.
But if this grace is to be generally extended to all the faithful, it should be noted that anyone who is cleansed by the fountain of their Lord, fed with the flesh of the Lamb, and ignited by spiritual fire, is thus helped.
There are those who, even if they do not seem to have public martyrdom in action, are proven to have it before God in disposition.
Because of this, they are in the sight of God's throne and serve Him day and night in His temple. The Church, to which He has set ascensions in the heart, as mentioned in Psalm eighty-four, in the valley of weeping, in the place He has set, serves Him day and night, in both prosperity and adversity.
The Church is understood to be the temple because it is remembered to serve in the temple, just as the throne.
And it follows:
"And He who sat on the throne dwelt in them."
For the soul of the just is the seat of wisdom.
Wisdom is Christ, and Christ is God.
Therefore, they will never hunger or thirst again, nor will the sun beat down on them, or they suffer any heat.
They will not hunger because they are fed with the living bread.
He said, "I am the living bread that came down from heaven."
They will not thirst because they are filled with such a splendid cup. As the Truth said in John 6: "Whoever believes in me will never be thirsty," and also in John 4: "Whoever drinks the water I give them will become in them a spring of water welling up to eternal life."
The sun will not beat down on them, nor will they be burned by deadly heat. God promises something similar to His Church through Isaiah, saying in Isaiah 25: "A shelter from the storm, a shade from the heat." He proclaims the integrity of His sacraments to flourish in them, ensuring they cannot be tormented by any burning temptation.
For the Lamb at the center of the throne will be their shepherd. Earlier, it was said that the Lamb received the book from the right hand of the one seated on the throne. Now it says that the Lamb at the center of the throne will be their shepherd, teaching that the throne of the Father and the Son is one, because the Father is in the Son, and the Son is in the Father. In the midst of the Church, the whole Trinity, one God, dwells through faith.
He will lead them to springs of living water, and God will wipe away every tear from their eyes. This spring is signified in Psalm 36: "With you is the fountain of life; in your light, we see light." Christ leads His own by ruling Himself, providing the way, and revealing the homeland, fulfilling what He promised by the oracles of life.
Solomon, pointing to this spring, says in Proverbs 18: "An overflowing river, a fountain of wisdom."
And God will wipe away every tear from their eyes. As they said in Psalm 42: "My tears have been my food day and night." In the time of consolation, it is said they will be taken away. When the fullness of immortal joys is obtained, all sorrow can be consigned to oblivion. For behold, says Isaiah 65: "I will create Jerusalem to be a delight and its people a joy. No longer will there be heard in it the sound of weeping and crying.
Chapter Eight
When he opened the seventh seal, there was silence in heaven for about half an hour.
In heaven, which means in the Church, this half-hour of silence signifies the beginning of eternal peace.
He experienced part of this silence because there was still more to come.
Even with the seventh seal, he couldn't see everything that was to come, allowing many things to be revealed more clearly.
The silence was interrupted; if it had been continuous, it would have marked the end of the narrative.
But the silence needed to occur again, and so the narrative fittingly resumes after my own silence, continuing in the following book.