In the year of Our Lord 877, Charles the Bald was the King of the Franks.
The Letters of Charles the Bald
FIRST LETTER TO POPE NICHOLAS
He intercedes for Bishop Adventius and asks that he be received back into favor.
To the most holy and reverend Father Nicholas, supreme pontiff and universal pope of the Catholic and apostolic see, Charles, by the grace of God, King and your spiritual son.
Our devotion to the holy apostolic see and your honor in these regions beyond the Alps is widely recognized, thanks to God, and the kindness of your paternal care towards our filial love is known not only by our friends but also by our rivals through clear signs, as befits your holiness and the peak of your religious standing:
Adventius, the venerable bishop of Metz, has sent this brother named Betto, whom we believe to be faithful to us, who has been regularly educated from infancy in a monastery of our kingdom and has been granted to him by our generosity, as agreed between us.
He asks us to send a letter to your most loving paternal care on his behalf, which he believes will benefit him greatly with your authority.
He also instructed me that he wishes to send, through this brother, his profession, which contains the correction of past mistakes and the precaution for the future, as prescribed by the holy rules, signed by his own hand to your apostolate, so that he may obtain forgiveness for his excesses, communion with the apostolic see, and the grace of your apostolic vigor.
Since our venerable and beloved uncle Drogo, who, although he lived in the kingdom of our brother, the late Emperor Lothair, after the death of our lord and father, because his seat had come to be in that part of the kingdom, was joined to us with the sweetest love and unwavering loyalty, he nurtured the same venerable Adventius and kept him in close domestic friendship, and Adventius himself is faithful and a friend to us:
As if kissing the most holy footsteps of your fatherhood, we earnestly ask with all devotion that, through our petition, Adventius may feel supported by your authority, and that neither he nor his seat be dishonored in any way whatsoever, which God forbid:
Our grandfather, the divine memory Emperor Charles, was honored by the apostolic seat, so that Engilramnus, his predecessor, his chief chaplain, and apocrisiarius of the apostolic seat in these regions, became for a time:
Later, by the supplication of the holy memory of Pius Augustus, our lord and father, with outstanding distinction, was honored by the apostolic seat in our venerable uncle Drogo, the bishop, so that along with the aforementioned ministry of the emperor and the apostolic seat, he also obtained the use of the pallium.
For even if this venerable man Adventius, driven by either the superstition of his prince or masters, or attracted by the favor and consent of many, or in any other way deceived or intercepted, was less provident in something than he ought to have been:
Because, as Augustine says, God loves to spare those who confess, and does not judge those who judge themselves; and divine punishment ceases if human conversion precedes:
The most gentle and commendable kindness of your apostleship to all who are converted will follow the sentence of your predecessor Leo, who says:
The moderation of the apostolic seat maintains this temperance, so that it acts more severely with the obstinate, and desires to grant pardon to the corrected: so that pardon may be granted if the error is eliminated.
We ask that you kindly and warmly welcome Betto, not only as his own person but also as our envoy.
He is a devout monk, knowledgeable in letters, and blessed with good intellect by the grace of God and diligent study.
He will be able to explain the tasks assigned to him through your intimate guidance.
May Almighty God preserve your holiness and grant you a long life in His will.
Please pray for us, most holy and most reverend father in the Lord.
Letter Two
Synodal, to the Bishops and Counts of Gaul, in the name of King Charles.
In the name of the holy and indivisible Trinity, Charles, by the grace of God, illustrious king, sends greetings to the bishops, beloved ones, and faithful envoys, our esteemed counts.
Let it be known to your loyalty that on the fifteenth day before the Kalends of March, that is, February 15, according to sacred authority, we convened a synod of venerable bishops and a meeting of our faithful at Carisiacum.
Among other matters of ecclesiastical benefit and kingdom necessity, we discussed how to address the plundering and depredations, partly due to invading pagans and partly due to the unrest caused by some of our own faithful, including those who should defend and protect the Church of God and ensure the kingdom's stability and peace.
With the Lord's approval, we aim to quell and remove these disturbances.
Following their counsel, we decreed that since sins, which initially seem significant, grow perniciously and irrationally affect minds, making them insensible; if they ever attempt to repent, they find themselves bound by their own circumstances, so that even if they wish to rise, they cannot.
Before ecclesiastical censure and legal sentences strike such marauders fearfully and damnably, let the bishops in their parishes, the envoys in their missions, and the counts in their counties all hold assemblies together.
This way, all public officials, royal vassals, and everyone, regardless of who they are or whose people they may be, in those same parishes and counties, must assemble without any exception, excuse, or delay.
And the bishops of that parish should briefly note down the judgments on such matters, specifically those with evangelical, apostolic, and prophetic authority, as well as the apostolic and canonical decrees, and read them aloud to everyone.
They should make sure everyone understands, in plain language, what a serious sin it is, what kind and amount of penance it requires, and what severe and dreadful punishment it demands, along with other necessary and useful teachings.
The legal envoys should also note down the judgments as they know them and ensure the chapters from our predecessors, both kings and emperors, and our own chapters on this matter are collected into one and made known to everyone.
The bishops, by the authority of God and the apostles, should forbid such plunderings to everyone, and our envoys and counts should firmly strive to prohibit them to all by our royal decree.
Everyone should know that if anyone dares to do such things in our kingdom from now on, they will receive divine judgment, be forced to make amends according to the laws and royal chapters, and receive fitting punishment according to the judgment of our faithful.
And if the person is such that our bishops, envoys, and counts can correct their wrong actions within their offices, they should strive to correct it according to the set instructions or ensure the person comes to our presence through guarantors.
If anyone disobeys, they should ensure we are informed as quickly as possible so that we can promptly summon the person to our presence and they can receive fitting vengeance according to the judgment of our faithful.
And if heaven forbid someone arises who disregards the fear of God, disrespects church authority, and rejects royal power, let them know, whoever they may be, that according to canonical authority, they will be excluded from the assembly of all Christians and the communion of the Holy Church, both in heaven and on earth.
They will be pursued as an enemy of God and the Church, and a destroyer of the kingdom by royal power and the unanimous agreement of all the kingdom's faithful, until they are driven out of the kingdom.
And if any count allows such things to happen in his county or permits them to spread and does not correct them or inform us so that our authority can address them, let him know that he will endure the same sentence as was customary during the time of our predecessors.
And if any travelers commit plunder and raids throughout our kingdom and the bishops, envoys, or counts are unable to correct this, they should promptly inform us.
We may then order these plunderers to return by the same route with our envoy and legally make amends for all that they have done.
They will endure the punishment, as we have commanded, or judgment, as we have determined with our faithful.
If, however, the men of our dear brother or our nephews commit such acts, and this is made known to us, we may inform them.
They should then ensure their men are punished as they see fit, just as we wish to punish our own men.
If in their kingdoms, they presume to commit any indecency or harmful acts, heaven forbid, those who seek to seize others' property should be admonished to heed carefully what the Lord says when He comes in judgment: "I was hungry and you gave me nothing to eat," etc.; to whom He says: "Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels" Matthew 25.
From this, it must be understood how severe the punishment will be for those who seize others' property, if those who indiscriminately held their own are struck with such a penalty.
Consider the guilt of those who seize property unfairly, especially if they escape penalty.
Think about the injustice they inflict, and how undeserving they are of any kindness.
To those who amass what is not theirs and weigh themselves down with sin, listen closely.
Accumulating earthly gains at the cost of your soul is like weighing yourself down with thick mud.
Hear what Christ says:
"What good is it for someone to gain the whole world, yet forfeit their soul?"
(Matthew 16)
In other words, what benefit is there in gaining everything outside yourself, if you condemn your very being?
Listen, those who rob in this world:
They will fail, and in the next world, they will leave everything behind but carry their sins to judgment, leading to their condemnation, as it is written elsewhere.
Pay attention to what the prophet Isaiah says:
"The plunder of the poor is in your houses, and the case of the widow does not come before them."
(Isaiah 1:3)
And the widow's tear falls down her cheek; and the Lord will not delight in them.
(Ecclesiasticus 35)
Listen, because in any house where there is robbery, whether it is the house of the body or the house of the dwelling, the Holy Spirit does not reside, but an evil spirit does.
If one approaches the communion of the body and blood of Christ without making worthy amends, they are not cleansed of sin by that communion, but instead become more fully possessed by the devil, like Judas who, full of robbery and wickedness, presumed to partake of the supper from Christ's hand, and thus hanged himself and burst open in the middle.
To those who ignore the widow's cause, if they do not make worthy amends, they will not be able to enter the heavenly Church.
Listen to what the prophet says again:
"Will you not be plundered yourself, you who plunder?"
(Isaiah 33)
Clearly, those who rob the goods of the poor, the churches, and the servants of God, will be plundered by the devil and become his prey.
Neither thieves, nor murderers, nor adulterers will inherit the kingdom of God.
First Corinthians Chapter 6.
Consider how great a sin robbery is, which the holy Apostle compared with adultery and murder.
He also says: If anyone is a fornicator, an adulterer, a thief, or a murderer, you should not even eat with such a person.
First Corinthians Chapter 5.
It is not allowed for a disciple of Christ, that is, a Christian, before satisfaction, that is, correction or amendment, and worthy penance.
Listen to what the holy John, the chosen and beloved Apostle of Christ, who leaned on His chest at the supper, forbids greeting such a person, saying: Do not say 'hello,' nor receive him into your house.
Second John Chapter 10.
Listen to what was decided at the Council of Toledo by the holy bishops who reign in heaven with God and shine with miracles on earth, gathered from all parts of the world.
If anyone powerful robs a cleric or any poor or religious person, and the bishop commands him to listen; and if he despises it, letters should immediately be sent through all the bishops of the province, wherever they can reach, so that he is considered excommunicated until he listens and returns the stolen goods.
Behold the robbers of the poor.
Listen to the robbers and plunderers of church property to what the holy Pope Anacletus, ordained as a priest by the Apostle Peter himself, judged with the priests of the whole world; he says: Whoever takes anything from the father or mother is a partner with murderers.
Without a doubt, our father is God, who created us: and our mother is the Church, which regenerated us in baptism.
Therefore, whoever steals or cheats Christ's money and the Church's money is a murderer, and will be considered a murderer before the sight of the just Judge.
"
Stealing money from a neighbor is an injustice, but taking money or property from the Church is considered sacrilege and must be judged as such.
(Seventeen, question four, chapter eighteen.)
Saint Urban, Pope and Martyr, said:
The property and assets of the Church are called offerings because they are given to the Lord; they represent the vows of the faithful, the prices of sins, and the inheritances of the poor.
If anyone steals them, they are guilty of the same damnation as Ananias and Sapphira, and such people must be handed over to Satan so their spirit may be saved on the Day of the Lord.
(Seventeen, question four, chapter five.)
Saint Lucius, Pope, stated:
By apostolic authority, we expel and condemn those who seize ecclesiastical property and assets from the thresholds of the holy Church, judging them as sacrilegious.
This judgment extends not only to the perpetrators but also to those who consent to the act.
(Romans one): The same punishment applies to both the doers and the consentees.
Saint Augustine, in his sermon on the Gospel of Saint John (tract fifty), says:
Judas is the sacrilegious thief of sacred and lordly treasures, and anyone who steals from the Church is compared to the lost Judas.
The sacred canons, dictated by the Holy Spirit and confirmed by the blood of Christ, state:
(Gangra seven): If anyone takes and gives the obligations of the Church outside of the Church without the bishop's knowledge and the approval of those entrusted with such duties, and does not act with their counsel, let them be anathema.
The bishop must explain what anathema is and, to prevent despair, show how long it lasts, which is until one corrects their error and makes amends to obtain reconciliation and indulgence.
If anyone dies in their sins, without satisfaction and reconciliation's indulgence, there will be perpetual anathema for them and a sin leading to death, for which the apostle says not to pray.
(First John five).
If necessary, each bishop will collect and say more.
Letter Three
FROM CHARLES TO POPE NICHOLAS I.
Written shortly before the Synod of Soissons, asking for permission to temporarily entrust the Church of Bourges to Wulfad.
To the most holy and reverend Father Nicholas, supreme pontiff of the Catholic and Apostolic See, and universal pope, CHARLES, by the grace of God king and your spiritual son.
If we were worthy to see the holiness of your fatherhood daily in person, or at least in our thoughts, we would rejoice with great, indeed indescribable, joy.
We would embrace you, whom we cherish deeply, with humble and devoted affection.
But since the distances of the lands deny us this as we desire, whenever we get the chance, we often wish to send our thoughts to your holiness through letters.
This way, we can be assured of your well-being, as many from other regions report various things that constantly distress us.
We would be overjoyed if we frequently received someone from you bringing news of your well-being.
Since you have thanked us so much for receiving one person, whom we took in not as we wished but as circumstances allowed, for your honor and love, it would show greater devotion if we could do this often.
For if, as we wish, and as Almighty God in His mercy grants, we were ever worthy to receive your holy eminence in these parts, or to see you there, then you would truly recognize how devoted and faithful we are towards you and the Church entrusted to you by God.
Just as divine providence has appointed you as a special father to His universal Church, we specially love your holy fatherhood in the charity of Christ and desire to obey your sacred commands.
For what you command is fortified by wisdom and piety.
Therefore, considering these matters, we have carried out your recent commands regarding our faithful minister Vulfad and his companions, who were deposed because of the ordination of Ebbo, the former Archbishop of Reims, to the best of our ability.
We have also made every effort to persuade the venerable Archbishop Hincmar to comply with your holiness's justice and commands concerning them.
Although he promises with sweet words, we still do not know what may be hidden under the honey.
But since you instructed us, if we could not bring him to obey you, we should avoid being swayed by any arguments he might use, so that we would not support him in disobeying you or be incited against the deposed individuals.
On the contrary, we earnestly pray that, with no one persuading you otherwise, you do not abandon what you began out of love for God, and that our actions under your command do not result in disgrace and contempt.
As you ordered, we are going to hold a synod on August eighteenth, where all the bishops and faithful of our kingdom are prepared to unanimously attend for the restoration of the deposed individuals and to complete your commands, while preserving your part.
Do not be surprised that we now convey these matters to your holiness through such messengers, as we have already communicated similar matters through Eric, the man of our most beloved nephew, Emperor Louis.
We inform you briefly so that you do not think it is done out of any lightness or inconstancy of mind.
Rudolf, Archbishop of the Church of Bourges, recently passed away, and that Church needs a wise, strong, and resolute pastor due to the lightness of some people's morals and the inconstancy of that nation.
Therefore, after consulting, all the bishops and faithful of our kingdom, as well as the diocese itself, unanimously agreed on the election of Vulfad.
For if we did not have such a person in our kingdom, he would have to be brought from elsewhere due to the great necessity of that place.
However, because we have entrusted the kingdom and the Church to our dearest son and namesake, whose childhood and weakness are due to our sins, we could not find a similar recovery.
Since his restoration is not yet decided in the upcoming synod, we did not want to act without consulting you.
We entrust all our plans, our wife, our offspring, the kingdom, and everything we have to you.
Through you, to the holy apostles and princes, whose protection we daily implore and whose help we humbly request, we seek to place him in charge of the aforementioned Church in any manner possible.
Therefore, we now send him back to your holiness quickly because we fear that his ordination might be delayed by some trick.
It is neither proper nor just to abandon him entirely, and we, along with our bishops, who have such authority, will not allow it.
We ask by the authority of your holiness that the aforementioned Church does not remain deprived against canonical authority.
He should be ordained to the office of priest in September, so he may soon perform the duties fitting for this ministry as a future bishop.
Otherwise, the great Mother Church could be greatly disturbed from all sides, which is why we urgently request this to be hastened.
If this displeases you before you are informed about the already mentioned synod, allow me to entrust that Church to him due to the frequently mentioned necessity, so it is not shaken by wicked men.
We confess that if you knew his life as we do, even if he were unwilling, you would have drawn him to the office of bishop.
Knowing him to be such a person, where the greatest need of our kingdom is imminent, we want to appoint him by divine providence.
Without divine will, we believe such a thing could not have happened, so that such a man might be placed in such a position, who could and would know how to rule according to God with the greatest diligence in labor.
If we were to send him among barbarian nations, we wouldn't be able to find any greater labor or reward for him.
Unless we were driven by divine zeal and inspired by the hope of his fruitful work, we wouldn't have wanted to separate him from us.
We know he benefits us and allows us to partly rest from his service.
We leave the rest entirely to your wisdom and holiness.
Just as you entrusted him and his companions to our protection, we now commend him and his colleagues to your care.
May their hopes not be frustrated, and may you receive eternal rewards among countless blessings for what they have received from you.
Letter Four
TO THE SAME PERSON. About what happened in the synod.
Praising Hincmar's obedience, the synod reserves the full restoration of the clerics to the bishop and writes that, in the meantime, he has entrusted the Church of Bourges to Wulfad.
We have respectfully received your holy fatherhood's letters, in which you revealed that the cries and groans of those deposed by the honorable Bishop Hincmar, namely Wulfad and his companions, have reached your dignified ears.
You have also strongly encouraged our filial duty to urge and admonish that venerable bishop for the love of God, saying that our diligence should persuade him to obey your excellence.
But if not, to carefully guard against him influencing us with any arguments not to obey you.
Therefore, we have acted with the utmost diligence, according to your fatherly request, and upon speaking with that aforementioned bishop about the matter, we found him as devoted in this as he is in other respects, ready to obey both you and us.
Not only did he not resist, but he also hastened to be the first to promptly comply with the orders of your apostolate.
However, regarding the restoration of the mentioned men, according to your declaration to him, which he did not complete with his suffragans, a letter sent by your command to the synod assembled at Soissons will explain more clearly.
As for the protection of those men which your holiness sought and informed us, your son, we would have undertaken it greatly if it had appeared necessary.
But with God's favor, the pontiff we are discussing kindly received your decree.
Like a loving father, he, along with other gathered venerable bishops, settled their case with utmost gentleness, willingly obeying your gentle communications in every way.
Those whom your excellency's devotion has clearly seen, he treated with a peaceful, calm, and kind disposition in the presence of the same synod, as we have discovered.
From then on, relying on your guiding counsel, he continued to support and kindly assist the aforementioned brothers.
He hastened to complete all these matters with the other fellow priests, unless the privilege of your predecessor, Lord Benedict, and your own, indicated that the final decision of the ongoing matter of restitution was to be reserved for you.
Since the aforementioned bishop was most devoted to your highness, and in full compliance with your apostolic decree and our urging, he did not attempt to refuse in any way.
He should rejoice that, at our humble petition, he received even greater grace from you and thus feels more favored by you.
Afterwards, because we find that brother Wulfad, about whom we are speaking, excels in morals and knowledge among us, as we have informed your sacred paternity in other letters, we have postponed giving the Church of Bourges without your apostolic decision.
We have hastened to entrust him with that same Church and its relevant matters, to ensure that the violent actions of any wicked persons, seeking to plunder what is not theirs and to cruelly devastate others' property, would not prevail in its destruction.
So, to ensure diligence can thrive in this place, we ask that you quickly reveal your decision regarding him and the others.
We humbly request that your eminence takes swift action, as we have often petitioned.
The people in that kingdom who have the best intentions are compelled by necessity to continually ask for this.
However, many disturbances have been a constant issue, both in our time and in the past.
Therefore, it is crucial to support our son, who is in a difficult situation, and those loyal to us and him.
To effectively resist adversaries, we need you, our most blessed and esteemed father and pope, to promptly address this matter with your support.
Letter Five
TO THE SAME PERSON.
Discussing the case of Ebbo, as ordered by the bishop through Ansegisus, he writes extensively.
He then excuses the accelerated promotion of Vulfadus and requests a pallium for him, also recommending his envoy, Bishop Actardus.
To the Lord and most reverent father NICHOLAS, supreme pontiff of the Catholic and apostolic see, and universal pope, CHARLES, by the grace of God king and your spiritual son.
Although the support and veneration of all priests serving God should be sought, it is fitting and most appropriate, most holy father and most excellent bishop, that our generosity should especially submit the royal neck to the reverence of your pontificate, and with the utmost devotion incline the ear of the heart to obey your most beneficial admonitions.
Indeed, we see more clearly than daylight that you have been established by God's most gracious mercy as the firmest anchor of the Church amidst the turbulent whirlpool of the world, and the immovable stake on which we can lay the burden of our sins.
Thus, our humanity burns more fervently with the benevolence of your piety, as we perceive you to be the sole defender against the cruel beasts intent on tearing apart the Church of Christ.
Therefore, since you have ordered the bishops of our kingdom through letters to write to you about the case of Ebbo, revealing whatever truth they could find, and since you commanded us not by letters but through your servant Ansegisus the monk, who returned to your fatherhood this year after Archbishop Egilo fell ill, to write to you the truth of the matter and sign our letter, we faithfully inform you of what we have seen and know to obey your holy fatherhood in all things.
For no bishop now remains, except Rothadus, who was present at that time concerning this matter.
And lest we leave anything unaddressed, we have decided first to recount his origins.
Therefore, Ebbo, originally from the royal treasury family, advanced and was received with royal kindness by our pious and glorious grandfather, Charles.
He was nurtured in the affairs of the palace, granted freedom, and promoted step by step in sacred orders due to his noble and energetic character.
Our father, the most pious Emperor Louis, who ruled the kingdom of Aquitaine, appointed him to serve.
Recognizing his diligent service and sharp mind, he soon appointed him as librarian.
After the death of our most excellent grandfather, Emperor Charles, our most pious father, Emperor Louis, inherited the empire by God's grace and came to the city of Reims.
There, your predecessor, the most holy Pope Stephen, came to meet him and consecrated him in the honor of the empire, inspired by God.
At that time, the venerable Archbishop Wulfarius of the aforementioned city was afflicted with a serious illness and died.
After his death, the emperor, according to the sacred canons, allowed the people to elect a successor.
They elected a man named Gislemar to the honor of the bishopric.
However, when he sat before the bishops for examination and was given the gospel text, he could read it somewhat but understood nothing, which everyone recognized.
He was rejected and dismissed by all as unwise.
Then it seemed right to the emperor that the aforementioned Ebbo, due to his capacity for knowledge and respect for his merits, should be promoted to the already mentioned bishopric.
When this was relayed to the people and all the wise, they unanimously approved.
Thus, according to the canonical institution, he was ordained as archbishop.
On the first occasion, when the people of the Franks, instigated by the devil, tried to remove the emperor, who was ordained by God and crowned by the apostolic see, from his rule, Ebbo remained steadfast in his loyalty, and, as was right, persevered until the emperor was restored.
However, secondly, with the encouragement and effort of our brother Lothair, all the people deserted our father of pious memory.
They took him and his wife to Italy, specifically the city of Tardona, where they placed him in custody.
They also assigned me, not yet ten years old, to be held in the same custody at the monastery of Prum, as if I were guilty of many crimes.
After the emperor was taken by Lothair to the monastery of Saint Medard in Soissons, Ebbo himself, along with almost all the bishops-some willing, some unwilling-removed the emperor from the communion of the Church.
They stripped him of his dignity, wife, son, and all loyal followers without him confessing or being convicted by anyone.
Finally, the mercy of our compassionate God looked upon the humility of the pious emperor.
He touched the hearts of those He chose, inspiring them with His mercy to free him from captivity and restore him to the empire.
When the archbishops and bishops brought him back from custody at the monastery of the most blessed martyrs Dionysius, Rusticus, and Eleutherius, they humbly confessed they had wronged him and earnestly sought his forgiveness.
They urged Lothair to withdraw from imperial power.
Consequently, Lothair and his supporters withdrew to other regions.
When these events were known to Ebbo, who was staying in Rheims, he fled, terrified, to the city of Paris to a certain recluse, hoping to hide and escape the emperor's wrath.
The emperor, having heard this, sent loyal and diligent messengers to capture him and place him in custody, and he entrusted the church of Rheims to the venerable Abbot Fulco.
From there, Ebbo was taken to the city of Metz, where, standing on the pulpit in the church of Saint Stephen before everyone, he confessed that he had unjustly judged his glorious lord, the emperor.
There, the most pious emperor was honorably crowned by all the bishops, clergy, and people and restored to his former empire.
At this point, after calling another general assembly, he ordered that Ebbo be brought before him.
Due to the insult and injury caused, and with several bishops present-since they wanted to satisfy the emperor and maintain episcopal respect-they convinced the emperor that Ebbo's case should be handled not in front of laypeople but in the sanctuary.
However, Ebbo, deprived of all temporal support and lacking any human comfort, sought advice from a certain recluse named Framegaud.
He sent through him a ring to our mother, the glorious Empress Judith, which he had once received from her.
Whenever he faced trouble, he used to send this ring and earnestly pleaded for her mercy.
Our mother had sent this ring to him at the time of our birth because he was an archbishop, and for his piety and holiness, so that he would always remember us in his prayers.
Remembering these things and recognizing his tearful sighs, she sought to persuade the bishops who had gathered there to show mercy.
She aimed to calm the emperor's mind by satisfying him and to avoid breaking divine laws, lest, by harshly punishing him who had wronged them, they might not seem to repay God appropriately, who had mercifully saved them from such great danger.
The emperor had resolved in his mind never to consent to the deposition of any bishop out of reverence for such a great ministry.
Because of this, he obtained from the merciful emperor that he would no longer push for his deposition.
According to the very moderate counsel of our glorious Empress mother, they satisfied the most merciful emperor and imposed no other sentence on Ebbo than the one he had written.
This authentic document was received from the venerable Abbot Fulco, to whom the Church of Reims had been entrusted at that time.
The venerable Archbishop Hincmar received it and transmitted it to you, as he reported to us.
But we do not know if it was directed to you purely and simply.
However, we know for certain that none of the bishops signed it with their own hand.
For Ebbo, having learned of the inevitable cause of his danger, brought forward three witnesses, his confessors: Archbishop Aiulfus, and Bishops Moduinus and Badaradus.
They acted on his behalf, testifying to the truth of Ebbo's confession and advising him to abstain from the episcopal ministry.
They also brought in three others who saw him confess: Archbishop Nothon, and Bishops Theuderic and Actard.
After these proceedings, he was taken back into custody.
When these decisions were made by the bishops, the emperor sent letters through Godefrid, the venerable abbot of the monastery of Saint Gregory, to your predecessor, Pope Gregory, requesting his assent, if possible, in the deposition of Ebbo.
Pope Gregory, through the aforementioned abbot, sent back letters of his authority, but what was included in them remains unknown to all the bishops and all the orders of our kingdom.
Your holiness could investigate through the archives what your predecessor thought about it.
We believe that if the emperor had your predecessor's support in rejecting Ebbo, he would have immediately appointed another bishop to the vacant Church.
But the emperor, delaying this action with careful counsel, acted wisely to curb the boldness of reckless men in the future and to maintain the stability of the Church.
After the death of the emperor, Lothair, who was guarding Ebbo, brought him back.
Our brother Lothair received him kindly and, with the bishops who were then with him, whose counsel Ebbo used, restored him to his rank with their common consent by presenting a document of his confession to satisfy the emperor.
While we were heading to parts of Aquitaine for urgent matters, the entire clergy and people of the Church of Reims eagerly requested our presence.
Thus, he was finally restored to his former seat by his fellow bishops and suffragans.
Then, all who were present communicated with him, and all the suffragans who had been ordained in his absence received their rings, staffs, and letters of confirmation from him, following the practice of the Gallican Churches.
Moreover, he ordained Vulfad and certain other sons of the Church there, who were given access to him.
We briefly mentioned Ebo's deposition and restoration so that your wise judgment can decide whether these pertain to Vulfad's deposition or not.
If anyone informed your holiness that he was canonically summoned to the Synod of Soissons and affirmed or submitted letters of his condemnation, know that this is entirely untrue, as he did not attend the synod.
With these matters settled, we found it necessary to humbly and devoutly render ourselves excusable in your majesty's sight, because before the return of the reverend Archbishop Egil or the response from your bishopric, we commended the aforementioned Vulfad to the seat of the Archbishop of Bourges.
The bishops promoted him to the honor of the bishopric, not out of recklessness but out of great necessity, relying on your great mercy.
We sent him to those parts of Aquitaine to our son and namesake and commended that Church to him, because we found him to be diligent in the education of another son of ours, namely Carloman, your servant, whom we specially commended to your blessedness.
In other matters of importance, he proved to be both capable and morally upright, and most faithful to us in all things.
If anything in this haste displeased your holy serenity, we ask that your holy fatherhood forgive us.
And because in that same kingdom, a great persecution by pagans was raging, which the merciful Lord often defeated through our son and the faithful, and on that occasion, the hostile outbreak against Christians was spreading widely, as the bearer of these letters can tell you in person.
With the urgent needs of that kingdom, the bishops, to prevent greater evils and to settle the present ones, and considering the seat of that region holds a chief position, have hastened its ordination.
They did this so that, with its wisdom and vigor, and relying on the authority of the seat, they might more easily quell the arising evils, consulting the time.
In the course of this ordination, because your permission was not awaited due to the imminent danger already mentioned, we ask for your most kind sanctity to forgive us.
Furthermore, we humbly beseech your glorious and most beloved fatherhood that if we dare to trust in your holy promises, it may appear here that we have great influence with you.
So that whatever must be forgiven in the aforementioned matters, you may forgive, and you may decorate and confirm with apostolic authority the aforementioned most faithful servant of yours, Vulfad, by adorning him with the cloak.
We send to your most holy fatherhood our faithful envoy, Actard, formerly the venerable bishop of the Namnetian seat, who suffered exile, chains, the sea, and harsh dangers but was freed by the grace of God.
Too close to the Northmen and Bretons, the city entrusted to him, once very flourishing, is now burnt and completely destroyed, reduced to a desert for a decade.
He will communicate verbally what our letters lack, as time and opportunity please you.
Since he has no hope in his own, if the vigilance and wisdom of your discretion grant and favor, we wish that he be established in the vacant seat, so that he may carry out the ministries entrusted and ordained to him, and that he may be able to serve ecclesiastical utilities and our commands.
He planned to stay in Rome for a while, so that when the Britons arrived, he could confront them in person and reveal the harm they had done to his church and neighboring churches.
Therefore, the Synod of Soissons and Troyes advised sending a delegation to ensure that this reckless, deceitful, and barbaric people would be restrained by the apostolic sword from such bold and excessive actions.
To our student and your servant, we pray, as usual, that your most compassionate hearts will be open: so that his mind, shaken by long-lasting sorrow, may be strengthened and refreshed by living and flowing waters.
Letter Six
TO ADON, ARCHBISHOP OF VIENNE.
Regarding the ordination of Bernarius as bishop of Grenoble.
CHARLES the King sends greetings to the venerable Archbishop ADON, whom we hold dear.
Through Odo and other loyal followers, we have conveyed our wishes to you: when you come to us, we will provide you with more details.
We instruct you to know that we have granted the bishopric of Grenoble to a certain cleric, a deacon formerly of the venerable Archbishop Remigius, and later of our dear nephew Lothair.
With your judgment, if you find him canonically suitable, he may be ordained bishop by your holiness.
For it is not right for that bishopric to remain without a bishop for long.
You are aware of the canonical authority: whatever is neglected will undoubtedly be attributed to you by the Lord, who has given you the duty to arrange and ordain.
Even if our beloved nephew, being occupied elsewhere, overlooks it, so that the people of God are not left without a shepherd.
You are responsible for that bishop and bishopric, and everything pertaining to that Church.
For Christ our God has entrusted His entire Church to you and all your bishops: to whom we must all humbly submit.
So, as you diligently fulfill your duties, without a doubt, we will trust you to intercede confidently with Him for us and our kingdom.
Farewell, and always remember us in your prayers.
Received on August 27.
Letter SevenTo Adrian the Second
To the most holy and revered Father Adrian, Charles, by the grace of God, King.
Your venerable paternity sent us a letter concerning Hincmar of Laon, formerly a bishop.
Here are the main points.
Our conversation begins with you, dearest son, and with the prophet who says: "This people honors me with their lips, but their hearts are far from me" Isaiah 29:13.
We had not wished to speak to your reverence in any other way, if not for the immense necessity that compels us to speak unwillingly and under duress.
You often send us letters of reproach and accuse us of unknown crimes based on what you hear from our adversaries. This is not appropriate for your holy ministry, nor fitting, and neither did your predecessors treat our predecessors in such a manner.
As we read in the letters of the pontiffs of the apostolic see and in those of Christian kings and emperors: the devout kings and emperors called the successors of the blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, Fathers; and the pontiffs of the apostolic Roman see called the Christian kings and emperors Sons and Lords up to your time.
Now, on the contrary, as the Apostle says: "Children, obey your parents," which we would most devoutly wish to do if it were allowed to us, and: "Fathers, do not provoke your children to anger" Colossians 3:20-21.
Not having confessed to perjury, tyranny, or treachery, nor having been legally and regularly convicted by judicial order: as Blessed Augustine, instructed by divine and human laws, says: "No one dares to assume both roles for himself, to be both the accuser and the judge."
We have endured such great injustices that we are provoked to anger, contrary to the command of the Apostle.
To keep silent about the royal person, we must note that no commoner or free man has ever been provoked by any priest up to now.
Neither according to church rules nor public laws has anyone been accused, voluntarily confessed, or been legally and regularly convicted and presented in judgment.
Your predecessor of blessed memory, Nicholas, caught our former nephew Lothair in public adultery but preserved the honor of royal power.
He did not address him in his apostolic letters the same way you address us, whom you neither hold as confessed nor convicted.
Nor did he excommunicate him, as you now threaten to excommunicate us without authority or reason.
We are well aware of the teachings of the Holy Scriptures and the pontiffs of the apostolic see.
We understand where, how, and in what manner and order any pontiff ought to regularly excommunicate someone.
We firmly believe that we understand your fatherhood and the Holy Roman Church.
The letters your predecessors and ancestors sent to the Christian emperors of the Romans and the Franks, and to our forefathers, are clear evidence.
Where necessary, they offered reminders without reproach, accusation, or charges.
Instead, they provided guidance on matters related to ecclesiastical ministry.
They did not take over the kingdom's affairs or secular matters for themselves, knowing, as Saint Gelasius says, that the world is principally governed by two powers: the sacred authority of the pontiffs and the royal power.
Christ, mindful of human frailty and what would be fitting for salvation, balanced these powers magnificently.
He distinguished the actions and dignities of each office, ensuring that his followers would be saved through humble service, not through human pride.
Christian emperors needed the pontiffs for eternal life, and the pontiffs relied on the emperors' arrangements for temporal affairs.
This separation ensured that spiritual action remained free from carnal incursions, allowing those serving God to avoid involvement in secular matters, as mentioned in Second Timothy chapter two.
Conversely, it was clear that those involved in secular matters did not preside over divine affairs.
It has been written to us that in the case of Hincmar, I acted not as a pious king but as an impious tyrant.
There is no middle ground; one who cannot be called good must be called bad.
Thus, not a pious king, but an impious tyrant is understood.
Although I confess myself a sinner, I deny being impious.
When Nathan the prophet rebuked King David for his deadly sins, he did not call him impious but said, "You are the man who did this." By confessing his deeds, he was not condemned with judgment but was fittingly absolved, as mentioned in Second Samuel chapter twelve.
But since it is written: "The lips of a priest should guard knowledge, and people should seek instruction from his mouth, for he is the messenger of the Lord of hosts" (Malachi 2), and with the Lord warning that no one should say to his brother without cause Raca or 'You fool' (Matthew 5), we do not believe such things were said towards me, a king, however humble, yet Catholic, and devoutly remaining in the Catholic faith, by you-whose mouth consecrates the body and blood of Christ through sacred invocation, as the Apostle testifies, who died for the ungodly (Romans 5).
Nor do we believe that you would have sent us this message recklessly based on false suggestions, for you uphold the teachings of Scripture: "I will go down and see whether they have done altogether according to the outcry that has come to me; and if not, I will know" (Genesis 18); and "I searched out the cause that I did not know with utmost diligence" (Job 29).
Indeed, holy and learned bishops, even those suffering prejudice from them, did not call Constantius an Arian or Julian an apostate in such a manner.
And if you review all the letters we have from the time when Roman pontiffs began writing to the kings of the Franks, you will find nothing of this sort in them.
It is also written to us in your voice that you would entrust all the matters committed to Hincmar by the Church to us until he returned to his own, so they might remain intact and incur no loss.
To which we respond, as the blessed Gregory says, we kings of the Franks born from royal lineage, have been counted not as stewards of bishops but as lords of the land up to this point: and as Leo and the Synod of Bourges wrote: Kings and emperors, whom divine power has commanded to rule over lands, have allowed the holy bishops to decide matters according to divine constitutions, but they have not become the stewards of bishops.
And Augustine says: Possessions are held by the rights of kings, not by episcopal authority making kings the managers of estates.
And the Lord commands that what is Caesar's be rendered to Caesar, and what is God's to God (Matthew 22), who also paid the tax to the king (Matthew 17).
And the Apostle wanted to serve kings, to be honored, and not to be trampled on by kings:
"Honor the king," he says in
First Peter
2.
And again:
"Let every soul be subject to the higher powers" in
Romans
13.
And a little earlier:
"Therefore be subject out of necessity, not only because of wrath, but also for conscience' sake."
As it is written about the bishops to be summoned by you to Rome from our kingdom, read the records of the Roman pontiffs and the letters of blessed Gregory to the king of the Franks, and also to Brunhilda, though she was a woman, yet a queen, and you will find that your predecessors, and our predecessors, wrote to summon bishops and to convene synods.
In the same letter, it is written to us that men from our kingdom, Celsanus, Walco, and Berno, be allowed to remain safe and unharmed with their people. If we act otherwise, we would not be able to partake in your communion until true satisfaction; and we would know that we would not escape your judgment if your decrees or warnings were violated further by us. To this, we respond that the pontiffs of the apostolic see did not usually command the kings of the Franks in such a manner, even for those who sought refuge at the thresholds of the apostles in their times.
Nor is it the Catholic doctrine that, for this or similar reasons, a king who corrects wrongdoers should be separated from the communion of the apostolic see, as blessed Augustine patiently showed:
"Spiritual people," he says,
"whether progressing in this very pious study, do not go out, because when they seem to be expelled by either some perversity or necessity of men, they prove themselves more there, than if they remained inside, as they do not rise up against the Church in any way, but are rooted in the solid rock of unity with the strongest strength of love."
This pertains to what is said in the sacrifice of Abraham:
"But the birds he did not divide" in
Genesis
15.
Therefore, it should not be believed that these commands came from your apostolic mouth.
Whoever wrote this did not consider well that anyone withdrawing their communion from me, who remains in the Catholic and apostolic communion, would be separating not me but themselves from the Catholic and apostolic communion.
For this reason, the blessed Gregory also says about the ruler of the Church: Often, in binding and loosing his subjects, he who is set over the Church of Christ is moved by his own will, not following the merits of the cases.
Hence, it happens that he deprives himself of the very power of binding and loosing when he exercises it according to his own will and not according to the behavior of his subjects.
And although this is the case, we have nonetheless dealt with Celsus, who falsely accused me of being part of the liar Hincmar's faction.
His church had more than two thousand manors, which was more than during the time of our predecessors.
We increased it, and during his time, it grew by more than six hundred.
He accused us before your Holiness, the pontiff of the apostolic see, of disrupting the ecclesiastical state.
Regarding Walco and Berno, who are noted for perjury and disloyalty to our royal person, and as fugitives, as it was written to us from your side, we obeyed, not considering their lies and the slanders spoken against us, but the honor and reverence of the apostolic see.
Therefore, with your peace and pardon, we say that the commands of the apostolic see, supported by evangelical truth and apostolic and canonical authority according to the course of the Holy Scriptures and the tradition of our ancestors, should be received and obeyed.
We wish to preserve this honor and rely on you, the bishop of the apostolic seat, by obeying the primacy of the blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, as voiced by the Lord.
The Church has always upheld and continues to uphold this, in line with the holy canons and sacred laws promulgated by Christian emperors, which show deference to the same primary seat.
Just as our predecessors showed deference to this holy seat, your paternity should honor us, just as their predecessors honored the Christian Roman emperors and the kings of the Franks, as well as the Roman and Frankish emperors, our ancestors.
Additionally, any letters that are unsuitable for your ministry and inconsistent with our royal dignity and power, sent to us in your name, I do not believe to be authored by you or the always discreet and cautious holy Roman Church.
The holy seat has always been known to correct with modesty and discretion, helpfully addressing each person and situation appropriately.
Therefore, let us preserve the rights of our royal power, and we will respect the authority of your pontifical office.
It was also written to us that we sent a letter containing heinous accusations against Hincmar, which we did not.
We did not write such accusations to you.
Instead, we relayed what many bishops, ecclesiastical leaders, nobles, commoners, and others in our kingdom were confessing about him.
We suggested this to you because we wanted to correct him before he reached the point he has now fallen to, and someone should inform you before you learned the truth about it.
Despite our many attempts to correct him, he has now reached this point, as you will find in the synodal acts directed to your authority.
Therefore, we earnestly request your authority, just as your predecessors and the predecessors of our predecessors, along with the archbishops and bishops of our kingdom, preserved the ecclesiastical privileges and dignities decreed by sacred canons from ancient customs for us, to strive to preserve them in this matter as well.
As Saint Gregory says, the apostolic see retains its own strength and does not diminish the rights it grants to others.
There are many things that could have been judged regularly together with those by whom he was judged, had it been permitted to remain longer in the synod.
But it was necessary for us, along with certain bishops, to hasten as quickly as possible to meet our brother for the reconciliation of his sons to their father and our brother.
We did this to prevent the stirred-up sedition and the close-to-fighting among themselves from resulting in the parricidal blood of Christians being shed.
This was also to ensure that the affairs of the churches of God were not divided, the faculties of priests and servants of God were not plundered, and the poor were not ravaged.
The synod could not determine certain judgments about all the accusations.
However, in these records, which are sent to your authority, you will see how long we, the bishops and leaders of our kingdom, have endured his intolerable and unbearable behavior and actions with the greatest effort.
Therefore, we believe your pontifical authority will act according to the sacred rules regarding him.
However, we assure you that as long as God preserves us in the governance of the kingdom, this Hincmar will not have the bishopric of Laon under his governance.
Although he does not deserve it, we have granted him, by consideration of piety, that any clerics or members of the household of the bishopric of Laon who wish to go, have permission to do so.
Finally, the venerable Actard, who has been baptized, tonsured, and nurtured in the metropolitan church of Tours, advancing through each rank to the order of bishop, is requested by the clergy and people of that church to be assigned to them.
Your fatherhood has commended him to us for this assignment, and if an opportunity arises in our region, you have recommended him.
We have granted him, at your request, the church that has been vacant without a pastor until a suitable place in your kingdom becomes available for his regular assignment.
We refer him to your authority so that, if it pleases you, you may assign him as archbishop in the aforementioned metropolis.
After his passing, the clergy and people of that metropolitan church, as sacred rules command and ancient custom requires, may elect, and the suffragan and provincial bishops there ordain, a new metropolitan bishop.
Finally, in honor of Almighty God and in veneration of the holy apostles, we beseech you not to send us and compel us with such letters of dishonor and commands as have come to us in your name until now, to us, our bishops, and the leaders of our kingdoms.
We wish to comply with what pertains to your ministry according to our ministry.
We say this for the honor of your privilege because we sincerely desire to obey you duly and competently in all things as the vicar of the blessed Peter, prince of the apostles, and we wish to avoid anything to the contrary.
We humbly request your Holiness to do the same.
May Almighty God, for the honor, salvation, and exaltation of His holy Church, deign to preserve you through all the years, most holy and reverend Father in the Lord.
Letter Eight To the Same Person
Responding to the two letters from Adrian with some agitation, he replies to both with a somewhat disturbed mind.
To the Most Holy and Revered Father Adrian, Supreme Pontiff and Universal Pope, Charles, by the grace of God, King and your spiritual son.
We read in the Book of Chronicles that the sons of Israel went to battle with a peaceful mind, because they fought not for revenge out of jealousy, but for the sake of obtaining peace.
We mention this again because you compel us, with your letters inappropriate to royal authority, to respond to you with a peaceful mind, albeit in a way different from what we would prefer.
Your letters dishonor us, your commands weigh us down in ways unsuitable to your episcopal modesty, and your insults and reproaches disgrace us.
We wish you to recognize that, although subject to human disturbances, we walk in the image of God as a man, having the sense inherited from our fathers and grandfathers, elevated by the grace of God to the royal name and peak, and what is greater, as a Christian and a follower of the orthodox faith.
We have been educated from infancy in sacred literature and laws, both ecclesiastical and secular, have not been legally and regularly accused of any public crime in episcopal hearing, and have certainly not been convicted.
And to avoid mentioning other things we could add, lest we seem to boast rather than speak the truth, we read that the Apostle said much about himself, compelled by the necessity of others' knowledge.
For often, we have spoken humbly to you, but could not obtain from you kind, peaceful, and honorable writings, so that we might somehow secure the peace and respect that we and our predecessors had with your predecessors.
We wrote to you through Bishop Actard, our envoy of gentleness, detailing individually and personally how inappropriate the things written to us in your name for the former Bishop Hincmar of Laon were.
We did not believe these writings came from you, thinking that, once the matter was discovered, you would retract what had been written to us thus far by others' instigation.
But, frustrated by vain hope, it turned out differently for us than we had expected.
At the beginning of the letter, which your esteemed paternity sent to us through Bishop Actardus, we found that you praised the commendable greatness of our charity and wisdom.
However, we also discovered that we were noted for hearing murmurs and tumultuous clamor of unjust reproach against your paternity.
Thus, while you praised our wisdom, you attempted to afflict us with more severe insults than usual, not out of foolishness but intentionally, demonstrating that we were delinquent in murmuring and clamoring against due charity.
You likened us to a vessel smeared with honey, and from the same source as the previous letters, these later ones offered us a harmful drink.
Confessing what we believed came from others' prompting, you admitted was yours.
In the previous letters, you called us perjurer, tyrant, perfidious, and a squanderer of church properties, although not confessed nor legally and regularly convicted in a judicial order.
In these letters, you accused us of the crime of murmuring and the stain of tumultuous clamor, citing the Lord rebuking carnal Israel through the prophet, where you accuse us because he did not bring about justice but only clamor (Isaiah 5).
And the Apostle says, "Let all bitterness, wrath, anger, clamor, and slander be put away from you" (Ephesians 4).
Murmuring is no less of an evil than those things for which you previously noted us, as the Apostle says, "Nor grumble, as some of them did and were destroyed by the serpents" (First Corinthians 10).
And as Blessed Gregory says, no one who murmurs is permitted to enter the kingdom of God.
From this, we can understand how grave a sin murmuring is, which bars the kingdom of God, just like those serious sins after whose enumeration the Apostle says, "Those who do such things will not inherit the kingdom of God" (Galatians 5).
And no, as you mentioned, we did not unfairly criticize your fatherhood with a loud outcry.
We simply responded with our own voice to what was written to us in your name, not with the voices of many, which often cause an uproar.
Because we did not believe that you sent such things and that they were dictated by the holy Roman Church, which has always been very discerning and cautious in all matters, we suggested that the holy seat is accustomed to correct with moderation and discretion according to each person's status and rank.
Therefore, if we spoke wrongly, bear witness to the wrongdoing.
But if we spoke rightly, why are you angry with us?
It is written, although Abraham is holy, as a man sanctified by God, he still said to God, "Will you destroy the righteous with the wicked? That is not like you, who judges all the earth" (Genesis 18), and the Lord did not take this ungraciously.
And you reproach us because, with humble placation, we suggested to you that it is not your place-not proven guilty, not legally and regularly convicted, and endowed with royal power by the grace of God-to accuse someone in writing as if they were a commoner proven guilty of crimes.
Knowing how serious it is to say to a brother, "You fool" (Matthew 5), which is less serious than what was imputed to us, and that no one should be slandered or cursed against divine law, especially not a king, as apostolic doctrine teaches, and in reverence for Saint David concerning Saul, who was already rejected by the Lord (First Samuel 26), and Solomon's wisdom, and the story of Naboth (First Maccabees 9).
We also found in your letters advice given to us, if it can be called advice, which is contrary to the example of the Lord and found against the decrees of the saints: namely, to use your words, to eagerly accept everything directed from the apostolic seat, which you preside over by God's grace.
For it is written to us in your name that we are perjurers, tyrants, faithless, and destroyers of ecclesiastical matters.
And should we eagerly accept this, embrace it with a grateful mind, and always receive it with humble intention?
Unless the writer perhaps wants to call us "silver Ethiopians" like the common people, implying that someone seems beautiful to us simply because they are called "pretty," and sing to themselves with Persius, "Whatever you tread on becomes a rose," and fall into that prophetic saying, "Woe to those who put bitter for sweet" Isaiah 5.
When the Lord responded to the Jews who said to Him, "Are we not right in saying that you are a Samaritan and have a demon?" He acknowledged by remaining silent, and patiently refuted what He heard falsely by saying: "I do not have a demon" John 8.
Following this example to the best of our ability, we humbly and patiently excused ourselves before your fatherhood for things we did not recognize in ourselves, lest by remaining entirely silent, we should admit by our silence and agreement to be what we were denoted, and be judged as confessed and convicted by our own confession.
And this encouragement, which we found in the letter delivered to us in your name by Bishop Actard, namely, that we should always receive with humble intention everything that comes to us from the apostolic seat, is found to be contrary not only to evangelical truth, as we have mentioned, but also to the decrees of the saints.
In whose decrees we read that one cannot be absolved who has declared himself to be the cause of death, which, if said about another, would be punished as false testimony, since anyone who is the cause of his own death is a greater murderer.
And hence they decreed Council of Valence, canon 4 that anyone who has said they are defiled by a mortal crime under the orders of deacon, priest, or bishop should be removed from the above-mentioned orders.
And if we were to agree by remaining silent to such things imposed upon us, we would not only exclude ourselves from royal governance but also from the communion of the Catholic Church.
Therefore, we should always eagerly receive, gratefully embrace, and humbly accept such writings from the Apostolic See and in your name.
As it is added in the same letters, according to the wise Solomon in Ecclesiastes 12, they seem to be like goads and nails driven deep, because they do not lightly touch the faults of wrongdoers, but pierce them.
We also refer to the words of the Wise One, who said: "Do not criticize anyone before you inquire, and when you have inquired, that is, tested them, correct justly" Sirach 11; just as Nathan first inquired of King David and, having tested him by questioning, corrected him: and when the reason for correction was lacking, he humbly worshiped, as we read in the sacred history in Second Samuel 7, 12.
Command and write what is fitting for your ministry and ours, just as your predecessors commanded and wrote to us and our predecessors, and we will receive with an eager mind and a grateful heart. However, letters in your name always pierce us without inquiry, that is, without testing, and they do not show sins, for which they unwillingly pierce, willingly confessed, or legally and regularly proven in judicial order: and when manifest and proven sins are lacking, they do not soothe with the encouragement and address of gentle exhortation.
The Lord reproves harsh rulers of the people here, saying: "But you ruled them with severity and power" Ezekiel 34. To whom the Apostle gave the rule of admonition, saying to each one: "Reprove, entreat, rebuke with all patience and teaching" Second Timothy 4, mix times with times, threats with kindness.
The sternness of a teacher, showing the loving concern of a father, should rebuke the undisciplined and restless more harshly, but encourage the obedient and patient to help them improve.
They should reprove and correct the negligent and disrespectful, and for serious sins, whether confessed voluntarily or proven through judicial order, judge them legally and appropriately according to the severity of the fault.
The Apostle did not want, says blessed Augustine (Homilies) on Repentance, chapter 4, a person to be judged by another based on arbitrary suspicion, or extraordinary judgment, but according to the law of God and the order of the Church, whether confessed voluntarily or accused and convicted.
Otherwise, why did he say: If anyone is named a brother, or a fornicator, or serving idols in First Corinthians chapter 6?
Because he wanted that naming to be understood as what is done when the sentence is declared with judicial order and integrity.
For if mere naming suffices, many innocents would be condemned: because often crimes are falsely attributed to someone.
Many good Christians remain silent and endure the sins of others they know, because they often lack evidence to prove what they know to ecclesiastical judges.
Although some things are true, judges may not easily believe them unless demonstrated by certain indications or proven by judicial order.
If they cannot be removed from the Church through judgment, they should be tolerated rather than avoided, to prevent anyone from perversely departing from the Church and binding themselves to hell.
What is written in those letters in your name, because your clergy have not patiently listened to our admonitions and corrections, shows they still lack some measure of perfect charity, of which the Apostle says: Charity is patient, kind, not inflated, not irritated, does not act wrongly, bears all things, endures all things in First Corinthians chapter 13.
If God had not chosen to honor your holy fatherhood, we would very much like to learn about love's measure and perfection in kindness, patience, humility, and endurance from your letters.
We could also learn this if, in response to our letters to you, you would tolerate our slight foolishness and support us.
As it is written in Second Corinthians 11.
Just as the great Peter, the first bishop of the apostolic and primary see, not only patiently but also joyfully accepted his reprimand from his co-apostle Paul.
He praised the letters in which he read he was reprimanded with the highest favor.
As it is written in Second Peter 3.
He could not have praised them so much unless he had read them and recognized his reprimand in them.
Because he praised them so greatly and accepted his just reprimand gratefully and patiently, he demonstrated this.
When he was reprimanded by his inferiors for going to the Gentiles, he did not respond with bare and arrogant words, expecting them to bear his actions most patiently.
Nor did he invoke his authority in their complaint, but instead appeased them with humble reasoning and even brought in witnesses in his cause of reprimand.
As it is written in Galatians 2.
For, as the blessed Gregory says, if he had invoked his authority in the faithful's complaint, he would not have been a teacher of gentleness.
If, therefore, the shepherd of the Church, the prince of the apostles, performing unique signs and miracles, did not disdain to humbly provide reasoning in his cause of reprimand, how much more, says the blessed Gregory, bishop of the apostolic see, should we sinners, when reprimanded for something, humbly appease our reprimanders with reasoning?
However, the letters sent to us in your name did not humble us, nor did they show that we sought reason and authority through reason.
Instead, they aimed to silence us with undue reproach.
By God's grace, we can still speak freely about the things imposed on us through letters sent in your name.
It is also written in those letters about Hincmar in this manner:
We wish, and by apostolic authority we command, that this Hincmar, bishop of Laon, relying on your power, come to the threshold of the saints and to our mercy.
When he arrives, let a suitable accuser also come, who cannot be dismissed by any legitimate authority: and then in our presence, and in the presence of the entire Roman see, the case will be thoroughly examined in a synodal assembly, and diligently investigated according to God and the constitutions of the holy canons proclaimed by the Spirit of God (Council of Africa, canon 105), and it will be concluded without any delay.
Although we found this statement contrary to the custom of your predecessors, which is to avoid introducing worldly pride into the Church, we did not doubt the intention, because human minds can easily mistake what is decided upon.
But we were very surprised where the writer of the letter delivered to us by Bishop Actard found it written that it should be commanded by apostolic authority that the king, corrector of the wicked and punisher of the guilty, and according to ecclesiastical and worldly laws avenger of crimes, should send a legally and regularly condemned criminal to Rome by his own power.
Especially one who, even before his deposition, was found in three synods to be acting against public order and peace, as is contained in the episcopal records sent to your paternity, and after his deposition, both by himself and by anyone he could, did not cease from his obstinacy.
But we are not surprised if, in the recent letters sent to us in your name, it is insinuated that someone legally and regularly condemned, who is not decreed by any laws to be restored by anyone to any rank or possessions before being found innocent in a provincial judgment-renewed by apostolic authority-may be found innocent, should he not be caught attempting to disturb public order and peace.
Our royal power comes to your aid in this, as zeal for rectitude is owed to the author condemned, not the clemency of resolution.
If these matters did not arise from the same origin but from the same effort as previous ones, in which it is contained that all things committed to the church of Hincmar, until he returned to his own, should be entrusted to us so they remain unharmed and incur no loss.
Therefore, as we wrote back to you, and now again have not hesitated to write to you, but the cause makes it necessary, because kings of the Franks, born from royal lineage, have been considered, not the deputies of bishops, but the lords of the land:
And as Leo and the Roman synod wrote, kings and emperors, whom divine power has commanded to be set over lands, have permitted the right of distinguishing matters to holy bishops according to divine constitutions, but have not been the stewards of bishops.
And Saint Augustine says, possessions are held by the laws of kings, but kings are not made stewards or agents of bishops by episcopal authority.
And the Lord commands to render unto Caesar the things that are Caesar's, and unto God the things that are God's (Matthew 22), who also paid the tax to the king (Matthew 17).
And the Apostle wanted kings to be served, wanted kings to be honored and not trampled upon.
He says, "Honor the king" (First Peter 2).
And again, "Let every soul be subject to the higher powers" (Romans 13); and a little earlier: "Therefore be subject out of necessity, not only for wrath but also for conscience' sake" (Romans 13).
If you look back at the records of your predecessors and those before them, you won't find directives like the ones in the letters sent to us in your name by Bishop Actard.
Our predecessors received nothing of the sort from your predecessors.
Therefore, we felt it necessary to write to you about a few of these matters.
Saint Gregory, a pontiff of the apostolic see known for his life and wisdom, and who is revered and emulated worldwide, wrote to the Frankish kings Theodoric and Theodebert, our predecessors, about the unjust treatment of a certain bishop.
Unlike what you wrote to us about someone who was justly deposed based on his merits, Gregory wrote in this manner (Book 7, Letter 120, Indiction 2):
"Our brother and fellow bishop Ursinus, the bishop of the city of Turin, is said to be suffering severe injustice within his parishes, which lie within the borders of your kingdom. It is reported that, contrary to ecclesiastical practices and priestly dignity, and against the decrees of the sacred canons, another bishop was ordained there without any crime on his part. And because it seemed insufficient to add illicit acts to illicit acts, it is also reported that the properties of his church were taken away. If this is true, it is intolerable for a man to be oppressed when he has done no wrong. Therefore, after offering a greeting of paternal affection, we ask that your Excellency, out of love for ecclesiastical reverence and consideration of fairness, grant what you can freely give, and kindly allow our intercession. Ensure that justice is upheld in all matters for him, as we trust in your sense of fairness, and correct what was done illicitly once the truth is revealed. For the benefit of your soul, may our exhortation find a place with you, etc."
Furthermore, he wrote to the Roman Exarch, of lesser dignity than we are by the grace of God of royal power, about a certain bishop in this manner (Book 1, Letter...).
It has come to our attention that Blandus, the bishop of Ortona, has been held for a long time in Ravenna by your excellency.
As a result, the church is without a leader, and the people are like a flock without a shepherd.
Children there are dying without baptism because of sins.
We do not believe that your excellency would hold him without probable cause, so it is necessary to hold a synod to determine publicly if any crime is charged against him.
If a fault is found in him that warrants his removal from the priesthood, we must seek another ordination, so the Church of God does not remain uncultivated and destitute of essential things for the Christian religion.
However, if your excellency finds otherwise, allow him to return to his church so he may fulfill his duty to the souls entrusted to him.
Following the instructions of your blessed predecessor Gregory, for those not legally and regularly deposed by synodal judgment for their crimes, compared with the writings sent to us in your name, from him who is legally and regularly deposed for his excesses by synodal judgment, let us send him, empowered by our authority, to Rome, to judge which should be followed.
We believe your authority will judge, so we follow what your predecessors wrote according to the Scripture and the preaching of the elders, rather than what the author of the mentioned letter written in your name has fabricated.
For blessed Augustine says in the book to Januarius, letter 119, chapter 19:
"All such things, which are neither contained in the authority of the Holy Scriptures, nor found to be established in the councils of bishops, nor strengthened by the custom of the universal Church, I consider should be cut off."
And Saint Leo, regarding those things contained in the sacred canons, decreed them to be so established and promulgated by the apostolic see that they cannot be overturned by any reasoning, stating that whatever is different from their constitution shall be entirely void of authority.
As if he were saying with Paul, "For the apostolic see cannot be contrary to itself in its constitutions. Even if we, or an angel from heaven, preach to you a gospel other than what we preached to you, let them be under God's curse" (Galatians 1).
But as it is read in the controversy of Quintilian, the flowers poisoned by the cunning of tricksters caused the death of bees, which were supposed to make honey.
Blessed Peter shows from the sacred Scriptures, speaking about Paul's letters, "which ignorant and unstable people distort, as they do the other Scriptures, to their own destruction" (Second Peter 3).
And concerning the ecclesiastical traditions, Saint Innocent (in his letter 29 to Decentius) said, "When each person considers not what has been handed down, but what seems right to them, it results in different practices being observed or celebrated in different places or churches, causing scandal among the people, who, not knowing the ancient traditions corrupted by human presumption, think that they or their churches do not agree or that some contradiction has been introduced by the apostles or apostolic men." Against this disease, Saint Celestine provided a healthy antidote for all, saying (letter 2), "No priest is allowed to be ignorant of the canons, nor to do anything that could contradict the rules of the Fathers. For what worthy thing will be preserved by us if the norm of decretal constitutions is broken by the license of some individuals permitted to the people?"
And Saint Gelasius in his decrees stated that our Fathers, namely the Catholic and learned pontiffs, in every sect raised up at any time, whatever they established once for faith, for truth, for Catholic and Apostolic communion, according to the path of the Scriptures and the preaching of the elders, wanted it to remain unshaken and firm thereafter, nor did they allow what had been established to be reconsidered in the same cause by any recent presumption.
Therefore, it must be seen what this path of the Holy Scriptures and the preaching of the elders define.
For we read in sacred history that the Lord said through the prophet to King Jehoshaphat: "You give help to the wicked, and you join in friendship with those who hate the Lord, and therefore you deserved the wrath of the Lord, but good works were found in you, because you removed the groves from the land of Judah" (Second Chronicles 19).
And in the Gospel, once and a second and a third time warned, and not obedient to proper correction, the Lord commands to be treated as a Gentile and a tax collector (Matthew 18).
And blessed Gregory in his decrees, as you can find in the acts of the synod, defines the usurper not only of others' property, but also of the church committed to him, as anathematized.
Yet if another acts in this way, the one who presides over the Church, if he either orders this to be done himself or neglects to punish it with the proper notice when done without his order, he anathematizes him.
We can hardly be amazed at the writer of the letter, delivered to us in your name, who produced this law engraved in gold.
This law was not written by the Lord's own finger, nor inspired by Him, nor given through angels by the hand of a mediator.
It was not decreed by a pagan, nor introduced by a Christian, nor decided by a churchman.
This law, under this sky, was not penned by the hand of justice in ink, nor proclaimed by the Spirit of the living God.
It commands me, a king appointed by God, marked by a double-edged sword, to be an avenger of the guilty and a defender of the innocent, as the Apostle explains in Romans chapter thirteen.
For the praise of the good, I am to be an advocate of the guilty, condemned, and anathematized, ordering Hincmar-a transgressor of sacred laws, critic of the holy priesthood, detractor of royal dignity, disturber of the kingdom, perjurer, author of seditions, afflicter of the church entrusted to him, sacrilegious fraudster, destroyer of ecclesiastical properties, scandalizer of bishops and all our people, invader of others' properties, and self-condemned by acting against his own subscriptions and professions-to be brought to Rome relying on royal power.
Who, therefore, vomited this entire law from hell?
What abyss belched it from its hidden and dark burrows?
Against it, the sacred writings have shown us the path to follow, with the form given, which we should imprint on ourselves.
The prophet cried out to the king of Israel, saying: Your servant went out to fight hand to hand.
When one man fled, someone brought him to me and said: Guard this man; if he escapes, your life will be for his life, or you will weigh out a talent of silver.
But while I was distracted here and there, suddenly he disappeared.
And the king of Israel said to him: This is your judgment, which you have decreed.
Then he immediately wiped the dust from his face, and the king of Israel recognized that he was one of the prophets.
He said to him: This is what the Lord says to you: Because you let go of a man deserving death from your hand, your life will be for his life, and your people for his people.
So the king of Israel returned to his home, sullen and angry, and came to Samaria.
(First Kings, chapter 20).
What madness has seized you, knowing that Christ said, the power and wisdom of God, "By me kings reign, and lawmakers decree what is just"?
(Proverbs, chapter 8).
And the sacred canons, as we believe, and as we often read in apostolic letters, are established by the Spirit of God and consecrated by the reverence of the whole world.
Therefore, let us see what the holy canons and sacred laws decree about such things.
The holy African council (Canon 29) says:
It should be requested that the leaders of the land establish that if any cleric of any rank is condemned by the judgment of bishops for any crime, it should not be permitted for him to be defended either by the churches he presided over or by any person, under the penalty of loss of money and honor, without regard to age or sex.
And then Valens, Gratian, and Valentinian decreed (Codex Theodosianus):
That anyone who has been removed from the episcopal position and name by the judgment of priests, and if found to be acting against public order or peace, trying to reclaim the priesthood from which he was expelled, should live a hundred miles away from the city he corrupted, according to the law of blessed memory Gratian.
He should be separated from their gatherings, from whose society he is excluded.
And it should be illegal for such persons, by the tenor of this law, to approach our sacred mysteries and obtain writings, and all writings obtained by persons who have been cast out from the priesthood for fault should remain invalid.
Those who defend them should know that they will not be free from reproach if they promise them support, who do not seem to have earned divine judgment.
Hence also Pope Leo (letter 47 to Pulcheria).
He asked the principal authority to move Eutyches, the instigator of scandal and depravity, further from that place, which was too close to the city of Constantinople, so that he would not benefit from the frequent comforts of those he had led into impiety.
And Gregory (Book 10, Letter 33): He decreed that Paul, the former bishop of the city of Diadema, should be sent to a monastery until he restored everything he had squandered or taken from the church's property.
If, after his deposition, he shamelessly and perversely spoke of the bishopric or attempted to aspire to it again with any presumption, he should be deprived of the communion of the Lord's body and blood and confined in a monastery until the day of his death to do penance, under the supervision of John, bishop of Prima Justiniana, so that he might learn to cleanse the stains of his crime with worthy tears.
This was according to the law of Emperor Justinian, who decreed in the Book of Constitutions that if any deposed bishop dared to enter the city from which he had been expelled or leave the place where he was ordered to stay, he should be handed over to a monastery in another province, so that, living in the monastery, he may correct the sins he committed in the priesthood.
These laws, promulgated and decreed by emperors and kings, namely our predecessors, we are obliged to preserve intact and inviolable, as the bishops of the apostolic see wrote to the lords and princes of the earth.
For Leo said to Emperor Leo (Letter 92): You must, he said, consider without hesitation that royal power has been conferred upon you, not only for the governance of the world but especially for the protection of the Church, so that by suppressing wicked endeavors, you may defend what has been rightly established and restore true peace to what has been disturbed.
And Gelasius to Anastasius (Letter 10, at the end): Indeed, Emperor Augustus, if anyone attempted anything against public laws, which God forbid, it could not be admitted by any means.
The laws issued by the supreme authority, which were adhered to by all bishops and even the popes of the apostolic see, should be followed by the leaders of the primary see.
Blessed Leo demonstrated this in a letter to Emperor Leo, stating in letter 80 that he should not oppose imperial edicts or the decrees established by his predecessors according to the Scriptures and the teachings of the elders.
He says,
"If I rebuild what I have destroyed, I make myself a transgressor, and I subject myself to the conditions of punishment that not only the authority of the blessed memory of Emperor Martian established, but that I also affirmed with my own consent."
Saint Gelasius also wrote to Emperor Anastasius in letter 10, at the beginning:
"If, as far as public order is concerned, the bishops of religion themselves obey your laws, recognizing the empire given to you by divine disposition, so that they do not seem to resist sentences even in worldly matters, with what affection, I ask, should you obey them, who are assigned to administer the holy mysteries?"
We also, following the exhortation of Blessed Gelasius, wish to promptly and willingly carry this out in matters pertaining to their ministry, with all priests rightly handling divine matters, especially the leader of that see, whom the supreme divinity has willed to be preeminent among all priests, and whom the continuous piety of the Church has celebrated. As our orthodox emperor and king predecessors have done, so that the pontiff of the apostolic see and the other priests of the Lord may bestow upon us what has been established by God. As Blessed Gelasius himself says, in the tome of anathema, at the end.
Because Christ, mindful of human frailty, in His magnificent stewardship, designed everything to suit the salvation of His followers.
He wisely distinguished the roles and dignities, separating the duties of each power, desiring His followers to be saved by humble medicine and not to be caught again by human pride.
Thus, Christian rulers would need priests for eternal life, and priests would rely on imperial arrangements for the management of temporal matters.
This way, spiritual actions would be distinct from worldly affairs, and those serving God would not be entangled in secular business.
Second Letter to Timothy, Chapter 2.
Conversely, someone involved in secular matters should not be seen presiding over divine affairs.
This would ensure the modesty of both orders, preventing either from becoming arrogant.
It would also align the appropriate professions with the nature of their actions.
As the Apostle says, every high priest is chosen from among men and is appointed to act on behalf of men in relation to God, to offer gifts and sacrifices for sins.
Letter to the Hebrews, Chapter 5.
This applies not only to the people but also because he himself is surrounded by weakness and must offer sacrifices for his own sins.
Likewise, it is the king's duty to manage the affairs of the kingdom, as the divinely inspired writings teach.
Therefore, according to the path of the Holy Scriptures and the preaching of the elders, and as the holy Gelasius also attests in Letter 10, there are two principal powers by which this world is governed: the sacred authority of the priests and the royal power.
Through the King of kings and the supreme priest of all priests, who alone could be both king and priest, the lawgivers decree just laws.
Proverbs, Chapter 8.
These laws have been called eternal by the principal powers, and the holy canons are established by the Spirit of God and consecrated by the reverence of the whole world.
As the blessed Ambrose says to Valentinian: The emperor enacts laws, which he himself must first observe, because what he prescribes for others, he prescribes for himself, so that no one would be free to judge otherwise.
And the blessed Augustine says: Once the laws are signed and confirmed, judges must adhere to them and cannot judge otherwise.
As part of your pontifical ministry, we seek to follow your guidance through our royal ministry.
Allow us to uphold the traditions established by our predecessors, and in preserving these actions, let us validate our current practices.
How can the laws of the princes be considered eternal if they disappear with each passing prince?
Pope Symmachus writes to Aeonius in his first letter: Just as the power of the Trinity is one and indivisible, the priesthood is one despite different bishops.
How can the statutes of former bishops be violated by their successors?
If there is a variety of judgments, it undermines the sacred religion itself.
Everything established by the priests of the Lord should be perpetual.
This only happens if a successor validates the acts of their predecessor, thereby confirming and making them valid.
How can we show proper reverence to the vicars of the blessed apostle Peter if their commands are dissolved when they pass away?
He says that all things established by the priests of the Lord, who receive divine guidance like Moses, should be perpetual.
This does not apply to those unjust laws condemned by the prophet in Isaiah chapter 10.
Nevertheless, what is established by the vicars of the blessed Peter should remain unshaken.
As Leo says in his third sermon on the anniversary: Neither excessive severity nor leniency is present where nothing is established unless it stems from the fairness of the blessed Peter.
We know these things are canonical and confirmed by apostolic authority, as stated by Gelasius in his tenth letter to Dard.
, in the beginning.
He confirms each synod by his authority and maintains it with continuous moderation, following the leadership given to the blessed Apostle Peter by the Lord's command, which the Church has always followed and still follows.
And a little earlier: We trust that no true Christian is unaware that the decrees of any synod, approved by the universal Church, should be carried out by the first see more than any other.
And again, in letter six to all bishops: Since we wish that nothing contrary to the reverence of the beneficial rules should be allowed, and since the Apostolic See, with the Lord's favor, strives to uphold the purpose set by the fatherly canons, it is very improper for anyone, whether bishops or others, to reject this observance, which they see the See of the blessed Peter both follow and teach:
It is very fitting that the whole body of the Church should agree on this observance, which they see flourishing where the Lord placed the leadership of the entire Church.
And concerning the sacred laws, which the Catholic Church observes along with the holy canons, Gelasius, as mentioned before, says in his letter to Emperor Anastasius, letter ten: As far as public order is concerned, knowing that the empire has been given to you by divine disposition, the bishops of religion also obey your laws, so that they may not seem to oppose your judgments even in worldly matters.
Since both ecclesiastical and secular sacred laws decree about the condemned bishop and synodal council, it is not within our royal authority to direct anyone condemned by the judgment of the sacred canons and the definition of the Apostolic See.
As you can find in the acts of the synod, anathematized, relying on our power, the sacred canons clearly define, along with the laws of Justinian and the edicts of other Catholic emperors, how, for what, and by whom a bishop should be judged.
After judgment, it specifies what and how it should be dealt with by the Apostolic See, which we unhesitatingly and appropriately grant.
From these definitions, no one is allowed to deviate.
As Saint Hilarus the pope says, "It is no less a sin to violate the sanctifications of holy traditions than to rush into an injury against the Lord himself."
Therefore, because the Lord says through the prophet, "The lips of a priest should guard knowledge, and people should seek instruction from his mouth, for he is the messenger of the Lord of hosts" Malachi 2:7, do not allow us to write in the name of your authority what is not contained in the sacred laws, established by the wisdom of God, and in the holy rules proclaimed by the same Spirit.
The prophet says again, that is, the priest commanding: "When you hear a word from my mouth, you shall give them warning from me" Ezekiel 3:17; from me, he says, and not from you. Those who speak from their own heart are rebuked because "he who speaks from himself seeks his own glory" John 7:18.
Therefore, as we have stated earlier, do not allow us to write orders or threats of excommunication in your name or by the authority of the Apostolic See, against the path of the sacred Scriptures, the preaching of the elders, and the constitutions of the sacred laws and holy canons. From now on, we pray, by any impulse, because you know, and we know, that everything is invalid if it differs from their constitution.
Saint Leo says (Sermon 3 on the anniversary)
From the Lord to the most blessed Peter, "I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven" (Matthew 16).
This power was also given to the other apostles, extending to all the leaders of the Church.
It's not without reason that this authority is entrusted to one, even though it is communicated to all.
It is specifically given to Peter because his example is meant to guide all Church leaders.
Therefore, Peter's privilege remains wherever a judgment is made according to his fairness.
It is clear that Peter's privilege does not remain where a judgment is not made according to his fairness.
When it is said "wherever," it means no place and no Church leader is exempt from making judgments according to Peter's fairness, nor are they praised for making judgments against it.
And because Peter's privilege applies universally, should we follow commands or accept judgments that are not pronounced according to his fairness and thus deprived of his privilege?
Blessed Gregory emphasizes what all bishops should follow and what the children of the Church should hold and observe regarding episcopal judgment.
Therefore, command and judge by the privilege of the great Peter, according to his fairness in judgment, so that, as his co-apostle says, your ministry may not be blamed (Second Corinthians 6).
We also, in our royal ministry, wish to observe what is written, "Children, obey your parents in the Lord" (Ephesians 6), meaning that which is commanded or judged by the Lord, saying to each one, who for the fathers the apostles of the Church, the apostolic men are born, "But you, hearing, will report to them from me" (Ezekiel 3).
Indeed, divine instruction teaches us that even Balaam, though persistently sought after by King Balak and swayed by the allure of greed and corrupted advice, could not be persuaded or forced by any means or influence to speak against Israel in the judgment of justice, other than what he heard from the Lord.
Numbers 22.
Regarding the letters sent to us in your name, stating that when Hincmar comes to Rome, an appropriate accuser should also come, who cannot be legitimately rejected, we reply that although this recommendation has no foundation in reason or authority.
If Hincmar alone is considered lawless among you, under a new law contrary to both ancient public and ecclesiastical orders, and is held by a new order and custom, so that he can only be judged by you and at Rome for these offenses, about which there are clear decrees of sacred canons and laws, which, as Leo says, cannot be overturned by any reasoning.
Since even in matters of faith, as Gelasius says, any bishop can, according to the rule of previously condemned error, separate anyone from Catholic communion.
And I, thus free from all accusations, not only from those in which the permission to accuse oneself is legally and regularly denied, but also from those in which accusation in personal causes is not denied, so that, as the laws and rules command, matters originating in a province cannot be terminated elsewhere, and according to the Antiochian canons, should not undergo the examination of provincial synods.
If you secure for us the means, with the will and consent of our beloved nephew, your emperor, against whose love and due honor, if he strives to show mutual love and appropriate honor to us, we do not wish to go there.
With the Lord's cooperation, peace in our kingdom against pagans obtained by virtue or any disposition of God, we will not delay coming to Rome at a suitable time.
Because we have legally accused him in a synod of bishops from many provinces for specific reasons, we will show that we are suitable accusers.
We will bring with us many credible witnesses of different orders and dignities to sufficiently prove our accusations.
Finally, we learned from the letters delivered to us by Bishop Actardus that you have neither read nor heard what we previously sent to your paternal care through him.
So, we are writing again what we wrote then.
We beg you, in honor of Almighty God and in reverence of the holy apostles, not to send us and the bishops and leaders of our kingdom such letters of dishonor and commands as we have received from your name until now.
Do not compel us to disregard your dishonorable commands and letters or to dishonor your envoys, whom we wish to obey in matters pertaining to your ministry, if indeed it is your ministry.
We say this out of respect for your privilege because we truly desire to obey you in all things suitably and properly, as the vicar of Blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles.
We wish to avoid any other outcome by all means.
We humbly ask your holiness to avoid this as well, so that you do not force us and our people, who are very unwilling, to turn to what is found to be held by us in the Fifth Universal Synod, from the apostolic see, as we read in the apostolic letters, especially in the synodic letter of Blessed Gregory to the four patriarchs, and in his other letters, together with the four preceding ones, praised and accepted.
We haven't included this in our letters as an example because we wanted to ensure we could turn the harshness of your commands toward us into kindness.
We understand that what's written in the name of the Apostolic See, following the Holy Scriptures, the preaching of the elders, and the decrees of the orthodox, must be adhered to.
Anything compiled or fabricated otherwise must be rejected and refuted.
If I have written back to you, most reverend father, in a way that seems foolish or inappropriate, it is because I felt compelled to do so.
However, we pray to the Almighty Lord to inspire your heart to treat us kindly.
We hope it will no longer be necessary to write to you in this manner, but instead, we can humbly and devotedly submit ourselves in veneration of the apostles and your apostolic leadership.
May Almighty God preserve you for many years for the honor, salvation, and exaltation of His holy Church, most holy and reverend father in the Lord.
Letter Nine
TO THE SAME,
Sent at the same time as the previous one
To the most holy and reverend Father Adrian, supreme pontiff and universal pope, CHARLES, by the grace of God king and your spiritual son.
Because letters in the name of your holy fatherhood were brought to us by the venerable Archbishop Actard, we felt it necessary to respond at length.
Contrary to our usual practice, we found it essential to write our response on a sheet signed with our seal, so it can be more clearly read, and the reasons that compelled us to respond to you can be fully understood by the reader.
May your holy fatherhood receive this response kindly and not with disdain, as it is written by us not with defiance but with a peaceful mind, as you will find in the same sheet.
We beseech you, in honor of Almighty God and in veneration of the holy apostles, not to send us and the bishops and nobles of our kingdom such letters of dishonor and commands as we have received in your name up to now.
Rather, may we be permitted to humbly and devoutly submit our necks and hearts to your apostolic pontificate, in veneration of God and the holy apostles, as we desire.
May Almighty God deign to preserve you through the course of years for the honor, salvation, and exaltation of His holy Church, O most holy and reverend father in the Lord.