Sermon of Saint Radbod on Saint Switbert.
Dear brothers, as we prepare to celebrate this special day of joy, remembering our blessed patron Saint Switbert, we must be ready for every good work and eager in spirit.
First, we should listen to the commandments of divine law and strive to follow them as best as we can in our actions, so we can teach others.
This is what our Lord Jesus Christ did, as it is written: "Jesus began to do and to teach" (Acts 1:1).
Otherwise, our teaching will be useless and empty if we undermine it by doing nothing.
For what benefit is it for someone to listen well but act poorly?
Or what good does it do if someone shows others the way but continues to stray in their own behavior?
Therefore, following in the footsteps of our Redeemer, let us eagerly listen to all good things; and with worthy actions, let us complete what we have heard, then move on to teach others, offering them the teachings and examples of good things.
To make this possible without delay, we should remember the works of our Father, whom we mentioned earlier: he provided an example for his listeners in everything he taught and never suggested anything be done in the Church that he himself did not first demonstrate.
To make this clear to those who wish to follow him, let his deeds, pleasing to God and necessary for all who hear them, be publicly recited so that the people of Christ may be edified by them and always rejoice in the glorious prayers of such a man.
However, since some things he did are known only to ancient times after God, as it is proven that he came to our land from the province of the English, the writings of the venerable priest Bede should be brought forth, who, in the Chronicles of the English, among other things, left this written about this most holy man.
In the time of Saint Willibrord, Bishop of Utrecht, the brothers engaged in ministry in Frisia selected a man named Switbert.
Known for his modesty and gentle heart, he was chosen to be ordained as their bishop.
Switbert was sent to Britain where, upon their request, the very reverend Bishop Wilfrid, then exiled in the region of the Mercians, ordained him.
At that time, there was no bishop in Kent because Theodore had passed away, and his successor, Berhtwald, had not yet returned from overseas where he went to be ordained.
After receiving his bishopric, Switbert returned from Britain and soon withdrew to the people of the Boructuarii, guiding many of them to the truth through his preaching.
However, not long after, the Boructuarii were conquered by the ancient Saxons, scattering those who had embraced the word.
The bishop, along with some others, sought refuge with Pippin, who, at the request of his wife Blithrude, provided him a place on an island in the Rhine, known in their language as "in littore."
There, Switbert established a monastery, which his successors still hold, and led a deeply devout life until his passing.
We believe no one would doubt that Bede mentioned these things about this holy man, unless perhaps someone, being preoccupied, either did not read the book where these details are recorded or overlooked them while reading.
We should not doubt at all that Switbert was fully engaged in the Christian faith, deserving his role as a shepherd of Christ's flock among the esteemed figures of the Church of God, which shone brightly in those days among the English and the Gauls.
If he had not been well-trained in pastoral duties, so many of Christ’s flock would not have been entrusted to his care.
Furthermore, unless he was a seasoned soldier, strong and fearless in the face of martyrdom, he would never have been appointed as the highest leader in Christ's army, nor as the chief centurion of the divine law's army.
Now that we've laid out these allegorical preliminaries, let's explore in a moral sense the exercises that made this remarkable soldier invincible, which can especially be seen in his pastoral duties.
In these duties, whether a roaring lion or a lurking wolf threatens Christ's sheep, if the vigilant shepherd either avoids the traps or bravely fends off the attack, he will safely return the flock to the Lord's fold.
However, if he never lays down his arms during daily routines, and either repels the enemy from the camp or triumphs in open field combat, he will later rule securely within the walls of the holy city.
We certainly don't doubt that the blessed Switbert achieved these things in both scenarios.
While serving as a bishop in the Church, he either withdrew his brothers from deceptive persuasions or recalled them from public disputes, keeping the fiercest lion and the most cunning wolf away from the Lord's flock.
When he defended those oppressed by the power of kings or harassed by the cruelty of princes with the sword of God's word and the shield of faith against tyrannical persecution, he, as an outstanding leader, led his soldiers back to the camp unharmed.
Therefore, if you want to know what weapons our leader used in daily encounters, recognize that they were not man-made but purely spiritual.
He wasn't burdened with iron but was girded with faith, hope, and charity; holding David's sling and its stone, striking the terrifying Philistine on the forehead, and rescuing all of Israel from the threat of death.
Moreover, don't think that he ever put aside such weapons, for he was adorned with them in peace just as he stood armed in war.
He was always humble, gentle and mild, patient in adversity, and modest in prosperity.
He was remarkable for his purity, energetic in self-restraint, sober in watchfulness, and steadfast in prayer.
When judging, he spoke fairly and without bias; in compassion, he empathized sincerely, not stubbornly.
He never coveted what others had but was very generous with his own possessions.
He strongly opposed vice in people but warmly embraced the individuals themselves.
His words were as sweet as honey, his preaching was delightful, his gatherings were full of spiritual nourishment, and his companionship felt angelic.
He rejected all evils as if they were deadly poisons and cherished all good things as if they were the aromas of paradise.
In conclusion, he was entirely perfect and completely filled with God.
These, brothers, were the weapons of our most blessed patron, Switbert, in both adversity and prosperity: with these, he fought every battle and triumphed everywhere.
For he did not wrestle against flesh and blood, but against rulers and authorities, against the powers of this world's darkness, and against the spiritual forces of evil in the heavenly realms.
Therefore, let us give thanks to Almighty God on this day of the solemnity of this holy bishop, praying together and asking that, as we proclaim his glorious life on earth, we may be worthy to enjoy his patronage in heaven.
Amen.