Sermon on the Life of Saint Honoratus by Bishop of Arles.
Preface
Dear friends, today is a day dedicated to the collective sorrows of the faithful.
As long as the Lord grants me life, this day will always come with both heavy bitterness and profound dignity.
Today, we mourn the passing of the bishop of this church, Honoratus, of blessed memory.
Anything I might add to my speech might seem absurd.
If I say, "He has gone to the stars," even while on earth, he was already among God's most brilliant stars.
If I say, "He stands with Christ," when did he ever not stand with Him in his life?
His entire life echoed Elijah's words: "The Lord lives, before whom I stand today" while speaking from First Kings eighteen, verse fifteen.
Should I say, "He has left earthly things," when, as the Apostle says, his existence was always in heaven while writing to the Philippians, chapter three, verse twenty?
So, in essence, whatever I say about such a man seems inadequate due to his greatness.
Joys and sorrows conflict.
Remembering him is sweet; being without him is punishment.
Thus, I am torn between two emotions.
On one hand, his merits urge me to speak; on the other, our shared loss draws me to tears.
Forgive me if, with these conflicting emotions, my speech cannot adequately serve both.
Whatever memory suggests in praise, pain claims it amid our loss.
Even if I had perfect clarity and my tongue could perfectly express my mind, could my words do more justice to his praises than your own thoughts?
I believe no one sees his grace as anything less than what exceeds the most eloquent speech.
As Scripture says, "the memory of the righteous is always with praises" while reflecting on Proverbs chapter ten, verse seven, and we cannot remember men of great merit without praise. I will offer, as best as I can, some of the things your loving hearts contemplate about him.
Your understanding truly supports my efforts, and even if I struggle to find the right words, your hearts will eloquently express their own thoughts.
It is said: Wisdom is praised at the end.
This implies that a wise person's words are celebrated at the conclusion of their speech.
Additionally, it is advised: Do not praise a person during their life.
And again: Do not praise anyone before their death, as stated in the Book of Sirach, chapter eleven, verse thirty.
It suggests: Praise after death; for the praises of the living can lead to vain boasting for the praised and flattery for the one praising.
However, praising the deceased is beneficial in many ways: first, because when the one we might flatter is absent, all praise is directed to the giver of grace; then, because only the admiration of virtue remains, removing any suspicion of flattery.
Therefore, praising the deceased in the holy gathering of the faithful is both edifying and free from boasting.
The merits of the one being praised also increase, as many benefit from their praise.
I am not concerned about being perceived as overly favorable, because nothing I say can truly capture his virtues, and everyone considers him their own, feels him as their own, and believes him to be their own.
Yet, I do not attempt to portray the life of such a great man relying on my own talent or eloquence: for even an ancient eloquent author would not only fail to embellish it but would be overwhelmed by the subject's significance.
Your love encourages me; your affection gives me the confidence to speak about him.
The speech will be enlivened, we believe, by his merits, even if with modest intellect; and what is expressed in words will be elevated by deeds, enriched by the love that resides in your hearts, dwelling in him.
Chapter One: The Nobility of Honoratus the Consular. The Young Man is Baptized.
In the field of oratory, it's common to start by praising someone's homeland and origins when speaking about their life.
This is often done to make up for any lack of personal virtues by highlighting the glory of their ancestors.
However, in Christ, we are all united, and being counted among the children of God is the highest form of nobility.
The honor of earthly origins doesn't add to our dignity unless it's set aside.
In heaven, no one is more glorious than someone who forsakes their ancestral lineage to be known only as a child of Christ.
Therefore, I won't speak of his family's secular honors or the nobility that led to the consulship, a prestigious status he disdained with a nobler spirit.
He didn't take pride in his ancestors' honors, as his love for truth made him no longer desire his own.
Instead, I'll focus on how, with great faith, he sought baptism in his youth and wisely avoided death.
He anticipated being deprived of life before baptism and longed fervently for his life to be renewed.
His childhood was sweet, his boyhood modest, and his adolescence serious.
He excelled in every stage of life with grace and virtue, making one truly believe he was guided by divine instruction.
He learned without any family pressure.
With God's help, he maintained his baptism without concern for others, and remarkably, he turned alone, without a guide.
I repeat, without a guide; despite opposition from his homeland, his father, and his entire family.
For grace touched everyone's hearts, and when Christ claimed him, the world eagerly embraced him in all his relations.
Some were drawn by his sweetness; others captivated by his companionship; and others admired his secular virtues in various youthful activities.
As numerous as the graces of his former life had been, just as many were the ties holding him back from conversion.
Everyone feared that a shared family honor might be lost.
Truly, who ever saw that appearance and didn't consider it their own?
What garments hadn't he once adorned?
It seemed like a splendid gem and a common glory for all was being taken from them all at once-his homeland, his family, and his parents.
They believed these things shouldn't be changed or improved, but rather thought they were fading away.
And thus arose the reason that, because his father saw him approach everything he did with vigor, he delayed his baptism as long as possible, fearing he would be completely consumed by a love for religion, which eventually happened.
However, his longing and love for Christ grew stronger, and overcoming his father's objections, the devoted son embraced baptism.
Even as a catechumen, he shaped himself with the foundational teachings of faith, rejecting frivolity out of respect for his future baptism, honoring clerics as fathers, and sometimes aiding the poor with his youthful resources.
Whatever his age could offer, and certainly more than novelty could desire, he gave with generous compassion.
Even then, in small ways, he was contemplating giving everything away and simultaneously offering all he had.
With these exercises, the catechumen's strong faith propelled him toward baptism.
Hence, his cautious father, anxious with earthly affection, tried to lure him with various pleasures, draw him into youthful activities, entangle him with worldly vanities, and almost rejuvenate himself through a bond with his young son.
He engaged him in hunting and various games, and armed him with all the delights of youth to subdue that stage of life.
Not without reason did his secular father fear losing him, whom he cherished as unique among the other most adorned youths.
But above all, his paramount concern was safeguarding baptism.
The young man dismissed what his elderly father cherished, always reminding himself: This life is pleasing, but deceptive.
In churches, different teachings are shared, while my ears hear other commands:
There, modesty, self-control, peace, and decency are taught; here, unrestrained indulgence is nurtured.
There, piety thrives; here, physical exercise.
There, Christ invites us to the eternal kingdom; here, the devil entices us to the temporary.
Everything in the world is vanity and the desire of the eyes, and the world passes away along with its desires; but whoever does the will of God remains forever, just as He remains forever.
So let us hurry to free ourselves from these traps while we are still less ensnared.
Things that have been tied for a long time are hard to untie.
It's easier to pull out tender roots than to cut down strong ones.
Save your soul on the mountain, lest evil thoughts catch you.
The poison of pleasure spreads quickly; the freedom gained through Christ's grace must be preserved.
Others admire gold and silver.
In my view, metals rule over those who rule.
Others possess lands and slaves without freeing their own soul.
Others revel in honors, yet they suppress the honor of God's image within them:
For me, it's enough not to be a slave to vices; for me, health is joy; for me, wisdom is a partner; for me, virtues are enjoyment.
Let Christ be my treasure, who will exchange fleeting joys for better ones and provide in this life both delight in learning and adornment, and through these, make one worthy of heavenly kingdoms.
Such reflection did not lead to long delays; instead, the spark of conversion, fueled by these encouragements, burst into flame.
Submitting my neck to the yoke of the Lord's service, I shook off the yoke of freedom, understanding that the greatest form of captivity is the license of youth.
Luxurious locks are trimmed to short hair.
The splendor of clothing shifts to the brilliance of the mind.
The beauty of a fair neck is covered by stiff garments.
Joy turns into calmness, the vigor of the body is replaced by the strength of the spirit.
Physical beauty fades with fasting, and what was once full of youthful vitality becomes full of seriousness.
And what more shall I say?
Suddenly, he seemed completely different than before, so much so that his father mourned as if he had lost a son.
In truth, it was a complete mortification of the body, but for him, it was a life of the spirit.
This caused total persecution from his parents.
He only defied his father when he claimed to be a son of God the Father, as ordained in him, just as Solomon commanded, with love.
For the prophet indeed proclaimed under God's voice: "Set love in order in me" (Song of Solomon 2:4).
He truly set it in order, and under the arrangement of love, he first sought to love God and then his neighbor.
The father's old age felt it was being condemned by the conversion of that youth.
He confronted, resisted, and threatened, yet none of these actions shook the youthful spirit that relied on God.
Chapter Two: Travels with Brother Venantius---His Passing---Honoratus and Venantius Leave Their Homeland---Pilgrimages to Sacred Places
The Lord, the Comforter, supported his novice and quickly brought one of his own brothers into the community.
Inspired by his example, the elder brother followed the younger, and in the brief time he was with them, he not only became part of the community but also matched him in virtue.
This led to friendly competitions between them in their dedication: whose mind was more inclined to piety, whose diet was simpler, whose speech was more pleasant, whose clothing was rougher; who spoke less, who prayed more; who was less attached to their bed, who was more devoted to reading; who was less affected by insults, who was more moved by compassion; who would more readily give away what they had taken for themselves; who would willingly offer a guest a bed of sackcloth and the usual stone pillow; who would more promptly tend to a stranger with tears before giving alms and first feed Christ with affection before feeding the guest at the table; whose mouth spoke less of the world and more of Christ; who, on that high level of virtues, seemed smaller in their own eyes, and the more they ascended in merit, the more they diminished in humility.
During this time, a certain private bishopric was exercised within their community.
I would be lying if I said that many bishops did not learn from them, as they were received, how to receive others: for those who weren't intimidated by the strictness of their lifestyle left with more humanity in their hearts than refreshment in their bodies.
Together, they adorned their entire homeland, and as much as remains in the minds of many, they cared for others' bodies and spirits, whether someone needed clothing, teaching, or sustenance, they were clothed, fed, and taught.
No one, weary from the labor of pilgrimage, arrived there without feeling like they had reached their homeland and the fields of their inheritance; no one leaving for further places departed without feeling as though they were once again leaving their home, and once more leaving behind their fellow citizens and relatives.
Meanwhile, their love continued to grow and spread, reaching far-off places.
The entire country was eager to show them obedience, love, and honor.
They couldn't stay unknown and poor; the more they tried to live quietly, the more their fame shone.
Each one praised and glorified the other, attributing everything to their shared virtues.
Even though each wanted to be hidden in the other's shadow, their reflected brightness illuminated them both.
Their seriousness, mature wisdom, and rare visits from even their closest female relatives, along with their complete avoidance of vanity, were remarkable.
They showed kind comfort and careful concern for the safety of those dedicated to their teachings.
They lived an angelic life on earth, full of patience, vigils, fasting, chastity, knowledge, perseverance, gentleness, the Holy Spirit, genuine love, the word of truth, and the power of God.
They feared their own glory and the widespread influence of their good behavior, though they saw it as praise to God.
They worried about the danger of vanity and felt they had already received their reward in life.
Disdaining human interaction and favor, they longed for solitude.
So, after consulting together and feeling a kind of persecution due to their honor, they set out for foreign lands.
Once again, the country rose up, and their relatives resisted.
They feared losing their guiding light, but now with more wisdom.
What a struggle of faith and love was there, dear Jesus!
What efforts of advice, prayer, and tears!
Who didn't claim a relative's duty, or whose tears didn't match a father's?
The whole country felt it was losing fathers in these young men.
Truly, they had an old age not marked by gray hair, but by grace; not worn in body, but beautiful in character.
Oh, Lord, how great is the management of your providence!
You allow the lamps of your faith, blazing with fire, not to stay fixed in one place, but you carry them to light up different areas.
This inspires a desire to move and to avoid glory, which certainly had to be multiplied by the very increase of virtue through the undertaken pilgrimage.
Although it has been divided by various acts of mercy for a long time, it still has plenty of substance; and both relatives and strangers are welcomed as participants in the inheritance.
So, there is no concern for parental profit at all, as if they are selling something that isn't theirs.
The possession that had served the poor, since it was held by them, is now distributed and sold to the poor.
The homeland receives the outpoured mercy and repays it with abundant tears.
They leave their land, their home, and their family, proving themselves true sons of Abraham by similar example.
To ensure their youthful boldness is not seen as rash, they bring with them an old man of perfect and complete seriousness, whom they always called their father in Christ, the holy Caprasius, still living an angelic life on the islands.
Although your love has not yet known his name or his life, Christ counts him among his friends.
They take him as a guide in the Lord and a guardian of their age, whom many young people had already chosen as their protector.
Thus, a refuge for pilgrimage is sought, and the fame of virtue is avoided; but wherever they go, willingly or not, other fame is born.
Blessed are the lands, and happy the harbors, which the pilgrim, thirsting for the heavenly homeland, illuminates!
Some approach the shores of the East, and other places full of saints to receive example, while others inspire good examples wherever they go.
Their substance is scattered everywhere, and in every place they visit, the good fragrance of Christ spreads.
Even then, the Church of Marseilles almost claimed for itself the very one whose memory we now celebrate, encouraged by the bishop of that city, who rejoiced in such fellowship.
But what could not that fervor of tears and the ambition of endearing contests conquer?
So, eager and warned by the new danger, they crossed the seas, seeking shores once considered barbaric but now rich in Roman eloquence.
It's a long story to tell how each place they visited was influenced by them, how much vitality they brought to the Churches without any clerical title, and how many teachers learned quietly from them.
Let it be enough to remember that they bravely faced the harshness of the sea out of a desire for Christ.
They journeyed to the rugged and barren shores of Achaia, and, despite being raised with such care and gentleness, they battled against the vast changes of water and wind.
The severity and difficulty of this for their delicate nature were evident in the death of his blessed brother in Christ, Venantius, and in their own and their companions' struggles.
Now, what he believed he either presented or received at that funeral in Methoni, he showed through numerous processions of singers.
Here the Hebrew, here the Greek, here the Latin rejoices, and even the Jew, who rejects Christ, admires the faithful servant of Christ.
The fervent choirs seem to shake the stars themselves, and as we believe, angelic choirs sing along with human voices; Christ welcomes his faithful servant.
"Well done, Venantius, good and faithful servant; and while you hear, 'Enter into the joy of your lord' from the Gospel of Matthew, Chapter 25, Verse 21, remember us who are still beset by worldly pleasures." The struggles of the flesh and soul come to an end; eternal life and glory begin.
Chapter Three: Honoratus, After the Death of His Brother, Comes to Italy and Stays with the Bishops-Leontius, Bishop of Forojuliensis-He Enters the Island of Lerins
From there, Christ brings Honoratus back to you, guiding his return with a hidden hand.
Everything he touches along the way is enlightened.
Italy celebrates his arrival, and Tuscany warmly receives him, weaving gentle delays through its priests.
Meanwhile, God's providence looks out for us, and Christ calls the one whose homeland yearned for solitude to the nearby desert of this city.
The island, uninhabited due to neglect and feared for its venomous creatures, lies under the nearby Alpine ridge, which draws him in.
In addition to the solitude, he is pleased by the closeness and affection of the holy Bishop Leontius and is held back by many attempts to draw him away.
The surrounding inhabitants spoke of the dreadful desolation and competed to claim him for their lands of faith.
However, eager to escape human interaction and longing for isolation, he carried this desire in his heart and often expressed it, sometimes to himself, sometimes to others, saying:
"You will tread upon the asp and the basilisk, and you will trample the lion and the dragon" (Psalm Ninety-One, Verse Thirteen);
and recalling Christ's promise to his disciples in the Gospels:
"Behold, I have given you authority to tread on serpents and scorpions" (Luke Ten, Verse Nineteen).
He enters fearlessly, and his confidence dispels his companions' fears.
The fear of solitude vanishes, and the serpents retreat.
What darkness could withstand such light?
What poison could resist his remedy?
Indeed, it is remarkable and surely among his miracles that despite frequent encounters with serpents, especially stirred by the sea heat, as we have seen, there was never any danger or even fear.
Why should I wait any longer?
With Christ's help, overcoming every challenge that once held him back, your Honoratus sets up God's camps there.
The place that once discouraged settlement is now brightened by angelic duties.
The hidden space is illuminated while the light remains concealed.
The darkness of an unknown exile gives way to the brightness of a willing exile.
So, what does this addition, this improvement, bring?
Wherever Honoratus goes, honor follows.
Here, he is first committed to the clerical duty he had long avoided; the priestly crown binds the runaway to his calling, and the dignity he once shunned now comes to him.
A priest appeared there, deserving not just double but multiple honors, before whom no distinction of priesthood, no privilege of the bishop's name, was acknowledged.
No bishop ever claimed enough to consider himself a colleague of that priest.
Yet he maintained the humility of a monk in the priesthood just as fully as he held the merits of the priesthood as a monk.
With his own industriousness sufficient there, a temple of God's chosen Church is erected; roofs suitable for monks' dwellings rise up, and waters long denied by time flow abundantly, presenting two Old Testament miracles in one emergence.
For when they flowed from the rock, they sweetly coursed through the sea's bitterness.
Now, the whole region eagerly directed all who sought God there.
Whoever desired Christ sought Honoratus; and indeed, whoever sought Honoratus found Christ.
For there he thrived completely, and his heart resided like a lofty citadel and a most splendid temple.
There chastity, holiness, faith, wisdom, and virtue dwelt; there justice and truth shone brightly.
Thus, as if with arms outstretched and open, he welcomed all into his embrace, meaning into the love of Christ; everyone eagerly flocked to him from all directions.
Indeed, what land or nation does not have its citizens in his monastery?
What barbarism did he not soften?
How often did he transform fierce beasts into gentle doves?
How many bitter characters did he sprinkle with the sweetness of Christ?
Those whose wickedness had once been their own punishment became a delight to everyone with grace.
After experiencing goodness, they couldn't help but increasingly despise what they once were.
As if brought into new light, they loathed the old prison of long-standing errors.
Through his exhortation, various plagues of the soul were driven away.
Bitterness, harshness, and rage gave way to the freedom Christ offered, and rest after long and heavy servitude under Pharaoh was delightful.
It was an amazing and astonishing transformation, not through Circe's potion, as they say, turning men into beasts, but rather turning beasts into men through Christ's word, like the sweetest potion served by Honoratus.
What couldn't be achieved with such persistence combined with enthusiasm?
Or which stones wouldn't be turned into children of Abraham?
There was such a workshop of virtues in refining minds that if he didn't lead a person to their salvation with lively exhortations, he would compel God through prayer.
He considered everyone's sufferings as his own and wept for them as if they were his.
He accounted for everyone's progress and efforts as his own, knowing how to rejoice with those who rejoice and to weep with those who weep.
He transferred both the vices and virtues of everyone into the sum of his own merit.
Just as virtue inspires virtue, so compassion, when given to the miserable, yields fruit.
For he would reap more with each person than each does for themselves.
The salvation of each one builds his singular glory.
Tireless, swift, and indefatigable, he persevered according to the nature and character of each person.
He approached one secretly, another openly; one sternly, another gently; and to adapt his correction, he often even changed the very appearance of his discipline.
Thus, we rarely saw anyone so much loved or feared.
He placed these two emotions in each of his followers in such a way that his love introduced fear of wrongdoing, and fear of discipline introduced love.
Chapter Four: The Excellent Teachings of the Lerins Island Monks-The Virtues of Honoratus-Honoratus, Gracious and Generous to Guests-Eucherius Wrote to Honoratus
18.
It's truly remarkable how much he cared to ensure that no one was weighed down by sadness or overwhelmed by worldly concerns.
He had an incredible ability to perceive what troubled each individual, as if he held everyone's thoughts in his own mind.
With great wisdom and compassion, he made sure that no one was burdened by too much work or dulled by too much rest.
It seemed as though he cared, if it can be said, even for the sleep of each brother with heartfelt affection.
He always motivated those strong in body to overcome laziness and encouraged those fervent in spirit to find rest.
It appeared that, through what I believe was divine inspiration, he understood the strengths, spirits, and needs of everyone, truly becoming a servant to all for the sake of Jesus Christ.
It's amazing how he managed to fulfill so many duties simultaneously, especially while suffering from various ailments.
He accompanied both the strongest and the newcomers in fasting and vigils, sharing the same rule despite their differences in strength.
Despite his own frailty, he visited the sick, caring for both the souls and bodies of others, ensuring that no one lacked anything.
He would always consider: this one is cold, this one is worried; this one finds the work hard; this food isn't suitable for that one; this one has been hurt by another; the wrong done by one is serious, and it is equally serious that the other felt it.
Great effort was needed to restore grace after an offense, so that one might see the insults received as minor or nonexistent, and the other might regret causing harm.
This was his constant mission: to lighten the burden of Christ for everyone, to remove whatever the devil had introduced, to clear away the clouds of sin, to bring back the brightness of grace, to instill love for Christ and neighbors by loving, and to cultivate everyone's minds as if they were his own heart; to renew joy and always kindle the desire for Christ as if it were the first day of conversion.
19.
As a result, the entire congregation, eager for divine service and gathered from different parts of the world, despite their differing customs and languages, united in their love for him.
Everyone called him lord and father; in him, they found their homeland, their relatives, and everything else restored at once.
They all learned to share in his compassion, seeing his pains as their own.
It was fitting that the distinguished and blessed man in Christ, Presbyter Salvianus, one of his dear friends, wrote that just as the sky changes with the sun's brightness or cloudiness, so this congregation, longing for heaven and devoted to heavenly pursuits, would receive either cloudiness or clarity of mind from him, like a special sun in Christ.
They would suffer when he suffered and regain strength when he recovered.
From this, the grace of the Holy Spirit, spread through his prayers, remains in his monastery, strengthened by the example and teaching of such a great teacher, in various gifts of the spirit, in humility and gentleness, in genuine love, and in the unity of glory in the diversity of its members.
Among these things, he showed great care for strangers and guests.
Who ever passed him by?
Who, upon seeing him, didn't abandon even the most favorable journey or the most pleasant winds, out of a desire for such a great man, disregarding their own advantage?
Or if it was not possible to reach the island, they considered the forced continuation of their journey and the harshest storms.
Everyone hastened there; no one felt delays; everyone left feeling completely secure, with him providing love, resources, and prayers, sending them off as if they were his long-time friends.
In the desolation of the wilderness, he provided delights by his presence, receiving everyone with such joy and love as if he had been waiting for them.
Furthermore, his generosity matched his resources, administered with equal faith.
For he who had gladly heard, "Sell all that you have, and give to the poor, and come, follow me" (Matthew 19:21), everyone enthusiastically entrusted to him anything they had dedicated in their hearts to charity, securely committing all their belongings to him, whose example they followed in leaving everything behind.
Hence, there was a frequent gathering to him from the vastness of different regions.
Truly, he was not like a stingy or fearful steward.
He would allocate some resources and save more for the congregation entrusted to him, which was growing daily.
But what didn't he do every day for others, that he had once done for himself?
In other words, he saved nothing for himself or his own, except for the food and clothing needed for the present days.
At one point, the resources he managed were exhausted, but his faith never wavered.
On one occasion, when the treasury held just a single gold coin out of the many thousands he had generously given, he gave this very coin to a passing poor person, even amidst a shortage of many things, and said to me and others standing by:
"It is certain that the one who will provide is now approaching, even if our generosity has nothing to offer."
In barely three or four hours, someone came who confirmed his words.
Oh, happy generosity, which faith served!
Oh, happy faith, which generosity never delayed!
Truly, as much as his faith supplied, he couldn't distribute it all with his own hand alone.
He had many trustworthy men in various places, whose hands always distributed what was brought to him.
Thus, through the grace of one steward, he had many stewards, and his faith, like a kind of common spring, flowed abundantly for the many who gave and received.
No distress reached him that extended beyond him or did not find its end in him.
From there, letters bearing greetings were eagerly brought to him, as he supposed or certainly hoped, from all sides where he was hidden, and he returned them with new, varied affections-how serious, how gentle, how sweet!
Therefore, the blessed Eucherius, splendid in the world and even more splendid in Christ, a rival of his virtue, when he received his letters on the nearby island where he lived, with wax tablets in hand, said:
"You have returned honey to the wax."
Who then did not believe themselves blessed, their home blessed, their chests blessed, enriched with great blessing from the small gift of his words?
His writings were filled with so much wit and charm that they truly deserved a place in the treasure chest of the heart, rather than just on shelves or in cabinets.
That's why so many people carry them in their minds, eager to share them as a testament to their affection.
After all, who else has ever connected with so many unknown people, making them feel like friends, as he did?
Chapter Five: The Conversion of Hilary through the Exhortations of S.
Honoratus - The Efficacy of the Grace of Christ in Hilary
As I think back on his immense kindness to everyone, I can't overlook the special care he showed me.
His concern for me in Christ brought about as much salvation as the love he left with you, marking grace and affection.
For my sake, considering his merit and my judgment, he didn't hesitate to return to the homeland he once avoided.
He didn't shy away from the difficulty of such a long journey, which was particularly tough because of his many longstanding illnesses.
During a time when I was too worldly and defiant towards God, he approached me gently, persuading me with truth to nurture my love for Christ.
It would take too long to fully describe the strength of his encouragement.
Even though he could have already applied the strongest motivations for conversion to himself, he shared wisdom he had gathered over time.
But when his words of piety barely reached my ears, he turned to the usual support of prayer.
The cry of his emotions, despite my stubbornness, reached and touched God's mercy.
In my resistance, sometimes tied down by the dangerous habits of the world, he prophetically promised: "What you do not grant me, God grants."
How long did he strive to soften my heart with his tears!
How earnestly he contended with me for my salvation with holy kisses and embraces!
Yet at that moment, as he said, I won a terrible victory.
From there, God's right hand took me to be corrected and subdued; for he had handed me over to God in prayer.
What storms arose in my heart then!
What conflicts of different and opposing desires were stirred!
How often did willingness and unwillingness succeed one another in my spirit!
And what more can I say?
In his absence, Christ fulfilled his role in me: after two days, through his prayers and by God's mercy, my stubbornness was conquered.
Sleep had escaped me, pushed away by my thoughts, and the world with its pleasures seemed distant.
Meanwhile, my kind Lord was inviting me.
My mind was engaged in a sort of conversation, like chatting with a friend, pondering what should be pursued and what should be left behind.
Thank you, good Jesus, thank you for breaking my chains, moved by the devoted prayers of your servant Honoratus, and for binding me with the bonds of your love.
If I hold onto these bonds, the chains of sin will never prevail.
So I return, humble, having left proudly, and putting aside all defiance, I approach anew as a supplicant.
This is how the prayers of the saints bring back their lost ones, how they soften the stubborn, and overcome the rebellious.
With what tears did he then water my dryness, with what gentle weeping did he draw me into tears!
He welcomed me with such humility and gentleness, as if he himself were being welcomed by me.
The reason for delay disappeared immediately.
Then, for the first time, he recognized that homeland he had long thought to flee from.
He leads me out with him as his prize; he rejoices, he triumphs, he exults.
Following his example, he eagerly encloses me, now desiring seclusion.
He first nourishes me with milk, and later with food.
He also gives me drink from that flowing source of heavenly wisdom within him.
If only my narrow spirit could have received as much as he tried to pour in!
He would indeed have prepared me for you, making me worthy of your desire; and unknowingly, he would have trained me to be a suitable successor for himself.
Now truly, how much of his overflowing love for all, which I say without envy, he bestowed upon me, and how much lighter he made that light yoke of Christ for me with his kindness!
How often did he call me his mind, his soul, his tongue!
How impatient he was in my absence, how eager he always was to see me, though I was most unworthy!
What can I say about all this, except that prophetic statement, that the Lord rewarded him for me?
Chapter Six: Honoratus Becomes a Bishop and Lives Episcopally-Alms for the Repose of the Dead
25.
My beloved, instead of going into every detail, I've shared with you what others knew about your dedicated pastor.
We've seen his priesthood in this church grow in reputation, but it was already exceptional in holiness and deeds.
But how is it, I wonder, that someone from so far away is sought after?
Who placed the grace of someone absent and unseen upon your hearts?
Who stirred that longing so he could be granted to you, having been given to those in the wilderness by the Lord?
Surely, it was He who oversees everything; He who let him stay in his homeland as long as it was fitting, and who brought the great grace of His servant across seas and lands for the benefit of those who saw it.
26.
From the short time he was with you, it's easy to gauge what I've said about him.
You saw, my beloved, his vigilant care, dedication to discipline, tears of devotion, and constant serenity of mind, all reflected in his unwavering expression.
You also heard his speech, aligned with his life, showing purity of heart and eloquence.
You witnessed his immense charity, so profound that it was rightly said charity itself should be depicted on Honoratus's face.
Who ever felt they had seen enough of him?
To whom was he not a source of all affection?
Who balanced kindness with severity so well?
Who offered discipline mixed with cheerfulness so effectively?
Whom did he not correct joyfully, even to the benefit of the one corrected?
When did his joy ever suggest anything improper?
When was his sadness not beneficial?
When did he sigh, except out of sorrow for another's sin?
Who did not find him more admirable than they had seen before?
Always striving for the highest virtues, he constantly found ways to grow.
Under his encouragement, who among the troubled didn't scorn their own pain?
Who with harsh manners didn't curse their own madness?
Who among the arrogant didn't detest their own pride more than anyone else?
And who among the lustful didn't abhor their own indulgence?
And what more can be said?
As the Apostle says, he became all things to all people First Corinthians chapter nine, verse twenty-two, and was a universal remedy for all.
There was hardly any grace he did not possess so fully that he seemed to cultivate and own it as if it were his sole possession.
In every area of life, he excelled so much that he seemed particularly suited to each one.
Moreover, when he first took on the leadership of this Church of Arles, his main concern was harmony, and his chief effort was to unite in mutual love the brotherhood that was still divided over the choosing of a bishop.
As a proven leader of Israel, he knew well that it was not easy to command those who were in discord.
He preferred to lead with love rather than rule with fear, so that voluntary correction would add this grace to his subjects, making it seem as though they were not compelled into their duties.
Therefore, with discord quickly driven out, he made room for love, which is the mother of all virtues.
Under him, the Church of Christ flourished, just as the monastery had flourished before.
It grew in grace and diminished in worldly wealth; with discipline taking root, it cast out the wealth of unrighteousness from its house as if it were the house of the Lord.
What had long been idly accumulated was finally assigned to worthy uses; he sent his treasures to those who had passed on, and those who had offered them felt the refreshment of their offerings once more.
He only kept what was sufficient for his ministry.
But if necessity had required, I believe he would not have spared even his ministry.
He made the desires of another time his own responsibility.
Chapter Seven: The Illness, Death, and Burial of the Honored One-The Saints in Heaven Pray for Mortals
Even in his final days, he continued to work tirelessly.
He enriched many by sharing the word from his bed.
But how long did his bed confine him, as he was used to overcoming fatigue, even when close to death?
On Epiphany, he delivered a sermon at the church despite his pains already resisting.
With faith battling his illnesses, he never allowed bodily pain to overshadow his spiritual fervor, serving your wishes beyond his own strength.
No sudden illness or fever overtook him; instead, a long-standing illness, worsened by his commitment and lack of rest, gradually wore him down by the eighth or ninth day after the celebration.
He scarcely denied us his presence in acts of charity for four days, fearing that his approaching end would sadden his people.
He was never a burden to anyone, even during his most severe illnesses.
His illnesses never caused the typical horror.
In this way, the dwelling place of the Holy Spirit came to rest.
It's remarkable how he maintained the vigor of his pure mind until the end.
He always comforted his people, fearing nothing more than them being consumed by prolonged despair, understanding that the end is almost easier to bear than uncertainty.
He wiped away the tears of those around him with well-chosen words, which ironically brought more tears.
He considered our pain heavier than his own.
No one, no matter how strong-hearted, found it easy to endure such trials and hardships, nor did he ever wish for or fear death.
For he, who was not reluctant to live in Christ's service despite difficulties, did not fear passing through the common doorway to new life.
The ultimate necessity of humans was something he had pondered, not something that came unexpectedly.
So, at the very end, as if he were departing and saying goodbye, he wanted to ensure nothing was left unfinished or less thorough than he intended.
He asked each of us to suggest anything that might have slipped his memory.
Meanwhile, he signed everything to confirm it and, with his gentle authority, urged us to handle everything that needed to be done, sparing us his own fatigue.
At one point, while I struggled to hold back my tears, he asked, "Why are you crying? Is it over the inevitable necessity of the human condition? Should my passing find you unprepared when it has not found me unprepared?" Even though I was hindered by sobs, I managed to tell him that I no longer grieved my loss. I was confident his prayers would never fail me and expected them to be even stronger after his passing. I was deeply affected by the pain of his struggles and his final moments. "And what," he said, "do I, the least of all, endure that many of the saints did not endure in their most bitter last moments?" After mentioning a few, he added something I think he read somewhere: "Great men endure much and are born as examples to teach others how to endure."
When the authorities, the prefect, and other officials gathered around him, he delivered such fervent instructions, already under the chill of death, taking the sharpest beginning of exhortation from his very end. It was truly fitting that he, who had always provided examples of living, also made his death an example. "You see," he said, "what fragile lodging we inhabit. However high we rise in life, death will pull us down from there. From this necessity, no honors or treasures can redeem anyone. This is common to the just and the unjust, the powerful and the humble. We owe great thanks to Christ, who, by his own death and resurrection, has given our death the hope of resurrection, offering eternal life and dispelling the fear of eternal death."
Live your life in a way that you don't fear its end, and look forward to what we call death as a journey.
Death isn't a punishment if it doesn't lead to suffering.
The separation of body and soul is tough, but it's much harder for them to remain together in the flames of hell unless, throughout life, the spirit acknowledges its nobility, declares war on the body, and fights against bodily sins.
By happily separating from the corruption of the flesh, it preserves both substances untainted for eternal peace, where they will be joyfully united.
The saints will rejoice in glory and be glad in their resting places, which are their bodies as their abodes.
When they recognize the parts of their bodies dedicated to righteousness as familiar homes, they will be content.
So, do this: Honoratus, your leader, leaves you this inheritance.
With his last breath, he invites you to inherit the kingdom of heaven.
Let no one be too attached to this world.
It's better to willingly let go of what you know you'll inevitably lose.
Let no one be overwhelmed by wealth, serve money, or be corrupted by the empty display of riches.
It's a crime to take the price of salvation and turn it into a means of destruction, and for anyone to be captivated by what could have redeemed them.
Meanwhile, he advised more with his face, more with his eyes, and more with his spirit shining towards heaven.
The words of the one reporting are indeed unequal to his fiery speech, but the words of the adviser were no less unequal to his spirit.
With such exhortation and an unusual movement, he poured out a rare gift of blessing.
As the service of his limbs failed, a new grace of mind always blossomed.
When everything was arranged, with not much less than fullness remaining in his actions, he mentally reviewed all his dear ones and named as many as weariness allowed, he enriched them with greetings sent through those who stood by.
To me, he whispered in my ear, "Apologize to that holy one for not being able to do what he wished."
What great and admirable foresight!
Even in the throes of death, he did his best to ease everyone's sorrow and ensure nothing was left unaddressed.
Think about this: though he left behind all those he loved, who had come to this city because of him, he didn't suggest anyone return home or form new communities, nor did he assign specific places for them to live.
It was as if he truly knew there would be no separation among his people, except for those who had already decided to leave while he was still alive.
Indeed, we rarely find anyone absent from our community unless he had already indicated who would leave-those who found either their homeland more appealing than his presence, or his discipline too challenging.
Meanwhile, a deeper sleep came over him.
When we, concerned, occasionally woke him, he said, "I'm surprised my sleep seems so heavy to you, given my severe weariness after such long periods of wakefulness."
And when we expressed concern that he remained seated longer at the end, he replied with his usual gentle humor and calm demeanor about how he tolerated our intrusiveness during his time of concern.
Thus, just before his life came to an end, his sweetness was fully consumed.
Then, overtaken by his final sleep, he passed into the peace of death without struggle, as is often the case in the last moments. He experienced no painful delays in dying.
That holy, noble, sincere soul, untouched by worldly stains, is welcomed by angelic choirs.
Meanwhile, many have different dreams, but all share one common vision: the holy one is met by the duties of the saints.
And truly, at the stroke of midnight, the church filled with people arriving to meet the holy body, as if awakened by angelic messengers.
His lifeless body, always animated by spirit and full of grace, was left behind: indeed, his face retained a beauty that pleased everyone.
You know these things well, and you can reflect on them with a deeper meditation of the mind than words can express.
No one seemed to feel a greater loss than those who couldn't see his body or kiss his face or limbs, as reverence or love urged them to.
They kissed the bier where his sacred body lay with deep devotion.
Later, as it was brought to the tomb, it was nearly stripped bare.
The faithful didn't spare the garments that sanctified him, seeing it as a precious gift to have even a fringe of his coverings.
Your affection was evident at his funeral.
You rekindled my hidden journey among you during his burial.
You nourished me with your abundant love for him.
Who stayed home that day?
Who wasn't brought to the basilica's walls, as if overwhelmed by personal mourning?
Touching the bier or placing a shoulder under it was considered a great honor.
You witnessed, along with your own glory, his glory:
For that reverent observance of the funeral was an act of faith, and it was as joyful to have known such a man as it was grievous to have lost him.
The grace of his tomb gives us great confidence, for with the bones we laid to rest here, we surely assume his intercession in heaven.
We saw the spices and incense carried before his bier; but God received even greater fragrances from your minds, in your profound affection for such a shepherd.
God's glory rejoiced in his glory, and there was a harmonious love among the varied choirs of different languages.
Chapter Eight: Hilarius, Successor of Honoratus, His Kinsman - Honoratus Invoked as Patron
A kind Lord, who guided your hearts to choose me despite my insignificance, allowed me to stay close to his tomb.
He will also grant, as you pray, that I do not stray from his path.
Instead, may I quickly follow in his footsteps, without questioning or debating his actions.
For, as I see it, through him, God has already prepared me for you.
He found me for you, though I was unaware, with much effort.
He educated me with great care, seeking in me a faith similar to his own.
He strove to bring me from the island where I retreated, leaving the beginnings of his bishopric out of a secret love, perhaps foreseeing, though I dare not say unknowingly, so that I might find a home near his tomb in your love.
But how should we interpret this, as he handed me over immaturely with his mature departure?
It is not for us to lightly judge the wisdom of the eternal King: you might not have realized what goodness you lost if it had been restored to you.
O great and illustrious Honoratus, your glory!
Your merit did not need signs to be proven, for your life, full of virtues and remarkable qualities, served as a perpetual sign.
We, who were close to you, know of many divine blessings granted to you, but you considered them the least part, finding greater joy in Christ recording your merits and virtues than in humans noting signs.
Yet, what could be a greater sign of virtue than to avoid and hide signs?
Truly, your prayers were so familiar to Christ's ears that I believe you earnestly prayed that signs would not announce your virtue.
Peace, too, has its martyrs; for you were a perpetual witness to Christ while you remained on Earth.
It's truly remarkable how, despite the strength of your youth being continually weakened by strict abstinence, you maintained a dignified appearance.
This slenderness, consumed by the daily cross, never led to any notable superstition.
You always avoided excesses and the pursuit of glory, which can often be similar to excesses.
From your mouth came only words of peace, chastity, piety, and love.
In your heart, Christ dwelled as the source of all these virtues.
Through you, He provided many with the fruits of love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, faith, modesty, and self-control, overflowing for the salvation and joy of many.
You rightfully sang to Him: "Those who fear you will see me and rejoice" Psalm one hundred and nineteen, verse seventy-four. You always attributed all the good in your conduct to Him, constantly reminding yourself and others: "For what do you have that you did not receive? And if you did receive it, why do you boast as though you did not?" Second Corinthians chapter four, verse seven. The good in your life was more truly yours, the more you denied it was yours.
You were a source of comfort for all who desired the Lord. While some boast in worldly successes, you urged rejoicing in God, your affectionate voice gently murmuring: "Let the hearts of those who seek the Lord rejoice" Psalm one hundred and five, verse three. There was no greater pleasure for you than in prayers and psalms.
Christ was so deeply embedded in your being that, at times, even when you were peacefully asleep, your tongue would echo Him in your usual duty, even in dreams. Often, while sleeping, you would repeat words of wise exhortation and heartfelt prayer. Indeed, while your body rested in bed, your mind was in Christ. We all experienced this, as everyone present can attest.
However, you have always been the sole source of rest for everyone.
You often spoke eagerly of dreams, not as predictions of the future or as worries about what lies ahead, but as the restless desires stirred within the soul.
In particular, it was martyrdom that you always carried in your meditations.
I believe that sometimes it hinted at and provoked your desire, as if the Lord, stirred by your faith, made you feel as though you were undergoing persecution.
And truly, I believe no one can deny that in your quest for martyrdom, it was torturers who were lacking, not your courage.
You were indeed a daily witness in the most sincere discussions of the confession of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
No one has easily discussed the Trinity of Divinity so clearly and lucidly as you, distinguishing it by persons and uniting it with the eternity and majesty of glory.
Remember, therefore, friend of God, always remember us, standing untainted before God, singing that new song, and following the Lamb wherever he goes.
You are his follower; you are our advocate, an effective interpreter of our prayers, and a strong defender.
Bring the prayers of the flock, offered at your tomb, and obtain for us, through mutual agreement, that both priest and people together may deserve to attain at least in part what you commanded and taught.
Through our Lord Jesus Christ, who has taken you into his glory, and who lives and reigns with his Father and the Holy Spirit, God, forever and ever.
Amen.
Letter of Saint Hilary of Arles, Bishop, to Saint Eucherius, Bishop of Lyon
To the most blessed lord, justly esteemed and to be esteemed, and in Christ most devotedly bound Pope Eucherius, Bishop, from Hilary, Bishop.
Although I mentioned in previous letters that I would bring your little books back with me, I couldn't delay because of the insistence and demand of the boy you sent.
So, I returned the delightful works of your blessedness, quite anxious that they, not yet copied, might be ruined by the pouring rain.
I only went through them once, marveling at everything.
May the Lord grant that I may someday review these splendid works of your glory in Christ, with you guiding me through the pages.
I ask only this, that you do not let me be deprived of these teachings for long.
Having one of your young men, for whom you arranged this education, please wish for me to have them more eagerly, as the challenges of youth press on me.
May the Lord remember you for the advancement of His Church and keep you for a long time, most blessed Pope.