In the year of our Lord 651. Saint Landericus, Bishop of Paris.
Historical Notice.
(From Gallia Christiana, volume 7.)
Landericus, Bishop of Paris, joined other bishops in granting freedom and immunity to the monastery of Saint Denis, a privilege given by King Clovis the Second on June 22, during the sixteenth year of his reign.
Furthermore, another similar privilege granted the previous year is evidenced by a bull from Pope Stephen the Second to Fulrad, abbot of Saint Denis, dated February 26, 757, and a charter from Abbot Hilduin in the ninth century regarding the division of the monastery's goods.
Although many consider this charter false or interpolated, it's noteworthy that during a council at Pistes in 862, Louis, abbot of Saint Denis, sought confirmation of the privilege initially granted by Landericus.
Aeneas, Bishop of Paris, among other bishops, supported and fully confirmed this privilege, honoring the legacy of his predecessor, Lord Landericus, in accordance with justice.
The Chronicle of Saint Maxentius mentions Landericus, Bishop of Paris, in Labbaeus's volume 2 of the Library: During the time of Clovis, son of Dagobert, Ansoaldus of Poitiers, Audoenus, Landericus, Bishop of Paris, and others are noted.
Various ancient and recently published Hagiologies and Breviaries also mention him, as detailed by the Bollandists in volume 1 of June.
It's surprising to some, including Valesius, that Audobert isn't listed between Chrodobert and the Bishop of Paris.
According to authors from the times of Dagobert, Clovis the Second, and Clotaire the Third, or from the councils held then, there's no record of a Landericus as the Bishop of Paris.
However, the Landericus addressed by Marculfus in his formulas might be another from Meaux, mentioned by Molanus in the index of saints of Belgium.
Although the records of the Church of Paris and ancient lists of its bishops mention him, Marculfus published his formulas during the reign of Clovis the Second, around the year 654, when Faro was in Meaux.
No other Landericus is recorded in church records except for the one in Paris, as clearly shown in the preface by the esteemed Hieronymus Bignon, a notable figure of the Parisian senate, who first brought Marculfus's formulas to light in 1613, later published by Baluzius in the second volume of the Capitularies.
Landericus is also said to have been the first to build and endow the famous hospital at the entrance of the mother church, commonly known as the house of God.
He is especially celebrated for his incredible charity towards the poor, famously selling even his household furniture during the famine of what Mabillonius believes was the year 651.
It's even said he destroyed the sacred vessels of the church to provide food for those in need.
Saint Landericus was buried in the Church of Saint Germanus of Auxerre, where his relics are still preserved.
In 1171, they were placed in a wooden box by Maurice de Sully.
Later, on 17 September 1408, Peter of Ordeomonte discovered them along with some old, worn documents bearing the name of Landericus, Bishop of Paris, and reverently placed them in a silver box on a column behind the main altar.
The memory of the holy bishop is solemnly celebrated in the Church of Paris on June 10th.
This is a charter in which Saint Landericus, Bishop of Paris, grants privileges to the Monastery of Saint Denis.
It was published by Dubletus in the "History of the Abbey of Saint Denis," page 443; Cointius, Annals volume 3, page 339; Sirmondus, "Councils of Gaul," volume 1, page 495; Harduin volume 3, column 985, and other collectors of councils.
The charter is also found in the "History of the Church of Paris," volume 1, page 180; and among the "Proofs of the Liberties of the Gallican Church," part 4, page 197.
While examining the authenticity of this charter, Mabillon in "Annals" volume 1, page 427, admits uncertainty but seems to lean towards a more critical view.
Launoius, in "Assertions of Inquiry into the Immunity of Saint Germain of the Meadows," part 4, chapter 10, section 1, 3, accused this document of being forged, offering several arguments.
Some of these arguments were refuted by Cointius and the writer of the "History of the Church of Paris."
Some say this charter is not entirely false but corrupted by interpolation.
We do not deny that a charter of immunity granted by Landericus to the Church of Paris existed, which was confirmed by Clovis the Second with a diploma. However, we believe it was lost and a new one was fabricated around the ninth century.
Certainly, if Landericus' charter, which we present here, is compared with Clovis' diploma, it will appear entirely different from the one confirmed by this diploma.
We follow the reading of Dublet.
Year 652.
From Brequigny Diplomatics, Charters, Laws, volume 2.
By the grace of God, Landericus, bishop of the Church of Paris.
Launoius, as mentioned above, denies that a Parisian bishop named Landericus existed at this time; this is incorrect, as can be seen in "New Gaul, Christian" volume 7, column 24.
Among the things we do over time, by God's providence, if anything has been done rightly, it undoubtedly glorifies Him who advised and gave us the ability, and it benefits us as well.
It is fitting, especially for those in sacred orders, to manage both private and public matters in a way that annuls their own sins and, if any virtue is found, always strive to elevate it further.
They should either commend the good deeds of others or be vigilant in correcting their faults.
There should be a grateful familiarity among all the faithful of God, along with timely readiness in expecting and giving benefits, so that nothing worthy is denied to anyone who requests it.
Not only should nothing be refused, but more worthy things may also be requested from others.
Therefore, let all worshipers of the Catholic Church know that the most glorious Lord Clovis, King of the Franks, illuminated by divine light, humbly requested our utmost humility, so that both we and our canons
remain vigilant in correcting their faults.
In the spirit of common brotherhood, and with the privilege of security and stability, we issue this decree in honor of Saint Dionysius and his companions Rusticus and Eleutherius.
Having been crowned with martyrdom, they rest at their basilica, where they are celebrated for their miraculous virtues.
This is also the resting place of Dagobert, a former king, and his mother, Queen Nanthildis.
The holy Carthaginian synod, convened by the esteemed Boniface and his fellow bishops, does not forbid monks from living under their own privileges.
Moreover, the writings of Saint Augustine on ecclesiastical ranks reinforce that monks who live peacefully according to their rule should rest under their unique law, free from clerical interference.
This ensures that the secular world does not disturb those governed by the strict rule of service to the Lord.
Considering this, and acknowledging that the canonical institution does not oppose us in this matter, we find the request of Lord Clovis the king compelling, as it is difficult to resist.
Out of respect for these great martyrs, to whom he has entrusted himself, we permit the monks to live according to their holy order.
They may pray to God for us and for all the brothers of our Church.
I have granted this privilege wholeheartedly, with the agreement of my brothers.
By this decree, and in the name of God, I forbid, both now and in the future, any of my successors from daring to break or violate this in any way.
Specifically, every priest or cleric, whether inside the castle of the most blessed martyr Saint Dionysius or outside, in the place called the Fountain of Saint Remigius, as marked by the road leading by the meadow called Formosum, up to the Church of Saint Quintinus the martyr, and from there along the royal road until reaching the fishpond at the head of the Tricinus Bridge, as marked by the meadows belonging to the brothers, up to the aforementioned place of the Fountain of Saint Remigius.
All those serving the churches within this defined area shall be free and exempt from all debt and payment of visitation dues.
However, we wish, and for the reverence of Saint Dionysius the martyr, we grant that if they have a need, they may receive chrism and oil from our bishopric or that of our successors without charge.
If any of the priests or clerics are killed God forbid or wounded, or if any accusation of injury arises from these situations, we grant the authority to the abbot in charge of that holy place, along with the other brothers, to manage these matters.
However, if anyone is driven by cunning or greed and recklessly violates what we have outlined here, they must do penance for three years, separated from the communion of brothers.
Nonetheless, with Christ protecting it, this privilege shall remain perpetual and uncorrupted, aiding those who preserve it and destroying those who wish to destroy it.
We have strengthened this decree with our signatures to ensure its validity in our times and in the future, and we earnestly ask our fellow bishops and brothers to also confirm it.
In the name of Christ, I, Landericus, though a sinner, bishop of the city of Paris, have agreed to and signed this privilege.
Munemundus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Gonualdus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Vulfolenus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Armentarius, bishop, agreed and signed.
Runicus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Malchardus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Eligius, bishop, agreed and signed.
Grator, bishop, agreed and signed.
Joannes, bishop, agreed and signed.
Burgundofart, bishop, agreed and signed.
Richoaldus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Baldomerus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Audoenus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Taurinus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Eustogius, bishop, agreed and signed.
Laridandus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Bertefredus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Audobertus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Clarus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Lastardus, bishop, agreed and signed.
Litterius, bishop, agreed and signed.
Bishop Palladius agreed and signed. Bishop Aetherius agreed and signed.
Bishop Ingildus agreed and signed. Bishop Audebertus agreed and signed.
This privilege was established on the first day of July, during the fifteenth year of the reign of the most glorious King Clovis.
I, Austrolenus, the tutor, wrote and signed this privilege at the command of Lord Bishop Landeric.