A Collection of Sentences on the Six Days of Creation by Bede, Drawn from the Church Fathers
The First Day
In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth.
This chapter is the head of all books.
All divine Scripture is divided into two parts: the Old Testament and the New Testament.
Some parts reveal inner meanings, such as: In the beginning was the Word (John 1).
Others narrate events, such as: In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth (Genesis 1:1).
Some announce future events, like: When the Son of Man comes in his glory (Matthew 25:31).
Others prescribe actions to be taken, such as: Love your neighbor (Matthew 22:39).
How are they divided?
Some are spoken in a figurative sense, like the Song of Songs; and there is: Adam heard the voice of the Lord God walking in the garden (Genesis 3:8).
Others are according to the faith of historical events, such as when the people crossed the Red Sea on foot.
Some are stated in both ways, like the crossing of the Red Sea and the miracles that the Lord performed in the Gospel.
It says: In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth.
We need to inquire what beginning this refers to, whether it is the beginning of time or the beginning as the start of His creation, from which other things began to exist.
They were not always co-eternal with God.
Let us say: In the beginning, co-eternal with Himself, God made the heavens and the earth,
that is, in the only-begotten Son, who is the Wisdom of the Father,
of whom the Apostle says: Christ, the power of God and the wisdom of God (First Corinthians 1:24);
and in the psalm, it says: You have made all things in wisdom (Psalm 104:24).
Again, the Apostle says: For in him all things were created, in heaven and on earth, visible and invisible (Colossians 1:16),
as the evangelist also says of Christ: He was in the world, and the world was made through him (John 1:10).
However, we must ask, did God first make the heavens and the earth or light?
And if light was created first, why does it not say: In the beginning, God created light?
We must understand that He created the heavens, the earth, and the light all at once.
Since the origin is the only thing that matters, just as a person can't tell two familiar stories at the same time, the Lord first explained the origin before describing what came from it, even though He could have done both simultaneously.
What comes first in action also comes first in storytelling.
Therefore, Holy Scripture needed to explain both the deeds done and the stories told.
It first had to explain where something came from before detailing what was made from it.
This was to help those who are slower to understand that physical things were created from something.
There's no difference between the creation of the heavens and the earth, and light, except the difference between the word and the voice.
That's why it doesn't say: In the beginning, God made the heaven and the earth, but rather: Created, because of the formlessness of matter and the deeper spiritual meaning.
In the beginning, God created the heaven and the earth.
Christ is the beginning, as He Himself says in the Gospel: I am the beginning, who speaks to you.
So, in this beginning, God made the heaven, meaning the spiritual ones who meditate on and seek heavenly things.
In Him, He also made the earthly ones, who have not yet let go of the earthly.
But the earth was empty and void, meaning it was not yet separated from the sea.
And void, meaning it was not surrounded by shores or adorned with vines, trees, or animals.
But the earth was formless and empty.
Our flesh, like the earth, was formless and empty before it received the shape of doctrine.
Darkness covered the surface of the abyss because there was no light to illuminate it.
If there were light, it would certainly remain.
But how was it?
It is the thickened air lacking daily light.
And darkness was over the face of the deep.
The blindness of sins and the profound darkness of ignorance covered our hearts.
And the Spirit of God was moving over the waters.
The blessed Apostle says: "Surpassing," he says, "the knowledge of the love of Christ" (Ephesians 3).
And elsewhere he says: "And it surpasses all understanding" (Philippians 4).
This shows that something had begun, over which the Spirit of God was said to move—not in place, but by surpassing and excelling in power.
There are two reasons why God loves His creation: because it exists and because it remains.
That it is formed and remains under the command of the Creator.
The Spirit of God was moving over the waters so that what existed would remain; hence, He first mentioned unformed things and then the Holy Spirit, because all small love is placed beneath the things it loves.
And the Spirit of God was moving over the waters.
This refers to the Spirit of God the Father.
About this Holy Spirit, the Apostle says: "Whoever does not have the Spirit of Christ does not belong to him" Romans 8.
If there is no difference between the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, why doesn't he say: "Whoever does not have the Spirit of the Spirit," or "As the Spirit of the Father says," or "Spirit of the Son"? Why not say "Father Spirit," or "Son Spirit"?
Because there's no relational way to express it, like saying "Servant of the Lord," or "Lord's servant," or "Son of the Father," and "Father of the Son." If he had said "Father Spirit," it would imply that God is the Father of the Spirit. Or if he had said "Son Spirit," it would suggest that the Holy Spirit is the Father of the Son, which is not the case. The Holy Spirit is neither Father nor Son but proceeds from the divine substance.
Therefore, he doesn't say that the Holy Spirit is born of the Father or the Son, because the Holy Spirit is not born like the Only Begotten, nor made like us to be called a son by the adoption of grace. How is the Holy Spirit said to be co-eternal with the Father and the Son? Because the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son and is co-eternal.
He has always proceeded, but he has not always been given, as he can always be a gift without being given. The Holy Spirit has always proceeded and was prepared by the Father to be given. For there was no one to receive him, neither angels nor humans, except the creator of all things alone.
If the three are one—Father, Son, and Holy Spirit 1 John 5—why then is the Father not said to be sent by the Son or by the Holy Spirit? The order of paternal reverence is maintained.
But the Spirit of God was already hovering over our dark and fluid hearts, just like over the waters.
In this Spirit, we would find rest, be brought to life by its breath, and be cleansed by its waters.
On the Creation of Light
God also said: Let there be light. But is this light visible or invisible?
It is said to be invisible because it refers to the angelic creation, which our eyes cannot see.
The reason is that on the fourth day, God created the stars in the sky, which our eyes could see.
Is this angelic creation temporal or timeless?
It was temporal in the angels but timeless in God.
It was temporal in the sense that we understand it as being expressed by the eternal God through the co-eternal Word in the spiritual creation, which He had already made when it was said: In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth.
But this speaking was not only without any sound but also without any physical movement,
the spiritual creation being somehow impressed upon His mind and reason through the co-eternal Word of the Father.
However, it is very difficult to comprehend how it is said that God did not command temporally, nor did the creation hear it temporally,
as He, in the contemplation of truth, surpasses all times,
but rather it was intellectually expressed to them as the co-eternal Wisdom of the Father, communicating to those below what was to be done in temporal things, whether to be formed or governed.
And there was light.
That is, the angelic creation, because they then came to know or understand their Creator.
This is why it does not repeat: And God made the light, as it does with other creations, such as in the firmament where it says: Let there be a firmament, and again: And God made the firmament.
This is because it was not necessary to say: God made the light, since it was an intellectual creation, that is, the angels.
However, when it says Let there be a firmament or other things in other creations,
this is said in the knowledge of the angels,
because it is no wonder that God wished to show His holy angels, who had turned to Him at the first condition of light, what He would make thereafter.
When it says: And God made, it means in the proper nature of things.
There was no need to repeat this about the angels again because they had already, as we said, turned to recognize their Creator.
When that eternal and unchangeable Wisdom, which is not made but begotten, transfers itself into spiritual and rational creatures (like holy souls, so that being illuminated, they could shine), a certain brilliant affection of reason arises in them.
This can be understood as the light being made when God said, "Let there be light."
There was already a spiritual creation, signified by the name "heaven," when it was written: "In the beginning, God created the heaven and the earth." This refers not to the physical heaven, but to the incorporeal heaven, in which all the holy angels are understood. And God saw that the light was good.
Why did He praise the light only and not the night? It's because night and day were not yet made, only the angelic light.
It was unworthy for God to praise something unformed, which was not yet made, but He praised what was formed: the angelic light. And He separated the light from the darkness.
What is the separation of light from darkness, if not the distinction of the formed from the unformed? And He called the light day.
Why did He call the light day, since the day was not yet formed? The same day was named after the appearance of the created thing. And He called the darkness night.
Why did He similarly call the darkness night, which was not yet formed? Because this night, which we know, is the absence of the sun over the earth. When the sun sets, we call it evening; when the morning begins, we call it day.
But here, night is the absence of work, or night itself is called the potential within created things, from which they can be made, even if they are not yet changed. And again, this is according to the spiritual sense.
God also said: Let there be light. That is, let the illumination of faith appear.
On the first day, He gave the light of faith because faith is the first step in conversion.
Thus, the first commandment is: The Lord your God is one God.
Because of this faith, the Lord Himself chose to appear invisibly in the world.
Even then, God, through the grace of His presence, separated the righteous, the children of God and light, from sinners, as from darkness: calling the former day and the latter night.
In the Church, the righteous are called by the name of light.
Listen to the Apostle: You were once darkness, but now you are light in the Lord (Ephesians 5).
And there was evening and there was morning, one day.
What is evening, if not the completion of individual works?
And morning, the beginning of the following ones.
On the Second Day
God also said: Let there be a firmament.
This is because of the stability of the firmament or the separation between the higher and lower waters.
However, we believe that the nature of the waters there is not vaporous but solid and icy, to mitigate the heat of the stars and prevent them from scorching God's creations below.
But how can there be any waters where we would least expect them?
Because the authority of this Scripture surpasses any human understanding.
However, we must question the consistency of the heavens.
The Lord speaks of one firmament, but the Apostle testifies that he was caught up to the third heaven.
What can we conclude, except that tiny drops gather to form a collection, and due to their weight, the air cannot support them, causing them to fall as rain.
Therefore, we understand that the sky is between the waters above and the waters below, with the air between the moist vapors where clouds form and the seas below.
The second heaven, which we perceive with the spirit, is where that disc full of animals descended to Peter in a vision.
The third heaven, which we know with the mind, is so secret and remote, or entirely purified and removed from the senses of the flesh, that those in that heaven can see the very substance of God, the Word through which all things were made, ineffably in the love of the Holy Spirit.
And God said: Let there be a firmament in the midst of the waters, and let it divide the waters from the waters.
Therefore, the Spirit of God should be written as being present, as if someone asked Him how it was made, He would rightly respond.
God said: Let there be, that is, what was in the eternal Word of God to be made.
Then He begins to narrate each thing made.
When we hear, "And so it was done," we understand that the created thing did not exceed the boundaries set by the Word of God.
However, when we hear, "God saw that it was good," we understand that it pleased Him in His gracious Spirit. It wasn't that it was unknown and only pleased Him after it was made. Rather, it pleased Him in such a way that it remained exactly where He intended it to be.
Regarding the shape of the heavens, it should be briefly stated that our authors knew the truth. However, the Spirit of God who spoke through them did not wish to reveal anything that wasn't useful for salvation.
Concerning the debate that often arises about the shape of the heavens—whether it is like an extended skin, a sphere, or a vault—we do not see anything that prevents an extended skin from being curved like a vault or extended into a round cavity like a sphere.
Then on the second day, God created the firmament, which means the foundation of the Holy Scriptures.
In the Church, the firmament is understood to be the divine Scriptures because heaven will be folded like a book.
He separated the waters above this firmament, which represents the heavenly hosts of angels, who do not need the Scriptures to hear the Word of God as they read.
Matthew twenty-four.
For they always see Him and love Him.
But He placed this firmament of His law over the weakness of the lower people so that those who receive it spiritually may know how to distinguish between the earthly and the spiritual, like the waters above and below.
On the Third Day
Then God said, "Let the waters under the sky be gathered into one place, and let the dry land appear." But why didn't He say, "Let the dry land be visible," or "Let the waters be gathered," unless it's because they are closer to the same formless state as the heavenly bodies, so that from these, in the numbering of days, the weaker things of the world are fashioned?
He did not want it to be understood that it was commanded to be done like the higher things, but rather He commanded that the gathered waters appear by themselves as the weaker things of the world.
So, where were the waters gathered if they first covered the entire earth?
They were gathered where they were drawn back, allowing the land to be exposed.
And if any part of the dry land appeared before, where could it have been gathered?
Thus, the abyss did not occupy the whole. It is better understood that either the water first occupied the land like a mist, or it surrounded the land, providing a hollow place for the waters to run to, so the dry land could appear.
After these events, on the third day, He gathered the salty lower waters into one place.
This refers to the unbelievers, who are tossed by the storms of desires and the waves of carnal temptations, and are filled with bitterness.
He separated the dry land from them, representing the source of faith for those who are thirsty.
He set boundaries for the proud and restrained them, preventing them from disturbing the dry land—that is, the soul thirsting for God—with the turbulent waves of their iniquities.
He allowed it to produce the fruit of good works according to its kind.
You shall love your neighbor by supporting their physical needs, having within yourself the seed according to likeness, so that from your own weakness you may feel compassion to help those in need, producing wood with strong timber.
And fruit-bearing, that is, providing benefit to rescue the one who suffers injustice from the hand of the powerful, and offering the shelter of protection with the strong timber of just judgment.
And God saw that it was good, and He said: Let the earth produce green plants, making seed, and fruit trees, making fruit according to their kind, whose seed is in itself on the earth.
And it was so.
The earth produced green plants and brought forth seed according to their kind, and trees making fruit, each having its seed according to its species.
And God saw that it was good, and it became evening and morning, the third day.
What does it mean that He commanded all these things to happen together, the earth to produce, and the waters to gather?
It means that all these things are rooted in the earth.
Therefore, they are said to belong to the same day because, although they spread far and wide through their growth, they are not moved from their own places by their connections.
Trees live, yet not through the soul, but through their greenness, as the sap is poured into the root, then becomes the quality of the tree, spreading through the branches, and finally in the greenness of leaves.
And the fruit-bearing tree, because not all trees produce fruit, each tree has its own purpose and usefulness, both in obvious and hidden ways.
God said, "Let there be lights in the sky to divide the day from the night, and let them serve as signs for seasons, days, and years. Let them shine in the sky and give light to the earth." And it was so.
God made two great lights: the greater light to govern the day and the lesser light to govern the night, along with the stars.
He placed them in the sky to shine on the earth, to govern the day and the night, and to separate light from darkness.
And God saw that it was good. There was evening and there was morning, marking the fourth day.
According to the Word of God and the begotten Wisdom, this was first made in the spiritual creation, that is, in the angels. Then the lights themselves were made to serve as signs and seasons.
It's clear that the mention of time beginning on the fourth day is somewhat obscure, as if the previous three days could have passed without time, even though they had the time of their creation. These three days did not have the distinction of stars.
The greater light governs the day because we know that the day cannot shine without the light of the sun. Similarly, the night, when the stars appear, cannot be illuminated as it is by the presence of the moon.
There is also the question of whether these principal lights of the sky have equal power but appear larger or smaller to our eyes due to different distances in the sky. Just as the sky was made first, it had to be adorned first.
The stars were made on the fourth day. By their shining, the lower habitation on earth is illuminated, ensuring that its inhabitants are not led into a dark dwelling.
Thus, with the movements that follow, the weak bodies of the lower parts are restored to rest. With the sun's circuit, the alternation of day and night occurs, allowing for the alternation of sleeping and waking.
But that night wasn't without beauty.
It was adorned by the light of the moon and stars, comforting those who travel and work at night out of necessity, and gently consoling the animals that cannot bear the sun's light.
When it says, "God said, 'Let there be,'" we understand that Scripture refers back to the eternity of God's Word. It did not recreate anything that wasn't already created in the Word of God.
Therefore, God didn't say "Let there be this or that" as many times as it's written in this book. He begot one Word in which He said everything before each individual thing was made.
And let them be for signs and seasons: not according to heretics or philosophers who follow vain signs, but according to the truth of the signs. Signs and seasons pertain to the moon and the stars of the sky.
We must inquire whether the sky revolves in a circle or if the stars move around. It is understood that the stars move around, but the sky stands firm.
And there was evening and morning, the fourth day. Why did He name evening and morning but not mention the night? What else can we say night is, but the absence of light, which seemed to remain between evening and morning? Or because the first light signified the creation of angels, who, by contemplating their Creator with harmonious love, continuously praise the Creator forever without the blindness of ignorance?
However, they clearly understood at the beginning and end of the work what is called evening and morning. And again, according to the spiritual sense.
On the fourth day, lights appeared, fixed in the firmament of the law.
These lights symbolize the evangelists, teachers, and holy Scriptures, which collectively shed the light of wisdom on everyone below.
At the same time, numerous other shining stars emerged, representing the many virtues within the Church.
In the obscurity of this life, like the night, these virtues shine brightly.
They differentiate, within the firmament of Scripture, the sensible and the intelligible, as if separating the light of the perfect from the darkness of the little ones.
These stars are signs of virtues and miracles.
They also mark times and years because preachers live and pass in their own eras.
Yet, the word of the Lord remains forever.
But why did the earth first bring forth life, and then the lights were created?
This is because, after performing good deeds, there comes the illumination of light to contemplate the form of supreme virtue.
On the Fifth Day
On the Fifth Day, God said: Let the waters bring forth swarms of living creatures, and let birds fly above the earth in the open expanse of the sky.
God created the great sea creatures and every living creature that moves, which the waters brought forth according to their kinds, and every winged bird according to its kind.
God saw that it was good, and He blessed them, saying: Be fruitful and multiply, and fill the waters in the seas, and let the birds multiply on the earth.
There was evening and there was morning, the fifth day.
Why, then, did He decorate the waters with creatures before the land with animals?
The reason was that water appeared visibly first, so it was adorned first, or because, in the beginning, the sky received its decoration, that is, the angels when they were created.
Similarly, the earth was adorned with plants and trees.
Thus, the waters received their adornment with creatures, and the air with birds.
Why is it that we often read about the creation of the sky, earth, and sea in the same way, but nothing is mentioned about the air?
It is not to be assumed that this element was omitted in Scripture.
Rather, it is customary for divine Scripture to refer to the whole world as heaven and earth.
Therefore, it is to be understood that the air belongs to heaven and earth.
Whatever is moist or vaporously expanded pertains to the earth, while whatever is calm and serene is said to belong to heaven.
It is evident that the air is similar to water, as it is proven to be enriched by its exhalations, creating the spirit of the storm—that is, wind and clouds—and it can support the flight of birds.
It does not say: Let the waters bring forth swarms of living creatures, and let the air bring forth birds above the earth; but it says: Let the waters bring forth swarms of living creatures, and let birds fly above the earth, because the air comes from water.
And whatever is wavy or fluid was given to the fish.
Anything that is moist or suspended like vapor clearly belongs to the air.
Just as fish swim in water using their fins, birds of the sky seem to fly through the air with their wings as if they were in water.
Therefore, it is said that they fly under the firmament of heaven, not in the firmament, because there is a continuous space where birds cannot fly.
This air flows from the luminous boundary of the sky down to the fluid waters and the bare earth; however, not all of it pertains to the earth.
From where it begins upwards, there are fire, hail, snow, ice, and stormy winds.
Whatever is above, due to its tranquility, is said to belong to heaven.
Demons are said to dwell in the air, and for this reason, the air tolerates them, because they use an aerial form, and from there they attack the human race.
As soon as they were created, they were cast out from the sight of God.
Thus, the Savior speaks to his disciples in the Gospel, saying: "I saw Satan fall like lightning from heaven" (Luke 10).
How could he be said to fall if he had not stood?
He did not persevere in the company of the holy angels.
As soon as he saw himself in the glory of God, he became proud against his Creator.
He said: "I will ascend above the heights of the clouds, and I will be like the Most High."
Immediately, he was cast out from the height of heaven into the air with all his followers who did not remain in divine love, unlike those who are confirmed so that they cannot sin even if they want to. They initially had free will, just as the human race now seems to have.
However, they fell from their own free will and received God's judgment that, even if they want to, they cannot be restored. Again, the Lord said: "He was a murderer from the beginning, and did not stand in the truth" (John 8).
How was he a murderer from the beginning?
He strangled the first Adam in paradise when he persuaded him to eat the fruit, and from being immortal, he became mortal.
Afterwards, he strangled the human race until the coming of the Savior.
How did he not remain in the truth?
Because he did not deserve to receive what was promised to him—to remain forever with his Creator and the other angels.
Instead, he was cast down to the earth with his followers, where they undoubtedly suffer punishment under a fiery, starry atmosphere.
They are confined to a kind of prison until Judgment Day.
Then, they will be thrown into eternal fire, where there is weeping and gnashing of teeth (Luke 13:28).
The air is often stirred up and becomes very cold, causing snow.
Sometimes, it becomes more tightly bound, creating storms, lightning, and thunder.
It eventually pours down to the lowest point because the air cannot sustain these phenomena.
Nonetheless, all these occurrences happen through divine providence and the hidden judgment of God.
Some relate the four elements of the world to the five senses of the body: fire to the eyes, air to hearing, moisture to smell and taste, and touch to the earth.
They say that nothing can be seen without fire, nor touched without earth, and thus all elements are present in humans.
Each element is named after what it has more of.
Therefore, when the body becomes excessively cold due to the deprivation of heat, the senses dull because the movement of heat within the body cools down.
Fire affects air, air affects moisture, and moisture affects the earthly, with the more subtle penetrating the denser.
The more subtle something is in physical nature, the closer it is to spiritual nature, although they are far apart in kind, since one is body and the other is not.
Since sensing is not of the body but of the soul through the body, it can be argued that the senses of the body are distributed according to the diversity of physical elements.
The soul, which possesses the power of sensing, exercises this power through the more subtle aspects of the body.
So, it begins movement in all senses towards the subtlety of fire, but it does not pertain to the same in all.
In sight, it reaches up to its light with suppressed heat;
in hearing, the heat of fire penetrates up to the thinner air;
in smell, pure air passes through and reaches the moist exhalation, where this thicker aura remains;
in taste, it passes through this and reaches the denser moisture, and once this is penetrated and transferred, when it reaches the earthly gravity, it activates the last sense of touch.
However, it is to be inquired when the smallest fish, or animals, or worms, which Scripture does not mention, were created.
When we must inquire from the largest elephant to the smallest worm, how they were created, we must understand by reason where this smallest creature comes from, since Scripture does not indicate this here.
It must be understood that when God separated the waters from the waters, then the smallest animals, which are made from the waters, had their nature in those waters.
And those worms, which come from dead bodies, where do they come from?
It must be understood that in the bodies they have their vigor of being born.
If the water covered the earth, or the earth covered the water, it is that the water covered the earth, as if some part of the land slid over the water, the water immediately returned to its place when the land was removed.
But how does it say in another place: because he founded it upon the seas, and established it upon the rivers (Psalm 24)?
If here the water covered the earth, it says this either about higher land where mountains appear to be; or it was said about islands where the land is higher than the water.
But this is more to be understood according to the sense that the simple ones in the Church are founded upon the prudent ones; and so, living waters are said to sustain those whom they see as weaker.
Because as much as there is between the moon and the stars of heaven, so much is there between holy rusticity and holy simplicity.
But as for fish, where are they created from, from water or from themselves?
This should be understood because they are created from waters, as it says:
"Let the waters bring forth swarms of living creatures."
And He blessed them, saying:
"Be fruitful and multiply."
Why did these animals deserve to receive a blessing like humans?
This is so we understand that this blessing remains in the other animals.
On the fifth day, living creatures were created in the waters, symbolizing humans renewed to life through the sacrament of baptism.
Birds were also created, representing holy souls ascending to the heavens.
On the Sixth Day
Regarding the sixth day, God also said:
Let the earth bring forth living creatures according to their kinds: livestock, creeping things, and wild animals of the earth according to their kinds.
Livestock, and every creeping thing of the earth according to its kind of living creature.
Simple animals are given for human use, while creeping things that crawl on the ground include snakes or other such creatures.
Wild animals of the earth include bears, lions, leopards, or other such creatures.
Wild animals are defined as anything that fights with teeth or claws.
It is necessary to consider whether these venomous creatures had venom in the beginning, as they do now.
It is to be understood that just as they were created then, so they remain.
But in the beginning, they did not have the power to harm, as we can see when a viper attacked Paul’s hand and did not harm him.
It had the power to attack but not to harm.
Similarly with wild animals, when Daniel was thrown into the lion's den, they did not harm him but licked his feet.
Or perhaps these venomous animals were created to frighten humans because God foresaw them sinning, so they would understand the punishments of hell, as it says elsewhere: Their worms do not die, and their fire is not quenched.
(Isaiah 66).
Therefore, wild animals harm each other, since they do not have the original sin from which to exact vengeance.
As the blessed Augustine says, "animals are fellow citizens in their kind." When they see an animal of another kind, they immediately quarrel among themselves, because animals live and feel; trees, however, live but do not feel. But man lives, feels, and understands, because he has the discernment to distinguish between good and evil.
On the Creation of Humans
And God saw that it was good and said: Let us make man in our image and likeness.
To suggest the plurality of persons, he speaks of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
Immediately after, he adds: And God created man to show the unity of majesty, in his image, so that he would remain immortal, and in his likeness, so that he would have the intellect of the mind, unlike animals who cannot distinguish between good and evil.
He did not endow him with bodily features, but with the intellect of the mind, so that he could understand his Creator and praise him forever without mortality.
However, when he was in honor, he did not understand; he was compared to senseless animals and became like them.
Psalm 48.
For when he did not want to observe the commands of his Creator, he became mortal like an animal in body, but not in soul, because he remained immortal.
Why then does he not repeat: And he made man, as with the other creatures he created?
It was not necessary, because he was an intellectual creature like angels.
Because to him, to be made is to understand the Word of God the Father, through whom all things were made.
John 1.
Why does he not say according to the kind, while the propagation of man is most evident?
It was not needed, because Adam was created in such a way that he would remain immortal, and time would pass, and he would remain immortal; or because the human race was to come from him, not from different creatures, like the different kinds of animals, fish, or birds.
It was not so with man, as if there were different kinds of humans on earth; but from one man, the human race came, because man surpasses animals, as his mind is directed towards heaven, and he understands to seek his Creator in heaven, who created him.
And let him have dominion over the fish of the sea, the birds of the air, and all the beasts, and all creatures.
That is, so that he would understand himself to be made in the image of God, while he surpasses so many animals with the intellect of his mind.
And God created man in His image.
In the image of God, He created him; male and female, He created them.
What does it mean that He created the female with the male, when she was not yet formed and would come from Adam, just as many things are hidden in the seed of a tree?
First, it is fixed in the root, then it becomes the tree, and later it spreads out into branches.
It grows leaves and so on.
In the same way, the woman was hidden in Adam's body because she was made from Adam's rib.
And He blessed them, saying: Be fruitful and multiply, and fill the earth, and subdue it.
Have dominion over the fish of the sea, the birds of the sky, and every living thing that moves on the earth.
Why did man deserve this blessing?
So that having children would not seem like a fault, which some might have said was a sin.
The Lord blessed man to have children to show that there was no sin in it, as long as it was done lawfully.
If Adam was created to remain immortal, what does it mean when it says: Be fruitful and multiply?
This should be understood to mean they should have children not out of carnal desire or any evil will, nor painfully as they do now, but as one commands their body to do something, like moving a hand to work or a foot to walk.
They should have had children in paradise in this way.
If they were to have children in such a way, why did they not come together to have children in paradise before they were cast out?
Because the woman, soon after being created, transgressed and was cast down from high immortality to the depths.
How did their bodies change if they were to remain immortal?
If they had not sinned, they would not have been able to die at all.
Their bodies, without mortality, after that number was fulfilled, would have been changed for the better, according to the number of angels.
And God said: See, I have given you every plant yielding seed and every tree with fruit, for you to have as food.
If Adam was immortal or mortal; and if mortal, how was he immortal?
And if physical, how was he spiritual?
And if spiritual, then why did he eat food just like the other animals?
He was both mortal and immortal because he could die; immortal because he could not die.
If he had not sinned, he would not have been able to die at all; but after he sinned, he became mortal.
He was mortal and immortal.
He was mortal by his nature, immortal by the grace of God, which he received from the tree of life, from which he was cast out when he sinned, so that he could die.
If that voice was striking the air, or how should this speech be understood?
His speech, before any sound in the air, and before any flesh, and the voice of the cloud, in that highest Wisdom through which all things were made, did not sound like it did to human ears.
So why is it that we, reborn through Christ, do not receive the same immortality which Adam had before sin?
We did not receive what we lost in Adam, that is, the physical body; but we receive something much better, as the spiritual is greater than the physical.
Hence the Apostle says: “It is sown a natural body, it is raised a spiritual body” (First Corinthians 15).
We did not receive the immortality of the spiritual body, but we received righteousness, which Adam lost through sin, of which the blessed Apostle says: “Be renewed in the spirit of your mind” (Ephesians 4).
How are we to be renewed?
That is, we will be renewed from the oldness of sin, not into the former physical body, in which Adam was, but into something better, that is, into a spiritual body, when we become equal to the angels of God in heavenly dwelling.
We will be renewed also in the spirit of our mind according to the image of him who created us, which Adam lost by sinning.
We will also be renewed in the flesh, when this corruptible puts on incorruption, and this mortal puts on immortality, so that the body becomes a spiritual body, in which Adam was not yet changed, but was to be changed.
Because we bear the image of the earthly man in the body, but the image of the heavenly man in the mind.
The Apostle says:
If there is a natural body, there is also a spiritual body.
As it is written:
The first man, Adam, became a living soul;
the last Adam, a life-giving spirit.
But the spiritual is not first, but the natural, and afterward the spiritual.
The first man was of the earth, earthly;
the second man is from heaven, heavenly.
As was the earthly man, so are those who are earthly.
Let us also bear the image of the heavenly man.
We have borne the image of the earthly man since the beginning of the human race.
Now, by faith, we carry the image of the heavenly man, which we believe will dwell in us in the resurrection.
And God saw everything He had made, and it was very good.
There was evening and morning, the sixth day.
If God created everything very good, where did evil come from?
Evil would not have existed if we had not made it.
It was not inherently part of nature, but the loss of good gave it this name.
Why did He not bless the trees or herbs, but did bless humans and animals?
He blessed these because of their ability to reproduce, or due to the male and female sexes, or because trees do not have the sense to feel or understand;
animals, however, live, feel, and do not understand.
Humans indeed feel and understand.
Therefore, He did not say to the trees: Grow and multiply.
On the Seventh Day
So the heavens and the earth, and all their array, were completed.
God finished His work on the seventh day, which He had made.
He blessed the seventh day and made it holy, because on it He rested from all His work, which He had created to make.
In doing so, He perfected the creation of the heavens and the earth.
The heavens with all their ornamentation, and the earth with all its work.
He finished His work on the seventh day.
On the sixth day, when He said: It is finished, and bowed His head and gave up His spirit.
On the seventh day, He rested in the tomb, fulfilling all things written about Him.
The Jews observed this day in shadow, as commanded to them by God through Moses.
But for us, this day signifies rest, because if we complete our works in good deeds, we rest with Christ forever.
The Sabbath means rest, because Christ is our rest, in whom we rest, as through His death, He transferred us from death to life.
He blessed the seventh day and made it holy.
Why did He bless the seventh day, on which He created nothing?
It was not because He was tired like a man who says: I thank my God, because I have finished my work.
Rather, the Lord created a day on which He created nothing to show it was no labor for Him to create everything, because He only said Let it be, and it was done.
Therefore, He rested on the seventh day, so that we might rest in Him.
In what did He bless the seventh day?
In nothing, except by Himself, because He is blessed by no one but Himself; sanctified by no one but Himself.
Although He did not create everything, He was not diminished, because nothing mutable is perceived in God—in eternity, in truth, or in will.
All remains fixed and unchangeable with Him.
What is this day?
It is the first, it is the second, it is the last, because it is the repetition of the seventh day.
And these three days that came before He placed the stars in the sky, do they count as days or not?
It should be understood that they do count as days because there was no light before that our eyes could see, as the authority of this Scripture is greater than any capacity of human intellect.
Just as Christ is light in one sense and a stone in another—light properly, stone figuratively—so also there was one kind of angelic light and another kind of the light of the stars.
So why did He not bless the first day, in which He created the angelic light, or that day in which He completed everything?
He did not sanctify the day in which He began this work, nor the one in which He completed it, so that it would not seem that His action brought joy either in the making or in the completion of these things, but rather in the day in which He rested in Himself after these works.
Yet, He never lacked that rest, but showed it to us through the seventh day, signifying that we would not attain His rest until after the completion of our work.
And thus it is known that on this day evening did not follow, because our rest after the completion of our work will be endless joy, as He ceased from all His work, that is, the creation of the new and unknown world, which God created to make, since He governs it until the end of the world, from where He Himself said in the Gospel: "My Father is working until now, and I am working" (John 5).
Why did He not place morning on the first day, nor evening on the last day?
Morning was not placed because it has no beginning; and evening because it has no end, nor is it enclosed by any boundary.
And again according to the spiritual sense.
Recapitulation of the Six Days
On the sixth day, the earth brings forth living creatures.
When our flesh abstains from dead works, it gives birth to living virtues, according to its kind—that is, by imitating the lives of the saints.
As the Apostle says: Be imitators of me First Corinthians 4.
We indeed live according to our kind when we imitate holy men in good deeds, as if they were our neighbors.
Then the earth produced beasts, representing men in the power of things, or in the ferocity of pride.
Similarly, it produced cattle, representing faithful men living in simplicity, and serpents, representing harmless holy men who, through the liveliness of their cunning, discern good from evil.
To the extent that it is lawful, they explore earthly things by crawling, through which they understand eternal things.
Not those poisonous ones who place themselves in the earthly desires of this world.
After this, God made man in His own image—a perfect man who, not by imitating any of the holy men, but by contemplating the very truth, acts justly, so that he understands and follows the very truth, in whose image he was created.
This man also received dominion over the fish of the sea, the birds of the sky, and the cattle, wild animals, and creeping things, because anyone who has become spiritual and made like God, according to the Apostle, judges all things, but he himself is judged by no one First Corinthians 15.
As for what follows: He made them male and female, He shows them to be spiritual and obedient in the Church.
For just as a woman is subject to a man, so is the less perfect person obedient to the spiritual and perfect man, as the Apostle says: We ask you, brothers, to recognize those who labor among you and are over you in the Lord First Thessalonians 5.
They are told: Be fruitful and multiply, whether in languages or in spiritual degrees of understanding, so that they may rule through the intellect of reason over all carnal disturbances, as if over irrational animals.
All plants that produce seeds and all fruit trees, which have been given to humans as food, are faithful, and they share their offerings with the saints.
Hence, the Apostle says:
"For if the Gentiles have shared in their spiritual blessings, they ought to also be of service to them in material things."
These are the fruitful trees.
In these stages, it's as if there are evenings where the perfection of each work is completed, and mornings where the next works begin.
In the seventh, after these works, which are like the six days of creation, man hopes for the rest of the mind, established in the spiritual paradise, signifying a blessed life.
Here, the fountain of wisdom is divided into four parts of virtue, where one can eat the grace of the tree of life, and pick useful teachings of morals, like the fruits of trees.
Paradise is indeed the life of the blessed; the four rivers are the four virtues; its trees are all useful teachings; the fruits of the trees are the morals of the pious; the tree of life is the wisdom from which all good things come, as written by Solomon:
"The tree of life is for those who take hold of her; those who hold her fast will be blessed."
(Proverbs 3).
The tree of the knowledge of good and evil is the transgression of the command.
The works of the six days, as they are spiritually understood in the Church, have been explained so far, and now we must add what they signify in the figure of the world.
God completed all His works in six days and rested on the seventh.
The six ages of humankind in this world, through the succession of times, suggest God's works:
the first is from Adam to Noah; the second, from Noah to Abraham; the third, from Abraham to David; the fourth, from David to the Babylonian exile; the fifth, from the Babylonian exile to the humble coming of our Lord Jesus Christ; the sixth, which is now ongoing, until the world ends, until the Most High comes for judgment.
The seventh is understood to be the rest of the saints, which indeed does not have an evening, because it is closed by no end.
Let's briefly go through these ages of the world and highlight their mystical differences by recounting their timeline.
In the first age, there was light, with man in paradise.
During this era, God separated the children of light, known as the sons of God, from the children of men, much like separating light from darkness.
The evening of this day was marked by the flood.
The second age was like a firmament between the waters: the ark floated between the rain and the seas.
The evening of this age was marked by the confusion of languages.
In the third age, God separated His people from the nations through Abraham, distinguishing them like dry land from the waters.
This was to bring forth the sprouting of herbs and trees, symbolizing the spiritual saints and the fruit of the Holy Scriptures.
The evening of this age was marked by the sin and wickedness of the evil king Saul.
The fourth age began with David, when God set lights in the firmament of the heavens.
This represented the splendor of the kingdom like the excellence of the sun, and the light of the synagogue like the light of the moon, with its leaders as stars.
The evening of this age was marked by the sins of the kings, which led to the people's captivity in Babylon.
In the fifth age, during the Babylonian exile, it was as if animals in the waters and birds in the sky were created, because the Jews began to live among the nations like in the sea.
They had no stable place, like flying birds.
The evening of this age was marked by the multiplication of sins among the Jewish people, to the point where they were so blinded that they couldn't even recognize their Lord.
Now, the sixth age is upon us with the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ.
Just as on the sixth day the first man Adam was formed from the dust of the earth in the image of God, so in this sixth age, the second Adam, that is, Christ, was born of the Virgin Mary.
He is a living soul, here in a life-giving spirit.
Just as a living soul was made on that day, so now, those desiring eternal life.
Just as on the sixth day the earth brought forth kinds of serpents and beasts, so in this sixth age of the world, the Church has generated peoples seeking eternal life.
This meaning was also shown to Peter in a vision.
Just as on that day male and female were created, so in this sixth age of the world, Christ and the Church are revealed.
Just as man is set over the beasts, serpents, and birds of the sky on that day, so Christ is set over the peoples, nations, and tribes in this age, to be ruled by Him.
Whether they are given to carnal desires like beasts, obscured by earthly curiosity like serpents, or lifted by pride like birds.
Just as man and the animals with him are fed with seed-bearing plants, fruit-bearing trees, and green herbs on that day, so in this age the spiritual man, a good minister of Jesus Christ, is spiritually fed with the elements of the Holy Scriptures and the divine law.
To conceive fruitful thoughts and words like seed-bearing plants, partly for the benefit of human conduct, like fruit-bearing trees, and partly for the strength of faith, hope, and charity into eternal life, like green herbs, which do not wither under the heat of tribulations but are nourished by spiritual food.
So he is fed with these foods to understand many things.
The carnal, that is, the immature in Christ, like God's flock, believe many things they cannot yet understand, but they all have the same foods.
May the evening of this age not find us, for it is about this that the Lord says:
"When the Son of Man comes, will he find faith on earth?"
Luke 18:8.
After this evening, morning will come when the Lord Himself will come in glory.
Then those to whom it was said:
"Be perfect, as your Father in heaven is perfect"
Matthew 5:48, will rest with Christ from all their works.
For such people do very good works.
After such works, rest is to be expected on the seventh day, which has no evening.
These are the generations of the heavens and the earth when they were created, in the day that the Lord God made the heavens and the earth, and every plant of the field before it was in the earth, and every herb of the field before it grew.
We must investigate whether all these things were made in one day or over six days, as Scripture recounts.
If they were made over six days, how does the Holy Scripture say: He who lives forever created all things at once, Ecclesiasticus 18?
Because He created all things at once according to the substance of things.
However, according to their form, He did not create all things at once.
Just as a mother nursing her infant waits for it to grow strong, so the Lord waited for the slowness of human understanding.
In the beginning, all things were created with Him, but they did not immediately appear in form when He said: In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth Genesis 1.
Then all things, as we said, were made with Him—whatever arose from the heavens and the earth—although He wished to divide them into forms over six days.
As it says on the fourth day, He placed the stars in the sky, yet on the first day they were made in the sky with Him, which appeared in form on the fourth day.
Just as many things are hidden in a grain of seed—root, bark, leaves, fruit, and many other things that come from the tree—so all these things were first hidden with God, which later came into form.
Therefore, He made all things at once, as the Lord said: My Father is working until now, and I am working John 5.
Although He created all things at once, He still governs daily, in watering, planting, building, and other matters.
Just as a man who works a field, if he leaves it, it remains uncultivated, so the world created by God cannot exist without God's governance.
According to the apostle Paul: Neither he who plants nor he who waters is anything, but only God who gives the growth First Corinthians 3.
There are also others who interpret these seven days as the seven gifts of the Holy Spirit.
These gifts are the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and strength, the spirit of knowledge and piety, and the spirit of the fear of the Lord.
(Isaiah 11)
It is said that through the spirit of wisdom, God made heaven and earth.
Through the spirit of understanding, He created the firmament and separated the waters.
With the spirit of counsel, He divided the waters from the dry land and made the earth produce vegetation.
Through the spirit of strength, He placed lights in the firmament to divide day from night.
Using the spirit of knowledge, He adorned the waters with creatures and the air with birds.
Through the spirit of piety, He populated the earth with animals and created man.
Finally, through the spirit of the fear of the Lord, He sanctified His work on the seventh day.
Thus, we too should embody these seven gifts of the Holy Spirit within ourselves.
Through the spirit of wisdom, we should meditate on heavenly things and forsake earthly ones, or separate light from darkness, meaning our perfect works from the darkness of the wicked.
With the spirit of understanding, we should create a firmament between virtues and vices, ensuring we do not fall into vices.
Through the spirit of counsel, we should distinguish the reprobate people from the soul that knows God's words.
With the spirit of strength, we should place lights in the firmament, symbolizing the love of God and neighbor, for as Saint John said, "Whoever hates his brother is a murderer." (First John)
Through the spirit of knowledge, we must fill the waters with creatures that crawl, and from the depths of our hearts, send our voices to heaven, just as fish leap from the water and birds soar through the sky.
Similarly, we should always elevate our thoughts to higher things.
Through the spirit of piety, we should act with simplicity and wisdom to distinguish good from evil and produce the fruits of good deeds.
By doing so, we follow the examples of the saints and the truth itself, in whose image we were created.
Through the spirit of the fear of the Lord, we should rest in the peace of eternal life, for it is written: "The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom" (Psalm 110).
Why did He not place morning on the first day or evening on the seventh day?
He did not place morning because He foresaw that man would sin in paradise, and the night of ignorance would follow him.
He did not place evening on the seventh day because He foresaw that man would return to grace through the coming of the Savior.
In the beginning, did night follow day, or day follow night?
Night followed day.
And now, after the coming of the Savior, day follows night, symbolizing that man fell when he transgressed, and night, representing sin, followed him.
But after the Savior's coming, day follows night because He restored us to grace and, through His death, transferred us from death to life, which we had lost through the fault of our first parent, Adam.
Night followed him because holy men were confined to the underworld until the coming of the Lord.
Now, day follows us because after His resurrection, all the saints who leave their bodies go to Christ.
What we lost in Adam, we regained through Jesus Christ.
These are the generations of the heavens and the earth when they were created, on the day the Lord God made the heavens and the earth.
Previously, seven days were counted, but now it is called one day, on which God made the heavens and the earth, every shrub of the field, and every herb of the region.
By the name of this day, according to the prophet, the entire span of this life is signified, in which the heavens and the earth were made—that is, in which visible creatures are arranged, managed, and exist.
But what does it mean that now, having named the heavens and the earth, he adds the shrub of the field and the herb of the region, while remaining silent about the rest that is in the heavens, on the earth, or even in the sea?
This is because, by the shrub of the field, he shows the invisible creature to be understood, such as the soul.
The shrub is mentioned because of the vigor of life; the herb, because of the same life, never withering.
Then, what he added: Before it was on the earth, is understood as before the soul sinned.
For being defiled by earthly desires, it is rightly said to be born on the earth, or to be on the earth.
For the Lord God had not rained on the earth, and there was no man to work the ground: therefore the earth had not sprouted, because the Lord had not rained on the earth; and there was no man to work the ground, because the earth sprouts and produces fruit especially because of the rain and the man who works it.
Hence he also added: For the Lord God had not yet rained on the earth, as if it were openly said: Before the soul sinned, the Lord had not yet granted the rain of the doctrine of the Scriptures to irrigate the soul.
Not yet had our Lord assumed the cloud of our flesh, through which he poured the abundant rain of the holy Gospel.
That he adds: And there was no man to work the ground, means no man worked in the Virgin, from whom Christ was born.
For he is the stone cut out of the mountain without hands, that is, without intercourse and human seed from the virginal womb, as if cut out of the mountain of human nature and the substance of the flesh (Daniel 2).