Saint Gall, Abbot and Confessor. In the year of our Lord 646,
Historical notice on Saint Gall. Fabricius, Library of the Middle and Late Ages.
Gallus of Ireland, a confessor and disciple of Saint Columbanus, served as abbot in Arbon, Germany.
He passed away in 640 A.
D.
at the age of ninety-five.
His memory is honored in the martyrologies on October sixteenth.
His life, documented in two books by Walafrid Strabo, is available in Surius on October sixteenth and in Thomas Messingham's "Florilegium of the Saints of Ireland," on pages two hundred fifty-five and two hundred ninety-four.
His memory is also recorded by Notker on October sixteenth and regarding his translation on November sixteenth, as well as by Ratpert in verses about the feast of Saint Gall.
On page four hundred fifteen, you can find a sermon delivered by him in the Church of Saint Stephen during the consecration of Bishop John of Constance in 614.
This sermon was first published by Canisius in volume five of the Ancient Readings, part two, page eight hundred ninety-six, and later reprinted in the Supplement of the Parisian Library of the Fathers, volume one, page six hundred seventy-eight, and in the Lyons Library, volume eleven, page one thousand forty-six. It was also published separately with notes by Caspar Barth in Frankfurt, 1623, octavo.
Regarding the church governance and the advice to Wulmar the priest mentioned by Baleus, I believe it has been lost or at least not published.
Among the small works of Gall published by Barth, which the distinguished man speculated about, they do not exist, as Barth only published the sermon by Gall already mentioned.
A brief letter to Desiderius, bishop of Cahors from the year 1635, where Gall the sinner always refers to him as his lord and apostolic Father, was published by James Ussher in the Irish Letters, page twenty-three.
In this letter, there is mention of the disaster at Marseille.
The renowned monastery of Saint Gall in Swabia, of the Benedictine order, is discussed by Goldastus in the Alemannic writings.
Refer to volume one, page six and following, and the epigrams and sacred hymns of the illustrious men of that monastery in volume five, part two, of the Ancient Readings of Henry Canisius, new edition volume two, part three, page one hundred eighty-five and following.
A very brief chronicle of the monastery of Saint Gall from 691 to 814 A.D. is found in Baluze's Miscellany, volume one, pages four hundred ninety-four to four hundred ninety-five.
Finally, Jodocus Mezler, a monk from St.
Gall, wrote two books about the notable men of the St. Gall monastery.
These books were published in 1606 and can be found in Bernard Pez's first volume of Anecdotes, part 3, page 555.
Here's some more information about Saint Gall.
(Galland, Library of the Fathers, Volume 12.)
According to the accounts written by Walafrid Strabo, Saint Gall, the abbot, was born around the middle of the sixth century in Ireland.
His parents entrusted him to Saint Columbanus for his education.
Under Columbanus's guidance, he was thoroughly trained in piety and scholarship, particularly in divine studies, and later embraced monastic life at the monastery in Bangor.
As a devoted follower of his teacher, he traveled to Britain, Gaul, and Alemannia.
He would have accompanied Columbanus to Italy, but he was struck by a severe fever and remained among the Alemanni.
After regaining his health, he began building a cell, which eventually became a famous monastery named after him.
While living there with twelve monks whom he had gathered around the oratory he constructed, he miraculously knew that Saint Columbanus had passed away at the monastery in Bobbio, even though he was far away.
Near death, it's said Columbanus sent his staff and a letter as a symbol of paternal goodwill to him.
Walafridus, who has already been praised, shares these and many other stories about Saint Gall.
After reaching the age of ninety-five, the blessed man finally passed away around the year 645 or the following year, on October 16, as more precise calculations by the learned Mabillon indicate.
Additionally, among Saint Gall's writings, there is a sermon he delivered in Constance at the church of Saint Stephen, on the day John was consecrated as bishop of Constance.
This sermon was first published from a manuscript in the Sangallensis library by Canisius.
Walafridus notes that, after the usual divine offerings were made, following the Gospel reading, the venerable Gall was invited to provide sacred instruction to the gathered crowd.
He ascended the platform with Bishop John, intending to gather the tools of edification while the bishop interpreted and conveyed them for the benefit of the barbarians.
So, he began to speak about the beginning of creation, recalling Adam's sin, which led to his expulsion from paradise.
He moved on to the story of the flood, briefly covering the times and actions of the patriarchs.
He also recounted the exodus of the Israelites from Egypt, their crossing of the Red Sea, the giving of the law through Moses, and the miracles of heavenly food.
After touching on the succession of kings and the times of the prophets, he laid out the time of the coming of the Lord.
Remembering the baptism of the Savior and the glory of his miracles, he truthfully added the disgrace of the cross and the forms of persecution by the wicked.
Hearing this, the church leaders, along with the multitude of people, wept abundantly; they said to one another, "Truly, the Holy Spirit has spoken today through the mouth of this man."
He continued his preaching up to the resurrection of Christ and concluded with the remembrance of the general judgment.
Therefore, all who were present, filled with joy, blessed the Lord and returned to their homes with joy.
Up to this point, Walafridus recounted the main points of this remarkable sermon.
Indeed, such a work is a distinguished and exceptional monument of ecclesiastical antiquity, as rightly judged by the learned writers of the Literary History of Gaul.
In another opinion, however, Basnagius had a different view regarding the value of this sermon, thinking that some parts needed correction.
Of the things this critic disapproved of, we consider one worth noting: for the rest, we do not delay, whether he is looking for trouble in a simple matter or shows himself carried away by a partisan interest.
The passage particularly noted by Basnagius is as follows: In the twelfth year of his age, when Christ remained in the temple unknown to his parents, they found him after three days among the teachers, acting with great wisdom.
When his mother asked why he had left her grieving, he replied, "I must be about my Father's business," clearly implying that the temple belonged to him no less than to God the Father.
These are the words of Saint Gallus, indeed a very good interpreter.
What does Basnage say to this?
He claims that Saint Gallus interprets the temple as referring to the things Christ was preaching about, which were commanded by the Father.
From this, he concludes with a rather weak argument that the temple belongs to Christ just as much as it does to the Father.
Thus speaks the most critical man.
Truly, ineptly.
The common interpretation by scholars is that "in his quae Patris" means "in the Father's affairs," specifically in the Father's business. However, even if the phrase "to be in someone's business" isn't incorrect, it's never read as "in his" instead of "in business." On the contrary, we can prove with countless examples that "en tois tou patros," "in his quae Patris sunt," means the father's house, just as "en tois tou despotou," "in his quae domini sunt," means the master's house. "en tois Aman," in the house of Haman, as interpreted by the common translator in Esther chapter seven, verse nine, and in Sirach chapter forty-two, verse ten, "en tois patrikois autes," in her father's, implying house. Similarly, "en tois tou Dios," in Josephus against Apion: "in his quae Jovis sunt," that is, in the temple of Jupiter. The temple was called the house of God. So, Jesus himself refers to it in John chapter two, verse sixteen. Therefore, the Lord’s response was fitting to his mother's concern: Why were you looking for me elsewhere than where it was proper for me to be, namely, in the temple, my Father's house? For he should not be sought anywhere else than in the father's house. The response of Christ matched Mary's words, as Theophylact elegantly notes: when she referred to Joseph as father, he said: This is not my true father; otherwise, I would have stayed in his house. But God is my Father, and therefore I am in His house, that is, in His temple. So far, V. C. and other very learned men, like Pole, Blackwall, Bosius, Ottius, Wolfius, and Glassius, not to mention others, have said nothing different. If Basnage had consulted at least one of them, he might not have concluded with such a weak argument, as I think, but with a very appropriate one, declaring that Saint Gallus concluded from the words "in his quae Patris mei sunt" that the temple belongs to Christ just as much as it does to the Father.
An important point to note, as highlighted by the esteemed scholars mentioned earlier, is a letter from Canisius addressed to Bishop Desiderius of Cahors.
Ussher, Cave, and Fabricius attribute this letter to Saint Gall, the subject of our discussion, while acknowledging another Saint Gall as the author.
Specifically, the Bishop of Clermont with the same name, the second, about whom the authors of Gallia Christiana should be consulted.
A Sermon Delivered at Constanceby Saint Gallus, an Abbot and Confessor
God is eternal and immeasurable, with His co-eternal wisdom, that is, His eternal Son, and the eternal love shared with Himself and His Son, which is the Holy Spirit.
He exists in blessed and immortal majesty, without any beginning or change in time, or need for places or services.
However, He is not thought to have remained alone without the service of His servants, as the Apostle clearly says:
"He chose us in Christ before the foundation of the world."
Ephesians 1:4.
This was done by eternal predestination, not by temporary creation, but by free calling or unearned grace.
God, who always orders all future things by His goodness as if they are already done, especially regarding the society of holy angels and humans, sometimes deemed it worthy, by His immovable counsel, to create from nothing the creature foreseen and predestined to praise Him and live blessedly from Him, in Him, and through Him, by His almighty workmanship.
He made a dwelling for blessed spirits in the heavens and prepared the earth for future humans.
We should understand the reason for their creation, dear Christian brothers, so that you do not disregard your dignity by considering yourselves worthless and lowly, fit only for the behavior of animals.
God, supremely good and full of benevolence, free from envy and unaware of malice, decided to create rational angelic spirits in His image, so that by knowing their Lord as the author of their origin and being refreshed by the richness of His love, they might delight in being blessed in Him.
However, when some of them, not yet having tasted His sweetness, presumptuously and foolishly convinced themselves that they were their own beginning and head, life, and sweetness, they became empty and void within, weighed down by the burden of pride.
As a result, they were cast down from the peaceful dwelling of the heavens into the stormy turbulence of this air, until the day of the general and eternal judgment, by a sudden fall.
Yet, the unchanging will of the kind Creator, aiming to complete the predetermined number of the blessed assembly, appointed the human race to take their place.
He left these humans, endowed with reason and guided by commands and warnings, to their own free will so that, by imitating God, they would reject wicked and unjust things and strive to uphold what is right and just.
However, the wicked murderer Satan, who did not spare even himself, was deeply troubled by the honor God gave to humans and, out of envy, persuaded the unsuspecting to fall into the same pride that destroyed him.
That is, they chose, with deadly delight, not to worship the eternal Creator as God, but to regard themselves, the temporal creature, as gods.
This greatest and most monstrous sin led to such vile acts and crimes that divine justice decided to destroy the world, adorned in every way, along with the human race appointed to govern it, by the waters of the flood.
And He would have done so, if His immense goodness had not surpassed our great wickedness.
Therefore, He did not leave such crimes unpunished, yet He did not entirely consume the well-created creature.
From all humans, He chose one just man, through whose foresight, or rather His own warning, an ark was constructed.
In it, this man, with his household and a suitable remnant of creation, survived the utmost dangers, marveling at how he remained as a survivor of a world seemingly dead.
And when almost a full year had passed, the Creator, out of compassion, brought out Noah, named as a prophetic consoler of such rightful vengeance, from the prison of that enclosure.
He blessed him, his offspring, and the seed of all creation with a new blessing.
And as the children of Adam began to flourish again, pride, which had been condemned at its root, revived to such an extent that mortal men, made of clay, attempted to build a tower of clay and bitumen, from whose summit they might invade the starry and immortal dwelling, even against the will of God, its rightful owner.
The plan of such an invincible machine, as it seemed to some, was easily disrupted by the all-powerful wisdom.
With the languages becoming so diverse and the similarities turning into differences, no one could understand the language of their relatives or brothers.
Because of this, people were scattered across different regions and places.
Divided by lands and languages, they were also divided by religion, or rather, madness.
Some worshipped the heavenly nature provided by God with divine worship and servitude through human services.
Others, however, created images of deceased people, invoking evil spirits as if they were protectors and supporters of the living, and began to worship them foolishly, though they were justly mortal.
But the tireless mercy of the immortal and true deity did not completely abandon the creature it kindly created, nor did it withhold its compassion.
From among the nations given to idolatry, it called Abraham, the father of future believers, to know the true and living God.
Abraham, full of incomparable obedience, followed the divine command, leaving his land and kindred without knowing where he was going, as long as he fulfilled God's command.
Because of this, he received a promise from above that he would receive the land of his sojourning as a possession, which came to pass among the Jews descended from him: and that in his seed all nations would be blessed.
We rejoice that this has been fulfilled in us through Christ, born according to the flesh from his seed through the Virgin.
Therefore, as a sign of this faith proven in uncircumcision, the sign of circumcision was imposed on Abraham.
It was necessary for the nation descended from his lineage to bear this sign until the one came who would redeem all who believed in him from all sin and the burden of circumcision, through his suffering.
When a large number of people left Canaan, where they lived, due to a famine, they entered Egypt.
God sent one of their leaders there to save many.
Through his foresight, the world, which was nearly threatened by a lack of food, was somewhat preserved.
According to the customs of that nation, they began to worship various strange creatures and were also oppressed by the Egyptians with very hard labor.
Remembering the faith and righteousness of their ancestors, God sent His servant Moses to them.
Through many signs and unbearable plagues, he defeated the Egyptians and led God's people, guided by divine leadership, to the land long promised to the patriarch Abraham.
As they left that land and rested, exhausted, between the edge of the Red Sea and the vast wilderness, the Egyptian king, angered by losing their servitude, gathered an army with chariots and trapped them like fish in a net.
As they raised their voices to the true God, the waters of the sea parted, providing a dry path for them to travel.
Seeing this, the worshipers of monkeys and the dog-headed Anubis realized it was useless to appease Neptune, since the waters were divided in such a manner.
All those who followed the paths of those who passed through entered the depths of their own destruction, and as the last of God's people crossed to the natural shore, they were so engulfed by the mountains of water that no one was left to report back home about what had happened.
When the supplies the Hebrews brought from Egypt ran out, God provided them with bread and meat from heaven, sweetened bitter water, or brought forth water from a rock.
He led them through the desert for forty years to the Promised Land to wean them from idolatry, which they had left behind and would encounter wherever they went.
Just as He guided them to avoid other evils, He warned them from heaven to steer clear of idolatry and instructed them diligently to know Him and follow good and just ways.
Remembering His promise, He mercifully brought them into the land.
Just as He had previously allowed them to cross the Red Sea, He now commanded and enabled them to cross the Jordan River on dry land.
While those who witnessed these wonders were still alive, the knowledge and worship of the true God and divine truth remained pure.
But when they passed away, their descendants, instead of following their ancestors' faith, fell into idolatry by worshiping the idols of the surrounding nations.
For this sin, they were delivered into the hands of their enemies, whether near or far.
When they were justly oppressed and turned back to the God of their fathers through prayer, He raised up someone from among their own people to be their savior against their enemies and a suitable judge to maintain unity among them.
Although they wavered for a long time, meaning when prosperity smiled upon them, they would turn to idol worship.
When persecution threatened, they would make every effort to return to the true God, their safest harbor.
Finally, He gave them a king named David, who defended them from the incursions of neighboring nations and maintained the fear of God, of whom he was full.
True to his name, "Strong Hand," he kept them on a steady course.
After his death, due to the sins of his sons, only two tribes, Benjamin and Judah, remained loyal to the descendants of David.
These tribes, along with a few priests and Levites, were known as the Jews.
The other ten, or rather eleven tribes, led by a king named Jeroboam and his wicked descendants, turned away from their glory, that is, from the eternal God, to the impurity of idolatry.
God delivered them into the hands of their enemies, where they were subjected and forced to worship idols, even those who didn't want to.
Even the most faithful lineage of David eventually fell into faithlessness.
So much so that even their kings and priests, neglecting the worship of the one true God, were driven by madness to worship Saturn, Juno, and Priapus in Jerusalem itself.
This city, chosen by Him for sanctification, witnessed such infidelity.
Because of this, God, wickedly abandoned by them, justly left them to the power of the pagans.
This fulfilled what He had previously warned them: Jeremiah Chapter Five, Verse Nineteen and Chapter Sixteen, Verse Thirteen, "Just as you served foreign gods in your land, so you will serve foreign gods in a land not your own, who will not give you rest."
But even then, not forgetting the faith of Abraham and David, He kept some of them as a remnant in their land.
He preserved His temple in Jerusalem for a while, until their increasing sins led to its destruction along with its citizens and the city.
Yet, divine mercy did not completely abandon them.
From the ashes and ruins of the overthrown city, He saved some, to whom the prophetic saying aptly applied: "You have become like a brand plucked from the fire, and yet you have not returned to me," says the Lord.
Amos Chapter Four, Verse Eleven.
We know this happened to those who were left in their own land.
Driven by desperation, they added sin to sin, devastating each other with mutual slaughter, and felt compelled to flee to Egypt for safety, despite the divine oracle's prohibition, only to meet slaughter.
Those who, by God's will, were subdued by the king who conquered their pride, were taken into distant captivity, where they turned to the God of their fathers with all their hearts.
They were refined in the fire of tribulation to such an extent that no material fire could separate them from His love.
Eventually, the merciful and compassionate Lord took pity on their severe hardships and changed the hearts of their captor kings, who then willingly granted them leniency and relief.
They even ordered that many resources from public revenues and treasuries be used to help them return to their land and restore the temple of God.
But alas, what a sorrow!
While they diligently tried to observe the law of God and its ceremonies as much as possible, despite obstacles from neighboring and mixed enemies, something unimaginable happened.
A wicked Greek king, like a precursor to the worst Antichrist, oppressed them so severely that they believed only the hand of the heavenly Emperor could lift them up.
He delivered them with such a miracle from the onslaught of savage, diverse, and innumerable adversaries that very few Jews survived, and those who did instilled not a little terror wherever they went.
When those who learned to fear the Lord of their fathers were wiped out by various misfortunes, leaving the world desolate by their deaths, because of the sins of those remaining, first lowly persons from among their successors were appointed over the people of God.
Later, they were mixed with foreigners or rather subjected to the yoke of servitude.
It was necessary that divine Wisdom itself, through which all things were made, deemed it worthy to consult in restoring the human race by itself.
In its incomprehensible majesty, the divine nature couldn't be grasped by the weak and mortal.
So, through a wonderful act of compassion, it arranged to conform to our mortal weakness while maintaining its unchanging power, being born from the womb of an incorrupt Virgin.
It grew in age and development like any other, reaching youthful years with unique grace and wisdom.
Even though its divinity wasn't obscured by its flesh, it remained hidden only from those who refused to receive it, even after knowing it.
At its birth, an angel of the Lord appeared with great brightness to the shepherds of that nation, announcing that its birth would benefit all nations.
In response, a multitude of the heavenly host sang.
At the same time, in distant regions of the East, a new star unexpectedly appeared to the wise, who were knowledgeable about the stars, leading them to the birthplace of the new king.
On the fortieth day after its birth, when the Virgin mother brought him to the temple of God to present him according to her nation's solemn custom, the Savior of the world was recognized by holy people there and announced to other faithful.
In his tenth and twelfth year, he remained in the temple, unbeknownst to his parents, who thought he had left the city with relatives and acquaintances.
Not finding him, they returned to the temple and, after three days, found him in the midst of the teachers, acting with great wisdom.
When his mother asked why he had left her in distress, he replied, "I must be in the things of my Father," clearly indicating that the temple belonged to him no less than to God the Father.
In the thirtieth year since he began living among humans, he went to be baptized by his servant, setting an example for those who followed him. He showed that no one should disdain being baptized by a lesser person, remembering that their Lord and God was baptized by the hands of his servant.
Although he sought baptism in water not because he needed it himself, but to teach humility, God the Father proclaimed from heaven, "This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased: listen to him."
The Holy Spirit, who had already conceived him, descended upon him like a dove, symbolizing his innocence and holiness.
Thus, Christ, glorified and empowered as a man to face the devil's challenge, went into the desert to complete a forty-day fast.
After this time, the cunning adversary noticed signs of hunger from his physical appearance, mistakenly thinking him merely human, yet feared him for his blameless life. He approached with this strategy:
If he could satisfy his hunger by turning a stone into bread, as the devil suggested, it would reveal his divine power, and the devil would stop his harm and persecution.
But if he couldn't, proving to be purely human, the devil would see him as just another mortal.
However, the admirable teacher of piety skillfully thwarted his tricks, ensuring that the devil neither witnessed divine power by turning stones into bread, nor gained confidence against our weaknesses, declaring that a rational soul's life isn't sustained by material food alone, but by every word from the mouth of God.
In this confrontation, the devil became more convinced than before.
Using the lure of vain glory, which he knew greatly tempted humans, he sought to probe Christ's divinity:
He took him to the pinnacle of the highest temple and suggested that if he were the Son of God, he should jump and remain unharmed.
To this undefeated warrior, he crafted his speech in such a way that he neither denied being the Son of God nor encouraged succumbing to the devil's temptations.
He explained that it would not be wise for anyone to presume to test their Lord and God.
So, defeated in this challenge, the enemy, through the greed by which he boasted of having destroyed the world and confident he could subdue Christ, showed him all the kingdoms of the world and their glory.
He proposed that if Christ worshiped him, he would give him all these things.
The teacher of humility, horrified by such extreme blasphemy, with righteous indignation, drove away this monstrous abomination.
He declared that a devout heart is to worship the Lord God and serve him alone.
Struck by the power of these words, the adversary withdrew from him until an opportune time.
As it is written in Luke Chapter 4, Verse 13, the angels, admiring the most victorious triumph of our King, paid him due homage.
With these things accomplished, Christ the Lord returned to the people.
According to Scripture, he brought salvation to the midst of the earth, restoring sight to the blind, hearing to the deaf, speech to the mute, and cleansing to lepers.
He gave mobility to the disabled, sanity to the possessed, strength to the paralyzed, and walking to the lame, granting healing to countless unnamed illnesses.
Furthermore, he fed four thousand followers with seven loaves and a few small fish.
At another time, with five loaves and two fish, he fed five thousand men, not counting the vast number of women and children, so that twelve baskets of leftover fragments were gathered as a testament to this great miracle.
He also walked on the sea with dry feet, raised the stinking dead from the tomb, and when invited to a feast, turned water into wine.
Above all, the Father from heaven, on one occasion while the disciples were listening, and sometimes with countless crowds present, proclaimed him as his Son.
He promised that he had already glorified him and would glorify him further.
But who can truly describe his teachings?
He presented such profound instructions to his disciples that human ability alone could hardly achieve them without the powerful aid of God himself.
He ensured these teachings were shared with everyone, regardless of gender or status, so that no one, unless very ignorant and utterly unworthy of divine grace, would be excluded from the kingdom of God.
Ultimately, he convinced the apostles and their followers to embrace the virtue of virginity, showing them that this was not due to human effort, but a gift from God.
He also taught them that giving up all possessions and attachments should be done with the understanding that they would receive much more in this world than they surrendered, and in the future, gain eternal life, joining him as judges on the day of the great judgment.
He instructed other believers to pursue humility, gentleness, peace, mercy, justice, and patience, never tiring in their quest for the kingdom of God, even enduring the persecutions of the wicked if necessary.
Furthermore, he commanded everyone not to, in anger, hurl curses or insults at their brothers, or, failing to avoid such actions, fall into murder.
He taught that no one should look at a neighbor's wife with impure intentions, thus avoiding adultery; nor should anyone rashly swear oaths, risking perjury; and no one should stubbornly resist their adversary, thereby endangering not only their soul but also their body.
For those who long for a more perfect life and eagerly seek the kingdom of heaven, He laid out a way of living that involves letting go of worldly things and embracing simplicity.
Yet, they were not to worry about lacking necessities, as He inspired other Christians with abundant worldly goods to support them.
Anyone who helped these poor people was believed to be serving Christ and God the Father.
He called out those who falsely worshipped God and those who boasted about their noble lineage as hypocrites and offspring of vipers.
He criticized the priests who pretended to be pious but hid evil in their hearts, calling them blind and leaders of the blind.
Using a fitting comparison, He likened them to whitewashed tombs, which look beautiful on the outside but are full of filth inside.
He also challenged the Pharisees, who considered themselves righteous and looked down on others, refusing to repent of their sins.
He stated that He came not to call the righteous, but to seek and save sinners and the lost.
He demonstrated that He was the true Son of God not only through miraculous signs and unmatched wisdom but also by fulfilling prophetic writings and presenting unassailable arguments.
However, the unbelieving Jews repeatedly disrespected God through His saints and continued their malicious schemes against His only Son, insulting Him with words and even attacking Him with stones.
Seeing them as incorrigible, He withdrew with His disciples, predicting the imminent downfall of these unfortunate people and the end of the world not long after.
He prophesied that He would soon suffer crucifixion for the salvation of humanity and rise again on the third day.
Meanwhile, an unholy group had already corrupted one of His disciples with greed and enticed him with money to betray his Master and Lord.
This disciple, filled with the devil, was ready to hand Him over to His enemies.
They seized the opportunity to capture, bind, and drag him away without the crowds that usually surrounded him, believing he had no chance to escape or defend himself.
After offering a very lengthy prayer for our salvation to God the Father, he went to meet his persecutors and asked whom they were seeking.
When they said they were looking for Jesus, his proper name, and he responded that he was the one, they stepped back and fell to the ground repeatedly.
But since he came to free us from eternal damnation through his suffering, he eventually allowed himself, by hiding his divine power for a time, to be willingly handed over to his frenzied captors, so that by his undeserved death, he might absolve us of all our sins.
Therefore, the wicked servants brought him bound to the tribunal of Pilate, the governor, accusing him of subverting their nation, forbidding them to pay taxes to Caesar, and claiming to be Christ, a king.
Thus, the judge, compelled by necessity, handed him over to his soldiers to be mocked.
They dressed him in a mocking garment, as if he presumed to claim a royal name for himself, and crowned him with a crown of thorns instead of a diadem, also placing a reed in his right hand as an imperial scepter.
They spat on his face, struck him repeatedly with blows and slaps, and mocked him, hailing him as king, and demanded he reveal the names of all.
As if he were a worthless slave, without mentioning that he was the Son of God, they shamefully treated the greatest prophet and performer of such great signs, the wisest of men.
Thus mocked, or rather punished, and, to speak more plainly, put to death, they presented him again to their governor.
The Jews, still not satisfied with such injuries, requested the governor to order his crucifixion.
When he repeatedly refused, saying he found nothing deserving of death in him, Luke Chapter 23, the wicked and detestable people condemned themselves with such a curse, wishing his blood to be upon them and their children, as noted in Matthew Chapter 27, Verse 25.
They added that they had a law, and according to that law, he should die because he presumptuously made himself the Son of God.
Yet he did not say it in simple words; instead, he allowed them to measure or guess from the works he did in the name of his Father whether he deserved to be called and believed to be the Son of God.
Thus, the governor, trembling and especially constrained by the threat he feared most as intolerable: "If you let this man go, you are no friend of Caesar," John Chapter 19, Verse 12, granted their request, Luke Chapter 23, Verse 24.
Then they placed the cross on him to carry to the place. But, as if honoring and pitying him whom they sought to kill with such an undeserved death, they forced a foreigner to carry the cross behind him.
And when they came to the place called Calvary, where those condemned to death were usually executed, they crucified Christ the Lord.
To make this most shameful death even more infamous, they hung a thief on his right and another on his left, and they mocked him with these words: "He saved others; he cannot save himself," Matthew Chapter 27, Verse 42.
One of the thieves, in a similar fit of madness, said to him, "If you are the Son of God, save yourself and us," Luke Chapter 23, Verse 39.
But the other, whose mind God graciously enlightened to recognize the present truth, rebuked his companion and begged the Lord hanging there to remember him in his kingdom.
Approving this believing mind and confessing mouth, Christ promised him that he would be with him in paradise that same day.
While the Creator endured these things from His rational creations, the irrational and insensible elements, terrified by His majesty, threatened mortals with their own ruin.
The sun turned dark, the earth shook, rocks split, tombs opened, and nature was disturbed because it could not bear the insult to God.
After this, when everything that needed to happen was fulfilled, so that Scripture would be completed, which said He would be given vinegar to drink, He said He was thirsty.
After He received the vinegar, He entrusted His spirit into the hands of His Father and said, "It is finished."
Then, bowing His head, He gave up His spirit.
Buried with honor by friends, He was carefully guarded by soldiers who feared He might rise on the third day, as He had foretold.
However, an angel coming from heaven left the soldiers guarding the tomb looking like dead men out of fear.
After a short time, when they regained their composure, they became witnesses to His glorious resurrection.
Meanwhile, as they lay there stunned, the angel kindly spoke to the women visiting the tomb with spices for His body and encouraged them not to be afraid.
He clearly revealed that the Lord Jesus Christ had risen, having conquered the power of death, and urged them to see the place where the Lord had been laid.
When they entered, they saw two angels in white sitting, one at the head and one at the feet, where He had been resting and now risen, the author of eternal life.
As they began to leave filled with fear, wishing to flee, the Lord Himself met them. He greeted them most kindly and sent them as messengers to His disciples of the victory over death.
On the same day, He appeared especially to Peter.
He also joined two people walking and talking about Him, explaining from the Scriptures that it was necessary for Christ to suffer, rise from the dead, and thus enter into His glory.
Invited by them to dinner, He was recognized in the breaking of the bread, though He had seemed unknown to them earlier due to their heart's blindness.
In the evening of that same day, he appeared to his apostles.
Bringing them the joy of peace, he breathed on them and said, "Receive the Holy Spirit. If you forgive anyone's sins, they are forgiven; if you retain them, they are retained."
John 20:22-23.
To reassure the doubtful hearts, who thought they were seeing a spirit rather than a body, he showed them his hands and feet, still bearing the marks of his recent suffering, so they could become undeniable witnesses of his resurrection.
But as they still did not believe and were overwhelmed with joy and amazement, he asked if they had anything to eat to prove the reality of his flesh through eating.
When they offered him a piece of broiled fish and a honeycomb, he ate before them and gave them the leftovers.
He reminded them that these were the words he had spoken to them before his suffering, about how it was necessary for the power of death to be broken through his death, and that repentance and forgiveness of sins must be preached to all nations in recognition of his resurrection.
He also promised that they would be strengthened by the glorious sending of the Holy Spirit.
However, he did not want to leave them immediately after instructing and comforting them with this promise, so he visited them for forty days, providing various proofs.
Sometimes he appeared among them with the doors closed; other times, when they labored all night in vain fishing, he stood on the shore and filled their nets with a multitude of fish.
While dining, he instructed blessed Peter, after giving him the keys to the kingdom of heaven and the power to forgive or retain sins, to take care of his sheep, and he foretold that for the care of these sheep, Peter would endure the cross.
Then, after they followed him to a certain mountain, he strengthened their faith and instructed them to go and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, teaching them to observe all the commands he had given them.
Matthew 28:19.
He said to them, "Whoever believes and is baptized will be saved; but whoever does not believe will be condemned."
Mark 16:16.
Since those who provoked God, the unbelieving Jews, and the idol worshippers needed signs to strengthen their faith, He empowered His apostles over all demons and gave them the ability to heal diseases, restore sight to the blind, cleanse lepers, and even raise the dead.
He instructed them to proclaim that the kingdom of God was near.
As they needed to preach this new doctrine to all nations and languages, He gave them the knowledge of different languages.
He promised and granted them and their followers even greater things, so while speaking in one language to people of many languages, they would be understood by all.
The sick would be healed by their passing shadow, and evil spirits would be driven away by their handkerchiefs or the fringes of their belts.
But when He instructed these things in another region, Galilee, either before His suffering or after His resurrection, to ascend to heaven near where He had recently endured the shame of the cross, He revealed to the faithful the plan of His incarnation, suffering, resurrection, and ascension into heaven:
He visited Bethany, known as the house of obedience, from where He would ascend to heaven with the apostles.
With the teacher of the nations explaining the significance: Jesus Christ became obedient unto death, even death on a cross; therefore God also exalted Him.
Philippians chapter two, verses eight to nine.
When those gathered asked Him if the day of judgment and the revelation of the kingdom of God was imminent, He said:
It is not for them, or any mortal, nor even the angels themselves, to know the times and moments which the Father has set by His own authority.
Acts chapter one, verse seven and following.
Instead, He instructed them to await the coming of the Holy Spirit in the city of Jerusalem.
Strengthened by this Spirit, they would be witnesses first in the same city, then throughout all Judea and Samaria, and finally to the ends of the earth.
After saying these things, He raised His hands and blessed them.
As they all expected nothing less, He lifted His incorruptible body to heaven as if on the wings of a dove.
Two angels soon appeared as witnesses to this event, indicating that he had entered heaven.
They mentioned that, just as he was taken up, he would return to judge the living and the dead.
Then, as commanded by the Lord of heaven, they entered Jerusalem and eagerly awaited the coming of the Holy Spirit.
Ten days later, the Holy Spirit arrived, teaching them the fullness of knowledge, granting them the gift of languages, and strengthening them against the rage of unbelievers.
This was accompanied by signs, like the sound of a mighty wind and tongues of fire.
Empowered by this authority, they confirmed the resurrection of our Lord Jesus Christ with prophetic authority, converting one thousand Jews to the faith on that very day.
In the days that followed, several thousand more were converted.
They even persuaded a group of priests to embrace the faith.
Meanwhile, the Lord allowed all nations to follow their own paths and embrace various erroneous beliefs.
Some revered the sun, moon, and stars, which were intended for human use, as divine.
Others, caught in even greater madness, worshipped gold, silver, wood, stones, animals, reptiles, birds, and even green plants of the earth as the creator God.
Eventually, the merciful creator of all, when we ourselves should have felt regret for our inventions and wicked deeds, sent his apostles to us.
They taught us to turn away from these vanities to the living and true God and to await his Son from heaven.
In receiving the Holy Spirit, which we received through rebirth in Christ, we believed we would obtain the forgiveness of sins.
So, representing this mission in our challenging times, we urge you, for Christ's sake, to continue rejecting the devil and all his works, just as you did at your baptism.
Acknowledge the one true God, the Father, who reigns eternally in heaven, His eternal Wisdom incarnated for us, and the Holy Spirit, the everlasting promise of salvation given to you on this journey.
Live in a way that is fitting for the children of God, steering clear of the temptations of gluttony, the chaos of drunkenness, the impurity of fornication, the idolatry of greed, the fury of anger, the cloud of sadness, the bitterness of boredom, the corrosion of envy, the vanity of pride, and the downfall of arrogance.
No Christian should engage in theft, murder, or insults, nor should they give false testimony about any crime.
Instead, be kind to one another and forgive each other, just as God forgave your sins.
Redeem past wrongs through penance or acts of charity, and with God's help, diligently avoid future ones.
Remember, the day of the general judgment is very near, and the uncertain hour of each person’s end is approaching.
Indeed, the final day of great judgment should be feared by all, for on that day, nothing uncorrected will escape eternal punishment.
But equally, the daily judgment of God should be feared by the wise, through which He tests some in the world for a time, while He justly forgets those condemned forever.
He mercifully lifts those who have long fallen into sin, while allowing others, confident in their righteousness, to fall into base desires.
He keeps some restrained with punishment, free from all crime, until the end.
Therefore, under these judgments of God, everyone in this life should live with reverence, so that in the future judgment, they may be deemed worthy to be freed from all fear of sin and death.
Almighty God, who desires all people to be saved and to come to know the truth
First Timothy chapter 2, verse 4,
who has shared these things with your brotherhood through the ministry of our language;
may He, through His grace, make these truths fruitful in your hearts,
with the help of our Lord Jesus Christ and the Comforter Spirit.
Blessed be God forever.
Amen.