Mystical Exposition on the Proverbs of Solomon
by Salonius
What language were the parables spoken in?
In Greek, but in Latin, they explain the parables.
Why did Solomon choose that name for the book?
This shows us that we shouldn't take what is said literally, but rather interpret it in a spiritual way.
What does Solomon mean when he speaks in parables?
The Lord Jesus Christ spoke to the crowds of Jews in parables because, even by his own name, he signifies the same Lord Jesus Christ.
So, how does Solomon interpret it?
Peaceful or loving; it refers to the one about whom the Apostle says, "Christ is our peace, who has made both one." Ephesians chapter 2, verse 11.
And also, "Making peace through his blood, whether things in heaven or things on earth." Colossians chapter 1.
Solomon, which means loving, very fittingly signifies him to whom the Father speaks, saying: "You are my beloved son in whom I am well pleased." Matthew chapter 3.
What does the peaceful state of his kingdom signify?
The everlasting kingdom of Christ and the Church, as it is written:
And of His kingdom, there will be no end
(Luke chapter 1).
Why, according to the translation of the seventy interpreters, are these sayings of Solomon called proverbs and not parables?
Parables are named so because they signify hidden and secret mysteries.
Similarly, proverbs are fittingly named because they are meant to be often spoken, committed to memory, and retained by the faithful.
As it is written in the Book of Proverbs, chapter 1.
What benefits do Solomon's parables offer?
Wisdom and discipline, of course; and this is what he says:
Learn wisdom and discipline.
What is the difference between wisdom and discipline?
Wisdom is the understanding of divine things.
Discipline, however, is the way to live a holy and pure life.
So, what does it mean to learn wisdom?
Know and understand how to believe correctly.
What does it mean to learn discipline?
To understand how each person should live, what actions are right to take, and where to focus their intentions, it follows:
The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom.
How many are the fears of the Lord?
Two, meaning the servant and the holy one.
Why is it called "servile"?
Because we serve the Lord like servants out of fear of hell, we avoid being led to torment.
Why is it called holy fear?
Just as a good son fears disappointing his loving father, even in the smallest way, those who are perfect in the Church fear offending God by sinning.
Who is the wiser of the two?
Servile, because anyone who starts to gain wisdom, meaning they realize after sinning that they have gone astray, is first corrected by divine fear to avoid torment.
What does holy fear actually do?
Increasing wisdom, because perfect love casts out fear.
First John, chapter 4, talks about that servile fear.
But holy fear remains forever.
Psalm 18.
What does Solomon say: "In vain is the net spread in the sight of any bird" (Proverbs Chapter 1).
Yet, don't birds often get caught in nets?
They are indeed accustomed to it.
So, who exactly are these winged ones?
Holy and chosen men possess the wings of faith, hope, and charity, along with other virtues that enable them to contemplate heavenly things.
They also have spiritual eyes, allowing them to foresee the snares of the ancient enemy and guard against sins.
Therefore, casting the net is in vain before the eyes of those with wings.
In other words, the snares of the devil's traps are set before holy and chosen men in vain, because they can easily overcome the devil's snares on earth, as their way of life is in heaven.
What is the wisdom Solomon speaks of? Wisdom calls out in the street.
She raises her voice in the public squares.
Jesus Christ, who is the power and wisdom of God, as the Apostle says.
So, how does this wisdom get shared outside?
Inside, he preached in secret before he suffered, revealing the mysteries of his divinity only to his disciples.
But after his resurrection, he preached openly.
With the Holy Spirit sent from above, he declared through the apostles to the world that he was the Son of God.
How did he raise his voice in the streets?
Because what he had previously taught in secret and in hiding, only among the Jewish people, he later proclaimed openly to all nations through the apostles.
He commanded them, saying:
What I tell you in the dark, say in the light, meaning openly;
and what you hear whispered, proclaim from the rooftops, that is, openly and in front of everyone.
What does he say? In the midst of the crowds, he cries out.
The leaders of the Jews are represented by heads.
He shouted among the crowds, openly reminding the Jewish leaders, through the apostles, of the murder they had committed against him, and he called them to the remedy of repentance.
How should this be understood as it follows?
At the gates of the city, she speaks her words.
Throughout the city, the holy Church is represented, gathered from both the Jews and the Gentiles.
The doors of this city's gates were the holy teachers who, by preaching the word of the Gospel, brought believers into it.
Wisdom was speaking at the doors of the city's gates when Christ was speaking through his apostles.
What does it mean when it says: "Incline your heart to understanding wisdom" (Proverbs 2)?
How can a person incline their heart?
He inclines his heart to understand wisdom, humbles himself, and cleanses his soul from sins, so that he may become worthy to receive the mysteries of the Divinity.
What does it mean when it says, "Do not rely on your own wisdom"?
Who actually relies on wisdom?
He who trusts in his own wisdom or strength to fulfill God's commandments.
Here it says again: Do not be wise in your own eyes. Proverbs Chapter 3.
Who is wise in their own eyes?
The one who elevates himself above others as a teacher and boasts about his understanding and knowledge of the words of the Fathers.
What is true human wisdom?
Fear the Lord and turn away from evil.
Here's what comes next:
Fear the Lord, and turn away from evil.
How can you tell if this is truly human wisdom?
As it is written in the Book of Job:
"Behold, the fear of the Lord, that is wisdom; and to turn away from evil is understanding."
Who is the man Solomon refers to when he says,
"Blessed is the man who finds wisdom"?
A faithful and devoted Catholic Christian.
When did he discover wisdom?
When he truly understands the teaching of the Gospel with both his mind and heart, and through the Holy Scriptures, he strives to know the will of the Lord.
When does wisdom flow?
When they listen to the divine commandments with great love and affection for their Creator, and strive to fulfill them.
What does it mean when it says: "Her ways are beautiful, all her paths are peaceful"? What are these ways of wisdom, or what are her paths?
The ways of wisdom are the actions of the Lord that He performed in the flesh, or His teachings found in the books of the Gospel.
These ways are beautiful because they are divine.
The paths of wisdom are the commandments and orders of the Lord, leading to eternal peace.
Peaceful, because all the Lord's commandments lead to eternal peace.
What law or advice is Solomon referring to when he says: Keep the law and advice?
The law and the wisdom of the Lord Jesus Christ.
What is the law of wisdom?
The law of wisdom says:
If you want to enter into life, keep the commandments.
That means, you shall not murder,
you shall not commit adultery,
you shall not steal.
As mentioned in the books of Matthew, Mark, and Luke.
What is the plan of wisdom?
If you want to be perfect, sell everything you have and give it to the poor.
What does it mean when it says, "Every mocker is an abomination to the Lord"?
And who exactly is a mocker?
A mocker is someone who distorts God's words by misunderstanding and misteaching them.
A mocker looks down on their humble and poor neighbors by insulting them.
A mocker despises God's great promises, treating them as insignificant, and scoffs at the punishment of eternal damnation, as if it is bearable.
The Lord detests all such people.
He converses with the simple, as they are enlightened by the grace of heavenly wisdom, free from deceit.
Why does Solomon say, "And I was a son to my father, tender and the only one before my mother," Proverbs chapter 4? How could he be the only one before his mother when his half-brother preceded him, as the holy Scripture of the Book of Kings First Kings chapter 12 testifies?
It's true that his half-brother was born before him, but he passed away shortly after birth.
Without even a name, it was as if he never existed.
That's why he considers himself the only son.
Why does it say: Do not turn to the right or to the left?
Who can control themselves so perfectly that their body doesn't lean to the right or to the left?
No one, but by the right hand, the good path is indicated, and by the left hand, the bad and wicked path.
It does not prohibit walking on the right path, but rather turning aside to the right.
Who then turns to the right or to the left?
The righteous person turns to the right, relying on their own justice and strength.
The unrighteous person turns to the left, despairing of being saved because of the weakness of the flesh.
The one who wants to know more than they should, as stated in Romans 12, turns to the right.
Meanwhile, the one who serves foolishness turns to the left.
Why then does he say a little later: "The Lord knows the ways that are right?"
Through the right paths, holy actions and good works are indicated.
The Lord knows these; He directs them, and they please Him.
Conversely, in judgment, He will say to the reprobates: I do not know you.
Meaning, I did not choose you because you do not please me.
Since I do not see you in my light, I do not see you in my righteousness.
What does it mean when it says:
"Do not give your honor to others, and your years to the cruel" (Proverbs 5)?
What honor is it referring to, and who are these others?
Speaking of honor, it is said that man was made in the image of God.
It refers to strangers as demons to emphasize this: Do not subject your honor, created in God's image, to unclean spirits by living poorly.
Who does he call cruel, and which years is he talking about?
Years are referred to as the spans of life.
The cruel devil, and the message is: Do not hand over the spans of life, which God gave you, to the devil by living badly.
From which cistern does Solomon teach us to drink water, or from which well does he teach us to drink streams, when he says:
Drink water from your own cistern, and flowing water from your own well?
He calls the cistern "catholic," referring to the teachings of the Old and New Testaments. The well, on the other hand, signifies the depth and height of the same catholic teaching. Water symbolizes knowledge, and streams represent the abundance and richness of knowledge—that is, the various understandings of the Holy Scriptures.
With these words, he advises us to beware of the doctrines of heretics and to focus on the readings of the Holy Scriptures. The idea is: Drink water from your own cistern, meaning, uphold and practice the teachings you preach to others. And streams from your own well, meaning, let the abundance of your words or knowledge overflow in you through good works.
Why does Solomon say, "Let your fountains be dispersed abroad," and "divide your waters in the streets,"
when he immediately adds, "Have them yourself alone, let not strangers be partakers with you"?
If we disperse our fountains abroad and divide our waters in the streets, how can we have them alone?
Although it may seem contradictory, there is no inconsistency because these statements can only be understood spiritually.
We channel our sources outward when we inspire others through the power of preaching, and when we share the words of Holy Scripture with them.
We distribute water in the streets when we preach to the people.
The term "street" comes from the word for width; it is a Greek term.
Therefore, we distribute water in the streets when we spread words of knowledge to a large audience and share divine teachings according to each person's capacity.
If we have to share water in the streets, how can we keep it just for ourselves?
We share water in the streets when we spread divine words to others, but we alone hold the water because we do not seek human praise from that preaching.
What does it mean when it says, "Let your springs be yours alone, never to be shared with strangers" (Proverbs 5:17)?
He calls them foreign demons, about whom the Psalmist said: "Foreigners have risen up against me, and the mighty have sought my soul" (Psalm fifty-three, verse five).
We invite evil, that is, unclean spirits, to be our partners and associates in preaching when we become proud and seek vain glory from our preaching.
About whom does Solomon speak:
A deceitful and useless man walks with a perverse mouth
Proverbs 6:12.
He calls a man who abandons the faith a schismatic, someone who works to divide the unity of the Church.
In what language is 'apostate' said?
Greek translates into Latin as "one who flees and departs from the truth."
Why, then, is a schismatic called an apostate?
Like a proud angel, he first swells with pride and then falls from his mental state.
As a result, he turns away from the love of his Creator and the truth.
If he hadn't turned away from the truth, he wouldn't spread injustice in the Church.
Why is it said about him:
He winks with his eyes,
shuffles with his feet,
and speaks with his fingers?
Guarding the mind internally helps keep the outer actions orderly.
This apostate, having lost his state and self-control, ultimately disrupted the outer aspects given by the Lord, leading to disorder.
What does it mean when it says about the law: "Bind it on your fingers, write it on the tablets of your heart" (Proverbs 7:3)?
How can someone bind the law on their fingers, and if they do, what purpose does it serve?
It says, in actions, meaning in deeds: for whoever strives to fulfill and adorn the law through good works binds it in their actions.
It says, in the tablets of the heart, meaning in the depth of thought.
Therefore, whoever receives the law with joy and commits it to memory writes it in the tablets of their heart.
What does Wisdom mean when it says:
Through me, kings reign, and lawmakers make just decrees;
Through me, rulers govern, and the powerful decide what is right?
Christ, the power and wisdom of God.
Does Christ give the kingdom and power to all wicked tyrants and rulers?
Certainly not, but with his permission, wicked kings and rulers take on kingdoms or empires, because it is written in the book of Job: "He allows the hypocrite to reign because of the sins of the people" Job 34. But in this context, the apostles are called holy kings, who first know how to faithfully govern themselves, and then the Church entrusted to them. Or he calls all the saints kings, who know how to govern themselves and others well.
Who does he refer to as the founders of laws?
The authors of both Testaments.
Whom does He consider leaders and powerful ones?
Other teachers and leaders of the faithful have received the kingdom, leadership, and authority through the wisdom of God the Father.
This means they received it through Christ, so they could accomplish good works, as he himself says:
"Without me, you can do nothing."
(John, Chapter 15).
What does Wisdom say? "I was delighted every day, playing in front of Him."
That means always being in the presence of the Father while living in the world.
Did Wisdom, the Son of God, play childishly before the Father?
Of course not. But what he says while playing must be understood as rejoicing.
He was playing every single day, meaning he was celebrating being one; that is, of one substance with the Father, from the beginning, from the days of eternity.
How did he manage to play all the time, no matter where he was in the world?
Since the beginning of the world and creation, the Son has always rejoiced, because he has always remained in the Father, just as he was.
What does it mean when it says, "Wisdom has built herself a house"?
Proverbs 9.
And what kind of house has she built for herself?
Wisdom, who is the Son of God, built Himself a house.
He created man in the womb of the Virgin, whom He took on in the unity of His person.
How did he manage to destroy the seven pillars?
He built seven pillars because, through the sevenfold grace of the Holy Spirit, he established churches around the world.
These churches, like pillars, sustain and preserve his memory, reflecting the mystery of his Incarnation.
Can it be understood differently?
It is truly possible: The House of Wisdom is the Church of Christ.
The pillars of this house are the holy teachers.
These pillars are rightly said to be seven because the holy teachers are filled with the sevenfold grace of the Holy Spirit.
So, how did Wisdom carve these columns?
He cut down the columns because he separated the minds of the preachers from the love of this present age
and raised them up to support the structure of the Church.
Regarding these maidservants, he mentions a bit later:
He sent his maidservants to call out to the citadel and the city walls.
Proverbs 9:3.
He refers to the holy apostles as his servants.
Why does he call them maids?
Because of foolishness, weakness, and poverty; He chose uneducated, weak, poor, and despised people as apostles.
He sent them into the world to preach so they might call the faithful to the citadel of eternal happiness and to the walls of the heavenly Jerusalem.
Who is the wise son that makes his father happy?
And who is the foolish son that brings sorrow to his mother?
He who receives the mysteries of faith and baptism, keeps them well, and fulfills them through actions, is a wise son.
Without a doubt, he brings joy to God the Father.
But he who receives the sacraments of faith and baptism and then corrupts them with evil deeds or heretical depravity is a foolish son.
He is certainly a source of sorrow to his mother, namely the Church, because he grieves her.
What does it mean when it says, "A fool will be beaten with lips"?
How can a foolish person be beaten with lips?
In this context, "beating" signifies condemnation.
Therefore, the fool will be beaten with words, as he will be condemned for the wicked and evil things he has said.
Hence, elsewhere Moses (or rather Solomon) says:
"Life and death are in the power of the tongue"
(Proverbs 18),
because each person will either be condemned or justified by their words
(Matthew 12).
Why do we say "hands of the tongue" when a tongue can't have hands?
It is metaphorically said, through a figure of speech, just as the winds are said to have wings Psalms 17, 103, etc.
: the hands of the tongue represent the very words by which one earns life by speaking good, or earns death by speaking evil.
In the Holy Scriptures, works are often referred to as "hands," as in the phrase: "You shall eat the labor of your hands" Psalms 127.
He says "in the hands of the tongue," meaning in works. For the works of the tongue are good or evil conversations, from which either death or life is born.
Who is that lazy person of whom it is said:
Just like vinegar to the teeth and smoke to the eyes, so is the lazy one to those who send him
(Proverbs 10:26)?
A lazy and poorly living Catholic is someone who does not strive to earn eternal happiness.
The deceit of heretics is symbolized by vinegar and smoke.
The eyes and teeth represent the preachers of the holy Church.
They are called eyes because they foresee the right paths, and teeth because they provide spiritual nourishment to the faithful.
Just as vinegar is to the teeth and smoke is to the eyes — meaning the deceit of heretics causes sadness, distress, and tears to good teachers — a lazy person, or a bad Catholic, is a burden to those good teachers who command him to fulfill his faith through actions.
It is even more burdensome because he destroys his faith with bad deeds.
What does it mean when it says, "Hand in hand, the wicked will not go unpunished" (Proverbs 11:21)?
How is the wicked person "hand in hand," and why will they not go unpunished?
The one who joins hands in wrongdoing accomplishes nothing at all.
Therefore, as long as the wicked person holds hands with another, he will not be innocent.
Because even if he temporarily withdraws his hands from evil work, as long as he remains wicked, he cannot have innocence of heart.
As it is said above: A perverse heart is an abomination to the Lord.
Proverbs eleven, twenty.
What is at hand? The kingdom of God is at hand. Repent and believe in the gospel.
A guilty conscience comes from doing something wrong.
How should we understand this:
"A gold ring in a pig's snout is like a beautiful woman without good sense"?
Imagine putting a gold ring in the nose of a pig.
As the pig digs around in the ground, the gold ring gets plunged into a mud pit and loses its beauty.
Similarly, a foolish woman, no matter how beautiful she is or how much fine jewelry and clothing she has, tarnishes her own beauty and loses her elegance if she soils herself with lust and corrupts herself with adultery.
How can we understand this sentence from a spiritual perspective?
Whoever studies the Holy Scriptures carefully and continuously examines the divine words, gains the adornments of knowledge.
But if they live poorly and destroy what they have understood well, they are like a pig with a golden ring in its nose; digging in the earth, defiling, and immersing themselves in mud.
The ornament they gained through knowledge of the Scriptures becomes soiled by impure actions.
Such a soul is like a beautiful and foolish woman: beautiful through knowledge, but given to carnal pleasures, foolish through her actions.
What does it mean when it says, "The soul that blesses will be enriched, and the one who refreshes others will also be refreshed?"
There are many who refresh others, but they themselves are not refreshed.
He doesn't speak of physical drunkenness, but of the spiritual soul.
If it blesses, it will be enriched, because whatever it blesses outwardly by preaching, it receives spiritual blessing.
In other words, it increases and grows in spiritual grace.
Similarly, the one who strives to intoxicate the minds of listeners with sacred words is also intoxicated and filled with the infusion of the Holy Spirit.
Why did it not say: Man, but rather Soul which blesses will be enriched?
In the Holy Scriptures, it's common for a part to represent the whole, or the whole to represent a part.
This figure of speech is known as synecdoche.
In this instance, a part represents the whole person, and the whole represents a part, as in the phrase:
"They have taken the Lord out of the tomb" (John 20).
Here, "The Lord" refers to the body of the Lord.
Who is the one about whom it is said:
"He who withholds grain will be cursed by the people"
Proverbs
11:26?
Should someone be cursed just because they don't distribute their grain to everyone?
Grains symbolize the words of holy preaching.
So, if anyone hides these grains—the words of holy preaching—keeping them to themselves and not sharing them with others, they will be cursed among the people.
They will be condemned for the sin of silence, as they could have helped many.
But since they chose not to, they will justly be punished for the suffering of many.
Who are the ones who sell grain, as it soon follows:
"But blessings will be on the heads of those who sell"?
Those who share words of life and holy teachings with their listeners are like sellers of grain.
What price do they get from them?
The price of faith and holy confession.
How will the blessing come upon their heads?
Because the Lord will say to each of them: "Well done, good and faithful servant," as it says in Matthew 25, etc.
What does it mean when it says, "He who troubles his own house will inherit the wind"?
How can someone inherit the wind?
The house, in this context, refers to the mind, where each person lives as in a home through their thoughts.
The winds represent unclean spirits.
So, anyone who isn't afraid to disturb their house, that is, their mind, with evil and harmful thoughts, will surely end up possessing winds.
Through bad thoughts, they have made a way for demons to enter and live in them.
They will possess winds, that is, demons, to their own condemnation.
A loving woman is a crown to her husband,
but a disgraceful woman is like rot in his bones.
Proverbs 12.
A good and chaste woman honors her husband in everything.
Because she loves him and manages his household well, she is his crown, adding grace to his virtues.
Thus, she is crowned by the Lord.
However, an adulterous woman, although she may appear beautiful on the outside, is rot in the bones.
Inside, she pollutes her members with the stench of her own lust.
How should we understand this saying:
A poor person who is self-sufficient is better than a glorious person who lacks bread?
Indeed, a brother who is uneducated and simple, but does the good things he knows, thereby deserving to have eternal life in heaven, is better than a glorious one.
That is, one who is renowned for his knowledge and learning of the Scriptures or adorned with the office of a teacher, who lacks the bread of love because he neither loves the Lord nor his neighbor.
Or certainly, he lacks bread because he does not practice what he understands or teaches.
Who is the clever person that hides knowledge?
As it is said: A clever person hides knowledge.
Clever, in this context, is used positively, meaning wise and prudent.
So, a clever man—a wise and prudent man—sometimes deliberately hides knowledge for two reasons:
First, because he cannot speak to weak listeners as if they were spiritual, but rather as if they were worldly.
First Corinthians chapter 3 states that he does not dare reveal the great mysteries of the Holy Scriptures to them, lest they be scandalized.
Second, because he does not want to give what is sacred to dogs, nor throw pearls before pigs.
Matthew chapter 7.
What does it mean when it says, "The lazy person wants and does not want" (Proverbs 13:4)?
If they want, then how do they not want?
Laziness identifies a person who does not want to engage in good works.
The lazy person wants to reign with God but does not want to work for God.
They seek happiness but do not want to follow Christ's commandments to deserve that happiness.
Regarding this, James says:
A double-minded person is unstable in all their ways.
James chapter one, verse eight.
About hard work, he says:
"But the soul of those who work will be made rich."
Proverbs 13:4
It talks about those who do good deeds and strive to follow the Lord's commandments.
Their souls will be enriched with spiritual grace and the sweetness of the heavenly kingdom.
Why will the souls of those who do good be enriched?
Because after the labors of this life, he will be rewarded with unfading compensation.
There's a saying that goes: "The messenger of the wicked falls into evil."
The messenger of the wicked, meaning the angel of the devil—Arius, Sabellius, and the other heretics—are considered the angels of Satan.
They certainly fell into evil, which means the torment of eternal hell.
Who is the faithful messenger mentioned in the saying: "A faithful messenger brings healing" (Proverbs 14:5)?
Every faithful Catholic preacher and teacher is an ambassador, gaining eternal health and salvation for themselves and their listeners.
Why does it say: The wicked will hide from the good, and the unrighteous will be at the gates of the righteous, when in this life it's more common for the good to lie before the wicked, and the righteous before the gates of the unjust?
In the final judgment, the righteous will be crowned, and the wicked, who afflicted them in this life, will be condemned.
Therefore, it is said: "The wicked will lie before the good, and the impious before the gates of the righteous."
However, when it says "before the good" and "before the gates of the righteous," it does not refer to physical proximity, because the wicked and the good will not be close to each other then. Rather, it refers to the vision of the good, as they will always see the torments of the wicked, from which they will offer greater thanks to God, their deliverer, without end.
What does it mean when it says, "The Lord's decisions are like weights and scales, and all His works are measured accurately" (Proverbs 16:11)?
How are weights and scales related to the Lord's decisions?
Because the Lord established everything in weight, measure, and number, Wisdom 11.
Weight and balance are the judgments of the Lord.
As He willed, He distributed to each the measure of faith and the grace of the Holy Spirit.
Who are known as the stones of the age?
The righteous and strong in faith: all the stones of the world, meaning the holy and chosen men, are works of the Lord.
No one is chosen by the Lord for the heavenly building by their own strength or merit, but only by His grace and mercy.
What does it mean when it says:
"The crown of the elderly is their children's children, and the glory of children is their fathers," in
Proverbs 17?
If the grandchildren are bad, how can they be a glory in this context?
He calls the patriarchs and prophets, whose sons are the holy apostles.
The successors of the apostles are the holy preachers, the sons of their sons.
All these form the crown of the elders—the patriarchs and prophets—honoring them with worthy praise.
Through their examples and prophecies, they came to the knowledge of grace.
How are fathers influencing their sons?
The preachers of the New Testament hold great honor because they have earned the right to be called the children of the ancient fathers, the patriarchs, and prophets.
Why does it say: The one who releases water is the start of conflicts?
Isn't it the one who lets water flow freely that stirs up disputes?
Or isn't it more common for wine rather than water to cause arguments?
This is spoken figuratively:
Water represents a loose and unrestrained tongue.
Those who let their tongue run excessively are the source of quarrels.
Because failing to restrain their tongue incites arguments and disputes, disrupting harmony.
Tell me, how does wisdom shine on the face of the wise, as Solomon says:
"But the eyes of fools are on the ends of the earth?"
A wise person often reflects the depth of their thoughts and the clarity of their understanding in the brightness of their face.
But fools, trying to imitate this seriousness, fail to elevate their minds.
Instead, they focus on how to achieve the fulfillment of carnal pleasures.
Should we understand it only this way?
We should especially understand this as referring to Christ.
In the face of the wise one, namely the Savior, the wisdom of divinity shone, which He, appearing in the flesh, demonstrated and confirmed through the testimony of virtues and teachings.
But the eyes of fools—that is, the unbelieving Jews—were more inflamed with earthly desires than with His saving warnings and teachings.
What does it mean when it says: A person's gift makes room for them and brings them before great people (Proverbs 18:16)?
What is this gift that creates opportunities and leads them to influential individuals?
This gift is one of charity and other virtues, which the faithful receive from the Lord.
It broadens a person's path, meaning their actions.
The more each faithful person is filled internally with the grace of the Holy Spirit,
the more they expand their path externally by multiplying their good works.
They grow and increase daily in holy desires and good deeds.
How can this gift pave the way for someone to stand before rulers?
Because among the great leaders of the Church, he grants him the highest honor in the public sphere and the glory of eternal happiness.
Why does it say: "The lazy person hides his hand under his armpit and does not bring it to his mouth" in Proverbs 19 and Proverbs 26?
Who is so lazy that, even while eating or drinking, wouldn't bring their hand to their mouth?
Someone who hides their hand under their armpit certainly does not want to do any work.
Therefore, a lazy person represents a preacher who doesn't follow through with actions.
Indeed, someone who extends their hand to their mouth strives to practice what they preach.
Who is that lazy person mentioned in the saying:
"Because of the cold, the lazy person did not want to plow, so he will beg in the summer and nothing will be given to him"
from the Book of Proverbs, Chapter 20?
If the lazy person didn't want to plow during the cold season, will he find anyone in the summer who will give him anything?
Often, lazy people find others who will give them alms during both cold and hot times.
In this context, the lazy person is someone who, due to their laziness and the hardships of this world (represented by the cold), neglects to work in the service of God.
Therefore, on the future day of judgment, they will beg because they will not have good works to deserve happiness.
Whatever a person sows, that they will also reap.
As it says in Galatians chapter 6.
So, why is the day of judgment and the kingdom of God compared to summer?
Because then, all the clouds of our sorrow will pass away, and the days of that life will shine with the brightness of the eternal sun.
Which king is it said:
"The king who sits on the throne of judgment dispels all evil with his gaze"?
About Him who is the King of kings and Lord of lords, that is, the Lord Jesus Christ, who sits on the throne of judgment.
The Father does not judge anyone but has given all judgment to the Son.
As it is written in the Gospel of John, chapter 5.
He dispels all evil with His gaze, penetrating even secret thoughts by His power, to repay each one according to what they have done.
In the Gospel of Luke, chapter 12, He says: Nothing is so covered that it will not be revealed, and nothing hidden that it will not be known.
While the righteous are crowned with the Lord, only the wicked will undergo eternal punishment.
What does it mean when it says:
"A weight and a weight, a measure and a measure, both are detestable to God"
(Proverbs 20:23 and 21:22)?
Weights and measures, different weights and different measures.
Whoever has varying weights and measures in their house does so to weigh and measure differently for themselves and their neighbor, which is detestable to the Lord.
Hence, in the law of Moses, the Lord commanded, saying:
You shall have honest scales and honest weights
Leviticus 19.
So, how should we understand it spiritually?
He keeps different weights and measures in his house, always looking for ways to be praised in his actions, while scrutinizing others to find reasons to blame them.
Such a person is certainly detestable to God, displeasing Him as much as he desires to please himself, for God searches all the secrets of the heart.
How should we understand this saying:
"It is bad, it is bad," says every buyer,
and when he has gone away, then he boasts
(Proverbs 20:14)?
According to the letter, buyers usually criticize what they want to purchase, saying: "It's bad, it's bad." However, if they get a good deal, they will boast about it when they leave.
But how do you understand it on a spiritual level?
He truly seeks to earn eternal rewards in heaven for himself.
He strives to exchange earthly things for heavenly ones, fleeting things for lasting ones, and temporal things for eternal ones.
Therefore, he acknowledges that whatever he suffers in the present is bad because he understands it that way.
However, because he patiently endures all adversities for God, when he departs from this world, he will rejoice, as he will have reached blessedness.
Also, how should we interpret the phrase that comes shortly after:
"An inheritance gained hastily at the beginning will not be blessed in the end"?
This inheritance can be understood as the acquisition of greed:
Therefore, whoever desires to multiply riches for themselves in this life through the wickedness of greed, must understand that in the future they will lose the happiness of eternal inheritance.
Alternatively:
Whoever seeks human praise for good deeds may rush towards inheritance in the beginning:
but in the end, they will lack blessing, because they will receive no reward from God.
For it is written about such people:
"Truly I tell you, they have received their reward" (Matthew 6:2).
What does it mean when it says:
The downfall
of a person is to consume the holy ones, and to handle things rashly after making vows
(Proverbs twenty-six)?
What does it mean to consume the holy ones?
To devour the saints is to bind oneself by a vow.
The wicked devoured the saints when they vowed to persecute and kill them, just like the forty Jewish men mentioned in the Acts of the Apostles:
They vowed not to eat or drink until they had killed Paul.
Similarly, the pagans often vowed the blood of Christians to their gods.
What does it mean when it says: "And after making vows, to consider them"?
Proverbs chapter 20, verse 25 states: "It is a trap to dedicate something rashly and only later to consider one's vows."
After making promises, it feels like persecuting and tearing apart the saints, treating them like worthless slaves.
How, then, does it become the downfall of man to devour the saints and to handle things after making vows?
If it's a sin to harm anyone, it's an even greater sin to persecute, offend, or injure the saints of God.
Therefore, those who persecute the saints are setting themselves up for eternal damnation.
How should we understand this: Just as the divisions of water, so is the heart of the king in the hand of God?
Why does it say that only the heart of the king is in the hand of God, and not everyone's hearts, when it is written elsewhere: In his hand are all the ends of the earth (Psalm 95)?
If all the ends of the earth are in God's power, aren't the hearts of all people in his hand too?
We shouldn't see the king in this passage as just a temporary ruler in name only.
Instead, we should view him as any holy, faithful, and religious Christian man, whose soldiers are sacred virtues, and who knows how to conquer the battles of vices within himself.
Just as God, through various divisions of waters, fills the wide boundaries of the earth and air, He will also incline the heart of the king wherever He wishes.
That is, to whatever good He desires to direct it.
Just as He grants divisions of graces to angels and humans according to His will, He also fills the hearts of kings, meaning the saints, with various gifts and adorns them with different blessings.
What does it mean when it says, "A man who strays from the path of understanding will rest in the assembly of the giants" (Proverbs 21:16)?
Who are these giants, in whose assembly will he rest if he strays from the path of understanding?
Giants are referred to as unclean spirits, or demons, about which blessed Job says:
"Behold, the giants groan beneath the waters, and those who dwell with them" Job 26.
This means that demons and all those they have deceived, and who have agreed with them, are tormented under punishment.
Veronus, why are demons called giants?
Demons are proud, arrogant, evil, and strong, much like giants once were.
In the gathering of these giants—that is, demons—all who have strayed from the path of truth will dwell.
Together with the demons, they will endure the torment of eternal damnation.
What is the city of the strong, or who is the wise one referred to in the saying:
"The wise one ascends the city of the strong and pulls down the strength of its confidence"
(Proverbs 21:22)?
He calls the world a city and the strong, demons.
This world was once a city of the strong, dedicated to the worship of idols,
serving demons, and placing its trust in the worship of those who are not gods,
but merely the works of human hands.
Who is that wise person who ascended to this city of strength?
That Son of the Virgin, the power of God, and the wisdom of God, who came to this city when born in the flesh, appeared visibly to the world.
He destroyed the strength of its confidence by overthrowing and removing the worship of gods, in whom the pagans trusted, from the world.
What does the proverb mean:
Train up a child in the way he should go,
and when he is old he will not depart from it
(Proverbs 22)
?
Don't many people leave the bad path they walked in their youth?
Indeed, many people, inspired by divine grace, turn away from the vices of their youth as they grow older.
Solomon does not deny that this can happen.
However, it is more common for the habits a person learns in youth to remain unchanged in old age.
While he doesn't confirm that this always happens, he offers this proverb to remind everyone to strive from an early age in virtues and good works.
This is to avoid the possibility that in old age, they cannot learn the pursuit of good works which they neglected in their younger years.
What does it mean when it says, "A deep pit is the mouth of a strange woman" (Proverbs 20:19)?
Who is this strange woman, and why is her mouth described as a deep pit?
The mouth of a stranger is like the mouth of a prostitute.
So, anyone who eagerly listens to a prostitute's words and enjoys her kisses is like someone knocking on the door of a deep pit, which is hell.
Unless he quickly distances himself from her conversation or kiss, and if God abandons him, he will immediately be plunged into the pit of death.
And this is what is meant by: "The one whom the Lord is angry with will fall into it."
What does he mean when he says: Apply your heart to my teaching?
And shortly after, he adds: Look, I have described it to you three times in thoughts and knowledge, to show you firmness and words of truth (Proverbs 22).
How has he described his teaching and knowledge three times?
And what does it mean to apply and understand the teaching?
He describes his teaching in three ways: urging everyone to strive to fulfill it in thought, word, and deed.
Regarding these boundaries, he advises:
Do not cross the ancient boundaries set by your ancestors.
Proverbs 23:10.
The ancient boundaries refer to the boundaries of truth and faith, established from the beginning by the Catholic teachers.
Therefore, it was commanded that no one should accept the truth of the holy faith and the doctrine of the Gospel in any way other than how it was handed down by the holy Fathers.
Likewise, no one should interpret the words of the holy Scriptures in any way other than according to the intention of each writer.
What are the riches he talks about?
Don't set your eyes on riches you can't have, because they'll make wings for themselves and fly to heaven.
What wings can riches, meaning wealth or abundance, make for themselves?
These riches are the secrets of Divinity and the mysteries of heavenly matters.
The idea is: Do not lift the eyes of your mind to scrutinize these secrets and mysteries, which you cannot penetrate or understand.
They are revealed only to eagles; in other words, they are clear only to heavenly citizens.
What are the storerooms he refers to?
In teaching, the storerooms will be filled with all kinds of wealth, precious, and beautiful things
(Proverbs 24:4).
The hearts of the righteous are like storerooms, filled with precious and beautiful treasures through the teachings of wisdom.
In other words, they are enriched with virtues and good deeds.
What does it mean when it says:
"For a righteous person falls seven times, and rises again"?
If they are righteous, how is it that they are said to fall, meaning to sin?
Here Solomon speaks about minor and everyday sins, which none of the righteous could avoid in this life.
As he says elsewhere: "I will bless the Lord at all times." Seven times (Psalm 34).
Sometimes, seven times signifies often and frequently, which can be most appropriately understood here: the righteous will often fall and often rise again.
Or certainly, at all times he falls and rises, namely by divine grace, as was said above.
How should we understand:
Prepare your work outside, and diligently tend to your field, so that afterwards you can build your house
?
What should a person prepare outside?
The work calls for a good action, and therefore he added, yours; that is, useful and necessary for you.
So, we prepare our work outside when we arrange our actions well externally.
And, to please God, we organize.
How do we carefully cultivate our field?
We can diligently cultivate the field if we clear our bodies of the thorns of vice.
After working in the field, how will we build our house?
If we properly arrange our actions outwardly, we build a good house for ourselves by maintaining a pure life and keeping even our thoughts clean, adorning the dwelling of our mind with pious thoughts.
Who is the Lord, and who are the kings mentioned in the phrase:
"The glory of the Lord is to conceal a matter; the glory of kings is to investigate a matter"
Proverbs 25:2?
This Lord, the Son of God, known as Lord Jesus, chose to hide His divine nature.
When He appeared in the flesh, He wanted to be recognized more as a man than as the Son of God.
This was so the devil would not recognize Him, and thus, through His suffering, He could redeem the human race.
If the devil had known He was the Son of God, he would never have crucified Him.
Therefore, the glory of the Lord was in concealing His divinity by appearing as a man.
By showing the weakness of the flesh, the devil was not prompted to prevent His suffering.
Through ignorance of His suffering, He reached the glory of the resurrection.
So, who are the kings whose glory is to search out a matter?
These holy kings were apostles who diligently sought to understand the words of the Lord, signifying their devotion to Him.
When He did not openly reveal Himself as the Lord but wanted to be understood in a mystical way, they carefully examined His words with the utmost diligence.
An example of this is: "I and the Father are one" John 10.
When He concealed His divinity and revealed the weakness of the flesh, He asked these kings, saying: "Who do people say that the Son of Man is?"
To this, the most distinguished of the kings, the blessed apostle Peter, who had often heard His words before, immediately replied: "You are the Christ, the Son of the living God."
They say heaven above, earth below, and the hearts of kings are unsearchable.
Proverbs twenty-five.
The prophets and apostles, who were worthy of knowing divine secrets through the revelation of the Holy Spirit, are called kings.
The knowledge and understanding of the prophets and apostles are symbolized by the hearts of kings.
So, how should we interpret this statement:
Heaven is above, Earth is below, and the heart of kings is unfathomable.
Just as we can't fully comprehend the height of the sky or the depth of the earth, our fragile minds can't grasp the profound knowledge and understanding of the prophets and apostles.
How do these statements agree with each other, or how can they fit together?
"Do not answer a fool according to his folly, lest you become like him," and "Answer a fool according to his folly, lest he appear wise in his own eyes" (Proverbs 26).
These statements certainly seem very contradictory.
They really match well when we consider them carefully.
By saying, "Do not answer a fool according to his folly," it advises us that since a fool does not grasp wisdom, we should not imitate his foolishness, but rather scorn and despise it.
And whenever we speak to him, we should not do so rudely, angrily, or arrogantly, but honestly, patiently, humbly, and wisely, so we do not become like him.
However, by what follows, "Answer a fool according to his folly," it advises us to wisely rebuke and refute the fool and clearly show how great his foolishness is, lest he might think he is wise if he does not recognize his own foolishness.
Who is that whisperer everyone talks about?
"The words of a whisperer are like simple things, reaching the innermost parts of the stomach."
He calls the whisperer a creator of conflict and a double-tongued person, who pretends to praise with words.
His words may seem simple, but they reach deep into the innermost parts of the stomach.
The whisperer is always on the lookout for opportunities to sow quarrels, which the stomach resents, disturbing all the innermost parts.
Who is that hidden love, about which it is said:
"Open rebuke is better than hidden love" (Proverbs 27:5).
Love hidden in this place refers to illicit love, such as adulterous love, which is kept secret out of shame to avoid rebuke from the wise.
Therefore, open correction is better than hidden love, because it is much better to openly rebuke someone to correct them than to secretly love with the intent of sinning together.
What does it mean when it says, "A satisfied soul will trample on honeycomb; a hungry soul will take bitter for sweet"?
How can a satisfied soul trample on honeycomb?
According to the letter, a satisfied soul tramples on a honeycomb because anyone who is full of food despises and scorns sweet food.
But whoever is hungry, even if they taste bitterness in their food, does not mind.
But spiritually, how should we understand this statement?
A soul that is full is the soul of the rich, who in this present life have their consolation because they abound in worldly goods.
Hence the Lord says in the Gospel:
"Woe to you who are full, for you shall hunger"
Luke 6.
Therefore, the soul of the rich tramples the honeycomb because, for earthly goods, it despises the sweetness of the heavenly kingdom.
But a hungry soul will take even the bitter as sweet, because those who hunger and thirst for righteousness
Matthew 5
take all bitterness as sweetness, since they patiently endure all the adversities of this present life for the love of the supreme sweetness, that is, eternal blessedness.
Who is Solomon addressing when he says, "Diligently know the face of your flock, and consider your herds" (Proverbs 27)?
Is he teaching us to think about actual woolly flocks?
It speaks to the shepherd of the Church, urging them to carefully take care of those under their care.
They must recognize the minds and actions of each individual.
If any faults are found, strive to correct and cleanse them quickly.
Why does he immediately add, "For you will not have power forever, but a crown will be given for generations upon generations?"
So that the shepherd of the Church continually takes care of the sheep entrusted to him.
The meaning is: You will not always have the power to feed the Lord's sheep, but a crown will be given from generation to generation, meaning an eternal crown is prepared, which you will also receive if you have well fed the Lord's sheep.
Why did Solomon need to say: "The meadows are open, the green grass has appeared, and the hay has been gathered from the mountains?" Who doesn't already know this?
Truly, no one, if we take these words literally.
So, how should we understand this?
Truly only spiritually.
What do the meadows signify?
The meadows symbolize heavenly mysteries and are called meadows because they nurture faithful souls.
These divine mysteries have long been hidden under symbols and legal figures.
When and how are these meadows open?
The meadows are indeed open, because through the grace of the Lord Savior, the heavenly mysteries have been revealed.
He opened the minds of His disciples
so they could understand the Scriptures,
as stated in the book of Luke, chapter 24.
Then the green grasses also appeared, symbolizing the new teachings of gospel truth and glory.
What does the hay gathered from the mountains signify?
The mountains signify the holy Fathers of the Old Testament, and the hay represents their writings.
The hay is gathered from the mountains because the writings of these holy Fathers are collected to nourish and refresh the Lord’s sheep, meaning the souls of the faithful.
What does it mean when it says, "The poor and the creditor met together; the Lord is the maker of them all" (Proverbs 22)?
Who are the poor person and the creditor who met together?
The poor person is humble, a listener of the word.
However, the creditor is the one who, by preaching the word of God, entrusts money to the humble listener.
What happens when the poor and the creditor meet?
When the listener and the preacher come together in the grace of divine mercy, something beautiful happens:
The Lord illuminates both
Proverbs
twenty-nine.
Without the grace of divine mercy, the preacher couldn't preach, and the listener couldn't believe.
What does it mean when it says, "When prophecy fails, the people will be scattered"?
What is this prophecy, and why will its absence cause the people to be scattered?
Prophecy refers to the teaching and instruction of priests.
So, when these teachings and instructions cease, the people will be scattered.
Without the admonition and rebuke of priests, people are left to their own will and judgment, and soon, they become corrupted by various sins and vices.
How every word of God is like a fiery shield: for Solomon says, "Every word of God is a fiery shield to those who trust in Him" (Proverbs 30).
Every word of divine authority is called a fiery shield because it ignites the hearts of those who place their hope in God.
With its brightness, it enlightens them with the knowledge of truth.
It consumes and cleanses the filth of vices it finds in them, protecting them from the snares of enemies and all adversities.
What is the leech, which is said to have two daughters?
It is said that the leech has two daughters who always say, "Give," and they are never satisfied.
The leech is like the devil, always thirsting for blood.
He desires to lead people into sin and constantly ignites their thirst for wrongdoing.
What are those two leech daughters saying?
"Give, give," and they are never satisfied?
Luxury and greed clearly mirror the spiritual thirst and burning of the devil.
Just as he is never satisfied with sinning, neither are greed and luxury.
The more someone indulges in luxury and fornication, the more they enjoy it.
Similarly, the more someone accumulates wealth, the more they desire to increase it.
Why did Solomon use the example of the lizard, saying, "The lizard is caught with hands, yet it lives in kings' palaces"
(Proverbs 30:28)?
To motivate those who are lazy and slow-witted to work and receive blessings.
What kind of animal is a stellio?
The lizard, known for being very lazy and displaying various colors, got the name stellio because it is marked and varied with spots, almost like stars.
So, what does the lizard mean?
It refers to those who are slow to learn, but through daily effort and diligence, they ascend to the eternal hall.
This means that, although they reach knowledge of the Holy Scriptures with great labor, they can penetrate the secrets of heavenly mysteries.
About such people, it is written in the Gospel: Whoever has will be given more, and they will have an abundance.
Because whoever has the diligence to read will be given the ability to understand.
(Matthew 13:12).
What are the three things that Solomon mentions?
There are three things that move gracefully, and a fourth that strides confidently.
The lion is the strongest of the beasts, fearing no encounter.
The rooster stands tall, and the ram. No king can resist them.
These are the ones who walk with confidence.
Who does this lion symbolize?
The one about whom it is written:
"The Lion of the tribe of Judah has triumphed," etc. (Revelation five),
namely the Lord Jesus Christ, who is called the strongest of beasts,
because what is weak in God is stronger than humans (First Corinthians one).
What is God's weakness?
God's weakness was taking on the flesh of our mortality.
But this is stronger than men, because He, born of the Virgin, was perfect God.
Why is this lion unafraid of any encounter?
Because he committed no sin, nor was deceit found in his mouth First Peter chapter 2 hence he himself says in the Gospel: Behold, the ruler of the world is coming, and he finds nothing in me.
What does it mean when a rooster has girded loins?
Holy preachers
Why are roosters called preachers?
Amid the darkness of this present life, they proclaim the true morning, the true light, by preaching the glory of eternal happiness.
Why do people say these roosters have their loins girded?
Because the holy preachers suppress indulgence and lust within their followers.
What does the ram, which faces no king to oppose him, signify?
Through the ram, holy confessors and priests are symbolized.
Like rams leading the flock, they guide the faithful by their example.
These rams, if they live spiritually and righteously, have no king who can stand against them.
No persecutor is so fierce that they can hinder their purpose, for even when evil is inflicted upon them, they endure everything patiently for Christ.
What is that fourth thing that walks so gracefully?
He seemed foolish after being elevated to a high position.
Who is he?
The Antichrist will be revealed in a high, exalted position.
Despite being the most wicked man, he will consider himself worthy to be called the Son of God and will falsely claim to be God.
How does a fool appear when elevated to a high position?
Because in his arrogance and pride, he will suddenly be struck down by the divine sword.
Why does he say about the previous ones: "There are three things that move gracefully" (Proverbs 30)?
But about the fourth one that moves successfully?
Why didn't he say the same about this one: "It moves gracefully"; instead, he says, "successfully"?
Just because something goes well doesn't mean it's always successful, and not everything that's successful is always done well.
What are the things that go well, or what things bring happiness?
Those who walk holy and justly walk well; those who find success in this life walk happily.
The lion, the rooster, and the ram walk well, but not happily, because even Christ fulfilled the will of God the Father in all things, yet endured many adversities and death.
Similarly, holy preachers and confessors strive to fulfill the divine will, but they endure many persecutions in this life.
The Antichrist, however, will not walk well, because he will act proudly against the will of God.
But he will walk happily, as he will experience great glory and prosperity, albeit for a short time.
Who is King Lemuel, mentioned as:
"The words of King Lemuel, a vision his mother taught him?"
In Hebrew, it's called Lamuhel.
In Latin, it means "In whom God."
This undoubtedly refers to Solomon, the king of Israel, in whom God resided.
Without God's presence, he wouldn't have been able to understand or write such profound and numerous divine mysteries.
Who was his mother, the one who raised him and taught him vision?
According to the letter, his earthly mother, Bathsheba, the queen, wisely taught him.
However, in this context, the mother is better understood as spiritual and divine grace, which invisibly instructed him in his heart and imparted the understanding of wisdom that he preached and wrote about to people.
Who is that strong woman of whom it is said:
"Who can find a strong woman?"
Her worth is far above rubies.
The strong woman is known as the Holy Catholic Church.
She is called a woman because she spiritually gives birth to God's children through water and the Holy Spirit.
She is called strong because, out of her faith and love for her Creator and Redeemer, she scorns and despises all the adversities and prosperities of this world.
Why did Solomon say, "Who can find a strong woman?"
Through the Holy Spirit, it was revealed that no prophet or chosen one could redeem the human race, except for the one mediator between God and humans, Christ Jesus.
And so it was said: Who can find a strong woman?
This is understood to mean Christ.
Why did he soon add:
Is her value far above that from the ends of the earth?
To show that Christ, a man pure from the stains of sins, would not come in his time but long after him, and that no one like him was coming; at the end of the ages, the Son, who would be born of a Virgin, would descend from the heavens, and he would be perfect God and man.
This is what is meant by "far off," meaning long after. It signifies the time from the days of Solomon up to the birth of the Virgin.
And concerning the last boundaries, it says that his departure is from the highest heaven.
What price did the Lord pay for this woman?
He himself, as the Apostle says,
"Who loved us and gave himself up for us as an offering and sacrifice to God for a pleasing aroma."
Ephesians chapter 5.
How has a strong woman become like a merchant's ship?
Solomon says: She has become like a merchant's ship, bringing her bread from afar.
The merchant is called a trader because he is always striving to acquire and multiply his goods and profits.
Therefore, a merchant's ship, loaded with various commodities abundant in his homeland, sails across the sea to foreign places.
There, after selling all the goods he brought, he returns with more valuable items.
In the same way, the strong woman, that is, the holy Church, always desires to be laden with the riches of virtues and to abound in good works.
Navigating through the sea of this world, she aims to acquire greater things, that is, the gifts of divine grace.
Who's the captain of this ship?
The Lord Jesus Christ paid the price with His blood and redeemed the Church.
Therefore, the Holy Church, following the example of its teacher—its Lord and Redeemer—strives to multiply the virtues and good works, so that through them, it may deserve to acquire greater rewards, namely, the prizes of eternal happiness.
This is what is meant by "Bringing her bread from afar"; in all the good things she does temporarily, she desires only the satisfaction of wine and bread, because she expects only the eternal reward.
What does it mean to say, "She makes linen garments and sells them, and supplies belts to the merchant" (Proverbs 31:24)?
The Church created and sold the shroud because the faith it had woven through belief, it shared through words.
It received the faith of proper conduct from the unbelievers.
Therefore, it handed over the belt to the Canaanite, because through the strength of demonstrated justice, it bound the loose works of paganism.
This ensured that what is received may be held by living it.
What does it mean when it says, "She made a bedspread for herself, fine linen, and purple are her clothing"?
What exactly is a bedspread?
A striped garment typically features a very strong, varied weave.
So, what exactly is meant by the embroidered garment?
The mighty works of the holy Church and the various adornments of virtues, of which the prophet says:
The queen stands at your right hand in gold-woven clothing, surrounded by variety.
(Psalm Forty-Four).
How are byssus and purple similar to the clothing of that woman, which is the holy Church?
Byssus is a type of very white linen, representing bodily chastity and the purity of holy conduct.
Purple, on the other hand, symbolizes the shedding of blood.
Therefore, the strong woman, which is the holy Church, clothes herself in the byssus of God, meaning she maintains bodily chastity and shines with the brightness of holy conduct.
She also clothes herself in purple when the holy martyrs shed their blood for the name of Christ.
If fine linen and purple are the clothing of the holy Church, then why does it say in Proverbs 31:
"Strength and dignity are her clothing, and she laughs at the time to come"?
There is no contradiction because strength is associated with the purple, while beauty is associated with the whiteness of fine linen.
Therefore, strength is the garment of the holy Church, as it patiently endures the wickedness and persecution of evil people for the sake of faith in Christ and justice.
And beauty is also its garment, as it works justice and adorns itself with the grace of virtues.
So, why does it say: She will laugh on the last day, when the Lord says in the Gospel:
Woe to you who laugh now, for you will mourn and weep.
Luke Chapter 6?
In the Holy Scriptures, laughter usually signifies joy.
As the Lord says in the Gospel,
"Blessed are you who weep now, for you will laugh," meaning, you will be joyful.
And blessed Job says,
"The mouth of the truthful will be filled with laughter," meaning with joy.
Therefore, the strong woman, that is, the holy Church, will laugh on the last day, meaning she will rejoice in the reward of the heavenly kingdom.
Who are the children of the woman who is called most blessed?
And who is her husband who praises her?
For it says: Her children rise up and call her most blessed, and her husband praises her.
Proverbs 31.
The children of this woman, which is the holy Church, are all the elect.
Her husband is the Lord Jesus Christ.
On the last day of judgment, the children of the Church, meaning all the elect, will rise from the dust of the earth.
Adorned with the glory of immortality, they will proclaim their most blessed mother.
In other words, they will praise the holy Church, which gave birth to them for God, through water and the Holy Spirit.
Her husband will also rise, meaning the Lord Jesus Christ, when on the day of judgment he will appear manifestly in the power of divinity.
He will praise her, saying in judgment:
"Come, you blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the beginning of the world. I was hungry, and you gave me food."
Matthew 25.
So why did he use the past tense, saying, "They have risen?" He should have said, "They will rise."
Solomon was absolutely certain about what would happen.
So, like a prophet, he spoke about the future as if it had already happened.
It is said: Many daughters have gathered riches, but you have surpassed them all.
Proverbs 31.
The Church refers to many groups as the churches of heretics and the gatherings of misguided Catholics.
Who are referred to as the daughters of Christ or the Church?
And why are they called the sons of Christ or the Church?
Because of the sacrament of faith and baptism, and the adoption as children that they received during baptism.
Which daughters have gathered these riches?
Prayers, fasting, almsgiving, affliction, and chastity of the flesh,
restraining the tongue,
meditation on the Scriptures,
and the wealth of other good works:
these are true riches if done with a spiritual intention, aiming for the reward of the heavenly kingdom.
Otherwise, they are of no benefit to those who do them.
Hence, the daughters, namely the heretics or the multitude of evil Catholics, have gathered riches in vain;
because either they erred in faith, or certainly did not do such good works with a spiritual intention.
About these, the Lord says in the Gospel:
Many will say to me on that day,
"Lord, Lord, did we not prophesy in your name, and cast out demons in your name, and do many mighty works in your name?"
And then I will declare to them,
"I never knew you"
(Matthew 7).
But the holy Catholic Church has surpassed all of these,
meaning it has transcended them all,
because whatever it does, it acts only with right faith and spiritual intention.
What grace and beauty is he referring to when he says:
"Charm is deceptive, and beauty is fleeting; but a woman who fears the Lord is to be praised"
(Proverbs thirty-one).
The deceitfulness of human praise is something hypocrites seek from everyone.
Beauty is vain; it's the beauty of chastity or good deeds that hypocrites want to display to others in order to receive praise.
Why are grace and beauty said to be deceptive and vain?
Pretenders deceive and mislead.
They seek rewards in this life but will receive none in the future.
Even if they maintain chastity or do good works, all they do is in vain.
Who is the woman fearing the Lord?
The holy Church, which always lives in reverence of the Lord, constantly strives to follow His commandments.
How will this woman be praised?
Solomon clearly demonstrates this at the end of the book, where he says: "Give her the reward of her hands, and let her works praise her in the city gates." (Proverbs 31)
Whose words are these?
Men of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
When will he say these words?
On the day of judgment, when the angels are commanded to lead the Church to the joys of the heavenly kingdom after the end of this life, the angels will be instructed as follows:
"Give her the fruit of her hands," meaning the reward for her good works. Hands represent deeds; it's as if to say clearly, because she has taken care to do good works, such as love, joy, peace, kindness, goodness, modesty, self-control, faith, and patience, give her a reward worthy of these fruits.
And let her works praise her at the gates: in other words, in judgment or at the entrance to the heavenly homeland, let the very works she did praise her; let her be rewarded for the good works she performed.