Confession of the Monk Gottschalk After the Condemnation of Heresy
I believe and confess that the almighty and unchangeable God has foreseen and predestined holy angels and chosen humans to eternal life by grace.
The devil, the head of all demons, along with all his followers and the reprobate humans who are his members, has been predestined to eternal death as a just reward for their future evil deeds which were certainly foreseen.
The Lord himself says in his Gospel: "The ruler of this world has been judged" (John 16:11).
Blessed Augustine explains this in his tractate on John, tractate 95, and speaks openly about it: "That is, he is irrevocably destined to the judgment of eternal fire."
Also, about the reprobate, the Truth itself says: "But whoever does not believe has already been judged" (John 3:18), which, as the aforementioned author explained, means "has already been condemned."
The judgment has not yet appeared, he says, but the judgment has already been made.
Also, explaining John's words: "No one accepts his testimony" (John 3:32), he says: "No one" means certain people prepared for the wrath of God, to be damned with the devil.
Also, about the Jews: "These indignant ones are dead and predestined to eternal death."
Why did the Lord say to the Jews: "You do not believe because you are not among my sheep" (John 10:26)?
Because he saw them predestined to eternal destruction, not purchased by the price of his blood for eternal life.
Also, explaining these words of the Lord: "My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me, and I give them eternal life, and they shall never perish, and no one will snatch them out of my hand. My Father, who has given them to me, is greater than all, and no one can snatch them out of my Father's hand" (John 10:27-29), he said: What can the wolf do?
What can the thief and the robber do?
They can only destroy those predestined to destruction.
Also, speaking about two worlds (tractate 87).
The whole world is the Church, and the whole world hates the Church.
Therefore, the world hates itself, the enemy reconciled, the condemned saved, the polluted cleansed.
Also, in tract 110: There is a world of which the Apostle says: "So that we are not condemned with this world" First Corinthians 11:32.
For this world, the Lord does not pray, for He knows what it is predestined for.
Also, in tract 107: Judas, the betrayer of Christ, is called the son of perdition, predestined for betrayal.
Also, in the Enchiridion, chapter 100: For the damnation of those whom He has justly predestined to punishment.
Also, in the book on the Perfection of Human Righteousness, chapter 13: He says, no one was doing this good that is to be sought, no one up to one; but in that kind of people that is predestined for destruction. For on these, indeed, God's foreknowledge looked and pronounced judgment.
Also, in the books on the City of God, book 22, chapter 24: What will He give to those whom He has predestined to death?
Also, Blessed Pope Gregory, in Morals, book 34, chapter 2: Leviathan with all his members is assigned to eternal torments.
Also, Saint Fulgentius, in the third book on the Truth of Predestination and Grace, book 3, chapter 5: God, he says, has prepared punishments for sinners, indeed those whom He has justly predestined to suffer penalties.
Blessed Fulgentius composed a whole book on this one question alone, that is, on the Predestination of the Reprobate to Destruction, to his friend named Monimus, book 1.
Wherefore, Saint Isidore also says, in Sentences, book 2, chapter 6: There is a twofold predestination, either of the elect to rest or of the reprobate to death.
Thus, therefore, in all things with these elect of God, and Catholics, I believe and confess, as divinely inspired, encouraged, and armed, I am helped. Amen.
For he is a false witness who corrupts either the meaning or the surface of the words of anyone.
The Extended Confession of Gottschalk
Almighty Lord God, my mercy, all-powerful and incomparably merciful king, with indescribable kindness and patience towards the human race, and profoundly wise in an unsearchable way.
Indeed, all your chosen ones always need you so they may be able to please you through you alone.
Just as branches need the vine to bear fruit, or air and eyes need light to be clear or to see; otherwise, the branches wither without the vine and burn when thrown into the fire, the air is dark without light, and eyes are open in vain.
Therefore, I humbly call upon you, Almighty, most merciful, and most glorious, triune and one Lord God, to kindly be my most pious helper and listener.
Graciously grant to me, the most needy, through the invincible power of your free grace, that what I believe in my heart from you, through you, and in you about your foreknowledge and predestination (thanks to you) for righteousness, just as I have often confessed through your grace, I may also truthfully and simply confess with my mouth for salvation.
Ultimately, may the invincible and endlessly blessed truth be revealed to your chosen ones from my part, and may the defeated and utterly cursed falsehood fade away as it should.
Amen.
For I indeed believe and confess that you foresaw everything that was to come, whether good or bad, before the ages: but only predestined the good.
The good predestined by you has been discovered by your faithful ones in two ways, indeed clearly revealed by you to them, that is, in the benefits of grace and judgments of justice.
For as the Psalmist clearly indicates, you, Lord, love both mercy and judgment.
Psalm 33:5.
Therefore, you have predestined eternal life by grace for all your chosen ones, and nonetheless, you have predestined them for eternal glory.
Surely, it would have been in vain to predestine life for them unless you had also predestined them for it.
So, almost certainly, the devil, his angels, and all reprobate men have been justly predestined for eternal punishment, and you have similarly predestined them for it.
Indeed, you would not have predestined them for the punishment of eternal death without reason unless you had also predestined them for it.
They would not go unless they were destined, nor would they be destined unless they were predestined.
You, who have existed before all ages and cannot be mutable even for a moment, will be proven unchangeable through all ages afterward.
If any of the reprobate were destined there, which is not the case, they had not been predestined.
Therefore, because you, Lord, alone are who you are Exodus 3:4, as you yourself testify, and as David also says, "You are always the same" Psalm 102:28, and as you say elsewhere, "You are the Lord, and you do not change" Malachi 3:1.
Your excellent preacher Paul also affirms, "You alone have immortality" First Timothy 6:16, that is, immutability; with whom, as asserted by another apostle, "there is no variation or shadow of change" James 1:17.
It is perfectly clear and evident, and to any wise person abundantly clear, that you have foreknown and predestined at once, without any interval, both all and each of your works before the ages. As said by Isaiah, "You have made things that are to come" Isaiah 45:11, according to the Septuagint.
Following and explaining very truthfully the prophet David, your most faithful servant Augustine says, "God, according to that will of his, which is eternal with his foreknowledge, has indeed made in heaven and on earth all things whatsoever he willed, not only past or present, but also future."
Therefore, since Your will is eternal, O Lord, and as Augustine says, in Your omnipotence concerning Your works, knowing is the same as willing, according to what Orosius writes to Augustine.
Your willing itself is also an act, as Ambrose says.
It is clear beyond doubt that whatever is to happen in action outside has already been accomplished by You in predestination, according to what Pope Gregory asserts, teaches, and writes.
Hence, let it be far from any of Your faithful Catholics to suspect any interval between Your foreknowledge and the predestination of Your works, since all that You willed to do, You did at once when You read or heard it.
Especially since You did nothing in effect before You incomparably knew the future and arranged it with eternal counsel by predestination.
But now, it is time, O Lord, to present the truthful testimonies of the divine books, by which it is taught without any doubt and declared without ambiguity that the reprobates are predestined to the eternal fires of torment.
First, I think it is right to bring forth Your invincible truth, Lord Jesus Christ.
"Whoever does not believe," You say, "has already been judged" (John 3:18), meaning, as Augustine explained, has already been condemned.
For he says, "the judgment has not yet appeared, but the judgment has already been made." Likewise, "The prince of this world has already been judged" (John 16:11), meaning, as Augustine explained, "he is irrevocably destined to the judgment of eternal fire."
David also says, "Therefore the wicked will not stand in the judgment" (Psalm 1:5).
Augustine explains that they are already destined for certain punishments.
Likewise, "You struck all who oppose me without cause." Rightly, he says, it is spoken in predestination about the devil and his angels. And lest it be said that the devil alone with his angels is destined for death, which is proven to be wholly absurd, that the head should be separated from the body by predestination: David says again, "You have brought me down to the dust of death" (Psalm 22:15).
Solomon also says, "The Lord has made everything for its own purpose, even the wicked for the day of evil" (Proverbs 16:14).
In the book of Ecclesiasticus, it is said, "He who turns from righteousness to sin, God has prepared him for the sword" (Sirach 26:27).
This must be understood as referring only to those who are rejected.
Hence, Job also says, "Ask any of the travelers, and you will find that they understand this too, because the wicked are kept for the day of destruction and brought to the day of wrath" (Job 2:29).
Gregory, the explainer of this, explains it thus: Often, he says, divine patience tolerates those whom it has already condemned to foreseen punishments.
Hence, when he explained this: "With Him are wisdom and strength" (Job 12:13), he said among other things: Even the delay in judgment can be signified by the name of counsel.
So when punishments for sinners are delayed, it is not because the guilt of the wicked is unnoticed, but so that the sentence of their condemnation, postponed to give them time to repent, may seem to come slowly and with deliberation.
Therefore, what the open sentence sometimes judges outwardly, lay hidden in the counsel of Almighty God from before the ages.
Similarly, explaining: "You have set his limits, which cannot be passed" (Job 14:5), he says: Nothing happens to humans in this world without the hidden counsel of Almighty God.
For God, foreknowing all things to come, decreed before the ages how they should be arranged through the ages.
Again, explaining this about the wicked: "They are like straw before the wind, and like chaff that the storm scatters" (Job 21:18), he says: In the eyes of Almighty God, the life of the wicked is like chaff.
Because even if it appears green for a moment, it is already seen as consumed by His judgment, for it is destined for eternal destruction.
Of such people and their crimes, you, Lord, through Moses, say: "Aren't these things stored with me, sealed in my treasures? Vengeance is mine, and I will repay them in due time." (Deuteronomy 32:34-35).
The day of destruction is near and the appointed time is hastening.
(Deuteronomy 32:35).
"I will lift my hand to heaven and say: As surely as I live forever. When I sharpen my flashing sword, and my hand takes hold of judgment, I will take vengeance on my enemies and repay those who hate me. I will make my arrows drunk with blood, and my sword will devour flesh from the blood of the slain and the captives, from the unprotected heads of the enemy. Rejoice, nations, with his people, for he will avenge the blood of his servants and will render vengeance to his enemies." (Deuteronomy 32:40-43).
If anyone presumes to say that all these things and many more scattered throughout the canonical Scriptures are foreknown but not predetermined: let him carefully consider how contrary he is to the truth, and how much he supports harmful falsehood by daring to subject you to changeability.
As Saint Augustine said, Augustine: "No changeable nature would be rewarded unless you, Lord our God, remained unchangeable."
He would hardly care if you were thought (God forbid) to be changeable from eternity to the Day of Judgment and even on the Day of Judgment, as if you were not predestined, by sending the reprobate to torment, thus being changed.
And then forever being changed, that is, proven dead (God forbid): for how can one who is changed die, as the authority of Augustine, Gregory, and other doctors attests?
But it is far removed that you, Lord, who could never be changed, can or will ever be changeable, even for a moment, without any beginning, until the Day of Judgment, and from then on appear changed forever solely because of the damnation of the reprobate and their due torment.
Indeed, Lord, it would have been better if only you had been created mutable.
How much more should it be avoided that you would be changed for the sake of the vessels of wrath and fury, upon whom your face turns because of their evil deeds, so that you may erase their memory from the earth?
As it is written in Psalm 34:16, "The face of the Lord is against those who do evil, to blot out their name from the earth."
About whom it is also truly sung to you day and night by the faithful: "But you, O God, will bring them down into the pit of destruction," from Psalm 55:23.
And about whom the apostle Peter says: "For whom judgment has been from long ago and their destruction does not slumber," from Second Peter 2:3.
And Paul, in Romans 9:22, says: "Wanting to show his wrath and make his power known, God endured with much patience the vessels of wrath prepared for destruction."
According to Jerome, "prepared for destruction"; according to Ambrose, "prepared for destruction"; according to Augustine, "perfected for destruction," meaning surely predestined, as Augustine himself has clearly explained.
The same preacher also says in First Thessalonians 2:16: "To fill up their sins always, for the wrath of God has come upon them to the utmost."
Jude also says: "Certain men have crept in unnoticed, who long ago were designated for this condemnation, ungodly men," from Jude 4.
By stating they were designated for this condemnation, he implied they were not only foreseen but also predestined.
Since you, eternal God, have predestined them before anyone temporally born knew them as foreseen.
Because those you foreknew would persist in damnable sins through their own misery, you, as the most just judge, indeed predestined them to destruction justly and rightly.
And not only did you predestine, but by predestining you already destined them.
Hence, David says, as if about those already predestined to hell, although they were yet to be placed there by your command: "Like sheep, they are laid in the grave," from Psalm 49:14-15.
It is clearly in perfect harmony, as the apostle John says in the Book of Revelation:
"The books were opened, and another book was opened, which is the book of life; and the dead were judged according to what was written in the books, based on their deeds."
Revelation 20:12.
Also: "Each one was judged according to their deeds; and death and Hades were thrown into the lake of fire.
And anyone whose name was not found written in the book of life was thrown into the lake of fire."
Revelation 20:13-15.
A little earlier, it says: "And the devil, who deceived them, was thrown into the lake of fire and sulfur."
Revelation 20:9.
A little later, it says: "And he said to me: Write, for these words are faithful and true.
And he said to me: It is done."
Revelation 21:5-6.
And so that no one would doubt upon hearing this from John, you yourself immediately follow up and say (Lord Jesus Christ):
"I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end.
To the thirsty, I will give water from the spring of the water of life without cost.
The one who is victorious will inherit all this, and I will be their God, and they will be my child.
But the cowardly, the unbelieving, the vile, the murderers, the sexually immoral, those who practice magic arts, the idolaters, and all liars—they will be consigned to the fiery lake of burning sulfur.
This is the second death."
Revelation 21:6-8.
Therefore, let the unbelievers and liars fear and avoid being among the aforementioned accomplices if they choose to stubbornly resist such clear truth.
Also: "Look, I am coming soon! My reward is with me, and I will give to each person according to what they have done."
Revelation 22:12.
Unless in the predestination which you have unchangeably, irrevocably ordained.
You continue and say:
"I am Alpha and Omega, the first and the last, the beginning and the end.
Blessed are those who wash their robes, that they may have the right to the tree of life and may go through the gates into the city.
Outside are the dogs, those who practice magic arts, the sexually immoral, the murderers, the idolaters, and everyone who loves and practices falsehood."
Revelation 22:13-15.
Let everyone hear this, especially those who are habitual liars, and particularly those who have no fear or shame, and who easily deceive in religious teachings.
For surely, no more serious lie can ever be found.
Indeed, none is as grave, though to some it may seem trivial or even enjoyable.
But listen to what follows if they ignore the preceding.
I, Jesus, have sent my angel to testify to you in the Church (Revelation 22:16).
And a little later: I solemnly declare to everyone who hears the words of the prophecy of this book If anyone adds to them, God will add to him the plagues written in this book.
And if anyone takes away from the words of the book of this prophecy, God will take away his share from the tree of life and from the holy city, which are described in this book.
The one who testifies to these things says, "Yes, I am coming soon" (Revelation 22:18-20).
Behold, Lord Jesus, in this holy book of yours, I find that the devil, his angels, and all reprobate humans are already destined by you to be cast into the lake of fire and sulfur, as was mentioned earlier.
I do not dare to deny you, that is, the truth, because I fear being denied by you, as you yourself testify: "Whoever denies me before others, I will also deny before my Father who is in heaven" (Matthew 10:33).
Also, Paul says: "If we deny him, he will also deny us" (Second Timothy 2:12).
Therefore, as I said before, I do not dare to deny you because I fear being denied by you.
I neither presume to add nor to take away anything, fearing that the plagues written in this book may be added to me, or that my share may be taken away from the book of life.
Therefore, in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, I beseech you, Lord, as much as I can, to deign to help me as I need, and do not allow any longer for any of your chosen ones (God forbid) to doubt this.
But rather, do not delay to reveal this most health-giving truth to them, as you see it is very necessary for them to know.
According to the truthful testimony of the blessed Augustine, which he openly shared with the people by clearly and faithfully explaining the gospel's perplexities:
"They build lies in people," he said, "what do they expel from them, if not the truth? They send in the devil, they exclude Christ; they send in the adulterer, they exclude the bridegroom; namely, the groomsmen or rather the pimps of the serpent.
For they speak so that the serpent may possess, and Christ be excluded. When falsehood possesses, the serpent possesses; when truth possesses, Christ possesses.
For He said: 'I am the truth' (John 14:6); but about the other it is said: 'He did not stand in the truth, because there is no truth in him' (John 8:44).
Therefore, what that same blessed servant of yours, Augustine, truly endeavored to bear witness to, is that the reprobates are damned by foreknowledge, while elsewhere he acknowledges that they are predestined to death: both are entirely true, because both are true here.
For as he wisely and truly acknowledges, sometimes foreknowledge is used for predestination.
Nor does it contradict the truth but rather agrees with it, as the Apostle said: 'God has not rejected His people whom He foreknew' (Romans 11:2).
Although elsewhere, combining both, but distinguishing them with a reasonable difference, he wonderfully defined it by saying: 'By predestination God foreknew those things which He Himself was going to do.
'
Hence it is said: 'Creating things that are to come' (Isaiah 45:7, according to the Septuagint).
Similarly, connecting predestination more plainly and fully with foreknowledge, he says about the Trinity: In His foreknowledge, which cannot be deceived or changed, He disposes of His future works; that is entirely what predestination is, and nothing else.
Similarly, more briefly but much more clearly in the earlier sense, since the Apostle said, 'God has not rejected His people whom He foreknew' (Romans 11:2).
When Augustine explained that in this context, "foreknowledge" means predestination (XI, 7), he mentioned a bit later:
To predestine is to foreknow what he himself would do.
Therefore, as I have already said, both are true: the reprobates are condemned by both foreknowledge and predestination.
Those destined for destruction by law are certainly condemned.
This is sufficiently proven by the aforementioned testimonies, which Catholics undoubtedly consider invincible.
However, if a testimony for this matter should have been complete, it could have been understood metaphorically.
It should have been complete so that what follows could be understood by what precedes.
Nevertheless, if they still desire to hear more about this, for the love of truth, which they consider greatly opposed, I pray that they listen and make efforts to defend the truth immediately.
Listen, I say, to Augustine speaking marvelously here, through the divine grace abundantly infused in him.
He says: This good thing, which is to seek God, was sought by no one, not even one, except those predestined to destruction.
Speaking again of the two cities, he says: One is predestined to reign eternally with the Lord; the other to undergo eternal punishment with the devil.
Again: If the Church were so certain about some, that it even knew who they are, who, although still living, are predestined to go into eternal fire with the devil, it would no more pray for them than for the devil himself.
Again: What will he give to those he predestined to life, who also gave these things to those he predestined to death?
And again, in the Enchiridion, which the old man wrote about faith, hope, and charity with the most subtle sense, the most trained intellect, the purest eloquence, and the most splendid style, marvelously and singularly by God's favor, he says: For the damnation of those whom he justly predestined to punishment.
In the same way, it is said that the children of hell are not from there but are prepared for it, just as the children of the kingdom are prepared for the kingdom.
What could be clearer?
What could be more sufficient?
Just as the children of the kingdom are prepared for the kingdom, so too are the children of hell prepared for it.
This is nothing other than predestination.
Surely, if such a great author, who is truthful and perfectly aligned with the Catholic faith, had not seen this and many other things, he would not have left them uncorrected.
When he thoroughly reviewed his books, he would have corrected them.
And he certainly would not have spoken to the people so frequently, boldly, fearlessly, freely, willingly, confidently, trustfully, and joyfully, without any servile fear, illuminated by your love and authority, if he had recognized any danger in it.
I have already mentioned some points above, and I have decided to add a few more here.
There is a certain group prepared for the wrath of God, condemned with the devil.
Also, there is a certain group born for the wrath of God.
Why did the Lord say to the Jews: You do not believe because you are not my sheep (John 10:26)?
It is because he saw them predestined to eternal destruction, not bought for eternal life with the price of his blood.
What can a wolf do?
What can a thief and robber do?
They only destroy those predestined to destruction.
These indignantly dead and predestined to eternal death.
The world, he says, hates the world, the enemy reconciled, the condemned saved, the unclean cleansed.
Judas, the betrayer of Christ, is called the son of perdition, predestined for damnation.
He does not pray for this world, for he knows what it is predestined for.
Blessed Fulgentius also says this: God has prepared punishments for sinners, specifically for those whom he has justly predestined to undergo punishment.
Here he clearly acknowledges both that punishments are predestined for the reprobate and that they are in turn predestined for those punishments.
In seven books, the very influential and prolific doctor debated against the two heretics, Faustus—a former monk of Lérins who later became the bishop of Riez.
This remarkable doctor refuted Faustus, crushed the devil's lies, and, along with fourteen other holy bishops, expelled him from the Church of Christ, eliminating the lethal poison of the Antichrist.
Additionally, he wrote three books about the truth of predestination and grace.
He also wrote one book entirely on this question, in response to Monimus, who consulted him on the matter.
The glorious Gregory, whom I have mentioned before, spoke on this matter as follows:
"The Lord saw the dark enemy when he penetrated the gates of hell. He struck down the cruel spirits and condemned the rulers of death by dying."
"Therefore, this is not spoken of as something in the future, but as something that has already happened, because whatever was to happen in action has indeed already happened in predestination."
"Leviathan and all his members are assigned to eternal torments."
"The day of judgment itself is predestined," he explains from the book of Job:
"'A lamp despised in the thoughts of the wealthy, prepared for the appointed time' Job 12:5. He says that the time of the despised lamp is the predestined day of final judgment."
Saint Isidore also speaks on this matter:
"There is a twin predestination: either of the elect to rest or of the reprobate to death."
"For he does not say there are two, but twin, meaning twofold. Because you, Lord, have spoken: with one, but still twin predestination, you freely justify and save the elect perpetually, and rightly reject and justly condemn the reprobate."
"As the aforementioned Gregory says, looking upon some, you redeem; leaving others, you destroy."
The concept of double predestination is explained like this: it is divided into the elect and the reprobate, even though it is one, it appears dual.
It's similar to what Saint Augustine and other Church Fathers say about twin charity or love, which is one but appears dual because it involves both God and neighbor.
It's also like what Augustine mentions: that God's work is divided into two parts, seen as twin, and that the world is described by him as fourfold.
However, it is not four, but one, and he recognizes the continent as divided into five parts, yet teaches it is one.
Therefore, Saint Gregory calls the knowledge of the Jews twin, and although it seems dual, it is acknowledged as one.
This way of speaking is very common, even among secular authors.
Because it is accurate and truthful, it is appropriate to present some examples to support this argument.
For instance, some have described a twin tree, meaning one tree, not two.
Another has said a name's quality is divided into two parts, and the condition of all feet as threefold.
Priscian, an equally skilled scholar, explained threefold as tripartite.
It should not seem strange to any wise person if double predestination is believed to be one in you, our Lord, but also threefold in a personal sense.
According to Augustine's faithful belief and confident assertion, you are good in rewarding the chosen and just in punishing the others.
Moreover, as he professes, you are good in all things because it is good when justice is served, and just in all things because it is just when the due is given without deceit.
I believe and confess all these things here, thanking you for granting them to me freely.
In your writings, especially through the works of your ministers, and clearly explained by your grace, I find truths that I dare not contradict.
I fear denying the truth from you, as you have warned, and I am mindful of Paul's words: If anyone preaches to you a gospel other than what you received, let him be accursed.
Galatians 1:8.
My devotion to you, Lord Jesus, is unwavering.
As Augustine rightly says, I am not influenced by a desire to please people or to avoid inconveniences, when it comes to the truth.
Blessed Gregory also teaches us: as much as we can avoid the scandals of our neighbors without sin, we should; but if a scandal arises from the truth, it is better to allow the scandal than to abandon the truth.
No one is exempt from this, whether it's Augustine or the Apostle.
They are subject to the same anathema worthy of the Apostle's condemnation.
As Gregory admits: as long as the matter is conducted with faith intact, it is virtuous to endure any difficulties.
If possible, I would rather die a thousand times for the truth than yield even once to anyone speaking otherwise.
Remembering your words: Whoever acknowledges me before others, I will also acknowledge before my Father in heaven.
Matthew 10:32.
I also recall: Do not move the ancient boundary which your fathers have set.
Proverbs 22:28.
As Gregory explains, heretics move these boundaries by transgressing the constitutions of the Fathers, leading the ignorant astray with their perverse teachings and destructive gifts.
Those whom the blessed Job also rebukes, saying: "Does God need your lies, that you speak deceitfully on His behalf?" (Job 13:7).
God does not need lies, because the truth does not seek support from falsehood.
However, heretics, unable to defend their erroneous beliefs about God with the truth, seek shadows of falsehood as if to approve a ray of light.
They speak deceitfully on His behalf, deceiving weak minds from understanding Him through foolish seduction.
Again: "Will it please Him, who nothing can be concealed from? Or will He be deceived like a man, by your fraudulent acts?" (Job 13:9).
Heretics offer fraud to God because they assert things that are not pleasing to Him, and while they strive to defend Him, they offend Him by falling into opposition to the very One they claim to serve through their preaching.
Hence, it is also said through the Psalmist: "To destroy the enemy and the defender" (Psalm 8:3); for every heretic is an enemy and defender against Almighty God.
In trying to defend Him, they oppose His truth.
Since nothing can be hidden from God, He judges them by what they feel inside, not by their outward appearance.
Therefore, since God is not deceived by their frauds like a man would be, it is rightly added: "He will rebuke you because you secretly accept His face. As soon as He moves, He will trouble you, and His terror will fall upon you" (Job 13:10).
This statement that they secretly accept the face of God can be understood in two ways.
There are some who indeed feel the truth in their hearts, yet speak false things about God outwardly.
So as not to be seen as defeated, they know the truth inwardly, yet outwardly they attack it.
Hence, it is well said: "He will rebuke you because you secretly accept His face"; as if it were openly said: you are all the more condemned for falsehood before Him since you see what is true within yourselves.
What a heretic is, so that no one has the liberty to invent something different, some of the Fathers, and Cassiodorus, have beautifully defined:
A heretic, he says, is someone who, driven by either ignorance or contempt of divine law, stubbornly adheres to a new error or follows a sect that prefers to oppose the Catholic truth rather than submit to it.
I thought it necessary to include this because I have discovered that many are both deceived and deceive others on this point, suspecting those who believe and confess the truth of this Catholic faith about the predestination of the reprobate to be heretics, against those resisting and contradicting it.
Conversely, they assert those as Catholics who do not fear to whisper against such clear truth, but openly preach falsehood, disregarding the words of the blessed Basil, who, nourished by divine teachings, does not suffer any corruption of divine doctrines, nor any syllable to be altered.
For these, if it happens, they embrace all kinds of death.
And also disregarding Gregory Nazianzen’s saying: It is the strength to persevere in the truth, even if someone is defeated by things that are nothing.
Indeed, falsehood and lies are nothing, which surpass all sorts of bodily deaths, and the hearts of the always truthful rightly avoid and dread them.
Especially in the doctrine of religion, they completely avoid the precipice of false speech.
This is, thanks to you, Lord, holy Trinity, my unbreakable faith and confession about your foreknowledge and predestination which Truth itself preached, and as the aforementioned disciples of His against false-speaking supporters, and (unless they are corrected) children of falsehood and perdition, and against their pestilent poisons and heretical doctrines.
If sprinkled with your grace, carefully attend, weigh, and consider, how from the beginning of the angelic fall, as Peter the apostle says: You did not spare the angels when they sinned.
But you have reserved them, bound with chains and imprisoned in hell, for greater torment on the day of judgment.
You destroyed the original world because of the wickedness of men's crimes.
You also punished the abominable deeds and sins of the Sodomites, burning them with heavenly fire, destroying them, and plunging them into eternal punishment.
You cast Pharaoh and his army into the sea, annihilating them like chaff.
If they carefully consider these things with a calm mind and reflect wisely with your help, they will easily understand that the aforementioned angels, who, as Jude, the brother of James, writes, did not keep their own domain but abandoned their proper dwelling, have been reserved in eternal chains under darkness for the judgment of the great day.
And that you threw them into this dark prison of the air according to the eternal decree of your predestination, reserving them for greater punishment through the ages, as both apostles testify.
And that those things which are subsequently narrated about the reprobate men were not done without predestination (God forbid).
Otherwise, before all ages, you would be found mutable and at the beginning of the ages, according to their most deceitful doctrine, you would have immediately changed (which cannot happen even for a moment): you, who alone are believed by all Catholics to be immutable, and are known to be more clearly revealed by your light.
Please, Lord God, make it so that those who are bold, stubborn, and obstinate, and who are neither quarrelsome, deceitful, nor lying (because such people, who oppose the truth, are certainly not able to perceive it clearly, no matter how naturally smart they may be), but instead become simple lovers of truth, may consider with all their spiritual vision that if the souls of the wicked, from the first, namely Cain, up to the last one who will die before the day of judgment, are extracted from their own bodies, whether they are destined by your eternal predestination, or you are now and daily destining them (whenever they die, have died, or will die) to the torments due and rightfully assigned to them;
Not only would you be changeable before the ages, but also (which you cannot be in any way) you would have been changed since the beginning of the death of these same wicked people, indeed since the beginning of the damnation of the evil angels.
You would be changed frequently, indeed countless times, and you would be changed every single day and night.
Without a doubt, you would remain changed forever, because of the children of hell alone, whom the enemies of truth stubbornly and deceitfully deny to be predestined to eternal punishment.
These things, I say, Lord, make them consider, weigh, and judge as they should, and finally, someday, see what they have so far pretended not to see: what great and terrible evil they have proclaimed, preached, and asserted in your Church about you, our ever-unchanging Lord God, falsely and fatally for their own and their followers' ruin.
I pray that you mercifully bring them back to the path of salvation, so they do not persist stubbornly in such a deadly error of heresy.
Let them see, I say, what a great and terrible evil it is that, although your chosen ones have always done, do, and will continue to do all good things with wisdom (as they are evidently aided by your gratuitous help of kindness), they presume not only to lie but also to perjure themselves openly before everyone, claiming that you, the author of all, the source of wisdom, indeed the triune and eternal wisdom, have wanted, been able, or even should have done anything (which is far from the truth) without counsel.
I do not mention, from the very beginning of the human race, the souls of the dying reprobates, or even those same souls with their bodies restored on the day of judgment, being destined with the devil and his angels without the counsel of predestination.
But having inspected these things as is fitting with keen insight and understanding, let them be rightly confused and ashamed, and thus someday finally submit humbly to the truth, and cease from troubling me.
However, if, with an exhausted source and without any remaining shame, they prefer to persist in falsehood rather than retreat from such a great error, as they ought to have done, let them see for themselves where they are heading: toward destruction.
I pray to you, Lord God, that you would graciously protect your Church, so they no longer corrupt it with their falsehood, and that their heresy does not overturn what remains of their wickedness, even though they sorrowfully destroy themselves and their followers with them.
I was truly taught by the truth itself, which the esteemed teachers of your Church have preached.
These ministers are the most faithful, devoted, and renowned in proclaiming this truth.
This is clearly expressed here about your predestination, the Catholic faith—freely inspired by you and filled with devotion, encouraged, armed, mercifully and wonderfully helped, protected, supported, and upheld.
Thanks to you, I firmly believe, hold, and openly defend this faith.
Anyone teaching contrary doctrines, I avoid like a plague and reject as heretics.
It is with great sorrow that, following the command of the blessed Augustine, I declare anyone who stubbornly resists the invincible truth and teaches contrary to it as a heretic and an enemy of the Christian faith, to be anathematized by all Catholics.
Moreover, if any of them, after reading and understanding these things, refuse to yield and harden their hearts like Pharaoh, despising such evident truth, I, following the counsel of the Apostle Paul, consider them to be avoided.
I see that such a person is subverted and condemned by their own judgment, as stated in Titus 3:11.
However, for the sake of the less experienced who might be lured by them and, unless corrected, lost, I wish for a public meeting, if it pleases you, Lord.
This way, with the truth openly established and falsehood utterly destroyed, we could collectively give thanks to you, who have granted us the most desired outcome, even beyond what we asked or understood.
I suffer great pain and bear the deepest sorrow day and night because, due to the vileness of my name, I see the truth being disregarded.
People do not keep sincere love towards you, as they ought.
To appear as my victors, they have loved and love you very little or not at all, denying you because of me.
And I wish, Almighty and most merciful Lord, that just as I believe and hope in You, given that You have graciously allowed me the ability, as You have long been willing to grant, and continue to grant daily, that before a multitude of people chosen from all who fear You, in the presence of the ruler of this kingdom, with a venerable assembly of bishops, priests, monks, and canons, it would be granted to me, if they would not accept this truth of Your predestination in the Catholic faith, to prove it by the method I am about to describe, with Your grace assisting me, before the eyes of all who are watching.
Namely, by placing four vessels one after another, and filling them separately with boiling water, thick oil, and pitch, and finally setting a large fire, I would enter each one, calling upon Your most glorious name, to demonstrate my faith, indeed the Catholic faith, and pass through each one until, with Your guidance, presence, and support, offering Your right hand and mercifully leading, I would be able to emerge unscathed.
So that the clarity of this Catholic faith might shine in Your Church, falsehood might disappear, faith might be strengthened, and treachery might be avoided.
May You, Lord, inspire those who read and understand these words, as is necessary, with the desire to pray earnestly to You, so that You may swiftly bring about this desire of my heart as Your Church needs.
And if, with Your help, I emerge unscathed from all these, they may embrace the truth and detest falsehood.
But if I hesitate either to begin or to complete what I believe, confess, hope, and love from You, through You, and in You, assured solely by You and Your grace, let them immediately cast me into the fire and allow me to perish there deservedly.
Humbly, I ask you, Lord, in your most sweet name, that no Catholic will rashly—God forbid—judge me in their heart for daring to request such things.
As you know, I do this not out of recklessness but take them from you by your kindness.
Anyone who truly fears and loves you, and reads or hears these words, implores your mercy with brotherly compassion and love.
You, the only helper in times of need, as stated in Psalms 9:10, may urgently help me, a believer hoping in your compassion, and enrich me to begin and complete these things with full faith.
Strengthen me with solid hope, give me sincere charity, and grant me true humility before you always.
Drive far away from your orthodox Church the falsehood of deadly doctrine, and let me rejoice with your elect for the truth of the Catholic faith revealed to your faithful.
Let us have true and sincere joy in you alone, the highest exultation, and common boasting, that by your mercy your people have been made immune from the treachery of heretics.
None of your elect has ever pleased you through their own merits but rather by your free grace.
They have pleased you, still please you, and will always please you by what comes from you.
Therefore, animated by this free faith, strengthened by hope, and inflamed with charity, I humbly beseech you, most good God, to give me true humility and always make me rejoice with solid joy in life.
Finally, to you and your name, I give the glory that is due through the ages.
Because of justice, as you rightly humble the proud, bend them down, and lower them; but because of grace, you freely exalt, lift up, and raise the humble.
Through both of these, I humbly ask you, all-powerful and merciful Trinity, equally one, to completely forgive all the debts of your enemies—whoever they may be, whether they harm me unknowingly or knowingly, or even want to harm me, yet in truth only harm themselves—and pardon all their crimes and offenses entirely.
Amen.
I give thanks to you, triune and one Lord God, as many times as possible, for graciously allowing and still allowing me to believe in and confess the Catholic faith about predestination.
And as I believe and hope, you will continue to allow me more and more, day and night.
You are my enlightener, inflamer, and supporter.
Amen.
I pray, as much as divine humility allows me, before the most present majesty of the triune unity and one Trinity, that whoever reads this not with the bitterness of envy, but rather with the love of a dove, may remember the sinner Gottschalk before God, and simply implore with paternal or fraternal affection his most kind mercy, that he may graciously grant me the excellence of true humility always and everywhere before him, and the perpetual eminence of sincere charity.
May he thus protect me ceaselessly in his tabernacle from the contradiction of tongues, as stated in Psalms 31:21, that is, in the true faith of the Catholic Church from the slanders of heretics, so that I may prefer to endure all present adversities from their persecutions for the name of our Lord God and the love of truth, rather than to deviate even for a moment—God forbid—from the love or confession of truth, or from the prescribed faith of Catholics, which has been declared by the mouth of truth itself, and also by the most invincible authorities of its ministers.
Indeed, I owe my neighbor as much love as I owe myself, but I owe God all my heart, since whatever good we have either is Him or comes from Him.
To you, the faithful reader and skilled interpreter of this faith and my confession, accept it wisely, as I respectfully pray to you as a father, or faithfully exhort you as a brother.
If you wish to see the truth forever and rejoice eternally with the holy angels, the chosen humans, and the faithful witnesses of that truth, you should abhor the most pernicious and destructive kind of lying, especially in the teaching of religion, even more than the death of the body.
As divinely stated by the blessed Augustine, let the most beautiful and modest love spread in our hearts and receive gratefully the kiss of doves, so that the most cautious humility may avoid, or the most solid truth may blunt, the canine tooth.
The kiss of doves signifies the inspection of the upright and truthful in heart around themselves and their words, whereas the canine tooth signifies the malicious and mocking reproach of the perverse and deceitful.
Therefore, beseech and pray to the Lord our God and His majesty that, against the barking of heretics, we may have the truest, simplest, and most benevolent love.
In the end, we may blunt their teeth and their most biting falsehood through the most invincible and solid truth.
If anyone is angry with me for saying these things, they will admit it is said about themselves, or another author will affirm it.
Therefore, whoever still presumptuously dares such things and similar matters, either fearing the truth not at all or very little, and boldly denies that the reprobates are predestined to eternal punishment, is the one who does not fear the same truth to say to him on the final day, in the hearing of all, "Behold, I now rightly deny, because you once unjustly denied me."
Such a person, I say, if they want to and dare to deny the truth, does not fear to offend it, which we equally need day and night.
But we, hearing the truth from it:
"The day of vengeance is in my heart" (Isaiah 63:4);
and: "Behold, our God will bring vengeance and retribution" (Isaiah 35:4):
let us crush this harmful falsehood and preach the truth, so that the same Truth, my God and the Son of God, may have mercy on us now and on the day of vengeance.
For if we truly fear the wrath of the deceitful, we may be able to please Him who rules and protects us, and defends us against the rage of the violent forever.
Amen.
Lord God (blessed and invincible Trinity and unity), I pray, instill faith in those reading these words, and grant strength to those who believe to confess.
To those who believe with their heart for righteousness, and confess with their mouth for salvation (Romans 10:10), bestow the abundance of copious rewards and the blessedness of eternal light with you.
Amen.