Prologue.
To the most beloved follower of Christ, deeply cherished by Him, the most blessed Mary Magdalene, known for her contemplative life, and her esteemed sister, Martha, a devoted servant of Christ, celebrated for her active life, along with their revered brother Lazarus, noted for his friendship with Christ and his resurrection.
The Catholic Church worldwide faithfully believes and honors these figures, not based on modern traditions, but according to the authentic testimonies of the four Gospels, proclaimed long ago as if from the very beginnings of our faith.
Therefore, this devotion, endorsed by such divine oracles, requires no human praise.
Whoever has ears to hear, let them hear what the Spirit says to the churches.
As written in the Gospel of Matthew, chapter nine, verse fifteen, and the Book of Revelation, chapter two, verse seventeen.
Through the words of the blessed John the Evangelist, we learn about the greatness of love, the abundance of familiarity, and the sweetness between the Son of the glorious Virgin and His friends, Martha, Mary, and their brother Lazarus.
As it is written: "I love those who love me," from the Book of Proverbs, chapter eight, verse seventeen.
The Lord Jesus loved Martha, her sister Mary, and Lazarus, as stated in the Gospel of John, chapter eleven, verse five.
This is the testimony borne by John, as noted in the Gospel of John, chapter one, verses nineteen to thirty-two.
The testimony given by the disciple whom Jesus loved above all others, as mentioned in John, chapter twenty-one, verse seven.
This is the testimony given by the apostle who reclined on the Lord's chest at the supper, as described in John, chapter thirteen, verse twenty-five, and chapter twenty-one, verse twenty.
This is the testimony borne by the evangelist to whom Christ entrusted His Virgin Mother from the cross.
Truly blessed and genuinely fortunate are those to whom such magnificent, illustrious, and clear testimony is given by the holy Gospel.
To illustrate this more clearly, I find it worthwhile to recount the various categories of the evangelists who agree on this matter, and then discuss, with truthful style, what our fathers have passed down in their writings about what happened to His friends after the Savior's ascension.
To make this clearer, let's take a step back and briefly revisit what the ancient histories say about their origins and lineage.
We'll also delve into their rise and education, along with their diligence and character, all to praise the Lord Savior and honor and glorify His friends.
CHAPTER 1 - The origins and family background of the Savior's friends, Mary, Lazarus, and Martha.
Near Jerusalem, on the Mount of Olives, about 15 furlongs from the holy city and facing the sunrise, you'll find Bethany.
This village is well-known among the evangelists as the home of Mary Magdalene, Lazarus, and Martha.
It holds great significance due to the physical presence of the Lord Savior, as noted in the Gospel of John, chapter 11, verse 1.
Bethany is famous for its hospitality, celebrated for its feasts, noted for miracles, remembered for tears, impressive in processions, distinguished by its relics, and remarkable for the Ascension.
From this village came the esteemed hostess and devoted servant of the Son of God, our Lord Jesus Christ, the most blessed Martha, as mentioned in the books of Matthew, chapters 21 and 26; Mark, chapters 11 and 14; Luke, chapters 19 and 24; and John, chapters 11 and 21.
Her noble mother, Eucharia, was descended from the illustrious royal lineage of the Israelites.
Her father, Theophilus, a Syrian by birth, also had a distinguished lineage and title, and was well-known for his noble administration.
Indeed, as a leading figure among the satraps of the province, which was highly regarded, he was celebrated as a leader and ruler of all of Syria and the entire coastal region.
Later, he became even more significant as a disciple of Christ, inspired by Christ's teachings to leave behind worldly burdens and humbly follow in His footsteps.
The sister of the blessed Martha, born of the same mother, was a remarkably beautiful woman named Mary, and their brother, known for his excellent character and youthful energy, was named Lazarus.
These three excelled in intelligence and diligence, acquiring a deep understanding of Hebrew literature in their childhood.
Their natural talents and commitment to the arts were matched by their integrity; each of them exhibited a remarkable beauty in appearance, charming manners, and delightful eloquence in speech.
They seemed to compete with each other in looks, manners, and grace, each striving to surpass the others in excellence.
CHAPTER 2: How Martha Managed the Estates as the Head of the Household; and About Mary's Nature
As I mentioned earlier, they were noble by birth and distinguished by their connections.
They inherited a significant amount of property, including estates, money, and servants, which encompassed a large part of the city of Jerusalem and three estates:
Bethany in Judea, as mentioned in the Book of John, Chapter Eleven, Verse Eighteen, about two miles from Jerusalem;
Magdala in Galilee, situated on the left side of the Sea of Galilee, two miles from Tiberias;
and Bethany beyond the Jordan, also in Galilee, where John was baptizing, as noted in the Book of John, Chapter One, Verse Twenty-eight, and Chapter Ten, Verse Forty.
Living together in harmony, they enjoyed abundance.
However, both the brother and sister wanted Martha, as the eldest, to oversee all the affairs and estates.
She did not misuse this responsibility arrogantly but handled it with a brave spirit and a generous heart.
Without a husband, she thrived in purity.
She was sweet and loving to her family, gentle and approachable to the poor, and, in general, compassionate and generous to everyone.
In short, she was a woman to be respected and admired by all, because she was noble by birth, wealthy, celebrated for her beauty, glorious in her purity, hospitable, generous, and gracious to everyone; this was Martha.
But Mary, when she reached marriageable age, shone with stunning physical beauty, exceedingly lovely, with graceful body lines, a charming face, wonderful hair, and an incredibly pleasant demeanor and gentle mind.
Her charming mouth and the grace of her lips, as mentioned in Proverbs, Chapter Twenty-two, Verse Eleven, were like the mixed color of roses and lilies' whiteness.
Her beauty and grace were so remarkable that she was said to be a unique and wonderful creation of God's craftsmanship.
CHAPTER 3.
How Mary Abused the Gifts of Nature and Hard Work
Because beauty often doesn't go hand in hand with chastity, and wealth can be an enemy to self-control, the young woman, surrounded by luxury, started to take pride in her noble spirit and was drawn to worldly pleasures, as is common at her age.
Her youthful vigor, attractive appearance, and wealth began to erode her good morals.
Her beautiful body, playful spirit, and wrongful indulgence started to invite love.
The pride in her lineage, the beauty of her face, and her ample resources began to shake the modesty of her heart.
The warmth of her age, the temptations of the flesh, and her weaker nature completely overturned her bodily chastity.
Alas, what a pity!
Her gold lost its luster, and her greatest virtues were overshadowed by her love for earthly things.
The purest aspects of her industriousness were altered by the lure of carnal desires.
Drawn by seductive impulses, she leaned toward all things illicit, turning everything God had given her for virtue into indulgences of a life of ease.
She misused the sweetness of her spirit to the peril of her soul, the beauty of her body to the disgrace of her heart, and the vitality of her youth to the destruction of her purity.
All her beauty vanished from the daughter of Zion, and all that divine generosity was wasted as she sinned against the Lord even more grievously because of how much she owed Him.
But why dwell on these things any longer?
The soul of the young woman wandered; she briefly dwelt in worldly love.
She abused the pleasures of the flesh and returned to a place of dissimilarity.
Having strayed far from God, the young woman quickly squandered the gifts of nature and hard work.
But as soon as she realized she was suddenly deprived of divine virtues, recalling how many precious things she had lost and from whom she had received so much, she quickly hurried back to His grace.
CHAPTER 4.
At this time, the Lord Savior, now a young man, performed miracles and healed sinners.
Indeed, the time of grace had arrived, and the virgin had given birth; Emmanuel had come down from the heavens to fulfill his work on earth.
Isaiah 28:21.
But his work was unfamiliar to him, as God was revealed, the healthy was wounded, and life itself died.
This is wisdom.
Whoever has understanding should divide into seven parts and even eight, so that injuries touch man, and miracles reveal the Lord.
Ecclesiastes 11:2.
By this time, Jesus, growing naturally, had reached his youthful years.
He had already been baptized by his forerunner and had fasted for 40 days, but afterward, he was hungry.
Matthew 3:16; 4:2.
Not in a shadowy, fantastical, or imaginary way, but truly, he bore our weaknesses.
Isaiah 53:4.
He had chosen many disciples from the province; by now, over 30 years old, he had turned water into wine.
From then on, with signs and miracles befitting the Son of God, he became renowned; diligently fulfilling his mission to heal the sick and save sinners.
For I have not come, he said, to call the righteous, but sinners.
Mark 2:17.
A doctor is not needed for those who are well, but for those who are sick.
Matthew 9:12.
For the Son of Man came to seek and to save what was lost.
Luke 19:10.
His fame spread throughout all of Syria, Galilee, and even to the seashore, Tyre, and Sidon.
Matthew 4:24.
One day, while preaching in Galilee about the kingdom of God, he compared the Jews to children playing, calling out: We played the flute for you, and you did not dance; we mourned to you, and you did not weep.
Matthew 11:17.
Soon after, he explained why he said this, remarking, John the Baptist came neither eating nor drinking, and they say, He has a demon; the Son of Man came eating and drinking, and they say: Look, a glutton and a wine drinker, a friend of tax collectors and sinners.
Luke 7:32, 33, 34.
Chapter 5 - How the News of Christ's Miracles Changed Mary's Mind
Then, behold, the Savior was invited to a meal by a certain Pharisee named Simon, as mentioned by our evangelist Luke 7:36.
I believe this man was a citizen of Magdala and closely connected to the blessed Martha through affection and kinship.
As He reclined in Simon's house with many gathered around, news of His arrival quickly spread throughout the city.
Word was that a holy, kind, gentle, modest, pious, and merciful man was present.
He was friendly to the humble, approachable to sinners, beloved by the repentant, a supporter of sobriety, and a lover of chastity.
Some even believed Him to be the Son of God and the Christ.
This news also reached the ears of Mary, the young woman I mentioned earlier, who was known as "Turrensian" because of her estate in Magdala, which means "Tower." As previously mentioned, she lost her modesty due to her exceptional beauty and influenced others with her appearance, youthful age, and wealth, leading a life that was contrary to good morals. Her numerous vices led people to say she was possessed by seven demons.
Upon hearing about the arrival of this compassionate prophet, she turned inward and reflected deeply on herself. She recalled all her past transgressions, both natural and acquired, from her childhood years. Lamentations 1:7. As she pondered this, Lamentations 3:21, she realized how far she was from God and from her true self, and she began to weep.
God, who sees all, moved her to deep repentance. Mark 14:72. He urged her to flee from impending judgment. Psalm 59:5. "Unless you are converted," He warns, "He has sharpened His sword, bent His bow, and prepared the instruments of death." Psalm 7:13-14.
Immediately, by the sudden and free impulse of the Holy Spirit, who breathes when and where He wills. John.
He breathes where He wills and how much He wills; He shows mercy to whom He wills and hardens whom He wills.
Romans 9:18
The inspired young woman speaks to herself:
"Know yourself, Mary," she says, "and remember what you were, what you are now, and what you will be.
Be ashamed that you have completely fallen into disgrace, and regret that you have misused yourself.
Grieve that you have lost your own purity, and lament that you have been a scandal to those around you.
Mourn that you have ignored the Lord for so long, and be ashamed that you have responded poorly to God's best gifts.
Do not do this carelessly or only occasionally, because life is short and death is certain, but the time of death is uncertain.
Health is deceitful, and beauty is vain.
A woman who fears the Lord will be praised, and her works will praise her on the day of her death.
Proverbs 31:30
Therefore, Mary, fear eternal destruction; look to the supreme judge; anticipate the Lord as accuser; detest your former life and hasten to improve.
Thus, through wisdom, the hawk takes flight, spreading its wings to the south.
Job 39:26
Chapter 6-Where Mary takes the alabaster and visits Simon's house.
Mary quickly rose and took a vessel made of Indian alabaster, a type of white marble with various colored streaks, filling it with a precious and wonderfully fragrant ointment.
She deemed it worthy and honorable enough to be used on the feet of the prophet she planned to visit, who was rumored to be the Son of God and whom she had already begun to love deeply.
Mary had an abundance of spices, perfumes, balsam, and all kinds of fragrant liquids.
Since childhood, she used these sweet-smelling things to enhance her body's fragrance.
Carrying the fragrant vessel in her hands, because it is written not to appear empty-handed before the Lord, as mentioned in Exodus twenty-three fifteen and elsewhere, and bringing an even more valuable gift-a heart full of faith and hope for forgiveness-she wept bitterly, her heart crying out to God:
"Woe is me," she said, "for I have miserably wasted the years of my youth.
Look, Lord, and see how worthless I have become," a sentiment echoed in Lamentations one eleven.
"My God, let my past wrongs be enough for me.
I renounce the temptations of the heart and flesh and worldly vanities; I detest wandering any longer, and I promise to change from now on."
Repeating these words to herself with a voice full of heart and conscience, she went to the feast where she knew the Son of God was reclining at the table.
This did not escape the notice of the One she approached, from whom no secret is hidden; indeed, with the sevenfold Spirit, He anticipated her coming, welcoming her with blessings of sweetness, as stated in Psalms twenty-one four, and drew her to Himself as she hastened.
Immediately, the seven demons were disturbed, forever banished, expelled, and removed from her heart and body, while the sevenfold Spirit filled her with good gifts.
Enriched by these, through faith she conceived good hope and gave birth to the most fervent love, for the outward sign of the sweet-smelling alabaster was a reflection of her inner burning sacrifice of repentance.
With a heavy conscience and a deep repentance for his past life, he was filled with a sincere devotion to God, strengthened by the hope of forgiveness.
He then arrived at the Savior's banquet.
CHAPTER 7 - How Mary did something unheard of throughout the ages at the feet of Christ, and why Christ defended her against the Pharisee.
Mary entered the banquet, looked around, and saw the Son of the Virgin Mary reclining at a distance.
Without hesitation, she prostrated herself, worshiped Him, and then approached the couch where the Savior lay.
Standing confidently behind the Messiah, she regretted having strayed from His path and began to wet His feet with her tears, shed from eyes that once desired earthly things.
She wiped His feet with her hair, which she had previously used to adorn herself.
She had misused her mouth for pride and lust, but now she kissed His feet and anointed them with the perfume she brought, feeling remorse for having used it for her own vanity.
The Pharisee who had invited the Lord to the meal was indignant and envious, showing no compassion for Mary, forgetting his own weaknesses.
He criticized both her, who came seeking salvation, and the Savior, who came to help.
He murmured to himself, "Is this man really a Jew? Truly, if He were a prophet, He would know the past, present, and future, and certainly would know what kind of woman this is, whose service He accepts gratefully, without disdain."
Responding to the Pharisee's thoughts, God, the discerner of thoughts and examiner of intentions, said: "Simon, I have something to say to you." The Pharisee, smoothing his brow out of habit, spoke with a heart full of pretense, as if he had murmured nothing, and replied plainly, "Teacher, say it." And the Lord said:
"Two people were in debt to a certain moneylender. One owed 500 denarii, the other 50. When they could not pay, he forgave both. Which of them loves him more?" To this, Simon, like a madman weaving a rope to entangle himself, not realizing the parable was about him, which could not be expressed more succinctly or clearly, said, "I suppose the one who was forgiven more."
The Lord said to him, "You have judged correctly." Then, turning away from the table and towards Mary, in whom he found more joy than at the meal, he showed her his lovely face and kindly looked at her with his most serene eyes. However, before speaking to her, he stood up to defend her against the Pharisee. Looking at her but speaking to him, he said, "Do you see this woman?" Then, recalling the acts of washing, wiping, anointing, and kissing, he gratefully accepted them all while openly rebuking Simon for failing to do the same, addressing each act specifically: "I entered your house because you invited me, yet you did not provide water for my feet-a common courtesy for guests. But she, with an unheard-of service, washed my feet with her own tears and wiped them with her hair, which is more precious than any towel. You did not give me a kiss-a sign of affection-but from the moment she entered, she has not stopped kissing my feet. You did not anoint my head with oil, which would be a sign of devotion; but she, with not just simple oil but with perfumed balm, anointed my feet. Therefore, I tell you, her many sins have been forgiven, and rightly so, because she has shown great love. But whoever is forgiven little, loves little; although one should not love the Lord any less, who is kept from sinning by God."
CHAPTER 8 - Where Christ forgives Mary's sins and dismisses her in peace.
After saying this, the Savior realized He had brought Mary immense joy and happiness.
Psalm 50:9.
She heard her acts of service to Christ being acknowledged and appreciated.
She felt even greater joy knowing that her gifts of devotion were valued more than Simon's meal.
But her greatest joy came from understanding that the sparks of her love were recognized by God and that her sins were being considered for forgiveness.
Comforting her with incredible cheerfulness and indescribable sweetness, as she wept and continued to kiss His feet tirelessly, He said to her:
"Your sins are forgiven."
For the passion of your love has erased the tarnish of all your sins.
Hearing this, those dining with them were scandalized and began to say to themselves, "Who is this who even forgives sins?"
For this is the work of God alone.
However, the Savior left those pondering such things to themselves and turned to Mary, saying:
"Your faith, with which you believed you would receive what you sought diligently, has saved you; go in peace."
Strengthened by this most blessed oracle, Mary worshiped the Savior and, filled with indescribable joy, left the gathering and went to her own place, carrying the sevenfold Spirit in her heart.
The flow of her tears was not stopped, but diminished.
For what had been tears of bitterness from punishment became tears of joy from received pardon.
Then the river's flow made Mary's mind glad, the city of God, then the Most High sanctified His dwelling within her.
Psalm 46:5.
From then on, there was neither a vice of the mind nor of the body in her.
From then on, she was chaste as none more chaste!
From then on, she overcame nature, and even nature itself yielded to her.
From then on, she so eliminated her faults that every part of her was good, with no part of evil.
Such is Mary, whom it is good to know and worthy to speak of.
This is the only praise I offer her, yet I confess I am unable to speak of her worthily.
CHAPTER 9 - Where Mary, along with her female companions, gladly and diligently served.
After this, as the Lord Savior traveled through cities and villages with the twelve apostles, he preached about the kingdom of God, and noble women followed him.
Among them was the leader, a special friend of the Lord Savior, Mary Magdalene, along with Joanna, Susanna, and many others who supported the Lord and the apostles with their resources, responding with great affection and diligent devotion, as they had received benefits from him.
He had healed them from evil spirits and illnesses.
For the daughter of Jairus, a leader, who was twelve years old, he said, Talitha cumi, and raised her from the dead.
He also commanded that she be given something to eat.
Accepting the faith of the Syrophoenician woman, he cleansed her daughter from a demon.
He cured the woman with the issue of blood by the touch of his garment's hem and highly praised her faith.
She was a citizen of Caesarea Philippi and was called Martha.
Her house is still visible there; in front of it stands a pedestal, prominently placed, with a bronze image of the woman, depicted as if kneeling and stretching out her palms in supplication.
Next to her is another bronze statue of a man, dressed in a robe, offering his right hand to the woman.
At the feet of this statue grows a certain herb, of a unique kind, which grows up to the hem of the bronze garment.
When the herb reaches the top of the hem, it gains the power to heal all diseases and ailments; so that, with just a small sip of the soaked healing herb, they are driven away.
It holds no power at all if it is picked before it grows to the top of the bronze hem.
They say this statue is made in the likeness of the face of the Lord Jesus Christ.
It's not surprising that such a woman, having received benefits from the Savior, would strive to offer this as a memorial gift.
This is still observed by Christians today, albeit from a pagan custom, and they honor those whom they consider worthy of honor in this way.
The symbols of the ancients are preserved as a sign of honor for them and love for those who come after us.
Eusebius, Church History, translated by Rufinus.
Chapter 10: In this chapter, Christ is welcomed by Martha into her home, and he defends Mary for prioritizing spiritual matters.
Around this time, the Savior was transfigured in Galilee on Mount Tabor.
As the days of his journey were drawing to a close, he set his sights firmly on Jerusalem, determined to go to the place where he had chosen to suffer, with unwavering resolve.
On his way, he entered a certain village, specifically Magdala, known for being the home of Mary Magdalene.
There, Martha welcomed him into her home and wholeheartedly prepared a lavish meal and offered hospitality.
Accompanying the Lord were twelve apostles, seventy-two disciples, and a large group of noble women.
While Martha was busy managing the household tasks that needed attention, her very holy sister chose to sit at the Savior's feet, listening to his words rather than assisting with the serving duties.
Martha then approached the Savior and said, "Lord, don't you care that my sister has left me to serve alone? Tell her to help me."
Upon hearing this, Mary did not respond to her complaining sister, leaving her defense to the Savior, who was already enjoying her contemplative presence. "In the shadow of him whom I desire, I sit, and the fruit of his mouth is sweet to my taste," as it says in the Song of Solomon.
Recalling these things in my heart, I will have hope, as mentioned in Lamentations.
The Savior replied, "Martha, Martha, you are anxious." The repetition of her name shows his love. He loved her greatly for her charitable actions, just as he loved Mary for her devotion to contemplation.
"You are anxious," he said, "about household tasks and are troubled by many things, necessary for the sick and afflicted. However, above all, one thing is necessary: to remain constantly close to God. This is the best part. This your sister, Mary, has chosen, and it will not be taken away from her; her contemplation, love, and desire have already begun faithfully here and will never fade; indeed, they will be perfected in heaven."
He spoke and then sat down with the twelve apostles, the seventy disciples, and the devout women.
Martha, ever generous, was busy serving the tables, as she always did.
Marcella, the steward of her household and an exceptional woman, was there, along with Susanna and Joanna, whose husband managed the kingdom of Antipas, the tetrarch of Galilee.
CHAPTER 11.
---Where the Queen of Heaven appears, and the blessed Marcella blessed the womb and breasts of the Virgin Mother.
From then on, the Savior frequently traveled through the cities and fields of Galilee, often returning to Magdala.
He stayed with his joyful company at the home of Martha and Mary, and the sisters served him diligently and generously, providing all necessities from their own resources.
Whenever they stayed at home, as domestic duties required, and the Lord was preaching far away, they sent someone to deliver to the Savior and his companions whatever they knew would be useful.
These were also given to one of the twelve, Judas Iscariot, who had the Lord's money bag and carried what was sent.
(John twelve, verse six), secretly stealing from it.
One day, after the Savior healed a demon-possessed man who was blind and mute,
(Matthew twelve, verse twenty-two), the crowds gathered, marveling and praising God.
But the Pharisees were blaspheming, accusing him of doing this by Beelzebub.
The Savior, however, confidently claimed that he cast out demons by the finger of God.
Then the Queen of Heaven, together with her sisters and relatives, came to see and speak with the Son of God, the Savior.
Unable to reach him due to the crowd, someone at the door rose and said to the Savior, not by accident or simply, but insidiously, testing whether he would prioritize flesh and blood over spiritual work:
"Look," he said, "your mother and your brothers are standing outside, seeking you."
(Matthew twelve, verse forty-six).
Hearing this, the Savior remained seated, pretending not to recognize his mother, not to deny her, but to respond to the one testing him:
"Who is my mother, and who are my brothers?"
And stretching out his hand toward his disciples, he said, "Look, my mother and my brothers, through special anointing; for whoever, in either gender, does the will of my Father in heaven, is my brother and sister and mother."
For whoever preaches me to the heart of the listener gives birth to me; she becomes my mother, through whose voice my love is generated in others.
At these words, the multitude of believing men and women rejoiced.
Among the devout women present with the Savior was Marcella, whom we mentioned earlier.
She was the caretaker and companion of the blessed Martha, a woman of great devotion and faith.
With remarkable sincerity, she believed in the Incarnation of the Savior and bravely stood against the accusations of the rulers and Pharisees who approached.
Raising her voice from the crowd, she said to the Savior:
"Blessed is the womb that carried you, giving you flesh to grow, and blessed are the breasts that nursed you, providing milk to nurture you."
The Savior replied:
"Not only is the mother who gave birth to me, the Word of God, blessed for nourishing me with her milk, but indeed blessed are those who hear, receive, and conceive the Word of God in the womb of their mind."
(Luke 11:27-28).
They rejoice in the same gift of grace mentioned, and through faith, they nurture the seed of the Word with the sustenance of hope and love, and they protect it.
"
Chapter 12 - Where Christ Liberates the Sinner
On the fourth day of the Feast of Tabernacles, Jesus went up to the temple to teach.
When evening came, he left with his disciples and went to the Mount of Olives, to Bethany, the village of Mary and Martha, where his friend Lazarus lived and where he stayed.
Because they had earned his friendship, they often hosted him, both in Magdala, a town in Galilee, and in Bethany beyond the Jordan, as well as in Bethany near Jerusalem.
Truly blessed and happy are those who were worthy to host such a guest, feeding on the bread of angels, by whom they were also fed!
On the eighth day of the Feast of Tabernacles, the Savior came down from Bethany early in the morning to the temple.
All the people gathered around him, and he sat down to teach them.
Here, we'll briefly recount how mercifully and wisely he saved a certain sinful woman from the danger of death, even if it seems we are going a bit far.
The Savior was very pleasing to the people because he advocated mercy and compassion.
But the Pharisees always plotted against him and were envious because he welcomed sinners.
Seeking to catch him in something he might say that could be criticized or condemned, they brought to him a woman caught in adultery, thinking, "Let's test him on justice to see if he speaks against it, as he preaches mercy."
If he says the adulteress should be stoned, the people will scorn his teaching, against which he will have given his judgment.
If he says she should be released, we will shout: Enemy of the law, contrary to Moses, enemy of God, guilty of death, and should be stoned with the adulteress."
Approaching him, they said, "Teacher, this woman was just caught in adultery. In the law, Moses commanded us to stone such women; what do you say?"
To this, the wisdom of God, God himself, did not immediately judge nor respond; instead, as he sat with a stern face, he leaned down and wrote in the ground with his finger the sins of those who accused the sinner.
For he himself had no sins of his own to write.
The Savior provided us with a valuable example here: when we hear about someone's wrongdoings, we shouldn't rush to judge immediately.
Instead, we should first examine ourselves with a discerning eye to see if we've committed similar or worse actions, or if we might be capable of doing so.
Meanwhile, the Pharisees were pressing for his judgment, already anticipating and mocking, thinking he couldn't escape: believing he would have to choose between justice or mercy.
But there is no wisdom, no understanding, no advice against the Lord.
Proverbs 21:30.
So Christ stood up to give his judgment, teaching that those who wish to condemn the guilty must be upright themselves.
He stood up and, with mercy intact, judged with justice: "Let the one among you who is without sin be the first to throw a stone at her."
After wisely delivering this judgment, he bent down again and wrote on the ground, turning away so the Pharisees could leave; he knew they would rather leave than ask more questions.
By bending down and writing again after giving the judgment, he also teaches us to humbly examine our conscience with fear not only before we judge but even after, to avoid deserving a harsher sentence. They left, enveloped in confusion like a cloak; thus, mercy and misery stood alone. Psalm 109:29.
Finally, the Savior stood up to offer a merciful judgment, having first given a just one: "Woman," he asked, "where are your accusers? Did I perhaps drive them away? Has no one condemned you?"
She replied, "No one, Lord; for none of them is without sin, but you, who are without sin, if you wish, you can condemn me."
To which the Savior said: "No one? Neither do I condemn you for the past; go, be careful in the future, and do not sin anymore."
Chapter 13 - Where Lazarus is sick and dies; and Christ is summoned.
In the middle of winter, on the fifteenth day of the month of Kislev, the Feast of Dedication took place in Jerusalem.
The Savior was walking in the temple on Solomon's porch, where He was preaching and saying, "I and the Father are one." The Jews picked up stones to stone Him.
John 10:22, 30.
But He escaped from their hands and went again across the Jordan to Bethany in Galilee, the village of Mary and Martha, where John the Baptist had first baptized; and He stayed there.
Meanwhile, His friend Lazarus was sick in Bethany of Judea, the village of his sisters Mary and Martha.
So his sisters sent a message across the Jordan to the Savior in Bethany, saying, "The one you love is sick."
John 11:1, 2.
They believed it was enough to inform the beloved of the illness of his friend: our friend is Lazarus, whom He loves, and He will not easily abandon the one He loves dearly.
Upon hearing this, the Savior said, "This sickness is for a miracle, not for death, but for the glory of God, so that the Son of God may be glorified through it."
Jesus loved Martha, her sister Mary, and Lazarus.
He was sick, they were sad, all were beloved; but by whom were they loved?
Jesus loved them, the Savior of the sick, indeed even the raiser of the dead, and the consoler of the sorrowful.
O fortunate and glorious generation!
Although the Truth says, "I love those who love me," it is rare to find in the Scriptures those faithful ones who are specifically named as beloved by the Lord.
So when the Savior heard that Lazarus was sick, He delayed going; He delayed helping, so that He might bring him back from death.
And then He stayed where He was in Bethany of Galilee for two days, so that the four days might be completed.
Meanwhile, a terrible fever was consuming Lazarus's body.
The doctors could do nothing, the medicines were of no use; thus, there was no remedy for the sick one, unless the Lord willed to heal him.
His sisters sat by the young man's bed, promising the arrival of Jesus, assuring the man struggling for breath of health.
Finally, as the heat from the chest dries up due to the fever's power, the vital spirit evaporates.
The young man is mourned by the holy sisters, who tear their clothes and embrace his lifeless body.
You could see their cheeks wet with blood, their eyes darkened with tears, and the air filled with cries of mourning.
After the funeral rites are performed, the body is carried out in a grand procession.
Lazarus is laid to rest in a marble tomb, and tears wet the stone that seals it.
Because he was of noble lineage, and even more noble in character-innocent in actions, wise in words, generous with his hand, and liberal in spirit-the more noble people of Jerusalem came to Bethany to console him and also attended his funeral.
Chapter 14: Where the Lord reproaches his fearful apostles, discusses the devotion of Thomas, and approves the faith of Martha.
After two days, the Savior said to his twelve disciples, "Let's go to Judea again" John 11:7.
The frightened apostles advised the Lord not to go, fearing that he who came to die would die, and that they themselves might die too.
They said, "Rabbi, the Jews just tried to stone you, and you're going there again?"
Jesus replied, "Are there not twelve hours in a day? If anyone walks at night, they stumble because there is no light in them; but if they walk during the day, they do not stumble because they see the light of this world.
I am the day, I am the light of the world; you are the twelve hours: it is my role to lead; yours to follow, as hours follow the day.
So let me suffer; do not give me advice, but follow me, if you do not want to stumble."
After saying this, he told them, "Lazarus, our friend, is asleep, but I am going to wake him up."
The disciples responded, based on their understanding, "Lord, if he is asleep, he will be saved; for sleep is usually a sign of recovery for the sick."
However, Jesus had spoken of his death, but they thought he was talking about sleeping.
Then Jesus said to them plainly, "Lazarus is dead; and I am glad for your sake, so that you may believe that nothing is hidden from me: because I was not there, and yet I know he is dead; but let us go to him."
Then Thomas said to his fellow disciples, "Let's go too, so that we may die with him."
Behold the true affection of lovers, either to live with him or to die with him.
Christ came and found that he had been in the tomb for four days already.
Bethany was near Jerusalem, about fifteen stadia away, roughly two miles, a stadium less: many of the Jews had come to Mary and Martha to comfort them about their brother.
So when Martha heard that Jesus was coming, she went to meet him.
But Mary stayed at home.
Martha said to Jesus, "Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died.
But even now, I know that whatever you ask from God, God will give you.
I believe you can raise him if you wish, but I leave that decision to you, Lord.
I don't ask you to raise him because I don't presume to know if his resurrection would be beneficial."
Jesus replied, "Your brother will rise again."
Martha said to Him, "I know he will rise in the general resurrection on the last day."
Jesus told her, "I am the resurrection and the life.
Because I am life, he will rise through me; he will rise then through me if I wish, and even now.
Whoever believes in me, even if they die physically, will live, just as Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, whose God I am, live as those who are alive.
Believing in me, even dead, they live; not believing in me, even alive, they are dead.
And everyone who lives in the flesh and believes in me, even if they die physically for a time, will not die forever, because they will live in the soul for now, until they rise again in the body."
After saying this, He asked, "Do you believe this?"
Knowing Martha's faith, He sought her confession; for with the heart one believes unto righteousness, and with the mouth, confession is made unto salvation.
She said to Him, "Yes, Lord, I have believed that you are the Christ, the Son of the living God, who came into this world for the salvation of the world."
CHAPTER 15 - When the Savior saw Mary weeping, he also wept.
After these words, Martha went quietly to her sister and said, "The Teacher is here and is calling for you."
This shows that the Lord called Mary, though John didn't detail when or how he called her due to the narration's brevity.
So, upon hearing that the Lord was asking for her, Mary quickly got up and went to him.
Jesus hadn't yet arrived in the village but was still at the place where Martha had met him.
The Jews who were with her in the house, comforting her, saw Mary rise quickly and leave.
They assumed she was hurrying to the tomb to mourn, so they followed her, saying, "She is going to the tomb to weep there."
When Mary reached the place where Jesus was and saw him, she fell at his feet and said, "Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died, for in your presence, no illness ever dared to appear, as life usually resides with you."
Seeing Mary weeping, Jesus was deeply moved in spirit and troubled himself, as he chose to be troubled when he wanted to, a state no one else could impose on him.
Even today, when a sinner reflects on the good received from God and the wrongs returned to Him in exchange, their spirit is stirred and they feel remorse.
Faith stirs in a person when they rebuke themselves for their sins: Christ stirs in them, Christ is troubled, for faith in Christ, Christ is in the heart.
Jesus asked, "Where have you laid him?" They replied, "Lord, come and see." And Jesus wept.
Oh, the depth of compassion! Oh, the sign of great love! Oh, the indication of an indescribable closeness!
Who could possibly estimate that mutual love, burning between the Lord Savior and his friend Mary at that moment, a sign we recognize in that sweet burning of tears!
I truly believe that love is incomprehensible to all human, and even angelic, creatures.
And Jesus wept. Oh, tears worthy of reverence, not to be mentioned without tears!
Tears flowed from the purest eyes of the Son of God, dripped from his beautiful eyes, and touched his serene face.
When he saw Mary crying, he groaned in spirit and was troubled.
And Jesus wept.
For Jesus loved Martha, her sister Mary, and Lazarus.
The Jews remarked, "See how he loved him."
But some of them asked, "Couldn't he, who opened the eyes of the man born blind, have prevented this man from dying?"
He could have, but he chose not to; because raising the dead is greater than healing the sick.
Chapter 16: Where Christ prays and raises Lazarus.
Jesus, deeply moved again, came to the tomb.
If you're burdened by the habit of sinning, let yourself be moved too, if you wish to come back to life.
It was a cave with a stone placed over it.
Jesus said, "Take away the stone."
Martha replied, "Lord, by now he smells; he's been dead for four days."
Jesus said to her, "Didn't I tell you that if you believe, you will see the glory of God?"
And what is the glory of God?
Where sin increased, grace increased all the more.
Romans Chapter 5, verse 20:
"And that she loves more to whom more is forgiven."
Luke Chapter 7.
So they took away the stone.
Jesus looked up and said, "Father, I thank you for hearing me."
"I knew that you always hear me; but I said this for the benefit of the people standing here, that they may believe that you sent me."
After saying this, he called out in a loud voice.
He called out loudly because it's hard for someone weighed down by bad habits to rise.
And in Zechariah Chapter 5, verse 7: "Wickedness sits on a lead talent."
Therefore, he called out in a loud voice, he was moved, he was troubled, and he wept.
And he said, "Lazarus, come out."
And immediately, the one who had been dead came out, his hands and feet bound with strips of cloth, and his face wrapped with a cloth.
Similarly, a sinner is bound in inner darkness by the hardening of the mind; and in the outer darkness, there will be the deserved future damnation.
But Christ first freed him from the bond of death on his own; then he immediately commanded the apostles to set him free from the outside.
And he said to them, "Unbind him and let him go" (John 11:44).
For I have said, "You are gods" (Psalm 82:6); and you shall not speak ill of gods, and a servant who wishes to be free shall be brought to the gods (Exodus 22:28; 21:6).
Therefore, those who attribute the forgiveness of sins solely to God, denying human participation in it, are mistaken.
They go against God's command by detracting from the gods, taking away the power given to them by God.
Only God is good; only God works wonders; only God forgives sins.
Matthew Chapter 19, verse 17; Psalm Chapter 72, verse 18.
Without God, no one is good. Without God, no one can perform miracles.
Without God, no one can forgive sins.
No one is good except God alone; no one can do miracles except God alone; no one can forgive sins except God alone.
Therefore, it's incorrect to say about the righteous Joseph: A good and just man.
Luke Chapter 23, Verse 50.
Or about the blessed man: He performed miracles in his life.
Ecclesiasticus Chapter 31, Verse 9.
Or about Christ, who says: Whose sins you forgive, they are forgiven them.
John Chapter 20, Verse 23.
No.
Instead, it's God himself acting through man; indeed, it's much better and truer that man acts through God.
For God did not tell Peter: What is already bound in heaven, you will bind on earth afterward, but the opposite.
Matthew Chapter 16, Verse 19.
Therefore, Peter's judgment follows the judgment of heaven.
Thus, when the Lord gives a man the power to forgive sins, it means God himself forgives sins through the man.
If a person truly repents of their sins but can't reach confession, I confidently declare that the high priest completes with them what the mortal could not; and with the Lord, it's considered done what the person truly wished for but couldn't fulfill: provided that it wasn't contempt that excluded confession, but necessity that prevented it.
Chapter 17: Martha is serving dinner, Lazarus is reclining, and Mary is anointing Jesus' feet.
Many of the Jews who came to Mary and saw what Jesus did began to believe in him.
However, some of them went to the Pharisees and reported what Jesus had done.
So the chief priests and the Pharisees gathered for a council, where Caiaphas, the high priest, prophesied that Jesus would die for the Jewish people.
From that day on, and likely before, they planned to kill him.
Jesus, however, no longer walked openly among the Jews.
Instead, he went to a region near the wilderness, to a town called Ephraim, and stayed there with his disciples.
The Jewish festival of Passover was approaching.
The chief priests had ordered that if anyone knew where Jesus was, they should report it so he could be arrested.
(John chapter eleven, verses forty-five through fifty-six).
But Jesus, aware of their plot against him, returned to Bethany, near Jerusalem, like a lamb to the slaughter, six days before Passover, on the following Friday, to be sacrificed, crucified at the sixth hour; he who created all things in six days, formed man on the sixth day, and came in the sixth age to redeem man.
It was then the solemn day of the Sabbath, and they held a dinner for him there, in the house of Simon the leper.
(John chapter twelve, verse two; Matthew chapter twenty-six, verse six).
Simon, whom he had already cleansed from leprosy, was there.
So Jesus reclined, along with the twelve apostles and many who had gathered.
Lazarus was one of those reclining with him.
(John chapter twelve, verse two).
This was to prove that he was not a ghost, but truly alive.
And the blessed Martha, as usual, served the table with a generous hand, a cheerful face, and a generous spirit; while Mary Magdalene, foremost among Christ's servants, driven by great zeal and the ardor of Christ's love, which did not allow her to rest, took a pound of expensive ointment and, approaching the Savior with utmost reverence, anointed his feet as he reclined.
(John chapter twelve, verse three; Matthew chapter twenty-six, verse seven).
The ointment was genuine and pure, not mixed with other herbs or roots, unlike the usual practice of perfumers who often trick both the sense of smell and sight.
It was made from nard, a fragrant shrub that smells like a garden or cyperus.
Nard has a heavy and thick root, which is fragile but oily, with a rough taste, and small, dense leaves.
The ointment was also enhanced with spikes, as the tops of the nard spread into spikes, and perfumers value both the spikes and the leaves.
Indeed, the ointment from Christ's perfumer, Mary, wasn't made from the root of nard alone.
To make it even more precious, its fragrance and strength were boosted by adding the spikes and leaves.
Nard is essential in making ointments: thus, it was a precious ointment, Indian and more valuable than any other, worthy to be applied to the feet and head of the Lord, as testified by three evangelists: Matthew, Mark, and John.
Matthew 26; Mark 14:3; John 12:3.
Finally, after anointing the Savior's feet with the precious nard, she rubbed them all over with her hands and fingers, massaging them.
Then, she gently wrapped them with her hair, which was beautifully shiny.
Applying them to her chest and face, she wiped them sweetly; finally, embracing them, she cherished them for a long time before letting them go.
CHAPTER 18 - Where Mary anoints Christ's head, Judas grumbles, and Christ praises.
The act of anointing by Mary, one of the Savior's closest followers, seems small compared to what comes next.
After anointing his feet, her heart, ignited by the immense love he inspired in her, led her to serve him with deep trust and confidence in God.
She often participated in such matters, I'm sure.
Worshiping the Savior, she approached his sacred head with reverence, a head adored by angels, archangels, principalities, and powers.
Running her fingers through the hair of the Almighty, she broke an alabaster jar and poured the remaining nard over the head of the Son of God.
Then, gently rubbing her hands through his hair, she anointed his curls with drops of nard, spreading the sacred liquid from his forehead to his temples and around his neck with the grace of a noble perfumer.
In this way, Mary completed her acts of pious devotion, fulfilling what King Solomon once sang in the Songs of Love: "While the king was at his table, my nard gave forth its fragrance." The fragrance of Mary's hair, hands, and lips was remarkable from contact with Christ's feet, whose scent of ointments surpasses all spices! The house was filled with the aroma of the ointment, and the world with the fame of her deed.
The grace of the Holy Spirit was abundant in Mary's mind, given to her from above by the Father of lights, allowing her to enjoy such intimacy with the Son of God. Her devotion to Almighty God's Son was pleasing, her love sweet, her service acceptable, as the evangelists testify: Judas Iscariot was indignant, sensing the sweet lingering scent on the Lord Savior's feet and head, and with a traitor's mind and voice, he exclaimed: "Why this waste? This ointment could have been sold for a large amount and given to the poor."
He was furious with Mary, fulfilling what David said:
"The sinner will see and be angry; he will gnash his teeth and waste away" Psalm 37:12.
He was consumed by the midday demon, like a pestilence in darkness
Psalm 91:6, hiding his greed behind a show of concern for the poor.
He said this not out of care for the poor, but because he was a thief, in charge of the Lord's money bag,
taking what was meant for the Savior and secretly stealing it.
The Lord no longer wanted to endure the traitor's complaints. Instead of calling out his greed,
he praised the woman who loved him, even his perfumer, hinting at his impending death:
"Leave her alone," he said, "so that she may keep it for the day of my burial,"
subtly indicating he knew Mary would soon come with spices to anoint his body.
Although she didn't complete this in action, she did so in devotion:
what you desire and cannot do, God counts as done.
Everyone at the feast was amazed, focusing on Mary, admiring her closeness and presence,
taking in the fragrance of the nard and recognizing her love and devotion.
Some, persuaded by Judas's words, not with his intent, but with simple hearts caring for the poor,
were angry with her, saying
(Matthew 26:8; Mark 14:4; John 12:5):
"Why wasn't this perfume sold for 300 denarii and given to the poor?"
To this, the Savior immediately responded:
"Leave her alone, why are you bothering her? She has done a good deed for me:
you will always have the poor with you, and you can do good for them whenever you want,
but you will not always have me. She did what she could; she anointed my body beforehand for burial:
she has prepared me for burial; by pouring this perfume on my body, she has anticipated the service of my burial.
Truly, I tell you: wherever this gospel is preached throughout the world,
what Mary has done will also be told, in memory of her"
(Mark 14:6-9; Matthew 26:12-13).
CHAPTER 19 - When the crowd met Christ, Christ wept, was hungry, and why He returned to Bethany daily.
A large crowd of Jews found out that Jesus was in Bethany.
Driven by curiosity rather than love, they came not for Jesus, but to see Lazarus, whom Jesus had raised from the dead.
The chief priests even plotted to kill Lazarus because many Jews were leaving them to believe in Jesus because of him as if He who raised someone dead for four days couldn't raise someone who had been killed.
The next day, the Savior, riding on a donkey, with palm branches and praises from the people, descended from the Mount of Olives.
Seeing the city, He wept over it.
Entering the city, He went to the temple, drove out the money changers and merchants, healed the blind and the lame, and debated with the chief priests.
After shedding many tears for the doomed city, a symbol of a perishing soul, after hearing the shouts of praise, Hosanna to the Son of David, after processions with cloaks, flowers, and branches laid on the road, after performing many miracles, and after everyone saw the divine brilliance on His face, which scared away the merchants, and after long discussions and teachings, He found nowhere to rest His head despite the many gathered for the festival.
Looking around to see if anyone would invite Him to stay as evening approached, He was in such poverty and never sought to flatter anyone, that in such a large city, He had no place to stay.
He left for the Mount of Olives with the twelve apostles, so that what He lacked in Jerusalem, He could find in Bethany, lodging with blessed Lazarus and his sisters.
The next day, as He went out, He was hungry because He chose to be; seeing a fig tree by the road, He went to see if it had any fruit.
Finding nothing but leaves, He cursed it, saying, "May no fruit ever come from you again." And He spent the whole day teaching in the temple.
As evening came, he went back to Bethany to be with Martha and Mary.
The next morning, Tuesday, he returned to the city with the apostles.
They saw that the fig tree he had cursed had withered.
The Savior used this as an example to teach the apostles about praying with confidence, assuring them that they could achieve whatever they ask for, even if it seems as impossible as moving mountains.
When evening arrived, he left the city and returned to his usual lodging.
On Wednesday, at dawn, he went back to the temple and spoke extensively to his apostles about the end of the world.
Meanwhile, Judas Iscariot promised the chief priests to betray Jesus to them.
The Lord Jesus concluded the day's teachings by telling his disciples: You know that in two days, the Passover of the symbolic lamb will take place, and then the true Lamb, the Son of Man, will be handed over to be crucified on the third day.
Mark Chapter 13, Matthew Chapter 24, John Chapter 14, verse 10, and Matthew Chapter 26, verses 1 to 2.
He said this; and when evening returned, he left the temple and went back to Bethany, intending to spend his last moments with his friends and servants, Lazarus, Mary, and Martha, like a young deer, Song of Solomon Chapter 2, verse 9, which returns to its resting place in the evening after wandering during the day.
Thus, the Savior, preparing to suffer and ascend, returned to the house of obedience in Bethany, showing that he values obedience above all from his friends.
CHAPTER 20.
Where Christ, after having dined, is betrayed and led away in chains: the apostles flee, and Peter denies while Mary clings to Christ.
On the first day of unleavened bread, as stated in Matthew 26:17, he said farewell to his beloved hosts, Lazarus, Mary, and Martha, for the last time.
When evening came, he dined in Jerusalem with his twelve disciples.
This dinner was renowned as a blessed meal, during which he washed his apostles' feet and transformed bread and wine into his body and blood.
This was followed immediately by the betrayal and suffering of the Savior.
He was betrayed with a kiss by one of his apostles in the garden across the brook Kidron, to the cohort and servants of the chief priests, who brought lanterns, torches, and weapons.
When he was led away in chains, all his disciples abandoned him and fled, as mentioned in Matthew 26:56.
However, Mary Magdalene's devotion did not waver.
Then, as described in Job 19:20, her bones clung to her skin, because while Judas betrayed, Peter denied, and the ten apostles fled, Mary Magdalene, beside him, always found the strength of the Redeemer.
Who can express the sorrow of her heart and the bitterness of her mind?
Her heart burned as she watched her beloved being betrayed with a kiss, bound in chains, and taken to the palace of the high priest Annas.
There he was accused, questioned, judged, declared guilty of death, spat upon, slapped, blindfolded, struck, and blasphemed.
Who can recount Mary's lamentations and the tears with which she followed her beloved from the high priest's house to the governor Pontius's praetorium, and then from the governor's praetorium to King Herod's palace?
Who can explain Mary's sobs and various cries of grief, with which she was overwhelmed while he was accused by the chief priests at Herod's place, questioned by the king, scorned by the soldiers, mocked by the crowd, and then, dressed in a white robe, sent back to the governor's court?
Who can recall Mary's tears without shedding tears themselves?
She wept deeply as she saw him standing before the courts, remaining silent despite the accusations against him.
The priests accused him relentlessly, and the governor tried for a long time to find a reason to release him.
He demonstrated his innocence in every possible way and pleaded earnestly, hoping that, at least in honor of the Passover, he might be set free.
But the priests objected, asking for the release of the thief Barabbas, and shouted for Jesus to be crucified.
Mary's sorrow deepened when she saw her Lord stripped, tied to the column, and his body lacerated by whips.
Even the column itself bears witness to this, showing clear signs of the Lord's blood to this day for those who see it.
Then Mary's sadness and anguish intensified when Pilate granted the priests' request.
The soldiers gathered the entire cohort, mockingly dressing Christ in purple, crowning him with thorns, and giving him a reed for a scepter.
They saluted him mockingly, gave him vinegar and gall to drink, struck his head with the reed, spat on his face, and finally took off the scarlet cloak and dressed him in his own clothes again.
And carrying his cross, he left the city, crowned with thorns.
The Queen of Heaven followed him, along with her sisters, Mary Magdalene, and the other women who mourned and lamented for him.
These were the ones who had followed him not only from Galilee but also from Judea and Jerusalem.
Turning his eyes and face to the women who loved him, Jesus said: "Daughters of Jerusalem, do not weep for me, but weep for yourselves and for your children; for if they do this when the wood is green, what will happen when it is dry?"
John Nineteen: Seventeen; Luke Twenty-three: Twenty-seven; Mark Fifteen: Forty; Matthew Twenty-seven: Fifty-five; Luke Twenty-three: Twenty-eight.
CHAPTER 21. Christ is crucified with Mary standing by.
He is taken down and wrapped in burial cloths with Mary present.
As the Song of Solomon, chapter 8, verse 6, says, "Love is as strong as death." The Lord's suffering is witnessed, and Mary's devotion remains unwavering. Christ is led to be crucified, and Mary follows, showing her love through her tears.
Christ is lifted onto the cross, and Mary cries out in anguish. As Christ is nailed to the cross, Mary's soul is pierced with the thorns of sorrow.
Christ is mocked by the chief priests, ridiculed by soldiers, insulted by thieves, and blasphemed by passersby shaking their heads and shouting "Woe." Meanwhile, he prays to the Father for those who are crucifying him, as recorded in the Book of Matthew, chapter 27, verse 40.
Amidst all this, how immense was Mary's sorrow? What sobs and sighs as she witnessed the suffering of her beloved among thieves! Yet she endured seeing such harsh, prolonged, and beloved torments of the Lord.
Imagine her bitterness and anxiety when she heard the Messiah cry out from the cross, "I thirst." When she saw a sponge soaked with vinegar, absinthe, myrrh, and gall placed on a reed, offered to his lips, and when he tasted it, he refused to drink!
Mary's sorrow was renewed when she heard God's Son bid her farewell from the cross. He entrusted her care to Saint John, then twenty-three years old; cried out "Eloi"; declared "It is finished"; commended his spirit into the Father's hands; and, with a loud cry, chose to breathe his last.
After the sun was eclipsed, after three hours of darkness, the temple veil torn, the earthquake, the rocks split, the tombs opened, and the centurion and crowd departed, she saw soldiers sent to break the legs of the still-living thieves: Who can deny that Mary was intensely afraid for the breaking of her Lord's legs?
Right after this, a deep sadness enveloped the scene.
One of the soldiers pierced the Savior's side with a spear.
From His cold heart, blood and water flowed.
Mary was so grateful for the arrival of the noble Joseph of Arimathea and Nicodemus, a leader.
They brought one hundred pounds of myrrh and aloes to prepare for the Lord's funeral.
She watched gladly as the nails were removed from the Savior's hands and feet.
The body was taken down, anointed, and wrapped in linen, with a cloth around the head.
All this happened as Mary stood by, watching, mournfully and inconsolably lamenting.
CHAPTER 22 - Where Christ was buried, and when Mary bought spices.
There was a garden near the city, close to where Jesus was crucified.
In this garden, Joseph, a noble council member, had carved a tomb for himself from the reddish and white rock.
The tomb was tall enough that someone standing inside could barely touch the ceiling with an outstretched hand.
The entrance and door were on the east side, while the mausoleum, carved from the tomb's floor, was on the north side, measuring seven feet in length.
It was solid on top; the southern side was completely open.
The Savior's body, wrapped and prepared, was placed into the tomb from the east, into the mausoleum on the south side.
He lay on his back with his head to the west, his left side against the solid north, and his right side against the open south.
They completed these tasks quickly to avoid being caught by the evening of the first day of the week, leaving the tomb with many tears and great sorrow.
The men rolled a large stone to the entrance of the tomb and then returned home.
However, Mary Magdalene and her companions sat across from the tomb, mourning and weeping for the Lord.
After noting the location of the tomb, which they planned to visit often, they went to the city market and bought the finest spices and balms, storing them until the evening of the second day of the week.
Despite their inconsolable mourning and intense wailing, their deep grief couldn't erase the memory of their beloved faith.
It was the day of preparation, and the Sabbath was approaching.
The chief priests persuaded Governor Pilate to place guards at the tomb, claiming that otherwise, the last deception would be worse than the first.
To which he replied, "The error is yours, both the first and the last; it should be enough for you that I agreed to his death; you have a guard, use it if you wish."
So, the Jews went and secured the tomb by sealing the stone and setting guards.
Matthew 27:64-66
CHAPTER 23.
---When Christ Rested, How Mary, and About the Preparation of Spices, and the Narration of Times.
It was a significant day, that Sabbath John 19:31, when, after enduring so much suffering, the body of Christ rested in the hope of resurrection Psalm 16:10, without any trace of corruption.
Mary Magdalene observed the Sabbath as usual, remaining silent, yet not entirely silent Luke 23:56, for the sobs of her heart and the tears in her eyes were not fitting for the Sabbath.
But when the much-awaited evening of the Sabbath arrived, with Joanna, Susanna, and their fellow Marys by her side, she began to prepare and mix the chosen and pre-selected spices and balm with the finest powders of all perfumes Song of Solomon 3:6.
This woman possessed the courage of men, as she completed the task that King Solomon sang of in her honor.
Her hands dripped with myrrh, her fingers covered in the finest myrrh and aloe, along with all the best ointments Song of Solomon 5:5; 4:13.
Tears flowed continuously as she mixed, drawn from the richness of her heart, the memory of her beloved, and as her heart burned with the fire of love, the remaining oil of kindness flowed from her eyes.
One could see the dew of her eyes moistening the spices, gradually shaken with sobs, as tears mixed with the spices, her hands wet from the showers of maidens, drops flowing from her eyelashes, dearer than any drop and cassia, and undoubtedly more pleasing to God.
Indeed, she made the night of the Lord's resurrection famous, bright, and radiant, with her acts of devotion, becoming a glorious perfumer of the Savior, alongside her companions, so that from that point on, God, the creator of times, wished for the order of times to be narrated and for the day to follow.
Chapter 24 - When Christ rises, an angel descends, and the Marys go to the tomb.
After the somber Sabbaths, a joyful day began; and as the sun rose straight from the lower parts of the east, it lit up the sky with a rosy dawn.
Meanwhile, the true sun of justice, Christ, rose victoriously from the dead Malachi 4:2, and at the time he chose, he rose immortal from the dead.
At that moment, a great earthquake occurred, and many bodies of the saints who had fallen asleep rose Matthew 28:2; Matthew 27:52.
Meanwhile, Mary Magdalene, a noble woman with ointment, had prepared her mixtures before dawn, filling her alabaster jars with the finest and most precious perfumes, so valuable they could be worth the world's price, and so plentiful they were more than enough to anoint the body.
Very early in the morning, while it was still dark, she hurried to the Savior's tomb with arms full of spices, as every moment felt too slow to her.
The fervor of love could hardly bear the night's delays.
Following Mary Magdalene were the other Marys, namely Cleophas, Salome, Joanna, Susanna, and others with them, each carrying the spices they had prepared.
The evangelists describe different times of visitation, not falsely or carelessly, but intentionally, as a sign of their devoted visits, for they frequently came and went, unable to stay away from the Savior's tomb for long.
To ensure we stay true to the accounts of the evangelists, which is crucial, I've carefully recorded the exact words of each one after naming them.
I did this because some commentators mix up and confuse the different accounts of angelic appearances, which the evangelists report differently.
There's disagreement on whether Mary saw angels four times, three times, or just twice.
It's as if it's impossible or inappropriate for God to have at least six angels present at such a significant event as the resurrection.
For example, Matthew mentions one angel sitting outside, Mark notes another sitting inside, and John describes two angels seen only by Mary Magdalene.
In the Book of Matthew, Chapter 28, verse 1, we read: "In the evening of the Sabbath, which dawns gloriously on the first day of the week, after the sequence of time had changed, Mary Magdalene and the other Mary came to see the tomb."
In the Book of Mark, Chapter 16, verse 1, it says: "Very early on the first day of the week, Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother of James, and Salome came to the tomb. Christ, the sun of righteousness, had risen after His body was laid to rest. They asked each other, 'Who will roll away the stone for us from the entrance of the tomb?' because it was very large. As they approached the tomb, they saw that the stone had been rolled away, showing that the Savior had already come out, though the tomb's door was closed and the seal of the priest was intact; just as He entered the world through the closed womb of a virgin, keeping the seal of purity intact."
"That's why the angel rolled away the stone and sat on it. The guards were so terrified of him that they became like dead men. His appearance was as frightening as lightning, and his clothes were as white as snow."
Chapter 25 - Where Mary brought Peter and John; and an angel speaks outside, an angel speaks inside.
John: Mary Magdalene came early in the morning, while it was still dark, to the tomb and saw the stone had been taken away from the tomb.
John twenty verse one.
Afraid that his body had been taken, she was distressed and anxious over the loss of such a beloved figure.
Quickly returning, she went to Simon Peter and the other disciple whom Jesus loved, hoping they would search with her or share in her grief.
She said, "They have taken my Lord from the tomb, and we don't know where they have put him."
Here, where she says, "They have taken my Lord from the tomb," the Greek texts add "my" to show a greater affection of love or service.
So Simon Peter went out, and the other disciple, and they went to see what they had heard.
The disciples ran, and Mary followed.
Both disciples entered the tomb, saw the linen cloths, and the cloth that had been on Jesus' head, lying separately; they saw the empty tomb and believed that the Lord had been taken away, as Mary had said.
Then the disciples returned to their homes from where they had come.
But Mary, staying behind, fixed her emotions more strongly in the same place; she stood outside the tomb, weeping with tears and longing.
Troubled in mind and eyes, she wept while searching for Christ, driven by her desire for him.
She searched diligently, looked everywhere, and asked around; not finding him, she punished her own eyes with tears, those eyes that were searching for the desire of her soul but could not find him.
They saw but did not recognize him.
Later, other devout women, also troubled in mind and full of tears, joined her.
The angel, who had rolled away the stone from the entrance of the tomb and was sitting outside on the right side as you entered, could not bear their sorrow any longer.
Feeling compassion for their grief, he began to comfort them more closely and urged them not to be afraid, speaking to them familiarly.
Matthew continues.
The angel said to the women, "Do not be afraid; I know you're looking for Jesus, who was crucified.
He is not here; he has risen, just as he said he would.
What he promised has indeed happened."
He invited them to enter the tomb and see the place where the Lord had been laid.
"And if you don't believe my words, believe what you see with your own eyes."
In the Gospel of Mark, Chapter 16, Verse 5, it narrates:
As they entered the tomb, they saw a young man sitting on the right side, dressed in a white robe, and they were amazed.
He said to them, "Do not be alarmed; you should not be afraid, for those you see are your fellow citizens.
You are servants, we are messengers of the same Lord.
You seek Jesus, the Savior from Nazareth, who was crucified three days ago; he has risen, he is not here, yet he is everywhere."
Mary and the others stood inside the tomb, which they had entered from the east, in front of the sepulcher.
The angel sat before them at the right of the sepulcher.
Extending his hand, he pointed with a finger to the now empty tomb, saying, "Look, this is the place where the leaders of the Jews, a noble centurion, and others who buried him with devotion, laid him.
But since he truly has risen from the dead, go and tell his disciples, who were afraid when he was arrested and fled, leaving him; and Peter, who followed him from afar when the others fled, and after denying him three times, was looked upon mercifully by Christ, causing him to weep bitterly after leaving the courtyard of the high priest.
Tell them, I say, so they do not despair from either fleeing or denying, that he has risen.
And he is going ahead of you into Galilee.
There you will see him, just as he told you."
But the women, leaving the tomb, fled in fear and trembling and said nothing to anyone because they were afraid.
CHAPTER 26 - Where Mary Magdalene alone first sees two angels sitting, and then Christ.
John: But Mary Magdalene stood outside the tomb crying, as stated in John, Chapter 20, verse 11.
She mourned more because he had been taken from the tomb than because he had been crucified.
Indeed, she had no memory of her beloved, whose living presence she had lost, even in his relics.
She wept inconsolably, fearing she had lost him forever, the one whom the soldiers who crucified him and the Jews who sealed the tomb had left to her.
Yet she didn't believe herself, having seen the empty tomb before dawn, nor the apostles, who had searched with her.
Nor the apostles she told about his being taken, nor the women companions who often searched in vain, nor the angels who said he wasn't there but had risen.
She bent over, weeping, and looked into the tomb, truly led by his instinct and inspiration, urging her to seek him, inflamed by the fire of his love.
By his teaching, she thought it wasn't easy to believe the apostles, the women, or even her own eyes.
And she saw two angels in white sitting, one at the head and one at the feet, where the body of Jesus had been.
They said to her, "Woman, why are you crying?"
Mary, thinking they were asking and not unaware of her tears, replied, "Because they have taken my Lord, indicating a part from the whole; and I don't know where they have put him."
"And this adds to my sorrow, as I do not know where to find the comforter of my grief."
After saying this to the angels, bending at the entrance, for the tomb's doorway was low, and one could only see inside by stooping, she stood up again, turned toward the sunrise, and saw the Lord Jesus standing in the garden.
And she did not know that it was Jesus.
She loved deeply the one she longed for, whom she had searched for a long time.
Because she hadn't found him, she was losing hope of ever finding him.
As a result, she saw him but didn't recognize him.
It seemed she could rightly say that prophetic phrase:
"My eyes are dim with weeping" (Job 16:17), because the one who comforted me was far from me.
Jesus said to her,
"Woman, why are you crying? Whom are you looking for?"
Upon hearing this, Mary was filled with desire. Expressing her sorrow with broken words, she respectfully responded to the one she thought was the gardener. She didn't say why she wept or whom she sought, as it is natural for those who love deeply to assume that what they love is on everyone's mind. She prepared herself to carry away the one she believed had been taken:
"Sir," she said, "if you have carried him away, tell me where you have put him, and I will take him."
Oh love, as strong as death! Truly, for one who loves, nothing is difficult. The strength of love, with which Mary burned for Christ, convinced her that she could carry the Savior's body, wrapped with a hundred pounds of aloes and myrrh, all by herself.
At this, the Savior, who had come to comfort Mary, was further ignited by her search for him. He could no longer bear to hide, seeing her longing and hearing her lament. Her spirit was almost exhausted from the magnitude of her longing and the depth of her sorrow, while the one she was searching for was present but concealed from her sight and revealed himself to the unseen. He called her by name, with the abundance of his sweetness (Psalm 31:20), saying,
"Mary, recognize me, from whom you are recognized. I know you by name (Exodus 32:12), I know who you are, and what you want: Here I am, do not cry, here I am whom you seek.
"
Instantly, the bitterness of Mary's sorrow ceased, as the comforting voice of her friend and the sweetness of her Lord sounded. She recognized the familiar voice, felt the usual sweetness with which she was accustomed to being called,
"Mary."
And immediately, with her face lowered, she worshipped him with reverence and, as a disciple, greeted her Master, saying,
"Rabboni" (which means Teacher) (John 20:16).
Approaching to humble herself at Christ's feet, as she had done on the ninth day, she embraced them.
She heard from the Lord:
"Do not touch me, for I have not yet ascended to my Father.
Do not touch me with physical embraces, for you do not yet believe that I have escaped the chains of death.
You who seek the living among the dead.
Instead, touch me first with the embraces of the heart, firmly holding faith in my resurrection.
For I have not ascended to the Father in your heart, you who do not believe that I have risen or that I am equal to God the Father."
Hearing this, Mary no longer doubted, but believed in Christ, drawing faith from hearing the voice of the Lord she longed for and from seeing the face she desired.
The mustard seed that the good gardener Jesus had sown in her heart quickly took root and grew into a great tree
Matthew thirteen, thirty-one;
Luke thirteen, nineteen
of unwavering faith.
She undoubtedly believed that Christ, the Son of God, whom she loved while alive, was truly God, that He had truly risen from the dead, whom she had seen dying, and that He was truly equal to God the Father, whom she had sought lying in the tomb.
Chapter 27 - Where Christ sends Magdalene to the apostles as a messenger.
Finally persuaded, the Savior, with the enduring warmth of his special friendship that never ceased to glow in the heart of his dear friend, knowing well-since nothing is hidden from him-that he had already ascended to the Father in the heart of his faithful follower, appointed her as the messenger to the apostles of his ascension.
This was a fitting reward of grace and glory, granting her the first and foremost honor, rightfully recognizing her as the standard-bearer among all his servants.
Recently, he had made her the herald of the resurrection, and he said to her:
"Go to my brothers, and tell them: This is what the Lord says: I ascend to my Father by nature, and your Father by grace; to my God under whom I am a man, and your God."
John 20:17
"Among whom I am the mediator."
He said this, and immediately vanished from her sight. Yet, elevated by such a great and foremost honor and grace from the Son of God, the Lord and Savior, and illuminated by his first and most excellent appearance, she was the most intimate, devoted, and beloved by God among all women, second only to the unique Virgin Mother of God. Without delay, she fulfilled the duty of apostleship she had been honored with.
Indeed, she quickly went to the apostles and said to them:
"Rejoice with me, all who love the Lord, because the one I was seeking has appeared to me; and while I was weeping at the tomb, I saw my Lord. He said to me: 'Go to my brothers, and tell them: This is what the Lord says: I ascend to my Father, who begot me before the ages; and to your Father, who adopted you as his sons. To my God, because I descended; and to your God, because you have ascended.'"
"Behold, the life that was taken from the world through Eve is restored and announced through the Virgin Mary. Then Eve, with a poisonous drink, intoxicated her husband in paradise; now Magdalene offers the cup of eternal life to the apostles. Eve first tasted the serpent's poison"
Job 20:14
"in the garden of delights; Mary first saw the conqueror of death in the garden of the tomb."
Eve persuaded her husband with the serpent's promise:
"You will be like gods, knowing good and evil"
Genesis 3:5.
Mary announced the resurrection of the Messiah to her fellow apostles:
"I have seen the Lord," and foretold the ascension:
"And he said to me: I am ascending to my Father and your Father"
John 20:18.
Mary was a far more truthful prophetess than Eve; the latter servant was much better than the first.
This is the change of the right hand of the Most High
Psalm 76:11.
She had come to the tomb carrying spices to anoint the dead, and upon finding him alive, she joyfully changed her role to serve the living Savior, offering the apostles the balms of true life.
The fact that the Savior appeared first to Mary Magdalene, as we have explained according to
John, is also confirmed by the evangelist
Mark.
Jesus, rising early on the first day of the week, appeared first to Mary Magdalene
Mark 16:9.
And since we read about many Marys, lest we think there were also many Magdalenes, as some have suggested, he adds a notable act and a certain sign: From whom he had cast out seven demons.
Not only did she see the risen Lord first, but she was also the first to announce it to the apostles, affirming:
She went and announced to those who had been with Jesus, who were mourning and weeping; and they, hearing that he was alive and had been seen by her, did not believe.
When she couldn't persuade them, she returned to the tomb, hoping, as it happened, to see the Lord again.
CHAPTER 28 - Where two angels stood, and Christ appeared a second time, and about other appearances.
So far, we've discussed the first appearance of the Savior, where He chose to reveal Himself first to Mary Magdalene, among all mortals.
We also talked about the appearance of two angels, who were only seen and spoken to by Mary, highlighting her role as an apostle.
On this profoundly significant day-unmatched in joy and celebration-she was honored by the Son of God Himself.
She was the first to announce to her fellow apostles that the resurrection had already occurred, and she alone foretold the future ascension.
By being the first to offer the drink of life to the apostles, she redeemed Eve's offering, as told by the evangelists John and Mark.
Now, let's briefly explain the vision of the two angels, who, as per Luke, were seen standing by Mary and other women, and also the second appearance of the Savior, where, according to Matthew, He chose to be seen by the two Marys.
Luke, Chapter 24, Verse 4: And it happened that while the women were puzzled, not finding the body of the Lord Jesus, suddenly two men stood by them in bright clothing.
As the women were afraid and bowed their faces to the ground-hence the tradition arose in the church of God, throughout the Easter season, to pray with faces to the ground rather than kneeling-the angels said to them: "Why do you seek the living among the dead? For tombs are places for the dead; He is not here, but has risen. Remember how He spoke to you, for He foretold His resurrection not only to men but also to holy women, when He was still in Galilee, saying: 'The Son of Man must be handed over to sinners, be crucified, and rise on the third day.'" And the women remembered the words of the Lord Jesus.
Matthew, Chapter 28, Verse 8: And Mary Magdalene and the other Mary left the tomb with fear and great joy, running to tell His disciples. And suddenly, meeting them, He said: "Greetings," so that the curse of Eve, just as it was undone first in the singular Virgin through the mouth of Gabriel, was now undone in the Marys through the mouth of the Savior Himself.
They approached and held his feet, which he had previously forbidden one of them to touch because she did not yet believe, and they worshiped him.
Like the universal Church, they kissed the Lord's feet.
Then Jesus spoke to them, saying, "Do not be afraid; go, tell my brothers to go to Galilee, where they will see me."
Luke 24:9: And they left the tomb and reported all these things to the eleven and to all the others.
The women were Mary Magdalene, Joanna, Mary the mother of James, and others with them, who told these things to the apostles.
But their words seemed to them like nonsense, and they did not believe them.
However, Peter got up and ran to the tomb, and bending over, he saw only the linen cloths lying there; and he went away, wondering what had happened.
Then the Savior appeared to him; for he appeared to Simon Peter for the third time.
Mark 16:12: After this, he appeared in a different form to two of them as they were walking into the countryside, to the village now known as Nicopolis, a notable city in Palestine, sixty stadia from Jerusalem, which is seven and a half miles.
And they went and told the rest, but they did not believe them either.
Luke 24:33: And they found the eleven gathered together, and those with them, saying, "The Lord has truly risen and has appeared to Simon Peter."
For he appeared first of all to Peter among the men.
While they were speaking about this, Jesus stood among them and said, "Peace be with you."
These are the five appearances of the Lord and Savior, by which, on the day of his resurrection, he wanted to comfort those he loved and to be seen by those who loved him dearly.
And after eight days, he appeared to them for the sixth time; he offered his side to be touched by the apostle Thomas John 20:26.
For the seventh time, he appeared to those fishing at the Sea of Tiberias John 21:1.
For the eighth time, he appeared to them, as he had instructed through Mary Magdalene, on the mountain in Galilee.
Chapter 29 - Summary: How pleasing Mary's service was to Christ, and how it was rewarded even in the present.
It's worth noting-as many rightly wonder, and should deeply reflect upon with much spiritual sweetness-the individual acts of service that Mary Magdalene showed to her beloved Lord and Savior.
Unlike the services of other saints, which are quietly accepted and reserved for eternal rewards by the Father of lights, who sees in secret, hers were immediately proclaimed, praised, and magnified by the mouth of the Savior.
If anyone dared to criticize or accuse them, they were quickly defended and approved.
As it is written in the Gospel of Mark: she received, here and now, grace upon grace, until she enjoyed eternal glory in heaven.
When her most holy sister complained about her, she sat under the shadow of the one she loved and gathered the sweet fruits of his words.
She tasted and saw how sweet the Lord is.
Eagerly drawing from the life-giving channels from his heart, who enriched her with spiritual wealth, intoxicating her understanding and heart with the trickling of his words in which holy affections were germinated, this holy woman rejoiced as God multiplied the fruits of her devotion.
Many daughters have gathered riches, but Magdalene, the chief among his servants, surpassed them all.
Like a young deer, whose spirit rests only upon the humble and quiet, preparing a resting place in her heart where he may lie down, roam, feed, and be fed, and be delighted by her devoted service.
So, setting aside the experiences where the contemplative woman had a glimpse of the saints' wondrous glory, she was already adoring the true joys she now enjoys in her eternal home.
It's heartwarming to recall that first, as a sinner in the house of Simon the Pharisee, she washed the Lord's feet with her tears, dried them with her hair, caressed them with her eyes, and anointed them with perfume.
Contrary to Simon's judgment, she wasn't rejected; instead, she left forgiven for her sins and filled with the sevenfold grace of the Spirit.
Indeed, it was a joyful reward for such an unprecedented act of service!
Once more, the devoted follower, in the house of Simon the leper, broke an alabaster jar and poured nard over the Lord's feet and head.
According to Judas the betrayer, the perfume was wasted, but she gained grace and glory, receiving praise from Almighty God and the promise of eternal remembrance through the Gospel.
Now, for the third time, the renowned perfumer, with no less, and perhaps even greater, devotion, prepared the most precious spices to anoint the body of Christ and hurried to do so.
Although the Savior, respecting her intention, had already risen, she still received a great reward for her devotion.
She was enriched with many divine favors, being honored as the first to see the risen Christ;
elevated to the honor of apostleship;
made the evangelist of Christ's resurrection;
and appointed as the prophetess of the ascension to the apostles.
Chapter 30 - About the Three Oils: Feet, Head, and Body.
Mary Magdalene's precious oils were set aside, sold at a high price, and shared among the disciples of the Lord Savior.
The Son of God chose not to have them used on His deceased body, keeping them instead for His living Church.
For the Church of God is alive and consumes the living bread.
It is the beloved body of Christ, and to keep it from perishing, another body was sacrificed.
Mary dedicated her ointments to serve this body, specifically for the disciples, diligently offering to its members what was not given to the head.
The Savior, the source of mercy, understood that Mary's ointments prepared for Him were blended with both the essence of balsam and great kindness.
Thus, He chose to reserve them not for Himself, as He was already immortal and did not require mercy, but for His members, who needed kindness to alleviate their poverty.
Blessed is the soul that, alongside you, O blessed sinner and fervent lover of Christ, reflects on its past in the bitterness of its soul, embracing the feet of the judge and of mercy.
Like one filled with abundance, with the hope of forgiveness, it appeases the strict judge with the sacrifice of a contrite and humble heart and a troubled spirit, through the fire of pain and true repentance!
Such a soul receives the gift of understanding from God, with the Lord saying: Because I ate ashes like bread, incorporating the repentant with me, and mingled my drink with tears.
Even more blessed is the one who, with you, O wonderful contemplator and devoted servant, rises from the feet of embraced humanity to the head of divine desire, granting seven and also eight parts, attributing sufferings to man, ascribing miracles to God, and for all His blessings, offering God the sacrifice of praise, with a voice of joy and confession.
Offering the precious nard of many nations to God, the Father of mankind, from whom every good gift comes.
Filled with the oil of devotion and fueled by the unending fire of divine love!
Such a soul receives grace upon grace from God, as the Lord says:
"The sacrifice of praise will honor me" Psalm 49:23.
For whoever glorifies me, I will glorify.
But those who despise me will be disrespected First Samuel 2:30.
Blessed is the joyful person who shows mercy and lends Psalm 112:5, who, along with you, O celebrated Balsamite and leader of the Savior, carries the spices of kindness in the heart, benefiting the entire body of Christ, offering themselves to the Almighty.
Who diligently seeks out the countless grains to relieve the needs of the poor.
Who pours out the balm of mercy on them, in whose heart charity will always burn like a fire on the altar Leviticus 6:12, which neither the frost of greed can freeze nor the wind of vanity can blow out!
Such a person becomes like God through God's transformation.
For nothing pleases God more than living in such a way that one's goodness benefits the community.
These reflections on the three ointments of Christ's special friend, for the feet, the head, and the body, with which she served the Son of God in her love, are enough for the great lover, the wonderful contemplator, the happy fragrant one, to ponder.
Happy is the one who hears about these things from Mary Magdalene, believes joyfully, and remembers with devotion!
Even happier is the one who, while piously admiring these things about Mary, affectionately venerates her and passionately emulates her!
Indeed, the happiest is the one who is so moved by Mary's best fragrances, so delighted, that they imitate her way of life, are impressed by her conduct, are intoxicated by her spirit of devotion, and partake in the best part she chose Luke 10:42.
CHAPTER 31 - On Christ's ascension, with the apostles and Marys present.
On the 40th day after His resurrection, the Savior, preparing to ascend to heaven, wanted to see those who were still in the world and be seen by them.
He appeared to them while they were eating in the holy city and joined them at the table, eating with them to clearly demonstrate the truth of His physical resurrection.
It was truly a sight of solemn joy, a meal to be remembered for all time, an occasion worthy of proclamation to both angels and humans.
Sitting with the Son of God was His blessed and glorious mother, the Queen of Heaven, the Virgin Mary; the apostle and evangelist, prophet and virgin, John, whom Jesus loved more than the others; Mary Magdalene, a close friend of the Savior and a leader among His female followers; His devoted hostess Martha; Lazarus, whom He had raised from the dead; Mary of Clopas, Salome, Joanna, and Susanna were also present.
Peter was there, who had recently walked on the sea near Tiberias, and during the meal, he affirmed his devotion to Christ three times.
Also present were the gentle Andrew, James the brother of John, Philip the son of gentleness, and Thomas, the most eager to examine Christ's wounds.
Bartholomew, the mediator of the apostolic group; Matthew, also known as Levi, the first writer of the Gospel; and James the son of Alphaeus, later the patriarch of Jerusalem, also known as Oblias and Justus, a Nazirite from birth; Simon the Zealot, and Judas the brother of James, also called Thaddeus and Corculus, were all there.
Many others related to Christ by blood and kinship had gathered as well.
By this time, they were already believers, even though it had been said before His passion that His brothers did not believe in Him.
The Son of God graciously dined with them, and after addressing their disbelief, He said, "I will send the promise of my Father upon you; but you must stay in the city until you are clothed with power from on high."
You will be baptized with the Holy Spirit, not many days from now.
(Luke 24:49; Acts 1:5)
He then gave them the responsibility of preaching, instructing that it should begin in Jerusalem, move through Judea and Samaria, and then, as the Jews turned away from the word of life, he directed the Gospel to be spread across the entire world, promising those who shared it the power of all signs.
(Mark 16:17)
He spoke these and similar words to the leaders of his people while in the royal chamber.
(Psalm 113:7; Song of Solomon 1:11)
After the meal, he got up and led his guests outside to Bethany, on the Mount of Olives, near Jerusalem, a walk of about 1,000 paces, the distance allowed on the Sabbath.
Finally, with the Queen of Heaven, Mary, the apostles, and around 120 disciples in attendance, he bid them farewell one last time.
(Luke 24:50; Acts 1:12, 15)
"Behold, I am with you," he said, "until the end of the age." And, lifting his hands, he blessed them. (Luke 24:50)
Then, as they watched, he was lifted into the air and carried into heaven.
Immediately, a very bright cloud appeared, taking the Savior into the sky, as the Queen of Heaven, the apostles, and Mary, beloved of God, looked on.
(Acts 1:9)
CHAPTER 32.
About those who ascended with Christ, and the excellence of John the Baptist, Christ's forerunner.
So, when Christ ascended on high, as mentioned in Ephesians 4:8, he brought up from the underworld the captives, the thousands of rejoicing souls of the first humans, as noted in Psalm 68:18, and all who were pleasing to God from the beginning of the world, as stated in Wisdom 9:19.
He did not want to ascend alone, just as he did not want to rise alone.
The witnesses of his resurrection, whose tombs were opened when the Lord was crucified, as described in Matthew 27:50-53, rose again with him.
Afterwards, when the Lord appeared in Jerusalem, they appeared to many, and when the Lord ascended into heaven, they ascended with him.
They would not have been true witnesses of the resurrection if they had risen only in appearance, as shadows, or in imagination, and not in reality.
The army of angels met the triumphant King and were sent immediately to their Lord on the Mount of Olives, where, standing with those watching him ascend into the heavens, along with the Queen of Heaven, the apostles, and the holy women, they announced his return:
"He will come in the same way as you saw him go into heaven," as mentioned in Acts 1:11.
Let it not seem absurd that we have recounted this with diligence and included it in the deeds of blessed Mary Magdalene, because she participated with full devotion in all these events.
Just as she was aware of the resurrection in the garden, she was also a witness of the ascension on the mountain.
As she announced the resurrection to the apostles, she also prophesied the future ascension to them.
Standing with the apostles as he ascended, she pointed out the one ascending, like a finger pointing, more than a prophetess.
From her remarkable conversion to Christ and incomparable closeness to him, she is celebrated throughout the world.
Just as he, through his life in the wilderness and holiness from the womb, is incomparable to all the saints.
John says he is unworthy to untie the strap of his sandal, as stated in Luke 3:16: see great humility.
Mary wet his feet with her tears, hands, hair, eyes, and ointments, washed, dried, cherished, and anointed them: see wonderful closeness.
The one who baptized Christ trembled and did not dare to touch the holy head of God.
Matthew three, fourteen.
She, on the other hand, poured ointment over the Lord's head, the most precious head, indeed more precious than all the wealth of the world.
The deeds of both are recorded by the four evangelists.
They wrote about him because he heard the Father's voice and saw the Holy Spirit.
They wrote about her because she, with incredible devotion, served the Son of the Virgin Mother with her resources, stood by Him during His crucifixion, anointed Him, was the first to see Him risen from the dead, and held Him.
He was honored by Christ, and his angelic life was praised.
Matthew eleven, seven, ten.
She was defended when the Pharisee murmured, excused when Martha complained, praised when Judas grumbled, and sent as an apostle to the apostles themselves.
The Baptist was the greatest among those born of women.
Matthew eleven, eleven.
Equal to the highest after the King of Heaven, or superior to all; Magdalene, among the daughters of men, was equal to the highest after the Queen of Heaven, inferior to none.
Chapter 33: How the friend of Christ was troubled by His absence.
Despite the celebrated glorifications of Christ, Mary Magdalene felt immense public joy over the glory of her Lord and Redeemer.
Yet, inwardly, she grieved deeply over the physical absence of her beloved.
It's natural and necessary to feel deeply about friends: experiencing joy when they are present, and sorrow when they are absent.
The depth of love for those who leave is shown by the tears of those who remain; the joy of being together is felt by the pain of separation.
Only Mary felt what lovers usually feel when parted, although she hadn't lost her Lover, but sent Him ahead to prepare a place for her.
During meals, walks, and conversations, she had sweetly and delightfully listened to the Savior.
She had gazed intently at the Son of the Virgin, whose face she could never get enough of, who is fairer than the children of men.
Psalm 45:2.
Who could dare to estimate?
What about after the final farewell and solemn words of blessing, when He was suddenly lifted into the air?
What about when, taken up by a cloud of light, piercing the depths of the sky, she followed Him with unwavering eyes?
What about when, received into open heaven, He was no longer visible?
Luke 24:50, 51.
I can hardly believe she stood there for long, if at all; rather, she fainted and collapsed with a heavy heart, her body cold and pale.
As her heart warmed again, tears welled up, and she wept profusely.
Could Mary, I ask, remember her beloved Lover, the Lord Jesus, without sorrow or tears?
Could she from that point on have a moment without pain, a moment without delay, an hour without weeping, even though she knew she should not grieve, especially when she remembered His promise: that He would go to prepare a place for them and return to take them to Himself, so that where He is, they may also be?
John 14:3.
Reflecting on this in her heart, she turned her mourning into joy.
Lamentations 3:21.
John 16:20.
While continually contemplating, he saw the Son of God present in spirit.
This tempered his longing for physical presence, allowing him to rest sweetly in the cherished memory of Him.
After many sighs, long desires, and a deep hunger for the most blissful vision, he was fulfilled by the sight of his beloved's face.
This allowed him to embrace the sweetest and most delightful moments in the bed of eternal contemplation.
CHAPTER 34.
About Pentecost and the Holy Spirit, the communal life of the early Church, and Mary's contemplation.
After the vision and words of the angels, the apostles worshipped at the spot where the feet of the Lord Savior once stood.
They accompanied the Queen of Heaven back to Jerusalem with great joy.
Upon entering the temple, they praised and blessed the Lord.
They went up to the upper room with Mary, the Mother of God, along with other holy women and Christ's relatives, and devoted themselves to prayer in unity.
There were about 120 of them together.
(Luke 24:52; Psalm 132:7; Acts of the Apostles 1:1 and following).
After Saint Matthias was added to the apostles, the day of Pentecost arrived.
The Holy Spirit descended at the third hour of the day, taking a physical form as tongues of fire with a mighty sound.
They began to speak in the languages of all nations and to prophesy.
(Acts of the Apostles 2:1 and following).
Whatever language any of those 120 men and women spoke, it appeared to each listener that the speaker was speaking in their own language.
There were religious people from every language and nation under heaven residing in Jerusalem, celebrating the feast.
Among these, 5,000 immediately believed, followed by countless others.
All who believed were together and shared everything in common.
Those who owned lands and houses sold them and laid the proceeds at the apostles' feet.
(Acts of the Apostles 2:44; Acts of the Apostles 4:34).
Lazarus, a friend of the Lord Savior, along with his sisters Mary and Martha, owned significant wealth and property in Jerusalem, Bethany of Judea, Magdala, and Bethany of Galilee.
They sold everything and brought the proceeds to the feet of the chief of the apostles.
Noble women and widows also served with remarkable devotion and fitting affection towards the Queen of Heaven, the glorious Virgin Mary, Mother of God.
They offered, according to the customs of their country, services to the holy apostles of Christ and were honored for it.
These women were close and devoted to the Lord and Savior, especially Mary Magdalene, the special friend of the Son of God and leader of the women who served Him, known as the apostle to the apostles.
They also included the most blessed Martha, the hostess of Christ and daughter of His generosity, as well as the Lord's aunts, Mary of Clopas, Salome, Joanna, and Susanna, who were His servants and kin to the Queen of Heaven, described by the evangelists as her sisters.
Due to this dedication, a complaint arose from some Jews from Greece, as the widows from Galilee and Judea were given precedence in the daily service of the saints.
As it is written in the Acts of the Apostles, Chapter 6, Verse 1 and following.
When this was brought to the attention of the apostles' leader, a council was convened, and seven deacons were selected and appointed over food distribution, including those serving at the tables: Stephen, Philip, Parmenas, Timon, Prochorus, Nicanor, and Nicholas.
As it is written in the Acts of the Apostles, Chapter 6, Verse 5.
Stephen quickly became renowned for his miracles and was soon crowned with martyrdom.
However, all the disciples of the Savior, along with the deacon Philip, were expelled from Jerusalem, except for the apostles who stayed with the Queen of Heaven and the noble women who served them.
As it is written in the Acts of the Apostles, Chapter 8, Verse 1.
Mary Magdalene remained devoted to the glorious Virgin Mary as the Queen of Heaven and Mother of the eternal King, serving her with remarkable affection and dedicating herself to heavenly contemplation.
She often deserved to be comforted and refreshed by the angelic visions and visits that her mistress constantly enjoyed.
As the servant and special friend of her Son, our God and Lord, Jesus Christ, His vision and conversation were often revealed to her.
She continuously meditated on the memory of Christ's abundant sweetness, as it is written in the Book of Psalms, Chapter 145, Verse 7 and in contemplating Him, the fire of love was kindled.
Chapter thirty-eight, verse four.
An unquenchable fire consumed her daily, like a burnt offering, filled with an insatiable desire for her Redeemer.
Chapter 35.
Summary: How beloved the friend of Christ was to the Queen of Heaven and the holy apostles.
This holy woman was cherished by the glorious Mother of God and the holy apostles, both in love and honor, because of her profound and magnificent closeness with the Lord and Savior.
They loved her more fervently, knowing that the Son of God, their divine master, had shown her great affection.
They honored her more insistently, realizing that the Creator and Redeemer of the world had honored her greatly.
They consoled her more attentively, having seen God, the source of all comfort and solace, regularly comfort her through angels and Himself with love.
(Second Corinthians 1:3; Romans 15:5).
They constantly recalled and often preached to the people about how she turned from worldly vanity to the discipleship of the Savior.
They presented her repentance to sinners, for whom Christ wished to die, as an example of conversion, encouraging sinners to repent.
And since repentance without the hope of forgiveness is fruitless and superficial, even punishable, they highlighted Mary's faith and trust to demonstrate the certainty of forgiveness, so that penitents might find comfort.
However, simply turning away from evil is not enough to be dear to God; one must also do good.
They presented Mary's life as a model of holiness, offering guidance and an example of good behavior.
(Psalm 37:27; Luke 1:77).
So that they might be drawn to the fragrance of her virtues and be transformed in faith.
(Song of Solomon 1:3).
But because the hope of perfect conduct and the fruit of pious living is heavenly favor and abundant reward, they used Mary to illustrate divine mercy, so that all might rejoice in her example.
The apostles often remembered the deep devotion of his sister, the most holy Martha, in serving the holy Savior, attending to their own needs, and her heart full of generosity and kindness.
They spoke to the people about how familiar, gracious, and beloved these two devoted sisters were to the Son of God, more than any other women; how deeply they loved him, how sweetly God loved them, how kindly he often visited their home, and how affectionately they provided for him and themselves from their own resources.
They confidently sent a message to him from their brother: "Look, the one you love is sick."
And he lovingly revealed their brother's death to his apostles, saying, "Lazarus, our friend, is asleep."
Seeing them weep, he wept compassionately, mourning with them, so much so that the Jews said, "See how he loved him," with the disciple whom Jesus loved above others affirming this: "The Lord Jesus loved Martha, and her sister Mary, and Lazarus" John 13:23, 21:7, 20, 11:5.
The apostles decided to make this house of Christ's friends, Lazarus, Mary, and Martha, a house of prayer Mark 11:1.
They remembered how the Son of Almighty God and the Virgin Mother often walked, sat, reclined, slept, stayed overnight, prayed, and performed many miracles there; and how with his holy presence, stay, and residence, the Savior himself sanctified and dedicated it.
As the number of believers grew, they appointed the holy Lazarus as the bishop of his own city in the same basilica.
Later, during the Jewish persecution, he went to Cyprus to preach the word of Christ; there he served as the first bishop and lived for 24 years after his resurrection.
The memory of him and his sisters is also reverently commemorated on the 17th of December at Bethany, even to this day.
Chapter thirty-six: The Division of the Apostles, and the Twenty-Four Elders and Friends of Christ.
After the martyrdom of the blessed Stephen, the first martyr, Saul was called to faith from heaven Acts 9.
However, he was not called Paul until twelve years later.
Those scattered with Philip and the other companions of Saint Stephen traveled around, preaching the kingdom of God, until they reached Antioch.
There, a great church of disciples was gathered Acts 11.
It was there that the name "Christians" originated.
The blessed Peter established the patriarchal chair there, and later, after ordaining Evodius as patriarch, he returned to Jerusalem to join the co-apostles.
By the command of the Savior, they preached exclusively to the twelve tribes for twelve continuous years in the land of promise Hebrews 11.
In the thirteenth year after the Ascension, James, the brother of John, was killed by the sword; Peter was imprisoned.
Saul, driven by the Holy Spirit, was given apostleship to the Gentiles and received the name Paul.
In the fourteenth year, the apostles were divided Acts 12:2; Acts 13:2.
The East was assigned to Thomas and Bartholomew; the South to Simon and Matthew; the North to Philip and Thaddaeus; the central part of the world to Matthias and James; the provinces of the Mediterranean Sea to John and Andrew; the Western kingdoms to Peter and Paul.
Around the same time, Paul went to Jerusalem to see Peter Galatians 1:18; Galatians 2:9.
He exchanged the right hand of fellowship with James, John, and Peter.
After that, he went with his co-apostle Barnabas to Syria and Illyricum to preach the Gospel.
Peter, about to leave the East for Rome, appointed preachers of the Gospel to the regions of the West that he could not visit himself.
He chose from among the more noble in Christ and the older disciples of Christ.
To the region of Gaul, which has seventeen provinces and as many bishops; to the region of Spain, which has seven provinces and the same number of teachers.
Among these twenty-four elders, the foremost leader was Maximinus, chosen from the seventy disciples of the Lord Savior.
He was an exceptional teacher, renowned for his miraculous grace, and after the apostles, he stood as a standard-bearer of the Christian faith.
Blessed Mary Magdalene formed a close bond with him, ensuring that wherever the Lord called him, she would not be separated from his company.
The Queen of Heaven had already been assumed into heaven, and in her service, Mary, devoted to contemplation, experienced the delights of paradise.
The division of the ten apostles had already taken place, and they had stayed together for a long time in pious devotion.
However, with the Jews' envy inciting persecution in the Church, Herod beheaded the apostle James, imprisoned Peter, and expelled believers from their lands.
In the midst of this persecution, the faithful scattered, seeking different regions of the world assigned to them by the Lord, to steadfastly preach the word of salvation to those unaware of Christ.
As they departed, noble matrons and widows who had ministered to them in Jerusalem and the East joined them, unwilling to part from the special friend of the Lord Savior and the leader of His ministers.
Among them was the venerable hostess of the Son of God, the most blessed Martha, who followed in her sister's footsteps, with her most reverend brother Lazarus then serving as a bishop in Cyprus.
Accompanying her was the blessed Marcella, a woman of great devotion and faith, a servant of the blessed Martha, who had said to the Lord: "Blessed is the womb that bore you" Luke 11:27.
Also present was Saint Parmenas, a deacon full of faith and the grace of God Acts 6:8, to whose care the most blessed Martha entrusted herself in Christ, just as Saint Mary did with Saint Maximinus the bishop.
With a wonderful divine plan, they embarked on a journey to the western regions of the world.
The aim was not only to spread the praise and memory of the Gospel of blessed Mary and her sister across the globe, but also to ensure that the western region, like the East, would be illuminated by their physical presence and sacred relics.
CHAPTER 37 - How the Twenty-Four Elders Came to Gaul and Spain.
Setting sail on the sea with the devoted servant of God, Mary Magdalene, her blessed sister Martha, Saint Maximinus the archbishop, and the revered Parmenas the archdeacon, along with bishops Trophimus and Eutropius and other leaders of the Christian mission, they departed from Asia, driven by the east wind.
As they journeyed between Europe and Africa, through the Tyrrhenian Sea, they bypassed the city of Rome and all of Italy on their right, along with the Alps, which stretch from the Ligurian Gulf to the Gallic Sea, ending in the Adriatic Sea to the east.
They successfully arrived on the right side, in the province of Vienne in Gaul, at the city of Marseille, where the Rhone flows into the Gallic Sea.
There, invoking God, the great ruler of the world, they divided the provinces of the region as the Spirit guided them; and soon they ventured out, preaching everywhere, with the Lord working alongside them, confirming their words with accompanying signs.
For the king of virtues gave the word to those who evangelized with great power, granting to the house of God the spoils of the strong man armed.
Saint Maximinus was given Aix, the metropolis of the second province of Narbonensis, where blessed Mary Magdalene completed her pilgrimage; Paul received Narbonne, the metropolis of the first province of Narbonensis; Austregisilus received Bourges, the metropolis of the first province of Aquitaine; Irenaeus received Lyon, the metropolis of the first province of Lugdunensis; Gatianus received Tours, the metropolis of the third province of Lugdunensis; Sabinus and Potentianus received Sens, the metropolis of the fourth province of Lugdunensis; Valerius received Trier, the metropolis of the first province of Belgica; Feroncius received Besancon, the metropolis of the largest province of the Sequani; Eutropius received Saintes, a city of the second province of Aquitaine, with its current metropolis being Bordeaux; Trophimus received Arles, then the metropolis of the province of Vienne.
These ten provinces of Gaul embraced their preaching.
Other teachers didn't preach in the remaining seven provinces, but rather in seven cities within those provinces:
Eutropius in Aurasicum, a city in the province of Vienne;
Frontinus in Perigueux, a city in Aquitaine the Second;
George in Velia, a city in Aquitaine the First;
Julian in Le Mans, a city in Lyon the Third;
Martial in Limoges, another city in Aquitaine the First;
Saturninus in Toulouse, in Narbonne the First, where he was martyred by being thrown from the Capitol for his faith in Christ;
Parmenas in Avignon, in the province of Vienne, departed with the venerable servant of the Lord Savior, Saint Martha, and also his servant Marcella.
Epaphras and Sosthenes, Germanus and Euchodia, and Syntex were associated with other cities:
Rouen, in the province of Lyon the Second, which is now known as Normandy;
Mainz, in its province, Germany the First;
Cologne, in its province, Germany the Second;
Martigny, in the province of the Alps Graiae and Pennine;
Auch, the metropolis of its province Novempopulania;
Ebreduna, the metropolis of its province the Maritime Alps;
Reims, the metropolis of its province Belgium the Second, were set aside for other teachers.
The names of those sent by the apostles to Spain are as follows: Torquatus, Thesiphus, Secundus, Indalecius, Caecilius, Esicius, and Euphrasius.
These seven united the seven provinces of Spain with the Christian faith.
CHAPTER 38: How Blessed Mary Engaged in Preaching and Contemplation at the City of Aix.
Upon entering the city of Aix, Blessed Maximinus spread the seeds of heavenly teaching in the hearts of the Gentiles.
He dedicated himself day and night to preaching, prayer, and fasting, aiming to guide the unbelieving people of that region towards the knowledge and worship of Almighty God.
After the evangelical preaching had fostered a new growth of faith, the blessed bishop Maximinus, leading the Church of Aix, shone with many and varied miraculous powers.
Alongside him, the glorious and special follower of the Lord Savior dedicated herself to heavenly contemplation in that same Church.
As a true and passionate lover of the Redeemer, and the most prudent chooser of the best part-which, as God testifies, was never taken from her since she acquired it at the feet of Christ-Mary, with a hunger for the Word of God, stirred and refreshed her mind in a marvelous way.
Drawn by the sweetness of her beloved Lover, intoxicated with a desire for the cup of the Lord, she gathered herself entirely within and elevated herself beyond.
Dissolved by the warmth of the purest love, she tasted inner joys.
Still on earth, she walked in heavenly realms, mentally strolling among the angels.
This was her way.
Concerned also for the salvation of others, for whose sake she had come to the Western ends of the world, she sometimes set aside the sweetness of contemplation to preach to unbelievers or to comfort believers with her gentle spirit.
She instilled sweet words into the souls of her listeners.
For it was from the abundance of the heart that the mouth spoke, as it says in First Corinthians, chapter twelve, verse thirty-four.
This is why all her preaching was truly divine contemplation.
She always presented herself to sinners as an example of conversion, to those doing penance as a sure sign of forgiveness, to the faithful as a model of mercy, and to all Christians as a demonstration of God's compassion.
She showed the eyes with which she had wept so much that her tears washed the feet of Christ.
With those same eyes, she was the first to see Jesus risen from the dead.
She showed the hair with which she first dried his feet after washing them with her tears, and later wiped his feet again when she anointed them with costly perfume during the supper.
She showed her mouth and lips, which had kissed the feet of Jesus; not just when he was alive, but even after he died and when he rose from the dead; over and over again.
She showed the hands and fingers with which she first held, washed, and anointed the feet of the Almighty God.
She anointed them again with pure nard and even poured the rest of the perfume over the head of the Son of God.
Why mention each act one by one?
Which of the Gospel writers remains silent about Mary Magdalenes merits?
Which of the apostles was closer to the Lord?
Who drank in his teaching more eagerly?
It is right, then, that just as she was sent as the apostle to the apostles to announce Christs resurrection, and became a prophet of his ascension, so also she should become a preacher of the faith for all believers across the world.
This was known by the One who saw and approved her devotion when she anointed his head, saying: "She has done a good work for me. Truly I tell you, wherever this gospel is preached in the whole world, what she has done will also be told in memory of her." (Matthew 26:10-13; Mark 14:9)
Chapter Thirty-Nine: Where Blessed Martha Preached, and About the Miracles of Both Sisters.
Blessed Martha, along with her companions, shared the message of the Lord Savior with the people in the city of Avignon and Arles, as well as the villages and towns along the Rhone in the province of Vienne.
She openly testified about what she had witnessed around Him and what she had learned from His teachings.
She supported her teachings on divine powers with her own miracles.
Whenever the chance arose, after praying and making the sign of the holy cross, she received the grace of healing, as described in First Corinthians Chapter Twelve, Verse Thirty:
cleansing lepers, healing the paralyzed, raising the dead, and aiding the blind, mute, deaf, lame, weak, and sick.
This was Martha.
Similarly, Mary performed miracles with remarkable ease to reinforce the faith of her words and to inspire belief in her listeners.
There was a venerable beauty in both their faces, an honesty in their behavior, and a graceful eloquence in their words that was very persuasive.
It was rare, if ever, that anyone left their preaching without being moved to belief or tears.
Who would not be inspired with love for the Lord Savior in their presence, or moved to tears by reflecting on their own struggles?
Their lifestyle was characterized by simplicity, and their attire by modesty and religious devotion.
Although Mary no longer cared much for food and clothing after she lost the physical presence of the Lord Savior, those who supported her and showed her great affection were generous matrons.
From this also came the apocryphal tale, if it is indeed entirely apocryphal:
just as it is common for witches to mix more honey so they can secretly offer gall.
From there, perhaps, came the story that she was daily lifted into the air by angels, then set down again by angels, and that she was refreshed by heavenly food served by angels.
If this is understood mystically, it is not entirely unbelievable.
For truly and without doubt, she was frequently refreshed by the sight of angels, supported by their services, and comforted by their conversations.
It was truly fitting, and indeed remarkable, that in a wonderful and unprecedented way, God, the God of all consolation
Second Corinthians 1:3, would comfort Mary, who herself showed extraordinary and unparalleled devotion on earth.
However, the claim that after the Savior's ascension, she immediately fled to the wilderness of Arabia, hid in a cave without clothing, never saw a man afterward, was visited by a certain priest asking for clothing, and other such tales, are completely false and borrowed from the fabrications about the deeds of the repentant Egyptian.
Even those who invented the story admit to their deceit at the start by attributing their narrative to Josephus, the very learned historian, even though Josephus never mentioned Mary Magdalene in his writings.
Let this be enough about these matters.
Now, let's return to the sequence of the narrative and, setting aside for now the contemplation of Mary, continue with the acts and miracles of her most blessed sister, Martha.
CHAPTER 40. Where Blessed Martha Freed the Province of Vienne from a Tarasque.
Between Arles and Avignon, cities of the province of Vienne, along the banks of the Rhone, there was a wilderness of barren shrubs and river gravel, infested with wild beasts and poisonous reptiles.
Among these venomous creatures, a terrible dragon roamed, incredibly long and massive.
It breathed out deadly smoke, emitted sulfurous sparks from its eyes, hissed with a piercing sound from its mouth, and roared horribly with hooked teeth.
The dragon tore apart anything that crossed its path with its claws and teeth, and anything that came too close was killed by the stench of its breath.
It's unbelievable how many livestock and shepherds it devoured and how many people it drove to death with its foul odor.
One day, while the blessed woman was preaching God's word to the gathered crowds, the conversation turned entirely to the dragon.
Some people earnestly pleaded, while others, as usual, tested her, saying that if there was any power in her Christ, she would show it, for it was not possible for any human effort to remove this dragon.
To which she replied: "If you are ready to believe, all things are possible to the one who believes" Mark 9:23.
Promising their faith soon after, she gladly led the people, boldly approached the dragon's lair, subdued its ferocity with the sign of the cross, tied her own belt around the dragon's neck, and, seeing the people watching from afar, said:
"Why are you afraid? Look, I am holding the serpent, and you still hesitate; come forward bravely in the name of the Lord Savior, and cut this poisonous beast into pieces."
She spoke, forbidding the dragon with great power from harming anyone with its breath or teeth.
Then rebuking the crowds of little faith Matthew 8:26 and urging them to strike with confidence, she indeed subdued the dragon immediately, but barely encouraged the crowds.
Finally, using their weapons and strength, they tore the beast apart piece by piece.
They were amazed by the faith and steadfastness of the blessed Martha.
Without any fear, she held the massive beast still with her fragile belt as it was being cut down.
Before, that place in the wilderness was known as the Black Hearth.
From that moment on, it was called Tarascon, named after the dragon, Tharascus.
Upon seeing or hearing about the miracle, the people of the Viennese province believed in the Lord Savior and were baptized.
They glorified God through the miracles of His servant.
From then on, because of her exceptional merits, Martha was loved and honored by all the provincials.
Chapter 41: How Blessed Martha Lived in Tarascon
After being driven away by God's power from the desert of Tarascon, where all the venomous creatures were gone, the most holy Martha chose to live there.
She turned a once hated and detested place into one that was livable, pleasant, and lovely.
There, she built a House of Prayer, as mentioned in the Book of Mark, Chapter 11, Verse 17, enriching it with virtues and miracles instead of useless feminine ornaments.
She lived there alone, as referenced in Lamentations Chapter 3, Verse 28, for seven years.
During this time, her diet consisted only of vegetable roots, green herbs, fruits, and tree produce.
However, she believed it was wrong to eat this meal more than once a day for herself, though not for others.
She didn't want her daily fasting to be a punishment without compassion or a burden to those living with her.
Always remembering her past hospitality, she was never without the poor, to whom she gladly gave whatever was brought to her.
She always shared her table with the needy, offering them necessary food with loving care and her usual kindness.
She provided for them with greater enthusiasm and more frequently than if she were serving herself, remembering that the one she used to serve on earth, who hungered and thirsted because he chose to, no longer needs material gifts as he used to; thus, he wished to be refreshed in the poor now.
The servant of Christ remembered what Christ would say to his own: that whatever you did for one of the least of my people, you did for me, as stated in the Book of Matthew, Chapter 25, Verse 40.
Therefore, as she once served the head of the Church, she now sought to provide for the members of Christ: always lovable to everyone and approachable to all.
And because God loves a cheerful giver, as mentioned in Second Corinthians Chapter 9, Verse 7, he provided for his servant with his usual mercy, so that an inexhaustible source of new abundance would arise, as referenced in Sirach Chapter 24, Verse 6, and the storerooms would be filled, as mentioned in Deuteronomy Chapter 28, Verse 8.
Even when emptied by daily generosity, without any worry of her own, the devotion of the faithful contributed even more, allowing her to give abundantly; for she, with her natural generosity, gave gladly.
However, he didn't send the rich away empty-handed.
Many came to her, receiving benefits for both body and soul.
Her clothing was simple-just a sack and haircloth-worn for seven years, bound to her body with a knotted horsehair belt, so that worms would emerge from her decayed flesh.
Oh, incomparable patience!
It was as if, while living in the flesh, she became food for worms.
She was always barefoot, her head covered with a white veil made from camel hair.
Her bed was made of tree branches and twigs, topped with a blanket, and she used a stone for a pillow.
Amid these hardships, a thousand times a martyr, the most holy Martha longed for heaven.
Her mind was completely devoted to God, lost in sacred prayers, and she stayed watchful all night.
Anyone she had once seen in her home with humility, she continuously adored on bended knees, worshiping him as he reigned in heaven.
She often traveled to cities and towns, preaching the faith of the Lord Savior to the people, and when she returned to her solitude, she brought back many new believers.
What she taught with words, she immediately confirmed with miracles and signs.
With prayer alone, by laying on hands, she expelled demons from possessed bodies and performed every kind of virtue, empowered by the Holy Spirit.
Chapter Forty-Two - Where Blessed Martha Revived a Young Man Drowned in the Rhone.
In Avignon, a city in the province of Vienne, just outside the city gates, in a picturesque spot between the waves of the Rhone River and the city's fortifications, Blessed Martha was seated one day, preaching the word of life to crowds of citizens and healing the sick.
A young man on the opposite side of the Rhone noticed the gathering and wanted to hear the word of God.
Without a bridge or boat available, he was driven by the desire to listen and witness the miracles.
Relying on his swimming skills, he stripped off his clothes and entered the waters of the Rhone, beginning to swim.
Everyone on the other side of the Rhone watched him Luke 4:20, when suddenly he was overwhelmed by the swelling waves of the turbulent Rhone and drowned.
A clamor rose from the crowd; acknowledging the young man's devotion, they lamented his misfortune.
The entire populace shared the same thought, wish, and prayer: that fishermen and nets be sent out swiftly to search for the young man's body, hoping that by the mercy of the Lord Savior, it might be found.
The next day, at the ninth hour, after much effort, the body was found, retrieved, and brought to the most holy Martha.
The entire city gathered for this spectacle Acts 13:41.
The city's nobles, both men and women, earnestly pleaded, kneeling before Christ's servant, to witness the wonders of Christ the Savior in the resurrection of this young man.
She agreed with a grateful heart, on the condition that all present would commit themselves to the Christian faith.
Everyone cried out with one voice: We will believe that the Lord Savior is the true Son of God and God Himself, who chose you as His servant.
Upon hearing this, Blessed Martha, rejoicing and confident in the Lord Savior's compassion and power, prostrated herself in tears and prayed; the people, moved by her example, did the same.
With loud cries Genesis 27:38, they implored the mercy of Almighty God to show His power in this miracle for the honor and glory of His name Psalm 79:9.
After finishing the prayer, the servant of Christ stood up.
Approaching the body, she said,
"In the name of the Lord Savior Jesus Christ, Son of God, rise, young man, and tell us how much kindness the Redeemer has shown you."
At this command, with his soul returning, the young man came back to life and sat up
Acts 3:6; Luke 8:39; Luke 7:15; Acts 9:40
and immediately confessed his belief in Christ and was baptized.
After the great joy of the rejoicing crowds, he returned home healthy and unharmed.
Seeing this, all the people shouted together: Jesus Christ is the true God, and there is no other God besides Christ
Judith 9:19.
From then on, the reputation of Martha, the most holy servant of Christ, was celebrated everywhere;
she was loved by men and honored by women.
Chapter forty-three: Where blessed Martha turned water into wine at the dedication of her house.
Around this time, throughout all the provinces of Gaul, especially in Vienne, Narbonne, and Aquitaine, there was a well-known rumor and a delightful scent of good reputation, like the aroma of a field blessed by the Lord.
Genesis twenty-seven, twenty-seven.
This stirred the hearts of all the people in these provinces towards faith in Christ and love for the handmaid of Christ, the most holy Martha.
Her sister, the most blessed Mary Magdalene, who should be named with the highest reverence, shared in her joy and celebration.
Maximinus, the archbishop and organizer and guardian of the most holy and contemplative life, who was eager to see and speak with the servant of Christ, traveled from his province of Narbonne to Vienne, and then to Tarascon.
Acts twenty-eight, twenty.
Similarly, Trophimus, the archbishop from the city of Arles, and Eutropius, the bishop from Orange, were drawn to Tarascon by the same intention, desire, and vow on the same day and hour.
Although none of them suspected the arrival of the others, they all met together, inspired by God, who arranges everything smoothly.
Wisdom eight, one.
The sacred woman welcomed them honorably, entertained them generously, and insisted they stay.
On the sixteenth day before the Kalends of January, which is the seventeenth day of the month of Kislev, called December by the Romans, they dedicated to the Lord Savior a church in the house of the most blessed Martha.
This was notable for her signs, virtues, and holy way of life.
After the dedication of the temple, when the bishops came to dinner, the most holy Martha served them with her wondrous and customary affection.
Many others who had gathered were also reclining at the table.
When the wine ran out, the hostess of the Lord Savior ordered water to be drawn in the name of Jesus Christ and generously served to all.
John two, three.
When the bishops at the feast tasted it, they realized that the water had been turned into excellent wine.
As a result, the priests agreed by a common decree that this day should be solemnly observed each year, in honor of the basilica's dedication and the miraculous transformation of water into wine.
CHAPTER 44 - Where blessed Martha greets Mary, introduces the leaders, and foretells the day of her passing.
Following the passing of blessed Martha, a miraculous event led to the tradition of celebrating the feast of her passing on the day her house was dedicated.
They also celebrated the martyrdom of Saint Lazarus, the bishop, her brother.
This mirrors what we observe with blessed John the Baptist, and the apostles of Christ, John, James, Simon, and Jude, along with many other martyrs.
Their martyrdoms are celebrated not on the days they suffered, but on the days their churches were dedicated or when their relics were discovered.
Finally, the blessed bishops, servants of Christ, bid farewell, entrusting themselves to her holy merits and prayers.
After exchanging blessings, they parted ways.
Acts fifteen verse thirty-nine.
The blessed virgin greeted her sister, the venerable and universally renowned Mary Magdalene, earnestly asking her to visit while she was still alive.
When the chief bishop conveyed this to the blessed lover of God, she returned the greeting to her sister and agreed to the request, although it was fulfilled not in the body, but after the body.
This shows that the saints of God remember their own after the body, fulfilling what they promised in the body.
During that time, a fierce persecution by the pagans arose in the province of Aquitaine, and many Christians were exiled.
Among them, Frontinus, the bishop of Perigueux, and George of Velay sought refuge with the most blessed Martha in Tarascon.
She welcomed them with kindness and generosity as a sign of charity and ensured they were honorably cared for until they could return to their own dioceses.
Finally, as they were preparing to return, the servant of Christ said a final farewell:
"O bishop of Perigueux, know that I will depart from this body of death after the completion of the next year."
Romans seven verse twenty-four.
"I beseech you, if it pleases you, may your holiness come to bury me."
To which the bishop replied: "I, daughter, will be present at your service, God willing, with life as my companion."
The priests returned to their own places
Acts
21:6,
and the most blessed Martha gathered her people and told them that the day of her passing would come in a year.
As she lay on her noble bed made of twigs, she suffered from fevers almost all year, much like gold tested in the furnace by fire
Wisdom
3:6.
CHAPTER 45: Where the blessed Mary sees Christ; she departs and is buried.
Meanwhile, the blessed Mary Magdalene, dedicated to heavenly contemplation and holding onto the best part she chose, as noted in the Gospel of Luke chapter ten, verse forty-two, though still physically on earth, found her mind wandering through the delights of paradise, nourished by an indescribable sweetness, as much as is permitted to mortals.
But who can truly capture the depth of the sighs that drew her, or the prayers she, a friend of the Savior, breathed, even as she already enjoyed the company of angels?
With what longing, I ask, did she burn, yearning to be with Christ, as expressed in the letter to the Philippians chapter one, verse twenty-three, to see Him, whom she had once seen humble in the form of a servant, now reigning in majesty, as described in Philippians chapter two, verse seven.
Finally, as the moment approached for her most holy soul to be freed from the flesh and enter those courts she longed for, where she fainted, as mentioned in Psalm eighty-four, verse three, to be more fully joined with the Lord, the Son of God, the Lord Savior appeared to her.
She saw her heart's desire: Christ Jesus Himself, surrounded by a multitude of angels, kindly and mercifully calling her to the glory of the heavenly kingdom, as stated in Revelation chapter three, verse twenty-one.
"Come, my beloved, and I will place you on my throne; for the king has desired your beauty, fairer in form than the sons of men," as noted in Psalm forty-five, verses twelve and three.
So that you, who diligently served His earthly needs while He lived among men, as mentioned in Baruch chapter three, verse thirty-eight, may joyfully and exultantly receive from Him the rewards of heavenly life, among the choirs of angels, forever.
The special friend of the Lord and apostle of the Savior passed away on the twenty-second of July, with angels rejoicing. She became a co-heir of heavenly powers and worthy to enjoy the glory of eternal brightness with them, seeing the King of the Ages in His beauty, as described in Isaiah chapter thirty-two, verse seventeen.
Her most holy body was laid in a wonderful mausoleum by the blessed Maximinus, the bishop, embalmed with various spices. Then, over her blessed remains, he built a basilica of honorable architecture.
His tomb, crafted from white marble, illustrates how he earned forgiveness for his sins in the house of Simon, as well as the kindness he showed during the burial of the Lord.
CHAPTER 46.
Where blessed Martha saw her sister's soul being carried to heaven by angels.
During these events in Aquis, the capital of the ecclesiastical province of Narbonne,
at the same time, in the province of Vienne, in Tarascon, the most holy servant of the Lord Savior, Martha, was bedridden with a fever, yet she remained devoted to divine praises.
As she meditated on heavenly matters, she witnessed the choirs of angels carrying her sister Mary Magdalene's soul to heaven.
She called those around her to share what she had seen, asking them to rejoice with her, and exclaimed:
"Oh most beautiful sister, what have you done?
Why have you not visited me, as you promised and instructed me?
Are you enjoying the embraces of the Lord Jesus without me, He who loved us so much because we loved much?
I will follow you wherever you go.
But for now, live eternal life, be happy forever, and remember your soul, not wanting to forget us."
Delighted by this vision, the holy woman longed more than ever to be free and with Christ, finding it difficult to remain in the flesh any longer, separated from her sister and the angels she had seen.
Knowing her departure was near, she advised, taught, and comforted the believers.
As the news spread that the servant of Christ was nearing her end, a great multitude of the faithful gathered and stayed with her until she was buried, with tents spread through the woods and fires burning all around.
CHAPTER 47 - Where Christ and Magdalene, His friend, appeared to blessed Martha.
On the seventh day at evening, He instructed them to light seven candles and three lamps.
Around midnight, as they were overcome by heavy sleep, they all fell asleep.
Suddenly, a strong gust of wind rushed in with a mighty spirit, extinguishing all the candles and lamps.
Understanding this, the servant of Christ, making the sign of the cross, prayed against the snares of demons.
Then she woke the guards and asked them to relight the lamps.
While they hurried and delayed for a long time, suddenly a light from heaven shone down.
In that light, the apostle of Christ the Lord Savior, Mary Magdalene, appeared, holding a fiery torch in her right hand.
She immediately lit the seven candles and three extinguished lamps with her heavenly light.
Standing by her sister's bed, she said: "Greetings, holy sister."
Immediately, her sister replied: "Look, as you instructed me through the blessed bishop Maximinus, I have visited you in the body while you live in the body. Behold, your beloved, the Lord Savior is here to call you from this valley of misery, just as He appeared to me before my transition, inviting me to the palace of His glory. Come now, and do not delay."
She said: "The Lord is joyfully approaching." As He came closer, gazing at Martha with the most gentle face, He said: "To whom you have most devotedly ministered from your resources; to whom you have offered the most gracious hospitality; to whom after my passion, in my members, you have done many good deeds, behold, I am here. To whom long ago, prostrated, you said: 'I believed that you are the Christ, the Son of the living God, who has come into this world.' Come now, my hostess, come from exile; come, you will be crowned."
Hearing this, she tried to rise and follow the Savior immediately.
The Savior said,
Wait,
because I am going to prepare a place for you, and I will come again and take you to myself, so that where I am, you may also be with me
(John Fourteen:2-4).
He spoke and then disappeared; but his sister,
Saint
Mary, did not appear either.
However, the light that came with them remained.
Then the guards came, and they were amazed at the lamps, which they had left extinguished, now shining with an unusual light.
Chapter Forty-Eight: Where, when, and how, and with whom present, the blessed Martha departed from her body.
At dawn, she asked to be placed outside under the open sky.
Every moment felt slow to her, as if that morning were delayed by a thousand years.
Straw was spread under a leafy tree, and on the straw was a sackcloth, with a cross made from ashes on it.
As the sun rose, the servant of Christ was brought out and laid over the ashes, and, at her request, an image of the crucified Savior was set before her.
After resting for a bit, looking at the crowd of faithful, she asked them to pray for her passing to be hastened.
As they wept abundantly, she lifted her eyes to heaven and said:
"O guest, why, Lord Savior, why do you delay?"
"When will I come and appear before your face?"
"Since you spoke to me at dawn, my soul has melted away."
"From then on, with longing for you, all my limbs stiffen, my nerves grow numb, my bones waste away, my marrow fades, and all my insides wither."
"Do not let me be disappointed, Lord, in my hope."
"My God, do not delay, Lord, do not linger."
As she pondered these things, she remembered how Christ had died on the cross at the ninth hour, and that she had once brought with her from Jerusalem the account of Christ's passion written in Hebrew.
She called for Saint Parmenas, asking for it to be brought and read aloud to her, to ease the weariness of her waiting.
It happened as she hoped.
While she listened to the account of her beloved's suffering, read in her own language, tears of compassion fell, and she began to weep; for a moment, she forgot her own passing, focusing entirely on the story of the passion.
She listened until the part where Christ, commending his spirit into the hands of the Father, breathed his last; she sighed deeply and passed away.
He passed away in the Lord on July 29, just eight days after his sister, Saint Mary Magdalene, on a Friday at 3 PM, in his sixty-fifth year.
His body was respectfully laid to rest and wrapped, and his companions, who had traveled with him from the East and remained faithfully by his side until that day, brought him into his own church.
Among these companions were Saint Parmenas, Germanus, Sosthenes, and Epaphras, who were all companions of Saint Trophimus, the Archbishop of Arles.
Also with them were his servant Marcella, and Euchodia and Syntex.
These seven held a three-day vigil during his funeral, with a multitude of people gathering from all around.
They kept watch over the holy body in praise of God until the third day, with candles lit in the church, lamps in the houses, and fires in the woods.
CHAPTER 49 - Where, when, and how she was buried by the Lord Savior and Saint Frontinus, even though he was not physically present.
On Saturday, a significant burial site was prepared for her at her own basilica, which had been dedicated by the bishops.
On the following Sunday, at the third hour of the day, everyone gathered to properly embalm the holy body, just before August 1.
Suddenly, at that same hour, in the city of Perigueux in Aquitaine, as Saint Frontinus, the bishop, was about to celebrate Mass, he dozed in his chair while people waited.
Christ appeared to him and said: "Son, come and fulfill your promise to be present at the funeral of Martha, my hostess."
As soon as he spoke, in the blink of an eye as described in First Corinthians chapter 15, verse 52, they appeared in Tarascon, holding books in hand, within the church: Christ at the head, the bishop at the feet, standing. They alone placed the body in the tomb, astonishing everyone present. They left after completing the funeral rites.
One of the clergy followed them, asking the Lord who he was or where he came from. The Lord did not respond; instead, he handed over the book he was holding. The cleric returned to the tomb and showed the book to everyone; on each page, it read: "Martha, the hostess of Christ, will be remembered forever; she will not fear bad news," as written in Psalm 111, verse 6. This was the only content in the book.
Meanwhile, in Perigueux, a deacon woke the bishop, noting that the time for the sacrifice was passing and the people were growing weary. The bishop replied: "Do not be disturbed, as stated in Acts chapter 20, verse 10, nor be weary for having waited so long. For I have just been caught up in spirit, whether in the body or out of the body, I do not know: God knows, as written in Second Corinthians chapter 12, verses 2 and 3, to Tarascon, with the Lord Savior, to bury his most holy servant, Martha, as I promised her when she was alive. Now send someone to fetch our ring and the golden gloves, which I placed in the hands of the sacristan while I laid the holy body in the tomb."
The people were amazed upon hearing this and sent messengers to Tarascon.
The people of Tarascon wrote to those in Perigueux about the unknown day and hour of the burial, and how a venerable person, along with their well-known bishop, attended the funeral.
They mentioned the booklet and its title, in case the bishop might have overlooked it.
The ring received by the sacristan was returned, while one glove was kept as a testament to the great miracle.
Some of those who served the ministers of the Savior returned to the East, spreading the word of God's kingdom.
Notably, Epaphras, Saint Marcella, and the blessed Syntyche, who was buried in Philippi and mentioned by the Apostle, ended her life in blessed peace.
Parmenas, filled with faith and grace, achieved the glory of martyrdom.
Germanus and Euchodia, bringing comfort to the faithful, assisted the blessed apostles, along with Saint Clement and their other co-workers, whose names are recorded in the book of life.
In the basilica of the most blessed Martha, from the day of her passing, countless miracles occurred.
The blind, deaf, mute, lame, paralyzed, withered, leprous, possessed, and those suffering from various ailments received all kinds of healings.
The king of the Franks and the Germans, Clovis, the first to embrace the Christian faith, was moved by the multitude and magnitude of the miracles of the most holy Martha, and he traveled to Tarascon.
Upon touching the saint's tomb, he was freed from the severe kidney illness he had been suffering from miserably.
In gratitude for such great power, he offered to God, sealed with his ring, land covering three leagues around the church of the most holy Martha, on both sides of the Rhone, including villages, fortresses, and forests, all of which the sacred woman possesses to this day with perpetual immunity.
Thefts, robberies, sacrileges, or false judgments are immediately and severely punished there by the judgment of God, to the praise of the Lord Savior.
CHAPTER 50 - On the passing and burial of the holy Archbishop Maximinus.
We've shared the religious life and precious death of the venerable servant of the Son of God, our Lord and Savior, the most holy Martha.
Now, let's briefly recount the wonders that occurred after her sacred passing, either through her or around her.
We'll save for a new beginning the life full of virtues and the passion of her brother, the blessed Lazarus, bishop and martyr.
We'll also mention the miracles performed through Mary Magdalene, beloved of God.
First, let's briefly recount the passing of the most holy Archbishop Maximinus.
As the time approached, revealed to him by the Holy Spirit, that he would leave this life to receive the reward for his labors from the merciful judge, he arranged for his burial place to be prepared within the basilica.
This basilica, which we've mentioned before, was beautifully constructed above the most holy remains of the blessed Mary Magdalene.
He requested that his sarcophagus be placed next to the mausoleum of the beloved of God.
After his holy passing, when his sacred body was honorably placed there by the faithful, the site became adorned with miraculous powers, providing spiritual and physical benefits to those who sought them through their intercession.
This place was later held in such reverence that no king, prince, or anyone with worldly grandeur dared to enter the church to seek favors without first laying down their arms, setting aside all beastly fierceness, and entering with complete humility and devotion.
No woman, regardless of her status, order, or dignity, ever presumed to enter this most sacred temple out of any rashness.
The monastery is called the Abbey of Saint Maximinus, built in the County of Aix, and is richly endowed with all things and honors.
The blessed Bishop Maximinus passed away on June 8th and was joyfully crowned in heaven.
Here ends the life of Blessed Mary Magdalene and her sister, Saint Martha.