On the Prophet Hosea
by Haymo Bishop of Halberstadt
Chapter One
The word of the Lord came to Hosea, son of Beeri, during the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, and during the days of Jeroboam, son of Joash, king of Israel.
We should understand that the word of the Lord here refers to what John says at the beginning of his Gospel: In the beginning was the Word.
This Word is not made in its nature but begotten by God the Father before all ages.
Therefore, when it is said here that the word of the Lord came to Hosea, it means that the word of God the Father was to be spoken to Hosea.
By speaking the word of the Lord to Hosea, He made him a god and savior of His people.
Hosea means "savior," as he was the one who, through teaching and the example of holiness, worked to save the people to whom he was sent.
However, the same Hosea and the other prophets who were called gods to whom this word came, the Lord reveals in the Gospel: If you (says the Lord) call them gods to whom the word of God came, etc.
Therefore, just as God makes people gods by speaking to them, so the Savior makes them saviors too.
Saints are called gods and saviors by grace, while there is only one Savior and God by nature.
It is important to note that it does not say: The word of the Lord came in Hosea, so it is not understood as if the word came through him to another, but to Hosea, to show that the word was specifically directed to him.
As Blessed Jerome explains, it is one thing for the Lord to speak in Hosea, and another to Hosea.
In Hosea, Hosea himself does not speak, but the word is directed through Hosea to others, as the Prophet says in the Psalm: I will hear what the Lord God will speak within me, for He will speak peace to His people.
This shows that through the one who spoke this, God was speaking to others.
But speaking to Hosea, He shows that the prophecy that follows specifically pertains to him when he is told: Go, take yourself a wife, etc.
He prophesied during the same time as Isaiah, Amos, Micah, Joel, Obadiah, and Jonah, as evidenced by the names of the kings mentioned in the titles of these prophets.
From this, we understand that he prophesied both before and after the captivity.
He predicted the captivity of the ten tribes, which he later lamented after witnessing it.
The son of Beeri.
The Hebrews say that whenever the names of the fathers or grandfathers of prophets are mentioned, the fathers or grandfathers themselves were also prophets.
Thus, it is clear that Beeri was a prophet, whose son is referred to as Hosea.
Hosea means, as we have said, "savior," and therefore signifies the Lord Christ, who is truly the Savior of the world. Hence, he is also called Jesus, to whom the following pertains. Thus, Hosea is called the son of Beeri, which means "my well." God the Father also says through the Prophet: "They have forsaken me, the fountain of living water, and dug for themselves cisterns, broken cisterns that cannot hold water."
The difference between a well and cisterns is that a well has perpetual water flowing from a living source, while a cistern has external, temporary water. The Prophet speaks of this source: "My soul thirsts for God, the living source." In the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah. Uzziah is also called Azariah elsewhere, who ruled in Jerusalem over the two tribes called Judah for 52 years. He was succeeded by his son Jotham, who ruled for 16 years. After him, his son Ahaz ruled for 16 years, in the eleventh year of whose reign the ten tribes were taken into captivity to the mountains of the Medes and Persians by Shalmaneser, king of the Chaldeans. After Ahaz, his son Hezekiah ruled for 29 years.
From this, it is clear, as we said above, that Hosea prophesied both before and after the captivity and the impending captivity itself. In the days of Jeroboam, son of Joash.
We shouldn't confuse this Jeroboam with the first king of the ten tribes, who was the son of Nabat.
The Jeroboam mentioned here was the son of Joash, the great-grandson of Jehu.
Jehu, after killing the wicked queen Jezebel and the two wicked kings, Joram, the son of Ahab, king of Samaria, along with his seventy brothers, and Ahaziah, king of Judah, was promised that his descendants would reign until the fourth generation.
However, since they returned to the sins of the kings of Israel, they quickly lost the kingdom.
The beginning of the Lord speaking in Hosea.
These words can be understood in two ways: either because the captivity of the ten tribes was first announced to him before Isaiah and the others who were his contemporaries, or because the first message given to him by the Lord was about the union with a prostitute.
Hence, it is immediately added: And the Lord said to Hosea: Go, take for yourself a wife of prostitution, and have children of prostitution, because the land will surely prostitute itself away from the Lord.
Although some argue that these things were done literally, excusing the prophet from the sin of prostitution since he obeyed God's commands, they do not consider that God never commands anything unjust or shameful.
However, it is better understood in a mystical sense, just as what was said to Ezekiel: You will lie on your left side for 390 days, and you will not turn to the other side, and again you will lie on your right side for 40 days.
Also, what was commanded to Jeremiah, who was imprisoned, to go to the Euphrates and hide the loincloth he possessed among the neighboring nations hostile to the people of Israel.
Although he could not even go out to sell his field among his own people, he was captured and bound by his own citizens as a traitor and informer and placed in prison, especially since Jerusalem was already besieged and surrounded by enemies.
As for the literal meaning, the wife of fornications is an adulteress who exposes herself to the lust of many and brings a stranger into her husband's life.
The children of fornications are those born from such a union.
He went and took Gomer, the daughter of Diblaim, and she conceived and bore a son.
Since all these things, as mentioned earlier, are to be understood spiritually, Hosea, which means savior, signifies the Lord Jesus Christ.
Through the mystery of the Incarnation, he took a wife of fornications—the Jewish people—who, abandoning the one true God, worshipped various demonic idols.
From this, he begot children of fornications, showing that all were under sin.
Hence, it is fitting that the wife of fornications is called Gomer, which means perfect or complete in evil work, undoubtedly referring to the same people.
Therefore, it is also fitting that she is called the daughter of Diblaim, which means pleasure, who always pursued her own pleasures.
She bore a son, representing a strong people in evil.
However, if we wish to scrutinize this more deeply and interpret it in a positive sense, the son born from the Israelite people is understood to be the Lord Jesus Christ, who, having joined the same people to himself through divinity, wished to be born from them through humanity.
This interpretation aligns with the meaning of the name by which the son is ordered to be called, for Jezreel means "seed of God."
Hence, it follows: And the Lord said to him: Call his name Jezreel, for in just a little while I will avenge the blood of Jezreel upon the house of Jehu. Jezreel means "seed of God."
In the literal sense, it was a metropolitan city in the kingdom of the ten tribes where Naboth was killed, for whose blood Jehu was raised up to avenge, destroying the house of Ahab and Jezebel. But because Jehu himself was the avenger of the blood of the righteous, and his sons did evil in the sight of the Lord, the blood of Ahab was poured out on his house, meaning it came back upon them when his sons were led into captivity and killed.
Not long after, both the kingdom and the kings ceased to exist.
Jeroboam, the great-grandson of Jehu, under whom Hosea began to prophesy, died, and his son Zechariah succeeded him as king.
In the sixth month of Zechariah's reign, he was killed by Shallum, who came from a different lineage.
Immediately, the Assyrian kings captured Reuben, Gad, and half the tribe of Manasseh, who were across the Jordan, then Naphtali, and eventually all the remaining tribes.
From Zechariah to Hosea, under whom all ten tribes were taken into captivity, only forty-nine years passed.
Hence, it is said: "Yet a little while, and the punishment of the house of Jehu will be completed."
Spiritually, Jehu, through whom the blood in Jezreel is said to be avenged, signifies the Jews, by whom the blood of Christ was shed. We have described this as being designated by the name Jezreel, whose blood was avenged upon them when they were killed by the Romans and taken into exile into all lands. To this day, they remain exiles from their own land.
"And I will cause the kingdom of the house of Israel to cease, and on that day I will break the bow of Israel in the valley of Jezreel."
We mentioned earlier that Jezreel was the capital city of the ten tribes, near which lies a vast valley, stretching more than ten thousand paces. In this valley, Israel of the ten tribes was slaughtered by the Assyrians, whose strength is symbolized by the bow.
According to mystical interpretation, all who think ill of Christ, such as heretics who depart from the house of David, that is, from the Church, are represented by the name Israel. In the valley of Jezreel, meaning in the humility of the seed of God, they are crushed, because the Father judges no one but has given all judgment to the Son.
And she conceived again and bore a daughter, and He said: Call her name "No Mercy," for I will no longer have mercy on the house of Israel but will utterly forget them. However, I will have mercy on the house of Judah and will save them by the Lord their God, not by bow, sword, war, horses, or horsemen.
When the Jews were stripped of their strength, they were referred to in the feminine, symbolizing fragility and weakness.
Thus, they were aptly called a daughter because they had a feminine spirit; they abandoned God and worshipped vain idols.
They were shown no mercy and were forgotten, continuing to serve the Persian kings with no end to their captivity.
However, the house of Judah and the two tribes allied with it received mercy because of their trust in God.
An angel was sent to strike down Sennacherib's army, one hundred eighty-five thousand strong.
"I will save them," He said, "in the Lord their God," meaning under the protection of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
Just as the Lord rained fire from the heavens, the Son from God the Father,
He will not save them through bow, sword, battle, or horses—no human strength or cavalry—but through the Lord their God, who will send His angel to defeat their enemies.
If this applies to those present at the coming of the Lord, they too are called a daughter, not a son, because they pursued their desires and called down God's seed's blood upon themselves, saying, "His blood be on us and on our children."
Thus, without mercy, they were handed over to the Romans, condemned to perpetual servitude, and forgotten.
But the house of Judah—meaning confession, such as the apostles and others who believed or taught in Christ's name—were saved not by sword or bow, but by the Lord their God, Christ, who chose them by His grace.
By the name daughter, we can also understand heretics, who, following vain doctrines and weakening the divine Scripture's meanings, are consigned to the devil, facing eternal damnation without mercy, perpetually forgotten by God.
The house of Judah, which is the Catholic Church, faithfully confesses the faith of the Holy Trinity in an inseparable unity.
They will be saved in the Lord their God, not by the multitude of armies or by their own strength.
And she who was without mercy was weaned.
One who is weaned leaves the mother and does not feed on the parent's milk but is sustained by different foods.
In ancient times, it was customary to hold a feast for neighbors and friends on the day of an infant's weaning, marking their separation from milk.
Therefore, the mother of Samuel said she would not go to the temple of the Lord until the child was weaned, meaning until he reached the age when he could be moved from milk.
In Holy Scripture, milk represents simple understanding.
The Jews were nourished by milk as long as they stayed within their law, reading the Scriptures.
But after being taken into captivity, they began to be fed by the food of the Gentiles and ate what was offered to idols.
From this, they fell into such misery that they lost even the small amount of knowledge they had, to the point where they could not even understand the surface of the law.
She conceived and gave birth to a son and said: Call his name, Not My People; because you are not my people, and I will not be your God.
The number of the children of Israel shall be like the sand of the sea, which cannot be measured or counted.
And in the place where it was said to them, You are not my people; it shall be said to them, You are the children of the living God.
These words can also refer to those who were captured by the kings of Assyria and taken into captivity, and to those who after the coming of the Lord were dispersed by the Romans among all nations.
They rejected God through idol worship, and after the denial and betrayal of the Son of God, they cannot have the Father without the Son.
Therefore, God rejected them so they would no longer be His people, but instead become servants of the devil.
And it would be said to them:
"Because you are not My people, I will not be your God. I will judge you unworthy of My possession and presence, and I will reject you forever."
This can also be understood to refer to heretics, who, by rejecting God and holding twisted beliefs about Him, are completely repelled by Him. They cannot say with the chosen ones:
"The Lord is my inheritance."
The number of the children of Israel will be as mentioned above. Although the Jews were oppressed back then and are now under severe captivity, they are still innumerable. As Isaiah says:
"If the number of the children of Israel is like the sand of the sea, the remnant will be saved."
This can be understood as being fulfilled both at the coming of the Lord and at the end of the world. After the people of Israel have been scattered throughout the world and their multitude has surpassed all counting, Israel, which is now in captivity, will have freedom.
And it will be in the place where it was said to them:
"You are not My people," as mentioned above.
We should understand this place to be Jerusalem, where it is now said to them:
"You are not My people," but it will be said to them, "Children of the living God," in the time of the Lord's Incarnation.
This was fulfilled in the apostles and other believers. For, as John says, all who believed in Christ were given the power to become children of God.
If we want to refer this to the Jews of today, the place where it is said to them:
"You are not My people," is understood to be the whole world. Because now, Jews in all nations are confirmed to be not servants of God, but of the devil.
However, when they believe through the preaching of Elijah and Enoch, they will be called children of God by all nations.
The children of Judah and the children of Israel will be gathered together, and they will appoint one leader for themselves. Judah signifies those two joined tribes, namely the tribe of Benjamin and the priestly tribe, the Levites. Because of the tribe of Judah, from which the kings who ruled over these tribes originated, these two tribes were also called by the name of Judah.
Most of the ten tribes retain the original name of Israel because, before the division of the ten tribes and the two, everyone was generally called by this name.
So, to those who were divided, it is promised that they will be gathered together as one by the Lord.
Indeed, at the time of the Lord's incarnation and resurrection, those who had returned from captivity, both from the ten tribes and the two tribes, were living in Judea, and many of them believed in Christ.
It is said here: The children of Judah and the children of Israel will be gathered together, that is, believers from the two and the ten tribes will come together into one flock of Christ.
And they will appoint for themselves one leader, namely the Lord Jesus Christ, about whom Ezekiel says: And one prince will be among them, my servant David.
Or we can understand Israel as representing the Gentiles and Judah as representing the Jewish believers; or Israel as representing heretics and Judah as representing Catholic men.
All of them, having converted to the unity of Christian faith, will appoint for themselves one leader, Jesus Christ.
And they will ascend from the earth, meaning from earthly senses and the humility of the declining letter; and they will be elevated to spiritual and vital understanding, because the great day of Jezreel is near.
Here, the day represents the entire time from the Lord’s birth to the end of the world, about which we sing in the Psalms: This is the day the Lord has made.
This is a great day, meaning it is a great period during which the remission of sins is granted to believers, and the door to the heavenly kingdom is opened.
Chapter Two
Tell your brothers, "You are my people," and your sisters, "You have received mercy."
If we want to apply this to the Jews, it encourages the people of Judea not to lose hope about the salvation of the ten tribes. Instead, they should daily encourage them to repent through words, prayer, and letters, because they are called brothers and sisters.
Brothers, as it says, "My people"; sisters, as it is called, "She who has received mercy."
If we want to apply this to the Gentiles, it tells them to say to those who remain in unbelief: "You will be my people if you believe in me and are willing to transition from old ways to a new life."
Or, you who believe in me and adorn your faith with good works, tell the remaining believers: "They will be my people if they believe in me, remain in the faith they were called to, and strive to adorn it with good works."
Also, tell your sister—that is, the same people who believe in Christ—that she has received mercy by believing in me.
Judge your mother, judge her, because she is not my wife, and I am not her husband. This is said to the apostles and other believers to judge, that is, to rebuke their mother, the synagogue, which, having become a wife from a harlot, does not abandon her old ways.
But again, rebuke your mother because she has committed adultery with her lovers again. Consider the patience and mercy of this man, who again urges his children to rebuke their mother because she has remained in unbelief while they believed.
This was fulfilled then when Peter told the weeping Jews: "Repent, and be baptized every one of you," etc. He says, show her that she is not my wife, and I am not her husband.
Because she has rejected me, I will also reject her so that I am not her husband. Indeed, Christ is the husband of the Church, about whom the heretics say to the same Church: "There is no husband in her house."
Let her remove her fornications from her face and her adulteries from between her breasts.
Sexual immorality or adultery in sacred scripture is understood in two ways: as impurity of the flesh and as idolatry.
As it is written: "You will destroy all who are unfaithful to you."
A woman commits sexual immorality or adultery when she is open to the lust of many or brings another man into her husband's life. Because God is the husband of the soul, the people of Israel had subjected themselves to many acts of unfaithfulness. They abandoned the almighty God and worshipped many demonic idols.
Therefore, it is now said: "Let her remove her sexual immorality from her face," meaning, let her remove the worship of gods from her love and presence. For she had been open to the lust of many by worshipping the gods of all nations. Let her also remove her adulteries from between her breasts, meaning from her heart, where evil deeds are first conceived.
The heart is indeed between the breasts, from which, as the Lord reveals, evil thoughts come. They first thought evil in their heart, and thus eventually brought these thoughts into wicked actions. Therefore, the divine word urges her to remove all these things from herself, lest she lose the good things given to her by God because of her committed crimes.
He says, "Lest I strip her naked and set her as on the day of her birth." The garment with which that people were covered is understood as God's help, the teaching of the law and the prophets, and the protection of angels. All these things God Almighty threatens to take away from her unless she repents of her committed crimes, so that she becomes naked and full of shame, as she once was.
And He says, "I will set her as on the day of her birth," meaning she will lack all these things, as she once did while living in Egypt. "And I will make her like a wilderness, and set her like an impassable land." A house becomes a wilderness when it loses its proper master. This people were reduced to a wilderness when God Almighty departed from them because of their sins.
Hence the Prophet says: "I have left my house; I have abandoned my inheritance," etc. And in the Gospel, He Himself threatens them that He will leave them, saying: "Behold, your house is left to you desolate."
There was also a kind of wasteland, because having lost the right path of faith, it lost God the Father and His Son who says, "I am the way."
And I will kill her with thirst, that is, with the lack of all good things, or with the thirst the prophet Joel speaks of: "I will send a famine and thirst upon them, not a famine of bread or a thirst for water, but a famine for hearing the word of God."
Or the water that was taken away from them, we can understand as the grace of the Holy Spirit, about which He Himself speaks in the Gospel, inviting all to Him to receive this water from Him: "If anyone is thirsty, let him come to me and drink, and rivers of living water will flow from his belly."
All these things apply to the Jews who deny Christ, and to heretics abandoning the true faith, following various erroneous doctrines in their hearts, words, and actions. Unless they repent, stripped of all virtues they received in the Church, they will be reduced to their state on the day of their birth, and having become a wasteland and impassable land, will suffer the thirst or dryness of Holy Scripture, so that even what they falsely seemed to have will be reduced to nothing.
And I will not have mercy on her children, because they are children of fornications, because their mother has committed fornication. When the Jews came out of Egypt, the Lord, angry with their fathers, killed them in the desert.
However, He had mercy on their children, preserved them for life, and gave them the land He had promised to their fathers. But now He threatens not to act this way, saying: "I will not have mercy on her children, but they will go into captivity along with their fathers, and there they will die, and they will never see the land of their birth again, because they are children of fornications," that is, they were born in the worship of idols. As their fathers held such faith, so they taught their children. Hence it is added: "Because their mother has committed fornication." Just as a viper gives birth to a viper, so this people have produced children like themselves. She was confounded, that is, astonished and turned to wonder, the one who conceived them and made them children of the devil.
Because she said: "I will go after my lovers, who give me my bread and water, my wool and linen, my oil and drink." The Jews said this while worshiping the gods of various nations.
"I will go," she said, "after my lovers," meaning, I will follow the gods with faith and love, or I will imitate the nations whose gods I worship, who give me bread and water, etc. For all the good things that the same people had received from God from heaven, they thought they had from demons, and they attributed everything to them.
This can also be spiritually referred to those who denied the Son of God, choosing Barabbas, the author of rebellion, for themselves, and crucifying the Son of God, the giver of all good things. Therefore, they were confused, and not only cursed themselves but also their descendants with a terrible curse, saying: "His blood is on us and on our children."
These words can also be understood literally in their explanation about heretics, who are confused; but also their children, born from bad doctrine, are ashamed with them. The reason for their confusion is revealed when it is added, because she said: "I will go after my lovers," meaning, I will follow the various doctrines of heretics, whose bread is eternal sorrow. And the water is perverse and foolish doctrine, by which they even kill those baptized. This water is contrary to that which is written: "Deep water from the mouth of a man."
By wool and linen, their simulated sanctity and purity are expressed. The Lord warns to beware of them, saying: "Because they will come to you in sheep's clothing, but inwardly they are ravenous wolves." By oil, their flattery is understood. Of which the Prophet says: "Let not the oil of the sinner anoint my head." Their drink also is understood as the holy Scripture, which they make muddy by misunderstanding.
Therefore, behold, I will block your way with thorns, and I will block it with a wall, and she will not find her paths. By thorns, the pricks of sorrow and the hardness of adversity are expressed. By the wall, an obstacle is meant, so that what she was seeking, she could not find.
I will block your path with thorns, meaning I will entangle your actions with the hardest of labors.
I will also block it with a wall so you can't reach what you desire.
Furthermore, the phrase "and she will not find her paths" has the same meaning. But as is common in prophetic speech, it abruptly shifts from one person to another.
She will follow her lovers, the Assyrians or Chaldeans, seeking help from them when faced with severe tribulation. However, she will not find them willing to help her; instead, she will be captured by them and taken captive. She will seek them but will not find them favorable. Then she will say: I will go back to my former husband. That is, I will return to Almighty God, who once betrothed me through the given law, because it was well with me then, as long as I obeyed His commands.
More so now, when I am afflicted by various tribulations because of idol worship. Indeed, the people of Israel, often raised by prosperity, would turn away from God by worshiping idols. But again, when afflicted by calamities, they returned to God, who raised up a Savior for them and delivered them.
These words apply both generally and specifically to us, who, raised by prosperity, sometimes go against God's commands. Yet again, when worn down by afflictions, we return to ourselves, recognize our sins, and seek His mercy, remembering how well it was under His protection. This often happens to those who, placed in the world, seek the riches and honors of the world. But, unable to attain them, are so troubled by various tribulations that they reluctantly leave the world: and, setting aside temporal cares, which they cannot achieve as they wish, they flee to a monastery.
And those who were once distressed because they did not have everything they wanted, rejoice, content with food and clothing, according to the Apostle, and serve God in poverty, who previously served the world and its desires. And she did not know that I gave her grain, wine, and oil, and silver, and I multiplied gold for her, which they used for Baal.
It was mentioned earlier that the people of Israel attributed all the temporary blessings they received from God to idols, not realizing that God Almighty had made them abundant in all these things.
Therefore, abandoning God, they made for themselves the idol Baal of the Sidonians from the gold and silver they had received for adornment, as the prophet Ezekiel describes in more detail in his book.
If we want to understand these words spiritually, we should take the grain to mean the law by which they should have been nourished; the wine, spiritual joy, which they should have had not in temporary goods, but in God; the oil, the illumination of understanding; the silver, the brilliance of eloquence, of which it is written: "The words of the Lord are pure words, like silver refined in a furnace" (Psalms 12:6); and the gold, the commandment to love God and neighbor.
In all these things, where they should have glorified God, they preferred to worship demons rather than God.
Therefore, says the Lord, I will turn from my mercy to cruelty, and I will take back my grain in its time, and my wine in its season.
The time for these fruits is when they are brought to maturity and gathered, and stored in cellars to provide sustenance throughout the year.
If at that time, when maturity is imminent, they are taken away from the people who should have gathered them, they are afflicted with the greatest sorrow.
He threatens to take this away from the Jews so that they suffer from famine throughout the year.
For often God, because of the sins of the people, sends a storm at harvest and vintage time, and takes away the fruits prepared for gathering.
And I will rescue my wool and my linen that covered her shame.
In some manuscripts, it is falsely written as "I will balance," whereas it should be read as "I will rescue." For they had the wool and linen under their servitude, while they themselves were servants of the devil. Therefore, God says: I will rescue my linen and my wool, so they are not possessed by wicked masters. Furthermore, the shame that these covered refers to their idols, whose altars were adorned with various decorations of garments.
Spiritual garments symbolize God's help and the protection of angels.
When people fail to recognize the giver, God removes these blessings, leaving them in their wickedness and handing them over to the devil for eternal torment.
And then I will reveal his folly in the eyes of his lovers.
He calls idols folly, which they had placed in the temple.
And he calls the lovers the Chaldeans, the Assyrians, and the Edomites, with whom they had long had peace.
In whose eyes the folly of the Jews was revealed when Jerusalem was captured and the temple was destroyed.
Seeing the images of Cherubim and the idol Baal, the aforementioned enemies began to say:
Behold, the Israelites, like all other nations, worship idols.
Which is why they rightfully fall under our power due to their wickedness.
And no man will rescue her from my hand.
This means that by no force or strength will she be freed from my hand.
But I will deliver her to the enemies by just judgment, and I will lead her into captivity.
And I will put an end to all her joy.
This was fulfilled in those who were taken captive by the Assyrians and Chaldeans, where they lost all joy.
And later in those who heard from the Lord: The kingdom of God will be taken away from you.
And: Your house will be left desolate.
Her solemnity, her new moon, her Sabbath, and all her festive times, it is implied, I will put to an end.
When he says solemnity, he puts one for all.
Or certainly in this specific name, he wants to be understood as the festival of Passover, which they were accustomed to celebrating honorably in memory of their liberation.
He calls the new moon the renewal of the moon, as they used to celebrate such a festival with joy at the beginning of each month.
On the Sabbaths, they also rested in leisure and feasts.
They also had other festivals, such as Pentecost, the festival of Tabernacles, the dedication of the temple, and other similar ones.
All of which were taken away from them when they were placed in captivity, where they were not permitted to celebrate these festivals with joy according to their custom, nor to rest in leisure.
All these things taken away by them are now celebrated spiritually in the Church.
And I will destroy her vineyard and her fig tree, namely by hail, drought, and frost, so that she has no fruitful tree.
Spiritually, the vineyard signifies the joy of the heart, while the fig tree represents sweetness and pleasantness, which have been taken from them.
Hence they are in sorrow and bitterness, as it was said: "These are my wages which my lovers gave me."
He explains why he took away the goods mentioned earlier, saying, "These are my wages," etc.
For he thought these were given to him by demons as a reward because he worshiped idols.
And I will make her a forest so she no longer has fruit-bearing trees but is entirely reduced to desolation.
This was partly done by the Assyrians and Chaldeans, but more fully completed by the Romans, who destroyed their land, reduced it to desolation, and also made them exiles with the final captivity from their land.
Hence it follows, "and the beast of the field will eat her," referring to the Roman army.
About this beast, the Psalmist says: "The wild boar from the forest ravaged it."
Or certainly, we can understand this beast as the devil, who devours them when he draws them to his cult, for which they later suffered destruction.
What was said about the Jews can also be applied to heretics, who, when they leave the Church, are abandoned by God, and their foolishness is revealed to those who were previously their admirers.
And being handed over to the beast, that is, the devil, they are torn by his bites and punished with eternal death.
And I will visit upon her the days of the Baals, during which she burned incense, adorned herself with her earrings and jewelry, and went after her lovers, and forgot me, says the Lord.
He still maintains the persona of the harlot woman, who adorns herself with gold and gems to please her lovers, and whatever beauty she lacks by nature, she acquires by art.
"I will visit upon her the days of the Baals," meaning, for the days she worshipped Baal, I will bring upon her the affliction of tribulation.
Here, "visitation" is placed in a negative context, referring to the distress, tribulation, slaughter, and captivity that came upon the Jews because of idol worship.
However, "visitation" is also used in a positive context, as in:
"The rising sun will visit us from heaven" and "Visit us with your salvation."
He says, "I will visit upon her," undoubtedly referring to Judea during the days of Baal, when they burned incense not to God but to demons.
Baal in the singular and Baalim in the plural, both masculine, refer to the same idols. Whenever the syllable "im" is found at the end of a Hebrew word, it indicates a masculine plural. However, when it is "oth," as in "sabaoth," it indicates a feminine plural.
Thus, cherubim and seraphim are masculine plurals, while sabaoth, which means "armies" or "hosts" or "virtues," is a feminine plural. Therefore, Baalim is a masculine plural, although some incorrectly read it as feminine.
The Jewish people adorned themselves with earrings and necklaces to please their lovers, that is, demons; they should have adorned their ears to conceive the spiritual precepts of God in their hearts, and their necks to proclaim them to others. They acted this way because, by following demons, they forgot God, who should have been their husband.
Heretics burned incense to Baalim when they followed the perverse doctrines they created as idols for themselves. They also adorned their ears, with which they hear words, and their necks, with which they speak, to please those they ensnare with the charm of their speech.
For divine words are also understood as necklaces, about which it is said to the Church:
"Your neck is like necklaces,"
which they would not do if they had not forgotten God.
Therefore, behold, I will allure her and lead her into the wilderness. For the Lord is merciful and gracious. Although He had previously threatened them with evil, He promises salvation to the same people so they do not despair, saying:
"Therefore, because I am merciful, I will allure her, that is, I will coax her to return to me."
Where it says: Repent, for the kingdom of heaven is near; and: Come to me, all who labor, etc.
And I will lead her into the wilderness—that is, I will free her again from captivity, just as I previously led her out of Egyptian servitude.
Just as I then led them through the desert wilderness, protecting and freeing them from every enemy, I will do the same when I bring them back from the land of their captivity to their own native soil.
And I will speak to her heart—that is, I will offer her gentle and comforting words, so I may relieve her sorrow with joy.
For this is what it means to speak to the heart.
Where it says: Shechem spoke to the heart of Dinah; and Joseph, after being recognized by his brothers, is said to speak to their hearts.
This was fulfilled when the Son of God, who speaks here through the prophet, appearing in the flesh, says to the apostles, indeed to all his disciples from that people who believe in him: I no longer call you servants, but my friends; he even calls them children, saying: Little children, I am still with you.
And I will give her vine-dressers from the same place.
Isaiah shows what this vineyard is, who says: The vineyard of the Lord of hosts is the house of Israel.
And David: You brought a vine out of Egypt.
Vine-dressers were given to it, first when coming out of Egypt, Moses and Aaron, and others who at that time, by word and example, cultivated that vineyard with good works.
Then, when returning from Babylonian captivity, Zerubbabel, Joshua, Nehemiah, and Ezra, and other prophets, who were good cultivators of it.
Also, at his coming, he gave her the best vine-dressers, namely the apostles, who were all from the same place—that is, from the same Israelite people.
And the valley of Achor for a door of hope.
Here it is necessary to recall the old story.
We read in the book of Joshua, that when the children of Israel had taken Jericho, Joshua cursed it and all that was in it.
And Achan son of Carmi, seeing certain things among the spoils of the city that were pleasing to him, took from the cursed things.
Since the children of Israel could not withstand their enemies and had consulted the Lord about it, He responded that they were defeated because of what Achan had done.
Joshua had him stoned by all the children of Israel.
The place of his execution was called the Valley of Achor, which means the Valley of Trouble, because Joshua said, "You have troubled us, the Lord will trouble you this day."
After his execution, the children of Israel had hope for future victory, and they went on to capture the town of Ai, killing its inhabitants. Their sorrow turned into joy, and they found hope where there had been despair.
Since it is certain that this happened, as stated, let's see what the prophetic words mean, which speak of the future, saying: "And the Valley of Achor will be a door of hope." Therefore, it must be understood that just as after Achan was killed, the Jews had hope of defeating their enemies, and they were not disappointed; likewise, after Jerusalem was destroyed by the Romans, the temple was burned, and the Jews were killed and scattered throughout the world, the apostles and other believers had hope of victory. They brought the entire world to the faith of Christ, and what had been foreshadowed—the temple and all the ceremonial observances—was turned into spiritual understanding, as is now done in the Church by the faithful.
This was their hope of victory, of which it is spoken here: "And the Valley of Achor will be a door of hope," implying "I will give." And she will sing there as in the days of her youth, and as in the days when she came up from the land of Egypt.
Even now, history maintains a similarity. In Exodus, it is read that after Pharaoh and his army were drowned in the Red Sea, the children of Israel sang a song to the Lord, saying: "Let us sing to the Lord," etc. That time of their youth is called a day because then the same people grew in faith and religion of God, for before they worshiped idols, that is, the calves of the Egyptians. Hence, later they made a calf, saying: "These are your gods, Israel," etc.
It's fittingly said: In the days of His ascension from the land of Egypt, because Egypt is in the plain, but the land of promise is mountainous.
Therefore, those traveling from Egypt to Judea are said to ascend, just as the Lord frequently reminded them: I made you ascend from the land of Egypt.
Now, let's explore the mystery.
Egypt, interpreted as darkness or sorrow, signifies the infidelity of the Jews.
The Red Sea represents baptism, consecrated by faith in the Lord's passion.
Pharaoh and his army drowning in the Red Sea symbolize the devil and original sins, which are washed away in baptism.
The desert, through which they traveled after crossing the Red Sea, being fed with manna and water from the rock, symbolizes this present life.
Here, the faithful receive manna and water from the rock, which represents the body and blood of Christ, or the teachings of divine eloquence.
The land of promise signifies the heavenly homeland, reached after baptism and the struggles of this life.
It is promised to the congregation of believers that, just as the believers then sang a song to the Lord after Pharaoh's destruction, they, after emerging from the darkness of infidelity, will, after the devil's defeat and the suppression of vices, transition with joy and gladness to the heavenly homeland, where the land of the living is.
Rightly, those traveling from Egypt are said to ascend, because we ascend when we strive to move from earthly things to heavenly things, from vices to virtues.
And it shall be on that day, says the Lord, every man will call Me his husband, and will no longer call Me Baal.
I will remove the name of Baal from his mouth, and they will no longer remember their name.
Regarding the name of Baal, literally, this must be said: Belus was the father of Ninus, the first king of the Assyrians, who named the city he built after himself, calling it Ninus, which the Hebrews and our people call Nineveh.
He made his father Belus into a god, creating an idol named Bel, which he desired everyone to worship.
By what name it is called by the Babylonians, as it is written in Daniel: the Sidonians and Phoenicians call it Baal, but the Hebrews call it Beelzebub due to the filth and impurities of sacrificial blood.
This means "the man of flies" or "having flies." Because it was worshiped in many places, it is pronounced in the plural as Baalim.
Now, let's see what these words of the Lord mean when He speaks of the faithful people, saying: They will no longer call me Baalim. As we mentioned, Baalim is the same as Baal, translating to "Baal possessing," but Baalim means "possessing me." Hence, Hebrew and Syrian women call their husbands by this name, saying: My Baal, meaning "possessing me" in marriage.
There's also another name in the same language with the same meaning, Is, which sounds like "man." Therefore, a woman is called Issa, as if "virago," because she was taken from her man. Those who do not want to call their husbands Baal or Baalim, call them by another name, Is meus, meaning "my man," signifying possession in marriage.
Thus, when the Lord says: They will not call me Baalim, but will call me "my man," it is to be understood as wanting to show me as their man. They will never call me Baalim, which could be said well, but will call me Is, meaning "my man." For God so dislikes the names of idols that He does not even want His chosen ones to remember them. Therefore, He says of the faithful people: They will no longer call me Baalim, because of the ambiguity of the word. Lest, while saying one thing, they remember another, and by calling a man, think of an idol.
Hence, it is also added: And I will take away the names of the Baalim from their mouths, and they will no longer remember their names. And I will make a covenant with them in that day, with the beasts of the field, and with the birds of the sky, and with the creeping things of the earth. Here, the union of the Jews and the Gentiles in the unity of the faith of Christ is clearly described, as they were separated from each other before His coming.
So, the Jews used to exclude the Gentiles from their community.
But later, as they came together into one fold of Christ, they now boast of having peace and brotherly love in one faith in the Almighty God.
Hence, Isaiah says to this same people: "Your former stranger will join you, so that he will no longer be a stranger, but will be recognized as a brother." For the Gentiles are represented by the names of animals, birds, and serpents, because they worshiped these as gods. But having been purified from these, they are no longer called by these names, but are called rational humans.
So, when Peter saw the sheet sent down to him from heaven, in which animals, birds, and serpents were shown, and he heard that he had to kill and eat them, he responded, "No, Lord, for nothing common or unclean has ever entered my mouth." It was said to him, "What God has purified, do not call common." And I will break the bow, the sword, and the battle from the earth. That means, I will give the utmost peace and tranquility on earth, that is, in the Church. Although many wars increase on earth, yet compared to that time, great is the peace among people, especially among the elect, among whom no seed of discord finds a place.
About this time Isaiah says: "Nation will not lift up sword against nation, nor will they train for war anymore." And I will make them sleep securely, that is, I will make them rest in my faith and peace. Or certainly, this sleep is understood as the rest of the elect, who now quietly sleep in the hope of the future resurrection. And I will betroth you to me forever, and I will betroth you to me in righteousness and justice, and in mercy and compassion, and I will betroth you to me in faith; and you will know that I am the Lord. It should be noted that He promises to betroth the same people to Himself three times. First, He betrothed them in Abraham, to whom He gave the sign of circumcision to be a sign between God and his offspring forever, or also when He led them out of Egypt. Second, on Mount Sinai, giving them the law.
Therefore, it is said in the second place: I will betroth you to me in justice, which means observing the law and following my commandments, so you can live justly and understand the difference between good and evil; and in mercy and compassion, so that if you are handed over to captivity because of your sins and then repent, you will receive mercy once again.
Thirdly, with the coming of the Son of God, it is also said: And I will betroth you to me in faith, that is, in the holy Trinity.
About this betrothal, the Apostle, speaking of Christ, says: I have betrothed you to one husband to present you as a pure virgin to Christ.
And again, speaking of Christ, he says: He has betrothed the Church to himself, not having spot or wrinkle.
But the Synagogue, betrothed three times by the Lord, made all the betrothals void.
It did not keep the first betrothal in Egypt and worshipped foreign gods.
Then, it was taken again by the law and the sacred Scriptures of the prophets of the Old Testament, as if confirmed by second betrothals, so that it would not withdraw from the embrace.
Thirdly, Jesus Christ, the Son of God, wished to unite it to himself through the grace of the holy Gospel.
However, with few believing, the majority neglected the presented betrothals and remained in unbelief, as the blessed Stephen reproaches them, saying: You always resist the Holy Spirit, just as your fathers did.
However, those who received his faith were joined to him by the bond of love, believing that he was Christ God, whom they had previously denied.
Among these were those who, at the preaching of the blessed Peter, believed—five thousand in one day, and three thousand on another day.
And it will be on that day: I will respond, says the Lord, and I will respond to the heavens, and they will respond to the earth, and the earth will respond to the grain, the wine, and the oil, and they will respond to Jezreel.
According to the letter, this means the Lord promises material goods to those who believe in him.
Spiritually, the heavens represent the apostles, of whom the Psalmist says: The heavens declare the glory of God, etc.
These heavens were heard in their time.
Asking for the Lord's incarnation, praying for the Canaanite woman and Peter's mother-in-law.
Now, the heavens listen to the earth, meaning the people living in the Church, and this earth listens to the wheat, which represents the simple teachings of the Old and New Testaments.
This fulfills the Lord's saying: Blessed is that servant whom his Lord has set over his household to give them their measure of wheat at the proper time.
The wine will be heard, providing spiritual understanding and bringing joy to the hearts of the listeners.
The speech of the teachers should be tailored to the quality of the listeners.
It also hears the oil, as bishops and priests give the faithful the grace of the Holy Spirit.
This is heaven and earth, namely the apostles and the universal Church.
And these will listen to Jezreel, the seed of the Word of God, leading to action so that this seed produces a hundredfold, sixtyfold, or thirtyfold fruit.
Furthermore, it follows: And I will sow her in the lands.
This pertains especially to the apostles who were sown from Jerusalem, so that through their preaching and miracles, the earth (the hearts of their listeners) would bear fruit.
Of these, it is written: These are the seed whom the Lord has blessed.
For the apostles themselves are both the seed, because they are dispersed throughout the whole world, hearing from the Lord and going into all the world.
They are also the sowers, as it is said: Their sound has gone out into all the earth.
And I will have mercy on her who was without mercy, that is, the Synagogue now believing in me, which before, while it wandered through many demonic wonders and worshiped them as God, was without mercy.
And I will say to not my people: You are my people; and they will say to me: You are my Lord.
This is what he says to his faithful from that same people: You are the ones who have remained with me in my trials, and I appoint to you, as my Father appointed to me, a kingdom.
And he himself says: You are my God, just as Peter said: You are the Christ, the Son of the living God; and Thomas: My Lord and my God.
The words can specifically refer to the ten tribes and generally to all Israelites, particularly those who believed.
Chapter Three
And the Lord said to me: Go again, and love a woman who is loved by a friend and is an adulteress, just as the Lord loves the children of Israel, but they turn to other gods and love raisin cakes.
Through these two women, the former prostitute named Gomer, and the adulteress, we should understand Israel and Judah.
This refers to the ten tribes in Samaria under King Jeroboam from Ephraim, and Judah, who reigned in Jerusalem from the line of David.
Ezekiel describes these two women as sisters, Oholah and Oholibah.
If we want to distinguish them more carefully, the former, called a prostitute, represents the ten tribes, while the latter, called an adulteress, represents Judah.
In general, through both of them, the entire Israelite people can be understood, as will be shown in what follows.
According to the letter, it is to be understood as it says, Go again, etc.
The sense is this: You love her, but she does not love you in return as she should.
She neglects your love and is an adulteress, as she is joined to another man and loves him more than you.
This is revealed when it is added: Just as the Lord loves the children of Israel.
Just as you love that woman, yet she loves another more than you, so the Lord loves the children of Israel with supreme love.
But they, spurning Him, turn to other gods, venerate and worship them, and love raisin cakes.
He calls raisin cakes what we call grape skins, the husks of grapes thrown out after being pressed.
Spiritually, these raisin cakes represent demons, who, when they were in their dignity, were like grapes, filled with the richness of the Holy Spirit.
But after they, in their pride, wanted to become like God, they were emptied of the grace of the Holy Spirit.
They became barren and, as if useless, were cast out of heaven, withering in old dryness and possessing none of their former grace.
Thus, the Jews, due to their lack of faith, were abandoned by God and now love demons that are void of any sweetness of goodness.
Or we can understand by "dregs" the traditions of the scribes and Pharisees, completely empty of truth and full of superstition, which the Jews loved, abandoning the traditions of God for the traditions of men.
And I bought her for fifteen silver pieces, and a homer of barley, and a half homer of barley, and said to her, The seventy translators, as the blessed Jerome says, for what our interpretation has as "I bought," they put "I hired," which indeed pertains to a woman, because she is hired for this purpose, to remain faithful to her husband, and not to join another while he lives. But when he says, "I bought her for myself as a wife," he shows he wants to signify the vineyard, which, as the prophet testifies, is the house of Israel, of which it is written: "You brought a vineyard out of Egypt."
Therefore, this woman is bought and hired for fifteen silver pieces, and a homer of barley, and a half homer of barley, which is forty-five measures, for a homer has thirty measures, and a half homer has fifteen. And having been hired for this price, she heard from the Lord: "You will wait for me many days; you will not commit adultery, and you will not be for another man." This means: you will not disgracefully prostitute yourself to lovers, nor will you be joined to me, your lawful husband, from whom you were hired, and don't think you have been wronged; for I said: "You will wait for me," I will repay you equally, for I too will wait for you.
Mystically, the fifteen silver pieces pertain to the fifteenth day of the first month, that is Nisan, when the Jews left Egypt, after the firstborn of the Egyptians were struck down. For on that very day, that is the fifteenth moon, the Lord brought them out of Egypt and hired them into His service, liberating them by the slaughter of the lamb from the plague brought upon the Egyptians. And He began to teach them, establishing for the firstborn of His sons, who did not feel the common plague, five silver shekels to be offered in the offerings of the house of God.
On the forty-fifth day, which is symbolized by forty-five measures of barley, they arrived at Mount Sinai.
The next day, Moses was instructed to sanctify the people for three days, abstain from women, and prepare to receive the law.
After three days, on the fiftieth day, Moses received the Ten Commandments.
Thus, those who arrived at Mount Sinai on the forty-fifth day are rightly said to have been carried there with forty-five measures of barley.
The phrase, "You will wait for me many days," refers to the present time, when the Jewish people, who were once symbolically hired for fifteen pieces of silver and forty-five measures of barley, await the coming of the Lord after His incarnation. This waiting continues until, as the Apostle says, the fullness of the Gentiles comes in, and thus all Israel will be saved.
The instruction, "You will not commit adultery, and you will not be with a man," indicates that, in the meantime, although the Jewish people do not serve idols, they also do not have God. They are deprived of both lovers and a husband; because they lack a husband, they do not partake in the food of men, which is wheat, but consume the barley of irrational beasts. This signifies that they do not grasp the life-giving spiritual sense but follow the killing letter.
The phrase, "but I will wait for you," applies to those who hope to be received into the embrace of Christ at the end of the world, when Jews and Gentiles will unite into one flock with one shepherd, who declares, "I am the good shepherd."
For many days, the children of Israel will be without a king, a prince, a sacrifice, an altar, an ephod, and household idols. The Jews often relate these things to the seventy years of their captivity, but as the blessed Jerome suggests, it is better to understand these words as referring to the present time or the final conversion of the Jews. These words align with the earlier statement: "You will wait for me many days, you will not commit adultery."
For now, the Jews remain in a contracted state because they lost their upright status.
They are without Christ the King, who says, "But I have been appointed king by Him," and without a leader, that is, the Savior Himself, or even a high priest, about whom it is written: "You shall not curse the ruler of your people."
They are also without sacrifice and an altar, because they lost the place where they had the temple and altar, as commanded in the law: "In the place which the Lord chooses, you shall offer sacrifices to Him, and not in every place," thus they do not offer legal sacrifices.
And without the ephod. The ephod is properly called a shoulder garment, but here it means any garment. Sometimes it also refers to linen garments, as we read about Samuel, who was dressed in a linen ephod.
Theraphim are properly called figures and idols. In this context, they do not refer to cherubim and seraphim or other temple ornaments, but to all priestly ornaments.
After the Jews lost all these things, they were spiritually given to us in the Church. For we have the true king and priest, Christ, who is a priest forever according to the order of Melchizedek; we have the true sacrifice of the body and blood of the Lord; we also have the ephod, the garment of innocence and simplicity, having been made priests and kings ourselves, as Peter says: "You are a chosen people, a royal priesthood, a holy nation."
We also have the theraphim, the sign and memory of God imprinted in our hearts, as we sing to Him: "The light of your face is signed upon us, Lord."
And after these things, the children of Israel will return and seek the Lord their God and David their king.
After these things, that is, after all these have been fulfilled, when the fullness of the Gentiles has come in, the children of Israel will return through the preaching of Elijah and Enoch, and seek the Lord their God and David their king, that is, the Father and His Son Jesus Christ, confessing Him as the one true God with their hearts, mouths, and deeds.
And they will be in awe of the Lord and His goodness in the last days.
The Holy Spirit, who is not separate from the Father and the Son, but together with them is one God.
He says to His disciples:
If you, being evil, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more will your Father in heaven give the Holy Spirit to those who ask Him!
Chapter Four
Listen to the word of the Lord, children of Israel, because the Lord has a judgment against the inhabitants of the land.
These words specifically pertain to those who were present at the coming of the Son of God, although they can also apply to those who lived at that time in the twelve tribes, to whom the prophet speaks.
This shows that God's anger and severe punishments were not in vain, as He threatened and inflicted them so that the people would be without a king and without the other things in which they had previously gloried.
But because they were without truth, mercy, and the knowledge of God, and because curses, lies, murders, and many other sins had flooded in, by God's just judgment, all these things were taken away from the inhabitants of that land.
They were handed over to captivity, adding sin to sin, and piling new sins on old ones.
However, as we have said, this mainly refers to those who saw and heard God in the flesh but did not want to believe in Him, as well as their descendants.
For it is said to them: Listen to the word of the Lord, children of Israel, because the Lord has a judgment against the inhabitants of the land, that is, against the Jews who always desire earthly things, in contrast to those who are called heavenly, who consider themselves strangers and pilgrims in this life, aiming for heavenly things.
With these inhabitants of the land, He conducts judgment, promising to hand them over to eternal damnation.
He explains why He does this, adding, For there is no truth, but everyone speaks lies with his neighbor.
Or there is no truth, because He who says of Himself: I am the truth, does not dwell in their hearts.
And there is no mercy, because they persecute their subjects and do not have mercy on the orphan and the widow.
Thus, they did not even spare Christ Himself, but like rabid dogs, opened their mouths against Him, saying: He is guilty of death, and: Crucify Him, crucify Him.
And there is no knowledge of God.
That is, faith and the knowledge of God's name are not in their hearts, as they only think of earthly things.
Certainly, here is the text translated into modern, easy-to-understand English:
Or certainly, knowledge, that is, the wisdom of God the Father, who says of Himself through Solomon:
"I, wisdom, dwell in counsel and am present in learned thoughts."
And of whom the Apostle says, "Christ is the power of God and the wisdom of God."
He does not dwell on earth, meaning He does not rest in the minds of those who are alien to His faith.
It follows: "Cursing, lying, murder, theft, and adultery have overflowed."
Cursing pertains to their insults and reproaches, like when they said: "You have a demon," and, "You are a Samaritan," and other such things.
Lying pertains to what they said: "He is guilty of death," and, "This man is a glutton and a drunkard."
Murder pertains to the fact that they handed Him over to death and all the prophets, as He Himself reproaches them, saying: "Fill up, then, the measure of your fathers. Behold, I send to you prophets and wise men and scribes," etc.
And blessed Stephen says: "Which of the prophets did your fathers not persecute? And they killed those who foretold the coming of the Righteous One, of whom you have now become betrayers and murderers."
Theft pertains to the fact that they stole themselves and their children, saying: "His blood be on us and on our children."
Or when they bought Christ secretly with thirty pieces of silver.
Adultery pertains to immorality or idolatry.
All these things had overflowed among the Jews, meaning they had become abundant.
For by the word "overflow," the greatness of the crimes is shown.
"And blood touched blood." Blood touches blood when murder is joined to murder, and when sin is increased by sin.
For by the name of blood, sin is designated, as in "Deliver me from bloodguiltiness."
Because of this, the land will mourn, and everyone who lives in it will languish, along with the beasts of the field, and the birds of the sky; even the fish of the sea will be gathered.
Because for good deeds, the aforementioned vices have overflowed, the land will mourn.
The land seems to mourn when it remains uncultivated, with its inhabitants removed, and what once produced joyful fruits now begins to bring forth thorns and thistles.
Therefore, the desolation of the twelve tribes is highlighted here when it says: The land will mourn.
We can interpret the Jews themselves as the land, seeking it and possessing earthly wisdom.
Thus, it immediately follows: And everyone who lives in it will weaken—referring to those who remain there out of love and desire.
Having been captured by their enemies, they mourned and weakened because they were losing the things they had loved deeply and taken pride in, whether it was the beast of the field or the bird of the heavens.
As the blessed Jerome mentions, it is natural that if the land is abandoned by its inhabitants, the beasts and birds also leave.
On a deeper level, the beasts of the field symbolize fierce peoples oppressed by beastly stupidity; the birds represent the proud, the haughty, and the frivolous, similar to the Jews who boasted of their merit and despised others.
The fish of the sea can be understood as those immersed in the depths of vice and the darkness of sin.
Alternatively, the fish could represent the philosophers of the world, who ponder deep questions about temporal matters.
The fish of the sea, he says, will be gathered, implying into death.
Another translation suggests: The fish of the sea will fail.
He advises no one to judge or blame.
He had earlier called them to judgment so they might recognize they were being judged justly, not oppressed by God's power but handed over to enemies because of past sins.
Yet, because they worsened, they became so imprudent that they felt no shame even when convicted.
He instructs the just not to judge or blame the unjust, as they are unworthy of correction.
Let each just person, he says, refrain from judging the unjust, and let the impious not be blamed by the pious, because the enormity of their crimes renders them unworthy.
For your people are like those who contradict the priest.
Just as an ordinary person disobeys a priest whose commands they don't want to follow, and just as a student disobeys a teacher, so your people contradict my words.
Therefore, they are not worthy of being rebuked by a prophet or anyone righteous.
You will fall today, and the prophet will fall with you.
Earlier, he addressed the prophet about the people, but now he speaks directly to the people themselves, specifically the ten tribes, saying: You will fall today, meaning in the present time, or certainly in broad daylight, and you will be led into captivity before everyone’s eyes.
And the prophet will fall with you.
We can understand the prophet here in two ways: either as a false prophet, because it is an ambiguous term, or as the prophetic dignity, because we do not read that the ten tribes had a prophet after their captivity.
As long as the ten tribes were not captured, they had Elijah the prophet, Elisha, and other sons of the prophets who prophesied in Samaria.
Indeed, the two tribes had prophets during and after their captivity.
But the ten tribes, after being taken to the Medes and Persians, are reported to have had no prophet.
Therefore, it is said to them: The prophet will also fall with you, meaning the prophetic dignity will perish from you, or the false prophets who gave you false prophecies will perish along with you.
And at night I silenced your mother.
The mother refers to the Jewish people in general.
The children of this mother are either individuals from the people or those scattered through towns and villages.
So at night, meaning in the darkness of captivity, sorrow, and pressing distress, I silenced your mother because she did not dare to grieve her misfortune before the enemies.
My people were silent because they had no knowledge.
This means, captured by the enemies, they withered in silence, not daring to resist.
The reason given for this is that they had no knowledge of God’s law and did not keep His precepts, to serve Him and scorn idols.
Because he had previously closed his mouth to the praises of God, he justly came to this misery, so that he did not even dare to lament his evil among enemies.
Because you rejected knowledge, I will reject you, so that you will not serve as a priest for me.
The people themselves rejected knowledge, that is, God, when they began to worship the work of their hands with the most foolish mind.
Abandoning the Creator of heaven and earth, they venerated golden calves in Dan and Bethel.
Therefore, they were rejected, so that there would not be priests from them in the house of the Lord, but rather in the temples of idols.
And you have forgotten the law of your God, which forbids the worship of foreign gods.
I will also forget your children, handing them over to eternal captivity, nor will I have mercy on them, as I once had mercy on their fathers in the desert.
For the one who ignores will be ignored.
All these things can also be referred to heretics, who have left the house of David and Jerusalem, that is, Christ and the Church.
Therefore, covered with eternal night, they fall silent from the praises of God, as it is written: "In hell, who will confess to you?"
This is because they did not have the knowledge of God, that is, Christ, to believe his true faith. Hence, they are justly rejected by the Lord, so that they do not serve as priests for him. Often, such people, taken from this life by untimely death, perish eternally. Neither they, unworthily handling the body and blood of the Lord, would be a stumbling block to others, nor would their evil doctrine, by living long, be a cause of perdition for many.
Their children are also said to be forgotten by God, that is, those who are generated from their perverse doctrine. They will be handed over to eternal damnation along with their fathers. According to their multitude, they have sinned against me. That is, as many people as Israel had, so many altars they built for demons, in whose sacrifices they sinned against me. I will turn their glory into disgrace. He calls their glory the idol in which they gloried, and in whose veneration they rejoiced, which was then turned into disgrace, because for this crime, along with it, they were led into captivity.
The sins of my people they eat.
This statement needs to be understood in two ways.
The priests consume the sins of the people by accepting the sacrifices offered for those sins.
These offerings, whether made in the past or now in the temple of the Lord, are used by the priests.
Hence, it is also stated in the canons that laypeople should not eat from what has been consecrated.
But those who consume the alms of others without praying for them properly are similar to the Jews.
Those who pray properly for them live by the works of their own hands.
Alternatively, the priests consume the sins of the people by flattering those who do evil, thus taking their sins upon themselves.
For those who consent to the sins of others become participants in those same sins.
When they see others sinning, not only do they not rebuke them, but they also praise the sinners.
Hence, it is added: and they will lift up their souls to their iniquity.
While they served sins, the priests lifted up their souls, saying: Because you are the people of God, descended from the lineage of Abraham, God will spare you for the sake of his friendship if you sin against him.
Taking confidence in these words, they sinned boldly, puffed up with pride, or deceived by false flattery, saying: Your sins are forgiven.
Thus, they lifted up their souls, because believing their words more than their own conscience, they thought themselves to be righteous while they were sinners.
Hence it is: My people, those who call you blessed, they deceive you.
And it will be as with the people, so with the priest.
That is, because they sin equally, they will equally endure the judgment of an angry God.
However, these priests, to whom evil from the Lord is foretold equally as to the people, were not from the tribe of Levi.
They came from any tribe, filling their hands with gold or silver, giving gifts to the kings of the ten tribes, and became priests in the temples of idols.
But even any priest or prelate who takes upon himself the sins of others by flattering them becomes equal to them and will be equally condemned with them.
And I will visit upon him, that is, upon the priest, his ways.
I will indeed punish all his works, for here, "visit" means to afflict and torment. I will repay him for his thoughts.
They will suffer punishment not only for their bad deeds but also for their worst thoughts, which led them to commit such acts.
It is easy to understand that the more heretics there are, the more they sin against the Lord. According to their number, they multiply various erroneous doctrines, turning the glory of wisdom and Christianity into disgrace.
Because of their past sins, by God's just judgment, they are allowed to fall into various errors, for which they are eventually handed over to eternal punishments. The Apostle says about them: God handed them over to a depraved mind, to do what ought not to be done.
They consume the sins of the people when they speak pleasing things and deceive the hearts of believers with sweet words, devouring widows' houses. When they see others sinning, they say, God seeks nothing else but the truth of faith, and if you keep that, He does not care what you do, misunderstanding the Lord's saying: Whoever believes and is baptized will be saved.
While saying these things, they lift up their souls in their iniquities, so they do not repent or humble themselves. Instead, they rejoice in their crimes and walk with heads held high.
Hence, both the people and the priest—those who are taught and those who teach—will be bound by the same judgment. They will be punished not only for their deeds but also for their evil thoughts.
They will eat and not be satisfied; that is, they will engage in evil works and not be fulfilled. The lustful and the greedy will never be satisfied with their wickedness.
On the contrary: Blessed are those who hunger and thirst for righteousness, for they will be filled. Specifically, those of whom the Prophet says: The poor will eat and be satisfied.
Just as righteousness fills, iniquity, having no substance, deceives those who consume it with empty deceit. It leaves the stomachs of those who devour it empty, that is, their minds: They have committed fornication and have not stopped.
It is suggested that they commit adultery because the desires of perverse people lead them to it, and their urge to commit adultery never rests.
Since they did not heed the warning, "You have sinned, be at rest," they will hear on the day of judgment, "Depart from me, you cursed, into everlasting fire."
The ten tribes also committed adultery with idols under Jeroboam, the son of Nebat, and continued to worship idols thereafter. Why is this? Because they abandoned the Lord by not keeping His commandments. Adultery, wine, and drunkenness take away the heart. By not keeping His commandments, it is implied that they worshiped idols, because they forsook the Lord their God, unable to serve two masters at the same time.
By not keeping His commandments, it is implied that they did not follow His command: "You shall worship the Lord your God, and Him only shall you serve." Adultery and wine, and so on, cloud a person's sense and understanding. The meaning is: just as excessive wine and drunkenness make one lose control of their mind, so adultery, whether physical or spiritual, corrupts the sense and weakens the spirit. It turns a rational person into a brute animal, chasing after brothels and dens of lust, and believing that wood and stones are gods, worshiping the works of their own hands.
My people, it is implied, once inquired of their wood, and their staff spoke to them. This was a type of divination done with wood and staves, by which they sought omens of future events. Hence, it is written in Ezekiel that Nebuchadnezzar, proceeding against Amon and Jerusalem, stood at a crossroads where he mixed arrows among other divinations, and one came out against Jerusalem. Perhaps these people did likewise, seeking what was more beneficial to them, whether to worship God or idols.
Because they were so perverse, leaving the truth to follow a lie, by God's just judgment, they were abandoned by God and seduced by the devil through the response of the staff. Hence, it follows: "For the spirit of fornication has deceived them, and they have committed adultery against their God"; that is, through idolatry, they have departed from their God.
The spirit of fornication is understood to be the devil, who persuades people to turn away from God and worship wooden and stone idols.
The creation of idols is indeed the beginning of this fornication.
Heretics, to whom these things can apply, are never satisfied with their errors and do not stop indulging in the shame of fornication.
They commit acts of bodily impurity and do not follow the law or other Scriptures.
They abandon God, go insane, and become drunk, losing the vigor of their minds, and worship idols that they have created in their hearts, embodying the spirit of fornication.
They sacrificed on the tops of the mountains and burned incense on the hills.
The children of Israel, following their desires and the lusts of the flesh, abandoned God and, scorning His temple, sacrificed to idols on the mountains and hills, burning incense—which is a sweet-smelling perfume—to them.
There, because of the pleasantness of the places, they ate, drank, slept, and engaged in excess, calling these high places.
They did this because they did not have the Most High God.
We read about these high places in the Acts of the Kings: "However, the high places were not taken away; the people still sacrificed on the high places."
They are said to have done this on the high places because they worshiped on the rooftops of their houses, following, as I think, the custom of the serpent raised on a pole.
Under the oak, poplar, and terebinth trees, it is implied that they sacrificed because its shade was good.
The Jews lost the truth, and that is why they did this.
For the Lord had commanded in the law that they should not sacrifice except in the place He had chosen. But because of their desires, as mentioned above, they sacrificed to idols in the delightful places of groves and mountains, making altars under the shade of trees, attracted by their pleasantness, and engaged in bodily impurity.
Therefore, the Lord had forbidden planting a grove near His altar.
Hence, your daughters will fornicate.
It is implied that foreigners, or those abandoning the Lord, will worship idols.
Your brides will be adulteresses, leaving their own beds to join with others.
I will not punish your daughters when they commit fornication, nor your brides when they commit adultery.
Israel has turned away from the Lord their God, so their daughters and brides commit these acts without punishment.
They are left to their own wickedness, so they may understand the pain of God, who is so angry that He will not strike them down.
He says, "I will not punish your daughters when they commit fornication, nor your brides when they commit adultery." Instead, He will allow them to indulge in their vices freely, so they recognize their own offense against Him. He will not avenge their wrongdoings, except through ultimate captivity.
They consorted with prostitutes and sacrificed with the effeminate. This explains why He will not avenge the daughters' and wives' iniquities. The number of the sons of Israel was so great that punishment seemed hopeless for reform.
They consorted with prostitutes and sacrificed with the effeminate, committing abominations in the temples of their gods. The people, not understanding, will be punished by God for their own sin, struck by the blows and lashes of captivity.
If we want to understand these things regarding heretics, their daughters or brides are souls begotten in error and betrothed to their doctrines. Such people are unworthy of God's correction, for all their worship is fornication, and the vile mix with the vile. Therefore, they will be punished, so perhaps through blows, those who have abandoned the Lord may repent.
If you fornicate, Israel, at least let Judah not sin. Israel here signifies the ten tribes, while Judah signifies Benjamin and the priestly tribe, the Levitical, joined with the same tribe.
Which tribe is now being urged by the prophetic speech not to abandon God for the worship of idols, as Israel did—the ten tribes—by worshiping the idols that Jeroboam, son of Nebat, made for them?
"If you commit adultery," it says, "you Israel, who have mingled with prostitutes, anyone who filled his hand, either his own or the king's, by giving gifts, became a priest of idols."
At least you, Judah, who possess Jerusalem and have priests and Levites according to the law, and the temple with its legal ceremonies, do not commit the sin of imitating them by worshiping idols.
"And do not enter into Gilgal."
Gilgal is the place where the sons of Israel, having crossed the Jordan, first set up camp; and there, after receiving the second circumcision, they were purging idols. The tribe of Judah is now prohibited from veneration there, as it is said:
"Do not go up to Gilgal," implying that you should not worship gods there, as the Israelites do—the ten tribes.
"And do not go up to Bethaven." Bethaven is the same as Bethel, which was previously called Bethel, meaning the house of the Lord. But after idol worship arose there and the calves were placed there by Jeroboam, it was called the useless house and the house of idols.
Hence, the Septuagint translates Bethaven as "house of vanity," because one of the golden calves had been placed there by Jeroboam.
"Do not," it says, "go up to Bethaven to offer sacrifices there, because it is no longer the house of God, but the house of idols. Neither swear, 'As the Lord lives.'"
They are forbidden to swear by the name of the Lord, who had been idol worshipers and had mouths polluted with praises of demons. For praise is not fitting in the mouth of a sinner. The Lord had prohibited in the law that Jews should not swear by the names of idols or foreign gods, allowing them to swear by His name.
For each person either loves or venerates the one by whom they swear. Hence, to prevent them from loving or venerating idols, they were prohibited from swearing by the names of idols, lest by mentioning them, they might be enticed to love and worship them.
Instead, they should always have the name of God in their mouth, worshiping and adoring Him.
Because the Jews had already abandoned God and were worshiping idols, they were forbidden to swear, "The Lord lives." This oath was common among them, as Elijah said, "The Lord lives, in whose sight I stand." And we read very frequently that they used this oath. For you must not swear, "The Lord lives"; it is as if God were saying, "I do not want my name to be mentioned by your mouths, which are polluted by idolatrous worship."
Just as a wanton cow, Israel has turned away: now the Lord will feed them like a lamb in a wide field. The wanton cow is called proud because of its excessive fatness, which refuses to accept the yoke and, driven by a gadfly, leaves the straight path of the furrow. Similarly, Israel (that is, the ten tribes) has thrown off the yoke of the law from their necks, and driven by a demonic spirit, they have taken the wide path by following their pleasures, of which the Lord says, "Wide is the path that leads to destruction." Now he will feed them as above.
The prophet's voice continues about the same people: and because he began to speak about the wanton cow, he keeps the metaphor in the rest. In the wide fields, he says that God will pasture the Israelites like a lamb. Now, he says, that is at the present time, while this spirit rules these bodies, that is, while I am alive, the Lord will feed them in the wide field like a lamb. This means they will be taken into captivity by the Assyrians and in the wide land of captivity, they will be scattered, and there they will remain for a long time.
Allegorically, the name Israel refers to heretics, but Judas means any ecclesiastical man confessing God. To them, it is said: If you fornicate, Israel, that is, if you, O heretic, depart from God through false doctrine, let not Judas offend; that is, let not the ecclesiastical man follow the dogmas of your perversity. And let him not enter into Gilgal, that is, the assemblies of the heretics, where all sins are revealed, and like pigs, they wallow in the mire of vices. For Gilgal means revelation or wallowing place. Nor let him go up to Beth-aven, that is, to the arrogant fabrications of false dogmas, because there is no house of God there, but a house of idols.
Those stained by such crimes are also forbidden
to swear in the name of the Lord, whose majesty
they pollute by thinking bad things about Him.
They, like a frisky cow,
struck by a shelter, have been hit by the devil's burning arrows
and have abandoned the knowledge of the law.
Therefore,
they will graze on the wide and spacious path that leads to death.
Ephraim is a partaker in idols.
Ephraim in this
place refers to the ten tribes after the separation from
the house of David to Jeroboam, who was from the tribe of Ephraim,
to whom Jacob had given the blessing of the kingdom.
Sometimes,
they are also called by the name Joseph because Joseph
was the father of Ephraim.
Therefore, Ephraim (that is, the ten
tribes) participated in idols because they were like them,
whom they worshiped as gods made by their hands.
For the Psalmist says: Let those who
make them and all who trust in them become like them.
Leave
him.
O Judah, you understand, that is, do not ignore the words
of the prophet and do not follow the impiety of Israel, who is a partaker and friend of idols,
whose worship, religion, and
food are separated from your table, hence it follows:
Their table is separated, that is, the sacrifice
to idols is separate from yours, because you offer to the Almighty
God, but they to demons.
With fornication
they have fornicated.
Repetition of the speech is a confirmation;
it is as if he said: They fornicate every day,
and they love their fornication, and always
increase fornications with fornications.
For at first,
they worshiped the idol that Jeroboam,
son of Nebat, had made for them, then the gods of all nations.
They loved
to bring shame.
His protectors
were called Jeroboam and
his other kings, who should have taught them the way of righteousness and
defended them from enemies.
They loved to bring
shame, that is, idolatry, whose actions caused the unhappy
people to adopt the worship of idols, and who should have been
guides to them in the way of salvation, became leaders
of error and eternal destruction.
The spirit bound him in its wings.
Spirit and
wind are expressed by one word among the Hebrews, which
is Ruach.
The word "spirits" here refers to demons, who have bound both kings and the people under their influence, wrapping them in their wings, or shadows, causing blindness of mind and preventing them from walking freely wherever they wished.
The spirit indeed bound him when it joined with him, uniting him so that he no longer worshiped correctly but instead adored it through idols. And they will be ashamed of their sacrifices.
This means that when they are captured by enemies, they will feel ashamed and embarrassed, recognizing that this punishment came upon them because of the sacrifices they previously offered to idols. On a deeper level, this also refers to heretics, who participated in idol worship by following various doctrines.
Therefore, the prophet urges the churchman to dismiss and disdain their madness and to scorn their entire company, because their sacrifices are separated from those of the faithful, as they do not rightly celebrate the mysteries of the body and blood of the Lord. Thus, they fornicate by following various errors and serving the impurities of the flesh.
And they love to bring disgrace, meaning they rejoice in providing their listeners with vain and superfluous traditions. These spirits, or the devil, bind them, preventing them from remaining firmly in the Church, and they are carried about by every wind of doctrine. They are truly ashamed of their sacrifices, for their bread, that is, their reward, will be perpetual mourning.
Chapter Five
Listen to this, priests, and pay attention, house of Israel, and house of the king, listen: because judgment is for you, for you have become a trap for observation and a net spread over Tabor.
He speaks to the priests of the ten tribes and calls their kings to judgment, not because they are priests from the tribe of Levi, but because they are called priests by the people.
But also Israel, that is, the people, is called to judgment, and no one is exempt, so that priests, people, and kings who had led the people astray and appointed such priests for them may all hear what they have done and why they are handed over to their enemies.
Listen to this, everyone, and pay attention, that is, perceive with the ear of the body and retain with the understanding of the mind, because judgment is for you.
Condemnation is imminent due to your wickedness, for you have become a trap of captivity and slaughter.
I indeed appointed you as watchmen and leaders of the people, to guide them when they go astray.
But you have become a trap, and therefore you are no longer called watchmen and leaders, but hunters.
Just as a net is spread over Mount Tabor to catch birds, so your teaching and example have ensnared the people and led them to death.
Tabor is a mountain located in the plains of Galilee, round and lofty, and it is equally bounded on all sides.
About it, the psalm sings: "Tabor and Hermon shall rejoice in your name."
And you have led sacrifices into the depth. Sacrifices are led into the depth when they are offered to demons.
The people of the two tribes made their sacrifices, which they offered to Almighty God, ascend upward (that is, to the heavens).
But Israel, because they sacrificed to idols, made them descend into the depth, that is, into hell.
Morally, the sacrifices of the Lord are the praises of believers, the repentance of sinners, the tears of prayers, about which it is written: "The sacrifice to God is a contrite spirit."
But there are some who, after the tears and repentance of sins, return to the sins already committed.
Hi, certainly, the repentance they had for their past sins, they abandon completely, because they become worse.
About such people, it is written:
A dog returns to its own vomit.
According to mystical interpretations, heretical priests and leaders are understood, while the people are their disciples and subjects.
Both the leaders and the people are rebuked and brought to the judgment of condemnation.
Because those who ought to be teachers of the people have begun to lead them astray through corrupt teachings and have caused them to err.
The same heretics also lay a trap over Thabor, which is interpreted as 'coming light', when they lay their snares in the Church.
By which perverse doctrines they capture birds (that is, souls flying to heaven).
They draw the victims into the depths, persuading people to sacrifice to demons while dragging them into their own errors, so that they do not repent of their sins and rise to contemplate heavenly things.
And I am the teacher of all of them.
So that the people and their leaders might not despair, that is, the princes and the priests, believing they could return to grace, the Lord mercifully announces that he will be the teacher of all of them, saying:
As if to say: If they are willing to repent and cease to serve the gods they have worshiped until now, let them not despair: because I, their teacher, will teach them what they should do, as I wish to correct, not punish them: and to save, not to destroy.
I know Ephraim, and Israel is not hidden from me.
By the name Ephraim, he includes Jeroboam, son of Nebat, and all the kings from the same tribe.
I also created the people subjected to the kings.
Therefore, since they are my creation, and I observe all their actions, let them not despair, but repent, and I will accept them.
Because Ephraim has now played the harlot.
That is, their kings at the present time, turning away from the worship of God, have begun to commit idolatry by worshiping golden calves.
And Israel is defiled.
Because when the king committed idolatry, the people followed and completed the same impiety with equal zeal, which should be connected from above, and this I know.
They will not turn their thoughts to their God because the spirit of adultery is among them, and they have not known God.
Although the Lord mercifully called Himself their teacher earlier, knowing the intention of their hearts, He adds: They will not turn their thoughts to their God, meaning they do not repent of their evil thoughts, to prevent them from completing the evil deed they have planned.
And He gives the reason, saying: The spirit of adultery (that is, the devil) is among them.
And they have not known God, meaning they have not understood Him to worship and adore with proper reverence.
Because the devil dwelled in their hearts, he blinded them so they could not return to the true light to know God, that is, to understand that He alone is to be worshipped.
For it is said of the sons of Eli: Moreover, the sons of Eli were sons of Belial; they did not know the Lord.
Likewise, God knows the leaders of false teachings (that is, heretics) and the people subjected to them, because He considers all their works and even their hidden thoughts, and nothing is hidden from Him.
And because their subjects were also contaminated by their wrong doctrine, they will not turn their thoughts to repentance and return to God, because they are seduced by the spirit of adultery, which is among them, and therefore they do not know God.
And the arrogance of Israel will respond in His face.
Arrogance, that is, the pride of Israel, by which they, swelling against God, despised His worship, and in offense to the Creator, worshipped idols.
This arrogance will respond in His face when, due to the merit of their wickedness because of idol worship, they are handed over to captivity, so they are not left unpunished but are humbled by their enemies' contempt.
And Israel and Ephraim will fall in their iniquity, that is, both the subjected people and the kings who led them to idol worship will fall together and be weakened, so those who were strong in wickedness will be forced to return to God.
Judah will also fall with them.
These words show that the tribe of Judah was already worshiping idols at that time.
It says this will not only happen to Israel and Ephraim—that is, the ten tribes and their kings, who will be taken into captivity—but also to Judah, the two tribes that reigned in Jerusalem, who will follow in the footsteps of the captives.
Just as they imitated their crimes, they will also suffer the same punishment.
Their arrogance will confront the heretics directly, as their pride in always boasting of knowing higher things will cause both teachers and disciples to fall together.
Judah too, a man instructed in church doctrine who remains in the Church in body but not in mind, and who shares the same erroneous knowledge with the heretics, falsely professing the name of the Church, will also be punished along with the heretics.
They will go with their flocks and herds to seek the Lord, but they will not find Him.
This applies to both the ten tribes and the two tribes.
When Israel, Ephraim, and Judah are oppressed by enemies, they will, led by late repentance, seek the Lord with their offerings, eager to appease Him with sacrifices, whom they had previously offended with their transgressions.
But they will not find Him, because as they departed from divine worship, He also departed from them.
Therefore, it is said, He has been taken away from them.
They will not feel His presence as a helper, nor will they be able to appease Him with their offerings, especially since the Psalmist says: I will not accept calves from your house; and: Will I eat the flesh of bulls, etc.
They committed treachery against the Lord, specifically when they worshiped idols instead of God, because they bore foreign children—that is, they joined to idols and bore children to demons, not to God.
Foreign children are understood to be those born in the error of idols, or those whom they consecrated to idols by leading them through fire.
Now the month will devour them with their portions.
He says that because they acted this way, soon their enemies—the Assyrians and the Chaldeans—will come and devour them along with their lands and possessions, which they received by lot and measure.
The Septuagint translation reads: Rust will devour them with their ivy.
The meaning is that every month, the enemy will come to destroy everything belonging to them, killing some and taking others into captivity.
This is shown in the history of the Books of Kings and Chronicles, where it is recounted that this people were taken captive multiple times.
Heretics believe that by offering many sacrifices, they please God, and Judas (that is, the clergy) thinks that by giving alms, they can redeem their sins, even though sacrifices usually atone for past, not present, crimes.
People like this do not find God because He withdraws from them.
They transgress by neglecting God's commandments and producing illegitimate children through their evil deeds.
Therefore, they are condemned daily and individually, rushing towards eternal damnation with their wicked actions.
Blow the trumpet in Gibeah, the horn in Ramah, cry out in Beth-aven.
The trumpet is made from the horn of an animal with a curved shape, but the law commands the horn to be made from bronze or silver, and it sounds in wars and festivals.
Gibeah and Ramah are cities in the tribe of Benjamin, close to each other.
Gibeah is where Saul was born.
Ramah is the place where the king of Israel tried to block the exit and entrance of the tribe of Judah and Benjamin, as recorded in Kings.
Beth-aven is in the tribe of Ephraim, previously called Bethel.
Having mentioned the captivity of both the ten tribes and the two tribes, saying: Now the month will devour them with their possessions, he encourages them, as captivity is near, to sound their trumpets and horns, urging each other to a common lament.
And the meaning is: Do not mourn your captivity quietly, but sound the trumpets and horns so that all around can hear.
This meaning fits well because Gabaa means "hill" and Rama means "high place." So they are told: Sound the trumpet in Gabaa, the horn in Rama, meaning go up to the mountains and hills and loudly lament your impending captivity.
Also, wail in Bethaven, where one of the golden calves is, for the inhabitants will be handed over into captivity because of their worship. It is fittingly added, "Behind you, Benjamin," for where the tribe of Benjamin ends, this city is not far, situated in the tribe of Ephraim, specifically in the rear part of Benjamin.
Ephraim will be in desolation on the day of correction. Here, Ephraim refers both to the kings descended from him and to the people of the ten tribes. The day of correction refers to the time when they were handed over to their enemies because of their sins, so that those who did not want to serve God in prosperity would endure correction, afflicted by various miseries from their enemies.
On that day, both kings and their subjects were made desolate; some were killed, and others were taken into captivity, leaving their land empty of its inhabitants. In the tribes of Israel, I have shown faithfulness. The Septuagint says: In the tribes of Israel, I have shown faithful things, using the past tense for the future, saying "I have shown" instead of "I will show." As if to say: When the things I spoke of before through the prophets come to pass, I will show faithfulness, meaning I will reveal my faithful and true words, because everything I spoke about their destruction will be fulfilled.
But heretics also dwell in Gabaa and Rama, that is, in the prideful knowledge, thinking they possess high wisdom, and there they worship idols, meaning the false doctrines they created from their own hearts. Therefore, they are commanded not to hide their evil in silence but to publicly reveal it to everyone.
They are commanded to wail in Bethaven, which means "house of uselessness." Their hearts, which were once Bethel through true faith, the "house of God," have now through various errors become useless.
This aligns with Bethaven being mentioned as behind Benjamin. Benjamin means "right hand" and signifies the saints who will reach the prosperity of the heavenly kingdom. Because of eternal joy, they leave behind all the comforts of the present life, echoing the Apostle's words:
"One thing I do: forgetting what is behind and straining toward what is ahead, I press on toward the goal" (Philippians 3:13-14).
Heretics, however, are behind Benjamin because they longingly desire and delight in the things the saints despise in this life, placing all their hope in transient things.
Those who previously seemed like Ephraim, meaning "fruitfulness," will be in desolation when the day of correction comes, the day of judgment. Stripped of all the goods in which they seemed to excel, they will be handed over naked and empty to the unquenchable fire.
At that time, the Lord will show His faithfulness in their damnation. He will demonstrate His faithful and true words by accomplishing through action what He had previously foretold about their destruction.
This applies not only to heretics but also to all the reprobates in general.
The leaders of Judah have become like those who move a boundary. They should have wept and encouraged their people to turn away from idol worship to avoid suffering similar consequences. Instead, they rejoiced that their land was open for wider possession. They became like those who move the boundaries of Israel, crossing their own borders and seeking to expand their kingdom and possessions in the lands that once belonged to them.
Therefore, it is said: I will pour out my wrath like water upon them.
This means the Babylonians will come upon the leaders of Judah and overwhelm them like a flood, bringing complete captivity and abundant death.
This will happen not by their own strength, but by my indignation.
The term "pouring out" signifies the abundance and magnitude of the event. He also tells the leaders of Judah, meaning the Church, that they should not have rejoiced or considered their own salvation in the destruction of the reprobate, but rather mourned their loss, remembering their own condition.
Hence, the Apostle admonishes church members not to boast over the breaking off of the Jewish branches, but rather to fear that they might also be broken off. Some rejoice in the destruction of the reprobate and think they stand firm when others fall, but the Lord pours out his wrath like water upon them. Often, when some rejoice at others' downfall, they themselves fall into the same evils for which they mocked others, thus incurring the wrath of God.
The leaders of Judah also move the boundaries set by their fathers when they replace truth with lies and preach something other than what they received from the apostles. Ephraim suffers slander, broken by judgment.
The people of Israel, still persisting in the hardness of their hearts, claimed they were broken by judgment and unjustly oppressed by their enemies. They said: Because we are descended from the lineage of Abraham, friends of God, we should not have been handed over to those worse than us, meaning the uncircumcised and idolaters, entirely alien to the worship of God. They called the affliction brought upon them by their enemies slander, claiming they were condemned unjustly and without fault.
Therefore, to make them understand they endure this not without cause, it is said they began to follow filth. As if to say: They were not handed over to the Chaldeans because their oppressors were more righteous, but because the Jews, once my people, deserted me and began to follow filth, meaning idols.
Therefore, they are compared to filth and uncleanness, and thus a just sentence is delivered, showing that they suffer slander and are handed over to worse things because Ephraim, that is, Jeroboam, began to follow idols and abandon God.
He made golden calves, which the people later worshipped.
Regarding heretics, it is clear that they oppressed the Church with their sophistries and dialectical skills.
But in doing so, they did not follow the purity of true faith, but rather the dirt of lies.
When they see themselves condemned with the devil and his angels, they believe they are suffering slander and that the truth of judgment is broken against them.
This also applies to all the reprobates.
And I am like a moth to Ephraim, and like rot to the house of Judah.
A moth eats clothing, but rot or decay consumes wood.
In these words, the meaning is: Just as a moth consumes clothing and rot consumes wood over time, so I, first with the ten tribes and later with the two tribes, gave them long periods for repentance and urged them to salvation, but ultimately handed them over for damnation.
It should be noted that the moth refers to Ephraim, but the rot to the house of Judah.
For the moth consumes clothing faster than rot consumes wood.
Hence, it is shown that the captivity of the ten tribes occurred first, followed by the two tribes.
It should also be noted that while all of Ephraim is declared to be consumed like a moth, speaking of the tribe of Judah, it is said: And I am like rot to the house of Judah.
In these words, it is shown that a certain part will be preserved from them, which later returned, from which Christ originated, to whom the promise is kept, as Jacob says: And he will be the expectation of the nations.
However, with the heretics punished, understood by the name Ephraim, even Judah, that is, those who remain in the Church and are restrained by the vices or errors of the heretics, will be subject to a similar sentence, because it was necessary that those who imitate their actions should suffer the same punishment as them.
Ephraim saw their sickness, and Judah their wound; Ephraim went to Assyria and sought help from the avenging king.
Ephraim, representing the kings of the ten tribes, recognized their weakness, while Judah understood their wound, signifying that captivity was near because they shared in the ten tribes' sins.
They turned to Assyria because they did not seek help from God, who could have resolved both their sin and captivity.
Instead, they sought assistance from the king of the Assyrians.
In the Book of Kings, we learn that during Menahem's reign over the ten tribes, Israel sent gifts to the Assyrians to be freed from the enemies of Damascus.
Similarly, Judah sent gifts to Tiglath-Pileser during Ahaz's reign to escape Pekah, king of Damascus.
Yet, although they were temporarily saved from their enemies, the same Assyrians later conquered them and became the instruments of God's punishment, who were once seen as their liberators.
Thus, it is noted: And he shall not be able to heal you, nor release you from your wound.
With God opposing them, the Assyrians could neither free them nor release them from captivity.
Allegorically, Ephraim and Judah can be seen as heretics and ecclesiastical men.
When they recognize their wound—that is, when they realize they are bound by sins, as it is written: Each one is bound by the cords of their sins—they do not seek God's help but turn to the devil, the avenger of all sins, as it is written: To destroy the enemy and the avenger.
Because they do not call upon the true helper and judge, they remain in their pains and various errors of sin.
The devil cannot heal them nor release them from the chains of their sins, and they will perish with him by God's just judgment.
For I am like a lioness to Ephraim, and like a young lion to the house of Judah.
The meaning is clear: Although they went to Assyria and sent gifts to the avenging king to be freed, they could not be healed nor released from their captivity.
For I will show that with me opposing them, all human help is in vain.
For I am like a lioness to Ephraim.
The Seventy interpreted it as a panther instead of a lioness, which is similarly said in Greek as in Latin.
According to Blessed Jerome, this animal is the fastest, and rightly so.
The Lord, speaking against Ephraim—that is, against the ten tribes—says He will become like a panther, signifying quick captivity.
Not long after, their destruction came through the Assyrians.
Against Judah, however, He says He will be like a lion, which is the strongest of beasts, indicating that their captivity would happen after some time through the strongest kingdom of the Chaldeans.
The Lord compares Himself to beasts in their condemnation, so that they may understand the severity of His anger.
I will capture, go, and take away, and there will be no one to rescue.
Because He said earlier that He would be like a panther or a lion, He maintains the metaphor by saying: I will capture, meaning through my ministers.
The Chaldeans or Assyrians did not capture them by their own strength; rather, God Almighty captured them because of their iniquities.
Therefore, even the enemies could not spare them when the Lord was angry with them.
I, He says, will capture, meaning I will make them be captured by the enemies, and I will go with them, so that even in captivity, they will endure the presence of my vengeance, against which they sinned.
I will take them from their own land, and there will be no one to rescue them, meaning no one can snatch them from my power.
No one can snatch anyone from the hand of God, unless the one who is held wants to escape by his own will, as Judas the betrayer did.
Going, I will return to my place, until you perish and seek my face.
We must understand the place of God as His magnificence and majesty, or we may refer these words specifically to the Son of God, through whom all prophecy is carried out.
His place is God the Father, as He Himself says: I am in the Father, and the Father is in me.
He said, "I will return to my place. When you have been handed over to your enemies, I will sit securely in my majesty, or even in the Father, and I will not come down to experience human emotions. I will not be angry with you, nor will I have pity, forgetting your wrongdoings. Instead, I will allow you, whom I previously protected, to be subjected to your enemies. I will offer no help or compassion until you are exhausted and, compelled by servitude, seek my face, repenting."
Even for heretics and sinning church leaders, Almighty God, because of the magnitude of their sins, though He is most merciful, turns into the cruelty of wild beasts and takes away their prey—that is, their disciples, whom they had snatched from the Church—making them return to the true faith. There is no one who can rescue them, because whoever's heart He has enlightened, no one can deceive.
While He does this, He departs from the assemblies of the perverse and dwells in the Church of the believers. He despises and rejects them until they waste away in their impieties and fail in their iniquities, seeking His presence, from whom they had been forsaken, saying: "Illuminate, Lord, your face, and we will be saved."
Chapter Six
In their trouble, they will rise early to me.
These words can partly refer to those who, pressed by the tribulation of captivity, began to repent and seek God, whom they felt was absent and angry.
And in the morning, that is, in the light of repentance, they say to one another: Come, let us return to the Lord.
Generally, these words are applied to all Christians who believe in Christ, who, afflicted by various tribulations, when the light of truth dawns on them, in the coming of Christ in the morning, that is, in the light of faith, rise from the darkness of unbelief and error, and begin to encourage each other, saying: Come, let us return to the Lord.
Indeed, those who returned from captivity from the two tribes, not content with their own salvation, encourage each other, saying: Come with the steps of love and faith, let us return to the Lord, whom we abandoned by sinning, and from whom we were justly left.
Because he captured us, leading us into captivity through Nebuchadnezzar; hence it is said above: I will capture; and he will heal us, by bringing us back from captivity, like a father his children.
He will strike us, by whipping us with various tribulations and beatings, and he will heal us from the wounds of sins, if after the whippings we perform worthy repentance.
As it is added: He will revive us after two days, this is specifically referred to the believers, who, called and illuminated by the faith of Christ, mutually provoke each other to return to the Lord, from whose worship they had once departed, and by worshipping various demonic idols, they deserved his absence.
Because (it says) he captured us, when the Word became flesh.
Hence Paul says: He took hold of the seed of Abraham.
And he will heal us, because the heavenly doctor, after the pain of wounds and sins, will give us full health.
Hence the Lord, intending to heal the paralytic, first purifies the soul, then relieves the body from the trouble of infirmity.
He will strike us, you understand, in various ways, and after striking will heal us, according to that: Whom the Lord loves, he chastises.
Hence he also said to a certain healed person: Behold, you have been made well, etc.
He will revive us after two days.
The Hebrews, blessed Jerome says, mistakenly believe that after a cycle of 1,000 years, they will be saved.
They base this belief on the salvation of believers being promised on the third day, because the Lord rose from the dead.
They refer to the second day as the coming of their Christ and the third day as his coming for judgment, by which they are to be saved.
But when they say this, they need to explain why they acknowledge only the second and third days.
Those who accept the second and third days indicate that they have lost sight of the first day, since the second and third days cannot exist without it.
And since they cannot account for the first day, we should refer all these things to the first and second coming of Christ, through which the salvation of believers was fulfilled.
So, let's accept the first period of God as the second coming of Christ.
After this day, He will bring us to life through faith, having been dead through unbelief.
Or certainly, He brought us to life in the hope of resurrection, as the Apostle says: He brought us to life and made us sit in the heavenly places in Christ Jesus.
On the third day, He will raise us up, because with His resurrection from the dead, we also rose with Him.
His resurrection signifies our own, as it is written: Just as He rose from the dead by the glory of the Father, so we will rise with Him.
Alternatively, we can consider the first day as the coming of Christ in humility, the second as His coming in glory, where He will be seen by all, and the third as the day when, after judgment, He will reveal the greater glory of His radiance to His chosen ones.
For God the Father has ordained that the general vivification and resurrection of all the saints will be accomplished through the Son.
Our first day is when we are reborn through the water of baptism and the grace of the Holy Spirit, coming from darkness to light, as the Apostle says: You were once darkness, but now you are light in the Lord.
The second is the rest of souls, and the third is the general resurrection.
We will live in His presence, as John says, when we will see Him as He is.
Or if we want to refer this to the present time, we live in His presence because, in Him, we move and exist.
We will know and continue to seek to know the Lord.
We will recognize the majesty of His divinity by believing and understanding His Trinity in persons, and unity in majesty.
We will follow His footsteps by imitating Him or ascending to the heavens.
Hence, it is added: So that we may know the Lord.
This will truly be fulfilled when what we now see through a mirror dimly, we will behold face to face.
Hence, it is written: And this is eternal life, that they may know You, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom You have sent.
Just like the dawn, His coming is prepared.
The dawn is called the small light of day, which, when it rises, dispels the darkness of night and the brightness of day begins to appear.
Therefore, the meaning is: Just as the rising dawn dispels the darkness of night, and the light of day opens, so with Christ being born in the flesh, the darkness of our sins was dissipated, and the sun of righteousness rose for us, illuminating our blindness, opening the eyes of our mind, and revealing the brightness of the heavenly homeland and the light of true knowledge.
And beautifully, this same birth is called His coming forth, about which the Psalmist says: And He is like a bridegroom coming out of His chamber.
Indeed, He came out like a bridegroom from His chamber when He took on an immaculate body from the untouched womb of the Virgin and appeared born in the flesh.
About whose birth it is rightly added: And He will come to us like the early and late rain upon the earth.
Literally, He calls the early rain the rain that is given by God to the land of the Palestinians after the seeds are sown, which, when poured, causes the seeds to grow; and the late rain, which brings the fruits to maturity.
Indeed, the promised land does not receive rain from heaven as frequently as ours, but only twice a year.
Hence, the Lord promises through the prophet to the same people saying: I will give you the early and late rain.
Spiritually, however, Christ is the early rain for us, when we receive the foundations of His faith, by which being rooted, we may abound in good works.
Later on, when the crops are ready for harvest—that is, when our good deeds are complete—we will be stored in the Lord's barns.
For now, the rain is early, while we only know in part.
There will be a later rain when what is perfect comes.
Therefore, the Jews who did not receive the early rain and harvested without rain will not receive the fruit of the seed in the end times.
What shall I do with you, Ephraim?
What shall I do with you, Judah?
How can I hand you over to enemies without feeling pain in my heart?
What remedy can I apply to restore you to health?
Your mercy is like the morning cloud and like the early dew that passes away.
Just as the cloud that made the night dark passes when the sun comes, and just as the early dew dries up when the sun rises, so that mercy with which I used to show you compassion has passed away.
Now the time of captivity is near for you, soon to come through the Assyrians and Babylonians.
Because of this, I have shaped you through the prophets.
So that the Jews would not make excuses, saying: "We were deceived by false prophets who promised us peace, and that is why we sinned," the Lord testifies that He first killed the prophets. Understanding that those who caused their error were killed by the Lord, they might turn their deaths into an opportunity for salvation.
From this, we read in the Books of Kings about 450 prophets who were killed, and another countless multitude by Jehu, who overthrew the house of Ahab. Hence it is added, "I have killed them with the word of my mouth." The mouth of the Lord was Elijah, who commanded them to be killed.
Alternatively: Because, specifically, mercy has departed from those who act wickedly; I have shaped them, that is, I have foretold through the prophets that they would be shaped, as was Isaiah, Jeremiah, and others; and with my fearful words, I threatened them so that those who despised the merciful one might fear the offended one.
And I have killed them with the word of my mouth, so that sinners might be punished by the terror of words before captivity approached. All these things, as my judgments, by which I will judge you, will go forth like light; that is, they will be made manifest.
Because I often rebuke you and you remain unrepentant, you will be condemned in broad daylight with many nations watching.
My judgments will certainly go forth like light, so no one will doubt that you have justly suffered what you are enduring.
These words can also refer to heretics or to the men of Judah, whom the Lord calls to mercy and wishes to return to salvation.
For those who are unrepentant, the prosperity of this world, like clouds or dew, will be taken away from them, much like what happened to the rich man dressed in purple, who realized that everything he enjoyed passed away like a cloud or dew.
The Lord always warns the prophets of heretics by threatening them with eternal punishments.
Their judgments will become evident when, with everyone watching, they will be condemned along with the devil and his angels.
For I desired mercy and not sacrifice, and the knowledge of God more than burnt offerings.
The Jews, sinning in various ways, thought they could be purified by the offerings of sacrifices.
But the Lord showed that he rather wanted mercy—first, that they have mercy on themselves, as it is said: Son, have mercy on your soul, pleasing God; then on the poor, and the knowledge of true faith with self-awareness, rather than burnt offerings, because without faith and mercy it is impossible to please God.
But they, like Adam, have transgressed my covenant.
As if to say: Therefore, they cannot be purified by sacrifices, as they think, because just as Adam, by tasting the forbidden fruit, despised God's command, so they, by transgressing the divine law, act against God's command, which said to them: Do not make for yourselves other gods.
Just as Adam lost paradise, so they will lose the land they had received as an inheritance.
Where this is, in Adam, or even in paradise, they have transgressed against me, according to what the Apostle says: In whom all have sinned.
Daily, the Lord also calls to repentance those who are within the Church and sin, and those who dwell outside the Church, to the mercy and knowledge of true faith, saying: I desire mercy, etc.
These people seem to offer gifts to God, pursue humility, and do charity, which would be considered sacrifices if they came from the right faith and good will.
But since they reject both mercy and the true knowledge of God, they falsely boast of having other parts of faith while missing the most important part.
They have broken God’s covenant in the Church, just as Adam did in paradise; and just as Adam was cast out from paradise, they will be cast out from the Church.
Gilead is a city of idol worshipers.
Gilead is the name of a city or mountain, but here it refers to a city located across the Jordan in the tribe of Gad.
In this city, an idol was first consecrated because it was inhabited by priests.
It was also a city of refuge, but because it was so prominent and had greater authority, being assigned to the priests, it became the origin of idolatry and all evils.
Since they were the first to consecrate idols, they were the first to be captured by the Assyrians and taken into captivity.
Overthrown by blood.
We read in the Book of Kings that Jehu, anointed as king in Ramoth-Gilead, destroyed, under the Lord’s command, the entire house of Ahab, including his seventy sons and others who agreed with him in evil.
Therefore, the city itself is said to be overthrown (that is, humiliated) by blood, or because the vengeance for the blood it shed came upon it, as we will see later.
And like the jaws of robbers.
The jaws of robbers are caves and other hidden places where they hide, rob, and kill passers-by.
Such dwellings existed in the same region.
Therefore, it is said that Gilead is like the jaws of robbers because, just as those robbers, lying in wait, stripped and killed people, so the priests of Gilead, lying in wait for the simplicity of the people, robbed them of faith and killed them in mind.
Those they could not deceive, they stripped of their clothes and killed physically.
And this is what follows, the accomplice of the priests in the way of those killing travelers from Shechem.
Sichem is a city on the border of twelve tribes, known today as Nablus.
The Israelites would pass through on their way to Jerusalem, the only place they were allowed to offer sacrifices.
Therefore, during the three times a year when the people were required by law to go up to the temple of God, the priests of idols would place robbers along the route to ambush those traveling, so they would worship golden calves in Dan and Bethel instead of the Lord in Jerusalem.
Those they could not turn back, they would kill on the same path.
The priests of Gilead were involved in this, as they conspired and agreed with the aforementioned priests, and similarly killed those traveling to Jerusalem through their own agents.
Hence, it follows that they committed a crime, either in killing those people or in idolatry.
But even now, false teachers lie in wait on the way, that is, on the journey of this present life, for those traveling to the heavenly Jerusalem, and kill those they can in Sichem, that is, in good works, by leading them back to wickedness through their false teachings or bad example.
Sichem means "shoulder."
On the shoulder, however, work is understood.
Hence, we read about Issachar, that he put his shoulder to work.
In the house of Israel, I have seen something horrible.
Horror sometimes means fear, as it is written: "It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God."
Sometimes it means filth and something disgusting; hence: "You did not shudder at the virgin's womb," meaning you did not consider it dirty.
Therefore, in this place, horror is used to mean the fear of idolatry.
For the prophet was terrified seeing the idol that the Israelites had made, abandoning God, and thus he said: In the house of Israel, that is, in the congregation of the twelve tribes, I saw idolatry.
For what could be more dreadful than twelve tribes suddenly turning to idol worship?
There, the fornications of Ephraim, Israel was defiled.
It was mentioned earlier that by the name Ephraim, Jeroboam is understood, namely the first king of the twelve tribes, and Israel, referring to his entire kingdom.
In the house of Israel, something terrible appeared: the fornications of Ephraim, which refers to Jeroboam from the tribe of Ephraim.
He abandoned God and began to worship idols.
A man commits fornication when he deserts the Creator (who is the husband of the soul) and joins himself to an adulterer (that is, the devil).
With Jeroboam fornicating, Israel, the people under his rule, were contaminated, as they largely retained the common name of Israel.
The discourse then turns to Judah, adding: But you, Judah, prepare a harvest for yourself.
The meaning is clear: Do not think you are secure just because Israel is being taken captive; you too need to prepare crops to be harvested, meaning children who will be cut down by Nebuchadnezzar and his army.
Not long after, you will be taken captive to Babylon, and the time of your harvesting (that is, killing) will come.
When I restore the captivity of my people, you will understand and see.
This was fulfilled under Cyrus, king of the Persians, when through the efforts of Zerubbabel, Jeshua, and Nehemiah, the Jews returned to their land.
Many who had witnessed the captivity also saw the return of those born in Chaldea, and they returned together.
Note, however, that the captivity and return of Judah are equally prophesied, but nothing is said about Israel.
While Judah returned after seventy years, Israel remained perpetually captive.
Something terrible also appears in the house of heretics when, following corrupt doctrines, they have wrong thoughts about Christ.
By the error of their fornication, the people seduced by them are defiled.
Judah, meaning ecclesiastical men, are also instructed to prepare a harvest of cutting, to be reaped because of their sins on the day of judgment, by the one who in the Revelation of John is said to have a sharp sickle in his hand.
This, however, is not said with the wish of one desiring it, but as a prophecy.
For even these, if they repent, will see their conversion from evil to good.
Chapter Seven
When I wanted to heal Israel, I understood that their idolatry, which they practiced in Egypt or in the desert when they fashioned the calf’s head, saying: These are your gods, was the issue.
I preferred the repentance of a sinner over death.
The iniquity of Ephraim was revealed, specifically the idolatry of Jeroboam, who suddenly became king over the Israelites and made golden calves.
The wickedness of Samaria, meaning the people who followed the wicked king, was exposed.
Both the king and the people practiced falsehood, worshipping idols.
Just as falsehood is contrary to truth, so is an idol to God.
In this falsehood, they acted by proclaiming these idols as gods, transferring the glory of God to them.
A thief entered to steal, and a bandit stayed outside.
The difference between a thief and a bandit is that a thief seeks the night and acts secretly, while a bandit openly uses force.
In this context, we should understand the thief or bandit to be Jeroboam, who secretly stole the house of Israel from God and openly robbed the people of God's protection.
The sense is: When I wanted to erase the old sins of my people due to their ancient idolatry, Ephraim and Samaria found new idols.
This can also mean that when the Lord Savior wanted to heal the sins of the Church, both of the Jews and the Gentiles, new false teachings arose, causing many to work falsehood against Christ, and through them, a thief and bandit, representing the devil, entered the Church.
Or we may understand the thief and the bandit to be the heretics, of whom the Lord says: He who does not enter by the door into the sheepfold but climbs in another way, he is a thief and a bandit.
All who came before me are thieves and bandits.
From this, he significantly says that the bandit outside robs.
For they cannot deprive those they have taught of Christ’s garment unless they have led them outside of the Church and made them follow their doctrines.
And so, they don't say in their hearts, "He remembered all our wickedness. Now their own schemes have surrounded them." They don't think, "He is punishing us for old sins, and we are paying for the faults of our fathers," as it is written: "Our fathers ate sour grapes, and the children's teeth were set on edge."
But now, in the present, their own schemes have surrounded them. This means that I am punishing them not for the sins of their fathers or for old iniquities, but for their current ones. They thought their wickedness was hidden from God, but God sees everything. Therefore, it is said: "Before my face, their deeds are done," meaning I always see their wicked deeds, which they commit in my presence without fearing me. The wicked are condemned not only for past sins but because they add new impiety to their old deeds every day. When they think they can hide from the Lord, they cannot avoid His eyes, because it is written: "The face of the Lord is against those who do evil."
In their wickedness, they cheered the king, giving their consent to King Jeroboam to worship idols as he wished, and in their lies when they said, "These are your gods." It is implied that the princes also cheered because they consented to the king. Note that this explains what they did in his presence. Everyone who serves a perverse work or thinks badly of Christ, like Arius and others, cheers the king (that is, the devil), and in the lies of wicked doctrines, the princes (the devil's followers), who are called the princes of the devil's darkness.
The opposing forces greatly rejoice in our sins.
All adulterers are like an oven heated by the baker.
This is spoken against those who cheered the king in their wickedness and the princes in their lies.
All adulterers, meaning those who turn away from their own husband, God, are like an oven heated by the baker.
Just as an oven is heated to bake bread, they were heated by the wickedness of Jeroboam and the fire of idolatry.
The city took a brief respite from the spread of new practices, until everyone was influenced.
Indeed, after creating the idols, Jeroboam did not force the people to worship them, fearing that some might resist for the sake of God and religion, which would undermine that worship.
Thus, the city rested for a while until the people, by their own choice, aligned with the king.
First, the leaders, then their followers, supporting the king and the leaders, and eventually, the entire population was led astray.
This is what is meant by: Until the whole was leavened.
For actions taken willingly last long, whereas those done out of necessity quickly fall apart.
Considering this, Jeroboam preferred that the people willingly adopt the new idol worship rather than being coerced.
Yeast can be used both positively and negatively.
In a positive sense, as the Lord mentions in the Gospel, a woman took yeast and hid it in three measures of flour.
However, here it is used negatively, representing the corruption of the people through idol worship.
Heretics also hide their malicious intentions for a long time, masking falsehoods with truths, until their followers willingly obey them.
Eventually, the hearts of the deceived swell with the yeast of their wicked doctrine, about which the Lord says: Beware of the yeast of the Pharisees.
The day of our king.
The entire population, inflamed with the worship of the golden calves, began to say at the gates of Jeroboam's palace: The day of our king, meaning, this is the day our emperor declared festive for us.
We celebrate, we rejoice, and we worship golden calves.
The leaders began to lose control due to wine.
While the people shouted: This is the day our king made sacred for us, the leaders, who should have guided the people, instead lost their reason and indulged in madness from luxury and idolatry.
He stretched out his hand with mockers, because their hearts were like an oven, while they lay in wait.
When the king saw the people shouting as we had foretold, and the leaders were also drunken and immersed in the wine of idolatry, he extended his hand with the mockers.
These leaders were wickedly deceiving the people and leading them far from their God by blessing and giving thanks, or by agreeing with their errors.
They had turned their hearts like an oven, burning and blazing with the flames of idolatry.
Therefore, the king clapped his hands and gave thanks to the people along with the leaders, because he understood that they had completely turned their minds to errors.
He did this while plotting against them, so they would not go up to the temple of the Lord but would worship the calves he had made.
He had deceitfully created those calves to prevent the people of Israel from going to the temple of God in Jerusalem and reconciling with the king of Judah.
The whole night he slept, cooking them, and in the morning, he himself was ignited like a flame of fire.
After he implanted the fire of wickedness in their hearts and saw them raging, with no one resisting his will, he slept the whole night securely, dwelling in darkness and cooking them with the fire of impiety.
But in the morning, he himself was ignited with the flames of his crimes and came to sacrifice.
All were heated like an oven because, when they no longer secretly but brazenly turned from the worship of God to the ceremonies of idols, they were all set ablaze with the wickedness of their iniquity.
They devoured their judges—those who did not agree with them but even rebuked them, and they killed them.
Or certainly, those who had stood before their judges were spiritually killed by being drawn into their wickedness.
When they remembered the religions of the Lord, seeing the king, the leaders, and all the people given to idolatry, they began to say: What shall we do?
Behold, the king, his leaders, and all the people worship gods.
Now, because we are among them, we cannot help but do likewise, lest we be stripped of all things, even lose our lives.
While they were saying these things, they also fell into the crime of idolatry.
All their kings have fallen.
From Jeroboam to the last king Josiah, all the kings of Israel fell into idolatry and faced eternal destruction.
They followed the ways of Jeroboam, son of Nebat, who caused Israel to sin.
Not one among them called to me, meaning no king or subject turned to God and left behind idols.
Blessed Jerome refers all these things to the heretics and their disciples, who, intoxicated by the malice of the devil (who is the king over all the wicked), celebrate the days of their leaders.
For example, Marcion, Arius, and Eunomius abandoned the Church and trampled on the truth of the faith.
Hence, those who lead the rest applaud them because they see their hearts filled with wickedness and infused with the wine of iniquity.
Solomon says: "Leaders should not drink wine, lest they forget wisdom." They also become insane from wine. Moses said: "Their wine is the fury of dragons," etc.
As for Jeroboam sleeping all night, it shows that heretics, dwelling in the darkness of unbelief, cannot perceive the light of the true sun. For those who sleep, sleep at night because their senses are oppressed. Their hearts are known to be heated by anger, greed, and other vices. They devour their judges, meaning if anyone has the virtue or sense to discern good from evil, they are drawn away from them. All the leaders of such people fall under God's predestination. There is none among them who calls to the Lord, to call on the name of the Lord and be saved.
Ephraim mingled with the peoples. Here, Ephraim does not only refer to the kings, as mentioned earlier, but to the entire people of the ten tribes. Ephraim, meaning the entire kingdom of the ten tribes, mingled with the peoples, meaning they were similar to the nations worshiping idols. Ephraim is like a half-baked bread that is not turned. A bread that is not turned is full of filth on all sides.
In this way, Ephraim became unable to repent.
Remaining unchangeable, he was surrounded by the ashes of sins.
If he had wanted to turn away from his wickedness, he could have been purified.
Foreigners consumed his strength, and he did not know it.
By "strength," it means the leaders and all the strong men of the people, or the treasures in which they trusted. Foreigners, from God or even from the Jewish nation, specifically his enemies the Chaldeans and Assyrians, consumed his strength by killing the leaders, claiming their goods, and devouring whatever power they could.
Ephraim was so foolish that he did not know his God or understand why he had been handed over to his devourers, considering himself righteous. But even gray hairs are sprinkled upon him, and he did not know it.
The gray hairs of men are sometimes mentioned for good, as in Solomon’s saying: "Gray hair is the wisdom of a man, and the age of old age is a blameless life." However, here they are mentioned for ill, showing that wickedness persisted in the same people until the end of the kingdom.
But even gray hairs, he says, are sprinkled upon him, meaning that wickedness persisted abundantly until old age and the end of the kingdom. And he did not know that the end of his kingdom was near.
And the pride of Israel will be humbled before him. For Israel had raised itself against the Lord and trusted not in Him, but in the multitude of its own army. Because God resists the proud but gives grace to the humble, He now says through the Prophet: The pride of Israel will be humbled, meaning that the leaders and his army (in which he gloried) will be killed by the Assyrians and Chaldeans.
This will happen not long after, but now and in the present.
For this is what he says: Before him.
They did not return to the Lord their God, and they did not seek Him in all these things.
What he had previously stated obscurely, saying: Ephraim became like a cake not turned, he now states more clearly: They did not, he says, return to the Lord their God, and they did not seek Him in all these things.
If they had returned to the Lord their God, they would have surely heard the Lord speaking through Jeremiah:
"Return to me, and I will return to you."
But instead of seeking Him, they chased after idols and did not trust Him fully or act rightly in their adversities.
Now, if we apply this to heretics or wicked leaders, it's like Ephraim mixing with the people when a wicked leader draws others to his ways and becomes like them. As it was said before:
"Like people, like priest."
Ephraim also mixes with the people because heretics are no different from the errors of pagans. A once-leader of the Church becomes like bread baked on ashes, surrounded by the ashes of sins, and does not return to the Lord, remaining in his initial error. His strength—the virtue and intelligence—gets taken away by demons, the worst enemies of Christians. But he doesn't realize this, thinking those who devour him are friends. Gray hairs appear on him while his foolish heart remains unchanged until the end of his life.
Just as the wisdom of a righteous man is reflected in his gray hairs, the foolishness of the wicked is also apparent. Yet, he doesn't recognize the old age of his wickedness, about which it is written:
"What is becoming old and aging is close to destruction."
Though their pride is humbled daily by Christ, they do not repent or return to the Lord. Ephraim has become like a deceived dove, without a heart.
The dove is seen positively, as the Lord says in the Gospel:
"Be wise as serpents and innocent as doves,"
so that we neither harm others nor suffer deceit, showing a balanced person with both simplicity and prudence. Prudence without simplicity is cunning; simplicity without prudence is foolishness.
Therefore, in this context, the dove represents the foolishness of the Jewish people, who trusted in man rather than in God, calling upon Egypt and seeking help from the Assyrians.
For those who sought help from Egypt, which Isaiah calls a "broken reed staff," they were taken captive by the Assyrians. Thus, Ephraim became like a dove deceived by the devil, lacking heart—that is, the understanding of the mind.
It's noteworthy that they are not compared to an eagle, a hawk, a raven, or any other bird, but to a dove, which is so fragile that it cannot protect its own young. Similarly, they were captured by enemies and did not have the strength to defend themselves. They called on Egypt for help, either by worshiping their gods or asking for aid. They went to the Assyrians, not willingly, but as captives.
And when they are fully grown, I will spread my net over them, meaning that they will realize they cannot escape my sight by changing places. When they go into captivity, I will spread my net, showing my power over them, so they cannot freely return to their land as they think, until I allow it.
I will bring them down like birds of the sky. Just as a bird is brought down from the height of the sky by a net spread over the waters, so I will bring them down from the height of their pride. I will strike them according to the hearing of their assembly. The meaning is: Just as they all worshiped idols with a united plan and conspired to turn away from me, so with me angry, they will all be devastated together, as I strike them all together from the king to the beggar.
We can also refer these words to the time of the Lord's passion. Just as they conspired together regarding the Lord’s death, shouting to Pilate, "Crucify him, crucify him," so they were captured, struck, and killed by enemies during the Passover festival. Woe to them, that is, there will be eternal damnation after the present tribulation. Because they turned away from me, worshiping idols, they will be devastated by enemies and will be miserable. Because they broke faith with me, worshiping golden calves, and transgressing my commandment, which said: "You shall not make for yourselves other gods."
I redeemed them from Egyptian slavery and led them out with a powerful arm.
Yet they spoke against me with lies, making idols and saying: These are your gods, Israel, who brought you out of the land of Egypt.
They did not cry out to me in their hearts because they loved idols.
Instead, they howled in their beds, imitating the voices of wolves or dogs in praise of demons.
The songs they sang in praise of demons are called howling by Scripture.
They had lost their rational understanding and became like senseless beasts.
It is easy to understand this about heretics, for whom eternal woe is imminent, because they departed from God and transgressed His commandments, the One who redeemed them with His blood.
They speak lies against God, composing impious doctrines of falsehood, not crying out to the Lord in their hearts, but always howling in their assemblies, which are called dens of wild beasts, imitating the howling of wolves and the sound of irrational beasts.
They chewed over wheat and wine.
To chew over means to regurgitate, just as animals bring back what they eat during the day to their mouths and throats at night, and thus, by chewing over more thoroughly, send it back to their stomachs.
The sense is: Because they had an abundance of all things, which is comprehended in wine and wheat, they therefore fell away from me, which Ezekiel also recalls happening in Sodom and Gomorrah.
However, to show they were like beasts, he did not say they ate, but they chewed over.
They are also said to have chewed over in this way because they did not spiritually understand the food of divine words.
They departed from me, despising the worship of my religion and submitting themselves to the slavery of the devil.
I taught them, that is, I instructed them through Moses and other faithful ones.
I strengthened their arms, that is, I provided strength for fighting, as happened in the times of Joshua and the Maccabees.
And they thought evil against me, transferring my power to idols, and saying that I was not God, but the calves which they themselves made.
Can they do anything or harm me?
What they intended for evil against me, they have returned to their former state without a yoke.
That is, before I called them through Abraham, then through Moses and the others, they were without the yoke and knowledge of the law, mingling with all nations.
Now they have returned to their old ways, living without the yoke and guidance of God, recklessly following their desires.
They have become like a deceitful bow, perverse and turning the arrow back towards the Lord.
Though they were strengthened and extended by God to strike their adversaries, those whom God empowered against their enemies have turned against their own Lord, sending arrows of blasphemy against Him.
Their leaders will fall by the sword because of their furious words.
Just as the leaders were the head of malice and deceived the unfortunate people, now they will be the first to be truly confounded because of their furious tongues.
Mad with rage, they dared to call golden calves gods, repeating in the promised land what they learned in Egypt.
For the fury of their tongues, madness, and blasphemy are evident.
This mocking in the land of Egypt, meaning their current ridicule and idol worship, is not new.
What they did in Egypt and later in the desert, they still do now.
There they began to worship idols, and even now they persist in the same malice.
Spiritually, through wheat and wine, we can understand the mysteries of the body and blood of Christ, or the Holy Scripture, which provides food in obscure places and drink in easier places.
Heretics stumble over this wheat and wine, unworthily taking the body and blood of the Lord and interpreting the divine Scripture with a perverse understanding.
By continually reading and meditating on the law and other Scriptures, they pretend to understand what they do not.
In doing so, they depart from the Lord, who taught them in the Church and gave them strength to fight against adversaries.
They plot evil against God, creating the most wicked heresies, and become like the pagans, reduced to nothing.
Such people turn into deceitful bows, bringing eternal death upon themselves with their opinions.
Thus, the leaders of heretics, due to the madness of their speech and their blasphemy against the Lord, are struck by the judgment of the true judge.
They continue to do in the so-called false Church what they did before when they dwelled in Egypt, that is, in the darkness of unbelief and ignorance.
Chapter Eight
Let a trumpet be in your throat.
The voice of God is to the prophet, who is commanded to raise his voice like a trumpet, so that many may hear him shouting, because many have sinned.
Then, he immediately adds what the prophet should say with his raised voice: Like an eagle over the house of the Lord.
Here, the eagle refers to Nebuchadnezzar, coming against Jerusalem and the temple of God.
He is compared to an eagle because of his great speed and rapacity, mimicking the swift flight of an eagle hastening to its prey.
Hence, Ezekiel speaks of him metaphorically: A great eagle with large wings, with long pinions, came to Lebanon.
Indeed, the temple of God, over which the prophet is commanded to announce the arrival of the eagle, is called Lebanon by Ezekiel.
Therefore, Zechariah also speaks, saying: Open your doors, Lebanon, that fire may devour your cedars.
Because they have broken my covenant and have rebelled against my law.
This verse pertains to the above, where the prophet is commanded to cry out with a loud voice, as the eagle is over the house of God.
The meaning is: What I say to you, O prophet, and command you to let a trumpet be in your throat, that is, to announce with a loud voice the coming of the king of the Chaldeans, I command this for no other reason than that they have broken my covenant by making idols, and have rebelled against my law, where I said: You shall not make for yourselves gods of gold or silver.
They will call upon me, My God, we know you, Israel.
When captivity occurs, pressed by distress, compelled by necessity, they will call upon me, asking for help and mercy, and will say: We know you, Israel, that is, we who are called Israel and retain the ancient name of Jacob, who pleased you.
We know you and recognize you, and because of the knowledge of you that we have above all nations, deliver us.
Israel has rejected the good; the enemy will pursue him.
This is the response of Almighty God to what they had said: We know you, Israel.
And the meaning is:
How can you be called by the name Israel, which means "man seeing God," when you have rejected the good, that is, the Lord God, from whom Jacob was called Israel?
For the good that Israel rejected is understood to be God, of whom it is written: No one is good except God alone.
Therefore, Israel rejected the good, which means they abandoned their God and regarded Him as nothing.
Thus, when they cry out, I will not listen to them because of the false name Israel, but an enemy (that is, the Assyrian, or even the devil) will pursue and capture them, who, having abandoned me as their king, sought a king for themselves, as the other nations have.
Hence, it immediately adds: They have set up kings, but not by me; they have appointed princes, but I did not acknowledge them.
If we want to refer this to their first king, Saul, a question arises as to why the Lord says: They have set up kings, but not by me, etc.
, when the Lord chose him and established him as king by lot.
For even Samuel, after establishing him as king, said: Surely you see whom the Lord has chosen.
Hence, he also revealed him hidden in the house, and disclosed it to Samuel's ear before his arrival.
But it must be understood that Almighty God sometimes permits what He does not want, as is certainly evident from the choice itself.
For He saw their hearts inclined to the election of a king, and therefore allowed it to happen according to their request, against His will.
This is clearly shown by the thunder and lightning that occurred in summer, against the custom of that land.
Hence, Samuel, knowing that God did not want this, foretold to them the rights of the king, who would subject them to very harsh servitude, so that they might return to the Lord, the most merciful king.
But if we refer this to Jeroboam, who later ruled over the ten tribes, and to the other princes who succeeded him in the kingdom, we clearly recognize that this was done against God's order.
For although God, angered by Solomon's sin, wanted to divide the kingdom, yet against His will, the people of Israel chose Jeroboam.
He should have consulted God according to the command, to see if God wanted this to happen, and then chosen a king by lot, not by his own will.
Often, there are unavoidable reasons, but because people do not follow God's will and instead pursue their own, they sin gravely.
For example, it is said of the Lord Savior that the Son of Man must be handed over, die, and be buried, and then it is added: Woe to that man by whom He is betrayed.
Judas, in His death, did not consider our necessity or God's will, but followed his own greed.
Therefore, what God had preordained to happen, this man, by doing so, was condemned to eternal death.
They ruled, but not by my will; princes came forth, and I did not know them, that is, I did not choose them, and therefore I reject them.
For God's knowing is choosing, and not knowing is rejecting.
They made their gold and silver into idols for themselves to perish.
Because they had abundance, they neglected God who gave these to them for adornment and delight.
They made idols for themselves, leading to their own destruction, because the gods they made caused their death and ruin.
Spiritually, these things said about Nebuchadnezzar can be referred to the devil, who in many places of divine Scripture is called an eagle.
Hence, it is said: If you are exalted like an eagle, from there I will bring you down, says the Lord.
This eagle came over the gatherings of heretics, because they were once houses of God.
Since they transgressed God's law and invoke God in vain with words, but are far from Him in deeds, and reject God through false teaching, they choose kings for themselves against God's will, namely leaders and authors of perverse doctrines, which God does not acknowledge, because they do not deserve His recognition.
Those who, in their eloquence or spiritual brilliance, perversely understand and turn these into idols, which they fashioned from their own hearts, and because they did this, they perished.
Your golden calf has been cast away, Samaria.
Samaria, the capital of the ten tribes, represents all the cities of the same kingdom.
The golden calves were not in Samaria itself, but in Dan and Bethel, which are included in Samaria.
We should take one calf to represent the two, using a singular number for a plural, as often seen in the Scriptures.
When he says, "Your calf has been cast away," it means the temple of idols has been destroyed by the Assyrians. The calves themselves have also been cast away, melted down, and taken into captivity. Hence, it is immediately added, "My anger burned against them." This means I have avenged myself on them, whether on the calves or on those who worshipped them.
How long will they be unable to be corrected? It's as if to say: What madness is this, that while I am giving them a chance to repent, they refuse to turn to health?
Explaining what this calf was, from whose filth they could not be cleansed, he adds:
Because it is from Israel. They did not receive the calf from elsewhere, like Baal and Astaroth from the Sidonians, Chemosh from the Moabites, or Moloch from the Ammonites. Instead, they and their king Jeroboam made the calf. An artisan made it, meaning Jeroboam, the inventor of the evil, or certainly any artisan ordered by him, showing that it is not a god that the craftsman's hand forms, but an idol.
The calf of Samaria will be like spider webs, just as spider webs are dissolved and annihilated by the wind, so their calf will be reduced to nothing. Again, one calf is used to represent the two. Because they sow the wind, and they will reap the whirlwind. They sow is used for they have sown, the future for the past, as often happens in the Scriptures.
He says they sow the wind, meaning they perform vain works, making an idol completely devoid of divinity, and therefore they will reap the whirlwind, that is, captivity, storm, and misery. The standing stalk has no grain, and the sprout will not produce flour.
When seeds are scattered and spoiled by the wind, losing their inner core, they can't produce grain that can be made into flour.
This means that just as spoiled seeds do not yield fruit, good works cannot be found in them, nor can they have any semblance of fruitful action.
Hence, it is added: even if they do produce something, strangers will eat it.
This means that if they manage to have any power for a time or do any good, strangers, such as the Assyrians, will take it all away, or even demons, about whom the Lord speaks in the Gospel, saying that birds of the air ate the scattered seeds.
Israel was devoured by enemies who killed them or by demons who took all their good.
Now they have become like the nations, similar to the Gentiles who worship idols.
Hence, it is added, like an unclean vessel.
An unclean vessel, in the literal sense, refers to something used for holding and disposing of filth.
They were like this, stained with the filth and dirt of idols, made into a vessel not for honor but for disgrace, and so they were cast away by the Lord as unclean.
For what could be more unclean than a demonic spirit?
All of this can be applied to heretics, who follow empty things, and so they will depart empty.
Those who sow in the flesh will reap corruption and disgrace from the flesh.
While it may seem that the stalk of ecclesiastical doctrine stands in them because they are baptized and celebrate the mysteries of Christ's body, it will not make flour, meaning it will not lead to the fruit of good work, because all their actions are empty and worthless.
Even if they do something, strangers will eat it, because, elevated by human favor, they will lose all their good, and therefore they will lack the fruit of reward in the future.
They are often devoured by enemies, that is, demons, and become an unclean vessel, becoming like the pagans, even losing the name of Christianity.
Because they went up to Assyria, not willingly, but bearing the harm of captivity unwillingly.
The wild donkey, Ephraim, is alone.
A wild donkey is a wild ass that, unlike sheep, does not require domestic pastures but roams freely through different places and prefers solitary habitation.
The Jews who strayed from God became like this, running after various idols according to their whims and making various gods for themselves.
Abandoned by God, they became solitary.
It is further said, "They gave gifts to their lovers," that is, to the Assyrians, with whom they had once formed an alliance. This happened during the times of King Menahem or King Hoshea, as previously mentioned. They also hired nations with payment, implying they sought their help, as shown earlier when it is said that Ephraim went to Assyria and sent to the avenging king.
Now I will gather them, implying for battle, so that all may be led captive together. They will rest for a while from the burden of kings and princes. As if to say: Until now, they loved giving gifts to their adversaries, whom they cherished. But now, I will make them cease for a while, so that while they pass into captivity, they will not pay tributes even to their own kings and princes until they arrive in Assyria, where they will no longer give tributes and payments like free people but will be reduced to the utmost servitude.
Because Ephraim multiplied altars for sinning, the altars became a sin for him. This shows the reason why they suffer captivity and stop giving gifts to kings and princes for a while: because Ephraim, that is Jeroboam, or indeed all the people of the ten tribes, multiplied altars where they compounded sins with sins. Therefore, they sinned even more, because they worshipped idols not only in Dan or Bethel but also in the mountains, groves, and various places. These altars, that is, sacrificial altars, turned into sin for him, because the more they were, the more they sinned there.
"I will write for him my many laws."
Because they consider the law I gave them through Moses to be of no value by worshipping idols in various places, although I commanded that there should be one altar in Jerusalem, I will bring upon them many laws to correct them.
But again, noting their wickedness, he adds that even those laws are considered foreign.
It is as if he said: Because they despised the law they had previously received, what good will it do to write more laws?
They will bring offerings, sacrifice meat, and eat it.
Here it is shown that they made many altars to bring offerings and sacrifices in various places, to fill their own stomachs, not to please the Lord.
Therefore, it is added, the Lord will not accept them.
Because they were not offered to Him, but rather to demons.
For they did not sacrifice them to the Lord, but to their own stomachs and throats.
All their effort was to eat the offerings themselves, not to please the Lord through them.
Heretics also multiply altars for themselves when, abandoning the truth, they create various doctrines for themselves, not to please God, but to provoke Him.
Indeed, the altar of the Holy Church is one, even though many altars are built in different places around the world, just as there is one faith and one baptism according to the teaching of the Apostle Paul.
When heretics abandon this, they incur a more serious sin.
Therefore, they do not deserve to receive God's laws, because they despised the ones they had received before, abandoning the one true sacrifice of Christ's body, and offering various victims, eating and consecrating the mysteries of Christ as they please.
Hence, whatever they do, such as almsgiving, humility, chastity, and other works of virtue, are considered worthless by God.
Nor will the Lord accept any of these sacrifices, because they seek their own glory in them, not God's.
Now He will remember their iniquities and visit their sins.
There is a difference between iniquity and sin.
Iniquity is whatever is committed before divine knowledge.
Sin, however, when committed after the law, is considered even more severe.
Hence, it is said: Blessed are those whose iniquities are forgiven, and whose sins are covered.
And those who persist in their transgressions, the Lord remembers their iniquities, which they committed before the law, but He punishes their sins.
Therefore, because they sinned after the law was given, it is now said that He will remember their iniquities to avenge them, and He will visit their former sins with scourges and the torment of misery and captivity.
They themselves will turn back to Egypt.
This can be understood in three ways.
First, they turned back to Egypt by worshipping their gods in their minds.
Second, by seeking help, not trusting in God's protection.
And finally, when God commanded them not to return to Egypt, they despised God and physically returned to Egypt and lived there.
And Israel forgot their Maker and built temples.
By the name Israel, as often said, the whole people of the ten tribes are understood, retaining for the most part their former name.
They forgot the worship of their God, worshipped Baals and Astartes and other idols on mountains and hills and under shady trees, and built temples there, constructing temples for the gods.
And Judah multiplied fortified cities.
By the name Judah, two tribes are understood, namely Judah and Benjamin, along with the priestly tribe.
When they saw that Israel had turned away from the love of God, and their sins were visited upon them, they did not turn to the Lord but built fortified cities for themselves to protect them.
But it did them no good because, as the history of the Kings tells, in the fortieth year of Hezekiah, Sennacherib came up and destroyed all the fortified cities and captured them.
Hence, it is added: And I will send fire on their cities, and it shall devour their houses.
Fire indeed is called Sennacherib, who destroyed both public and private houses and burned them with fire.
If we relate these things to heretics, just like other matters, both the sins forgiven in their baptism and the new sins they committed after baptism are counted against them.
They are punished for returning to Egypt, which symbolizes the darkness of unbelief, from which they had departed through the confession of Christ.
By forgetting their God and creating various shrines—meaning doctrines of falsehood—Judas, a churchman, through his evil deeds or perverse interpretation of the Holy Scriptures, builds fortified cities for himself, not with the help of God, but through deceit.
While misunderstanding the Scriptures, he tries to confirm his errors with divine testimonies, which the Lord will burn with the fire of His Spirit and bring to nothing.
Chapter Nine
Do not rejoice, Israel, do not exult like other nations, because you have strayed from your God.
Nations that do not know God and worship various demonic idols rejoice in such things.
Seeing this, the Israelites also began to rejoice in the worship of their gods, thinking they were like other nations and enjoying peace like them.
Therefore, it is said to them: Do not rejoice, Israel, because you have turned away from me.
You will not have peace for long as you think; instead, you will be taken captive to be punished for your sins.
You wanted to pay me the tribute of servitude, but you became like people who do not know me, who also rejoice and celebrate in their gods.
So do not rejoice, because you have strayed from your God, and do not think you are like other nations, because it is different to be ignorant of God and different to turn away from God.
A servant who knows his master's will and does not do it will be beaten severely.
You loved reward more than all the threshing floors of wheat.
By threshing floors and wheat, we understand the abundance of all things that the same people enjoyed, all of which they thought were given to them as a reward because they had abandoned God and started worshiping idols.
For everything they received from God, they attributed to idols, which is why it is threatened that all these things will be taken away from them by God's just judgment, with the following being added:
The threshing floor and the winepress will not feed them, meaning I will send them famine so that no wheat will be found in the threshing floors and no wine in the presses.
This is known to have happened in the times of Elijah and Elisha when, driven by hunger, mothers fed on the corpses of their children.
And the wine will deceive them, meaning it will fail, and there will be none in the vineyards or presses as they thought.
It is also said to heretics not to rejoice, who think they are like other nations when they depart from the unity of the Church, because those who sinned without the law will perish without the law, and those who turned away from the true faith after knowing God will be punished more severely.
Those who have an abundance of worldly goods, with barns and wine presses—that is, the body and blood of Christ—are not satisfied.
Because while they eat unworthily, they prepare for themselves everlasting sorrow and eternal torment.
They will not live in the Lord’s land.
Not only will they suffer from hunger in the land they received from the Lord, but they will also be taken into captivity, unable to live in the land they have defiled with their crimes.
Ephraim has returned to Egypt.
This can be understood as either returning in their hearts or, as mentioned earlier, by worshiping their gods.
In Assyria, they eat what is defiled.
Just as they ate food sacrificed to idols in their own land, when taken into captivity, they eat the sacrifices of demons in Assyria.
What was offered to idols became defiled.
They will not pour wine to the Lord, but to demons, and it will not please Him.
For they could not pour wine to the Lord in Chaldea, as they did not have a temple or altar for this.
Their sacrifices are like the bread of mourners.
All who eat it will be defiled.
Among the Jews, when a sacrifice was offered for the dead, whoever ate from it became unclean, as did the sacrifice itself.
The sacrifice is called the bread of mourners because it was offered for the dead, whose relatives mourned their death.
Another way: It was customary among the Jews to mourn the dead for seven days.
During this time of lamentation, whatever was made in the house of the deceased was unclean.
Anyone who ate from that house or touched anything became unclean.
Therefore, they ate elsewhere until the seventh day.
On the first day, they mourned the dead, who were still lying in the same house.
After the burial, the bier was placed in the middle, and they lamented as if the dead were present.
According to this custom, the prophet says: Their sacrifices are like the bread of mourners.
The meaning here is: Just as the things in a dead person's house were considered unclean for seven days during mourning, and anyone who ate or drank there became unclean, so too are the sacrifices of those who offer them to idols unclean, including both the sacrifices themselves and those who offer or consume them.
Their bread is prepared for their own souls, meaning they offer bread and other items to idols to satisfy themselves and find joy in this present life.
Here, "soul" refers to the present life, as it often does in divine scripture, as in He who loves his life will lose it.
They will not enter the house of the Lord because their offerings are not to the Lord, but to demons. "Bread" is used to mean all food and sacrifice. It's easy to understand this about heretics, who do not dwell in the house of the Lord, meaning the Church of the faithful, often called "earth" because of the firmness of faith. Hence, John says: They went out from us, but they did not really belong to us.
They will return to Egypt, imitating the works of the unfaithful. They eat polluted things among the Assyrians, satisfying their desires in the company of demons, and do not offer wine to the Lord because they are not spiritually joyful in Him. Thus, they will not please Him, and whatever they do will be considered unclean.
They will not be able to enter the house of the Lord, because everything they do will turn into mourning. They may do good works, like preaching words, which are called bread, to give to their listeners, but they do so for present joy, deceiving and stripping the homes of widows. This defiles those who eat, as those who accept the doctrine of heretics become unclean. The assemblies of heretics are not houses of God but are called dens of thieves.
What will you do on the day of the solemn feast, on the day of the Lord's festival? We should understand the day of the Lord's solemn feast or festival to mean the time of captivity and misery when He avenges His enemies and foes. Although all days belong to the Lord, that day is specifically said to be His, as it is compelled to render vengeance.
When the day of captivity comes, he says, and the most savage enemy advances, what celebration is there for me to enjoy, because it avenges me of my enemies and puts an end to the injury?
What will you do?
Answer.
With them remaining silent, he answers himself, or rather, he sees with divine eyes what they will do.
Hence it is added: Behold, they have departed from devastation.
In this place, the past is used instead of the future, following the usual manner of Holy Scripture.
They have departed, namely, for what is to be departing, because with the Assyrians and Chaldeans pressing down with misery and devastation, and wishing to bind the captives, they will flee to Egypt to escape the hands of the enemies.
Hence it is also added: Egypt will gather them, Memphis will bury them.
This refers to the remaining two tribes who killed Gedaliah with Jeremiah against the Lord's command, fleeing the Chaldeans and entering Egypt, where they were later killed by Nebuchadnezzar, as the book of the prophet himself testifies.
Memphis, whose inhabitants buried the Jews killed there, was the capital city of Egypt before Alexandria.
Their desirable silver, nettles will inherit, and thorns in their tents.
These words signify long-lasting desolation, because where once there were beautiful houses, now thorns and nettles have sprung up.
For by that silver is understood what is bought with silver, namely villages and fields, which long-lasting desolation has turned into wilderness.
It is also said to heretics: When the day of the Lord's feast comes, that is, the day of judgment, when he will give life back to his friends, what will you do?
Behold, you have been devastated by enemies, that is, demons, who have stripped you of all virtues, you have imitated the works of the unbelievers, and you have become like other nations.
Therefore, Memphis will bury you there, which is interpreted as from the mouth, because according to the judgments and blasphemies of your mouth you will be condemned, and you will feel in punishments what you have spoken.
Then the desirable things, like silver and the brilliance of eloquence and false teachings, will be taken over by a nettle.
Perpetual fire will consume it, burning you eternally.
It will be a thorn in your tents, symbolizing the conscience of your sins and your former way of life.
Such cares will torment you.
The days of visitation have come, the days of retribution are here.
In this context, visitation means affliction and torment.
Elsewhere, it is used positively, as in: The sunrise from on high has visited us.
The days of visitation have come, as he said earlier: What will you do on the solemn day and the festival of the Lord?
The days of retribution have come, so you will receive according to what you have done.
Know, Israel, that the prophet is foolish, the spiritual man is mad.
The people of Israel used to call the true prophets of God madmen.
We read that the princes in Ramoth-Gilead said to Jehu: What did this madman say to you?
And he replied: You know the man and what he said.
So it is said: O Israel, now recognize your own words.
You called the prophet who spoke the truth to you and prophesied by the Holy Spirit, foolish and mad.
Know, therefore, that you are foolish, without understanding, and that the prophet you called mad was speaking my words.
You thought you were a spiritual man and believed that seeing through the Holy Spirit would benefit you.
Alternatively: Know, Israel, that the prophet is foolish because you promised yourself peace, and it did not come as you falsely estimated.
Know also that you are a mad prophet, who despised my words.
You thought you were a spiritual man and believed that seeing through the spirit would benefit you.
Because of your many sins and much madness, you lost your understanding.
You did not foresee the adversities coming to you, nor did you listen to those taught by the Holy Spirit who preached these things to you, whom you additionally called mad and insane.
The day of vengeance will also come for the wicked.
When the Lord comes for judgment, they will face punishment and be repaid for their actions.
While they lived, they claimed to be Israelites, meaning people who see God—but they were not, failing to recognize their own foolishness.
They said that the Son of God was a creation, denied the Holy Spirit, and asserted that one God is good and another is the creator of the world.
Their madness is manifold because their iniquities are numerous.
The watchman of Ephraim is with my God.
The prophet has become a snare of ruin on all his ways.
The voice of the prophet: the watchman of Ephraim, understood as, with my God—that is, he was appointed by my God as a watchman over Jeroboam, who is understood by the name Ephraim—so that he and his followers, the kings, would be watchmen over the people of God, providing good things for them, and governing and instructing them according to God's will.
The rulers and prophets of the people were called watchmen.
Hence, it is also said to Ezekiel: I have made you a watchman for the house of Israel.
Thus, Jeroboam was given as a watchman and as a prophet to the people with his followers, to correct the erring people and call them back to the right path.
But he, who should have educated them, became a snare of ruin in all his actions, because through power and wicked persuasion, he made them worship idols.
He, who should have been a prophet to show the people the worship of God, taught them idolatry.
Hence, it is added here: Madness, that is, an idol in the house of his God, that is, in Bethel, where previously the house of God had been.
There he set up the golden calf to be worshipped.
They have deeply sinned, as in the days of Gibeah.
Here the prophet recalls the crime of the sons of Israel, which once happened in Gibeah when they killed the wife of a Levite returning from Bethlehem with illicit intercourse.
Thus, he says that the Israelites of his time are sunk in the abyss of impiety, surpassing the crime that was once committed in Gibeah.
We can also take the days of Gibeah as the time when they chose Saul as king for God in the city of Gibeah.
They sinned by abandoning God and choosing a human king to rule over them.
They chose Jeroboam, the son of Nebat, as their king against God's will.
They turned away from God by worshiping the calves he had made.
He will remember their iniquities, those they thought were forgotten, and he will visit their sins through captivity unto death.
God sometimes does not allow forgetfulness but is said to remember when he renders vengeance to sinners.
These things can also apply to those placed over the Church, such as bishops and priests.
By teaching perverse doctrine, they became a snare of perdition for others.
Like paths in the desert, I found Israel, like the first fruits of the fig tree.
When all nations were deserted by God, whose knowledge they did not have, I found the people of Israel, like a path in the wilderness.
Just as eagerly as new fruits are eaten, so I chose them, leaving all other nations in the desert.
He adds, like the first fruits of the fig tree, meaning those which are delightful and gathered with love.
On its top, I saw their fathers.
This means, at the beginning of this people, by the grace of my mercy, I chose Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, because they pleased me, adhering to faith and good works.
To see God is to have mercy.
But they entered into Baal-Peor, the idol of the Moabites, and turned away.
In their abundance, they became abominable, worthy of rejection.
Just as they loved those things, as written in the Psalm: Let those who make them become like them, and all who trust in them, that they may not only be idolaters but also be called idols themselves.
But to bring this back to the faithful people, in the desert of this age, when the whole world was held in sin and the nations did not know God, the Lord first found the Christian people in the apostles and apostolic men, who saw God with their minds, and He was satisfied with their sweetest fruits.
But heretics who usurp the name of Christianity for themselves have entered into Beelphegor, serving lust.
It is difficult, as blessed Jerome says, to find a heretic who loves chastity, although he often professes it with his mouth, because he speaks one thing with his lips, keeps another in his conscience, and fulfills another in action.
Hence, they are abominable and have become unclean, just like the things they loved.
Ephraim has flown away like a bird.
This means that the people of the ten tribes quickly lost their own land and went into captivity.
The prophet called him a bird to show the swift journey to Babylon.
Their glory has flown away from birth, from the womb, and from conception.
The people of the ten tribes boasted in the multitude of their children and in the multitude of their armies, and in this, they thought themselves greater than their brother Judah, because they ruled over ten tribes, while Judah ruled over two.
Therefore, they had many children, in whom they gloried, but they were all taken captive or even killed, and their glory, that is, their boasting in their children, suddenly flew away.
Hence, it is added: "And even if they raise their children, I will make them childless among men," meaning that if they gather a multitude of children and have the freedom to raise them, it will benefit them nothing, because they will be handed over to death, and I will make it so that they do not glory in them, because they will see them killed and taken captive by enemies.
While other nations rejoice in the offspring of their children, they will be without children.
But woe to them when I depart from them. For since they have departed from me, I will also depart from them, and then they will feel woe, that is, eternal damnation, when they have lost all my help.
Ephraim, as I saw, was like Tyre, founded in beauty.
Tyrus was a noble city, rich in many ways, located in the middle of the sea.
It was known as an emporium because all manner of wealth for trade could be found there, and it was filled with many citizens.
Therefore, Ephraim, representing the ten tribes, proud of their wealth and population, saw themselves as similar to Tyrus, established in beauty, honor, and splendor.
The meaning is: Ephraim was as beautiful, he says, but is now deserted, once surrounded by God's help, just like Tyrus, encircled by the sea, which defies storms and whirlwinds.
Just as Tyrus is untroubled by the waves crashing against it, so too did Ephraim, protected by God's help, consider their adversaries as insignificant.
Ephraim will bring his children to the killer.
Let us understand the killer to be Hazael, the king of Syria, who besieged Samaria for a long time until hunger forced them to surrender, believing it better to die quickly by the sword than to suffer prolonged starvation.
Tropologically, heretics are understood as Ephraim, who, like the unstable and wanton, depart from the Church and boast of the multitude of followers they gain through false teachings.
To them, the Lord threatens that even if they are nurtured, they will be punished because they are born of fornication.
Thus, the fathers are left childless, while the disciples perish along with their corrupt teachers.
As it is said: Woe to them when I depart from them.
He also reminds us what Ephraim was like when he says he was in the Church amidst the temptations of this world.
Just as Tyrus, struck by sea waves but enduring adversity because of its foundation in Christ, upon which a house cannot be overthrown, Ephraim once stood firm.
But now, he brings his children to the killer, that is, to the devil, who eternally destroys wicked souls.
And he aptly says, he brings them out, meaning he removes them from the Church.
Morally, we can say that the sons of Ephraim represent the worst thoughts and doctrines contrary to the truth, all of which the Lord destroys, not allowing sinners to have such offspring.
Leaving them eternally with their depraved doctrines and wicked thoughts, He punishes them.
Hence, it is said:
On that day, all their thoughts will perish.
Give them, Lord.
What will You give them?
Give them a womb without children and dry breasts.
So that we do not misuse what God has given for blessings and turn the things given by Him into their opposite, it is necessary that they be taken away from us.
Indeed, since we have been given a tongue to praise God and speak good things, if anyone abuses it for blasphemy, the Psalmist prays against them: Let deceitful lips be silenced, etc.
Because Ephraim gloried in the womb, in conception, and childbirth, and in the multitude of people, for which he swelled with pride when he should rather have humbled himself and given thanks to God, who had multiplied them, the prophet speaks to the Lord, saying:
Give them, Lord, and answers himself.
What will You give them?
And immediately, by cursing and provoking God against them, he adds: Give them a sterile womb and dry breasts, so that they do not have reasons for pride, and in what they usually boast, they are confounded.
For their pride was in the multitude of children, thus he says: Give them a sterile womb, so they do not generate children, and give them dry breasts, so that even if they do give birth, they do not have the means to nurse them.
All their wickedness is in Gilgal, for there I began to hate them.
In Gilgal, Saul was anointed king, with Samuel announcing God's wrath to the people.
There (he says) I began to hate them because by asking for a human king, they departed from My command.
Alternatively, we read in the book of Joshua that in Gilgal, the people of Israel were circumcised a second time, where later, under the guise of religion, they first began to worship idols, in whose worship they committed all sorts of crimes.
True, because "Galgal" means "revelation" or "rolling," it is rightly said that the wickedness of heretics is in Galgal, as their deeds must be revealed, and they themselves are to be cast down to hell. They are truly deserving of hatred because they speak lies against God. Because of the wickedness of their inventions, that is, their idolatry, which they maliciously created against me, I will cast them out of my house, that is, from Bethel, which is called the house of God. Or we can also understand the house of the Lord to mean heaven, from which they were cast out because, failing in the body, they also perish eternally in spirit. I will no longer love them. It is clear that the Lord did not add to their love, so they remain in captivity to this day. All their leaders are retreating, you might understand. By leaders here, we should understand the kings of the ten tribes, who all turned away from God through idolatry, and none of them turned to God with their whole heart. We can relate all these things to the times of Christ and understand them about the two tribes that were cast out of the house of God at his coming, so that they would not be saved, so that Israel, that is, the Christian people, would be saved. Hence, in the Gospel, we read that the Lord made a whip of cords and drove them out of the temple because they had made his Father's house a house of trade. Ephraim was struck by God, who handed them over to enemies, their root dried up, and they will produce no fruit. He takes a metaphor from a tree, whose roots, if dried up, will not bear fruit; and if it produces a little, it will immediately wither in the flower. But what root of the Israelites should we understand, if not the good fathers from whom they took their origin in the flesh? And yet, because they did not want to keep their faith and imitate their examples, their root dried up because they could not help them to free them from imminent evil. Or certainly, we should understand the root as the Almighty God, in whom they were founded, who created, protected, and made them grow like all people.
The root has dried up in them because it no longer protects or defends them.
Therefore, it is said: They will not bear fruit, meaning they won't have children or produce good works.
And if they do have children, I will kill the beloved offspring of their womb.
That is, if they happen to have children against my will, it will not benefit them because I will kill the children they love dearly.
As it is mentioned above: And if they raise children, I will make them childless.
My God will reject them because they did not listen to Him, and they will wander among the nations.
They will follow various cultures in different places because they did not want to remain steadfast in worshipping the one true God.
This generally applies to all the Jews, whose leaders strayed from the Lord, leading the people to seek His death.
He cast them out of His house and no longer loves them.
Their root has been struck and dried up because they lost the understanding of the heart, and they do not comprehend the Holy Scripture with a sound mind.
Therefore, they do not bear the fruit of good deeds.
And if they do, meaning if they are seen meditating on the Holy Scripture and the law, and if they bring forth some knowledge and teaching as beloved children, they will be cut down by the opposing Lord.
For God rejected them, the God of all prophets, because they did not listen to Him, and they were wandering among the nations, having no altar, no temple, no city of their own.
Thus, David also says in the psalm: Do not kill them lest my people forget; scatter them.
Chapter Ten
Israel was a lush vine, symbolizing the saints, when it thrived in good works.
Hence it's said: The vineyard of the Lord of hosts is the house of Israel.
The fruit was abundant.
With good shoots and fruitful branches, it produced many clusters, and the grapes' fertility matched the branches' size.
According to the multitude of people, it abounded in good works, through the patriarchs, prophets, and other good men.
Another translation says: Israel is a watery vine, which we understand negatively, because a watery vine, if not pruned by the vinedresser, grows entirely in leaves.
The moisture that should turn into wine is wasted on the vain ambition of leaves and foliage, making such a vine harmful to farmers.
Israel was like this, growing in numbers but not yielding fruit for the farmer, God, because when it should have produced grapes, it produced wild grapes.
It is written: The vineyard of Sodom is their vineyard.
For they focused not on good works, but on an abundance of leaves.
According to the multitude of its fruits, it multiplied altars for itself.
As there were many people, they had many altars: what was once abundant in good works later turned this abundance into an offense, so the more people there were, the more altars they built.
Hence it's added, According to the fertility of their land, they flourished with idols.
Since their land was the most fertile, they made more idols there than all other nations, images of dead men or animals, to the extent that the abundance of the land was surpassed by the excess of idols.
Similarly, heretics, when planted in the Church, were called the vineyard of the Lord and brought forth abundant fruits.
But later, departing from the good altar, that is, from the unity of faith, they built more altars of their error.
According to the fertility of their land, that is, the sharpness of their mind and the force of their burning genius, they flourished with idols.
From ancient times, kings and nations worshipped golden calves, leading to their downfall and captivity.
The last king of the ten tribes was Hoshea, who, although he did evil in the sight of the Lord, was not as wicked as the kings before him.
He allowed the people, if they wished, to go to the temple of the Lord in Jerusalem.
Despite this permission, they chose not to go.
In the ninth year of Hoshea's reign, Shalmaneser, king of Assyria, captured the people of Israel, taking them to Assyria and settling them by the river Gozan in the cities of the Medes.
One might wonder why the people were not captured under the worst kings, but under Hoshea, who showed some inclination toward better ways.
The answer is that under the previous kings, the people justified their actions by saying, "We obey the commands of the kings and cannot resist tyranny. Therefore, we worship the calves we are compelled to adore and cannot go to the temple of the Lord." However, during Hoshea's reign, the king commanded that the calves should not be worshipped with such fervor, and allowed those who wished to go to Jerusalem and sacrifice at the temple. The people opposed this command, embodying the phrase, "Their heart is divided," meaning the will of the king and the people were not aligned. With no excuse left, they faced destruction and eternal captivity.
As soon as the people disagreed with the king, destruction and captivity followed, as the prophet Hosea predicted and mourned. He declared, "Now," referring to the present time, "He will break their idols and lay waste their altars." This refers to God Almighty, who, through the Assyrians, carried out His will, devastating and destroying their altars.
The opinions of heretics are divided among themselves since they have different views about Christ.
Therefore, they will perish; that is, they will be condemned to eternal punishment when God Almighty destroys the idols and altars.
These represent the various doctrines they have created from their own hearts.
For now, they will say.
"Now" refers to the ninth year when Hosea was captured by Shalmaneser, who is also known as Sennacherib, and put in prison.
After the Lord breaks the idols of Israel, they will say: "We have no king." This means they have no one to defend them because their king and all their leaders have been captured and killed.
Finally, explaining why the king and leaders have been taken from them, they add: "For we did not fear the Lord." It's as if they are saying: "We lost the human king who was supposed to defend us because we did not fear the true King, God."
And what will a king do for us? The meaning is: Even if we had a human king, what could he do for us? How could he defend us when God Almighty is angry with us, whose will no one can resist? It's like they are saying: "It would do us no good to have a king."
Speak the words of the useless vision. The prophet's voice is the speech of God mocking those who promised themselves peace and prosperity to come. Speak, he says, the words of the useless vision; that is, promise yourselves good things, and dream different dreams, which all declare that good things will happen to you, as you have done so far.
All the things that seemed good to you have turned into the opposite. Hence it is added: "And you will make a covenant, not with God, but rather with falsehood, saying: 'Peace will be with us.' And judgment will sprout like bitterness." That is, the very falsehood in which you trust will not produce the most peaceful fruits for you to be satisfied with, but rather the force of bitterness, namely, captivity and slaughter.
Over the furrows of the field, which represent your earthly hearts, from which you have produced bad fruits, according to that: "Evil thoughts come from the heart."
The disciples of heretics, when their lies are exposed, will say: "We have no king, that is, no teachers who previously commanded us and deceived us, making us not fear God." "And what will the king do for us now?" It's as if they're saying: "What benefit did we gain from following those who can't help us in our time of need?" They will say these things to find excuses, making it seem like they erred because of their teachers, not by themselves. Hence, the words and visions of heretics are useless.
They will make a covenant, not with God, but with the judgment of bitterness. About this judgment, the Lord says in the Gospel that some will receive greater judgment because, when the day of judgment comes, those who have sown lies in the hearts of people will reap damnation, while those who have sown in tears will reap in joy. It follows:
The inhabitants of Samaria worshipped the cows of Bethaven. Bethaven is actually Bethel, meaning the house of the idol, where Jeroboam placed the golden calf he made, mockingly calling the calves cows. It's as if to say: Israel has fallen into such misery that it worships not only calves but even cows.
The inhabitants of Samaria are understood to be all the inhabitants of the ten tribes, whose capital was the same city. Because his people mourned over him. To show that the calf in Bethel should be understood as the cows of Bethaven, it did not say: "The people mourned over them," but "over him." His people are those who worshiped the golden calf and mourned when (as we find later) it was taken as a gift to the avenging king.
The keepers of the temple, that is, his priests, rejoiced over him because his deceit was not discovered; they made bronze calves covered with gold and placed them in the same place, according to the Hebrews.
Therefore, when the people mourned in their time of need because the calves were taken by King Sennacherib of Israel, the priests rejoiced that their deceit could not be argued and discovered.
In his glory.
The glory of the people is called the calf itself, in which they gloried because they had golden calves.
But this glory will depart from them.
He explains why they rejoiced in their glory, which then departed from them.
It is added: For he himself was taken to Assyria as a tribute to the avenging king.
Sennacherib is the avenger because he avenged the insult to God against those who worshipped idols instead of God.
Note that he expresses the misery and condemnation of the people, because they even gave what they held most dear as a tribute.
The shame of Ephraim will seize him, and Israel will be ashamed of his own will.
In the book of Kings, we read that Menahem, king of Israel, sent Pul, king of Assyria, one thousand talents of silver, so that his hand would be with him, to provide help.
Some believe that even the calves, thought to be golden, were sent.
When the fraud of the gilded calves was discovered, it was reported to the king of Israel, and what they hoped would appease him, instead offended him, inciting those to whom they had sent the gifts.
They thought this was done not by the theft of the priests but by the deceit and counsel of the king.
Knowing the calves were bronze, he was very angry, thinking they wanted to mock him.
For this reason, he came and conquered them.
Therefore, it is said: The shame of Ephraim will seize him, and Israel will be ashamed, that is, will blush, for his own will, in seeking help from a foreigner.
Samaria made its king pass away like foam on the surface of the water.
Just as foam and bubbles quickly dissolve, so the kingdom of the ten tribes will quickly end.
It was said that Hoshea wanted and commanded them to return to the temple of the Lord, but because the inhabitants did not listen to him, they made him perish, like foam on the water during rain or drought.
And the high places of the idol will be destroyed.
As often stated in the books of Kings: Nevertheless, the people sacrificed on the high places.
But what these high places of the idol are is revealed when it is added: "The sin of Israel," you understand, were these same high places. They sinned greatly when they worshipped idols on mountains, in groves, and other pleasant places, abandoning the temple of God.
Thorns and thistles will grow over their altars. It is a sign of utter desolation when thorns and thistles have overtaken their tents due to long abandonment. And they will say to the mountains: "Fall on us," and to the hills: "Cover us." This can refer not only to the captivity of the ten tribes but also to the times of the Romans and the entire Jewish people.
This is also manifested by the Lord, who said in the Gospel: "Daughters of Jerusalem, do not weep for me, but weep for yourselves." On judgment day, they will say to the saints, who, because of the heights of their virtues, are called mountains: "Fall on us," meaning, cover our wrongdoings with your prayers. Literally, it signifies the excessive terror of sinners who, with the impending judgment day, would wish to escape God's presence and perish temporarily rather than eternally.
From the days of Gibeah, Israel has sinned. From the day when Benjamin in the city of Gibeah disgracefully and cruelly killed the Levite's wife through illicit intercourse, Israel has sinned against me. Or even from the day when, rejecting God so that He would not rule over them, they chose Saul as king. They persisted in those sins.
The battle in Gibeah will not overtake them against the children of iniquity, meaning they did not perish in the battle of Gibeah because they rose up against the children of iniquity, that is, against Benjamin, and destroyed it. But because they avenged a man and did not avenge the injury to God, allowing the idol to remain in the house of Micah.
They should have first exercised God's vengeance by overturning Micah and his house and reducing the idol to nothing, and then avenged the injury to the Levite.
They avenged a man, not God, and did this more for the sake of the man than for God.
Furthermore, they did not want to vindicate the sacrilege against their God.
Because of this, a battle will catch up with them.
According to my desire, I will punish them; that is, I will hand them over to their enemies according to my will.
People will gather against them, namely the multitudes of the Assyrians, when they are punished for their two sins.
We can understand these two sins as follows: they avenged a man, neglecting the injury to God.
Or, they committed two sins because they first sinned with the idols of Micah and secondly with the calves of Jeroboam.
They certainly committed two sins, referring to the two calves of Samaria: one in Dan, the other in Bethel.
Or, they committed two sins by abandoning God and worshiping idols.
Regarding these two sins, Jeremiah says: "They have forsaken me, the fountain of living water, and dug for themselves cisterns that cannot hold water." These two sins violate two commandments of the Decalogue, which say: "I am the Lord your God" and "You shall have no other gods before me."
Ephraim is like a trained heifer that loves to thresh. This refers to a custom in the promised land where heifers, along with other animals, were used to thresh grains. When they are exhausted by hard labor, they usually leave the threshing floor, but they love the threshing floor because they eat the grains there. Hence the saying: "Do not muzzle an ox while it is treading out the grain." They voluntarily return to the threshing floor.
So, Ephraim is like a cow or heifer because it has learned to thresh and has also begun to love what it was trained to do by annual custom, even though threshing is laborious. Similarly, the Israelite people, although frequently afflicted and suffering many adversities because of idolatry, nevertheless, desiring to follow their own wills and the gluttony of their belly, voluntarily returned to idols. Morally, we can refer this to those who, from a secular habit, convert to monastic religion and then voluntarily return to earthly labor.
Even when wearied by long periods of heat and cold, they willingly endure all these hardships, just as they had experienced before.
I overlooked the beauty of his neck, which symbolizes his pride and his refusal to accept my yoke due to his stubbornness.
In the context of God, "passing over" always signifies plagues and adversities. Remember, the destroyer also passed through Egypt.
The meaning is: Because Ephraim refuses to accept the yoke of the law, I passed over the beauty of his neck and subdued his pride by placing the yoke on him. Thus, it is said: I will go up against Ephraim, meaning I will confront him, so that the rebellious and stubborn cow learns to work, which it refuses to do.
Alternatively, we can see the yoke as the condemnations of all nations, which the Lord promises to remove so that they might return to Him. Judah will plow, and Jacob will break up the furrows. By Judah, we mean the two tribes who, upon seeing Israel taken captive by enemies, began to cultivate their hearts and discipline themselves in the worship of God.
By Jacob, we mean those remaining from the ten tribes who were called to the true worship of religion. They removed all hardness of heart and began producing the fruits of good works. It is written in Isaiah that Hezekiah sent them books and brought them to Jerusalem to worship God in His temple, repenting from idol worship.
In an anagogical sense, this can mean that Ephraim, who was taught the law of God to meditate on it day and night, began to reject the yoke of the law and contend against church leaders, leading listeners astray.
Hence, the Lord, seeing the raised neck and lofty ambitions, will either press it with the yoke or trample it under His feet, confronting it so that he may know he has God. Judah, representing the faithful, will continue to plow the land, persevering in their work.
Jacob, whose name means "supplanter," will break the furrows of vices. This means he will crush the hard clods of history and letters into pieces and spiritually divide them so they can yield spiritual fruits.
Sow for yourselves righteousness in truth. This continues the metaphor started by the farmers. Ephraim is said to love threshing like a trained heifer, and he himself goes over its neck to plow Judah and break the furrows of Jacob. Now it is commanded to sow in righteousness, meaning in the observance of legal precepts, and reap in the mouth of mercy, which means in the grace of the Gospel.
Hence it is: Repent, and so on. And: Do good to those who hate you. And: Whoever strikes you on the cheek, offer him the other also. Break up your fallow ground, which means make your hearts new, saying with the Psalmist: Create in me a clean heart, O God.
Literally, fallow ground is a field that has been plowed for the first time. However, the time to seek the Lord is implied to be when He comes to teach you righteousness. This is in the time of the Lord’s incarnation and passion when all things will be openly revealed through which the faithful will be justified. Hence it is: Seek the Lord while He may be found.
He provides reasons why you should sow, why you should reap, and why you should renew joyful fallow grounds. He says the time to seek the Lord is when Christ the Savior comes, who will teach you the righteousness you now hope for in the law. For Christ is the end of the law for righteousness to everyone who does good.
Similarly, it is commanded to those who are separated from the Church and falsely assume the name of Christians to repent and accept both Testaments: in the Old Testament to sow righteousness, in the New Testament to reap mercy, so that they renew for themselves fallow grounds of good works and seek God, who can teach them true righteousness.
You have plowed wickedness, you have reaped iniquity. The meaning is: While I urged you to sow in righteousness and reap in the mouth of mercy so that you would make me joyful with your joyful fallow grounds, you instead plowed wickedness, meaning you devised wicked plans to depart from me.
The greatest injustice is to turn away from God and worship idols instead.
This is why you have faced captivity and death because of your sins; you have brought this upon yourselves.
You deserved to harvest bad crops from bad seeds.
You received the reward of deceit, having eaten its fruit.
You dreamed of good things, but adversity rightly came upon you.
Similarly, heretics sow impiety when they teach unjust things.
Therefore, they will reap injustice and eat the fruit of deceit when they are condemned for their iniquity and deceit.
For whatever a man sows, he will also reap.
Because you trusted in your own ways, in idols, and in the strength of your kings and princes instead of God, a tumult will arise among your people.
The sound of the Assyrian army will come upon you, and at their shouting, all your fortifications will be destroyed.
Those things you considered fortified and safe will be exposed to the enemies.
Hence, it is written in Isaiah that Sennacherib ascended and captured all the fortified cities of Judah.
Just as Salmana was devastated in his house, avenging Baal on the day of the battle, with the mother being struck down over her children, so Bethel has done to us because of the wickedness of your iniquities.
The history of the Judges reminds us that an angel appeared to Gideon and said: Go in this strength of yours, and you will deliver Israel from the hand of Midian.
But first, he was urged to destroy the grove and the altars of Baal.
For this reason, he was called Jerubbaal, because his father said: Let Baal avenge himself on him who destroyed his altar.
So, he went with three hundred men, carrying torches inside jars, and he killed the army of the Midianites, who had come up with all they had, taking possession of and devouring all that belonged to Israel.
And the meaning is: Just as Salmana, the prince of the Midianites, was destroyed—killed by the family of Gideon, who avenged Baal by destroying his altar on the day of battle, with the mother dashed to pieces over her children—so Bethel, where you placed the golden calf, will do to you because of the wickedness of your sins.
You will be handed over to enemies and perish.
And what he says: The mother dashed to pieces over her children, refers to the same story, which says that after Gideon captured Zebah and Salmana, the princes of the Midianites, he asked them: What kind of men did you kill at Tabor?
Salmana replied: They were like you, each one like the son of a king.
Gideon then said: If you had spared them, I would not kill you.
And finally, he said: Just as your sword made women childless, so your mother will be childless.
And he struck him and killed him.
So the mother was dashed to pieces over her children, because she was shattered by excessive grief from the death of her sons, or perhaps she was killed together with them.
It could have happened that she was there and was dashed to pieces together with them, because, as previously mentioned, they went up to the land of Israel with all they had.
Chapter Eleven
Just as the morning passes, the king of Israel passes away.
He conveys the same idea using different figures, as he said before: Samaria caused its king to vanish like foam on the surface of the water.
He illustrates it with another metaphor: just as the morning swiftly passes when the sun rises, so did the king of Israel, Hoshea, get captured by enemies.
Morning is the dawn, from the end of the night until the rising of the sun.
Because Israel was a child, and I loved him.
He explains the blessings God had given them.
He says, Israel was a child worshiping idols in Egypt, thinking like a child, and I loved him through the patriarchs and other saints.
And I called my son out of Egypt, which you understand through Moses.
For he said to Pharaoh: This is what the Lord says: Let my firstborn go so he may worship me in the desert.
And elsewhere, My firstborn Israel.
And again: I raised and exalted sons.
If we want to refer this to Christ, who is the Son of the Father, he called him out of Egypt when (as Matthew says) at the command of the angel, he was brought back to the land of Israel by Joseph along with the virgin mother.
Spiritually, however, Egypt, which is called darkness, signifies this world.
Therefore, God called his Son out of Egypt when, through the glory of the ascension, he was lifted up from this world and placed in heaven.
They called them.
Because Israel, although mentioned singularly, is understood plurally, like the people and the crowd.
It rightly moves from singular to plural: They called them, that is, all the Jews, Moses, Aaron, and the others, to follow them out of the land of Egypt, and to fulfill God's command and will.
So they left their presence, meaning they quickly departed from their teaching, turning their backs and hardening their minds when they said to Aaron: Make us gods who will go before us.
For we do not know what happened to this Moses.
They then proceeded to shout: These are your gods, Israel.
They sacrificed to Baal and offered sacrifices to idols.
It wasn't enough for them to scorn those who called upon them; they also had to sacrifice to Baal during Ahab's time.
Ahab received the idol from the Sidonians because he married Jezebel, the daughter of the Sidonian king.
Baal, also known as Beelphegor, was worshipped by them.
They sacrificed to idols not only in Dan and Bethel but also on mountains, in groves, and other pleasant places, adoring various images.
It's easy to understand the heretics, whose king—be it the devil or any heresiarch—will pass away like the dawn.
God loved them when they were children, when they believed and were called by the Christian name.
He called them out of the tribulation and darkness of Egypt.
He called the apostles and the teachers of the Church.
But after being called, they turned away and worshiped Beelphegor, serving their vices and lusts, and sacrificed to the idols they had made for themselves.
Each heretic had their own gods, and whatever they imagined, they worshiped as if it were a carved or molten image.
I was like a foster father to Ephraim.
This shows how God loved Israel by calling them out of Egypt.
As stated in Deuteronomy: "The Lord your God carried you, as a man carries his little child," etc. I carried them in my arms, meaning with my strength. It's as if to say: I who was a father became a foster father, carrying my little one in my arms, protecting him in the wilderness, from the heat of the day and the darkness of the night. By day, I was a cloud; by night, a pillar of fire.
They didn't realize that I cared for them. Even when they sinned and made the head of a calf, I gave them a chance for repentance. They didn't know that I wanted to heal them, to cleanse them from their idols. I will draw them with cords of Adam, meaning with the affection of love with which I loved Adam. Just as I made him holy, I wanted to sanctify and purify them. Hence, it is also added: with the bonds of love, meaning with the highest affection of love. Another translation states: I will draw them with the cords of men.
And the meaning is: with the love with which I loved and bound to myself Abraham, Isaac, and the other saints, I will also join these to myself.
And I will be to them like one who lifts the yoke from their jaws.
That is, I will remove from them the yoke of the law, so they do not perish under its heavy burden.
As it says: Whoever makes an idol and whoever sacrifices to Moloch shall surely be put to death.
For since I desire mercy rather than vengeance, I will lift the yoke of the law so they do not succumb to its weight, or I will remove the yoke of captivity and domination of all the surrounding nations from them.
And I inclined to him to feed him, that is, I gave him manna in the desert to eat.
For when I inclined to him, it is to be understood that I made food incline to him.
We can also refer these words to the coming of the Lord's incarnation.
In this way, I loved them and was such a gentle shepherd that I myself carried the sick sheep on my shoulders.
But they did not understand that I would heal them by my suffering, and because I am a lover of humanity, I would draw them to believe with the bonds of love.
As it says: No one comes to the Father except through me.
And they thought my yoke to be the heaviest, and I inclined to them, leaving the kingdoms of heaven to dwell with them, taking on the form of a man; and I gave them the food of my body.
He shall not return to the land of Egypt.
The people of Israel, under Menahem, the king of the ten tribes, wanted to flee to Egypt from the face of Sennacherib, seeking help.
Against this the Lord speaks here, saying: He shall not return to the land of Egypt so that they may have Pharaoh as their king; but Assyria will be his king, that is, Sennacherib, and afterward he will be his king because he will be taken captive and led into captivity, and will rule over him by right of conquest.
The reason why they suffer such things is revealed when it is added: because they did not want to turn back through repentance, trusting in man rather than in God.
The sword began in his cities, and it will consume his chosen ones.
See how great the weight of their miseries is, so that not fields, or possessions, or farms are devastated, but the enemy enters into the midst of the cities.
The sword has begun (he says), in his cities — you understand, to kill — and it will consume his chosen ones, namely the leaders and the strongest of his army, and it will eat their heads.
This signifies the leaders themselves, who rule the others by right of leadership.
And my people will hang on my return, that is, when the time of captivity comes, and the sword has consumed all their warriors, and they cannot find any protection.
Then my miserable people will repent too late.
With the enemies devastating everything, they will hang on my return, sigh, and seek to convert, but it will not help, because once they were my people, but now they are not.
A yoke will be placed on them at the same time, which will not be removed.
Even to this day, they remain slaves in the mountains of the Persians and Medes.
This can also refer to the times of the Romans when the Jews were condemned to a final and perpetual captivity.
How can I give you up, Ephraim?
How can I protect you, Israel?
that is, you are not worthy of protection.
Here, the Lord speaks to Israel like a loving father.
How (he says) can I give you up?
that is, how can I give you up to captivity without my own pain?
How can I protect you, and what can I do for you?
By what method can I correct you, and how can I expose you without my greatest heartache?
Here he speaks like a loving father.
How can I give you up?
Like Admah, you understand, I will give you up; I will make you like Zeboiim, that is, although not without pain, I will hand you over and reduce you to dust and a vast wilderness.
I will destroy you to ashes and embers, just as I destroyed Admah and Zeboiim, and the remaining cities of the Sodomites.
It should be noted that where the Lord speaks against the two tribes through the prophets, Admah and Zeboiim are not mentioned, but Sodom and Gomorrah are.
Hence in Isaiah, we read, "Hear the word of the Lord, you rulers of Sodom; receive the law of our God, you people of Gomorrah." And the Lord says in the Gospel to the disciples, "It will be more tolerable for Sodom and Gomorrah than for the city that does not receive you." And to Jerusalem, Ezekiel says: "Sodom is justified by you."
When he speaks of the ten tribes, not Sodom and Gomorrah, but other cities subject to them are mentioned.
This is because, although the ten tribes were greater in number, two of them stood out in dignity due to the temple and priesthood.
Therefore, these two tribes sinned more grievously than the ten, which lacked these distinctions and were far removed from Jerusalem.
Similarly, Sodom and Gomorrah were greater in wickedness because their evil surpassed that of the other cities.
The subject cities also followed in their wickedness, and therefore it will be more severe for them.
Likewise, it will be more severe for the two tribes, which worshipped idols in the temple of the Lord, than for the ten.
For a servant who knows his master's will and does not do it will be beaten with many blows.
Hence, ecclesiastical men, if they are guilty of the same crimes as heretics, will not suffer the torments of Admah and Zeboiim, which are lesser, but of Sodom and Gomorrah, which are of greater crimes.
My heart is turned within me, my repentance is disturbed, that is, my will is shown with paternal affection.
As soon as I spoke against you and pronounced a cruel sentence, mercy touched me, overcoming strictness, just as a father's kindness mitigates the austerity of a judge.
As soon as I spoke that I would make Ephraim and Israel like Admah and Zeboiim, my bowels were moved, and I regretted that I had planned to destroy my people forever.
Thus, the Lord speaks here: Just as if any of you were to say: I will kill you, and immediately, driven by repentance, add: My fault, because I spoke against you in such a way.
I will not carry out my fierce anger; that is, I will not change my mercy to destroy Ephraim if he repents.
Therefore, it follows, I will not turn from my mercy to cruelty to destroy Ephraim, that is, the people of the ten tribes: for I do not strike to destroy forever, but to correct.
Indeed, my severity is a cause for repentance and kindness.
For I am God and not a man, holy among you.
Man strikes to destroy and gets angry to take revenge; his judgment is punishment.
But God corrects to improve and chastises to correct.
When we read, "In your midst is the Holy One," it means: "If you want to repent, I will be in your midst, dwell with you, save you, and not enter the city." This specifically refers to punishment, like judges, because I am not one of those who live in the cities and follow human laws.
The Jews understand this as: "If you repent, I will not enter the city of the Gentiles, but will stay with you."
Otherwise, we often read about two cities: one started by Cain and the other by Abel. One is for the wicked, the other for the righteous. Therefore, He does not enter the city built by a murderer, constructed from wickedness, but remains forever in Abel's city.
We can relate these same ideas to heretics and the people deceived by them. It is said to the heretics that unless they repent, they will be cast out like Admah and Zeboiim, with no hope of salvation.
Again, the most merciful Father says He will change His judgment and regret saying such things, to provoke them to repentance and conversion. He says, "I will not act in my fury, I will not destroy Ephraim, as much as it is in me, as much as I desire, if he corrects his error with truth, if he loves me more than the leaders of heresy. For I am God, not a man: I will extend my hand to those who have fallen, call those who err to salvation; and because I am holy, therefore I will not enter the assemblies and cities of the heretics: I gladly receive those who come out of their cities; I will not enter their cities."
They will walk after the Lord. The voice of the prophet, as if saying: Because the mercy of the Lord is so great, that He even promises forgiveness to sinners and prosperity: they will walk after the Lord, that is, they will imitate Him when they turn to Him.
He will roar like a lion, because He will roar, and the sons of the sea will tremble.
The lion, when hungry, usually lets out a great roar.
At the sound of this, all the beasts and birds are terrified and stand still.
Therefore, the Lord’s roar was a threat of captivity when He said, "I will make you like Admah and like Zeboiim." About this, Amos also says, The Lord will roar from Zion, and His voice from Jerusalem. Or, His roar is understood as the terror instilled in the nations so that the captivity of the Jews would end.
His roar was also heard when, present in the flesh, He said, Every tree that does not bear good fruit will be cut down and thrown into the fire. At this voice, when the true lion roared, even the false lion, who is, according to the apostle Peter, our adversary, immediately fell silent. He also roared when He said, Then the King will say to those on His left: Depart from Me, you cursed, into the eternal fire. This roar will be perfect and clear when He comes for judgment, and not only humans but also angels will be terrified. Hence it is added, And the sons of the sea will be afraid, meaning the sons of this world, as the sea often signifies the present world.
They will fly away like a bird from Egypt and like a dove from the land of Assyria, and I will place them in their homes. The Jews still await these things to come. But since we know they have already happened, let us say that from Egypt and Assyria, that is, from the east and west, north and south, the faithful flock to the faith of Christ, imitating the simplicity and innocence of the dove. Later, they can fly away from the power of demons to be placed in their homes, that is, in the heavenly mansions, namely in the bosom of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.
If we want to refer this specifically to heretics, upon hearing the voice of the lion threatening the judgment of their damnation, those who were born of the bitter waters of the heretics will take wings and fly like a bird, or like a dove from the land of Assyria, that is, from demons, or from Egypt, that is, from the sorrow of tribulation. Freed from this, they may dwell in their homes, that is, in the faith of the Church.
Surrounded by the dealings of Ephraim and the deceit of the house of Israel, Ephraim denied me.
This means Jeroboam worshipped idols and did not honor me as a deity.
Israel also tried to deceive by making idols, as if they held some divine power.
But Judah stood as a witness with God and the faithful saints.
The Hebrews say: when the children of Israel were leaving Egypt, they found themselves trapped.
On one side was a very high mountain, on the other the Red Sea, and on the third side, enemies.
While other tribes doubted and wanted to return to Egypt, Judah—that is, the two tribes who dwelled in the temple, the law, and the prophets—stood as a witness to the Lord's words.
Judah kept His commandments, humbled himself, and followed in the Lord's footsteps.
This was with the faithful saints, or with those who crossed over at the end, imitating the works of the fathers.
Heretics surround the Lord with lies and denial.
Whatever they speak is a lie.
They surround Him with deceit, much like the impiety of the house of Israel, crafting their falsehoods with artful speech and speaking against God.
But Judah, representing the faithful, does not become proud or swollen with heretical pride.
Instead, he humbles himself with God and stays faithful with the choir of saints.
He is either a faithful and strong witness, building his house upon a rock that no storm can shake.
Chapter Twelve
Ephraim feeds on the wind and chases the east wind.
The story tells that Menahem, king of Israel, after making peace with Assyria, sought help from Egypt.
This is what is meant by "Ephraim feeds on the wind," that is, he is deceived by false hope, placing his trust in man. And "chases the east wind," which means he goes to Egypt, located in the southern part of the world.
All day long he multiplies lies and destruction. At all times, he multiplies lies, such as idols, and brings calamity and affliction upon himself, preparing the downfall of his cities. Menahem, as mentioned before, made a pact with the Assyrians, sending them gifts to secure their alliance. He brought oil to Egypt. After making a pact with the Assyrians and realizing that he could not join forces with Sennacherib, but instead saw him coming against him, he sent gifts to the Pharaoh. Among these gifts, he also sent oil, which is the most distinguished and precious product in Samaria but is not found in Egypt.
Let's try to apply these same things to heretics. Ephraim feeds on the wind, meaning he pleases demons with his deeds. And chases the east wind, which is contrary to flowers and destroys all that sprouts. Therefore, the Septuagint translates it as "scorching wind." All day long, he multiplies lies, that is, false doctrine, and destruction, meaning ruin, for himself and his followers. He is not content with his own error but gathers many disciples of vanity. They also make a pact with the Assyrians, meaning they have peace with demons, whom they obey. And they bring oil to Egypt because, being in the darkness of error, they falsely claim to have the knowledge of the Holy Spirit, which they do not deserve, as they are outside the Church.
Therefore, the judgment of the Lord is with Judah. The captivity and miseries occurred because the ten tribes were taken captive for their sins. They did not repent but instead acted even worse, so much so, as the prophet Ezekiel reveals, that they surpassed their sisters in wickedness.
And visitation, meaning the magnitude of torment, whippings, and punishments, will come upon Jacob—that is, upon the two tribes that descended from his seed.
According to his ways and inventions, he will be repaid.
What he did, he will receive in kind.
For he did not fall by chance, nor due to human frailty, but because he sought out and discovered ways to sin.
In the womb, he supplanted his brother.
This refers to the old story, showing God's mercy towards Jacob and his stubbornness against God.
Even when he was still in Rebecca's womb, he supplanted his brother Esau—not by his own strength, but by God's arrangement, who considered him a future faithful patriarch.
And he was directed by his own strength with the angel.
When he was sent by his father to Mesopotamia, or when the angel wrestled with Jacob all night by the stream, receiving a blessing from him, he heard: If you have been strong against God, how much more will you prevail against men?
And he prevailed against the angel, obtaining by prayers that he would bless him.
He was strengthened by the blessing of the one he had overcome when it was said to him: You will not be called Jacob, but Israel will be your name.
He wept and begged him.
When he said, I will not let you go unless you bless me.
This is indeed the struggle he had with the angel, holding him by prayers to bless him—not by the strength of his work.
He found him in Bethel.
The order is reversed.
First, complying with the advice of his father and mother, while fleeing from his brother, he saw the angel in Bethel.
When he placed a stone under his head and slept, he saw God's angels ascending and descending, and he heard the Lord standing at the top of the ladder, saying to him: Jacob, Jacob, do not be afraid.
I am the Lord God of your fathers; descend, and I will be with you, and I will bring you back.
For this reason, he called the name of that place Bethel, meaning the house of God.
And there he spoke with us in our father, saying: The land on which you sleep, I will give to you and your seed.
The Lord God of hosts, the Lord is His memorial.
He gave this memorial of His name to him so that he might be called Israel, which means "man seeing God." This name is still retained by his descendants. He always remembers God's name, given to him by the angel, and by which he is called. And you will turn to the Lord your God.
The Prophet addresses Judah: Since things are so, you, O Judah, will turn to the Lord your God by repenting and believing faithfully in Him. This was fulfilled when three thousand believed in one day, five thousand on another day, and then many thousands.
Keep mercy and judgment, and always hope in the Lord your God. First, have mercy on yourself, as it is written: "Have mercy on your soul, pleasing God." Then strive to show mercy to others, as it is written: "Make friends for yourselves from the mammon of unrighteousness." Also, keep the judgment of discernment between good and evil, God and the devil. When you have done both, always hope in the Lord your God, advancing to greater things through good works.
We can apply these same things said about Judah to any church member who is corrected by the Lord for not remembering His former blessings but daily adding sins to sins. He also explains what these blessings are: When the Church bore you at birth, you supplanted Esau, implied to be the Jewish or Gentile people, by receiving his birthright. In your strength, you were directed against the angel, either by overcoming evil spirits or being strengthened by the angel's blessings. You prevailed against the angel, making him your helper through prayers, and you would prevail even against men. But after your victory, you wept and begged the angel of the Lord. Remembering your past sins, you found Him in Bethel, which means the house of God, which is the Church, or according to the Septuagint, in the house of the Oven, that is, of sorrow, tears, and repentance.
To understand who this Judas is, it says, "he spoke with us in the Church," meaning to us Christians. From that time, we are called by the name of Christ and are guided by His teachings.
Therefore, O churchman, known as Judas and a confessor, turn to your God daily through repentance. If you happen to sin, turn to your God, just as the Prophet cried out: “I am weary with my groaning.”
Keep God's commandments; show mercy to others, so that you may also receive mercy. Always hope in the Lord your God, and continually draw near to Him, progressing in virtue at all times, and always getting closer to your God.
Canaan, in his hand, holds a deceitful scale. He had warned Judah earlier to turn to the Lord his God, and by keeping mercy and justice, to always hope in the Lord his God. Now the speech turns to Ephraim, referring to the ten tribes called Canaan, not by nature, but by imitation, just as Daniel spoke to the elder, who was indeed of the seed of Judah: “Seed of Canaan, and not of Judah, appearance has deceived you.”
In Ezekiel, we read it said to Jerusalem: “Your father was an Amorite, and your mother a Hittite.”
A deceitful scale among Ephraim, contrary to: “Let your measure be fair, and your sextary just.” He loved oppression, meaning he not only had an unjust and deceitful scale but also loved oppressing the poor, stripping them of their possessions through power.
And Ephraim said: “Nevertheless, I have become rich.”
Now it is more clearly stated who this Canaan is, referring to the ten tribes who said: “I have become rich,” meaning they abound in all temporal goods. The sense is: I do not care where I have gathered these from, as long as I have what I possess.
Many suffer from this mindset because the riches they have, they do not distribute to the poor, nor do they give thanks to God for them, about which it is written: “Wealth gathered will be burned with fire.”
As Scripture says, "The redemption of a man's soul is his riches," and the Lord in the Gospel: "Make friends for yourselves by means of unrighteous wealth."
I have found an idol for myself. He calls those very riches, with which he was refreshed, an idol. Just as the belly is a god to gluttons, so gold is an idol to the greedy. This is true because they worshiped idols instead of God.
All my labors will not find for me the wickedness that I have sinned. This means that whatever I have sinned, because I had riches, it will not be charged to me by those who need my help. Since they need my goods, they will not accuse me for my sins but rather praise me, as it is written: "And he who acts unjustly will be blessed."
Riches and the ambition of servants are free from accusation. The rich have many friends. All these things apply to heretics, in whose hand is a deceitful scale: they fraudulently deceive whomever they can. They also love slander, while they persecute the innocent and oppress through power.
After deceiving others, they usually say: "We have become rich by the multitude of disciples who follow us." We have found an idol for ourselves, therefore heresies are composed chiefly to devour the houses of widows, who are always learning and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth.
And beautifully he says: "I have found an idol for myself." For all the fabrications of heretics are idols, and they differ in nothing from the impiety of the Gentiles; therefore, they usually say: "Whatever I do, whatever I act, it cannot be charged to me. For I have my riches, the arguments of philosophers, and the multitude of people, who, when they see it, will not think me a sinner."
And I am the Lord your God from the land of Egypt.
The meaning is: While you rejoice in sin and boast about your wealth, saying, "I have become rich, I have found an idol for myself," even though you have sinned grievously, I am the Lord your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt. When you served Pharaoh and built cities from mud and straw, I still grant you a place for repentance. Hence, it is added: "I will still make you sit in tents, as in the days of the festival."
He calls the day of the festival the Feast of Tabernacles, which is celebrated in the seventh month after Passover, in memory of their departure from Egypt. The children of Israel lived in tents. Just as, at that time, I freed you from Egypt and made you live in tents for forty years, so now I will do, bringing you out of captivity so that in the days of the Feast of Tabernacles, you may sit in tents like your ancestors, if only you do what I have commanded.
I have spoken through the prophets, like Moses, Isaiah, Jeremiah, and others, and I have multiplied visions. Hence, Isaiah said: "I saw the Lord sitting on a high throne." And Daniel said: "I was looking in the night visions, and behold, the Son of Man was coming." In the hands of the prophets, I have made myself known.
Just as Adam held the type of the one who, while sleeping, formed Eve from his side, so Christ formed the Church on the cross. Just as Jonah; hence the Lord said: "Just as Jonah was in the belly of the whale." Just as David defeated Goliath. Just as Isaac for whom the ram was sacrificed. To those who followed heretics, it is said to return to God, who wants the repentance of the sinner more than death.
It must be believed that He is the one who brought them out of Egypt, that is, out of the darkness and error of the Gentiles. And lest they remember the sin and return more slowly: "I will still," He says, "make you sit in tents, as in the days of the festival," so that what baptism did, repentance may also do, and they may live in the tents of the Savior, that is, in the churches, of which it is said: "Planted in the house of the Lord, they will flourish in the courts of our God."
And so that the heresiarchs and leaders of their error do not think they are speaking by the Spirit of God: "I am," He says, "the one who spoke to the prophets, not to your teachers. I multiplied visions and was compared in the hand of the prophets who are established in the Church."
If Gilead is an idol, then they wander in vain, sacrificing in Gilgal. Gilead is both a mountain and a city located next to that mountain across the Jordan in the tribe of Gad. Previously, we read: "A city of idol makers, overthrown by blood." But Gilgal is in the tribe of Judah near Bethel, about which it was previously said: "All their wickedness is in Gilgal."
Therefore, since both the ten tribes, signified by Gilead, and the two tribes, represented by Gilgal, worshiped idols in those places, it is rightly said: "If Gilead is an idol," meaning if the ten tribes worship idols, which lack the temple, priests, and the religion of God. Yet you, Judah, have forsaken God in vain and worship idols in Gilgal, even though you have the temple, priesthood, and everything that pertains to the true rite.
Furthermore, he calls oxen calves. For their altars will remain like heaps on the furrows of the field, it is implied, and will be left without care, with them being led into captivity, like mounds of stones and sands gathered together.
Jacob fled to the region of Syria. The prophet seems to touch on the history of Genesis, speaking about the flight of Jacob, who fled to Laban, his uncle, in the region of Syria. It was also said earlier: "In the womb, he supplanted his brother, and in his strength, he contended with an angel."
And Israel served; that is, Jacob himself, for a wife, that is, for Rachel, serving seven years, tending the sheep of his uncle. And he served for a wife, namely another seven years for another woman. But in the prophet, the Lord brought him out of Egypt, and in the prophet, he was preserved. Because he began to weave the history of Jacob and Israel, he connects the sons to the father, saying: "In the prophet, the Lord brought him out of Egypt," meaning Moses, by whose guidance they departed from the land of Egypt.
Certainly, if we want to understand this more deeply, the Lord, meaning God the Father, led His people out of the darkness of unbelief through the prophet, that is, Christ.
Furthermore, the same people were saved by the prophet when, due to the sin of the golden calf, with the Lord's anger raging, he prostrated himself before Him and said: "Either forgive them, or erase me from your book," until he received the response: "I have forgiven according to your word."
One would not be wrong to say that Jacob, the supplanter, and Israel, who saw God, prefigured the Lord, and that Rachel, initially barren and beautiful, whom Jacob loved greatly, signifies the Church. Leah, however, with weak eyes but fertile, represents the sacraments of the Synagogue. He led the faithful people out of the darkness of this age and brought them to the very bright waters of the Jordan, that is, baptism.
Ephraim provoked me to anger with his bitterness. The meaning is: When I freed Ephraim, that is, all ten tribes, from Egyptian servitude and granted him many blessings, he provoked me, who am naturally most sweet, with his bitterness. That is, he made me bitter and forced me to deliver retribution. And his blood will come upon him, meaning he will be the cause of his own death. Because of his sin, he will be taken captive and killed by enemies, as David said to the one who reported that he had killed Saul: "Your blood is on your own head." And the Lord your God will return his disgrace upon him, meaning the retribution for the blasphemy where he said: "These are your gods who brought you out of the land of Egypt," will be brought upon him by the Lord.
Heretics always provoke the most merciful Lord to anger, and they, whom He prefers to repent rather than die, compel Him to punish the hardness of their hearts. And their blood, with which they have shed both their own and many others' blood, will come upon them. The reproaches with which they blasphemed the Lord will be returned to them by the Lord their God, not because He is their Lord, but because He once was their Lord.
Chapter Thirteen
When Ephraim spoke, fear gripped Israel.
Ephraim, also known as Jeroboam, son of Nebat, from the tribe of Ephraim, commanded the worship of idols, causing excessive fear to grip Israel.
This fear led them to abandon God and sacrifice to idols.
As it is said: They sinned with Baal, specifically the idol of the Sidonians, who is also known as Bel, and they died, losing Him through infidelity, who says: I am the life.
For it is written: The soul that sins shall die.
And now they have added to their sinning.
Combining the sin of idolatry with another sin, they made a molten image, a calf, from their silver, so that they too would have their calves, resembling the idols.
Because the king had golden gods, the subjected people made silver gods for themselves within their means to resemble those.
It is all the work of craftsmen, that is, the work of man, not of God.
To these, they say: Sacrifice humans, worshipping calves.
For example, Manasseh and many others sacrificed their sons and daughters to demons, as it is written.
It is as if it plainly said: You, idol worshippers, because you lack sacrifices, sacrifice your sons and daughters, who also worship idols with you, that is, the calves.
But if, as some say, demons speak to the people: Sacrifice humans, for they bear calves.
Their greed is shown, those who are fed by the blood of victims and the smoke of burnt offerings, that, lacking sacrifices, they desire humans to be sacrificed, rejoicing not only in their death but also in their blood.
Therefore, they will be like the morning cloud, and like the morning dew that passes away: like the dust swept by a whirlwind from the threshing floor, and like smoke from a chimney.
Because, he says, they sacrificed humans to calves, or rather to one calf, and worshipped calves, therefore they will be like a cloud, all of which are seen for a time and quickly cease to be.
For clouds and dew are driven away and dried up by the coming sun; dust swept from the threshing floor, and smoke from a chimney dissolve into thin air.
Hence: As the smoke fades, they will fade.
And the meaning is: just as these four things disappear quickly, so they will be swiftly taken to the Assyrians.
That is why it was said earlier: Just as the morning passes, so has the king of Israel passed.
Heretics are compared to morning clouds, dew, and dust, about whom we read in the Catholic Epistle: These are clouds without water.
For they appear to be prophets and apostolic clouds through whom the truth of God has come, but they do not have water, that is, the grace of the Holy Spirit, about whom the Lord says: Whoever believes in me, rivers of living water will flow from within them.
I am the Lord your God from the land of Egypt.
It is implied, from when I brought you out of Egypt: and you will not know any god besides me, and there is no savior other than me.
Now it mentions what He did for them, leading them out of Egypt by the hand of Moses, when He said to them: Be careful, lest you eat and are satisfied; lest you forget your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, etc.
For there is no other God besides me, and there is no one else who can save.
I have known you, that is, I have loved you.
For just as not knowing God is to reject Him, so knowing Him is to love and choose Him.
That is why it was said to Moses: I know you by name, that is, I have chosen you especially above others.
In the desert, in the land of solitude, it is implied, I knew you, where there were neither crops nor vineyards, nor even fruit-bearing trees, but a scarcity of all things.
Near their pastures they were filled, that is, although there was a lack of all good things there, I gave them manna from heaven, I brought forth springs of water from the hardest rock.
And when they were satisfied, they lifted up their hearts, that is, they became proud, filled with manna, meat, and spiritual drink.
And they forgot me, whose benefits they should have remembered, according to what is written: The beloved grew fat and kicked.
For in such a vast wilderness, where not only crops but even trees and vines, not even grass grows, and no waters temper the heat of the sun, for forty years Israel could not have reached the land of Jordan unless the Lord had provided everything.
The Lord brought heretics out of the darkness of unbelief, where they served Pharaoh and his leaders, and commanded them in the Church to know no other god but Him, the Creator of all people who knows how to save those He made.
He recognized and nourished them in solitude, so they could say, "The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want."
He gave them bread from heaven, which they had never eaten in Egypt, and water from the rock that followed them; but the rock, according to the Apostle, was Christ.
Filled with the wealth of the Scriptures and satisfied, they lifted their hearts against the Creator and fashioned another god for themselves, forgetting the God who had commanded them to keep the words of the law before their eyes and in their hands, so they would never forget Him.
And I will be to them like a lioness, and like a leopard on the way to Assyria. A lioness is fiercer than all beasts when her cubs are taken, and a leopard is no less savage.
The meaning is: When they are handed over to enemies and taken into captivity, I, who always showed them the greatest mercy, will unleash the ferocity of all beasts against them. Hence it is immediately added: I will meet them like a bear robbed of her cubs, and I will tear open their chests.
Those who have written about the nature of beasts say that among all wild animals, none is fiercer than a bear that has lost her cubs or is in need of food; and the meaning is: Because they have thought blasphemies in their hearts against me and have spoken against me, I will turn into all beasts for them, that is, into all ferocity, and I will destroy and crush them through the Assyrians, and I will tear open the insides of their hearts, that is, I will take away the vital parts of their hearts.
And I will devour them there like a lion, a wild beast will tear them apart. As if to say: They are so wicked that even in captivity, they will justly feel my wrath.
Therefore, I will consume them there, like a lion devours its prey, a wild beast will tear them apart, namely Sennacherib, or the devil dwelling in the desert of this world.
Notice how the one who speaks to believers in the Gospel says:
Come to me, all you who labor and are burdened,
etc.
, up to: My yoke is easy.
Now, through the prophet, to the unbelievers and those unwilling to repent, he becomes a lioness, a leopard, a bear, and a lion.
Your destruction, Israel, is solely due to yourself; your help is only in me.
That is, you are the cause of your own destruction.
Another translation says: Perish, Israel, for you have descended into such depths of wickedness that you can only be saved by the mercy of God alone.
For in me is your only help, if you repent, not from yourself.
Where is your king?
Let him save you now in all your cities.
The divine word is spoken ironically to those who chose a king for themselves against God's will and boasted they'd be victorious relying on his strength.
Where is, he says, your king?
Jeroboam, clearly, or even Saul, about whom you said to Samuel:
Appoint a king for us to judge us.
And when he objected, you replied: By no means, but there will be a king for us, and he will go out before us and fight for us.
So, the one you promised yourself would fight your battles, let him save you now in all your cities, with the Assyrians now imminent, let him also rescue you from the imminent danger.
But you have no human king, because you have rejected me, you have no God.
And your judges, that is, your companions and other leaders, about whom you said: Give me a king and leaders, it is understood: Where are they?
I will give you a king in my anger, and I will take him away in my wrath.
I will give you a king, namely Saul, in my anger, to the extent that I showed rain during the harvest days against the nature of the promised land, and I will take away Zedekiah in my wrath, whom I will lead to Babylon with his eyes torn out.
Alternatively: I will give you a king, that is Jeroboam, in my anger, and I will take away Hoshea, the last king of the ten tribes, in my wrath.
Ephraim's wrongdoing is stored up, like something kept in a bag, and it doesn't disappear for the one who has it tied up.
Similarly, all the sins Ephraim committed against God are stored up and will stay until the time of captivity.
It's said: His sin is hidden.
Not from God, who sees everything clearly, but from Ephraim himself, who will recognize it at the time of captivity.
Birth pains will come upon him.
When the day of revenge and captivity comes, his sin will be revealed and known to everyone.
He will be struck with sudden pains, like a woman in labor.
He is a foolish son.
Ephraim was God's son, as it is written: Israel is my firstborn son, but he is foolish because he did not recognize the true Father, God, and instead worshiped idols.
Now he will not withstand the destruction of the children, meaning that when the days of labor and captivity come, he will not be able to endure the evil and destruction of the children, who will be killed in the presence of their fathers, or they will not stand because they will be taken captive.
I will deliver them from the hand of death, I will redeem them from death.
God Almighty speaks to those He chooses to free by His grace.
From the hand of death, He says, I will deliver them, meaning from the work of sin, which leads to death: because the hand carries out the work, it is rightly understood that the hand of sin means the work itself, which kills the soul.
Thus it is written: Death and life are in the power of the tongue; or certainly, the hand of sin is understood as the power of the devil.
I will redeem them from death, meaning I will free all believing Jews and Gentiles from hell.
It is said: I will be your death, O death, I will be your bite, O hell.
His death was because He destroyed death with His own death, leaving none of His people there.
He bit when He freed some, namely His chosen ones, but left some of the rejected ones there.
Just as when we bite, we consume part and leave part; or death and hell are understood as the devil, whom Christ bit so that he would lose his power, but not completely cease to exist.
Between death and the underworld, there's a distinction: Death occurs when the soul separates from the body, while the underworld is where souls are confined, either for refreshment or punishment based on their merits.
Comfort is hidden from my eyes.
The most merciful Father has decreed that we all must die, having judged us through Adam.
He says: Comfort is hidden from my eyes, because I see all of humanity perishing.
Or the prophet, seeing that everyone dies and descends into the underworld, knowing he will join them, says: Comfort is hidden from my eyes.
The meaning is: I am unable to be comforted; nothing I imagine can ease my pain as I consider the inevitable necessity of death.
Because he divides among brothers.
The underworld divides among brothers, receiving one taken from this life and leaving another behind.
In this place, understand that all charity is lacking, as even a mother is separated from her daughter, a father from his son, and a brother from his brother.
Therefore, anything that divides the unity of brotherhood and sows discord is rightly called the underworld.
Some interpret the two brothers divided by death, according to the history of that time, to be Judah and Israel, so what was once symbolized in part is now fully experienced.
The Lord will bring a scorching wind from the desert.
We should understand this scorching wind as Habakkuk says: God will come from the south, and the Holy One from Mount Paran.
For God the Father brought forth a scorching wind, His Son, who takes away the sins of humanity.
In Him, the devil, seeking rest, could not find it; or from the womb of the virgin, who conceived without the moisture of male seed; hence: How will this be, since I do not know a man?
Beautifully, in both Isaiah and here, a flower or an ascending wind is mentioned, because He ascended from the humility of the flesh to the heights, and led us with Him to the Father, saying in the Gospel: When I am lifted up, I will draw all to myself.
And it will dry up its veins, that is, the sins of its death.
We understand the veins of death as sins, which, through Christ, have been dried up, and death itself will also be dried up.
He will desolate its source, that is, the devil, about whom He said: "Now the prince of this world will be cast out."
He will seize the treasure of every desirable vessel. This can be understood in two ways.
First, the desirable vessels are the saints, about whom Paul says: "We have this treasure in earthen vessels."
Second, those whom the devil desired to hold as vessels forever, Christ Himself, upon coming, has seized from his power, and has led as the most precious vessels with Him into paradise.
Chapter Fourteen
Let Samaria perish, for it has provoked its God to bitterness.
We have often said that the ten tribes are called Samaria, after the metropolis Samaria, which is now called Augusta, or Sebastia, named after Augustus.
The Book of Kings explains why the city is called Samaria.
The prophet speaks here not as a wish, but as a proclamation: Let Samaria perish, because it has provoked its God to bitterness, when He was most sweet in devotion, forcing Him to bring vengeance upon them for their sins, with the sword, implying the Assyrians.
Let it perish: its children will be dashed to the ground, and its pregnant women will be ripped open by the sword, leading to death.
This is believed to have happened during the time of captivity and distress, when they lost their homeland, and those who escaped the sword were brought into perpetual servitude.
Return, Israel, to the Lord your God, because you have fallen into sin.
Historically, these words were directed at the ten tribes called Ephraim, who abandoned the Lord their God and worshipped the calves Jeroboam had made.
Spiritually, they can be applied to any sinner who, departing from their Creator, submits to an idol, which is every lie, hoping to be saved by Assur, that is, the devil, the author of lies.
So, let us briefly discuss both the historical understanding and the spiritual application to each individual.
Earlier, the prophet predicted the calamities and hardships threatening the ten tribes he was addressing; now he speaks to them, encourages them, and advises them to beseech the Lord by abandoning idols and turning to God.
Return, Israel, to the Lord your God, from iniquity to righteousness through the confession of sins and the performance of good deeds, because you have fallen into sin by making idols and worshipping demons.
You have fallen through idolatry; rise through worship and the fulfillment of the religion of your God.
Each of us should act in this way.
We are weakened and have fallen into sin.
Let us rise to repentance, producing fruits worthy of repentance, as John the Baptist foretold.
Let's turn away from our wicked deeds.
Take words with you, O people of the ten tribes, and turn to the Lord, and say to Him.
The prophet does two things: he urges them to repent and teaches them how to pray to the Lord.
He says, take words with you, meaning: Offer prayers, confess your sins, and turn to the Lord with both words and deeds.
Someone truly turns from their wickedness to perform good works when they proclaim with their mouth what they believe and hold in their heart.
Remove all iniquity, and accept what is good, and we will offer the calves of our lips.
Each one of the faithful should say such things: Remove all iniquity, that is, cleanse us from all sins, as it says: Cleanse me from my hidden faults.
And accept what is good, which means confession, sincere prayers, and thanksgiving.
The prophet adds: We will offer the calves of our lips, speaking wonderfully.
Who ever had calves on their lips, unless a part was taken to eat?
He does not command us to offer calves and sacrifices, the victims that the Jews used to offer in the temple.
By "calves of our lips," we should understand praises and thanksgiving, as the Psalmist says: Offer to God a sacrifice of praise and fulfill your vows to the Most High; and also: A broken spirit is a sacrifice to God.
Thus, each of us offers calves, that is, praises, to Almighty God when we confess to believe in God the Father unbegotten, the Son begotten, believing Him to be true God and man, and the Holy Spirit proceeding from the Father and the Son—having the Trinity in the distinction of persons, unity in the power of the Godhead.
By doing this, we fulfill what the Apostle says: With the heart one believes and is justified, and with the mouth one confesses and is saved.
Assyria will not save us; we will not ride upon horses.
Blessed Jerome mentions that, according to Jewish tradition, during the reign of Menahem, king of Israel, Menahem and the people of the ten tribes sent one thousand talents of silver to Pul, the king of Assyria.
This was done to secure his support and ensure peace, providing assistance against the Egyptians.
Among these gifts, they also included two calves made of bronze and gilded to resemble the golden ones created by Jeroboam.
The priests had secretly kept the gold for themselves and replaced it with bronze.
The Prophet previously referred to these calves, saying: "And it (the calf) was brought to Assyria as a gift to the avenging king," using the singular to refer to the plural.
Therefore, speaking on behalf of the people, the Prophet said: "Assyria will not save us." He implied that while they hoped for the Assyrians' protection, true safety did not come from them. He emphasized that they should no longer trust in man but in God, as it is written: "Cursed is the man who trusts in man and whose heart turns away from the Lord."
He further added: "We will no longer ride on horses," indicating their previous reliance on the swift horses of the Egyptians. The meaning is: "We will no longer place our hope in the Egyptians; instead, you will be our refuge."
Allegorically, if we interpret this, Assyria can be seen as representing the devil and the horse as his pride. So, if anyone has placed their trust in Assyria, appeasing him with gifts—namely evil deeds he delights in—to ride the horse, that is, to rise with arrogance, it will happen as the Lord says in the Gospel: "Everyone who exalts themselves will be humbled." We will no longer declare, "The work of our hands are our gods," referring to the golden calves we made. We will no longer consider them gods or seek help from them, for you will have mercy on those who are in you, your people. This refers to the people of Israel, of whom you said: "Israel is my firstborn son."
He said, "You will have mercy on the people who are in you through faith and repentance, who once sinned and turned away from you. But after returning through repentance, you will heal their brokenness and love them freely.
Because they said, turning to God through repentance, 'Remove all iniquity and accept what is good;' recognizing the Father they had left, the Lord responded, 'I will heal their brokenness.' That is, 'I will forgive their sins, which had deeply broken and wounded them. I will love them freely,' meaning, voluntarily.
Because my anger has turned away from them, as they have repented. I will be like dew, and Israel will blossom like a lily. For I, who was angry with them because of their sins, will now have mercy on them because of my compassion. And I will be to them like dew, because my mercy will remove the heat of burning passion and lust from them; and they will blossom like a lily, because they will grow and flourish in the beauty of virtues and the fragrance of good deeds.
Hence Paul says, 'We are the fragrance of Christ to God.' For the chosen ones blossom; indeed, they flourish like a lily, imitating their Lord God, who says in the Song of Songs, 'I am the flower of the field and the lily of the valleys.'
And their roots will spread out like those of Lebanon, that is, their good will shall be brought to the fruition of good deeds. Lebanon is a mountain whose trees extend their tops to the skies and their roots deep into the earth, so that no storm can shake them, but they stand firm. Its branches will spread, that is, they will progress from strength to strength, and their glory will be like an olive tree.
Because it says, 'Its root shall spread out like Lebanon;' lest we think it speaks of a holy person from unfruitful trees, it compares the converted man to a fruitful olive tree. Oil signifies mercy, which works through charity and all good deeds. Therefore, it says, 'Its glory will be like an olive tree,' that is, it will be enriched by works of mercy, so that, by lighting a lamp in the darkness, it may shine and provide an example of good deeds to others.
And its fragrance will be like that of Lebanon. In Greek and Hebrew, Lebanon refers both to a mountain and to incense."
Here, however, is placed instead of frankincense:
Just as we are delighted by the smell of frankincense, so too are we delighted by the reputation of a righteous person.
Those who sit in his shade will be restored.
Specifically, those who had distanced themselves from God the Father by sinning will return to Him.
And after they have turned back, they will receive the reward for their conversion: to sit under the shade, that is, to live under His protection, and they will be able to say with the Church:
"I sat under the shade of Him whom I had desired, and His fruit was sweet to my taste."
They will live on wheat and flourish like the vine. When they sit under His shade, those who had died will live on wheat, that is, they will abound in good works, or by the Body and Blood of the Lord. Certainly, they will live on wheat because through Christ, who is the true grain, they will rise from death to life.
Hence it is written: "Unless a grain of wheat falls into the ground and dies, it remains alone."
He is also the vine, who intoxicates those who believe in Him with spiritual wine. As the Psalmist says: "You visited the earth and intoxicated it."
And the Lord Himself to the disciples: "Eat, friends, drink and be intoxicated, beloved."
Therefore, like the vine, the chosen will flourish, because they will imitate their Lord with good works, as the Lord Himself says: "Whoever serves me must follow me."
His memorial is like the wine of Lebanon. We can call the wine of Lebanon mixed, and prepared with various spices, so that it has the sweetest fragrance. And the meaning is: just as spiced wine has a pleasant fragrance to people, so too is the memory of a righteous person who imitates the works of the Lord sweet and pleasant.
We can also understand the wine of Lebanon as that which was offered to the Lord in the temple, of which Zechariah says: "Open your doors, O Lebanon," etc.
For just as Almighty God delighted in the wine that was offered to Him, so too does He rejoice and is glad from the fragrance of the faithful, returning the fame of their faith and good works.
Ephraim, what more do I have to do with idols? It is understood that you oppose them. And the meaning is: Since you are about to receive so many blessings because you have begun to do penance and be mine, what more do you want to worship idols? I will hear and guide him who does penance and calls out to me.
I will guide him, meaning I will lead him on the right path; the path is Christ, through whom access to the Father is possible.
I, like a flourishing tree, have given him life, so he may have the vitality of faith and good deeds, and always seek heavenly things with a clear vision.
From me, his fruit was found, meaning all his actions and the observance of both the Old and New Testament came from my gift, without which you can do nothing.
But it must be known, as we have often said, that the salvation of Israel and the return to God and redemption from captivity should not be understood literally, as the Jews dream, but should be fulfilled spiritually and truly.
Who is wise and will understand these things?
Who is intelligent and will know them?
In these words, the Prophet shows the obscurity of the text and the difficulty of its explanation.
Who can understand what Jezreel means, what his sister who did not receive mercy means, what his third brother who is not my people means, what the harlot joined to Hosea means, and other things mentioned in the chapter, or what the scorching wind means at the end?
Considering the obscurity of these matters, he says: Who is wise and will understand these things?
And if the one who wrote it confesses it is difficult or impossible, what can we do, we who, with weak eyes darkened by sins, cannot gaze upon the bright light of the sun?
As it is written: Oh, the depth of the riches of the wisdom and knowledge of God!
How unsearchable are his judgments and his paths beyond tracing out.
Because the ways of the Lord are right, and the righteous will walk in them.
The ways of the Lord are understood as the commandments of the Old and New Testament, in which the righteous walk, fulfilling them in action, saying to God with the Psalmist: Make my steps firm in your paths.
But transgressors will stumble in them.
Transgressors are understood as Jews, heretics, and false Christians who transgress the commandments of the Lord.
They will stumble in them, because those who sinned under the law will be judged by the law.
And the servant who knows his master's will and does not do it will be beaten with many blows.