Prologue
I want to honor all your religious wishes as best as I can, dear brother and son Boso.
I feel especially obligated when I see these wishes arise for your sake.
I am confident that when you read the book Why God Became Man, which you strongly encouraged me to write and in which I included you as my discussion partner, you might uncover another reason beyond the one I provided there.
This reason explains how God took on human form from the sinful mass of humanity without sin.
Your keen mind is eager to explore what that reason might be.
Therefore, I would feel unfair to you if I kept my thoughts on this matter from you.
So, I will briefly share my feelings on this, in a way that respects all faithful opinions on the subject, and I won't stubbornly cling to my own view if it can be reasonably shown to contradict the truth.
However, I believe the reasoning I provided in that same work is completely valid and sufficient if considered carefully.
After all, there can be multiple reasons for the same thing, each sufficient on its own.
Chapter One
Understanding the concepts of original and personal justice or injustice.
To grasp how God assumed a human nature from sinful humanity without sin, we first need to explore original sin, as it raises this question.
If we can understand why Christ wasn't subject to this sin and how His conception was free from all sin, it becomes clear.
It's certain that the term "original" is derived from "origin."
So, if original sin exists only in humans, it seems to be named either from the original human nature, which is fundamental from its beginning because it originates from the essence of human nature itself, or from the origin, meaning from the start of each person, since it comes from their beginning.
However, it doesn't seem to stem from the beginning of human nature, as its origin was just when the first humans were created just and without sin.
Thus, it appears to be called original from the very start of each individual.
Nonetheless, if someone claims that sin is called original because it passes down to individuals from those who provide the origin of nature, I won't disagree, as long as it's acknowledged that original sin is inherited with the beginning of each person.
In each human, there exists both nature, which makes one human like everyone else, and a person, which distinguishes one from others, as when they are called by specific names, like Adam or Abel.
The sin of each is in both nature and person: Adam's sin was in the human aspect, which is nature, and in the individual known as Adam, which is personal.
However, there is a sin that each person inherits with nature at their very start, and there is a sin that isn't inherited with nature, but is committed by the person after they become distinct from others.
The sin inherited at the beginning is called original; it can also be termed natural, not because it is part of the essence of nature, but because it is acquired with it due to its corruption.
Once someone becomes a person, any sin they commit is considered personal because it stems from their own fault.
In a similar vein, we can talk about original and personal righteousness.
Adam and Eve, right from the start of their existence as humans, were immediately just and righteous without delay.
However, righteousness is termed personal when someone who was unjust receives righteousness, which they didn't possess initially.
Chapter Two
How Human Nature Was Corrupted.
If Adam and Eve had maintained their original righteousness, their descendants would have been righteous like them.
However, because they sinned, even though they initially had the strength to maintain righteousness easily, their nature became weakened and corrupted.
The body, after sin, became like that of animals, susceptible to corruption and carnal desires.
The soul became infected with these desires due to the body's corruption and the loss of what it once had.
Since all of human nature was within them, and nothing was outside of them, the whole was weakened and corrupted.
Thus, it retained the obligation of full righteousness without injustice, which it received; and the need to make amends for abandoning it, along with the corruption incurred through sin.
If it had not sinned, it would have continued as God made it; but after sin, it propagates as it became through sinning.
Because it cannot make amends for the sin or recover the lost righteousness on its own, and the corruptible body burdens the soul Wisdom Nine: Fifteen; especially when it is weak, like in infancy and the mother's womb, unable to understand righteousness:
it seems necessary for it to be born in infants with the obligation to make amends for the first sin, which it could always have avoided, and to have original righteousness, which it could always have maintained.
This inability does not excuse it in infants, because it does not pay what it owes, having abandoned righteousness in the first parents, in whom the whole was: and it is always indebted to have the power to maintain righteousness.
This appears to be original sin in infants.
We should also consider the sins of nearby relatives, which are passed down to the third and fourth generation.
While it might be debatable whether all of this should be considered in terms of original sin, I want to make it clear that I'm not downplaying its significance by questioning it.
So, for now, let's assume it's as serious as it gets.
Chapter Three
That there is no sin except in rational will.
Truly, whether we refer to original sin or something less, I believe it cannot be said to exist in an infant before they have a rational soul.
Just as there was no righteousness in Adam before he became a rational human being.
If Adam and Eve had conceived without prior sin, righteousness would not have been present in the seed, nor could it be before they were formed into a living person.
So, if a human's seed is not capable of righteousness before becoming human, it cannot take on original sin before being human.
Certainly, we should not doubt that original sin is unrighteousness.
If all sin is unrighteousness, and original sin is sin, then it is indeed unrighteousness.
But if someone argues, "Not all sin is unrighteousness," they would have to claim that something could have sin without unrighteousness, which seems unbelievable. If it's said that original sin should not be called sin absolutely, but instead "original sin," much like a painted man isn't truly a man but a painted man, it implies that an infant, who has no sin except original sin, is innocent of sin.
And the Son of the Virgin was not the only human who, in the womb and being born, was without sin. Hence, either an infant who dies without baptism, having no sin except original sin, is not damned, or is damned without sin. But we accept none of these ideas.
Therefore, all sin is unrighteousness, and original sin is absolutely sin, which means it is unrighteousness. If God does not condemn except because of unrighteousness, but condemns someone because of original sin, then original sin is nothing other than unrighteousness.
And if that's the case, and unrighteousness is simply the absence of due righteousness-since it doesn't seem to be unrighteousness unless in a nature that, when it ought to have righteousness, does not have it-then original sin falls under the same definition of unrighteousness.
If justice is the correctness of will maintained for its own sake, then this correctness can only exist in a rational nature.
Therefore, no nature is obligated to justice except the rational one, just as no nature is capable of justice except the rational one.
Since injustice can only exist where justice ought to be, original sin, which is injustice, exists only in rational nature.
However, rational nature is only found in God, angels, and the human soul, through which a human is called rational, and without which a human is not.
Since original sin cannot be in God or in angels, it exists only in the rational human soul.
It must also be understood that justice can only exist in the will if justice is the correctness of will maintained for its own sake.
Therefore, so too can injustice.
The absence of justice is not called injustice unless justice ought to be there.
Thus, nothing is called just or unjust except for justice or injustice itself, unless it is the will, or because of a just or unjust will.
Through this, we say a person or an angel is just or unjust; a soul, or an action, is just or unjust.
Chapter Four
Nothing is inherently just or unjust, except justice or injustice itself, and nothing is punished except the will.
Nothing, whether it's a substance, an action, or anything else on its own, is just unless it is justice; or unjust or sinful unless it is injustice; not even the will itself, where justice or injustice resides.
The power of the soul to will something is distinct: this power, which can be seen as the instrument of willing-like vision is the instrument of seeing-is what we call the will.
Justice is something else, which when possessed, makes the will just; and when lacking, makes it unjust.
The uses and affections of this instrument are also called wills, but it's too lengthy to include here.
Desires, which the Apostle refers to as the flesh, which lusts against the spirit, as mentioned in Romans Chapter Eight; and the law of sin in the members, opposing the law of the mind, as noted in Galatians Chapter Five, are not just or unjust by themselves.
They do not make a person just or unjust merely by being felt; but unjust, only when the will consents when it should not.
For the Apostle says there is no condemnation for those who are in Christ Jesus, who do not walk according to the flesh, as stated in Romans Chapter Eight, meaning those who do not consent to the will of the flesh.
If feeling without consent made a person unjust, condemnation would follow.
Therefore, it is not the feeling itself, but consenting to it, that is a sin.
If these desires were unjust by themselves, they would make a person unjust whenever they were consented to.
But when animals consent to them, they are not called unjust.
Similarly, if they were sins, they would be removed in baptism, since all sin is washed away; which is clearly not the case.
Therefore, there is no injustice in their essence; but in the rational will following them in a disordered way.
When the will resists them, delighting in the law of God according to the inner self, then the will is just.
Justice, as commanded by law, is known as the law of God because it originates from God.
It's also called the law of the mind because we understand it through our minds.
Similarly, the old law is referred to as the law of God due to its divine origin and the law of Moses because it was delivered through Moses.
I mentioned that no action is inherently unjust; it becomes unjust due to an unjust will.
This is evident in situations where actions might be performed justly, such as killing in certain contexts, like Phinehas did in Numbers twenty-five, or the union of both sexes in marriage or among animals.
In cases where actions are never justifiable, like perjury and some other acts that shouldn't be mentioned, the concept is not as straightforward.
However, if an action results in something that only exists while it's being done and ceases once completed, like writing something inappropriate, the sin would exist only while the action is being performed.
If the act of writing is complete but the written words remain, the sin would cease to exist once the action is finished.
Yet, if the result of the action remains, the sin would also persist.
Yet, we observe that sins often aren't erased when the action stops, and they can be erased even if the result remains.
Therefore, neither the action that passes nor the outcome that remains is the sin itself.
Finally, if the body parts and senses involved in unjust voluntary actions are accused, they might argue: God has subjected us to the will, so we cannot help but follow its commands.
The will guides us like instruments to perform actions.
We can't resist it on our own, nor can we prevent the actions it dictates.
To the master God has given us, we must comply.
When we obey it, we obey God who established this law.
So, how can the body parts, senses, or actions sin if they serve the purpose God has assigned to them?
Whatever they do should be entirely attributed to the will.
Given this, you might wonder why the body's parts and senses seem to be punished for the actions of the will.
In reality, it's only the will that is punished.
Nothing is considered a punishment unless it's against someone's will, and nothing experiences punishment unless it has a will.
Body parts and senses on their own don't have any will.
Just as the will acts through the body parts and senses, it is also through them that the will experiences pleasure or pain.
If you're unsure about this, remember that it's the soul, where the will resides, that actually feels and acts through the senses and body parts; thus, it experiences pleasure or pain through them.
It's common to refer to the actions an unjust will commits as sins, because the sin resides in the will that commits them.
We also use specific terms to indicate that these actions are done unjustly, like fornication and lying.
However, we perceive something different when we consider the action itself or its expression, compared to when we consider whether it's done justly or unjustly.
Chapter Five
The concept of evil, which we equate with sin or injustice, is essentially nothing.
Since all essence comes from God, and nothing from God is unjust, no essence can be inherently unjust.
Injustice, like blindness, is simply the absence of something.
Blindness is the lack of sight where it should be, just as it's not something extra in the eye nor in a tree where sight isn't expected.
Injustice doesn't infect or corrupt the soul like poison to a body, nor does it directly cause something, even when a malicious person acts wrongly.
Think of a wild beast that runs free when its chains are broken, or a ship that drifts aimlessly if the captain abandons the helm, sailing into danger.
We say this happens because the chains or the helm are absent-not that their absence is something or does anything, but because their presence would prevent chaos.
Similarly, when an evil person spirals into danger through their actions, we blame injustice.
It's not because injustice is a tangible thing or does anything, but because the will, which guides all voluntary actions, is led by desires without justice, pulling itself and everything else into various evils, recklessly and without direction.
Justice, if present, would stop this from happening.
From this, we can see that injustice has no essence.
The inclinations and actions of an unjust will, though something in themselves, are what we refer to as injustice.
In the same way, we understand that evil is nothing.
Just as injustice lacks due justice, evil is simply the absence of good.
No essence, even if labeled evil, is actually nothing, nor is being evil a thing of essence.
For any essence, being evil is merely lacking the good it should have, and this lack is not the presence of anything.
The reason something is bad isn't because of any inherent quality.
I've briefly explained this regarding evil, which is essentially nothing and is undoubtedly injustice.
Discomfort is considered evil, which is why discomforts are referred to as evils.
Sometimes it's an absence, like deafness and blindness; other times it appears to be something, like pain and sadness.
Justice is the rightness of the will, valued for its own sake, while injustice is simply the absence of justice, lacking any essence.
I believe I've adequately demonstrated that all essence comes from God, and nothing from God is anything but good, as discussed in the treatise On the Fall of the Devil, especially chapters one, fifteen, and sixteen.
I've explained justice more thoroughly in my work On Truth, chapter thirteen.
Chapter Six
When God punishes for sin, it's not without reason.
Some people, when they hear that sin is nothing, often ask, "If sin is nothing, why does God punish someone for it, since no one should be punished for nothing?"
Although this question seems simple, because they don't fully understand what they're asking, a brief response is necessary.
Even though the absence of justice is nothing, whether it should be present or not, God rightly punishes sinners not for nothing, but for something. As I mentioned in the previous book, He requires the honor due to Him, which they refused to give willingly, from those who are unwilling. To maintain order in His kingdom, He separates them from the just in a suitable arrangement.
However, He doesn't punish creatures where justice shouldn't exist for the absence of it-that is, for nothing-because there's nothing He expects from them, nor does the order of the universe demand it.
Therefore, when God punishes for sin, which is the absence of due justice, He doesn't entirely punish for nothing. It's true that unless there's something for which He should punish, He doesn't punish for nothing at all.
Now, sin and injustice are nothing, and they exist only in the rational will; nothing else can rightly be called unjust except the will.
From what has been said, I believe this is clear.
Chapter Seven
How human seed is said to be unclean and conceived in sin, even though there is no sin in it.
It seems that a baby either has a rational soul from the moment of conception, without which it cannot have a rational will, or there is no original sin present at that point.
However, it's hard to accept that a rational soul is present right from conception.
This would imply that each time human seed is conceived and perishes before forming a human, a human soul would be condemned as it hasn't been reconciled through Christ, which seems too absurd.
Thus, we need to discard this part of the argument.
But if a baby doesn't have sin immediately from conception, how do we understand what Job says to God:
"Who can make clean what is conceived from an unclean seed? Is it not you who alone are?"
(Job 14:4).
And how do we interpret David's words:
"I was conceived in iniquity, and in sin did my mother conceive me" (Psalm 51:7).
So, I will explore, if I can, why infants are said to be conceived in iniquity and sin with unclean seed, even though there is no sin in them immediately from conception.
Often, divine Scripture declares something as true, even if it hasn't happened yet, because it is destined to occur.
For example, God tells Adam about the forbidden tree:
"On the day you eat of it, you will surely die" (Genesis 2:17); not because he died physically that day, but because he received the inevitability of dying eventually.
Similarly, Paul says, because of the inevitability of dying someday:
"If Christ is in you, the body is dead because of sin, but the spirit lives because of righteousness" (Romans 8:10).
For their bodies, to whom he spoke, were not dead; but they were destined to die because of sin:
because through one man sin entered the world, and through sin, death (Romans 5:12).
Just as we all sinned in Adam when he sinned-not because we sinned ourselves, as we weren't yet in existence, but because we were destined to come from him.
At that moment, the necessity for us to sin when we came into being was established, because through the disobedience of one man, many were made sinners.
See Romans chapter five, verse nineteen.
Similarly, a person can be considered to be conceived in iniquity and sin from unclean seed; not because there's impurity or sin in the seed itself, but because from that seed and conception, a person begins to exist and acquires the necessity to have the impurity of sin when they have a rational soul, which is essentially sin and iniquity.
Even if a child is born from corrupt desire, the fault isn't in the seed any more than it is in spittle or blood if someone spits with ill will or emits some of their blood.
The blame lies not with the spittle or blood, but with the ill will.
Thus, it's clear how sin isn't present in infants immediately from conception; and the truths I mentioned from divine Scripture hold true.
Indeed, they don't have sin because they lack the will without which there is no sin; yet it's said to be present because they carry the necessity to sin when they become human beings from the seed.
If these things are true, as I believe, then what is passed from parent to offspring, since they have no will, means there's no sin in them.
Chapter Eight
That there is no sin or necessity of future sin in the seed taken from the Virgin.
It is clear that in what the Son of God took on from the Virgin, there could be no stain of sin.
It's been said that seed is inherited from parents with a necessity for future sin when it is joined with a rational soul.
This is because human nature is born with the obligation to atone for the sin of Adam and of the nearest parents, something it cannot achieve.
As long as it doesn't achieve this, it sins because it cannot regain the justice it lost on its own.
The soul, burdened by a corruptible body, cannot even understand this justice, and it cannot be preserved or possessed if it is not understood.
If the seed taken from the Virgin can be shown to be free from these necessities, it will be evident that it carried no necessity for sin.
The necessity by which human nature alone cannot regain justice on its own, and the one by which the corruptible body burdens the soul, preventing it from preserving justice received in maturity without grace, or even understanding it in infants, can be seen as foreign to that seed through the personal unity of the one assuming and the nature assumed.
If the necessity is first removed, by which it seems bound to atone for the sins of the first and nearest parents, it becomes clear.
It will not be doubtful that no obligation follows from the nearest parents if it can be understood to be free from the obligation of the first parents.
Therefore, with God's help, I will first try to investigate how this can be known, so that once this is demonstrated, there will be no need to labor much in other areas.
Chapter Nine
Why is the sin that condemned the human race attributed more to Adam than to Eve, since he sinned after and through her?
First, let's consider why the sin that condemned humanity is more often attributed to Adam rather than Eve, even though she sinned first and Adam's sin followed hers.
The Apostle states: "But death reigned from Adam to Moses, even over those who did not sin in the likeness of Adam's transgression" (Romans 5:14).
Many other passages also seem to place more blame on Adam than Eve.
I believe this happens because the union of the two is entirely encompassed in the name of the principal part; much like how a whole is often represented by a part.
Or perhaps because Adam, with his rib, although it was made into a woman, could still be referred to as Adam, as it is written: "God made them male and female, and blessed them" (Genesis 1:27).
And he called their name Adam on the day they were created.
Or maybe because if Adam hadn't sinned, but only Eve, it wouldn't have been necessary for the entire human race to perish, just Eve.
God could have made another woman from Adam, in whom he had created the seed of all humans, allowing God's purpose with Adam to be fulfilled.
For these reasons, I will refer to both of them by the name of Adam, unless it is necessary to distinguish them.
Chapter Ten
Why do people carry the burden of Adam's sin, even though they weren't aware of it?
Each person is indeed a child of Adam, a human by creation, an Adam by propagation, and an individual with their own uniqueness.
A person doesn't exist because of Adam, but through Adam.
Just as Adam didn't make himself human, he didn't create within himself the nature of propagation; instead, God, who made him human, instilled this nature in him so that humans would be propagated from him.
There's no doubt about the source of each person's obligation: it's not because they're human, nor because they're an individual.
If each person were guilty of this debt simply for being human or an individual, Adam would have been bound by this debt before he sinned, merely for being human and a person, which is absurd.
Thus, one becomes a debtor because they are Adam; but not just any Adam, specifically Adam the sinner.
Indeed, if Adam had never sinned, it would be absurd to think those propagated from him would still be born with this debt.
It's worth reiterating why each person is burdened by Adam's sin or debt because they are propagated from him, even though they were unaware of the sin.
When God created Adam, He endowed him with the nature of propagation, which He placed under Adam's control, to use as he wished, as long as he remained subject to God.
Adam was meant to use it not with animalistic and irrational desire, but with a human and rational will.
Just as animals desire nothing with reason, humans should desire nothing without reason, which they always should, because Adam received this power and could always maintain it.
God also granted him the grace that, just as He created him without any operating nature of propagation or the will of a creature, He made him both rational and just at the same time.
So, if Adam hadn't sinned, those he generated would be both rational and just, possessing a rational soul through the operation of nature and will.
Just as it has been shown that a rational nature was created to be just, as often demonstrated in the earlier work, Book 2, Chapter 1, it's also proven that those born from human nature, without any prior sin, would naturally possess both justice and rationality.
Indeed, the one who created the first human without parents also creates those born through the nature of propagation that he established.
Therefore, every person, if no sin had occurred, would be just like Adam, both just and rational.
However, because Adam chose not to follow God's will, even though the nature of propagation remained, it was not subject to his will as it would have been if he hadn't sinned.
He lost the grace that he could have kept for his descendants.
Everyone born through the nature he received is born bound by his debt.
Therefore, because human nature, which was entirely in Adam with nothing outside of him, dishonored God by sinning without necessity, it could not satisfy God's honor on its own.
Adam lost the grace that he could have always preserved for his descendants, and the sin, along with its penalty, spreads with the nature of propagation, no matter how far it extends.
Chapter Eleven
The birth from the Virgin does not follow the natural laws and merits of typical human propagation; there are three distinct courses of events.
We must carefully consider whether this so-called inheritance of sin and its punishment rightfully extends to a person born from Adam through the Virgin.
It's clear that Adam received the nature of propagation through both a man and a woman.
Human nature doesn't have, and it's known to be impossible, the ability for a man alone or a woman alone to create a human being through their own natural will.
Just as the clay of the earth didn't possess the nature or will to form the first man, though it was by God's action that it could be made:
in the same way, a woman wasn't made from the man's rib, nor was a man made from a woman alone, by natural processes or human will.
But God, by His own will and power, created one man from clay, another from a woman alone, and a woman from a man alone:
though nothing happens except by God's will, whether by direct action or permission, some things His power and will accomplish directly; some by created nature; and some by the will of the creature.
Just as created nature can do nothing on its own except what it has received from God's will, the will of the creature can achieve nothing by itself unless nature assists or permits it.
God's will alone established the nature of things in the beginning, granting each its appropriate will so that natures and wills might fulfill their roles according to the order given to them:
and He continues to do many things, working with those same natures and wills, which they could never accomplish on their own.
It is only through God's will that the sea provides a dry path for people to walk through, that the dead are brought back to life, that water is transformed into wine, and that by the Holy Spirit, people gain insights they couldn't achieve on their own or through any other means.
It's also by grace alone that harmful desires are redirected towards what is beneficial.
Many other events occur that neither creatures nor their will could bring about under normal circumstances.
Nature tends to move light things upward and heavy things downward.
Sometimes the earth, through the efforts of those who cultivate and plant it, and sometimes without any intentional action, produces countless plants and trees that grow and bear fruit.
Many such phenomena are more easily understood through experience than through formal teaching.
Activities like making a path, building, writing, and speaking are attributed to will, as they are accomplished through intentional effort.
Therefore, when we examine everything that happens, it occurs either solely by God's will, by nature according to the power granted by God, or by the will of creatures.
The things that neither nature nor the will of creatures can achieve, but only God can, are always to be marveled at.
There are clearly three categories of occurrences: miraculous, natural, and voluntary.
The miraculous doesn't conform to the others or their laws at all, but rather, it freely governs them.
It doesn't do them any injustice when it appears to oppose them, because they possess nothing except what they've received from it, and it has given them nothing except under its own terms.
Therefore, the birth of a man from only a virgin is neither natural nor voluntary but miraculous, like the creation of a woman from only a man and the creation of a man from clay.
It's clear that this doesn't fall under the laws and merits of propagation, which both will and nature, although separately, operate; for will does one thing there, nature another.
Yet, it's equally true that Adam came from a non-human, Jesus from only a woman, and Eve from only a man, just as any man or woman is truly human from a man and a woman.
Everyone is either Adam or descended from Adam, but Eve came from Adam alone, and all others come from Adam and Eve.
Since Mary, from whom Jesus alone was born, is descended from Adam and Eve, he cannot be from them in the same way.
It was fitting that the one who would redeem the human race was born from the ancestors of all humanity.
Chapter Twelve
Adam's wrongdoings do not affect this man in any way.
Understanding why the Son of the Virgin is not burdened by sin or Adam's debt is also straightforward.
Adam was originally created righteous, free from the often-discussed sin and debt, and free from its penalties.
He was given the ability to always maintain the righteousness he received, along with the freedom and happiness that came with it.
Since Adam could have kept these blessings without any trouble, but chose not to, he lost them and ended up with their opposites.
Consequently, he became a slave to sin, or injustice, and incurred a debt he couldn't repay, along with the misery of being unable to regain what he lost.
Just as he couldn't take away the good things he had or attract the evils he didn't have, except by failing to preserve those goods when he could, he also couldn't take away those same goods from anyone else or impose those evils, except by failing to preserve the goods for those he had the power to help.
However, he could only preserve those goods for those whose generation he had the power to influence by his will.
Therefore, he couldn't pass on the aforementioned evils to anyone, no matter how they were descended from him, if he had neither the means to influence their generation nor the ability to do so.
Thus, there is no reason or right for Adam's aforementioned evils to affect the man conceived by the Virgin.
Chapter Thirteen
Even if there were no God, but only a pure man, it would still be essential for him to be like the first man was created.
If we look closely at God's wise justice with clear reasoning, it seems quite absurd that through that lineage, neither created nature, the will of a creature, nor any given power produces or plants.
Only God's own will, by a new strength, separates the world from sin through a Virgin, so that no necessity of another's sin, debt, or punishment passes to this man; even if he is not assumed in the person of God but is made as a pure man.
By the same logic, God should not have made Adam except as just, nor burdened by any debt or inconvenience.
The rational mind clearly sees that the one whom He similarly creates by His own will and strength should not be subjected to any evil, because it is very unsuitable for the goodness of the omnipotent and wise God to create a rational nature by His own will alone from material in which there is no sin.
Whoever does not understand this does not recognize what is unsuitable for God.
Therefore, even if God were to create a pure man in this way, it would be necessary for him to be endowed with no less justice and blessedness than Adam was when he was first made.
Chapter Fourteen
The reason proposed is not contradicted by the writings that say man is conceived from unclean seed and in iniquities, even if these writings refer specifically to some.
If someone does not understand what I mentioned about human seed-that it holds no sin before the rational soul but is called unclean due to future sin and iniquity-it is because, when it becomes a person, it will bear uncleanness.
They may think it is unclean at conception, as posed in the question: Who can bring a clean thing out of something conceived in an unclean seed?
Job Chapter 14.
And: I was conceived in iniquities, and in sins did my mother conceive me; Psalm Chapter 51.
I am not concerned here, because I do not require that which cannot be understood to be understood; rather, I ask that attention be given to what I briefly convey.
Indeed, those who made these statements may have intended them to be understood about all human seed, or only about seed sown with the sense of pleasure, which would not exist except in brute animals if man had not sinned.
But if they felt this way about all seed, then they claimed that the seed from the Virgin alone was unclean, which is impious to believe.
Therefore, they did not write this about that.
If they expressed this about any human seed in this sense, they meant it only about seed conceived with the aforementioned pleasure.
This does not contradict our reasoning, which asserts that the seed taken from the Virgin is pure, even though it originates from a sinful mass.
Chapter Fifteen
How a sinful mass is not entirely sinful.
Just as blindness isn't present in every part of a person, even though we call them blind, it's only in the eye where sight should be.
It's not in the hand or the foot.
Similarly, deafness is only in the ear when we say someone is deaf.
In the same way, while humanity is often called a sinful mass, sin isn't in every part of it.
As mentioned, it's only in the will, which isn't known to have any seed at conception.
Therefore, with no true or plausible reason to argue otherwise, if we consider what was said earlier, we can conclude that there's no reason, truth, or understanding that suggests anything should be attributed to the man conceived from the Virgin alone from the sin of the sinful mass, even though he was taken from it, even if he weren't God.
Chapter Sixteen
Why John and others conceived through a miracle are not inherently free from sin.
If John the Baptist and others born from barren women-where the ability to conceive had died due to old age-are presented as objections, suggesting they should have been born without sin because they were conceived miraculously, it's important to understand that the reasoning which exempts the virginal conception from the necessity of sin is entirely different.
There's a difference between doing something unheard of, unimaginable, and unknown to nature, and healing nature weakened by age or defect to restore its function.
If Adam had not sinned, he would not have been weakened by old age or any other cause, and the nature of procreation, created in him and under his control, wouldn't have been hindered by any circumstance.
Therefore, in John and others like him, nothing new is added to Adam's nature, unlike with the son of the Virgin.
Instead, what was weakened is understood to have been restored.
Thus, because they were generated through the natural procreation given to Adam, they cannot and should not be considered similar to him in the miraculous conception we're discussing, to suggest they could be freed from the bond of original sin.
Chapter Seventeen
Why God became incarnate, when He could have made sinless humans from Adam, as many as needed, but not gods.
You might wonder: If a pure human, who wasn't God, could be made from Adam without any sin, as suggested, why did God need to become incarnate?
After all, God could have redeemed sinners through a sinless person, or by creating as many such humans as needed to complete the heavenly city.
To this, I respond briefly: God became human because a mere human would not be enough to redeem others, as has been frequently discussed.
Therefore, He didn't create as many sinless humans as needed, because if no one from natural propagation was saved, it would seem as though creating that nature in Adam was pointless, and as if it was corrected without being made; which doesn't align with supreme wisdom for any nature.
Earlier, I intended to explore how the seed from the Virgin, which was shown to be sinless, could be seen as free from the necessities that I mentioned all other humans are conceived with.
And regarding the necessity by which human nature, having abandoned justice, cannot recover it by itself;
and the one by which the corruptible body weighs down the soul, especially in infants, I was confident it could be liberated because that human was God, if the necessity of sin and the debt of Adam and the nearest parents could first be rightly removed.
So, in Book One, I began to explore how these issues could be understood concerning the necessity of sin and the debt of Adam, so that later it would be easier to find what I was seeking regarding the other matters.
And with the abundant grace of Him whose conception is being discussed.
.
It's clear that he was not only recognized as free from all sin and debt but also from the necessities mentioned earlier.
A person conceived in this way should be endowed with just as much justice and happiness as Adam was when he was created.
This holds true even if he were just a human and not God.
It seems equally unreasonable for sin or its punishment to be passed down to him from any parents through such propagation, and for God to make a naturally rational being unjust or miserable without any wrongdoing on their part.
Chapter Eighteen
That God was conceived by a righteous Virgin, not out of necessity, as if He could not be born from a sinner, but because it was fitting.
The Son of God was truly conceived by the purest Virgin, but this was not out of necessity.
It wasn't that a righteous child could not be born from a sinful parent through such propagation.
Rather, it was fitting for this miraculous conception to be from a most pure mother.
It was appropriate that the Virgin, whom God the Father intended to give His only Son-whom He loved as Himself, being born equal to Him from His own heart-should possess a purity that could not be greater under God.
The Son was to be naturally the common Son of both God the Father and the Virgin.
He chose this Virgin to truly make her His mother.
From her, the Holy Spirit wished and intended to conceive and bring forth the one from whom He Himself proceeded.
How the same Virgin was cleansed through faith before her conception is explained in Book Two, Chapters Sixteen and Seventeen, where I also provided another explanation of this topic.
Chapter Nineteen
How this explanation and another given elsewhere agree and differ.
These two explanations each seem sufficient on their own to address the question, but together they provide a deep satisfaction for the mind seeking the power of reason and the beauty of action.
Although they aim for the same goal, they differ in this way: the explanation I presented here shows that God, even from the substance of a sinful Virgin, ought to produce a righteous offspring, indeed only a righteous one, because sin exists in human nature only through will, and there is no reason to oppose such propagation.
The other explanation proves that even if there were sin in the entire essence of the Virgin, she could still be made pure through faith for such a conception.
Moreover, in this explanation, all necessity of death and any corruption or toil are clearly excluded from that man; while in the other, a question seems to arise about this very point.
But it is resolved with sufficient reasoning, if carefully considered.
Therefore, from both explanations, it is clear that our Lord and Redeemer endured nothing in all that he suffered except by a holy will.
Born of a Virgin, He possessed original righteousness instead of original sin.
As I see it, it has been clearly shown, as I intended, that original sin could not possibly be passed down from parents to someone conceived by a Virgin; rather, by nature, He had to be just and blessed.
Therefore, since He was born just from a just Father in His divine nature, and from a just mother in His human nature, He was just from the very beginning.
It's fitting to say that instead of the original injustice that all other children of Adam have, He possessed original righteousness from the start.
Chapter Twenty-One
Why He Could Not Have Personal Injustice.
It's unnecessary to discuss personal injustice in His case because it simply didn't apply to Him.
Human nature was never separate from the divine in Him, nor was His soul ever burdened against His will or constrained by a corruptible body.
This soul, being both the whole man and the Word of God, always existed as a single person.
He was never without perfect justice, wisdom, and power, which He possessed from Himself as God.
While in human form, He received what He had from the divine.
I do not deny that there might be another reason, higher than this one, for how God took on human form from a sinful mass without sin, like unleavened bread from leavened.
Besides the one I've presented here, and the one mentioned elsewhere in Book Two, Chapter Sixteen.
If another reason is shown to me, I will gladly accept it, and if it can be demonstrated that mine could go against the truth, I will not hold onto them.
Chapter Twenty-Two
On the Extent of Original Sin.
Original sin cannot be greater or less than what I've described.
Since an infant is already rational, human nature doesn't have the justice that was given to Adam and should always have.
It's not excused by the inability to have it, as discussed earlier in chapter two.
However, I don't consider it as severe as I previously indicated.
When I aimed to show that it doesn't apply to the man conceived from the Virgin, I presented it in such a way that nothing could be added, ensuring I didn't seem to downplay its importance during my investigation.
Now, I'll briefly explain my thoughts on this.
I don't believe Adam's sin is passed to infants in a way that they should be punished for it as if they personally committed it, like Adam did, even though it results in none being born without sin, leading to condemnation.
When the Apostle says that death reigned from Adam to Moses, even over those who didn't sin like Adam did, as stated in Romans Chapter Five, Verse Fourteen, it seems to clearly indicate that Adam's transgression isn't personally imputed to them, even though he states that all children of Adam, except the Son of the Virgin, are sinners and children of wrath.
When he says, even over those who didn't sin in the likeness of Adam's transgression, it can be understood as saying, and even over those who didn't sin as much as Adam did by transgressing.
And when he says, but the law came in, so that the offense might abound, as mentioned in Romans Chapter Five, Verse Twenty, we understand that sin before the law, in those who didn't sin like Adam, was less than Adam's sin.
Or if it wasn't less, sin increased in them after the law beyond Adam's sin, which I can't comprehend when I consider it, regarding the weight and satisfaction in Cur Deus Homo, which I've explained as it seemed to me, as you've already read in Book One, Chapters Nineteen and Twenty.
It's true that no one can return to the purpose for which humans were created, nor can they be rescued from the evils into which human nature has fallen, without addressing the sin that caused these evils in the first place.
Someone might ask: If individuals don't bear Adam's sin, how can you say that no one is saved without addressing Adam's sin?
How does a just God demand payment for a sin they don't have?
To that, I say: God doesn't demand more from any sinner than what they owe.
But since no one can repay what they owe, Christ alone repays on behalf of all who are saved and more than they owe, as I've already mentioned before.
Chapter Twenty-Three
Why and How Sin Passes Down to Infants.
We need to look at why sin is less in infants than it was in Adam, even though it has descended from him to everyone else.
Through Adam, sin entered the world, and with sin came death.
Understanding why it is less requires us to understand why and how it exists.
This has been mentioned before to the extent necessary for the topic, but it's worth briefly repeating here.
It's undeniable that infants were in Adam when he sinned, but they were there in a causal or material way, like seeds.
They are personally themselves, since in him they were the seed itself; in themselves, they are different individuals.
In Adam, they were not distinct from him, but in themselves, they are different from him.
So, in him, they were him; in themselves, they are themselves.
Therefore, they were in him, but not yet themselves, because they were not yet individual beings.
Some might argue that saying others were in Adam is meaningless and shouldn't be considered existence.
If so, they should also claim that Christ being in Abraham, in David, and in other ancestors, according to the seed, is meaningless.
And that God did nothing when He created all things from seeds initially.
But if it were not true, these things we see would not exist.
If it weren't true that what nature creates from seeds was first something in them, they wouldn't come from them.
It's foolish to deny this; therefore, it was not meaningless but true and substantial that all humans were in Adam.
God did not make something empty when He made them to be in him; as was said, in him they were not different from him, and therefore very different from how they are in themselves.
However, although it's clear they were all in him, the Son of the Virgin was in him in a very different way from the others.
All others were within him such that, by the nature of propagation-which was subject to his power and will-they came from him.
However, this one was not within him in a way that, by his nature or will, he would originate from him, because after Adam sinned, it was determined that he would be the source from which others would arise.
From this individual, there was a difference; he was to be what he was meant to be, not so that he would originate from him, because it wasn't within his power to be propagated in that way.
Nor was it within his capacity to be made from another essence or from nothing.
Thus, it wasn't within him to exist in any form.
It was neither in the power of his nature nor his will to exist in any manner.
Yet, the nature from which he was to be propagated was within him, not by his power, but by God's power.
Even though up to the Virgin mother, both will and nature played roles in the parents' creation, bringing her forth partly through natural and voluntary means from Adam, like everyone else, neither did the creature's will produce offspring, nor did nature germinate in her.
Instead, the Holy Spirit and the power of the Most High miraculously created a man from the Virgin woman.
Therefore, he was in Adam, in that others were to come from him, but he was not in him in any way to be; just as he was not in the clay from which the first man was miraculously made, nor in the man for Eve to be made from him.
He wasn't in any of those from Adam to Mary in such a way to be; however, he was in them because it was from them he was to be assumed, just as he was in the clay from which the first man was made, and in him from whom Eve was made, not by the creature's will or power, but by divine virtue alone.
But this one was in a much more miraculous and greater grace; while they were pure humans, this one was made God-man.
So, this one was in Adam in a very different way when he sinned than those who are procreated by voluntary and natural means.
In a sense, he creates those who are Adam, whom human will brings into being through the power given, and nature nurtures by birth.
However, this one was made solely by God, though from Adam: not through Adam, but by His own power, as if from Himself.
What could better demonstrate the greatness of God's goodness and the fullness of grace given to Adam than the fact that those under his influence were such that what he was by nature, they were through him?
Likewise, it was in his free will that, just as he was in righteousness and happiness, he could propagate these qualities to them.
This was thus granted to him.
Since he was placed in the heights of such great grace, he willingly abandoned the good he had received to keep for himself and them.
Consequently, the children lost what the father could have given by maintaining it, but he took away by not keeping it.
This, in my view, is a sufficient reason why Adam's sin and its consequences descend to infants.
If we set aside our biases, which often hinder our understanding of justice, and consider justice itself more carefully, this becomes clearer.
Now, I'll briefly explain how the same sin seems to descend to them.
There is sin from nature, as I mentioned in chapter one, and sin from the person.
Therefore, what is from the person can be called personal; but what is from nature is natural, also known as original.
Just as the personal influences nature, so does the natural affect the person in this manner.
What Adam ate was required by nature, as it was created to do so.
But eating from the forbidden tree was not natural; it was a personal choice, his own will that led to this.
Yet what the person did was not done without nature.
For the person was Adam, and nature was man; therefore, the person caused nature to become sinful, because when Adam sinned, man sinned.
Indeed, it wasn't because he was human that he presumed to eat the forbidden fruit; rather, it was by his own will, which nature did not require but the person conceived.
Similarly, this occurs in infants, albeit in reverse.
Indeed, the absence of justice in them, which they should have, isn't because of their own will, like it was with Adam, but rather due to a natural deficiency inherited from Adam.
In Adam, who was the only one of his kind, justice was taken away.
This is always lacking unless supported, because nature exists in people and people cannot exist without nature, making the nature of infants sinful.
Thus, Adam's actions deprived nature of justice.
As a result, nature, now lacking, causes all people it produces to be sinful and unjust with the same deficiency.
In this way, Adam's personal sin is passed on to all his natural descendants, making it original or inherent in them.
Hence, it's clear there is a significant difference between Adam's sin and theirs, because he sinned by his own choice; they sin out of a natural necessity, which his own actions brought about.
However, although no one doubts that different sins don't receive equal punishment, in this aspect, the condemnation of both personal and original sin is similar, because no one is welcomed into the kingdom of God, for which humans were made, except through the death of Christ.
Without this, what is owed for Adam's sin isn't repaid, even though not everyone deserves equal torment in hell.
For after the day of judgment, there will be no angel or human except in either the kingdom of God or in hell.
Therefore, the sin of infants is less than Adam's sin; yet no one is saved without that universal satisfaction, through which both large and small sins are forgiven.
Why it must be through that death, and how salvation comes from it, I have explored and explained in the aforementioned book, as God enabled me to do.
Chapter Twenty-Four
That the sins of parents after Adam are not counted as original sin in their children.
I don't believe that the sins of our parents contribute to the original sin of their children.
If Adam couldn't pass on his righteousness to his descendants, he certainly couldn't pass on his unrighteousness either.
Since no one after Adam has been able to preserve their righteousness for their children, there's no reason to think that the sins of parents affect the souls of their children.
Furthermore, it's clear that infants don't have a sense of right will for its own sake.
In this way, they are all equally unjust because they lack the justice everyone should have.
This lack of justice has been passed down from Adam, who lost it in human nature.
Even if Adam retained some justice-meaning human nature allowed him to maintain a right will in some aspects-he was deprived of the ability to pass this justice to his descendants.
So, it cannot be inherited with any justice.
Therefore, infants can't lose more than all justice and happiness, which isn't given to anyone lacking necessary justice.
It seems impossible for the injustice of parents to increase this lack in infants beyond Adam's sin.
Where there's no justice, none can be taken away.
Where no justice is absent, no injustice can be added.
Thus, unjust parents can't add any more injustice to their infants beyond the existing absence of justice.
However, where there's no justice, there's nothing stopping some justice from being added.
It seems more reasonable that if unjust parents could add injustice to their infants, then just parents might be able to give some justice to theirs.
If this happens, the children of the just have some measure of justice.
If this is true, then unbaptized babies of righteous parents are punished less than those of unrighteous parents, or if they are saved, they are chosen based on some prior merit of their own.
But the Apostle Paul denies this in Romans 5, where he uses the example of Jacob and Esau to show that no one is saved without grace coming before any merits.
Since righteous parents do not give any justice to their babies before baptism, it follows that unrighteous parents do not add any injustice to theirs either.
If someone says, "Unrighteous parents do not add any injustice to their children," because they cannot remove any justice from them, then they must believe that the original sin they have from Adam becomes heavier in those children. But if that is true, then righteous parents should be able to make it lighter in theirs. So, if the babies of righteous parents are less unjust than those of unrighteous parents, they should be less condemned than those others. But let the one who dares to say this also try to prove it.
As for me, I do not dare say it, because I see that both the babies of righteous and unrighteous parents are sometimes chosen for baptismal grace and sometimes not. And even if someone does say this, they cannot prove it. Just as no one is more righteous than another unless they more willingly choose what is good or avoid what is evil, so too no one is more unjust than another unless they more willingly love or despise what they should not.
So, if babies cannot be shown, right when they gain a soul, to will more or less of what they should or should not, then no one can prove that one baby is born more just or more unjust than another. Therefore, it seems that righteous parents do not actually make original sin lighter in their children through their own righteousness, nor do unrighteous parents make it heavier in theirs through their own unrighteousness.
So, if unjust parents can't increase original sin in their children through their own sins, it seems to me that the sins of parents, after Adam, impact their children's good merits.
The good deeds of parents bring many significant benefits to their children's bodies and souls.
Due to the parents' sins, children and grandchildren face various hardships in life up to the third and fourth generations, and perhaps even further.
They might miss out on good things, even spiritually, that they could have achieved if their parents had been righteous.
Giving examples of this would take too long to include here.
But I believe that original sin is naturally the same for all infants conceived, just as Adam's sin, which causes them to be born into it, affects everyone equally.
Chapter Twenty-Five
How the sins of parents can harm the souls of their children.
If the sins of parents sometimes harm the souls of their children, I believe it happens like this:
It's not that God holds the children accountable for their parents' sins or leads them into wrongdoing because of their parents.
Rather, just as children are often saved from sins by the merits of their righteous parents, they are also sometimes left to their own devices due to the merits of their ancestors.
No one is free from sin unless God sets them free.
When He doesn't set them free, it's said that He is leading them into sin, and when He doesn't soften their hearts, it's said to harden them.
It seems quite reasonable that God might leave a sinful soul, to whom He owes nothing but punishment, in its sins because of the parents' sins.
This allows it to be punished for its own actions, rather than burdening it with someone else's sins for which it would be tortured.
Thus, without contradiction, original sin is the same in everyone:
The son does not bear the iniquity of the father; each person carries their own burden and receives according to what they have done in the body, whether good or bad.
God repays the sins of the parents to the children to the third and fourth generation, even if this applies to the soul.
Clearly, the soul of the child does not die because of the father's sin, but because of its own.
No one bears the father's iniquity when left to their own, but their own.
They don't carry someone else's burden, but their own.
Nor do they receive according to what the father did, but according to what they themselves have done in the body.
However, because they are not freed from their own evils due to the parents' sins, the burdens they carry are attributed to the same sins of the parents.
Chapter Twenty-Six
How no one bears the sin of their father, but their own.
If someone argues that all who aren't saved through faith in Christ bear Adam's iniquity, consider that infants do not bear Adam's sin, but their own.
Adam's sin and the sin of infants are different; they are not the same.
Adam's sin was the cause, while the infants' sin is the effect; Adam lacked justice because he abandoned it himself.
Infants lack it not because of their own actions, but because someone else, namely Adam, abandoned it.
So, Adam's sin and that of infants are distinct.
When the apostle in Romans Five: Fourteen says, "Because death reigned from Adam to Moses, even over those who did not sin in the likeness of Adam's transgression," it suggests that the sin of infants is less than Adam's.
This clearly indicates they are different.
Therefore, when an infant is condemned for original sin, it's not for Adam's sin but for their own.
If they didn't have their own sin, they wouldn't be condemned.
Thus, they bear not Adam's iniquity but their own, though it's said they bear it because Adam's sin was the cause.
This cause in Adam, which means infants are born in sin, doesn't exist in other parents because human nature lacks the same power for righteous children to be born.
Thus, infants don't have sin because of their parents' sin as they do with Adam's sin.
Chapter Twenty-Seven
What original sin is, and how it is equal in everyone.
I understand original sin to be simply what exists in an infant as soon as it has a rational soul.
Whatever might have happened to the body before it was animated, like any physical corruption, or whatever happens afterward, either in the soul or body.
For these reasons, I believe it is the same in all naturally born infants, and all who die with only that sin are equally condemned.
Indeed, any sin added beyond that is personal.
Just as a person is born a sinner by nature, the nature itself becomes more sinful through the person.
Because when any person sins, humanity sins.
This sin, which I call original, is nothing more in those infants than the state I described earlier.
It is caused by Adam's disobedience to rightful justice, making all children of wrath.
It accuses the spontaneous nature created in Adam of abandoning justice.
Nor does it excuse individuals, as mentioned in chapter two, from the inability to recover, which is accompanied by a lack of blessedness.
So just as they are without all justice, they are also without all blessedness.
Through these two lacks, they are exposed in this life's exile, vulnerable to sins and miseries that occur constantly and overwhelm from all sides.
Except insofar as they are protected by divine arrangement.
Chapter Twenty-Eight
Against those who think infants should not be condemned.
Some people believe that infants who die without baptism should not be condemned.
This belief comes from the idea of injustice, as no one holds infants accountable for another's sin.
Given their age, they lack righteousness and understanding, making it seem unreasonable for God to judge them more harshly than humans do.
To these people, it's important to explain that God's expectations of infants are different from those of humans.
Humans should not demand from nature what they have not given and what is not owed to them.
It's not just for a human to blame another for being born with a fault they themselves cannot escape, except through another's help.
However, God has the right to demand from nature what He has given and what is justly owed to Him.
Even the judgment whereby infants are condemned is not very different from human judgment.
Imagine a scenario where a man and his wife, elevated to great dignity and status through no merit of their own but purely by grace, commit a grave and inexcusable crime.
They are justly cast down and reduced to servitude.
Who would argue that the children born to them after their condemnation should not be subject to the same servitude but should instead be freely restored to the privileges their parents justly forfeited?
This is similar to the first parents and their descendants, who, justly condemned from bliss to misery for their fault, continue to beget in the same exile.
Therefore, a similar judgment applies to similar cases, although more strictly, the more improbable their offense may seem.
Finally, every person is either saved or condemned.
Those who are saved are admitted to the kingdom of heaven, and those who are condemned are excluded from it.
Whoever is admitted is elevated to the likeness of angels, who have never sinned and never will.
This transformation cannot occur as long as any stain of sin remains.
Therefore, it is impossible for anyone to be saved while carrying any sin, no matter how minor.
So, if what I mentioned is true-that original sin is indeed a sin-then it's essential to understand that every person born with it, unless forgiven, will face condemnation.
Chapter Twenty-Nine
How the inability to have righteousness excuses them after baptism.
I mentioned that the inability to have righteousness does not excuse the injustice of infants.
Someone might then ask: if sin, which is injustice, exists in an infant before baptism, and the inability to have righteousness is not excused, as you say, and sin is only forgiven in baptism if it existed before; then how, after baptism, is the infant not unjust even though they cannot understand the righteousness they should uphold, since righteousness is the uprightness of will maintained for its own sake?
If a baptized infant dies in infancy, not immediately after baptism, and they do not yet know how to repent, since they do not have the righteousness they owe and are not excused by inability, they pass from this life unjustly, as they would before baptism, and are not admitted to the kingdom, which the Catholic Church does not believe.
But if in baptism the sin of future infancy is forgiven for infants, why would this not apply to those in later ages?
To this, I respond that in baptism, sins that existed before baptism are completely erased.
Therefore, the original inability to have righteousness is no longer counted as sin against those who have been baptized, as it was before.
Just as the inability to have righteousness could not excuse the absence of righteousness before, since it was itself at fault, after baptism it completely excuses it, because it remains without any fault.
Thus, the righteousness owed by infants before baptism is not demanded from them after baptism as if it were a debt.
So, as long as they lack righteousness due only to original inability, they are not unjust, because the absence of owed righteousness is not in them.
Indeed, it is not owed when it is impossible without any fault.
Therefore, if those who are not unjust die in this state, they are not condemned, but rather saved by the righteousness of Christ, who gave himself for them, and by the righteousness of the faith of the Mother Church, which believes on their behalf, as if they were just.
I've shared my thoughts on original sin based on my own understanding.
I'm not making definitive claims, just offering my perspective until God reveals something clearer to me.
If someone has a different view, I respect their opinion, as long as it can be proven true.