Four Books Against the Objections of the Greeks
by Ratramnus, a Monk of Corbie
Book Four
Chapter One
About the different customs of the Church.
What should be uniformly held by everyone in the Church.
Customs sometimes change.
The following objections, though they may seem unwise and ignorant, could have been left out if they did not risk causing confusion among the less discerning.
They might appear pious, but they can easily mislead those who cannot distinguish between true and false religion.
Since these objections do not concern the doctrine of faith, which is the essence of Christianity, but merely describe the customs of their own Church, there was nothing for our Church to either endorse or oppose.
As the Apostle says: "I urge you to all speak the same thing and that there be no divisions among you" First Corinthians 1:10.
He clarifies elsewhere what he means by this, saying: "One Lord, one faith, one baptism. One God and Father of all, who is over all and through all and in all" Ephesians 4:5-6.
In these essential matters, there is no diversity among believers. We all confess the Holy Trinity, the birth of our Savior Jesus Christ from the Virgin, His passion, death, resurrection, ascension into heaven, and His sitting at the right hand of the Father.
We believe in our hearts for justification and confess with our mouths for salvation.
We also believe that He will come to judge the living and the dead, and we uphold one baptism in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, regardless of who we are as Christians.
In these matters, the Apostle urges us to be of the same mind and not to think differently.
However, the customs of different Churches are not all the same and cannot be uniformly held by everyone.
At the beginning of the emerging Church, the Acts of the Apostles tell us that those who believed in Jerusalem owned nothing as personal property.
Instead, they sold their possessions, and the proceeds were laid at the apostles' feet and distributed to each as needed.
Everything was shared among them.
(Acts 4:34-35)
However, the same religious practice did not bind the Gentiles who believed.
It is written in the Acts of the Apostles that they received the commandments through the apostles, which, if followed, would make them partakers of eternal salvation.
These commandments were to abstain from idol worship, fornication, blood, and meat from strangled animals.
The apostles did not want to impose anything beyond these essentials, as confirmed by the letters sent to the Gentile believers:
"It seemed good to the Holy Spirit and to us not to burden you with anything beyond these essential things: that you abstain from what has been sacrificed to idols, etc.
And in conclusion: If you keep yourselves from these, you will do well."
(Acts 15:28-29)
Who cannot see the different religious practices?
To possess nothing of one's own but to live communally versus retaining all personal property and being bound by only a few commandments?
One thing is to achieve the highest level of perfection, as those who sold everything they had and distributed it to the poor, following the example of poor Christ.
Another thing is to follow just a few commandments at the beginning of the religion, not being excluded from those who aimed for the highest, even if they followed the least of the commandments.
Although the observances differed in quality, they were united in faith.
Eusebius, Bishop of Caesarea, writes in his Ecclesiastical History about the believers in Alexandria, noting their religious fervor and the excellent philosophy of their conduct.
(Ecclesiastical History, Book 2, Chapter 16)
He said: First of all, those who have devoted themselves to this kind of philosophy renounce all their possessions and give up their goods.
Then they cast away all the worries of life and leave the city to live in gardens or small plots of land, avoiding the company of those with different goals and lifestyles, knowing that these are obstacles for those who want to walk the difficult path of virtue.
And furthermore, he said: In each place, there is a house dedicated to prayer, which is called a semnion or monastery.
Semnion can mean a gathering place of honorable people, where they retreat to celebrate the mysteries of an honest and pure life.
They bring nothing related to food or drink, or other bodily needs, but only the books of the law, the volumes of the prophets, hymns to God, and similar things.
Trained in these disciplines and practices, they unite in continuous study towards a perfect and blessed life.
From sunrise to sunset, they spend all their time in the exercises of study, in which they are instructed in divine philosophy through sacred writings, interpreting the laws of the Fathers allegorically, believing that the things written in the letter of the law are forms and images of some hidden deep and divine mystery.
And in conclusion: They first place continence as a foundation in the soul, and then proceed to build other virtues upon it.
None of them take food or drink before sunset, combining the time of light with philosophical study, and bodily care with the night.
Some even go so far as to share food only after three days, driven by a greater hunger for study.
Now, those who are deeply engaged in the teachings of wisdom and in understanding the holy scriptures, much like those who eagerly reach for abundant feasts, cannot be satisfied.
Instead, they become more inflamed by what they learn.
They do not allow themselves food on the fourth or fifth day, but only on the sixth day, and even then, it's not so much out of desire but out of necessity for the body.
Writing about the lifestyle of the believers, he shows how much their way of living differed from that of other believers around the world, not only in Alexandria but throughout Egypt.
These believers were so fervent in their desire for the heavenly homeland that it could be rightly said to them: "But our citizenship is in heaven" Philippians 3:20.
Although they lived in the flesh, they led, so to speak, an angelic life on earth. It is said that they were instructed in this way by the blessed Mark the Evangelist, whom the apostle Peter sent from Rome to Alexandria to preach the Gospel of Christ. However, did they exclude other Churches of Christ around the world, who lived differently, from their fellowship or eagerly seek to convert them to their own rites and customs? They knew that grace was given to each, not only to individuals but also to the Church, according to the measure of Christ's gift.
Yet, because they had established continence as a foundational principle to be consecrated first, they did not condemn marriage. Unless one might think that among them, bishops and priests had wives, while it is known that even laypeople among them abstained from marriage. Nor did they have lunch on every Sabbath, as they extended their fasts until evening; and many of them barely provided food for their body on the third or sixth day.
Therefore, let the wise men of the Greeks, or at least their leaders, see how justly they reproach the Romans for fasting on the Sabbath. Then let them also reproach these people who fast every day; let them also reproach those who continue fasting the entire week.
Since it is clearly foolish,
I would like them at least to recognize the error of their imprudence or frivolity and strive to be imitators of virtue rather than disparaging those who fast.
For the kingdom of God is not about food and drink, but about righteousness and godliness, as the Apostle says in Romans 14:17.
And the Savior defeated the devil not by eating, but by fasting, as mentioned in Matthew 4.
Nor should all the Churches of Christ desire to follow their own custom;
since they see that both in the times of the apostles and their disciples, there were different practices observed;
yet they were not different in faith, even if they differed in observance.
Chapter Two
On the various customs of the Church.
The Lenten fast has been observed differently in the past, with variations in foods and rites.
There were also many sects among the Jews.
The Apostle writes to the Thessalonians:
"For you became imitators, brothers, of the churches of God in Judea that are in Christ Jesus" (First Thessalonians 2:14).
By saying this, he shows that even the churches of Gentile believers had different strengths, roles, and customs.
This is also confirmed by blessed Jerome in the Prologue to Paul's letters, saying:
"They do not follow the order in which they were written, but follow a certain progression of ranks; so that the first place is held by the letters sent to churches with lesser observance of doctrine or virtue.
The middle place is held by those sent to churches that had deviated from the beginnings but had not yet reached the peak of perfection.
The last place is held by those sent to churches that had attained perfection, excelling in both knowledge and virtue, having many below them, but none above them."
This shows that where there was a difference in the knowledge and virtue of the churches, there was also a difference in religious customs.
Indeed, those in Jerusalem who lived communally, sharing in the breaking of bread and persevering in prayer, possessing nothing of their own, behaved very differently from those who retained their possessions and commended the Gospel of Christ through their life, morals, and faith according to the grace given to them.
The Apostle greatly praises the Thessalonians, who were granted to suffer the same as those in Jerusalem suffered from the Jews.
Regarding the various customs of the churches, Socrates in Ecclesiastical History (Book 5, Chapter 21) says:
"What is celebrated as Easter according to a certain custom throughout the provinces, I think, stems from the fact that no religion seems to observe the same festivals."
Since there is one faith, many rules regarding Easter are established, so a few things need to be mentioned.
For example, you will find different fasting practices among different peoples: The Romans fast for six weeks before Easter, excluding Sundays, continuously.
However, the people of Illyricum, all of Greece, and Alexandria fast for six weeks before Easter; they call these fasts Lent.
Others begin their fasts seven weeks before Easter.
But they also do not have the same abstinence from foods:
some abstain completely from animal products; others eat only fish.
Some eat fish and birds, saying these according to Moses have their substance from water.
Others are known to abstain from vegetables and eggs as well.
Some eat only dry bread; others do not even do this.
Some fast until the ninth hour and then eat without distinguishing between foods.
There are countless customs among different peoples.
Since no ancient text is found on this matter, I believe the apostles left this to each person's judgment, so that each may do what is good, not out of fear or necessity.
Even regarding the celebration of gatherings, certain differences are found.
While sacrifices are celebrated weekly on the Sabbath in the churches established throughout the world, this is not done in Alexandria and Rome by some ancient tradition.
The Egyptians near Alexandria, and the inhabitants of Thebes, hold gatherings on the Sabbath but do not receive the sacraments in the usual way: after they have feasted and filled themselves with all kinds of foods, they communicate in the evening after an offering is made.
In Alexandria on Wednesday and Friday, Scriptures are read and interpreted by teachers; and everything is done except the formal prayer practice.
Also, in Alexandria, readers and psalm reciters, whether catechumens or already Christians, are chosen indiscriminately, while all the churches seem to have faithful members in these roles.
I also learned about another custom in Thessaly: when a cleric had lawfully taken a wife before becoming a cleric, if he remained intimate with her after becoming a cleric, he was deposed.
In the East, however, all bishops abstain voluntarily, not out of necessity.
Many of them even had children with their lawful wives while serving as bishops.
Additionally, in Thessaly, baptism is only performed on Easter, so many die without being baptized.
In Antioch of Syria, the altar is not towards the East of the Church but rather towards the West.
In Greece, Jerusalem, and Thessaly, they have evening prayers similar to those of the Novatians in Constantinople.
In Caesarea of Cappadocia and Cyprus, on Sabbath and Sunday evenings, bishops and priests interpret the Scriptures with lamps lit.
In Alexandria, a priest does not give a sermon; this practice began when Arius troubled the Church.
In Rome, they fast on all the Sabbaths.
In Caesarea of Cappadocia, those who sin after baptism are suspended from communion.
The Novatians around Phrygia do not accept those who have married twice.
In Constantinople, they neither openly accept nor openly remove such people; but in the western parts, they openly accept them.
It would take too long to gather all the diverse practices observed throughout the Churches around the world or to understand what has been observed since ancient times.
However, it should suffice to briefly compile these from the history of a single writer, and this Greek: so that the emperors may understand how unjustly and ignorantly the Greeks criticize the Romans for not observing their customs in everything.
Let them compel the whole body of the Churches of Christ spread throughout the world into the laws of their customs, and then, if they can, judge the Romans for the diversity of their religion, because they seem to be different from the customs of Constantinople.
Are they truly more knowledgeable than the apostles, or can they prove that their Roman customs are superior based on ancient writings?
Interestingly, one of their own historians notes that the holy apostles left these decisions to individual judgment, so no one would act out of fear or necessity but rather by their own free will.
Although they all share the same faith, they practice different customs when it comes to celebrating Passover and observing fasts.
Some observe more days of fasting, while others observe fewer.
They don't follow the same kinds of food, timing, or duration for their fasts, but each group is content with the customs of their province, their elders, or their personal abilities.
Churches also don't hold gatherings, or assemblies of people, at the same time or in the same way.
For example, the Alexandrians and Romans conduct their gatherings differently from the Egyptians and Thebans.
The Romans and Alexandrians don't hold assemblies on the Sabbath, unlike the churches of Christ throughout the entire East, which are proven to do so.
The Egyptians and those living in the Thebaid hold assemblies on the Sabbath, but they don't receive the sacraments of the body and blood of Christ while fasting.
Instead, they receive them in the evening after having eaten, which is contrary to the custom of the entire world.
The Alexandrians also add Wednesday and Friday to their custom, during which they hold assemblies to read the Holy Scriptures and have teachers interpret them, but they don't perform the solemn rite of offering on these days.
Despite these differences, they are not excommunicated by the other Eastern churches, even though their practices seem to differ.
Thessaly has customs that differ from other Eastern regions.
For instance, after taking holy orders, they do not allow anyone, as a historian testifies, to even acknowledge his own wife, whom he lawfully married before ordination.
If he does, he is deprived of his ministry.
However, in other Eastern Churches, no one is bound by this rule; it is left to their own judgment and free will.
Not only other ecclesiastical ranks but also priests and bishops can retain their lawful wives, whom they had before ordination, if they wish.
However, it is not permitted for those who do not have wives to marry, nor to enter into a second marriage if their previous wife has died.
Yet, this difference does not separate anyone from communion, as custom differentiates.
At the time of baptism, the Church of Thessalonica also differs from others.
They only baptize at Easter, although there are two times decreed by the elders for baptism: Easter and Pentecost.
Why should I mention Antioch in Syria, where it is customary to have the altar not facing the east of the Church, but rather the west?
The same historian reports that the people of Constantinople are divided on accepting or rejecting those who have been married twice, with some accepting and others disagreeing.
Meanwhile, the entire Western Church openly accepts without contradiction.
Yet despite their different customs, they are not separated in the unity of communion.
I ask, what is this wisdom or sacred zeal that Greek emperors do not allow among the Romans what the universal Church endures throughout the whole world?
They want neither the Romans nor the Westerners to differ from their custom, although the Easterners are separated by a variety of customs.
Is Constantinople itself content with one custom?
It is not enough to speak of the different customs among believers in Christ if I do not also show that the religious observance of the Jews was not uniform.
Even though they worshipped one God and followed the Mosaic law, their way of living and moral rules were not uniform.
As the historian Josephus recounts in Book 18, Chapter 2:
"The Jews," he says, "had three philosophical sects stemming from their ancestral traditions: the Essenes, the Sadducees, and the Pharisees. The Pharisees live modestly and humbly, avoiding luxury and comfort, and follow what their reason and judgment deem necessary. They do not oppose their leaders and honor their elders with respect, never responding contrary to them.
They believe that fate governs everything but do not deny human free will. They believe in God's judgment, where everyone will receive according to their deeds, whether they lived virtuously or succumbed to wickedness.
They say that souls are immortal and that in the afterlife, each soul is assigned a dwelling based on their merit, whether of virtue or vice, reflecting their pursuits in life. Some souls are confined to eternal prisons, while others are granted the ability to revive. For these reasons, they are credible and accepted by the people.
They also emphasize worship practices, the celebration of prayers, and the establishment of temples in their teachings. This dedication has earned them such a reputation that many cities and a great multitude, driven by the belief that they are superior to others, flock to them with great zeal."
The Sadducees, however, believe that souls are mortal and perish along with the bodies. They observe no other rules beyond the law. They consider it glorious to contest and resist the teachers of their philosophy, but their doctrine and practices reach very few."
However, the leaders among them are celebrated for their ranks and honors.
The Essenes, on the other hand, attribute everything to God.
They believe the soul is immortal and preach that justice is a precious thing worth fighting for until death.
But in the temple, they prohibit offerings.
They do not celebrate sacrifices or offerings with the people because they believe they differ greatly from them in purity and holiness.
They distinguish themselves from the common congregation by performing sacrifices in remote places.
They are considered the best in moral conduct and behavior, dedicating all their effort to cultivating the land and practicing every form of diligence.
They also have a remarkable and unique trait, not found among other nations, whether Greek or barbarian: all their possessions are held in common, and they share everything among themselves.
No one among them enjoys more wealth, and nothing is kept from the poor, as if no one owns anything personally.
They number more than 4,000 men.
They do not marry wives, nor do they hurry to acquire servants, as they consider it a source of injustice and strife.
They help each other in isolation, serving one another with mutual assistance.
They appoint those who manage their income and establish caretakers to administer all the produce of the land for necessary uses.
They select the best men as priests.
Their food is simple, their clothing unadorned and clean.
Josephus further describes, at the end, a fourth type of philosophy practiced among the Jews, whose leader he says was Judas.
We have omitted this either due to its brevity or because, being newly discovered, it was considered inferior to the others.
We have included these details about the Jews to show that in their worship of the Divine and observance of the Mosaic Law, they had similar practices and were equally fervent; however, in moral conduct and religious habits, they maintained a distinctly different way of life.
We don't approve of their religion in our times, but we want to show that even though they believed in one Divinity, their way of life was different.
They did not separate themselves from each other's communion.
Instead, they remained in the union of society, patiently tolerating that not all customs were the same.
They knew that the diversity of morals did not oppose their faith, since they shared the same belief about God and followed the commandments of the law.
The emperors of the Greeks are deeply offended that the Romans do not live in the same manner as they do, nor follow their customs—that is, the customs of the Greeks.
This cannot be found in the Churches of Christ, nor among the Jews, who, before the preaching of the Gospel, had a distinguished worship of Divinity.
Therefore, it is proven that such a reproach did not arise from a zeal for piety, but from the malice of envy and the arrogance of pride.
Let us now come to each point they seem to have made, by which, while they seem to boast either of their wisdom or religion, they reveal their own foolishness and irreligion.
Chapter Three
The Greeks blame the Romans for fasting on the Sabbath.
Why the Romans fast.
Purpose of Sabbath fasting.
Greek objection.
Response.
The Greeks criticize the Romans and Westerners for fasting on the Sabbath, because they, the Easterners, dine on this day.
They don't realize that not all Western Churches follow this tradition, but the Roman Church and some other Western Churches do.
In fact, most Westerners do not fast on the Sabbath.
They do not criticize the Romans for fasting, nor do the fasting Romans criticize them.
They understand the Apostle's words: "Let not the one who eats despise the one who abstains, and let not the one who abstains judge the one who eats" Romans 14:3.
However, not all Eastern Churches fast on the Sabbath.
The Church of Alexandria follows the ancient Roman tradition of fasting on this day.
There are no gatherings in Alexandria on the Sabbath, just like in Rome.
This indicates that the Alexandrians, like the Romans, do not dine on the Sabbath.
On gathering days, it is customary to perform sacraments and break fasts.
Among the Thebans and Egyptians, they break the fast on the Sabbath but only receive the sacraments of the Lord's body and blood in the evening after eating.
They are not criticized by other Churches for this, even though they do not follow any specific Church's tradition.
We are unsure if these new objectors criticize them, but we know that the Romans were instructed by the Apostle Peter, according to ancient tradition, to fast on the Sabbath.
It is said that apostles Peter and Paul fasted on the Sabbath before confronting Simon the Magician.
This established the custom of fasting every Sabbath among the Romans.
This is documented by the historian Eusebius in the booklet "Life of Pope Sylvester".
The Greeks approached Blessed Sylvester with a question about why the Romans fast on Saturdays.
In response, he said:
It should suffice that we know the early apostles practiced this; however, because you seek a reason, I will provide one.
If every Sunday is kept in honor of the Lord’s resurrection, then it is fitting that every Saturday is observed with fasting because of His burial.
By mourning with the apostles over the death of Jesus Christ, we can rejoice with them over His resurrection.
The Greeks argued that fasting should only be observed on one Saturday each year, marking the burial.
To this, Pope Sylvester replied:
If every Sunday is celebrated for the resurrection, then every preceding Saturday should be devoted to fasting.
This way, those who mourn His death can rightly rejoice over His resurrection.
However, I would say that to sympathize is to weep, without denying that the Lord’s passion is the peak of our joy.
The Greeks, accepting this reasoning, remained silent.
We mention this to show that the Roman practice of fasting on Saturdays is neither new nor insignificant, as it is supported by apostolic authority and sound reasoning.
It's surprising that the wisdom of the new scholars does not align with what their elders agreed upon.
Since the time the chief apostles, Peter and Paul, taught in Rome and affirmed their teachings with their martyrdom, it has been customary for Romans and some Westerners to fast every Saturday.
Nonetheless, the Eastern churches that do not follow this custom have not judged the Romans as estranged from their communion, even though they themselves refrain from fasting on Saturdays, just as on Sundays.
Doctor Augustine writes about this to the presbyter Casulanus (letter 86) and to Januarius (letter 118), addressing the same question and responding thus:
Saturday follows, on which day the flesh of Christ rested in the tomb, just as God rested on that day from all His works during the creation of the world.
This led to different practices in the Church regarding eating habits.
Some, especially in the East, preferred to break their fast to symbolize rest.
Others, like the Roman and some Western Churches, chose to fast to honor the humility of the Lord's death.
On the day when Easter is celebrated, everyone fasts to remember the time when the disciples mourned the Lord’s death.
Even those who usually eat on Saturdays throughout the year devoutly observe the fast on this particular Saturday, signifying both the mourning of the disciples on this day and the rest on other Saturdays.
Two things inspire hope for the happiness of the just and the end of all misery: death and the resurrection of the dead.
In death, there is rest, as the prophet says: "My people, go into your rooms and shut the doors behind you; hide yourselves for a little while until his wrath has passed by" (Isaiah 26:20).
In the resurrection, there is perfect happiness in both body and spirit.
Therefore, it was thought that both of these should not be signified by the labor of fasting but rather by the joy of refreshment, except on Easter Saturday, where, as we mentioned, the mourning of the disciples was marked by a longer fast to remember the event.
But since, as I mentioned earlier, we do not find in the Gospel and apostolic writings any clear command that certain days should be observed with fasting, this matter, like many others, allowed for variety in the practices of the Church.
I will share what the venerable Ambrose, the bishop of Milan who baptized me, answered when I asked him about this.
Since my mother and I were living in the same city, and both of us were still catechumens without much concern for these matters, she was unsure whether to fast on Saturday according to our city's custom or to have lunch as per the Church of Milan's tradition.
To resolve this uncertainty, I sought advice from the man of God I mentioned earlier.
He said,
"What more can I teach you than what I do myself? When I am here, I do not fast on Saturday; when I am in Rome, I do fast on Saturday. Wherever you go, follow the custom of that church to avoid causing or enduring scandal."
I relayed this answer to my mother, and she accepted it without hesitation, believing it should be followed. We also adopted this practice. However, in Africa, it is common for different churches, or even churches within the same region, to have varying practices—some people have lunch on Saturday while others fast. I believe that the custom of the congregation, as determined by its leadership, should be observed.
Blessed Augustine, the Catholic doctor, thought and wrote about fasting on Saturday, suggesting that no serious dispute should arise over this issue. Instead, each church's custom regarding fasting or having lunch on Saturday should be followed. Those who have lunch on Saturday seem to have a pious reason for doing so: they signify that on that day, God rested from all His works or they reflect the rest of believers, who will rest in the resurrection and enjoy eternal peace with the Lord.
Similarly, those who fast have a pious reason: because on that day, the disciples were physically saddened by Christ's death, and in wanting to imitate their sorrow, some faithful fast on Saturday. Others choose not to fast, to demonstrate the joy of the Lord's resurrection by having lunch, just as the apostles did when they witnessed the Lord's resurrection.
Because of the disciples' show of sadness, all the Churches around the world fast on one Saturday each year, which is the Saturday before Easter, even though they may eat or not eat on other Saturdays.
However, the Romans chose to remember it by fasting every Saturday, just as the memory of the Lord's resurrection is celebrated by all Churches every Sunday.
Since both those who fast on Saturday and those who eat have their reasons for their piety, and since there are no commands in the New Testament that either require or prohibit this, no serious disagreements should arise in the Churches of Christ because of it.
Instead, it should be left to each individual's choice what they prefer to do, while following the authority of their elders and their Church's custom.
If the Greek emperors had considered this, they would not have started a dispute, but would have followed what their ancestors held.
Should anyone be judged for fasting out of piety?
Indeed, there are other days on which some Churches have the custom of fasting each week, such as Wednesday and Friday.
There is a reason for this, as the blessed Augustine says, because on Wednesday the Jewish leaders gathered and conspired to capture and kill Jesus by deceit.
On Friday, they crucified Him.
Augustine speaks in Epistle 86: Why does the Church fast especially on Wednesday and Friday?
The reason seems to be this: according to the Gospel, on Wednesday, which is commonly called the fourth day of the week, the Jews are found to have held a council to kill the Lord.
After one day passed, on the evening of which the Lord ate the Passover with His disciples, which was the end of that day, which we call the fifth day of the week: then He was handed over that night, which already belonged to the sixth day of the week, which is clearly the day of His passion.
This day was the first of Unleavened Bread, beginning from the evening.
But Matthew the evangelist says that the fifth day of the week was the first day of unleavened bread, and that in the evening following, the Passover meal was to take place.
During this meal, the unleavened bread began to be eaten, and the lamb was sacrificed.
From this, we gather that it was the fourth day of the week when the Lord said, as recorded in Matthew chapter 26, verse 2 and following,
"You know that after two days the Passover is coming, and the Son of Man will be handed over to be crucified."
Because of this, that day was designated for fasting, as the evangelist continues and says,
"Then the chief priests and the elders of the people gathered in the courtyard of the high priest, who was called Caiaphas, and they conspired to arrest Jesus by trickery and kill him."
After one day had passed, as the Gospel says,
"On the first day of unleavened bread, the disciples came to Jesus saying, 'Where do you want us to prepare for you to eat the Passover?'" (Matthew chapter 26, verse 17).
Therefore, after this day had passed, the Lord suffered, which no Christian doubts, on the sixth day of the week.
Hence, the sixth day is rightly designated for fasting.
Fasting, indeed, signifies humility; hence it is said,
"I humbled my soul with fasting" (Psalm chapter 35, verse 13).
Blessed Augustine writes these things about fasting on the fourth and sixth days of the week to the priest Casulanus, explaining why it was instituted.
However, this fasting, observed on the fourth or sixth day of the week, is not practiced by all churches, whether Eastern or Western, but only by some who choose to observe it.
Those who fast on these days are not criticized by those who eat, and each church follows the custom it has received from its ancestors.
Thus, it is surprising why the Romans are criticized by the Greeks for fasting on the Sabbath, when they are not criticized for fasting on the fourth and sixth days, nor are other Christians throughout the East.
It is evident that the people of Constantinople are not bound by any law or custom to fast on the fourth or sixth day of the week.
In the British Isles, fasting is observed on every sixth day of the week, yet those in the West who do not have the custom of fasting on that day are not excommunicated.
The Scottish nation, inhabiting the island of Ireland, has a custom of fasting through monasteries of monks, canons, or any religious people at all times except on Sundays and feast days.
They do not indulge in food for the body except either at the ninth hour or in the evening: at the ninth hour in summer, and in the evening in winter.
Although no church, whether Western or Eastern, is bound by this custom, those who fast in this manner are neither excommunicated nor reproved by those who do not fast in this way.
It was previously mentioned how fervent the believers in Alexandria were about fasting when the Christian religion first began there.
No one ate before sunset; many ate on the fourth day, some on the sixth day of the week, not because it was desirable for the body, but because it was necessary.
Yet, those fasting were neither excommunicated nor reproved by others who did not follow this fasting custom.
Behold, the Romans who fast on Saturday are reproved either in memory of the Lord's burial, because of the disciples' sadness over the Lord's death, or because the apostles are said to have fasted on that day to combat the tricks and deception of Simon, to fight against the devil, and the madness of Nero.
Some also observe the fifth day of the week, refraining from fasting on that day, just as they do on Sunday.
This practice is approved by Eusebius, the bishop of Caesarea, in a book he wrote about the deeds of Pope Sylvester, where he states: "Pope Sylvester said: We ought to regard the birthday of the chalice as a solemn day like Sunday, on which the celebration of the Lord's body and divine blood began from the Lord himself."
On this day, holy chrism is made throughout the entire world; indulgence is granted to penitents; those in discord return to concord; the angry are pacified; princes grant indulgence to criminals; masters grant indulgence to bad servants; judges spare thieves, and prisons are opened worldwide.
On this day, those who had shut themselves away because of the severity of their sins come out to celebrate joyfully.
They had committed these sins through crying, laughing perhaps, or getting angry, or transgressing in other ways.
When Saint Sylvester spoke many things like this and similar, all contradiction ceased.
The most Christian and learned Greeks are said to have opposed, saying:
Truly, the apostolic seat learned this from Peter, which cannot be refuted by any reasoning.
If the Romans are judged for fasting on the Sabbath day, why are they not judged for fasting on the fifth day of the Sabbath?
Or why do the modern Greeks prefer to consider themselves more learned than their ancestors, so that what their ancestors received and praised with worthy praises, these people seek to criticize?
They are neither proven to be more religious nor more learned than them.
They should see that they might rather be criticized for being more insolent.
Why can what has been observed with Christian peace for so many centuries not be maintained now?
Instead, contradictions are heaped up, causing scandal and discord.
Are they so wrapped in the darkness of imprudence that they think they want to change the Churches of Christ by the criticism of the insolent, what has been firmly maintained for many centuries?
Melchiades, the thirty-third apostolic of the Roman seat from the apostle Peter, decreed about the fifth day of the Sabbath, that by no reasoning should any of the faithful fast on Sunday or Thursday, because those days were celebrated by pagans as if with sacred fasting.
Although the reason for dining on the Lord's Day, which the whole Church holds, seems more important, because on that day Christ rose from the dead, and because the rest of the future age is signified by it.
Also, about the fifth day of the Sabbath, which blessed Sylvester discussed with the Greeks, it should not be disregarded what Melchiades, the Roman bishop, taught.
For the Catholic Church ought rather to destroy than to imitate the fasts of the pagans, just as it ought to destroy all their festivals, in which it is known that they serve demons rather than the true God.
Therefore, it has been appropriately decided that Christians should not fast on the same days as pagans, so that the holiness of the pious religion is not tainted by the superstition of demonic worship.
While the first day of the week is generally observed by all Christians as a day not for fasting, the fifth day of the week isn't observed in the same way by everyone.
Many choose to fast on that day, especially during the Lenten season.
Nonetheless, there is no dispute among the Churches of Christ over this; each community follows the fasting or dining customs they have inherited from their ancestors.
If the leaders of the Greeks considered this, they wouldn't criticize the Latins or Romans for fasting on the Sabbath so lightly.
They would be content with their own customs and admire the Queen standing before Christ in a golden garment, adorned with variety.
They wouldn't try to impose strict rules on a matter for which they have no authority from either the New Testament or the Old Testament.
Chapter Four
The Romans are criticized for not observing Lent like the Greeks.
The reason for the forty days of fasting before Easter.
The number of weeks is observed differently.
Why some Westerners fast for thirty-six days.
The explanation of the forty days.
Let's now address the issue regarding the Paschal Lent.
Critics say that we do not fast like those who abstain from meat for eight weeks before Easter and from cheese and eggs for seven weeks according to their custom.
They speak as if all Eastern and Western Churches, except the Romans, maintain this practice.
Yet, there is much diversity found in both Eastern and Western Churches, as already shown above.
Some Churches fast for six weeks, excluding Sundays, before Easter; others start six weeks before Easter; some begin their fast seven weeks before Easter.
That is, some start the Paschal fast in the sixth week before Easter, some in the seventh, many in the eighth, and others even add a ninth week.
Let these critics consider who they follow or imitate.
They do not agree with the Romans, who fast for six weeks continuously before Easter, excluding Sundays; nor with those who start fasting in the seventh week.
These critics say they refrain from eggs and cheese during that week but have not yet fully observed the fast, which is done by those who dedicate seven weeks to the Paschal fast.
They also claim to abstain from meat for eight weeks before Easter, practicing a partial, not complete, fast, thus differing greatly from those who start the fast in the eighth week without changing their fasting pattern.
Moreover, these critics seem to have no connection with those who fast for nine weeks before the Paschal time, since they do not abstain from eggs, cheese, or meat in the ninth week.
Therefore, when they are found to differ in the observance of the Easter fast, not only from the Westerners but also from the Easterners, they ask why they criticize the Romans and are not afraid to be criticized by other Churches with whom they do not seem to agree in the Easter fast.
Or certainly, let them produce commands from either the Old or New Testament or authority to defend their custom, or let them rightly criticize the Roman practice.
Since they cannot do this, let the custom of the Churches teach them about the various ways of fasting, showing that this observance is not done based on any divine command that requires fasting out of necessity, but should remain a matter of personal intention or will.
So that with the joy of the Holy Spirit, one offers to God what seems right and possible, and not out of necessity, but as a voluntary good.
Yet, this should not be left to each person’s individual choice alone, but the authority and custom of each Church’s elders should be observed, so that everyone keeps what each Church received from its founders to be kept.
Unless perhaps it should be thought that the Greeks are to be preferred in this matter, because in the seventh week they neither eat eggs nor cheese, even though they are far surpassed by those who do not eat anything cooked throughout Lent, and by those who only eat bread.
They also appear much inferior to those who do not even eat this but are refreshed only by eating herbs.
Nor can they be compared at all to those who, throughout Lent, barely allow themselves food once or twice a week.
Let them cease to exalt themselves lest they fall, but rather humble themselves so that they may rise and recognize that the concord of peace and the unity of love are better than the observance of fasts.
Let them also consider why this variety of fasting before Easter has occurred.
Finally, we are taught by both gospel and legal authority that a fast of forty days should be observed: for it is read in the Gospel that the Savior fasted continuously for forty days and nights.
In the Old Testament, it is written that Moses completed this number of fasting days twice.
He did this once before receiving the Ten Commandments from the Lord, and a second time after being provoked by the people's transgression and breaking the tablets at the base of the mountain.
He fasted for forty days and nights for two reasons: to make amends for the people's offense to divinity, and to be deemed worthy of receiving the law from the Lord again.
Elijah also fasted for forty days and nights while fleeing Jezebel's wrath, walking through the wilderness until he reached the mountain of God, Horeb.
This led to the custom in the Churches of a continuous forty-day fast.
Therefore, while almost all of Christ's Churches strive to observe this number of fasting days, they do not all agree on the number of weeks due to variations in the days.
It is known that people observe the forty-day number of the Paschal fast, but not everyone fasts on each day of every week.
Some people only eat on Sundays, others do not fast on Saturdays or Sundays, and some break their fast on Thursdays.
Because they do not fast on Sundays, and others fast on specific days of the week, they do not complete the forty-day number.
To achieve the forty-day count, they fast for not just six but seven weeks before Easter, even though six weeks contain not just forty but forty-two days.
By subtracting the six Sundays from the forty-two days, thirty-six fasting days remain.
To complete the forty-day count, four days are fasted in the seventh week.
Hence, in the seventh week, only four days are fasted instead of six, which, when added to the thirty-six days, complete the forty-day count.
Those who do not fast on either Saturday or Sunday but still strive to complete the forty-day fast before Easter must begin their fast on the eighth week.
This is because they fast only five days each week, and eight times five equals forty, which completes the forty-day fast prescribed by law over eight weeks.
However, if they add Sunday and Saturday, days on which fasting is not observed, and prefer to add the fifth day of the week, they cannot complete the forty-day fast before Easter unless they fast for nine weeks.
Removing three days from seven (Sunday, Saturday, and the fifth day of the week), they are left with four fasting days each week.
Multiplying four by nine results in thirty-six, not forty.
Since they do not fast for forty days, they claim to complete the forty-day fast.
For this reason, the Greeks have no grounds to criticize the Romans for the difference in weeks, because what the Greeks achieve in eight weeks by fasting only five days each week, the Roman and Western Churches accomplish in six weeks, adding four days in the seventh week.
If the Greeks fasted six days in eight weeks like the Romans or almost all Latins do, they would fast much more than forty days before Easter: eight times six equals forty-eight.
Therefore, the Greeks should consider the authority they follow if they fast so many days before Easter.
Neither the Savior, nor Elijah, nor Moses observed this number of fasting days.
If they complete their fast in forty days to align with the New and Old Testament, they find nothing to criticize in the Western Churches, as both fast for the same number of days before Easter.
If fasting is an act of humility, as the Psalmist confesses, "I humbled my soul with fasting" (Psalm 35:13).
Not only the people in Constantinople, but also Romans and Westerners, fast for weeks.
In the weeks leading up to Easter, the Western Church refrains from solemn songs, like "Alleluia," and the celebrations of martyrs.
They avoid all celebratory glorification, which they usually enjoy throughout the year, so that they can rejoice more gloriously on Resurrection Day, having prepared themselves by humbling for a longer period for holy Easter.
The Lord commanded the children of Israel through Moses, after the making of the calf, to lay down their ornaments, so He would know what to do with them.
This wasn't because He was unaware of their guilt of idolatry, which deserved punishment, but so that through the affliction of humility, the people would show how they acknowledged their guilt and how they preferred to atone for their wrongdoings.
So, what do the ornaments that the people were commanded to lay down represent, if not the splendor of joy they were used to before their idolatry?
Similarly, both the Roman and Western Church lay down their ornaments by humbling themselves, abandoning the joyful feasts and hymns they usually celebrate throughout the year.
By adopting an attitude of humility, they set aside the glory of exultation, so that when they come before the Lord, they can receive the Easter celebrations with true joy.
Therefore, the Greek emperors have no reason to criticize the Romans or Westerners if they do not fast as many weeks before Easter as they do.
By fasting for forty days, they are equal in the number of days.
Fasting signifies humility, which means laying down joy, taking on affliction, adopting a habit of sorrow, and removing delight.
In fact, the Romans or Latins can be said to fast more than the Constantinopolitans, because by humbling themselves for nine weeks, they prepare for Easter, which is the main focus.
Critics of the Romans should reconsider if they truly wish to adhere to the laws of discipline.
The tradition of fasting before Easter varies among Churches, and there's no divine commandment binding them to a uniform practice.
Each Church has the freedom to follow the traditions of its elders.
If critics were aware of this, they wouldn't appear so arrogant, especially towards those who follow apostolic teachings and reasonable considerations.
Romans, for instance, fast for six weeks before Easter continuously, except on Sundays when they break the fast.
So, if they're known to fast for 36 days, which is four days short of 40, there's a pious and honest reason for this practice for those willing to understand it.
The solar year has 365 days; if you take one-tenth of these days, you get 36 days.
We are commanded to offer a tenth of our labors to the Lord.
Therefore, it's reasonable to offer even a tenth of our days to the Lord, living for Him by dedicating a tenth of the year's days and purging the sins committed throughout the year during these days.
However, because very few in the West complete 40 days of fasting before Easter, the reason must also be given for why they are content with 40 days.
Setting aside the authority of either the Gospel or the Law, which clearly teaches us to fast for 40 days: there are ten commandments in the Old Testament, and four Gospels, leading us to a new life.
Four times ten makes forty; and each person serving the Lord is seen to reach the height of perfection by combining the legal Decalogue with the perfection of the Gospel.
It's also evident that a human consists of four elements, just as the world does.
Because we often break the Ten Commandments, it is necessary for us to seek forgiveness for our sins by afflicting ourselves forty times.
This is why the Romans or Latins decided to fast for forty days before Easter; it is both a religious and mystical practice, as shown above.
Therefore, criticizing the practice of fasting for more weeks before Easter is both unjust and baseless.
It should be disregarded, except that charity, which endures all things, compels us to respond to such unreasonable objections.
By understanding the reason behind this practice, people may stop criticizing what is observed for the sake of honesty and religious dignity, and may peacefully return to unity and concord, from which they had strayed due to foolish presumption.
Chapter Five
On the cutting of the beard or head.
Let's explore how clerics are criticized for cutting their beards, not only by the Romans, but by all Western Christian Churches.
This issue is seen as so trivial that it was considered unworthy of a response, to avoid appearing as frivolous as those who raise it without reason.
What does the cutting or keeping of a beard have to do with the beginning, let alone the perfection, of justice?
Let those who criticize show what command is found about this in either the New Testament or the Old Testament.
Going further, what can they suggest is determined in the writings of the apostles or the decrees of ecclesiastical teachers?
This matter, like many others, is left to the custom of individual Churches, so that out of respect for their elders, they may either grow or cut their hair or beard.
Indeed, some have the custom of cutting the beard or head:
some do not cut the beard but shave the entire head:
some prefer to shave all the hair on the face and cut the hair on the crown of the head, leaving a part of the hair between the shaved crown and the temples.
But some do not cut the beard, only partially shave the head, and leave the other part unshaven.
This habit of clerics is not uniform across all churches, but varies according to the custom of their elders.
There has never been any contention among either Western or Eastern churches about this, as each has held to what they received from their elders or what the practice of the provinces has approved.
The apostle Paul reproached the Corinthians because the men were either growing their hair or covering their heads, while the women were neither covering their heads nor growing their hair.
This custom was rightly condemned by the Apostle, because although it seemed acceptable to the Corinthians, it appeared contrary to nature.
And why he reproves it, he clearly shows the reason, saying:
A man should not cover his head, because he is the image and glory of God.
But why a woman should grow her hair or cover her head, he similarly explains, saying:
A woman should have authority over her head because of the angels.
Therefore, clerics who grow their beards but completely shave their heads and, unable to endure either cold or heat, or wishing to hide such disfigurement of appearance, cover their heads with a garment, should consider if they are going against the apostolic command.
Indeed, they cannot deny that they act against Paul's statement:
Every man who prays or prophesies with his head covered dishonors his head.
We do not say this because we prefer to criticize such a custom: for we know that such a habit is a sign of humility; but to advise that Greek emperors have something nearby that they can either criticize or correct; and not lightly criticize those far away, whether Romans or Latins: who, if they shave their beards, neither grow their hair nor cover their heads when they pray or prophesy: although they have authoritative Scripture to defend their custom excellently.
And in the Old Testament, the custom remained for Nazarenes to shave their heads and beards during the time of consecration and to put it in the sacrificial fire: signifying that they consecrated not only their actions but also all their thoughts to the Lord.
Hence, the divine word speaks to the prophet Ezekiel:
And you, son of man, take a sharp sword, a razor, take it and pass it over your head and your beard.
For he was not a priest of foreign origin, but born of the priestly lineage: hence he is commanded, according to the custom of the Nazarenes, to shave both his head and beard.
In the Acts of the Apostles, it's written that Priscilla and Aquila, Jews who believed in Christ, shaved their heads in Cenchreae because they had taken a vow, as the Scripture indicates.
In Jerusalem, the elders spoke to the Apostle Paul:
"We have four men who have taken a vow upon themselves. Take these men, purify yourself with them, and pay their expenses so they may shave their heads. Then everyone will know that what they have heard about you is false, but that you yourself are living in obedience to the law."
And a little later:
"Then Paul took the men, and the next day he purified himself along with them and went into the temple to give notice of the date when the days of purification would be fulfilled."
Following this custom, the clergy of Rome and almost all the churches in the West shave their beards and cut their hair, taking their example both from those who were called Nazarites in the Old Testament and from those in the New Testament who are recorded as having done such things. But they do not completely shave their heads; rather, they signify with this partial cutting the royal and priestly dignity.
For it is a royal honor to wear crowns on the head, and priests used to wear tiaras in the temple.
The tiara has the shape of a hemisphere, while the crown, which is circular, customarily surrounds the head.
Blessed Peter the Apostle speaks to the believers:
"But you are a chosen people, a royal priesthood."
The clergy of Rome or the Latin Church wish to signify this by the partial shaving of the head, which resembles a tiara and hints at the priestly dignity. Moreover, the remaining hair surrounding the head, without touching the crown, represents the shape of a crown, which shows royal dignity.
Thus, this dual form signifies the royal priesthood.
Christ is also represented as both king and priest, as the prophet testifies:
"The Lord is our lawgiver, the Lord is our king."
Also:
"You will break them with a rod of iron."
The fact that He is a priest, the Father testifies to the Son, saying: "You are a priest forever according to the order of Melchizedek" Psalm 109:4.
Therefore, whether signifying the priesthood and royal throne of Christ or the clergy of the Latins, they wear this type of headgear.
Because every Christian nation should excel in royal and priestly dignity, they designate this in such a form.
In the uncovering of the face, they show the purity of the heart, alluding to that apostolic saying, where it states:
"But we all, with unveiled face, beholding the glory of the Lord, are being transformed into the same image" Second Corinthians 3:18.
For the face of the head implies the face of the heart: just as the head is the citadel of the heart, so the mind in this place, which is called the heart, exists as the pinnacle of the soul.
The face of the heart must continually be stripped of earthly thoughts, so that with a pure and sincere sight, it may behold the glory of the Lord and be transformed into it through the grace of contemplation.
Blessed Apostle Peter, as well as many others from the number of apostles and even of Christ's disciples, are recorded to have shaved both their beards and heads.
Indeed, images of Peter, which are still depicted today in such a form by the art of painters, testify that he did this.
Neither the Apostle nor the rest of Christ's disciples feared the reproach of the Greeks, who did not disapprove of assuming such an appearance.
Since no one has raised this question either before the law or after the Gospel until now, let the emperors of the Greeks see why they attempt to criticize something that by no means deserves reproach.
For if shaving the beard is some sin or any transgression of divine law, let them say why the prophet, at the Lord's command, shaved his beard.
Why this custom existed among the Nazarenes.
And finally, why the apostles did not abhor this practice.
But let's set aside this objection, as it neither stands on strong reasoning nor carries any serious weight.
Unless we thought it could mislead the less cautious, we wouldn't even consider responding to this argument.
Chapter Six
The celibacy of the clergy is defended against the Greeks.
The celibacy of the clergy is upheld by ecclesiastical laws.
We need to address the claim that the Romans condemn marriage because they not only refuse to let priests marry, but outright forbid it.
While some of their other objections may seem overly superstitious, this one either seems astonishing or very lamentable.
It's astonishing if they are so far from the light of wisdom that they do not see that the Romans, in this matter, actually stand praiseworthy, not blameworthy.
The virtues of continence and chastity are so clearly excellent that even non-Christians admire them; and while they are admirable in all ranks, they are especially so in priests and other ministers of the sacred altar.
Other virtues make them illustrious, but the splendor of holiness and the noble honor of chastity make them even more so.
It is truly lamentable if, knowing such things, they dare to criticize what they know to be praiseworthy, going against their own conscience.
They should have feared what the Holy Spirit speaks through Isaiah:
Woe to those who call evil good, and good evil, who put darkness for light, and light for darkness (Isaiah 5:20).
If they conclude that the Romans condemn marriage because bishops or priests do not marry, then the same judgment must apply to the Fathers of both the Old and New Testaments.
The prophet Elijah, who commanded the heavens to open and close and was taken up to heaven by angels, did not take a wife.
The prophet Jeremiah, sanctified in the womb, preferred the good of virginity and the purity of chastity over marriage.
Daniel, called the man of desires, chose continence over conjugal union.
Yet they did not condemn marriage, even though they did not marry.
The Savior chose to be born of a virgin; while He approved of sacred marriage, He did not refuse to attend weddings.
John earned the love of Christ by choosing discipleship over marriage.
The Apostle Peter, before being elevated to apostleship, did not disdain marriage.
However, after becoming an apostle and dedicating himself to evangelical preaching, he abstained from marital relations, though he did not reject his wife.
It is believed that the other apostles did the same.
Yet, no rational person would say they condemned marriage, even if they embraced the sanctity of continence.
Furthermore, how can the Romans be accused of condemning marriage when marriages are celebrated among them and children are born from legitimate unions?
The blessed Apostle Paul writes to the Corinthians: "I wish that all men were even as I myself. But each one has his own gift from God, one in this manner and another in that" First Corinthians 7:7.
He explains this a bit earlier when he established rules for married couples on how they should serve each other, not having authority over their own bodies, but yielding it to the other.
Thus, he concludes: "But I say this as a concession, not as a commandment" First Corinthians 7:6.
He immediately adds: "I wish that all men were even as I myself," and so on.
By this, he clearly signifies that he is celibate and not bound by marriage.
Elsewhere he writes: "Do we not have the right to take along a believing wife?" First Corinthians 9:5.
In this, he does not deny that Barnabas shares this right with him, saying: "Or is it only Barnabas and I who have no right to refrain from working?" First Corinthians 9:6.
Even though the blessed Apostle professes this about himself, he does not condemn marriage at all.
He gave instructions to the married and urged those who could not control themselves to marry.
Both the Savior and the blessed Paul do not reject the bonds of marriage; they even decree that a wife should not leave her husband, nor a husband leave his wife, except for the cause of fornication.
And if they do separate, they should remain unmarried.
However, desiring to persuade them towards self-control, Paul writes to the Corinthians:
So I say this, brothers: The time is short.
From now on, those who have wives should live as if they do not; those who weep, as if they do not weep; those who rejoice, as if they do not rejoice; those who buy something, as if it were not theirs to keep; those who use the things of the world, as if not engrossed in them.
For this world in its present form is passing away.
First Corinthians seven, twenty-nine through thirty-one.
Earlier, he had granted the incontinent permission to marry, offering it as a remedy for their weakness, saying,
For it is better to marry than to burn with passion.
First Corinthians seven, nine.
Now, he commands to restrain excessive desires even with one’s own wife.
What else does he mean by saying, Those who have wives should live as if they do not, except to suggest that even within marriage, restraint over passions is needed, and that love should serve children more than bodily desires?
For he had previously said:
It is good for a man not to touch a woman.
First Corinthians seven, one.
But since not everyone possesses this virtue, he therefore says,
But because of the temptation to sexual immorality, each man should have his own wife and each woman her own husband.
First Corinthians seven, two.
What is allowed here due to weakness, he later seeks to minimize, saying,
Those who have wives should live as if they do not.
Advising that we should not always serve our weaknesses, but rather accustom ourselves to the sanctity of chastity; for the world in its present form is passing away.
The world's form sought carnal posterity, rejoicing in the progeny of children, and exulting in the multitude of relatives.
But because the world is now at its end and awaits its conclusion; and as blessed John says,
It is the last hour.
First John two, eighteen.
Spiritual succession should be sought more than carnal progeny: So that those who live might no longer live for themselves but for him who died for them and was raised again.
Second Corinthians five, fifteen.
Therefore, he says that those who weep should do so as if they did not weep, so that they may console themselves with the hope of eternal joys amid the ruin and tribulations of this world.
Similarly, those who rejoice in worldly goods should act as though they do not, so that by disregarding the joys of temporal things due to their fragility and changeability, they may instead find joy in eternal things and attain everlasting happiness.
Those who buy should not desire to possess here on earth, but should aim for their possessions to be in heaven, echoing the Psalmist: "For what do I have in heaven, and what do I desire on earth besides you?" Psalm 73:25.
Therefore, those who use this world should act as though they do not, letting it be something they pass through, not something they desire; as a journey, not a destination; and as something seen from the side, not held or enjoyed with possession.
The text continues: "I want you to be free from concern: the one who is unmarried is concerned about the things of the Lord, how to please God. But the one who is married is concerned about the things of this world, how to please his wife, and is divided: and the unmarried woman, and the virgin, thinks about the things of the Lord, so that she may be holy in body and spirit. But the one who is married thinks about the things of this world, how to please her husband." First Corinthians 7:32-34.
Therefore, let the leaders of the Greeks, who strive to criticize the Romans about the continence of priests, consider how they intend to establish ministers of the altar in this matter; whether they want them to be free from concern, as the Apostle wishes, or entangled in worldly concerns, which the Apostle does not wish. For if they are without a wife, free from worldly concerns, they can handle the concerns of the Lord, always seeking to please God; keeping in mind this apostolic saying: "Whatever you do, do it always in the name of the Lord." Colossians 3:17.
But if they live with a wife, they are necessarily entangled in the concerns of the world, seeking to please their wife rather than God. Those who are in this situation are divided, torn between the love of their wife and the love of God, unable to say with the Prophet: "My portion, Lord, I said, is to keep your law." Psalm 119:57.
Neither with blessed Jeremiah, who said:
"The Lord is my portion," said my soul, "therefore I will wait for Him" Lamentations 3:24.
The Apostle says: An unmarried woman or virgin is concerned about the Lord's affairs, to be holy both in body and spirit First Corinthians 7:34.
Is it therefore fitting for the priests of the Lord and the ministers of the altar to be inferior to unmarried and virgin women, who think of the things of the Lord, preserving holiness in both body and spirit, while these priests think of worldly things, rejecting bodily and spiritual holiness?
They are deprived of both types of holiness, those who have their minds on worldly things, eager to please their wives; for, as the Apostle says: "A married woman is concerned about the affairs of this world, how to please her husband" First Corinthians 7:34.
The Savior said that no one can serve two masters Matthew 6:24.
Therefore, either bishops or priests, thinking about fulfilling their marital duties, cannot think about fulfilling their duty of service to the Lord.
And since clerics are said to be the Lord's portion (for this is indeed what the name means) and their portion is none other than the Lord;
priests serving their wives and thinking of worldly things reject the Lord's portion, to which they ought to cling specially; and their only possession is no longer the Lord; because by adhering to the world through constant meditation, they cannot cling to the Lord.
A mind embracing the world with its thoughts and clinging to the world cannot in any way embrace or cling to the Lord.
Because of this, it is remarkable that the Greek leaders strive to criticize priests of the Lord for distancing themselves from the company of women, so that they are not bound by worldly needs, but rejecting the world, they may be free to constantly cling to Christ.
How much the marital bond impedes the continuous supplication to the Lord, blessed Paul indicates, when he subsequently says: "I am saying this for your own benefit, not to impose a restriction on you, but for what is proper and gives you the opportunity to devote yourselves to the Lord without distraction" First Corinthians 7:35.
By clearly stating these things, he demonstrates that those who serve their wives cannot continually pray to the Lord, but only temporarily.
Therefore, let those who criticize marriage consider what kind of priests they desire: those who, by maintaining purity, can pray to the Lord without hindrance, remain holy, dwell always in sacred places, despise worldly matters, and contemplate heavenly things; or those who are bound by marital ties, unable to continually dwell in holy places, despise the world, or pray to the Lord at all times for their people, and whose understanding is far from the apostolic sense.
He advocates for continence, but they interpret the holiness of priests (without which no one will see God) as condemning marriage, forgetting what the Apostle says: I say this for your own benefit, persuading continence.
However, immediately considering human weakness, he adds: Not to put a noose around your neck.
He shows his preference but acknowledges that each person has their own gift from God, one in this way, another in that way.
Again, encouraging what is better, he adds: But to what is honorable; it is understood as an invitation.
By speaking in this manner, he places continence above marriage: not condemning marriage, but clearly stating that while marriage is good, widowhood is better, and virginity is the best.
Therefore, neither Romans nor Latins should be blamed if they suspend bishops or priests from the marital bed; for neither is the Apostle considered worthy of blame, who, while advocating chastity, encourages not entering into the bond of marriage so that the ability to continually pray to the Lord may remain for the faithful.
Indeed, those who must handle the sacraments of the Lord's body and blood at all times, how can they serve in marriage?
For David, when he came to the priest Abimelech, did not deserve to touch the sacred bread until he confirmed that he and his young men had been purified from the touch of women for three days.
And who doesn't know that the mystery of the body and blood of Christ is far more sublime than the bread set out each Sabbath on the temple table?
If it wasn't allowed for those who had not been sanctified by women to touch them,
how is it appropriate for women serving at sacred moments and those bound to marriage to touch holy things on Sundays?
The Church in Thessalonica, carefully examining this mystery, decreed that clerics who had known their wives before their ordination should be deposed.
It's surprising that the leaders of the Greeks criticize the Romans for this when they patiently allow it among the Thessalonians.
If, in modern times, they have perhaps agreed to their superstition, they may hold their convictions in any way they want, but they should know that such was the custom of their ancestors.
But let's come to the ecclesiastical decrees, so we can understand what they preferred to decide on these matters.
In the Council of Nicaea under Emperor Constantine the First, it was decreed by three hundred and eighteen bishops (canon 3, according to the version of Dionysius Exiguus):
The great synod completely forbade bishops, priests, deacons, or anyone in the clergy to have a woman living with them, unless perhaps a mother, sister, aunt, or those persons alone who are beyond suspicion.
Let the emperors of Constantinople hear this and judge whether those in such positions, for whom this chapter was decreed, should enter into marriage, when they are not allowed to live with women, except those who are beyond any suspicion.
For whoever takes a wife cannot have other women in the house besides his wife to fulfill domestic needs and household care.
Where the introduction of all women is forbidden, except for those completely free from suspicion, it is clear that marital union is also forbidden, which cannot happen without the presence of other women.
In the Council of Neocaesarea, it was decreed (canon...
From the same version: A priest who takes a wife should be removed from office.
But if he commits fornication or adultery, he should be expelled even more and brought to repentance.
These canons have been diligently observed by the Roman Church and all Western churches, knowing that what is evidently religious and worthy of divine worship must be maintained by all.
Let the Greeks consider if they insist on holding any statute; if they do, they wrongly criticize the Romans, whom they clearly see as their equals in observing ecclesiastical councils.
But if they freely transgress this constitution, they are found guilty of violating ecclesiastical laws.
While this was established in the East, it should indeed be observed by the Easterners, as it is proven to be sanctioned for the discipline of the Church.
It is strange why they strive to blame the Westerners, who do not hesitate to observe what the Easterners do.
If they are ignorant of ecclesiastical laws, who does not know that they deserve to be rightfully disregarded, driven to speak not by the weight of wisdom, but by the lightness of ignorance?
In the Council of Carthage (African Council, year 424, canon 37): When the incontinence of some clerics towards their own wives was reported, it was decided that bishops, priests, and deacons, according to earlier statutes, should refrain from their wives.
If they do not, they should be removed from ecclesiastical office.
In this chapter, not only are the aforementioned ranks prohibited from taking wives, but they are also commanded to abstain from their own wives, whom they had before being ordained.
If they do not, they are ordered to be deposed.
This decree is agreed upon in both the Nicene and Neocaesarean councils, as both command priests to be separated from their wives.
Therefore, let the imperial criticisms consider how it is just for priests to take wives contrary to the decrees of the elders, who are prohibited from their own wives, whom they had taken before ordination.
If they choose to keep these laws, they should know they are wrongly accusing the Romans.
But if they refuse, they should also criticize the bishops of the entire province of Africa, along with the Romans, and their own Eastern bishops who, following the established rules, decree that bishops, priests, and deacons must live celibately—unless they choose to violate their own decrees.
In the book of the Constitutions of Emperor Justinian, it is decided in chapter 24 as follows:
"It is necessary that he who becomes a bishop should neither have a wife nor a concubine, nor children, nor those unknown to the laws. And if anyone acts against these rules, both he who was made and he who made him shall be expelled from the honor of the episcopate."
Let the Greek emperors see now, who accuse the Romans of condemning marriage because they do not allow bishops, priests, or deacons to marry, where they want to place their laws, that is, those established by their ancestors.
Behold, Emperor Justin of the Romans decreed by law that he who is to become a bishop should neither have a wife nor a concubine. But you, on the contrary, establish that both bishops and priests should have the rights of marriage.
The laws established by your ancestors instruct that those who do this should be deprived of the honor of their rank. But you blame those who do not do this for condemning marriage, and you do not wish to admit them to your communion.
Therefore, it appears that both by ecclesiastical laws and by your own sanctions, you are in opposition:
hence, you bind yourselves with the guilt of a double offense, as transgressors of both divine and human law, as well as ecclesiastical constitution.
(Justinian, as cited above, Novel 123, chapter 29).
Furthermore, we also forbid priests, deacons, and others in the clergy who do not have wives according to divine rules from having a woman in their house, except for a mother, daughter, sister, or other persons who avoid all suspicion.
If anyone has a woman in his house, raising suspicion of impropriety, and he is advised by his clerics to not live with such a woman but refuses to remove her; or if an accuser emerges and proves he is living dishonorably with her, then the bishop, according to church canons, should remove him from the clergy and hand him over to the court of the city where he serves.
This law was specifically decreed for bishops, but it equally applies to priests and deacons.
What is forbidden for bishops is also forbidden for ministers of the altar and those handling the mysteries of the Lord's body and blood.
Even if there is no strict decision concerning priests and deacons, the present decree removes all doubt, clearly forbidding not only priests and deacons but also subdeacons and any other clergy members from marriage.
They are only allowed to live with their mothers or others free of any suspicion of impropriety.
If they are found guilty of violating this, they are to be removed from the clergy and handed over to the court for punishment.
We do not believe that the Greek Churches hold the same views on the marriages of priests as the leaders of Constantinople.
Therefore, they should not presume to go against church regulations or attempt to criticize those which are observed by the Churches and maintained by perpetual law.
If the powers of the world reject such things with their presumption, which both ecclesiastical and human laws prohibit and condemn, it's strange why they don't realize that their sanction is not only condemned by the Western Church but also not accepted by the Eastern Church, unless perhaps some part in the East, worn out by tyranny, is going to accept it.
But they should be frightened by the Lord's statement:
Whoever causes one of these little ones who believe in me to sin, it would be better for him to have a large millstone hung around his neck and to be drowned in the depths of the sea
(Matthew 18:6).
But the fixed statement of the Savior to Peter stands:
You are Peter, and on this rock, I will build my Church
(Matthew 16:18).
Also, in the same book at the end of the same chapter:
No bishop should live with a woman at all; but if he is found not to have observed this, he should be deprived of the honor of the bishopric because he shows himself unworthy of the priesthood.
Let the glorious princes of the Greeks then explain with what audacity and presumption they dare to go against the established traditions, the laws of the Church, and the customs observed up to now, criticizing the Romans and Latins for not allowing bishops, priests, deacons, and subdeacons to marry.
Behold, they are indeed refuted by imperial laws, which, while being enacted for Romans and Latins, undoubtedly condemn those who contravene them.
In the Old Testament, Levites or priests serving in the tabernacle or temple did not approach their wives, nor did they presume to enter or touch the holy things unless they were sanctified.
And you say that priests, whose duty it is to celebrate the mystery of the body and blood of the Lord daily and never withdraw from the sacred things, should marry wives, and that there should be no difference between laypeople and ministers of the sacred altar.
If asked where such an opinion originated, you can undoubtedly show no other authority than ignorance and boasting, from which the audacity of light-mindedness usually arises.
Chapter Seven
The Greeks argue that the sacrament of confirmation can be administered by priests.
The author refutes them.
The difference between a priest and a bishop.
Now let's address the objection that among the Romans, priests do not anoint the foreheads of the baptized with chrism.
This objection, like the others, is proposed more out of lightness than reason.
They are simply following the custom of their own Church, not some authority from divine law.
However, it is clear that this practice is derived both from the Gospel and from the Acts of the Apostles, among the Romans and all Westerners.
The grace of the Holy Spirit is given through the anointing of the forehead with chrism by the bishops, which evangelical authority testifies has been granted to no one except bishops.
For the Lord, rising again and appearing to the disciples, breathed on them and said:
Receive the Holy Spirit:
If you forgive anyone’s sins, their sins are forgiven; if you do not forgive them, they are not forgiven.
(John 20:22)
Therefore, if the forgiveness of sins is granted through the Holy Spirit, and this gift is known to have been given specifically to the apostles, then rightly this grace is reserved for bishops alone, who clearly have inherited the succession and ministry of the apostles in the Church.
We also read in Exodus that Moses anointed Aaron and his sons with holy chrism for the priestly ministry.
Furthermore, in the Old Testament, kings and priests were anointed with holy oil by the high priests, representing the true King and High Priest, our Lord Jesus Christ, to whom the Psalmist sings:
God has anointed you, your God, with the oil of joy above your companions.
(Psalm 45:7)
It is clear that the entire Church is the body of Christ, namely, the King and Priest, hence all Christians are a royal and priestly race.
For this reason, after the washing, we are anointed, so that we may be called by the name of Christ; and only by the high priests, by whom kings and priests were anointed under the law.
In the Acts of the Apostles, it says:
When the apostles in Jerusalem heard that Samaria had accepted the word of God, they sent Peter and John to them.
When they arrived, they prayed for them to receive the Holy Spirit.
For the Holy Spirit had not yet come upon any of them; they had simply been baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus.
Then Peter and John placed their hands on them, and they received the Holy Spirit.
Acts 8:14 and following.
Notice that they were first baptized in the name of the Holy Trinity, which is in the name of the Lord Jesus; since the invocation of the entire Trinity is contained in the name of the Lord Jesus.
Yet they had not received the Holy Spirit.
But after the apostles laid their hands on them, they received the Holy Spirit.
This practice is still observed today in the Church: believers are baptized by priests, but the grace of the Holy Spirit is given by the laying on of hands by bishops, which happens when the foreheads of the baptized are anointed with holy chrism by bishops.
Also, in the same Acts:
While Apollos was in Corinth, Paul traveled through the interior regions and came to Ephesus.
There he found some disciples and asked them, "Did you receive the Holy Spirit when you believed?"
They answered, "No, we have not even heard that there is a Holy Spirit."
So Paul asked, "Then what baptism did you receive?"
"John's baptism," they replied.
Paul said, "John's baptism was a baptism of repentance. He told the people to believe in the one coming after him, that is, in Jesus."
On hearing this, they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus.
When Paul placed his hands on them, the Holy Spirit came on them, and they spoke in tongues and prophesied.
Acts 19:1 and following.
Here, too, you see that Paul did not baptize them himself, but had them baptized.
Then Paul laid his hands on them, and the Holy Spirit came on them.
We are taught that the grace of baptism can be conferred by priests.
However, the gift of the Holy Spirit, given through the laying on of hands when the foreheads of those being baptized are anointed with holy chrism, can only be granted by bishops.
The difference between priests and bishops is significant.
Priests, like other ecclesiastical ranks, are consecrated through the ministry of bishops; but bishops are not blessed by priests.
Bishops also sanctify the holy chrism and consecrate the oil.
All ecclesiastical ranks operate under their direction.
Considering this, ecclesiastical authorities decreed that the foreheads of those being baptized should be anointed with holy chrism by bishops, not priests.
As it is written about Saint Sylvester in the Apostolic Acts, The Book of the Popes by Pope Damasus states:
"He decreed that the chrism should be made by a bishop; and it should be the privilege of bishops to anoint those baptized with holy chrism, due to the accusation of heresy."
Pope Innocent also decrees this in his Decretals, Letter One, Chapter Three.
Regarding the anointing of infants, it is clear that only a bishop is permitted to do this.
Although priests are clergy, they do not hold the highest rank of the episcopate.
This should be reserved for bishops alone, to either anoint or bestow the Holy Spirit, as ecclesiastical custom dictates.
And the Acts of the Apostles asserts that Peter and John were sent to bestow the Holy Spirit on those who had already been baptized.
Priests, whether in the absence or presence of a bishop, can baptize and anoint the baptized with chrism consecrated by a bishop.
However, they are not allowed to mark the forehead with the same oil, which is reserved for bishops alone when they bestow the Holy Spirit.
From here, all Western bishops, following the tradition of their elders, adopted the custom of anointing the foreheads of the baptized with chrism.
They reserved this privilege for themselves, not allowing priests to perform it.
However, they do not make the chrism, as the Greeks falsely claim, from the baptismal font, but from the juice of balsam or olive oil.
This practice is followed not only by the Greeks but by all the Churches of Christ.
Chapter Eight
The Greek emperors tried to place the Patriarch of Constantinople above the Roman Pope.
The Roman Church holds a higher rank than all others.
They falsely accuse us of this, just as they do with the consecration of the lamb.
They also argue that deacons become bishops without first being ordained as priests, not considering that they undermine their own faith authority in other matters when they lie so blatantly in these.
They are not afraid of what the Holy Spirit says:
"The Lord abhors the bloodthirsty and deceitful man"
(Psalm 5:7).
And, "You destroy those who tell lies"
(Psalm 5:6).
And in Solomon:
"A false witness will not go unpunished"
(Proverbs 19:5).
As for their accusation that a deacon is being consecrated as a bishop, why don't they notice what is said against them, who make laymen who have just been tonsured into bishops, against church rules and imperial decrees?
For the Apostle
(First Timothy 3:6) explicitly forbids a novice from becoming a bishop.
Emperor Justin also decrees in his ecclesiastical constitutions
(Novella 6, Chapter 1, at the beginning):
"Neither is it permissible for a layman to immediately ascend to the episcopate, nor is it sufficient to have held the honor of clerical office simultaneously. It is necessary that he who becomes a bishop neither has a wife, nor a concubine, nor children, nor grandchildren, whether legitimate or unknown to the law. And if anyone acts against these, both he who was made a bishop and he who made him should be deprived of the honor of the episcopate. Nor is it permissible to become a bishop by paying money. He who becomes a bishop must be either a monk or a cleric: but he must have appeared in the clerical state for no less than six months," etc.
We see that not only ecclesiastical but also imperial constitutions are being opposed, so that someone is taken immediately from being a layman to the honor of the bishopric, when he should first be tested in the Church and taught according to ecclesiastical constitutions; so that by ascending through the succession of ranks in the royal way, he may be found worthy to obtain the peak of the highest summit.
However, the emperors of the Greeks, violating both divine and human laws, suddenly appoint laymen as bishops, even those with newly shaven heads.
They promote individuals who were not even worthy of the lowest rank to the highest peak of power.
They do this without fearing to slander the Church of Christ, speaking falsehoods as if they were truths, dismissing what the Savior said in the Gospel:
"Whoever causes one of these little ones who believe in me to sin, it would be better for him to have a large millstone hung around his neck and to be drowned in the depths of the sea" (Matthew 18:6).
That the punishment of death may be exacted upon them, and they may be swallowed by the waves of destruction, for charity did not make them subject to holy fear.
But where does such innate presumption come from that they do not fear to attack the Roman Church with false accusations?
Clearly, it comes from the fact that, ignorant of their status, they seek to claim leadership that neither Christ, nor the apostles, nor the teachers of the churches, nor any custom has granted them.
Instead, they imitate him who said in his heart:
"I will ascend above the heights of the clouds; I will exalt my throne above the stars of heaven; I will sit on the mount of assembly in the far reaches of the north. I will make myself like the Most High" (Isaiah 14:13-14).
What else do these Greek leaders proclaim with the arrogance of their hearts, who usurp the leadership of the Church and the exalted status of the apostles (whom the prophet Isaiah calls flying clouds) and claim the throne of their dignity above the stars of heaven?
That is, to be preferred above all the assembly of saints, and to usurp the veneration of the patriarchs, so that with the whole Church subject to them, they may become like Christ.
When no authority of the elders grants this to them, nor do ecclesiastical laws permit it, nor do human laws assign it.
They strongly prove their desire to claim all these things for themselves, by striving to place the patriarch of Constantinople above the Roman pontiff, and to prefer the city of Constantinople over Rome, as if it were within their rights to change ecclesiastical laws and arrange the pinnacle of kingdoms.
They should have remembered that Christ is the head of the entire Church, and that the Father said to Him through the Prophet:
"I will give you the nations as your inheritance; and the ends of the earth as your possession."
(Psalm 2:8)
He is the stone cut from the mountain without hands, which will break and crush to dust all the kingdoms of the world.
(Daniel 2:34-35)
He also said to Peter:
"You are Peter, and on this rock I will build my Church; and the gates of hell will not prevail against it. And I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven."
(Matthew 16:18-19)
Paul also testified:
"He who worked through Peter for the apostleship to the circumcised worked through me for the Gentiles."
(Galatians 2:8)
Both were placed in leadership in the Church by Christ and sent to Rome, as both ecclesiastical truth and the authority of their martyrdom reveal.
Both leaders were sent to where the leadership of the world was prominent: so that the Roman city, having subjected the whole world to itself by imperial power, might also preside over the kingdoms of the whole world by the summit of religion and the dignity of the apostleship.
Just as the Savior wanted to elevate Jerusalem by His birth, teaching, miracles, death, burial, and resurrection, He also chose to make the Roman city glorious by the blood, tomb, memory, and teaching of the chief apostles: so that as Christ, seated at the right hand of the Father, is honored in the heavenly Jerusalem as King and Lord with the service of angels and all the saints, Peter and Paul hold the leadership of the earthly Jerusalem, with Christ's Churches throughout the world subject to them.
This is confirmed both by antiquity itself and by the records of writings.
Socrates, writing in Ecclesiastical History, mentioned the Arians who gathered a synod in Antioch, Syria, aiming to subvert and destroy the Nicene Council and condemn Athanasius.
After listing the bishops who authorized the synod, he added:
"But neither did Julius, the chief bishop of the great city of Rome, attend, nor did he appoint anyone in his place; as the ecclesiastical rule indeed commands that councils should not be held without the judgment of the Roman pontiff."
Here we have a Greek historian who does not claim that Constantinople holds as much authority as Rome; he testifies that without the consent or command of the Roman pontiff, no councils can be held.
In the Council of Sardica (chapter 7, from the translation of Dionysius Exiguus), it is decreed:
"It was decided that if a bishop has been accused and all the bishops of that region, having gathered, judge and depose him from his position: if the deposed appeals and flees to the most blessed bishop of the Roman Church and wishes to be heard: if he deems it just that the examination be reopened, the Roman bishop should be pleased to write to the bishops who are in the nearest and neighboring province, so that they may diligently seek all things out and define everything according to the truth of faith."
"And if the one who asks for his case to be heard again moves the Roman bishop by his appeal to send presbyters from his side, it will be in his power to decide what he wants and what he deems appropriate. And if he has decided that those who are sent should judge in person with the bishops so that they also have the authority of the person by whom they were sent, it will be at his discretion."
"If, however, he believes that the provincial bishops suffice to bring the matter to an end, he should do what his most wise counsel has judged."
This council, held by the Eastern bishops in the province of Asia, thus decreed about the dignity of the Roman pontiff under the Roman Emperor Constantine the Great, who built the city of Constantinople and wished it to be called New Rome.
Is there any record of the Patriarch of Constantinople being given such authority by bishops?
We clearly see that the authority of the Roman Pope stands above all the Churches of Christ.
All bishops regard him as their head, and whatever is arranged in ecclesiastical matters depends on his judgment.
Whether something remains established, a mistake is corrected, or whatever needs to be renewed is sanctioned by his decision.
Eusebius of Caesarea, a bishop, also testifies to this in his history of the life of Silvester.
He says: On the fourth day, Emperor Constantine granted the privilege to the Pontiff of the Roman Church, so that priests throughout the entire Roman world should regard him as their head, just as judges view a king.
This matter is confirmed by the acts of the councils.
Every council, whether held in the East or in Africa, either always had the vicars of the Roman Pontiff presiding or received firmness from his authoritative letters for whatever was decreed.
For example, the council of Nicaea, which is revered by all the Churches of Christ, placed Victor and Vincentius, presbyters of the city of Rome, who were acting on behalf of the Roman Pontiff, first in the bishops' subscriptions.
This was right after Hosius, bishop of the city of Corduba in the province of Spain, who had been sent there by the Roman Pontiff because he was unable to come due to old age.
Thus, the remaining councils always had Roman Pontiffs or their legates in the first place, as vicars of the apostles.
And truly, all the Eastern and Western Churches have always revered the bishop of the city of Rome as the head of the bishops and looked to his judgment.
They endured whatever decisions he made on doubtful matters and obeyed his decree.
Whatever councils were strengthened by his decision remained valid; those he condemned were regarded as nothing and could have no authority.
Here is the translation you requested:
Although our statements are verified by the monuments of the ancient Fathers, we still find it fitting to illustrate our point with a letter from a Roman pope.
When Flavian, the Bishop of Constantinople, condemned Eutyches, the Archimandrite of Constantinople, for his incorrect beliefs about the Incarnation of the Lord, Flavian was himself condemned by a synod held in Ephesus, which went against ecclesiastical rules.
Flavian appealed to the Roman Pope Leo regarding this matter.
Leo then wrote to Emperor Theodosius, requesting a review of the synod and the annulment of the wrongful decisions.
Since this could not be accomplished under Emperor Theodosius due to his death, it was achieved under Emperors Valentinian and Marcian, who succeeded him.
Their letters, sent to the venerable Leo, Bishop of Rome, read as follows, before the Council of Chalcedon, letter 33:
"Victorious Valentinian and Marcian, glorious conquerors, always Augusti, to the most reverend Leo, Archbishop of the glorious city of Rome. We have come to this highest rule by the providence of God, and the most excellent Senate, and all the military.
Therefore, for the revered and catholic religion of the Christian faith, by whose help we trust our power is governed, we believe it right to address your sanctity, possessing the leadership in the episcopate of the divine faith, by sacred letters at the outset, inviting and requesting that for the firmness and state of our empire, your sanctity may pray to the eternal divinity, so that we may have such purpose and desire, that with all impious error removed, through the celebrated synod, with you as the author, the greatest peace may be established among all the bishops of the catholic faith."
Likewise, in a second letter, after the greeting and preface, it is written as follows, letter 34:
"It remains that if it pleases your Beatitude to come to these parts and celebrate the synod, you may deign to do this out of religious affection; your Sanctity will indeed satisfy our desires and decree what is useful for the sacred religion."
If, however, it is too burdensome for you to come to these parts, let your Holiness inform us through your own letters.
So that sacred letters from you may be sent throughout the entire East, and to Thrace and Illyricum, so that all the most holy bishops may gather at a specific location.
And so that they may declare, by their own arrangements, those things that will benefit the religion of Christians and the Catholic faith, as your Holiness will have determined according to ecclesiastical rules.
These letters from the emperors of Rome do not indicate that the Patriarch of Constantinople is considered superior to the Roman Pontiff.
Rather, they show that the Roman Pontiff holds the primacy of the bishops, by whose judgment a synod should be convened, and the matters to be discussed should be arranged by his disposition.
The letters of Emperor Valentinian to his father, Emperor Theodosius the Great, also testify to the dignity and honor that the Roman Pontiff should hold over all bishops.
These are known to be as follows:
"To the Lord Theodosius, most glorious victor and most excellent conqueror, emperor and father, Valentinian, glorious victor and conqueror, always Augustus and son."
When I arrived in the city of Rome to seek divine favor, the next day I visited the basilica of the apostle Peter.
After a venerable night celebrating the apostle's day, the Roman bishop and others gathered from different provinces asked me to write to your gentleness about the faith.
Although it should protect all faithful souls, it is said to be disturbed.
This faith, handed down to us by our ancestors, must be defended with proper devotion and its honor preserved for the blessed apostle Peter in our times.
Thus, the most blessed bishop of Rome, who has been granted the primacy of the priesthood by antiquity, should have the authority to judge matters of faith and priests.
Most sacred Father and venerable Emperor, for this reason, according to the solemnity of the councils, the bishop of Constantinople has also appealed to him through written petitions due to the controversy about the faith.
Galla Placidia, mother of the Emperor, also sent a letter to her son Augustus on this matter, saying:
"It is no small loss that the faith, which had been faithfully kept for so many years by our most sacred father Constantine, the first Christian emperor, has recently been disturbed by the whims of one man. This man is said to have caused hatred and contention at the council in Ephesus, using the presence and fear of soldiers to target the bishop of Constantinople, Flavian. He sent a petition to the apostolic see through those directed to the council by the most reverend bishop of Rome, who, according to the definitions of the Council of Nicaea, are accustomed to be present. Most holy son, venerable Emperor."
With this grace and gentleness, standing against such great crowds, you should ensure that the immaculate truth of the Catholic faith is preserved.
According to the form and definition of the Apostolic See, which we also regard as preeminent, it should remain intact within the priesthood, unharmed in every way by Flavianus, and sent to the judgment of the council and the Apostolic See.
The first to receive the heavenly keys established the leadership of the episcopate.
Therefore, it is fitting for us to show reverence in all things towards this greatest city, which is the mistress of all.
Take greater care, however, that what our generation preserved in ancient times does not diminish under us, and that current examples do not create schisms among bishops and holy Churches.
From this, it is clear that the Roman pontiff was never subject to the Patriarch of Constantinople.
Rather, whenever necessary, he sought the Apostolic See and requested that his case be judged accordingly.
Since the city of Rome is more honorable than all cities of the Roman Empire, and the Roman pontiff holds the primacy of the priesthood over all bishops, it is for this city to be the mistress of all.
Whoever has been the bishop of that city is considered, by ancient constitution, to be the prince of all Churches.
Therefore, with this authority, Leo, the venerable bishop of the city of Rome, wrote to Anatolius, the bishop of Constantinople.
What form of the council should have been held, condemning Nestorius and Eutyches, writing thus:
Although I hope your love is dedicated to every task, so that your efforts may be more effective, it was necessary and convenient to send my brothers, Bishop Licentius and Priest Basil (as we promised), to whom your love may be united, so that nothing concerning the state of the universal Church may be done either doubtfully or sluggishly.
With you residing, to whom we have entrusted the execution of our orders, all things may be done with moderation; so that neither the parts of benevolence nor of justice may be neglected, but the divine judgment may be considered in all things without favoritism.
And after some interjections:
And because the evangelical and apostolic faith defeats all errors, and on one side casts out Nestorius, and on the other side crushes Eutyches and his followers, remember to keep this rule:
That whoever was in that synod, which cannot and does not deserve to bear the name of a synod, in which Dioscorus showed his ill-will and Juvenal his diligence, brotherly peace should be granted to their satisfaction:
So that Eutyches, with his doctrine and his associates, may be condemned with the consecration of anathema by clear professions.
Concerning those who have sinned more gravely in this matter, and for this reason claimed a higher position for themselves in the same unfortunate synod, to burden the simplicity of humble brothers with the prejudices of arrogance:
If perhaps they repent and renounce the defense of their actions, converting to the condemnation of their own error, such satisfaction should be added, which may not seem to be rejected, but should be reserved for the more mature advice of the apostolic see;
So that, after all things have been examined and weighed, it may be judged what should be established according to their recognitions.
And no name of such persons (as we have already written to you) may be recited at the altar in the Church, over which the Lord willed you to preside, until the course of events shows what should be established regarding them.
And after a few words: Therefore, dear brother, strive to faithfully and effectively perform the duties that align with the Church of God, consistently with these brothers whom we have chosen as suitable authorities.
These letters show that the Roman Pontiff presides over the Patriarch of Constantinople, to whom he entrusts the duty of holding the synod.
He prescribes how to carry out each task and indicates what should be reserved for his own judgment.
He defines what he himself should determine.
However, he is not permitted to have the power of judgment alone but is joined by those sent from the Apostolic See to assist in determining matters.
The same blessed Leo, bishop of the holy synod of Chalcedon, also writes to condemn the Second Ephesian Synod, where the venerable Patriarch of Constantinople, Flavian, was condemned not by justice, but by violence.
These are his words, after the greeting: Indeed, my beloved, I had wished, for the love of our fellowship, that all the Lord's priests would persist in one devotion to the Catholic faith, and that no priest would be corrupted by favor or fear of secular matters, or stray from the path of truth.
But because many things often happen that can cause regret, and the mercy of God surpasses the faults of wrongdoers, and punishment is delayed so that correction can take place, we should embrace the plan of the most merciful prince, full of reverence.
He preferred to call your holy brotherhood to destroy the snares of the devil and reform ecclesiastical peace, maintaining the rightful authority and honor of the seat of the most blessed apostle Peter.
He even invited us through his letters to give our opinion to the venerable synod.
Although neither the urgency of the time nor any custom could permit it, nonetheless, in these brothers—that is, Bishops Pacasius and Lucentius, and Priests Boniface and Basil, who were sent by the apostolic seat—let your brotherhood consider me as presiding over the synod.
My presence is not separate from you, as I am now present through my vicars, and I have long supported the preaching of the Catholic faith.
And after other matters: Since we are not unaware that the status of many churches has been disturbed by corrupt rivalries, and many brothers, because they did not accept heresy, have been expelled from their seats and deported into exile, and others have been installed in their place, let the medicine of justice be applied first to these wounds.
No one should be deprived of their own, so that another may use what belongs to others.
If, as we hope, everyone abandons error, no one should lose their honor, but it is appropriate to restore their own with all privileges to those who have labored for the faith.
The decrees of the earlier synod of Ephesus, which the bishop Cyril of holy memory then presided over, remain specifically against Nestorius.
So that the impiety condemned then may not flatter itself in anything, Eutyches is rightly struck down.
For the purity of faith and doctrine, which we proclaim with the same spirit as our holy Fathers, condemns and persecutes both the Nestorian and Eutychian heresies along with their authors.
We certainly notice that the bishop of the Roman seat is not to be subordinated or compared, but rather preferred over the patriarch of Constantinople.
We see that the Chalcedonian synod was convened with his permission, and he chose to preside over it through his legates.
He also provided instructions through his letters on what should be determined about the second synod gathered in Ephesus.
Additionally, he addressed the situation of those who were expelled from their own seats and exiled because of their faith, as well as those who, under threats and terror, issued judgments against the faith and consented to them.
If they chose to return from their error and profess the truth of the faith, he decreed that the first synod of Ephesus, conducted by the blessed Cyril, bishop of Alexandria, should be preserved in every way, condemning both Nestorius and Eutyches who held erroneous views about the incarnation of our Lord Jesus Christ.
From all these actions, it is clear that the Roman pontiff is not only preferred in honor over the bishop of Constantinople, but over all Eastern bishops.
He should have full concern for all bishops and bear special vigilant care for all the Churches.
To further demonstrate the superiority of the Roman bishop over all Eastern bishops, we turn to the letter of the blessed Leo, bishop of Rome, directed to Anastasios, bishop of Thessalonica.
After greeting him, he spoke as follows:
If you had truly considered with reason and weighed justly the responsibilities entrusted to your brotherhood by the authority of the most blessed Apostle Peter, and also what has been entrusted to you by our favor, we could greatly rejoice in the devotion of the care assigned to you.
Just as my predecessors delegated duties to your predecessors, so I, following their example, have delegated my guidance to your affection.
This way, by imitating our gentleness, you might help fulfill the care we owe to all Churches primarily by divine institution, and extend our presence to provinces far from us.
With continuous and timely foresight, it would be easy for you to recognize what you should arrange on your own or reserve for our judgment in each matter.
While you are free to suspend greater and more difficult cases for our decision, neither reason nor necessity requires you to deviate beyond your measure.
You have ample writings from our advisors, in which we have frequently instructed you about the moderation of all actions.
This way, you might encourage the Churches of Christ entrusted to you towards healthy obedience through the exhortation of charity.
After other complaints of this sort, he further says:
While they seek to dominate rather than counsel their subjects, honor pleases, pride inflates, and what was meant for harmony tends towards harm.
That we have to speak this way comes from great pain of mind.
I feel somehow drawn into guilt when I recognize that you have excessively deviated from the rules handed over to you.
If you were careless about your own reputation, you should have at least spared mine; lest what was done solely by your mind might seem to have been done by our judgment.
Your brotherhood should review our pages and all the writings sent to your predecessors by the bishops of the apostolic see.
You will find that what you have presumed has already been addressed by me or my predecessors.
Our brother Atticus, the metropolitan bishop of Old Epirus, came to us with the bishops of his province.
He tearfully complained before your present deacons about the unworthy affliction he endured.
Your deacons, by not countering his mournful complaints, showed us that his claims were credible.
It was also read in your letters, which the same deacons brought to me, that Brother Atticus had come to Thessalonica.
Your letter confirmed the aforementioned complaints.
This revealed that the prefecture of Illyricum and the highest worldly power had been incited to act against the innocent bishop.
With the terrifying execution sent, all public offices were commanded to act, and the priest, falsely accused of no crime, was dragged out from the holy Church's premises.
He was given no respite due to illness or the harshness of winter and was forced to undertake a harsh and perilous journey through pathless snows.
This journey was so arduous and dangerous that some of those accompanying the bishop are said to have perished.
My dear brother, I am greatly astonished and deeply pained that you could have acted so harshly and violently against him.
Especially since, if he deserved such treatment, you should have awaited my response to your inquiries.
You have judged my character well and anticipated how I would respond to maintain priestly harmony.
Therefore, you acted without delay, ensuring you had permission to proceed without needing further instructions from me.
Perhaps you had learned of some wrongdoing by your brother, and the weight of a new accusation against the metropolitan bishop was pressing upon you.
However, you confirm that's not the case by not accusing him of anything.
Even if he had committed something serious and intolerable, it would have been necessary to await our judgment, so you wouldn't make any decisions yourself before knowing what pleased us.
We have entrusted our responsibilities to your care, calling you to share in the concern, not in the fullness of power.
While we are greatly pleased by the things you have managed piously, we are deeply saddened by those that have been improperly handled.
Therefore, after many trials, it is necessary to look more carefully and guard more diligently.
Through the Spirit of charity and peace, all sources of scandal must be removed from the Churches of the Lord, which we have entrusted to you.
Your episcopal authority should prevail in those provinces, but all forms of usurpation must be cut off.
According to the canons of the holy Fathers, established by the Spirit of God and consecrated by the reverence of the whole world, we decree that the metropolitan bishops of each province, to whom we extend the care of your fraternity by our delegation, should retain their ancient dignity.
They must not deviate from established rules, whether by negligence or presumption.
Additionally, all ecclesiastical matters for the Thessalonian bishop should be preserved.
We see that the bishop of Constantinople is not given preference over the Churches of Christ, except within his own diocese.
The Roman pontiff has been entrusted with this responsibility from ancient times, and all the Churches of Christ look to him.
It is his duty to manage ecclesiastical matters and maintain the form of ecclesiastical causes for each province, either established or permitted by the Roman pontiff.
This is approved by the decrees of the Roman pontiffs and is directed to all the Churches of Christ in both the East and the West, observed and respected by all the Churches as if they were laws of ecclesiastical affairs.
But who would allow the patriarch of Constantinople to be preferred over all the Churches of Christ?
Antiquity has not granted him this, nor have any decrees of the elders established it, nor is it upheld by ecclesiastical or human law.
Perhaps the modern emperors of the Greeks, not those of the Romans, think it is permissible for them to do what was not permissible for others, and to dispose of the Roman Church, which they revered as a mother, at their own will.
They seek to change the authority that Christ, the whole Church, and the principality of the entire world conferred on blessed Peter.
Since they see that the city of Rome, which holds the principality of all the Churches, is removed from their empire, and all the West, as well as Africa and almost the whole East except for a few provinces of Europe and Asia and a few islands, has been taken from them.
However, the respect that the bishop of Constantinople should hold, not by his own merit but because it is called the second Rome, is testified by the pragmatic of Emperor Justinian.
This document states: "The Roman Pope sits before all bishops and patriarchs, and after him, the archbishop of the city of Constantinople." Here, the patriarch of Constantinople is neither preferred nor compared to the Roman pope but is placed below.
Consider also that the honor given to this seat does not grant any peak of power.
In the History of Socrates, Book 5, Chapter 8, it is written as follows:
"Then they also preferred a rule, namely the bishops who appointed Nectarius as bishop of Constantinople, that the bishop of Constantinople should have privileges of honor after the Roman pontiff, because it is the new Rome.
But here, privileges of power are not granted to him, which are proven to remain with the Roman pontiff.
So where do the Greek leaders get the authority to prefer the bishop of Constantinople over all the Churches?
No antiquity supports them, no decrees of synods, no pragmatic sanctions of emperors, which even if some were shown, could not obtain the weight of authority without the approval of the Roman pontiff.
The right of power remains endowed by such antiquity, that without his authorization, neither Constantinople nor any city of the East or West can obtain privileges of power, except those which were either granted or confirmed by the Roman pontiff.
Indeed, the power and concern of all Churches remain with him, to grant or arrange whatever has been proven to serve ecclesiastical benefits according to ecclesiastical rules.
This is approved by many monuments of Scriptures, sent throughout all Churches by the Roman pontiff."
Hence, Acacius, bishop of Constantinople, writing to Simplicius, bishop of the city of Rome, says:
"To the holy father Archbishop Simplicius, Acacius.
You continually encourage us, bearing the concern of all Churches according to the Apostle, although we watch and act willingly.
But you demonstrate your concern with divine zeal, more certainly inquiring into the state of the Alexandrian Church, so that for the paternal canons you may undertake the labor, shedding the most pious sweat for these things, as always approved, and the rest."
We know that Acacius, the bishop of Constantinople, acknowledges that the Roman bishop holds responsibility for all the churches, as stated by the Apostle, and that this role has always been assigned to him since ancient times.
By saying this, he does not claim the management of all the churches for himself; he understands that this is far from his duty and does not presume to take on a role that he knows is not his.
When Acacius was found to have acted against church rules, doing something that no valid reason could justify, Felix, the bishop of the holy Catholic Church of the city of Rome, wrote to him as follows:
"You are guilty of many transgressions and have often acted in contempt of the venerable Council of Nicaea, recklessly claiming the rights of other provinces for yourself. You have received into your communion heretics and subversives, and those ordained by heretics, and even those whom you yourself condemned and asked to be condemned by the apostolic see. Not only did you accept them into your communion, but you also made them preside over other churches, which could not even be done with Catholics, and you elevated them to honors they did not deserve."
After writing many things about his transgressions, he concluded with this:
"Therefore, have your portion with those whom you willingly embrace, and by the present sentence, which we have directed to you through the defender of your Church, recognize that you have been deprived of sacerdotal honor and Catholic communion, and also separated from the number of the faithful. Recognize that the title and office of priestly ministry have been taken from you, condemned by the judgment of the Holy Spirit and our apostolic authority, and that you shall no longer be released from the bonds of excommunication."
Does this now prove that the Roman bishop is subject to the patriarch of Constantinople, through whom he is not lightly rebuked for his transgressions and condemned by the sentence of excommunication? It would be immense if we gathered all the evidence that proves the Roman bishop is superior to the bishop of Constantinople.
What we've discussed should be enough to clearly show that the Patriarch of Constantinople should not be placed above all other Churches of Christ.
He should be content with the honor that is rightfully his, without going against the decrees of the Council of Nicaea, which could diminish his own honor.
We've done our best to respond to what you have written to us.
If these words are agreeable, we give thanks to God.
If not, we await your correction.