Saint Pacian's Three Letters to Sympronian the Novatian.
Letter One On the Catholic Name
Pacianus to his brother Sympronian, greetings.
If it is not a carnal intention but, as I believe, a spiritual calling that prompts you to examine the faith of Catholic truth from us, then you should have indicated which different beliefs you were following.
You seem to have started far from the source and origin of the principal Church, not holding to its fountain and beginning.
You should have revealed what specifically caused you to break from the unity of our body.
For those parts that require healing need to be exposed.
Now, with the matter hidden, we do not see which parts of us most need curing.
So many heresies have arisen from the Christian head that the volume of their names is immense.
For instance, to omit the heretics among the Jews, like Dositheus the Samaritan, the Sadducees, and the Pharisees: it would be too long to count how many emerged during the times of the apostles: Simon Magus, Menander, Nicolaus, and others whom obscure fame has concealed.
What about later times with Ebion, Apelles, Marcion, Valentinus, and Cerdon: and not long after them, the Cataphrygians and Novatians, not to mention the more recent swarms?
So who should I first refute in writing?
The paper will not hold all their names if you wish to list them.
Except that in your writings, which condemn repentance everywhere, you declare yourself aligned with the Phrygians.
But even among these, their error is so manifold and diverse that it is not just one thing in them that opposes repentance, but rather, like the many-headed Hydra, several aspects must be cut off.
If your intention is not carnal but a spiritual calling, Lord, and you seek to examine our faith in the Catholic truth, you should have clearly indicated which teachings you intend to follow and how they differ.
You, who began far from the source and did not adhere to the origins of the main Church, should have revealed the primary cause that divided our unity.
For those parts that need healing must be exposed.
Now, with the letters, so to speak, closed, we do not see which parts need our special attention.
So many heresies have emerged from the Christian faith that the list of their names is immense.
To set aside the heretics of the Jews: Dositheus the Samaritan, the Sadducees, and the Pharisees.
It would take too long to count how many arose during the apostles' times: Simon Magus, Menander, Nicolaus, and others whom history has obscured.
What about later times with Ebion, Apelles, Marcion, Valentinus, and Cerdon?
And soon after them, the Cataphrygians and Novatians, not to mention newer groups?
Who then should I refute first by letter?
The names of all would not fit on a single page if you wish.
Except that in your writings, condemning repentance everywhere, you declare agreement with the Phrygians.
But in those very writings, dear Lord, the error is so varied and diverse that it is not just one thing against repentance, but many issues like the Hydra's heads that must be addressed.
First, they rely on many authors.
For I think even the Greek Blastus is among them: Theodotus and Praxeas also taught your people at some time.
Those notable Phrygians, who falsely claim to be inspired by Leucius, boast that they were instructed by Proculus.
Following Montanus, Maximilla, and Priscilla, they stirred up many controversies about the Paschal day, the Paraclete, the apostles, and the prophets.
And many other issues, like this about the Catholic name and the forgiveness of repentance.
Therefore, if we want to discuss all these matters, we need your full attention.
Even if I can't fully instruct you on these topics, we must still serve those seeking knowledge in any way possible.
To inform you, we will briefly talk about the subjects you've deemed important enough to write about.
If you want to understand our beliefs more fully, you need to speak more plainly about your own.
This way, by asking clearly, you won't leave us wondering whether you're questioning or provoking us.
As for the current matters, first of all, I ask you not to give authority to error.
You mentioned that no one in the entire world could refute or persuade you against your beliefs.
Even if we are unskilled, the Spirit of God is most skilled.
And even if we are unfaithful, God is faithful, who cannot deny Himself.
Second Timothy, Chapter 2, Verse 13.
Moreover, for a long time, it was not permitted to contend with the priests of God.
The Apostle says, "We have no such custom, nor does the Church of God." First Corinthians, Chapter 11, Verse 16.
After a single admonition, as you know, a contentious person should be avoided. Titus, Chapter 3, Verse 10.
But who can persuade someone against their will? Therefore, brother, it is your fault, not theirs, if no one has persuaded you of what is best. Even today, you have the power to disregard our writings if you prefer to reject them rather than accept them.
Furthermore, many resisted the Lord Himself and His apostles. The truth cannot persuade anyone unless they agree with it through their own faith. So, my lord, we did not write with the confidence that we could persuade a resistant person, but with the faith that we would not deny the path to good peace to one who is willing.
If this is in your mind and heart, there is no struggle with the name Catholic. If our people attain this through God, there is no need to question, with divine authority preceding. If through man, when usurped, it must be exposed. If the name is good, it does not receive hatred. If bad, it lacks envy.
First, they rely on many authors:
I believe that even the Greek Blastus is among them; Theodotus and Praxeas also once taught your people.
Notable Phrygians, who claim to be inspired by Leucius and instructed by Proculus,:
Following Montanus, Maximilla, and Priscilla, they have stirred up many controversies about the Passover day, the Paraclete, the apostles, and the prophets.
And many other issues, like the Catholic name and the forgiveness of repentance.
Therefore, if we want to examine all these things, a teachable presence is needed:
If I didn't sufficiently instruct you on these matters you wrote about, I will briefly address them for your sake because it is necessary to serve those who wonder in any way possible.
If you wish to know more fully about our side, you must openly confess your own; so that by consulting unclearly, you do not make us unsure whether you are questioning or provoking.
Regarding the present matters, first of all, I ask you not to lend authority to error for the reason you mentioned, that throughout the whole world there is no one who could refute you or persuade you otherwise.
For even if we are unskilled, the Spirit of God is most skilled; and if we are unfaithful, God is faithful, who cannot deny himself Second Timothy, 2:13.
Furthermore, it is not allowed to contend long against the priests of God.
The Apostle says, we do not have such a custom, nor does the Church of God First Corinthians, 11:16.
After one correction Titus, 3:10, as you know, the contentious person is avoided.
But who can persuade someone who is unwilling?
Therefore, brother, it is your fault, not theirs, if no one persuaded you of what was best.
Even today, it is within your power to disregard our writings if you prefer to defeat them rather than approve them.
However, many resisted the Lord himself and his apostles; and the truth could not persuade anyone unless they agreed with it by their own faith.
Therefore, Lord, we haven't written with the confidence to persuade someone who resists.
Instead, we've written with faith that we shouldn't deny access to those seeking peace.
If this aligns with your mind and heart, there will be no struggle over the Catholic name.
For if our people achieve this through God, there's no need to question, given divine authority.
If through man, whenever it’s usurped, it should be exposed.
If the name is good, it won’t receive hatred; if bad, it lacks envy.
I hear that the Novatians are named after Novatus or Novatian.
However, I don’t accuse the name, but the sect itself.
Similarly, no one has accused Montanus or the Phrygians over their name.
You might say, under the apostles, no one was called Catholic.
So be it, let that be allowed.
When heresies arose after the apostles, trying to tear and divide God's dove and queen into parts with various names, didn’t the apostolic people demand a name to distinguish the unity of the uncorrupted people so that the pure virgin of God wouldn’t be torn apart by the errors of some members?
Wasn't it fitting to mark the principal head with its own name?
Suppose I entered a populous city today and found Marcionites, Apollinarians, Cataphrygians, Novatians, and others who called themselves Christians.
How would I recognize the congregation of my people if it weren’t called Catholic?
Come on, who has granted such names to the other peoples?
Why do so many cities and nations have their own descriptions?
The very one who questions the Catholic name wouldn’t know the reason for his own name if I asked where it was handed down to him.
Certainly, it wasn’t borrowed from man, as it has endured for so many centuries.
This Catholic name doesn’t sound like Marcion, Apelles, or Montanus, nor does it take heretics as its authors.
The Holy Spirit, whom God sent from heaven as a teacher and comforter to the apostles, has taught many of us; reason, as Paul says, and honesty, and, as he says, nature itself have taught many things.
What?
Do we have little authority from the apostolic men, little from the first priests, little from the most blessed martyr and teacher Cyprian?
Do we want to teach the teacher?
Are we wiser than him, and are we driven by the spirit of the flesh against him, whom the noble blood and the crown of the most illustrious passion of the eternal God have produced as a witness?
What about all those priests from different regions, whom the same peace united with Cyprian throughout the entire world?
What about all those aged bishops, all those martyrs, all those confessors?
Come on.
If they were not suitable authors by claiming this name, will we be suitable by denying it?
Will our authority be followed by the fathers, and will the antiquity of the saints yield to be corrected?
Will the times, now decaying with vices, erase the canons of apostolic antiquity?
I hear Novatians being called after Novatus or Novatian:
however, I do not accuse the sect by their name;
nor did anyone object to the name of Montanus or the Phrygians.
But you will say, under the apostles, no one was called Catholic.
Let it be so, allow that.
When heresies arose after the apostles and tried to tear and divide the dove of God and the queen into parts under different names:
didn't the apostolic flock ask for its own name to distinguish the unity of the uncorrupted people, so that the virgin of God would not be torn apart by the error of some through the members?
Wasn't it fitting for the principal head to be marked with its own name?
Suppose I entered a populous city today and found Marcionites, Apollinarians, Cataphrygians, Novatians, and others of that kind, who called themselves Christians:
by what name would I recognize the congregation of my people if it were not called Catholic?
Come on, who gave such names to the other peoples?
Why does each city, each nation have its own description?
The one who questions the Catholic name would not know the reason for his own name if I asked from where it was handed down to me.
Certainly, it was not borrowed from a man, that which has not fallen through so many ages.
The name Catholic does not sound like Marcion, nor Apelles, nor Montanus, nor does it take heretical authors.
The Holy Spirit has taught us many things, whom God sent from heaven to the apostles as a comforter and teacher;
much reason, as Paul says, and honesty, and, as he says, nature itself.
What then?
Do we give little authority to the apostolic men, the first priests, or the blessed martyr and teacher Cyprian?
Do we want to teach the teacher?
Are we wiser than he is?
Are we driven by worldly desires against him, whom noble blood and the crown of a great passion have made a witness of the eternal God?
What about all the priests across different places, united in peace with Cyprian throughout the world?
What about the elderly bishops, the martyrs, the confessors?
Come on.
If they were not suitable authorities by claiming this name, will we be suitable by denying it?
Will our authority surpass that of the fathers?
Will we correct the traditions of the saints?
Will our current, vice-ridden times erase the canons of apostolic antiquity?
But do not be troubled, brother: Christian is my name, Catholic is my surname.
The former calls me; the latter defines me.
By this, I am approved; by that, I am identified.
If the meaning of the word Catholic must finally be given and explained from Greek to Roman: Catholic means one, or as the more learned believe, obedience to all, namely to the commandments of God.
Hence the Apostle: If you are obedient in all things (Second Corinthians 2:9).
And again: For as by the disobedience of one many were made sinners, so by the obedience of one, many will be made righteous (Romans 5:19).
Therefore, he who is Catholic is also obedient to the righteous.
He who is obedient is also a Christian: thus, a Catholic is a Christian.
Therefore, our people are separated from heretics by the name Catholic.
Additionally, if Catholic means one everywhere, as the superior ones think, David indicates the same saying: The queen stood in a golden vestment and adorned (Psalms 45:10), that is, one in all.
And in the Song of Songs, the Groom says: My dove is one, my perfect one, she is the only one of her mother, she is the chosen one of her who bore her (Song of Solomon 6:8).
And again: Virgins will be brought to the king after her (Psalms 45:15).
And still: Young maidens without number (Song of Solomon 6:7).
Therefore, in all things one, and one above all.
But don't worry, brother: Christian is my name, and Catholic is my surname.
The first identifies me; the second describes me.
This is how I am known, and that is how I am signified.
If we need to explain the meaning of the word Catholic and translate it from Greek into Latin: Catholic means 'universal', or, as the more educated think, 'obedient to all God's commandments.
' Hence the Apostle says, "If you are obedient in everything" Second Corinthians 2:9. And again: "For just as through the disobedience of one man many were made sinners, so also through the obedience of one man many will be made righteous" Romans 5:19.
Therefore, a Catholic is also obedient to righteousness. Whoever is obedient is also a Christian: thus, a Catholic is a Christian. This is why our people are distinguished from heretics by this name, Catholic: and if Catholic means 'one everywhere,' as the elders think, David also indicates this when he says, "The queen stood in gold from Ophir" Psalm 45:9, that is, one in all things.
In the Song of Songs, the Bridegroom says: "My dove, my perfect one, is unique, the only daughter of her mother, chosen by the one who bore her" Song of Solomon 6:9. And again: "They will be led to the king, the virgins, her companions who follow her" Psalm 45:14.
And also: "The maidens, without number" Song of Solomon 6:8. Therefore, she is one in all things and one above all. If you seek the reason for the name, it is clear.
As for repentance, may God grant that it is never necessary for the faithful; may no one fall into the pit of death after the help of the holy font: nor should priests be forced to offer late consolations or teach them, lest they open the way to sin while comforting the sinner with remedies. But we reveal this indulgence of our God to the wretched, not to the blessed, not before sin, but after sins are revealed: and we announce healing not to the healthy, but to the sick.
If spiritual evils have no power over the baptized, then neither does the deceit of that serpent which first led humanity astray and imposed so many titles of damnation on its descendants.
If it has retreated from the world, if we have already begun to reign, if no sin sneaks into our eyes, hands, or minds, then let this gift of God be discarded.
Let help be rejected, let no confession, no groans be heard; let proud justice scorn every remedy.
But if the Lord has provided this for His people, if He has granted rewards to those who stand and remedies to those who fall, then stop accusing divine mercy.
Stop erasing so many titles of heavenly clemency with rigorous objections, or denying the Lord’s free gifts with unyielding harshness.
We do not grant these things from our own resources.
Turn to me, says the Lord, along with fasting, weeping, and mourning; tear your hearts.
Joel 2:12.
And again: Let the wicked forsake his ways, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and let him return to the Lord, and He will have mercy on him.
Isaiah 55:7.
Likewise, the Prophet cries out in this way: Because God is gracious, and merciful, patient, and who relents from sending calamity.
Joel 2:13.
Does the serpent have such lasting venom, and Christ does not have a remedy?
The devil kills in the world, and Christ cannot help here?
Certainly, let it be painful to sin, but let it not be painful to repent.
Let it be shameful to be in danger, but not shameful to be delivered.
Who would take away a plank from a shipwrecked person to prevent their escape?
Who would begrudge the healing of wounds?
Does not David say: I drench my bed with my tears every night; I flood my couch with weeping.
Psalm 6:6.
And again: I acknowledge my sin; I did not cover up my iniquity.
Psalm 32:5.
And further: I said, "I will confess my transgressions to the Lord," and you forgave the guilt of my sin.
Did not the prophet respond to David after his guilt of murder and adultery, for Bathsheba’s repentance: The Lord has taken away your sin.
Second Samuel 12:13.
Did not confession free the Babylonian king after so many crimes of idolatry?
And what does the Lord say: "Does not one who falls get up, and the one who turns away come back?" (Jeremiah 8:4).
What do those many examples of the Lord's arguments respond to?
The woman who finds the lost coin and rejoices; the shepherd who brings back the wandering sheep; the father who warmly welcomes his returning son, after he squandered all his wealth and lived with prostitutes and sinners, and who scolds the jealous brother by showing reason?
Saying, "This son of mine was dead and has come back to life; he was lost and is found" (Luke 15:32).
What about the man injured on the road, ignored by the Levite and the priest?
Doesn’t he get healed?
Consider what the Spirit says to the churches (Revelation 2):
He accuses the Ephesians of abandoned love; charges the Thyatirans with adultery; criticizes the Sardians for halting their work, and the Pergamenes for teaching different doctrines; rebukes the Laodiceans for their wealth; and yet invites all to repentance with satisfaction.
What does the Apostle say to the Corinthians: "Lest, when I come, I should mourn over many of those who have sinned before and have not repented of the uncleanness, fornication, and lewdness which they have practiced" (Second Corinthians 12:21).
And again to the Galatians: "If anyone is caught in any transgression" (Galatians 6:1); that is, in any, you who are spiritual should restore such a one in a spirit of gentleness, watching yourself lest you too be tempted.
Does the head of the household in a large house keep only silver and gold vessels?
Does he not also honor clay and wooden ones, and some that are repaired and restored?
Now I rejoice, says the Apostle, because you were made sorrowful to repentance (Second Corinthians 7:9).
And again: "For godly sorrow produces repentance leading to salvation, not to be regretted" (Second Corinthians 7:10).
If you seek the reason for the name, it is apparent.
As for repentance, may God grant that it is not necessary for any of the faithful; may no one after the help of the sacred font fall into the pit of death; nor should priests be forced to offer late consolations or teach them, lest they open the way to sin while they soothe the sinner with remedies.
We reveal God's mercy not to the blessed, but to the wretched, not before sin, but to expose sins.
We announce medicine not to the healthy, but to those who are ill.
If spiritual wickedness has no power over the baptized, if the serpent's deceit—which first overthrew man and marked his descendants with so many titles of damnation—can do nothing, if it has retreated from the world, if we have already begun to reign, if no crime enters our eyes, hands, or minds, then let this gift of God be rejected, let the help be repelled, let no confession, no groans be heard.
Let proud justice despise every remedy.
But if the Lord has provided these things for His own; if He has given rewards to those who stand and remedies to those who fall, stop accusing divine mercy or erasing the many titles of heavenly clemency by the objection of severity, or prohibiting the free gifts of the Lord with unyielding harshness.
We do not bestow these from our own.
"Turn to me," says the Lord, "with fasting and weeping and mourning, and rend your hearts" (Joel 2:12).
And again: "Let the wicked forsake their ways and the unrighteous their thoughts, and let them turn to the Lord, and they will receive mercy" (Isaiah 45:7).
Similarly, the Prophet cries out: "For God is gracious and merciful, slow to anger and abounding in steadfast love, and relents from sending calamity" (Joel 2:13).
Does the serpent have such enduring venom, and Christ not have medicine?
Does the devil kill in the world, and Christ cannot help here?
Certainly, let it be painful to sin, but not painful to repent.
Let it be shameful to be in danger, but not shameful to be saved.
Who would snatch a plank from a shipwreck survivor to prevent them from escaping?
Who would begrudge healing wounds?
Does not David say, "Every night I flood my bed with tears; I drench my couch with weeping" (Psalm 6:6)?
And again, "I acknowledge my sin to you and did not cover up my iniquity" (Psalm 32:5).
And still, "I said, 'I will confess my transgressions to the Lord,' and you forgave the guilt of my sin" (Psalm 32:5).
Didn't the prophet respond after David was guilty of murder and adultery, and repented for Bathsheba: "The Lord has taken away your sin" 2 Samuel 12:13?
Didn't repentance free the Babylonian king after so many acts of idolatry condemned him? And what does the Lord mean when He says: "Doesn't the one who falls rise again, and the one who turns away return" Jeremiah 8:4?
What do all those parables of the Lord mean? That the woman finds the lost coin and rejoices; that the shepherd brings back the wandering sheep; that the father lovingly meets the returning son after he squandered all his wealth with prostitutes and sinners, and reproves the envious brother? The father says, "This son of mine was dead and is alive again; he was lost and is found" Luke 15:32.
What about the man who was wounded on the road, and passed by the Levite and the priest? Isn't he healed?
Consider what the Spirit says to the churches: He accuses the Ephesians of abandoned love; charges the Thyatirans with adultery; rebukes the Sardians for their incomplete works, the Pergamenes for teaching false doctrines; scorches the Laodiceans for their wealth; yet invites all to repentance through atonement.
What does the Apostle say to the Corinthians? "I fear that when I come, I may grieve over many who have sinned earlier and have not repented of the impurity, sexual immorality, and debauchery they have committed" 2 Corinthians 12:21.
And again to the Galatians? "If someone is caught in a sin, you who live by the Spirit should restore that person gently, but watch yourselves, or you also may be tempted" Galatians 6:1.
Does the master of a great house keep only silver and gold vessels? Doesn't he also keep vessels of clay and wood, some for special purposes and some for common use?
Now I rejoice, says the Apostle, not because you were made sorrowful, but because your sorrow led you to repentance 2 Corinthians 7:9. And again: "Godly sorrow brings repentance that leads to salvation and leaves no regret" 2 Corinthians 7:10.
But one could not repent. No one commands labor without reward: "The worker is worthy of his wages" Matthew 10:10; Luke 10:7.
God would never threaten someone who repents unless He intended to forgive them.
You might say, "Only God can do this." That's true: but what He does through His priests is still His power. What did He mean when He told the Apostles:
"Whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven" (Matthew 16:19; John 20:23)?
Why would He say this if it weren't allowed for people to bind and loose?
Is this permission only for the Apostles?
If only they can baptize, give the Holy Spirit, and cleanse the sins of the nations, because all this was commanded only to the Apostles, then what about us?
If in one place the power to release bonds and perform the sacraments is given, either everything has been passed down to us through the example and power of the Apostles, or none of it has been relaxed from the decrees.
"I laid the foundation," he says, "and someone else builds on it" (First Corinthians 3:10).
So, we build on what the doctrine of the Apostles has established.
Finally, bishops are also called Apostles, as Paul explains about Epaphroditus:
"My brother and coworker; your apostle" (Philippians 2:25).
Therefore, if the power of baptism and chrism, and the greater and long-standing gifts come down to bishops, they also have the right to bind and loose.
Even if we claim this right recklessly because of our sins, God will not deny it to those who hold the seat of the Apostles and the saints.
He has even granted bishops the name of His Only Son.
But it was not allowed to repent.
No one orders labor without a reward: "The worker deserves his wages" (Matthew 10:10; Luke 10:7).
God would never threaten someone who repents unless He intended to forgive them.
You might say, "Only God can do this." That's true: but what He does through His priests is still His power. What did He mean when He told the Apostles:
"Whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven" (Matthew 16:19; John 20:23)?
Why would He say this if it weren't allowed for people to bind and loose?
Is this only allowed for the Apostles?
Then is it also only allowed for them to baptize, give the Holy Spirit, and cleanse the sins of the nations?
Because all of this was commanded to no one else but the Apostles.
But if in one place, both the loosening of bonds and the power of the sacrament are given; either all of it is derived to us from the form and power of the Apostles, or none of it is released from the decrees.
"I, Paul, laid the foundation, and another builds on it,"
First Corinthians 3:10.
Therefore, we build on what the Apostles' teaching has founded. Moreover, bishops are also called Apostles, as Paul explains about Epaphroditus:
"My brother and fellow worker, but your apostle"
Philippians 2:25.
If the authority of baptism and chrism, and even greater gifts, have descended to the bishops; then the right to bind and to loose has also been given. Even if we claim it rashly because of our sins, God will still not deny it to those who hold the seat of the Apostles and saints; He even granted them the name of His Only Son.
I would write more, brother, if I were not pressed by the urgency of the returning messenger, and if I did not wish to save more detailed writings either for you in person or to confess the whole purpose. No one should despise a bishop because of human considerations. Let us remember that the Apostle Peter called our Lord a bishop:
"But now you have returned to the Shepherd and Bishop of your souls"
First Peter 2:25.
What will be denied to a bishop, in whom the name of God works? He will indeed give an account if he has done anything wrong, or judged corruptly and impiously. Nor is God prejudiced against rescinding the works of a wicked builder: meanwhile, if the administration is pious, it continues as an aid to God's works. Behold, the Apostle writes to the laypeople:
"If you forgive anyone, I do too. And what I have forgiven, if there was anything to forgive, I have forgiven in the sight of Christ for your sake, so that Satan might not outwit us; for we are not unaware of his schemes"
Second Corinthians 2:10-11.
If the Apostle says he has forgiven what the laypeople have forgiven, how will what a bishop has done be rejected?
So, neither baptism, forgiveness of sins, nor the renewal of the body has been granted to his holy authority because nothing has been commanded by his own usurpation.
All of it has flowed from apostolic authority.
I know, brother, that this very pardon for repentance is not given to everyone everywhere, nor is it relaxed before either an interpretation of divine will or a visitation has occurred.
With great weight and balance, after many groans, shedding of tears, and the prayers of the whole church, true repentance is not denied pardon, so that no one prejudges Christ, who will judge.
If you write more clearly what you think, brother, you will be more fully instructed.
I would write more, brother, if I were not pressed by the speed of the boy returning, and I would save more abundant things for you, either in your presence or for confessing the whole purpose.
No one should despise a bishop because of human considerations.
Let us remember that the Apostle Peter called our Lord a Bishop:
But now you have returned to the shepherd and overseer of your souls First Peter 2:25.
What will be denied to a bishop, in whom the name of God operates?
He will indeed give an account if he has done anything wrong or judged corruptly and impiously.
Nor is God prejudiced, so that he might not undo the works of a wicked builder.
Meanwhile, if that administration is pious, it continues to assist in the works of God.
See, the Apostle writes to the laity: If you forgive anyone, I also forgive them.
And what I have forgiven—if there was anything to forgive—I have forgiven in the sight of Christ for your sake, in order that Satan might not outwit us; for we are not unaware of his schemes Second Corinthians 2:10-11.
So if what the laity forgives, the Apostle says he has forgiven; how will what a bishop does be rejected?
So, neither baptism, forgiveness of sins, nor the renewal of the body has been granted to his holy authority because nothing has been commanded by his own usurpation.
All of it has flowed from apostolic authority.
I know, brother, that this very pardon for repentance is not given to everyone everywhere, nor is it relaxed before either an interpretation of divine will or a visitation has occurred.
With deep reflection and heavy hearts, after many sighs and tears, and the prayers of the entire church, true repentance cannot be denied.
No one should judge before Christ's judgment.
If you express your thoughts more clearly, brother, you will gain better understanding.
Letter TwoAbout Sympronian's letters.
Pacianus the bishop sends greetings to his brother Sympronian. I.
In this lengthy discussion, I will be as brief as possible.
I won't repay you, brother, with malice for your hidden verbal attacks disguised as good questions.
We are commanded to pray for those who persecute us and to bless those who curse us (Matthew 5:44)
Deceit is like a fox, while force is like a lion: both are very uncharacteristic of a person; but deceit is more deserving of hatred.
When you think you can cause more harm, you ask questions as if you are ignorant; when you believe you are teaching, you pretend to be learning.
The old Pharisees called the Lord "Rabbi" when they posed riddles from the law; they called Him "Master" when they claimed all authority for themselves. Whatever you do, brother, you will learn everything from me plainly. I prefer to be understood as unskilled rather than malicious; I prefer to be judged as foolish rather than cunning.
So, before I explain the reasoning behind our faith—which is what you're asking about—let me address a few points from your letter that you prioritized.
You mentioned that my previous letters have restored you, yet you immediately add that I responded with bitterness.
If bitter things restore, I wonder what sweet things would do; perhaps, like in medicinal drinks, the bitter tends to heal more than the sweet.
But I ask you to reread my letters to see if they contained any bitterness, pride, or unpleasantness.
You say I mentioned many heresies that no one asked about.
Well, what does it matter to you if you were not a heretic?
Since you questioned our faith and said you wanted to be taught, I noted that ignorance has many causes and asked you to clarify which one applies to you, so I wouldn't have to cover too many points.
I responded calmly about the Catholic name, explaining that it doesn't matter what someone else is called.
And if you seek the significance of the name—whether it is something marvelous, unique, or above all—or, as I haven't said before, related to the Christian people, know that it wasn't given to us to fade away.
Indeed, I am glad that although you prefer others, you still agree with us about the name.
If you denied it, nature would proclaim it.
And if you still have doubts, let's remain silent.
Whatever we are called, we will be, as shown by the name's enduring history.
But if you persistently demand to know, be cautious of the virtuous man's response: "Why do you ask my name? It is wonderful" (Judges 13:18).
You added that it shouldn't matter where the Catholic name comes from, just as the Valentinians are not blamed for being named after Valentinus, nor the Phrygians after Phrygia, nor the Novatians after Novatian.
You mentioned that my previous letters have restored you, yet you immediately add that I responded with bitterness.
If bitter things restore, I wonder what sweet things would do; perhaps, like in medicinal drinks, the bitter tends to heal more than the sweet.
But please, review my letters to see if they contain any bitterness or if I responded with pride or harshness.
You say that I mentioned several heresies that no one had asked about.
Well then, what does it matter to you if you were not a heretic?
When you raised questions about our faith and said you wanted to be taught, I explained that ignorance has many causes, and I asked you to reveal which one affected you the most, so I wouldn't be overwhelmed by addressing too many issues.
I responded calmly about the Catholic name.
I said that it doesn’t matter to others what someone is called.
And if you demanded the meaning of the name, whatever it is—whether it’s something wonderful, or one among all, or one above all, or what I hadn’t mentioned before—the son of the king, meaning the Christian people.
Surely, it wasn’t given to us for it to fade over many centuries.
And indeed, I am glad that even though you have preferred others, you also agree with us about the name.
What if you had denied it?
Nature would have cried out.
Or if you still have doubts, let’s keep quiet.
Both of us will be whatever we are called, with the age of the name as our witness.
However, if you persist obstinately, be careful lest that virtuous man cries out to you: Why do you ask my name?
It is wonderful.
Judges 13:18.
Then you added that the origin of the name Catholic shouldn’t be considered; because neither should the Valentinians be judged if they are named after Valentinus, nor the Phrygians if after Phrygia, nor the Novatians if after Novatian.
Here, you become seriously agitated, and as if pricked by a thorn, you rise up.
In your anger, you shout: Does it harm the holy man Cyprian that his people are called apostates, or Capitoline, or Syndrean?
You insult, and behold, I am unmoved.
Were we ever called any of these names?
Ask the world, brother, and all the years in their order; whether this name has stuck to us, or whether Cyprian’s people have been called anything other than Catholic.
I have never heard any of these names.
Now see, if someone could be called by a name they don’t know was given to them.
So what?
These are curses, not names; and curses from the angry, curses from the insolent.
I can call you by as many names as I want, if anger were permissible.
You call Cyprian holy, but his people apostates? How so?
If the beginning is holy, so is the whole batch of dough; and if the root is holy, so are the branches Romans 11:16.
Am I the apostate, or is it Novatus?
Novatus, who betrayed his father, abandoned the Church, and forsook his wife's childbirth?
Am I the apostate, or is it Novatian, who was made a bishop in absentia by a letter, and whose consecration was without ceremony, taking his seat on linen cloth?
But let these things be discussed later: for now, tell me what you are called.
Do you deny that Novatians are named after Novatian?
Whatever name you choose, that one will always stick.
Search through all the annals if you wish, and trust the centuries: you will answer "Christian."
When I inquire about the sect, you will not deny Novatian.
Yet I do not condemn the name of your Novatian, which you so often avoid with circumlocutions and hidden meanings.
Admit it simply: there is no crime in the name.
Why do you hide when asked so often? Why are you ashamed of the name?
When you first wrote, I thought you were a Cataphrygian.
Do you now confess in your second letter? Do you envy my name and avoid your own?
See who is ashamed of what he is called.
Here you are greatly agitated, as if pricked by a thorn; thus, in anger, you exclaim: Does it harm holy Cyprian that his people bear the name apostate, or Capitoline, or Syndrean?
You revile me, but I am not moved.
Have we been called any of these names? Ask the world, brother, and all the years in order; did this name stick to us, or was Cyprian's people ever called anything but Catholic?
I have never heard any of these names.
Now see if anyone could be called by a name they did not know was given to them. So what then? These are insults, not names; and insults from the angry, insults from the petulant.
I too can call you many names if I am allowed to be angry.
You call Cyprian holy, but his people apostates? How so?
If the beginning is holy, so is the whole batch of dough; and if the root is holy, so are the branches Romans 11:16.
Am I the apostate, or is it Novatus? Novatus, who betrayed his father, abandoned the Church, and forsook his wife's childbirth?
Am I a renegade or a Novatian, who, though absent, was made a bishop by letter and received the bishop's seat without any consecration?
But let’s leave that for later.
For now, you tell me what you are called.
Do you deny being called Novatians after Novatian?
Whatever name you choose, it will always stick.
Look through all the annals, if you will, and trust history: you will answer 'Christian.
' When I inquire about the sect, you won’t deny being Novatian.
Yet I don’t criticize the name of your Novatian, which you obscure with circumlocution and conceal in some hidden place.
Admit it simply: there’s no crime in the name.
Why do you hide when asked so often?
Why are you ashamed of the name?
When you first wrote, I thought you were a Cataphrygian.
Do you admit it in your second letter?
You envy my name and avoid yours?
See what shame causes, as it shuns what it is called.
What do you criticize and pursue?
Are we here for rhetoric, or is there some craft to be handled, or should I expound on verses of Virgil?
When I named numerous heretics, I added: 'And those whom obscure fame hides.
' And how do you think this comes from a verse of Virgil if you didn’t know Virgil at all?
But I deny that I quoted the verse in order.
For I said: 'Those whom obscure fame hides;' as is customary in human speech, to say something previously said.
But you repeated the verse in its proper order and structure.
Did you love Virgil so much that you thought it wrong if you broke his verse?
And yet, I learned it from childhood.
Is it surprising if I stumbled upon what I knew?
In you, brother, there’s such effort that you now read what you once blushed to read from others?
Should you accuse a Latin speaker for speaking Latin, as much as a Greek for speaking Greek, a Parthian for speaking Parthian, a Phoenician for speaking Phoenician?
The Medes, Egyptians, and Hebrews have their own language according to the abundance of the Lord, who modulated it into 120 tongues.
A bishop quoted a poetic verse.
What about the Apostle Paul?
Does he blush when he both quotes and approves that Athenian verse?
In the Acts of the Apostles, it says:
Some of your own poets have said:
For we are also his offspring.
Since we are God's offspring
(Acts 17:28, 29)
.
And again, he said to Titus:
One of them, a prophet of their own, said,
'Cretans are always liars, evil beasts, lazy gluttons'
(Titus 1:12, 13)
.
And he adds:
This testimony is true.
We sin by example:
We are not rhetoricians, but we believe in any voice that comes as the abundance of God.
Rome, Egypt, Athens, Thrace, Arabs, Spain confess God; the Holy Spirit understands all languages.
Why do you say,
"I will polish your writings with lively cedar against the decayed enemies of the Muses"?
Which Muses, I pray, are you talking about?
Are they the ones who invented letters and wrote pages that moths will pursue?
Tell me, brother, did the Muses discover letters?
Is not everything through the Lord, and everything from God?
Besides those 120 languages, was there another of the Muses?
Hesiod lied about that on Helicon, but the Athenians, as the Apostle said, did nothing but talk
(Acts 17:21)
.
We, as the Apostle testifies
(First Corinthians 14:10, 18)
,
retain all kinds of voices and all kinds of languages inspired by God.
However, I forgive you, brother, if you presume something from your author and combine the philosophy of Novatian, through which he suffered shipwreck in religion, with the authority of Hesiod.
Nevertheless, you should have remembered the Apostle who said:
Beware lest anyone cheat you through philosophy and empty deceit
(Colossians 2:8)
.
What are you criticizing and doing?
Are we coming to a rhetorician, or is it an art to be handled, or am I explaining verses of Virgil?
When I mentioned several heretics, I added:
And those whom obscure fame hides.
And how do you think this was taken from a verse of Virgil if you did not know Virgil at all?
But I deny it; I did not place the verse in order.
For I said:
Those whom obscure fame hides;
as it is customary for speakers to say something from the abundance of human speech that has been said before.
But you repeated the verse in its order and structure.
You loved Virgil so much that you thought it would not be right if you broke his verse?
I learned this from a young age. Is it any wonder I fell into what I knew?
Brother, you put in so much effort, only to now read what you once blushed to read from others?
If you were educated in Latin and speak Latin, should you not criticize just as you would a Greek speaking Greek, a Parthian speaking Parthian, or a Punic speaking Punic?
Medes, Egyptians, Hebrews all have their own languages, according to the abundance of the Lord, who expressed it in one hundred and twenty tongues.
The bishop quoted a poetic verse.
What about the Apostle Paul?
Did he blush when he recited and approved that Athenian verse?
For in the Acts of the Apostles, it is written: "Some of your own poets have said, 'For we are indeed his offspring.'" So being God's offspring (Acts 17:28, 29).
And he also said to Titus: "One of themselves, a prophet of their own, said, 'Cretans are always liars, evil beasts, lazy gluttons.'" (Titus 1:12, 13).
And he adds: "This testimony is true."
So we sin by example: we are not rhetoricians, but we believe in whatever voice, the abundance of God.
Latium, Egypt, Athens, Thrace, Arabs, Spaniards all confess God; the Holy Spirit understands all languages.
Why do you say, "I will preserve your letters with durable cedar against the decayed enemies of the Muses?"
Which Muses, I ask?
Are they the ones who discovered letters and wrote papers that moths will pursue?
Tell me, brother, did the Muses discover letters?
Is not everything through the Lord, and everything from God?
Besides those one hundred and twenty languages, was there another of the Muses?
Hesiod lied about this on Helicon, with the enthusiasm of the Athenians, who, as the Apostle said, had no interest except in talking (Acts 17:21).
We, with the Apostle as our witness (First Corinthians 14:10, 18), retain all modes of speech, all kinds of languages inspired by God.
I forgive you, brother, if you presume anything from your author, and if you combine Novatian's philosophy, through which he fell into the shipwreck of religion, with the authority of Hesiod.
Nevertheless, you should have remembered the Apostle, who said: "See to it that no one takes you captive through philosophy and empty deceit" (Colossians 2:8).
Now, what do you think of this accusation against Catholics?
If kings or empires have ever persecuted you,
by the same logic, should it not be held against you whenever Catholics have endured persecution from kings and empires?
Our people were persecuted by pagan rulers.
Did you endure the hatred of Christians?
But our people complained more.
Let the one who did this see with what intention and spirit it was done;
whether it was for peace or discord.
Even if some of them did wrong, as it is written,
Does their unfaithfulness nullify the faithfulness of God?
(Romans 3:3).
However, do not think that our people were merely complaining.
When Christian rulers began to emerge through our faith,
those rulers, favoring the Catholic side, that is, their own side, were moved by their own grief.
Unless perhaps it will be held against Daniel that he was vindicated by Darius,
or against the most holy woman Esther, when the king's leader was killed for her sake,
or against the three youths, because the Babylonian king threatened the profane and unbelieving because of them after the trials of the flames.
Did not Peter confound Simon, with the judge's approval?
Did not Paul blind Elymas, with Sergius's support?
And he would have been vindicated in Jerusalem, if he had any faith to hold on to.
Do you not know that the authorities serve the innocent and minister for the good of the holy fathers?
As the Apostle says: Rulers are not a terror to good works, but to evil.
Do you want to be unafraid of the authority?
Do what is good, and you will have praise from the same; for he is God's servant to you for good
(Romans 13:3-4).
And yet I have complained about no one, nor have I been avenged by anyone.
I do not think the Novatians are a hindrance to me, whose small number and weakness I could boast about if I wanted to.
Behold, no one accuses your people before the Emperor, and you are alone.
We all must stand before the judgment seat of God
(Romans 14:10; Second Corinthians 5:19).
One thing I know, the Novatians would complain if their cause was favored by any rulers.
You endured the hatred of Christians? But our people complained more.
Let the one who did this see with what intention and spirit; whether he sought peace or discord.
But even if some of them sinned, he says, does their unfaithfulness nullify the faithfulness of God?
(Romans 3:3)
Yet, you should not think that our people were complaining.
When Christian leaders began to emerge from our faith, those very leaders, favoring the Catholic Church—that is, their own side—were moved by personal pain.
Unless perhaps Daniel is to be blamed for being avenged by Darius, or Esther, the most holy woman, when the leader of the king was killed for her; or the three boys, because for them, after the ordeal of the flames, the Babylonian king threatened the impious and unbelieving.
Did not Peter confound Simon, with the judge agreeing?
Did not Paul blind Elymas, with Sergius approving?
He would also have been avenged in Jerusalem if he had any binding faith.
Do you not know that powers serve the innocent and minister for the good of the holy fathers?
As the Apostle says: Leaders are not a terror to good conduct, but to bad.
Do you wish to have no fear of authority?
Do what is good, and you will receive approval from it through the Lord: For he is God's servant for your good.
(Romans 13:3-4)
And yet I did not complain about anyone, nor was I avenged by anyone.
Nor do I think that the Novatians hinder me, whose insignificance and shortcomings I could boast of if I wished.
Behold, no one accuses your people to the emperor, and you are alone.
We all must stand before the judgment seat of God.
(Romans 14:10; Second Corinthians 5:19) This one thing I know, the Novatians would complain if their cause were pleasing to any princes.
You say it is more useful to win than to please.
But those who are driven by the desire to win advance through contention.
The Apostle, however, says: If anyone seems to be contentious, we have no such custom, nor do the churches of God.
(First Corinthians 9:16) On the contrary, regarding the desire to please: I try to please everyone in everything, not seeking my own advantage, but that of many, that they may be saved.
(First Corinthians 10:33) But you, while thinking of your own interests and not those of your brothers, prefer to crush by winning rather than to restore by pleasing.
To overcome evil with good is rational; however, in any situation, wanting to be victorious is a sign of irrational arrogance.
This perspective is not from Apostolic law but from Greek tradition, where it is believed that the entire Spartan custom was driven by the desire to win.
The muddy pig and the insane tiger, what else do they want but to win rather than to please?
You write that you have free time, and thus contentious things delight you.
As for me, occupied with Catholic affairs, your letters were delivered to me after almost 30 days and repeated after another 40 days.
It would be more useful, you say, to win than to please.
But those who are driven by the fervor of winning progress through contention.
However, the Apostle says: "But if anyone seems to be contentious, we have no such custom, nor does the Church of God" (First Corinthians 9:16).
On the contrary, regarding the effort to please: "I please all men in all things, not seeking my own profit, but the profit of many, that they may be saved" (First Corinthians 10:33).
But you, considering your own advantages rather than those of your brothers, prefer to crush by winning rather than to revive by pleasing.
To overcome evil with good is rational; however, in any situation, wanting to be victorious is a sign of irrational arrogance.
This perspective is not from Apostolic law but from Greek tradition, where it is believed that the entire Spartan custom was driven by the desire to win.
The muddy pig and the insane tiger, what else do they want but to win rather than to please?
You write that you have free time, and thus contentious things delight you.
As for me, occupied with Catholic affairs, your letters were delivered to me after almost 30 days and repeated after another 40 days.
You say that I am angry; far from it.
I am stirred, like a bee that sometimes defends its honey with a sting.
But consider both of our letters; you will see whether we arm our page with barbs or flowers.
As for those like you, the Apostle says they must be stopped (Titus 1:11).
But pay attention.
We contend with you like doves, more with words than with teeth.
Would that it were true that you wish to be taught!
I would already be offering you the holy oil of the Spirit with my own hands.
Do you love me?
I have not hurt you, I know.
Only then can you truly love, if you approach my work with kindness and without holding differing opinions.
You're curious why I appreciate the letters of Cyprian?
Why not, given that he is a blessed martyr and a Catholic priest?
You mention Novatian to me?
I know he was a worldly philosopher, and it's no surprise he strayed from the Church of the living God.
He abandoned the ancient law and the heritage of the old people out of envy towards Cornelius.
He supported the madness of Novatus and became a bishop without legitimate consecration.
Thus, he was never truly made one, even with a letter from those pretending to be Confessors, who sought to divide the one mother.
I'll prove these points to you, brother, through the writings of your own Confessors.
Your philosopher, trying to establish his own wisdom, as the Apostle says in Romans 10:3, is not subject to God's wisdom.
The world did not recognize God's wisdom through its own.
You think Novatian suffered, and you add that Cyprian mentioned it.
My adversary preceded me; see how clearly I respond.
Novatian never endured martyrdom, nor has this ever been heard or read from the words of the most blessed Cyprian.
Cyprian's letters report Cornelius, the bishop of the city, whom Novatian envied at that time.
Cornelius resisted enemy leaders, often confessed, and was frequently harassed.
He was made a leader by many Confessors and Martyrs and was crowned most gloriously with many others while Novatian was still alive and secure.
Indeed, Novatian left the church of Christ to avoid the burden of confession.
Driven by envy, he couldn't bear Cornelius's episcopate.
Ridiculed by a few letters, he committed himself to Novatus.
Cyprian's letters will teach you all these things about Novatian.
Even if Novatian did suffer, he wasn't killed; and even if he was killed, he wasn't crowned.
Why not?
Because outside the peace of the Church, outside concord, outside the mother, one cannot be a true martyr.
Listen to the Apostle: And if I have all faith, so as to remove mountains; but do not have charity, I am nothing.
And if I give away all my possessions to feed the poor, and if I surrender my body to be burned, but do not have love, it profits me nothing.
First Corinthians 13:2-3.
As for Cyprian, he suffered in harmony with everyone, in common peace, among the group of Confessors, and often confessed during repeated persecutions.
He was tormented with many lacerations and was finally offered the saving chalice.
This was his crowning moment.
Therefore, let Novatian keep his letters to himself; let him keep his arrogance and pride, which, while lifting him up, caused his downfall.
While sparing no one, he was scattered.
Behold the one who blocks the path of salvation for his brothers with unyielding religiosity!
Behold the one who confidently claims to bear himself openly and to purify the Lord’s threshing floor!
You say I am angry; far from it.
I am stirred like a bee, which sometimes defends honey with its sting.
But consider the letters from both sides; you will soon see whether we are arming the page with barbs or flowers.
The Apostle indeed speaks of similar people who must be silenced.
Titus 1:11.
But pay attention.
We fight with you like doves, more with our mouths than with our teeth.
If only it were true that you want to be taught!
I would already be offering you the holy anointing of the Spirit with my own hands.
Do you love me?
I have not harmed you, I know.
But you would truly love me if you did not think differently and approached my work kindly.
Are you surprised that I like Cyprian's letters?
Why wouldn’t I like the letters of a blessed martyr and a Catholic priest?
You mention Novatian to me?
I hear he was a philosopher of the world; nor am I surprised that he strayed from the Church of the living God.
I know he abandoned the root of the ancient law, the source of the old people, envying Cornelius, accommodating Novatus’s madness, and became a bishop without legitimate consecration, and therefore was not made one through the letter of those who pretended to be Confessors, who would tear apart the limbs of one mother.
These things, brother, I will prove to you with the confession of your own people, with letters.
Thus, your philosopher, seeking to establish his own wisdom, as the Apostle says, is not subject to the wisdom of God; for in his wisdom, the world did not recognize the wisdom of God.
Romans 10:3.
Because you think Novatian suffered before Cyprian, and you add that Cyprian said, "My adversary preceded me," see how clearly I respond. Novatian never suffered martyrdom, nor was this ever heard or read from the words of the most blessed Cyprian.
You have his letters in which he speaks of Cornelius, the bishop of Rome, whom Novatian envied at the time. Cornelius resisted hostile leaders, often confessed, was often tormented; he led many Confessors and Martyrs, and was crowned most gloriously with many while Novatian was still alive and even unconcerned. Novatian had left the church of Christ to avoid the burden of confession. Initially provoked by envy, he could not endure the episcopate of Cornelius; then he committed himself to Novatus, mocked by the letters of a few. All these things about Novatian, Cyprian's letters will teach you thoroughly.
Furthermore, even if Novatian did suffer something, he was not killed; even if he was killed, he was not crowned. Why? Because he was outside the peace of the Church, outside harmony, outside the mother of whom a martyr should be a part. Listen to the Apostle: "And if I have all faith, so as to move mountains, but do not have love, I am nothing. And if I give away all my possessions to feed the poor, and if I hand over my body to be burned, but do not have love, I gain nothing" (First Corinthians 13:2-3).
However, Cyprian suffered in the harmony of all, in common peace, among the group of Confessors.
He often confessed under repeated persecutions, was tormented with much laceration, and finally was offered the saving cup.
This was to be crowned.
Therefore, let Novatian keep his letters; his arrogance and pride, which, while lifting him high, cast him down; while he spares no one, he is spilled.
Behold, he who inexorably closes the way of salvation to brothers!
Behold, he who confidently claims to carry himself openly and cleanse the Lord's threshing floor!
Have mercy on yourself, brother Sympronian, and do not let Novatian deceive you under this facade; and let him not be considered more righteous because he despises others by comparison to himself.
Often, boldness pretends to be confidence; and to those desperate sinners, a false image of a good conscience flatters them.
On the other hand, all humility is innocence, even that which owes a debt, even that which sins, even that which flatters its soul with the sinner.
Moses said, Erase me from the book you have written, so that sinners might not perish (Exodus thirty-two, thirty-two).
The Apostle said, I wished that I myself were accursed in Christ for the sake of my brothers, my relatives according to the flesh (Romans nine, three).
Certainly, both are praying on behalf of sinners; and because of this, neither Moses nor Paul offended God.
Is Novatian better than them?
A reformer of the Prophets?
A teacher of the Apostles?
Does he now seem to be with Christ like Moses?
Does he now ascend to the third heaven like Paul?
Is he now heard alone, neglecting all others?
This should be enough to answer your letters.
But because you argued more extensively about not doing penance, or doing it before baptism; and filled the page of the treatise with many chapters of examples, I will respond to each abundantly: I will not be silent about what true faith holds.
You, as you generously commanded our hearing, offer a kind return to the treatise.
Perhaps the Lord will provide that we who have patiently presented ourselves to you, may also reap some fruit from your patience.
May the Lord deign to guard and protect you forever, and make you live as a Christian and Catholic, and be in harmony with us.
Amen.
Have mercy on yourself, brother Sympronian, and do not let Novatian deceive you under this pretense; and therefore be considered more righteous, because he despised others in comparison to himself.
Often, boldness pretends to be confidence; and to those desperate sinners, a false image of a good conscience flatters them.
On the other hand, all humility is innocence, even that which owes a debt, even that which sins, even that which flatters its soul with the sinner.
Moses said, Erase me from the book you have written, so that sinners might not perish (Exodus thirty-two, thirty-two).
The Apostle said, I wished that I myself were accursed in Christ for the sake of my brothers, my relatives according to the flesh (Romans nine, three).
Of course, both pray for sinners; and because of this, neither Moses nor Paul offended God.
Is Novatian better than them? A corrector of the Prophets?
A teacher of the Apostles?
Has he already been seen with Christ like Moses?
Has he already been elevated to the third heaven like Paul?
Has he been heard alone, neglecting everyone else?
This should suffice in response to your letters.
But because you broadly debated about not doing penance, or doing it before baptism, and you filled the page of the treatise with many chapters of examples, I will respond to each abundantly: I will not be silent about what true faith holds.
You, as you graciously commanded our hearing, kindly offer your graciousness again to the treatise.
Perhaps the Lord will grant that we, who have patiently submitted to you, may also gain some benefit from your patience.
May the Lord deign to keep and protect you forever, and make you live as a Christian and Catholic, and be in agreement with us.
Amen.
Letter Three Against the Treatises of the Novatians.
Pacianus, bishop, sends greetings to his brother Sympronian.
The entire treatise of the Novatians, which you have sent to me from all sides with propositions, my brother Sympronian, contains this: that it is not permitted to repent after baptism; that the Church cannot forgive mortal sin, and indeed that it perishes by accepting sinners.
A remarkable honor, unique authority, and great constancy; to reject the guilty, to avoid the touch of sinners, and to mistakenly trust in one's own innocence.
Who advocates this, brother?
Moses, Paul, or Christ?
Moses wished to be erased from the book for the sake of blasphemers Exodus thirty-two verse thirty-two,
Paul desired to be cursed for his brothers Romans nine verse three,
and the Lord Himself preferred to suffer for the unjust.
None of these, you say.
Who then?
Novatian has commanded this.
Someone pure and spotless, who has never heard of Novatus, who has never deserted the Church, who became a bishop by bishops, who was consecrated by the usual order, who succeeded to a vacant chair in the Church?
What does it matter to you?
you say; Novatian taught this.
But when, brother, and in what times?
Immediately after the Lord's passion?
After the reign of Decius, that is, nearly three hundred years after the Lord's passion.
What then?
Did he follow prophets like the Cataphrygians, or some Philomena like Apelles; or did he alone receive such authority?
Did he speak in tongues?
Did he prophesy?
Could he raise the dead?
For he should have had some of these things to introduce a new law of the gospel.
And even if the Apostle cries out against this, "Even if we, or an angel from heaven, preach a gospel contrary to the one we preached to you, let him be accursed" Galatians one verse eight.
Novatian understood it this way, you say: but Christ taught this.
So from Christ to the reign of Decius, no one understood?
After Decius, finally, every bishop was impatient; all others were dissolute who preferred to mix with the lost, who preferred to perish with the wretched, who preferred to be wounded by another's wound?
The entire treatise of the Novatians that you, my brother Sympronian, have sent to me contains this: that repentance is not allowed after baptism, that the Church cannot forgive mortal sin, and that it perishes by accepting sinners.
What an extraordinary honor, unique authority, and great steadfastness—to reject the guilty, to avoid the touch of sinners, and to wrongly trust in one's own innocence.
Who supports this, brother—Moses, Paul, or Christ?
But Moses wishes to be erased from the book for the blasphemers; and Paul wishes to be anathema for his brothers; and the Lord Himself prefers to suffer for the unjust.
None of these, you say.
Who then?
Novatian commanded this.
Someone immaculate and pure, who has not heard of Novatus, who has never deserted the Church, who became a bishop by bishops, who was consecrated by regular law, who obtained a vacant chair in the Church?
What's it to you?
you ask; Novatian taught this.
But when, brother, and in what times?
Right after the Lord's passion?
No, after the reign of Decius, almost 300 years after the Lord's passion.
What then?
Did he follow prophets like the Cataphrygians, or some Philomena like Apelles; or did he himself receive so much authority?
Did he speak in tongues?
Did he prophesy?
Could he raise the dead?
For he ought to have had some of these abilities to introduce the gospel of a new law.
And if the Apostle cries out against it: "Even if we, or an angel from heaven, preach a gospel to you other than what we have preached to you, let him be accursed." Novatian understood this, you say; but Christ taught this. Therefore, from Christ until the reign of Decius, no one understood? After Decius, finally, every bishop was impatient; all others were dissolute who preferred to mix with the lost, who preferred to perish with the wretched, who preferred to be wounded by another's wound? Under Novatian's rule, justice is liberated; under his leadership, everything that has gone astray is corrected.
Come on, you say, let us compete with examples and fight with reason.
But I have been at peace up to this point, content with the tranquility of the ancient congregation of the Church.
I have not engaged in studies of discord nor sought out arguments for disputes.
After you were separated from the rest of the body and divided from the mother, to justify your actions, you began to diligently search through every corner of books, probing into hidden things, and disturbing whatever was at peace.
Our ancestors did not engage in disputes; our security lies in simplicity.
What fortified arguments have you brought from your side?
I do not know what Novatian did, what Novatus admitted, what Evaristus boasted about, or what Nicostratus declared.
Since I ignore your weapons, I am not familiar with them; see if you can clash with unarmed truth.
Nonetheless, let’s wait to hear what you object to and what you say.
Could bare truth or innocent ignorance even stand up?
You propose, and rightly so, that the Church is a people renewed by water and the Holy Spirit, without denying the name of Christ, a temple and house of God, the pillar and foundation of truth.
First Timothy chapter 3, verse 15.
A holy virgin with the purest thoughts, the bride of Christ from His bones and flesh.
Ephesians chapter 5, verse 30.
Without spot or wrinkle.
Ephesians chapter 5, verse 27.
Adhering to the full rights of the Gospels.
Who among us denies this?
Moreover, we add that the Church is a queen in golden and varied attire.
Psalm 45, verse 10.
A fruitful vine on the sides of the Lord's house.
Psalm 128, verse 3.
The Mother of countless young women.
Song of Solomon chapter 6, verse 7.
The one beautiful dove of her mother, and perfect.
Song of Solomon chapter 6, verse 9.
She is the mother of all, built on the foundations of the Prophets and Apostles, with Jesus Christ Himself as the cornerstone.
Ephesians chapter 2, verse 20.
A great house enriched with a variety of vessels.
Come, you say, let us contend with examples and fight with reason.
But I have been at peace up to this point: content with the tranquility of the ancient congregation of the Church.
I have not engaged in studies of discord nor sought out arguments for disputes.
After you were separated from the rest of the body and divided from the mother, you diligently search through all the recesses of books to explain your actions.
You seek out hidden things and disturb whatever is otherwise secure.
Our ancestors did not engage in unnecessary disputes.
Our security is straightforward.
What fortified arguments have you brought?
I do not know what Novatian did, what Novatus committed, what Evaristus inflated, or what Nicostratus reported.
While I disregard your arms, I do not know them.
See if you contend with unarmed truth.
Let us wait, however, for what you object to, what you say.
Could naked truth or innocent ignorance stand on its own?
You propose, and rightly so, that the Church is a people renewed by water and the Holy Spirit, without denying the name of Christ, a temple and house of God, the pillar and foundation of truth 1 Timothy 3:15.
A holy virgin with the purest thoughts, the bride of Christ from His bones and flesh Ephesians 5:30, without spot or wrinkle Ephesians 5:27, faithfully preserving the laws of the Gospels.
Who among us denies this?
We even add that the Church is a queen in a golden and multicolored robe Psalm 45:10, a fruitful vine on the sides of the Lord's house Psalm 128:3, the mother of young maidens beyond number Song of Solomon 6:7, a unique, beautiful dove of her mother, and perfect Song of Solomon 6:8.
The very mother of all, built on the foundations of the Prophets and Apostles, with Jesus Christ Himself as the cornerstone Ephesians 2:20.
A great house enriched with all kinds of vessels.
But these are our arguments later.
For now, let us see yours.
The Church is a people reborn from water and the Holy Spirit.
Fine.
Who closed God's fountain?
Who took away the Spirit?
Indeed, with us, there is living water, the very one springing from Christ.
You, separated from the eternal fountain, from where are you born?
The Holy Spirit has not left the principal mother.
How did He reach you?
Unless perhaps He followed you in discord, content with an unconsecrated seat, having abandoned so many priests, and loved a worn-out pond of a counterfeit fountain.
Your people, where do they receive the Spirit that is not anointed by a priest?
Where do they get the water that has departed from the source?
Where is the renewal that has lost the cradle of the bride of peace?
The Church is a people who do not deny the name of Christ.
Do we not have among us confessors who were tested by chains, fires, and swords?
You might say, they were, but by accepting deniers, they perished.
I won't remain silent about the fact that even Novatian, when he was still in the Church, wrote, advised, and read the document about accepting back the deniers or the fallen.
Meanwhile, whom can you convince that the whole Church collapsed by accepting the fallen?
That by admitting penitents, those who admitted them became deniers?
And if some people were more lenient, did the others who did not approve their actions but followed the custom and peace lose the Christian name?
Hear the voice of Jeremiah: "In those days, they will not say, 'The fathers have eaten sour grapes, and the children's teeth are set on edge,' but everyone will die for their own sin."
Jeremiah 31:29-30.
Nor is the Lord silent in Ezekiel: "As the father’s soul, so also the son’s soul is mine. Everyone will die for their own sin."
Ezekiel 18:4.
And further down: "The son will not bear the iniquity of the father, nor will the father bear the iniquity of the son: the righteousness of the righteous will be upon them."
Ezekiel 18:20.
You yourself cite this example: "And if these three men were in its midst, Noah, Job, and Daniel, they would not save sons or daughters; they alone would be saved."
Ezekiel 14:16.
Behold, they are saved who are placed among sinners, who cannot save others. You bind the whole world with the chains of a few; you condemn the whole Church with the weakness of a small portion.
What of all the saints with you, whom Novatus trained, whom Evaristus chose, whom Nicostratus taught, whom Novatian instructed? You reject thorns and thistles. You do not have weeds in your crop. For you, the grains are already purified. The one who purifies will come to you without a winnowing fan.
Matthew 3:12.
Will you alone among all not have chaff?
But let’s leave our things for later; for now, let’s focus on yours.
The Church is the community reborn from water and the Holy Spirit.
So, who has blocked God’s fountain?
Who has taken the Spirit away?
On the contrary, among us, there is living water, the very water that springs from Christ.
You, separated from the eternal source, where are you regenerated from?
The Holy Spirit has not left the original mother: how does He reach you?
Unless perhaps He followed someone discordant, content with a seat not consecrated by so many priests, and loved the worn-out pool of a false fountain.
Where does your community get the Spirit; the people whom an anointed priest does not consecrate?
Where do they get the water, which has departed from the mother?
Where do they get renewal, which has lost the cradle of the peaceful bride?
The Church is a community without denying the name of Christ: are there not confessors among us, proven by chains, fires, and swords?
You will say, they existed, but by accepting those who denied, they perished.
I won’t even mention that, indeed, Novatianus of your group, when he was still in the Church, both wrote and advised and read a document about accepting those who had denied or lapsed.
Meanwhile, how can you persuade anyone that the entire Church has fallen by accepting those who lapsed?
That by admitting the penitent, the admitting people have become deniers?
And if some people have been more lenient, have the rest who did not approve of their actions but followed custom and peace, lost the Christian name?
Hear the voice of Jeremiah: "In those days, they will not say, 'The fathers have eaten sour grapes, and the children's teeth are set on edge,' but each will die for his own sin" (Jeremiah 31:29-30).
Nor is the Lord silent through Ezekiel: "Just as the soul of the father, so also the soul of the son is mine. Each will die for his own sin" (Ezekiel 18:4).
Further down: "The son will not bear the iniquity of the father, nor will the father bear the iniquity of the son: The righteousness of the righteous will be upon him" (Ezekiel 18:20).
You even cite this example: "Even if these three men were in it, Noah, Job, and Daniel, they would not save their sons or daughters; they alone would be saved" (Ezekiel 14:16).
Here are the ones who are saved, who are in the midst of sinners and cannot save others.
You bind the whole world with the chains of a few; you condemn the whole Church with the weakness of a small portion.
What about all the saints with you, those whom Novatus taught, whom Evaristus chose, whom Nicostratus instructed, whom Novatianus trained?
You have avoided thorns and thistles; you don't have weeds among your crops; for you, the grains are already cleaned.
The purifier will come to you without a winnowing fan; will you be the only one without chaff?
Come on, say the rest: the Church is the body of Christ.
Indeed, a body, not a part; a body gathered from many parts and members into one, as the Apostle says: For the body is not one member, but many.
Therefore, the Church is a full body, both a body and a solid one, already spread throughout the whole world.
Like a city, I say, whose parts are united; not like you Novatians, an insolent little part and lump gathered and separated from the rest of the body.
The Church is the temple of God; certainly a spacious temple, a great house, having indeed vessels of gold and silver, but also wooden and earthenware ones, some for honor, but many magnificent ones destined for various uses of various works.
The Church is a holy virgin, with the most chaste feelings, the bride of Christ.
A virgin; it is true: but also a mother.
A bride; it is clear: but also a wife and partner taken from her husband; therefore bone of his bones, and flesh of his flesh.
For David said about her: Your wife will be like a fruitful vine within your house; your children will be like olive shoots around your table.
Therefore, this virgin has many offspring and countless children, with which the whole world is filled, always buzzing with populous swarms.
This mother has great care for her children and a tender affection; the good are honored, the proud are punished, the sick are cared for; no one is lost, no one is despised; children are safely kept under the mother's indulgence.
The Church is without spot or wrinkle.
This means avoiding heresies, such as the Valentinians, the Cataphrygians, and the Novatians.
Among these are some blemished and wrinkled folds, envious of the ornaments of precious garments.
However, the sinner and the penitent are not a stain on the Church; because as long as he sins and does not repent, he is placed outside the Church.
When he stops sinning, he is already healed.
But the heretic tears, disrupts, corrupts, and wrinkles the garment of the Lord, the Church of Christ.
For when there are divisions and contentions among you, are you not carnal and walking according to man?
First Corinthians 3:3.
And their word spreads like cancer.
Second Timothy 2:17.
This is a stain on unity, this is a wrinkle.
Finally, where the Apostle speaks about these things, he proposes the love of Christ and affection.
Just as Christ, he says, loved the Church and gave himself up for her.
Ephesians 5:25.
To remove the heretics, because they did not know how to love.
But why is this for the miserable penitent?
Because he desires to love and to be loved.
Come, say the rest:
The Church is the body of Christ.
Certainly a body, not just a member: a body collected into one with many parts and members, as the Apostle says:
For the body is not one member, but many.
First Corinthians 12:14.
Therefore, the Church is a complete body, both unified and solid, and already spread throughout the whole world.
Like a city, I say, whose parts are united; not like you Novatians, a certain insolent fragment and outgrowth, separated from the rest of the body.
The Church is the temple of God: certainly a spacious temple, a great house, having indeed golden and silver vessels, but also wooden and earthen, some for honor, many indeed magnificent, destined for various uses in multiple works.
Second Timothy 2:20.
The Church is a holy virgin, with the most chaste senses, the bride of Christ.
Virgin; it is true: but also a mother.
Bride; it is evident: but also a wife and spouse taken from her husband: therefore bone of his bones, and flesh of his flesh.
Genesis 2:23.
For David spoke about this: "Your wife will be like a fruitful vine within your house; your children will be like young olive trees around your table." (Psalm 127:3).
Thus, this virgin has many children and countless offspring, filling the whole world, always buzzing like a beehive with a large population.
This mother has great care and tender affection for her children: the good are honored, the proud are punished, the sick are treated; no one is lost, no one is despised; secure offspring are kept under the mother’s indulgence.
The Church is without stain or wrinkle.
(Ephesians 5:27).
That is, it has no heresies, no Valentinians, no Cataphrygians, no Novatians.
For among them are certain stained and wrinkled parts, envying the ornaments of precious garments.
However, a sinner and a penitent are not a stain on the Church; because as long as he sins and does not repent, he is outside the Church.
When he stops sinning, he is already healed.
But the heretic tears, intercepts, spoils, and wrinkles the garment of the Lord, the Church of Christ.
For when there are divisions and disputes among you, are you not worldly and behaving like mere humans?
(First Corinthians 3:3).
And their talk spreads like gangrene.
(Second Timothy 2:17).
This is the stain of unity, this is the wrinkle.
Finally, when the Apostle speaks about these things, he speaks of the love of Christ and affection.
Just as Christ loved the Church and gave himself up for her.
(Ephesians 5:25).
To remove the heretics, because they did not know how to love.
But why mention these things to the miserable penitent?
Because he also wishes to love and be loved.
The Church is whole, guarding the laws of the Gospels.
Whole indeed because it is entire, because it is complete.
Where rewards are given to the faithful, where tears are not denied to the miserable, where the sick are treated, where insolent health and proud justice claim nothing for themselves, where caring charity perseveres in all things, believing everything, hoping everything, enduring everything.
(First Corinthians 13:7).
Hence that saying of the Apostle: "Who is weak, and I am not weak? Who is led into sin, and I do not inwardly burn?" (Second Corinthians 11:29).
Where the entire brotherhood bears its burdens together, grieving together, secure in mutual devotion.
All supporting one another in love, making every effort to maintain the unity of the Spirit through the bond of peace.
(Ephesians 4:3)
This will be the Church, my brother Sympronian; this will be the people reborn in Christ through water and the Holy Spirit.
You say, "I do not know if a sin can be forgiven by bishops," since the Lord said, "Whoever denies me before men, I also will deny before my Father who is in heaven." (Matthew 10:33)
Why then did your Novatian, not even a legitimate bishop at that time, long before Cornelius became bishop of Rome, long before he envied Cornelius' priesthood, propose these things?
You have the testimony of Cyprian; Cyprian whom you could never defame.
For in one place, he wrote to Antonianus in this manner:
"It was also added while Novatian was writing then; and what he wrote, he read aloud with his own voice; and Moses, who was then a confessor and now already a martyr, signed it; that peace should be given to those who had lapsed, who were weak and at the point of death: these letters were sent throughout the whole world and brought to the attention of all churches."
What do you say, my brother Sympronian? Novatian wrote these things, and to add the service of pure will, he also read them aloud. His right hand is a witness, the hand that wrote, is a witness: the tongue that read is a witness. Cornelius, for whom all this envy of yours erupted, was not yet a bishop. Much later, with many fellow bishops, with many confessors, and immediately with martyrs, as the same Cyprian writes, he agreed with the advice of the elders that it was permissible to grant peace.
If the door to repentance is to be closed, Novatian is guilty, who wrote, proposed, and read these things. Where then was the impatient rigor? Where was that fierce judgment? If no one had preferred Cornelius to you, the authority of the writer would remain. Now the whole opinion is displeasing, now weapons are thrown at us, supplied by the very authority by which the cause of the weapons prevailed.
The Church is, keeping the full rights of the Gospels. Whole indeed because complete, because full.
Where the reward is given to the faithful, where tears are not denied to the miserable, where the sick are healed, where insolent health and proud justice claim nothing for themselves, where caring love perseveres in all things, believing all things, hoping all things, enduring all things.
First Corinthians 13:7.
Hence the Apostle's statement: Who is weak, and I am not weak?
Who is offended, and I do not burn?
Second Corinthians 11:29.
Where the whole brotherhood bears its burdens together, sharing in mutual care.
All supporting each other in love, striving to maintain the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.
Ephesians 4:3.
This will be the Church, brother Sympronian; this will be the people reborn in Christ through water and the Holy Spirit.
You say, "I don't know if a sin can be forgiven by bishops," since the Lord said: Whoever denies me before men, I will also deny before my Father who is in heaven. Matthew 10:33.
Why then, did your Novatian, who was not even falsely a priest at that time, long before Cornelius became bishop of Rome, before he envied his priesthood, suggest these things? You have the testimony of Cyprian; Cyprian, whom you have never been able to defame. For in one place, he wrote to Antonianus in this way: It was also added by Novatian, who was writing at that time; and what he wrote, he recited with his own voice; and with Moses, then a confessor and now a martyr, subscribing; that peace should be given to the fallen and those on the verge of death.
These letters were sent throughout the whole world and made known to all the churches. What do you say, brother Sympronian? Novatian wrote these things, and to add the duty of pure will, he also recited the writings. His right hand is a witness, the hand that wrote is a witness: the tongue that read is a witness. Cornelius, for whom all this envy of yours erupted, was not yet a bishop. Much later, with many fellow bishops, with many confessors, and immediately martyrs, as Cyprian himself writes, he agreed with the council of elders that it was permissible to grant peace. If entry to repentance is to be denied, Novatian is at fault, who wrote, suggested, and read these things.
Where then is the impatient severity? Where is that fierce judgment?
If no one had preferred Cornelius to you, the authority of the writer would have remained.
Now the entire opinion is displeasing, and weapons are being hurled at us by the very people whose authority once strengthened our cause.
But when did the Novatian heresy begin?
Listen, please, and understand the entire sequence of your error.
Cornelius, already made bishop of Rome by sixteen bishops, had taken the place of the vacant chair.
In that same virginal purity with which he was endowed, he endured frequent persecutions from an angry emperor.
Then, by chance, a certain priest named Novatus from Africa, who had defrauded widows in the Carthaginian church, robbed orphans, withheld church money, thrown his father out of the house, causing him to die of hunger without burial, and struck his pregnant wife's womb with a kick, causing her to miscarry, came to Rome.
While in Carthage, as the day of his trial in the church was approaching, he hid.
Not long after, he influenced this Novatian, who was anxious about Cornelius's bishopric (for he had hoped for it himself), and with some supporters on his side, as usually happens in such matters, he encouraged him, fueled his hesitation, and urged him to hope for something great.
He found some of those who had escaped the storm of that persecution, among whom he could stir up jealousy against Cornelius for accepting those who had lapsed.
He sent their letters to Novatian.
Based on the authority of these letters, even though there was already a bishop in Rome, he assumed the title of another bishop for himself, against the singular priesthood’s rules: he accused Cornelius of communing with the lapsed and claimed himself to be innocent.
Against him, I must give an account, defend my modesty, and clear my life.
But when did the Novatian heresy begin?
Listen, please, and understand the entire sequence of your error.
Cornelius, already made bishop of Rome by sixteen bishops, had taken the place of the vacant chair.
In that same virginal purity with which he was endowed, he endured frequent persecutions from an angry emperor.
Then, by chance, a certain priest named Novatus from Africa, who had defrauded widows in the church of Carthage, robbed orphans, denied the church's money, thrown his father out of the house, and caused his father to die of hunger without burial, and who had kicked his pregnant wife in the womb causing a miscarriage, came to Rome.
And when in Carthage, as the brothers in the church pressed on him, the day of his trial approached, and he hid.
Not long after, he incited Novatian, who was anxious about the bishopric of Cornelius (for he hoped for it himself) and, as often happens in such matters, he swayed some followers to his side, encouraging and supporting the doubtful one; urging him to hope for something great.
He found some among those who had escaped the storm of that persecution; through whom he could stir up envy against Cornelius regarding the acceptance of the lapsed.
He sent their letters to Novatian.
Using the authority of these letters, while the bishop was already sitting in Rome, Novatian assumed the title of another bishop, which was contrary to the singular priesthood, accusing Cornelius of communing with the lapsed and claiming his own innocence.
Against this man, I must give an account, against this man, I must assert my honor, against this man, I must clear my life.
But you may say, "You bishops, why do you approve such things?" Let someone else say this: you defend Novatian. This cause may seem inexcusable to others, though it may be pleasing to you. Anyone who is innocent for you is guilty for another. Do not accuse someone else of a crime from which you cannot be freed. Come on, as bishops, we must owe all modesty, for we have received the name of the apostles, for we are marked by the title of Christ.
The Lord denies the denier, you say; you should not acknowledge the denier. Who acknowledges the denier? The one who drives him to repentance, rebukes, shows the crime, opens the wounds, reminds him of eternal punishments, corrects him by the destruction of the flesh? This is chastising, not acknowledging.
The Lord says to us, "You are the salt of the earth" Therefore, by rightly speaking these things, we do not become worthless, and anyone who hears will not be worthless. You see, we do not trample on the Lord's judgment, but we approve it; we do not reject severity, but we reveal His will.
But to the penitent,
you will say, you forgive sins; when it is only in baptism that you are allowed to forgive sin.
Not by me, clearly, but by God alone, who both grants pardon in baptism and does not reject the tears of the penitent.
Moreover, what I do, I do not by my own authority, but by the Lord's:
We are God’s co-workers, He says, you are God’s building.
First Corinthians 3:9
And again: I planted, Apollos watered, but God gave the growth:
So neither the one who plants nor the one who waters is anything, but only God who gives the growth.
First Corinthians 3:6-7
So whether we baptize, urge repentance, or grant pardon to the penitent;
we do this by Christ's authority.
You must consider whether Christ can do this, whether Christ has done this.
But you will say, bishops, why do you approve such actions?
Let someone else say this: you defend Novatian.
This cause may seem inexcusable to others, though it may be pleasing to you.
Let anyone be innocent for you, whoever is guilty on your behalf.
Do not accuse another of a crime from which you cannot be freed.
Come, let us bishops show all our modesty, because we have received the title of apostles, because we are marked by the name of Christ.
You say the Lord denies the denier: you, I do not want to admit the denier.
Who confesses the denier?
The one who urges repentance, reproaches, shows the crime, reveals the wounds, reminds of eternal punishments, corrects through the destruction of the flesh?
This is to chastise, not to admit.
The Lord says to us: You are the salt of the earth.
Matthew 5:13
Therefore, we rightly preserve by saying these things, and anyone who listens will not be worthless.
You see, we do not trample on the Lord's judgment, but approve it; we do not reject severity, but reveal His will.
But to the penitent,
you will say, you forgive sins; when it is only in baptism that you are allowed to forgive sin.
Not by me, clearly, but by God alone, who both grants pardon in baptism and does not reject the tears of the penitent.
Moreover, what I do, I do not by my own authority, but by the Lord's:
We are God's co-workers, He says, you are God’s building.
First Corinthians 3:9
And again: I planted, Apollos watered, but God gave the growth.
So neither the one who plants nor the one who waters is anything, but only God who gives the growth.
1 Corinthians 3:6-7.
Therefore, whether we baptize, compel to repentance, or grant forgiveness to the repentant, we do it by Christ's authority.
You must consider whether Christ can do this and whether Christ has done this.
If forgiveness of sins could be given to the repentant, you say, then baptism was not necessary.
This is a very foolish comparison!
For baptism is the sacrament of the Lord’s passion; the forgiveness for the repentant is the merit of the one confessing.
Everyone can obtain the former because it is a gift of God’s grace; that is, a free gift.
But this labor is for the few who rise again after a fall, who recover after wounds, who are aided by tearful cries, who revive after the destruction of the flesh.
You claim that I have wrongly cited the example where God says: I prefer a sinner's repentance over their death.
Ezekiel 33:11.
What if I had added the passage from Isaiah: When you turn and groan, then you will be saved and you will know where you have been?
Isaiah 30:15, according to the Septuagint.
What if I had quoted from Revelation: Remember where you have fallen from, and repent, and do the works you did at first?
Revelation 2:5.
You might say these were spoken to the Gentiles before baptism.
Listen to the Apostle: We know that whatever the law says, it speaks to those who are under the law.
Romans 3:19.
Therefore, those who lived without the law are not bound by the condition of repentance.
Even if they had repented, they did so freely by faith, not by the bond of repentance imposed by the law.
So then, you might say, Jews who repented before baptism cannot repent after baptism.
Who taught you this, brother Sympronian?
Who suggested that one who has repented before should not repent afterward?
But we will discuss this later.
Meanwhile, if repentance was denied to Jews after baptism because they fulfilled it before, at least grant that the Gentiles, who did not know the law of repentance before, should repent afterward.
But even regarding the Jews, I do not want you to be mistaken.
They repented earlier because they had corrupted the old baptism and were repenting as if they had betrayed their faith after believing.
Listen to the Apostle: "For I do not want you to be ignorant, brothers, that our ancestors were all under the cloud and all passed through the sea, and all were baptized into Moses in the cloud and in the sea. They all ate the same spiritual food and drank the same spiritual drink; for they drank from the spiritual rock that followed them, and the rock was Christ" (First Corinthians 10:1-4).
They had violated this baptism, and therefore they repented.
If the remission of sins could be given to those who repent, you say, baptism was not necessary.
What a foolish comparison!
Baptism is the sacrament of the Lord's passion; the pardon of the repentant is the merit of the one confessing.
Everyone can achieve the former because it is a gift of God's grace; that is, a free gift.
But the latter is the labor of a few who rise after a fall, who recover after wounds, who are aided by tearful prayers, who come back to life after the death of the flesh.
You falsely claim that I used that example of what God said: "I prefer the repentance of the sinner to death" (Ezekiel 33:11).
What if I had added that from Isaiah: "When you turn and groan, then you will be saved and you will know where you have been" (Isaiah 30:15, according to the Septuagint)?
What if I had added that from Revelation: "Remember from where you have fallen, and repent, and do the works you did at first" (Revelation 2:5)?
You might say these things were spoken to the nations before baptism.
Listen to the Apostle: "We know that whatever the law says, it speaks to those who are under the law" (Romans 3:19).
Therefore, the condition of repentance will not hold for those who lived without the law.
Even if they had repented, they did so freely, not under the compulsion of a law requiring repentance.
So, you say, even Jews who repented before baptism cannot repent after baptism.
Who taught you this, brother Symproniane?
Who persuaded you that one who repented before should not repent afterward?
But we will consider this matter later.
Meanwhile, if repentance is denied to the Jews after baptism because they have already made up their minds, then at least allow the Gentiles, who were unaware of the law of repentance before, to repent afterward.
But even regarding the Jews, I don't want you to be mistaken.
They repented earlier because they had corrupted the old baptism, as though they were repenting after betraying the faith.
Listen to the Apostle: "I do not want you to be unaware, brothers, that our ancestors were all under the cloud, and all passed through the sea, and all were baptized into Moses in the cloud and in the sea. They all ate the same spiritual food and drank the same spiritual drink. For they drank from the spiritual rock that followed them, and the rock was Christ" (First Corinthians 10:1-4).
They had violated this baptism and therefore repented.
Let's then see what you say: If God often commands a person to repent, you say, He often permits them to sin.
What are you saying?
Does the one who frequently shows the remedy for sin also show the sin?
Does the doctor, when he continuously treats, teach to wound repeatedly?
God does not want a person to sin even once, and yet He frees them from sin.
And certainly, when He frees, He does not teach sin; just as the one who frees from fire does not show the fire, nor does the one who rescues a shipwrecked person from rocks drive them onto the rocks.
It's one thing to be freed from danger, another to be driven into danger.
And perhaps I would allow this to be believed if repentance were considered a luxury; because such great labor is imposed, with the destruction of the flesh commanded, with constant tears, with eternal groaning.
Will the healed person then want to cut themselves again, to burn again?
Will they want to sin again and repent again, when it is written: "Do not add sin, lest something worse happens to you" (John 5:14)?
And again: "I do not pity those who continuously sin" (Ecclesiasticus 12:3).
But if, as you say, they are driven to sin, to whom the medicine of repentance is shown; what then will the person do to whom repentance itself is denied; to whom, with the remedy despaired of, the whole wound is covered; to whom, completely and altogether, the way of life is denied?
In baptism, you might say, we die once, as the Apostle says:
Do you not know that all of us who have been baptized into Christ Jesus were baptized into his death?
Therefore, we were buried with him by baptism into death, so that just as Christ was raised from the dead, we too might walk in newness of life
Romans
6:3-4.
Why is this surprising?
The Apostle taught that we should be new, so that no one would sin.
However, if someone did sin, they should repent.
The whole person would live, the cured would live: the innocent would receive a crown, the penitent would receive pardon.
The former would get a reward, the latter would receive healing.
Finally, the same Apostle says:
For if while we were still sinners, Christ died for us, much more now that we are justified by his blood, shall we be saved by him from the wrath
Romans
5:9-10.
From the wrath, of course, that was due to sinners.
If he did not allow the Gentile people to die, much more will he not allow the redeemed to perish.
Nor will he reject those he redeemed at a great cost.
For the loss of his servants is not a light matter to him.
He who rises will no longer die, as it is written
Romans
14:4.
But he is the advocate with the Father; he intercedes for our sins, a not insignificant advocate for the miserable, not a poorly qualified intercessor.
Let us then see what you say:
If God often commands man to repent, you say, he often allows him to sin.
What do you mean?
Therefore, does the one who often shows the remedy for crime show the crime?
And does the doctor, when he constantly heals, teach to be wounded?
God does not want man to sin even once, and yet he frees him from sin.
And of course, when he frees, he does not teach sin; just as one who frees from a fire does not show the fire; nor does one who rescues a shipwrecked person on the rocks drive them onto the rocks.
It is one thing to be freed from danger, another to be driven into danger.
And perhaps I would allow this to be believed if penance were thought to be a delight; whose labor is so great, whose destruction of the flesh is commanded, whose continual tears, whose eternal groans.
So will the healed person want to be cut again, to be burned again?
Will he choose to sin again and repent again, when it is written:
"Do not add sin, lest something worse happens to you"
John 5:14
?
And also:
"I do not pity the one who sins constantly"
Ecclesiasticus 12:3
.
But if, as you say, he is compelled to sin, to whom is the medicine of repentance shown?
What then will he do, who is denied repentance itself;
to whom the remedy is desperate, the whole wound is covered;
to whom, entirely and completely, the way of life is denied?
You will say, in baptism, we die once, as the Apostle says:
"Do you not know that all of us who have been baptized into Christ Jesus were baptized into his death?
Therefore we were buried with him by baptism into death, so that just as Christ was raised from the dead,
we too might walk in newness of life"
Romans 6:3-4
.
Why is this surprising?
The Apostle taught that we should be new, so that no one would sin:
but it followed that whoever had sinned, should repent.
Here the whole one, there the healed one would live:
the innocent would receive the crown,
the penitent would receive forgiveness:
the former would receive a reward, the latter a remedy.
Finally, the same Apostle says:
"For if while we were still sinners, Christ died for us;
much more now, being justified by his blood, will we be saved by him from wrath"
Romans 5:9-10
.
From the wrath, of course, that was owed to sinners.
But if he did not allow the Gentile people to die, much more will he not allow the redeemed to perish.
Nor will he reject those he redeemed at great cost;
for the loss of his servants is not small to him.
Indeed, he who rises will no longer die, as it is written
Romans 14:4.
But he is the advocate with the Father; he intercedes for our sins,
a patron not to be scorned of the wretched, a very capable intercessor.
Answer, brother, can the devil oppress the servants of God,
or can Christ not absolve them?
You say Peter’s repentance was before the Lord's passion?
No one proposed this to you.
And yet Peter had already been baptized:
for the Lord had said to him:
"He who is washed once, does not need to be washed again"
John 13:10
.
However, he later received the remedy of Christ, but he repented beforehand; and he was considered holy before he received the remedy.
His repentance would not have been recorded if it hadn't benefited the penitent in some way.
He wept, it says, very bitterly.
Matthew 26:75
Don't you want to be as faithful as Peter was?
Don't you want what benefited Peter to benefit us?
Come now, didn't my Thomas doubt the resurrection after the Lord's resurrection?
Didn't the Lord accuse him of faithlessness when he showed him the marks of the nails, the pierced hands, the wound in the side, and said to him: Don't be unbelieving, but believing?
John 20:27
So what then?
Was he ashamed to repent?
Wasn't he humbled?
Didn't he immediately confess his God and Lord?
Doesn't this confession commend him?
Answer, brother, can the devil oppress God's servants, or can Christ not absolve them?
You say Peter's repentance was before the Lord's passion?
No one proposed this to you.
And yet Peter had already been baptized: for the Lord had said to him: He who has bathed once does not need to wash again.
John 13:10
However, he later received the remedy of Christ, but he repented beforehand; and he was considered holy before he received the remedy.
His repentance would not have been recorded if it hadn't benefited the penitent in some way.
He wept, it says, very bitterly.
Matthew 26:75
Don't you want to be as faithful as Peter was?
Don't you want what benefited Peter to benefit us?
Come now, didn't my Thomas doubt the resurrection after the Lord's resurrection?
Didn't the Lord accuse him of faithlessness when he showed him the marks of the nails, the pierced hands, the wound in the side, and said to him: Don't be unbelieving, but believing?
John 20:27
So what then?
Was he ashamed to repent?
Wasn't he humbled?
Didn't he immediately confess his God and Lord?
Doesn't this confession commend him?
Now, how cleverly you absolve that point I made; the power given to bishops, that what they bind on earth shall be bound in heaven.
You say this does not pertain to the faithful, but to the catechumens; so that sins could be forgiven or retained for those who are still to be baptized.
You combine the chapters of two Evangelists, making them seem as one; and you add that what Matthew recorded less completely, John fulfilled.
The Lord said in Matthew:
"Go therefore and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit"
(Matthew 28:19) ;
and in John, he fulfilled it by saying:
"If you forgive anyone's sins, they are forgiven; if you do not forgive them, they are not forgiven."
(John 20:23) .
So, this forgiving or retaining seems to pertain to the nations that were to be baptized, because the first Evangelist spoke about the nations beforehand, and the latter fulfilled it by talking about forgiving and retaining.
What are you saying?
Did the two Evangelists report incomplete and half-finished meanings to each other?
Were they lacking words or reasoning; or did the Holy Spirit not fully complete everything, carrying the intended meanings and defining the words completely?
No one overrides a confirmed testament of a man; will a different tablet change God's tablet?
What is this desire to win in you that you dare such a thing?
What about the fact that the Lord said in Matthew before his passion:
"Whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven."
(Matthew 16:19) .
The Lord predicted this in Matthew and did not mention any nations there.
Why then do you join John's chapter where he placed his own and separate it from the nations?
Because if he had wanted it to pertain to the nations, he could have joined what he himself was placing.
Therefore, you have everything you seek in Matthew.
Why did you not read everything, you who teach the bishop?
Repeat the first part of this command.
According to Matthew, just before this, the Lord spoke to Peter to establish unity from one.
Immediately after, He gave the same command to all, beginning with Peter:
"And I say to you that you are Peter, and on this rock, I will build my Church, and the gates of hell will not prevail against it. I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven; and whatever you bind on earth shall be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven."
Matthew eighteen nineteen.
Tell me, brother, did He say this only to the Gentiles: "On this rock, I will build my Church"? Does He call the Church unbaptized nations? Is a man not yet reborn the body of Christ? What do I loose for the Gentiles if it is not bound? For if it is not accounted, it is not bound. What do I bind that I do not constrain by any law? A Gentile man is free from the Law.
See now, on the contrary, whether both apply to the baptized. Forgiveness is granted because he was held by sin; he is bound by anathema because he was released by faith and freed by grace. Even if I concede that this power to bind and loose was given to the Gentiles, I will prove much more that it pertains to the baptized. For if he who had no bond could be loosed or bound, how much more he who was held by the laws of faith?
Now, how cleverly you resolve that point which I raised about the power given to bishops, that what they bind on earth shall be bound in heaven. You say this pertains not to the faithful, but to catechumens, so that the sins of those about to be baptized might be loosed or held. You even combine the chapters of two Evangelists to make them appear as one, and you add that what Matthew less fully pursued, John completed:
for where Matthew wrote, "Go and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit,"
Matthew twenty-eight nineteen; John fulfilled it by saying: "If you forgive the sins of any, they are forgiven; if you retain the sins of any, they are retained."
John twenty twenty-three.
So, this binding or loosing seems to pertain to the nations that were to be baptized, because the first Evangelist spoke about the nations beforehand, while the latter fulfilled it regarding loosing and binding.
What do you think?
Did the two Evangelists present incomplete or half-formed ideas to each other?
Were they lacking in words or reasoning?
Or was the Holy Spirit not fully present in all things, carrying out the proposed meanings and fully defining the words?
No one overrides a confirmed human testament; so, will a different tablet change God's tablet?
Why do you have this desire to win, that you dare to say such things?
Consider that the Lord said to Matthew himself before His passion: Whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven (Matthew 16:19).
The Lord predicted this to Matthew without mentioning the nations: so why do you attach John's chapter to where He placed His own, separating it from the nations?
If He wanted it to pertain to the nations, He could have connected what He placed Himself.
Therefore, you have everything you need in Matthew.
Why didn't you read everything, you who teach the bishop?
Repeat the first part of this commandment.
As Matthew himself reports, the Lord spoke to Peter a little earlier; to one, to establish unity from one; soon after, giving the same command in common, but starting with Peter: And I say to you, you are Peter, and on this rock I will build my Church, and the gates of hell will not prevail against it.
And I will give you the keys to the kingdom of heaven: and whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven; and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven (Matthew 18:18-19).
Tell me, brother; did He speak only about the nations when He said: On this rock I will build my Church?
Does He call the Church the unbaptized nations?
Is a man not yet reborn the body of Christ?
What do I loose for the nations that is not bound?
If it is not considered, it is not bound either.
Why should I bind what I have no right to bind?
A Gentile, a non-Jew, is free from the Law.
Now consider the opposite case: does it apply to a baptized person?
Forgiveness is granted because he was bound by sin; he is bound by anathema because he was freed by faith and liberated by grace.
If I admit that the power to release or bind applies to Gentiles, then it is even more applicable to the baptized.
For if someone without a bond could be released or bound, how much more for one bound by the laws of faith?
You say that Matthew wrote: Matthew wrote: "If your brother sins against you, go and correct him privately" (Matthew 18:15); and immediately added the Lord's words: "Whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you release on earth will be released in heaven." So, it seems to pertain to the offense of a brother. But don't you see what he says above: "If your brother sins against you"; and here he adds: "Amen, I say to you. Whatever you bind on earth, etc." He commanded this to one person but gave permission to many: the former is released by the one against whom the offense is committed; the latter, by the Church: the former, without a priest or brothers; the latter, obtained by all. "Whatever you bind," he says; absolutely nothing is excluded. "Whatever," he says: whether great or small. Pay attention to what he says to Peter below: that what is sinned against a man should be forgiven seventy-seven times; to show that other offenses can be forgiven even once. However, whoever sins against Peter offends the Lord: as He himself indicated to Samuel: "They have not rejected you, but me" (First Samuel 8:7).
Therefore, it is granted to the Church even once, what is commanded of us many times.
You say that Matthew wrote: "If your brother sins against you, go and correct him privately" (Matthew 18:15); and immediately added the Lord's words: "Whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you release on earth will be released in heaven." So, it seems to pertain to the offense of a brother. But don't you see what he says above: "If your brother sins against you"; and here he adds: "Amen, I say to you. Whatever you bind on earth, etc."
He commanded one thing to a single person but permitted this to many: the former He Himself forgives for the one who sins against Him; but this, the Church does: the former, without a priest and without brothers; the latter is obtained by all.
"Whatever you forgive," He says; He makes no exception at all. "Whatever," He says: whether big or small. Observe what He says to Peter below, that what is sinned against a man must be forgiven seventy times seven; to show that otherwise, it could perhaps be forgiven even once. However, whoever sins against Peter offends the Lord, as He Himself makes clear to Samuel: "They have not rejected you, but me" First Samuel 8:7. Therefore, it is granted to the Church even once, what is commanded to us so many times.
Now let's return to the wandering sheep, the lost coin, and the younger son, which I briefly mentioned in my previous writing, and you have repeated in full, teaching and showing that the coin, the sheep, and the younger son relate to tax collectors and sinners; that is, to the humble people, not to the image of the Christian congregation, nor to the form of the faithful. I am glad to be taught, but I regret that it is not understood. For what should I assert? Whatever the law says, it says to those who are under the law Romans 3:19; indeed, I agree that this was also said primarily to the former, but in the form of the faithful, but in the image of the future, as the Apostle says: "These things happened to them as examples and were written down as warnings for us, on whom the culmination of the ages has come" First Corinthians 10:11. And again: "These were a shadow of the good things to come" Hebrews 10:1. Certainly, you agree, to tax collectors and sinners, that is, to the humble people, and therefore younger, those were dictated. So tell me: is the Christian people themselves younger? Have they adhered to the root? Have they joined those members? Built, as it is written, on the foundation of the apostles and prophets, with Christ Jesus Himself as the chief cornerstone Ephesians 2:20. Or is He the God of the Jews only? Is He not also the God of the Gentiles? Indeed, He is also the God of the Gentiles. Since there is one God, who justifies the ungodly by faith and through faith Romans 3:29, 30.
Certainly, the humble people, whom God compared to a coin, the younger son, and the little sheep, represent the Church.
From this Church came all believers, forming the Christian people.
We are also members of this body, grafted into the good olive tree from the wild olive tree of the Gentiles, as the Apostle says: "Partakers of its richness" (Romans 11:17).
Thus, we all become one in Christ, Jew and Greek, slave and free (Galatians 3:28).
So, if we are one body with the humble, the words spoken to the humble of old were also spoken to us.
Therefore, whatever was preached to a part of the body was announced to the whole body.
Now let's return to the wandering sheep, the coin, and the younger son: examples I briefly touched upon earlier, and you elaborated on, teaching that the coin, sheep, and younger son pertain to tax collectors and sinners; that is, the humble people.
Not to the image of the Christian community, nor to the form of the faithful.
I am glad to be taught; but I am displeased that it is not understood.
What shall I assert?
Whatever the law says, it speaks to those under the law (Romans 3:19).
Certainly, I agree this is primarily addressed to the former ones, but in the form of the faithful, and in the image of the future, as the Apostle says: "These things happened to them as examples and were written down as warnings for us, on whom the culmination of the ages has come" (First Corinthians 10:11).
And again: "These are a shadow of the good things to come" (Hebrews 10:1).
Certainly, you agree that these things were said to tax collectors and sinners, that is, the humble people, and therefore the younger ones.
So tell me: is the Christian people itself the younger one?
Have they been grafted into the root?
Have they joined those members?
Built, as it is written, on the foundation of the apostles and prophets, with Christ Jesus Himself as the cornerstone (Ephesians 2:20).
Is He the God of the Jews only?
Is He not also the God of the Gentiles?
Yes, also of the Gentiles.
Since there is one God who justifies the ungodly by faith and through faith (Romans 3:29-30).
Surely that humble people, whom God compared to a coin, the younger son, and a little sheep, was the Church.
From this came the whole crowd of believers, from which the Christian people emerged.
Our members are also joined to this body, all portions of believers, so that they might be grafted into the good olive tree from the wild olive tree of the nations, as the Apostle says: "Partakers of its richness" in the book of Romans chapter eleven, verse seventeen. And so, we all might be one in Christ, Jew and Greek, slave and free, as stated in Galatians chapter three, verse twenty-eight. Therefore, if we are one body with those humble ones, the words spoken to the humble of old are also spoken to us. Thus, whatever was preached about a part of the body was announced to the whole body.
Let me be clearer. That later people, that poor, that average, was an image of the Church, a humble and modest soul, a soul freed by Christ. The Lord came to save this, did not leave it in hell: this is the sheep carried back on the shoulders, that is, by the effort and strength of patience. This is the coin that is sought and shown to the neighbors when found. Do you see how its form matches the likeness of the repentant? Do you see mercy extending to this time? Do you see that whatever was said to the nascent Church pertains to the fullness of the Church? Hence, the Lord added there: "There will be joy in heaven over one sinner who repents, more than over ninety-nine righteous persons who do not need repentance" as found in Luke chapter fifteen, verse seven. For if all those things were written to remind us, to whom then will that humble sinner people be compared, if not to the repentant people? And if the figures recur in order, the ninety-nine healthy represent the whole Church. The one wandering is the portion of the delinquent, and the lost coin is that miserable sinner. Returning after his wrongs, he is considered similar to the redeemed one. Now you see rightly placed by me, when I was dealing with the cure of the repentant, that the Lord said: "Those who are well have no need of a physician, but those who are sick" in Matthew chapter nine, verse twelve. Rightly also: "Blessed are those who mourn, for they shall be comforted" as stated in Matthew chapter five, verse five.
Whatever has been said about tax collectors and sinners will apply to all the sick and all the wretched.
Let me speak more clearly: that latter group of people, the poor, the average, represents the Church, a humble and modest soul liberated by Christ.
The Lord came to save this soul and did not leave it in hell: this is the sheep that is brought back on the shoulders, that is, by the effort and strength of patience.
This is the coin that is sought and, once found, is shown to the neighbors.
Do you see how its form matches the image of penitents?
Do you see how mercy extends up to this time?
Do you see that whatever was said to the nascent Church applies to the fullness of the Church?
Hence, the Lord added: So there will be joy in heaven over one sinner who repents, more than over ninety-nine righteous persons who do not need repentance (Luke 15:7).
If all those things were written to remind us, to whom will that humble sinful people be compared, if not to the penitent people?
And if in recurring figures, the ninety-nine healthy ones represent the whole Church; the one wandering represents the portion of the delinquent; and the lost coin is the miserable sinner: the returning son after his wrongdoings is considered similar to the redeemed one.
Now you see correctly, as I laid it out, when dealing with the healing of penitents, the Lord said: It is not the healthy who need a doctor, but the sick (Matthew 9:12).
And rightly so: Blessed are those who mourn, for they will be comforted (Matthew 5:5).
Whatever has been said about tax collectors and sinners will apply to all the sick and all the wretched.
You say it is written only about the martyrs: Blessed are those who mourn.
So, does no one else besides them mourn their sins?
Doesn't David cry out: Every night I flood my bed with tears (Psalm 6:7)?
And again: For I eat ashes like bread and mingle my drink with tears (Psalm 102:10).
Doesn't Jacob say: The years of my life have been few and hard (Genesis 47:9)?
Doesn't the Apostle say to Timothy: Longing to see you, remembering your tears (Second Timothy 1:4)?
And yet he was not speaking of a martyr.
What now?
Are miserable penitents supposed to have dry eyes?
And do those who regret their sins not know how to cry?
We who partake in communion and are faithful, do we not have tears?
Does it please any of us to rejoice while the world rejoices?
You Novatians are already satisfied, you have become rich, you have begun to reign without us.
First Corinthians chapter 4, verse 8.
Thus, not everyone who is miserable begins to be pitiable.
After this, you propose and say it is written by the Lord: "Every sin and blasphemy will be forgiven people; but whoever sins against the Holy Spirit will not be forgiven, neither in this world nor in the future."
Matthew chapter 12, verses 31 to 32.
Either I am mistaken, or this example works against you. For if every sin and blasphemy will be forgiven, you see that forgiveness is not denied to the penitent. Therefore every sin, therefore even blasphemy itself.
You have what is added according to Luke: "And whoever speaks a word against the Son of Man will be forgiven."
Luke chapter 12, verse 10.
What more can be said about the mercy of God, about the clemency of the judge? Is your eye envious because the head of the household is good?
Matthew chapter 20, verse 15.
Is it not lawful for him to do what he wants? Indeed, who are you to judge another's servant? To his own master, he stands or falls; and he will stand, for God is able to make him stand.
Romans chapter 14, verse 4.
But you say, whoever blasphemes against the Holy Spirit will not be forgiven.
Matthew chapter 12, verse 32.
You are accustomed to reading the whole passages; why did you not read here what it means, "In the Spirit"? You have it written above, when the Lord was casting out demons by His word, and performing many miracles with special power, the Pharisees said: "This man does not cast out demons except by Beelzebub, the prince of demons."
Matthew chapter 12, verse 24.
This means sinning against the Holy Spirit, blaspheming what was done through the Holy Spirit. In other sins, we either stumble out of error, break from fear, or are overcome by the weakness of the flesh. This blindness is not seeing what you see, and attributing the works of the Holy Spirit to the devil, and calling the glory of the Lord by which the devil himself is overcome, the power of the devil.
This, therefore, is what will not be forgiven: the rest are forgiven to good penitents, brother Symproniane.
About the sun, you say it is written about the martyrs:
"Blessed are those who mourn."
Does that mean no one else laments their sins? Doesn't David cry out:
"I drench my bed every night" (Psalm 6:7)?
And again:
"I have eaten ashes like bread and mingled my drink with tears" (Psalm 102:10)?
Doesn't Jacob say:
"The years of my life have been hard" (Genesis 47:9)?
Doesn't the Apostle say to Timothy:
"Longing to see you, remembering your tears" (Second Timothy 1:4)?
And yet, he wasn't talking about a martyr.
So what now?
Do miserable penitents have dry eyes?
And do those who regret their sins not know how to weep?
Don't we, who share in this, who are faithful, have tears ourselves?
Does it please any of us to rejoice while the world rejoices?
You Novatians, are you already satisfied, made rich, and have begun to reign without us (First Corinthians 4:8)?
Therefore, isn't anyone who is miserable deserving of pity?
You then propose and say it is written by the Lord:
"Every sin and blasphemy will be forgiven men; but whoever blasphemes against the Holy Spirit will not be forgiven, either in this age or in the age to come" (Matthew 12:31-32).
Either I am mistaken, or this example works against you.
For if every sin and blasphemy will be forgiven, you see that forgiveness is not denied to penitents.
Therefore, every sin, yes, even blasphemy.
According to Luke, it is added:
"And whoever speaks a word against the Son of Man will be forgiven" (Luke 12:10).
What more can be said about God’s mercy, about the clemency of the judge?
Is your eye envious because the father of the household is good (Matthew 20:15)?
Is it not lawful for Him to do what He wants?
Indeed, who are you to judge another's servant?
To his own master, he stands or falls: And God is able to make him stand (Romans 14:4).
But you say,
"Whoever blasphemes against the Holy Spirit will not be forgiven" (Matthew 12:32).
You often go through entire readings: why didn't you read here what it means to be "in the Spirit"?
You mentioned earlier that when the Lord cast out demons with a word and performed many miracles with special power, the Pharisees said:
"This man does not cast out demons except by Beelzebub, the prince of demons"
Matthew 12:24.
This means they had sinned against the Holy Spirit by blaspheming the works done through the Holy Spirit.
With other sins, we either fall through error, break under fear, or are overcome by the weakness of the flesh.
This blindness is failing to see what is evident and attributing the works of the Holy Spirit to the devil, calling the glory of the Lord, by which the devil is overcome, the power of the devil.
This is what will not be forgiven; other sins are forgiven to those who truly repent, brother Symproniane.
After this, you refer to the branches and the vine.
The Lord says in John: "I am the true vine, and my Father is the farmer. Every branch in me that does not bear fruit, He will take away; and every branch that bears fruit, He will prune"
John 15:1-2.
Therefore, you see that fruit is required in the branches, meaning good works of repentance, as John says: "Produce fruit worthy of repentance"
Matthew 3:8.
You see that the branches are pruned, which symbolizes the losses of the flesh, the losses of joy, the losses of possessions, and the labors of life; these are the actions typical of those who repent.
You also see the farming of the Lord, who does not lose even those branches but prunes and gathers them, some clearly for the fire, others for planting and tending vineyards.
Eli the priest, you say, speaks and says: "If a man sins against another man, they will pray for him; but if a man sins against God, who will pray for him?"
First Samuel 2:25.
John likewise says: "If anyone sees his brother committing a sin not leading to death, he shall ask, and God will give him life. There is a sin leading to death; I do not say that he should make a request for this"
First John 5:16.
You see, this all pertains to ongoing sins, not to those who have sinned at some time and have begun to repent before anyone prays for them.
It would take too long to repeat all the examples.
Consider all the sins for which the Lord threatens; you will see they are present sins.
If past righteousness doesn't benefit the righteous person at the time of their iniquity, then past iniquity won't harm the wicked person at the time of their righteousness.
As it is written: Let the wicked abandon their ways, and the unrighteous their thoughts; let them return to God, and they will receive mercy.
(Isaiah 55:7)
If God punished past sins and established retribution for past actions, then surely He has the power to change His mind?
Did He not save Rahab, King Nebuchadnezzar, the Gibeonites, the Ninevites, and Zoar from predicted destruction?
Through the prophet Joel, He said: Return to the Lord your God with fasting, weeping, and mourning; for He is merciful, patient, and long-suffering, full of compassion, and repents of evil.
And who knows if He will turn and relent, and leave behind a blessing?
(Joel 2:12-14)
Therefore, whenever you see punishment established for sinners, understand it either as punishment for those who persist in sin, or as God’s freedom to change His decision if you repent and turn to better ways.
After this, you propose the analogy of the branches and the vine as follows: The Lord says in John: I am the true vine, and my Father is the gardener.
Every branch in me that does not bear fruit, He takes away; and every branch that does bear fruit, He prunes.
(John 15:1)
So, you see that fruit is required from the branches, meaning good works of repentance, as John says: Produce fruit in keeping with repentance.
(Matthew 3:8) You see that the branches are pruned, which signifies the losses of the flesh, the losses of joy, the losses of inheritance, and the labors of life; these are the proper acts of those who repent.
You also see the Lord’s gardening, who does not lose the branches but prunes and gathers them, some clearly for the fire, and some for replanting and tending to the vineyards.
You say that Eli the priest speaks and says: If a person sins against another person, they will pray for him; but if a person sins against God, who will pray for him?
(First Samuel 2:25)
John also says: If anyone sees his brother committing a sin that does not lead to death, he should pray for him, and God will grant him life.
There is a sin that leads to death; I am not saying that he should pray about that.
First John 5:16.
You see, this pertains to ongoing sins, not to those who have sinned at some point and then begun to repent before anyone prays for them.
It would take too long to recount examples.
Consider all the sins that the Lord warns about; you will see that they are present.
If past righteousness does not benefit the righteous person in his time of iniquity, then past iniquity will not harm the wicked person in his time of righteousness.
Ezekiel 18:24.
As it is written: Let the wicked forsake his ways and the unrighteous man his thoughts; let him return to God, and He will have mercy on him.
Isaiah 55:7.
If God even punished past sins and established penalties for past and overlooked actions, does He not have the power to change His decision?
Did He not save Rahab, King Nebuchadnezzar, the Gibeonites, the Ninevites, and Zoar from the foretold destruction?
Did not the prophet Joel convey this: Return to the Lord your God with fasting, weeping, and mourning; for He is gracious, compassionate, slow to anger, abounding in love, and relents from sending calamity.
Who knows, He may turn and relent and leave behind a blessing.
Joel 2:12-14.
Therefore, wherever you find a punishment established for sinners, you will understand that it is either established for those who persist in sin or that it leaves God the freedom to change His decision if you repent and turn towards better things.
You still say, it is written: If your hand or your foot causes you to sin, cut it off and throw it away.
Matthew 5:29.
Moses already explained what this means, as testified in Deuteronomy: If your brother, the child of your own mother, or your son or daughter, or the wife you cherish, or your closest friend secretly entices you, saying, "Let us go and serve other gods." Deuteronomy 13:6.
Then he added below: "You will bring him, and your hand will be upon him to kill him."
You see, therefore, it is not said about those who repent, but about those who persist in their crime and continue to scandalize us. These people, no matter how dear they are, must be left behind; no matter how useful, they must be abandoned.
You still propose that the Apostle Paul said: "Remove the evil from among yourselves" (First Corinthians 5:13): certainly, persistent evil.
Otherwise, repentance is not evil, as David says: "It is good to confess to God" (Psalm 111:2).
Nevertheless, he who repents is not with me, nor is he united with the saints or peace.
But the Apostle says: "If someone is called a brother and is either a fornicator, an idolater, greedy, a slanderer, a drunkard, or a robber, do not even eat with such a person" (First Corinthians 5:11).
You see it is not without reason that it is said, "and is," that is, someone who has not yet repented, who has not yet ceased to be wicked. And certainly, it is said equally about the greedy, drunkards, and slanderers. Answer, brother, is there no one of this kind held in your peace?
Therefore, it is from there that God cries out through Isaiah: "The wicked and the sinners shall perish together" (Isaiah 1:28); not those who repent, not those who seek works of mercy, to whom God again says through the same Isaiah: "Though your sins are like scarlet, they shall be as white as snow; though they are red like crimson, they shall become like wool" (Isaiah 1:18).
You still say, it is written: "If your hand or your foot causes you to stumble, cut it off and throw it away from you" (Matthew 5:29).
What this means, Moses foretold in Deuteronomy: "If your brother (for these are our eyes and hands), or your daughter, or the wife in your bosom, or your friend who is as your own soul, entices you, saying: 'Let us go and serve other gods whom you have not known'" (Deuteronomy 13:6).
Then he added below: "You will bring him, and your hand will be upon him to kill him."
You see, therefore, it is not said about those who repent, but about those who persist in their crime and continue to scandalize us.
No matter how dear they are, they must be left behind; no matter how useful they are, they must be abandoned.
You still propose that the Apostle Paul said: Remove the wicked person from among you (First Corinthians 5:13), certainly the wicked who persist.
However, repentance is not evil, as David says: It is good to confess to the Lord (Psalm 111:2).
Yet, the one who repents is not with me, nor is he united with the saints or in peace.
But the Apostle says: If anyone who is called a brother is sexually immoral or worships idols, or is greedy, or abusive, or a drunkard, or a swindler, do not even eat with such a person (First Corinthians 5:11).
It is not without reason that it is said, and is, who has not yet repented, who has not yet ceased to be wicked.
And certainly, it is also said about the greedy, the drunkards, and the abusive.
Answer, brother, is there no one like this among you?
Therefore, it is because of this that God cries out through Isaiah: The rebels and sinners will perish together (Isaiah 1:28); not those who repent, not those who perform works of mercy, to whom God again says through the same Isaiah: Though your sins are like scarlet, they shall be as white as snow; though they are red as crimson, they shall be like wool (Isaiah 1:18).
However, as you say, the Apostle condemned the wrongdoer.
For he says to the Corinthians: Even though I am not physically present, I am with you in spirit.
And I have already passed judgment on the one who did this, just as if I were present.
When you are assembled in the name of our Lord Jesus and I am with you in spirit, and the power of our Lord Jesus is present, hand this man over to Satan for the destruction of the flesh, so that his spirit may be saved on the day of the Lord (First Corinthians 5:3-5).
Note, brother, first, that he does not condemn those with whom this man communicates; only he who committed such a deed is handed over to Satan, only he is excluded, preserving the peace of the saints.
Do you condemn all churches for one sinner?
Then you see, this very incestuous sinner is not handed over to death, but to Satan, for correction, for discipline, for repentance.
Finally, he says, "To the destruction of the flesh, but not of the soul, not even of the spirit: but to the destruction of the flesh alone, namely the temptations, the sufferings of the flesh, the loss of members, just as he says elsewhere about the undisciplined: 'They will suffer tribulation of the flesh' (First Corinthians 7:28).
"
Do you want to know this? In the second letter to the Corinthians, the same Paul absolves this same wicked person. About him, he says: "For such a one, this punishment by the majority is enough; so instead you should rather forgive and comfort him, lest he be overwhelmed by excessive sorrow. So I urge you to reaffirm your love for him" (Second Corinthians 2:6-8).
Further down: "If you forgive anyone, I also forgive him. And what I have forgiven—if there was anything to forgive—I have forgiven in the presence of Christ for your sake, so that Satan might not outwit us" (Second Corinthians 2:10).
Do you see the Apostle's leniency, even moderating his own decisions?
Do you see the gentleness, so far removed from your arrogance?
So different from the severity of Novatian, considering the common life and salvation of all?
Nevertheless, as you say, the Apostle condemned the wrongdoer.
For in the first letter to the Corinthians, he says: "Even though I am not physically present, I am with you in spirit. And I have already passed judgment on the one who did this, just as if I were present. When you are assembled in the name of our Lord Jesus and I am with you in spirit, and the power of our Lord Jesus is present, hand this man over to Satan for the destruction of the flesh, so that his spirit may be saved on the day of the Lord" (First Corinthians 5:3-5).
Note, brother, first, that he does not condemn those with whom this man associates: he alone who committed this sin is handed over to Satan, he alone is excluded, with the peace of the saints preserved.
Do you condemn all churches for one sinner?
Furthermore, you see that this same incestuous sinner is not handed over to death, but to Satan, for correction, for punishment, for repentance.
Finally, he says, "To the destruction of the flesh, but not of the soul, not even of the spirit: but to the destruction of the flesh alone, namely the temptations, the sufferings of the flesh, the loss of members, just as he says elsewhere about the undisciplined: 'They will suffer tribulation of the flesh' (First Corinthians 7:28).
Do you want to know this?
"
In the second letter to the Corinthians, Paul himself forgives this same impious person.
He says: "For such a one, this punishment by the majority is enough; so you should rather forgive and comfort him, lest he be overwhelmed by excessive sorrow. Therefore, I urge you to reaffirm your love for him" Second Corinthians 2:6-8. And later: "If you forgive anyone, I also forgive him. And what I have forgiven—if there was anything to forgive—I have forgiven in the sight of Christ for your sake, in order that Satan might not outwit us" Second Corinthians 2:10.
Do you see the Apostle's leniency, even moderating his own judgments? Do you see the gentle mildness, far removed from your arrogance? It's far different from the sternness of Novatian, but rather concerned with the common life and the salvation of all.
Yet you also criticize us severely. You say that it is not permissible to break even one of the heavenly commandments, nor to associate sheep with wolves, and that every agreement in crime is wrong; and therefore, those who touch pitch will be defiled Sirach 13:1; nor is there any fellowship between light and darkness, or between the temple of God and idols, or any agreement between Christ and Belial Second Corinthians 6:14-15. Therefore, David says: "When you saw a thief, you consented with him, and you have been a partaker with adulterers" Psalm 50:18.
You finally say that we nullify the Lord's commandments. Do we bend even one iota of the Law; or rather, do the Novatians, who have violated all the laws of the Church and harmony, who after so many years of peace and so many holy covenants, have created new laws, new institutions, and new rites for themselves, feigning the mystery of justice with an unyielding demeanor? Did we receive wolves into the Church, while avoiding the mouths of heretics; or rather the Novatians, who, being ravenous wolves themselves, fear the slightly more pitiful little sheep? Do we consent to evil, touch the pitch, cling to darkness, join with idols and Belial; or rather those who received Evaristus, Nicostratus, and others who withdrew from the Church, defiled in speech, actions, and morals?
We encounter adulterers and thieves, or those who preferred Novatus over their own lives and well-being, after embezzling the money of orphans and widows.
The wretched parent and the wife’s childbirth murderer, not only unrepentant but even boasting?
But the Apostle Paul said in 1 Timothy chapter 5, verse 21, "Do not be hasty in the laying on of hands."
He teaches the same; whether late or after repentance, they should not be denied.
Moreover, you will be a severe critic against us.
You say, according to the heavenly law, it is not allowed to break one of the commandments, nor to join lambs with wolves, and that every agreement in crime is forbidden.
Therefore, he who touches pitch will be defiled, as it is written in Sirach chapter 13, verse 1.
Nor should there be any fellowship of light with darkness, or the temple of God with idols, or the union of Christ with Belial, as stated in 2 Corinthians chapter 6, verses 14 and 15.
Therefore, David says in Psalm chapter 49, verse 18, "You saw a thief and ran with him, and you shared your portion with adulterers."
You finally say that we nullify the Lord’s commandments.
We bend one jot of the Law; or rather the Novatians, who violated all the rights of the Church, all the laws of harmony, who after so many years of peace, so many covenants of sanctity, created new laws, new institutions, new rites for themselves, pretending an uncompromising front of justice?
We received wolves into the Church, who avoid the mouths of heretics; or rather the Novatians, who, being ravenous wolves themselves, fear the slightly more miserable little sheep?
We agree with the evildoers, we touch pitch, we cling to darkness, we join with idols and Belial; or those who received Evaristus, who received Nicostratus, and others who departed from the Church, defiled in speech, hand, and manners?
We encounter adulterers and thieves, or those who preferred Novatus over their own lives and well-being, after embezzling the money of orphans and widows.
The wretched parent and the wife’s childbirth murderer, not only unrepentant but even boasting?
But the Apostle Paul said in 1 Timothy chapter 5, verse 21, "Do not be hasty in the laying on of hands."
He teaches the same; whether late or after repentance, they should not be denied.
But when Jericho was lost, Achan, the son of Carmi, was killed because of the theft of a garment.
Come on, you, kill all the thieves of our money and books; and rage against the bones of Novatus.
Take up again that yoke which neither we nor our ancestors could bear.
Acts chapter 15, verse 10.
Why do you delay, Novatians, to demand an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth?
Deuteronomy chapter 19, verse 21.
To ask for a life, to restore the practice of Circumcision and the Sabbath?
Kill the thieves, stone the insolent ones.
Do you not read in the Gospel that the Lord spared even the adulteress who confessed?
John chapter 8, verse 11.
Whom no one condemned: that he forgave the sinful woman who washed his feet with her tears; that he saved Rahab in the very city of Jericho of the Phoenicians; that he absolved Tamar from the judgment of the patriarch; that, even when Sodom was perishing, he did not destroy the daughters of Lot; he would have also saved their sons-in-law if they had believed in the impending doom.
Come on, do you not recall saying to the Lord with David: "With those who hate peace, I was peaceful." Psalm chapter 120, verse 7.
Do not ignore the saying of Solomon either: "A brother helping a brother will be exalted." Proverbs chapter 18, verse 9.
What about the Apostle? "Brothers, if someone is caught in a sin, you who are spiritual should restore that person gently, considering yourselves lest you also be tempted. Carry each other’s burdens, and in this way, you will fulfill the law of Christ." Galatians chapter 6, verses 1 and 2.
And what I already mentioned before: "For I could wish that I myself were cursed and cut off from Christ for the sake of my people, those of my own race." Romans chapter 9, verse 3.
And again: "I have become all things to all people so that by all possible means I might save some." First Corinthians chapter 9, verse 22.
That is, to share the groans with the wounded, the toil with the sick; to share death with the dying, to mix the fall of brothers with their state, to give up something of one's own health, and to provide medicine to the failing ones.
But when Jericho was lost, Achan, the son of Carmi, was killed because of the theft of a garment. Come on; you, kill all the thieves of our money and books; and rage against the bones of Novatus.
Take up that yoke again, which neither we nor our ancestors were able to bear.
(Acts 15:10)
Why do you hesitate, Novatians, to demand an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth?
(Deuteronomy 19:21)
To demand a life, to restore the practice of circumcision and the Sabbath?
Kill thieves, stone the insolent.
Don’t you read in the Gospel that the Lord spared even the confessing adulteress, whom no one condemned?
That He forgave the sinner who washed His feet with her tears?
That He saved Rahab in the city of Jericho of the Phoenicians?
That He absolved Tamar from the judgment of the patriarch?
That, even when Sodom was destroyed, He did not kill Lot’s daughters?
He would have saved their sons-in-law too, if they had believed in the coming destruction.
(John 8:11)
Come on; don’t you remember to say to the Lord with David: With those who hated peace, I was peaceful?
(Psalm 119:7)
And not to ignore Solomon’s saying: A brother helping a brother will be exalted.
(Proverbs 18:9)
What does the Apostle say?
Brothers, if someone is caught in a sin, you who are spiritual should restore that person gently, watching yourselves so you also may not be tempted.
Carry each other’s burdens, and in this way you will fulfill the law of Christ.
(Galatians 6:1, 2)
And what I mentioned before: For I could wish that I myself were cursed and cut off from Christ for the sake of my people, those of my own race.
(Romans 9:3)
And again: I have become all things to all people so that by all possible means I might save some.
That is, to share cries with the wounded; to share labor with the sick; to share death with the dying; to mix the fall of brothers with one’s own state, to give up something of one’s own health, and to provide medicine to those failing.
(1 Corinthians 9:22)
What good does it do you to harden your face with pride and harshness, to govern with lofty necks, to turn your face away from the miserable, to shut your ears and eyes?
Have you never, I ask, fallen?
Is there no stain in your minds?
Is there no speck in your eyes, I ask?
Who will boast of having a pure heart, or of being clean from sins?
(Proverbs 20:9, according to the Septuagint)
I believe you, the just, the kind, the temperate, who have all your limbs healthy, whose entire body is intact, who do not need a doctor or medicine for ailments, can enter heaven now.
The gates of paradise are open; with the sword yielding, penetrate.
With so many of our people confessing the one God, close off your gifts.
But if circumstances are far different and your cruelty prevails, now you understand, Novatians, that God can have mercy.
Now, let the medicine, though late, be available to our unfortunate brothers confessing their past.
Now, the one wounded and neglected by the Levite and priest can be healed through Christ.
Now, the prayers of the Church must not be denied to the humble.
Now, the hands of the priests must be extended to these miserable brothers.
We understand your reproach, but the Church of God is a dove, not bitter with gall, not violent with tearing claws, even with small and tiny feathers.
We also know the well of living water and the sealed fountain, untainted by the filth of a heretic's whirlpool, and the enclosed garden full of great and small vegetables, both cheap and precious.
Consider the eight souls from the ark, among them Ham, and those thousands of birds and beasts, clean and unclean alike, by pairs and by sevens.
We think of the dry fountains and the clouds stirred by whirlwinds as the sterility of heretics and the force of insane voices.
We do not promise freedom while we ourselves are slaves to punishment; but having confessed our crimes, we urge others to confess as well and to believe in Him who justifies the ungodly by faith Romans 3:26, who reverses the judgment imposed against wickedness Joel 2:13.
We also heed the false prophets and ravenous wolves, as we guard against you Matthew 7:15.
We remember Jannes and Jambres who opposed Moses, just as you oppose the Catholics.
Thus the Apostle says: Just as Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses, so these men also oppose the truth.
They are men of corrupt minds, disapproved by God; but they will not get very far, for their folly will be plain to all, as was that of those two men 2 Timothy.
It is clear that you have been criticized for your inability to improve and for displaying your foolishness.
What good does it do to maintain a proud and harsh demeanor, to carry yourself with arrogance, to turn away from those in need, and to close your ears and eyes?
Have you never made mistakes?
Is there no flaw in your thinking?
No imperfection in your vision?
Who can truly claim to have a pure heart or be free from sins?
Proverbs 20:9 according to the Septuagint.
I believe you are just, benevolent, temperate, with all your limbs healthy and your whole body intact, not needing a doctor or medicine for ailments.
Enter heaven now; pass through the gates of paradise with confidence; and keep your gifts from those who confess the one true God.
If reality is far harsher and your unforgiving cruelty persists, then understand, Novatians, that God can show mercy.
For the brothers who confess their past sins, even late, let the remedy be available.
Now, the one wounded and ignored by the Levite and priest can be healed through Christ.
Now, the prayers of the Church should not be denied to the humble, and the hands of the priests should be extended to the pitiable brothers.
We, however, understand, as you criticize, that the Church of God is like a dove, not bitter or violent, even if small and delicate.
We also know the well of living water and the sealed fountain, untainted by the heretic's stain, and the enclosed garden full of various plants, both insignificant and valuable.
Eight souls were saved in the ark, including Ham, along with thousands of birds and animals, clean and unclean alike.
But we see the dry springs and stormy clouds as symbols of the sterility of heretics and the rage of senseless voices.
We do not promise freedom, as we ourselves are bound by punishment.
But having confessed our sins, we encourage others to confess and believe in Him who justifies the ungodly by faith.
Romans
Who reverses a decision against the malice inflicted (Joel 2:13, according to the Septuagint).
We guard against false prophets and ravenous wolves when we beware of you (Matthew 7:15).
Indeed, we believe that Jannes and Jambres resisted Moses, just as you resist Catholics.
The Apostle states: Just as Jannes and Jambres resisted Moses, so do these resist the truth—people with corrupt minds and rejected by God.
But they will not get very far, for their foolishness will be obvious to everyone, just as that of those men was (Second Timothy 3:8-9).
This clearly applies to you, who cannot advance any further nor hide your foolishness.
He who is baptized by a dead person gains nothing (Ecclesiasticus 34:30).
Similarly, he who is washed in a heretical font, or anointed with a sinner's oil, is filled with an unclean spirit.
Therefore, you will also be sons of blood.
For you desire not the peace of the brothers, but blood.
Your belief is a false faith.
An adulterous woman is like a heretical congregation:
For the Catholic Church, from the beginning, has not left her husband's bed and chamber, nor desired other lovers or strangers.
You have painted an exiled image with a new color;
you have separated your bed from the ancient union;
you have distanced yourself from the body of the one-bedded mother, adorned with new methods of pleasing and new enticements of corruption.
When you propose the most blessed Cyprian as a witness against me, because in the Epistle concerning the Lapsed, he says that Moses, Daniel, and Job prayed for sinners and did not obtain what they asked for, with the Lord saying:
And if three men were in the midst of them, Noah, Job, and Daniel, they would not save sons or daughters, but they alone would be saved (Ezekiel 14:20).
If only you would rely on Cyprian as a witness, if only you would agree with such healthful sentiments.
For he, when he urged the lapsed to repentance who did not want to repent, saying that they had received peace from confessors or martyrs, taught and showed that even those patriarchs would not obtain anything for those who do not repent.
Indeed, who can free an unwilling person?
Who can humble himself for the proud?
Who can intercede for those who do not repent?
When he said this, he was urging them towards the remedies of repentance.
A man of such seriousness and merit did not speak against himself but taught that sinners should offer prayers and practice confession diligently.
Cyprian’s own examples illustrate this, recalling that neither Moses nor other saints were able to intercede for sinners.
Those who are baptized by the dead gain nothing.
As it is written in Ecclesiasticus thirty-four, verse thirty: “Indeed, those who are washed in the font of heretics are like those anointed with the oil of sinners, that is, those who are filled with an unclean spirit.
” Therefore, you will be children of bloodshed.
For you do not desire the peace of the brothers, but blood.
Your faith is false, your belief is deceitful.
The heretical congregation is like an adulterous woman: for the Catholic Church has never left the bed and chamber of her husband from the beginning, nor has she desired other lovers or strangers.
You have painted an exiled form with a new color; you have separated your bed from the ancient marriage; you have departed from the body of the one true mother, adorned with a new kind of pleasing and new enticements of corruption.
You present the most blessed Cyprian to me as a witness against me because in the letter concerning the Lapsed, he says that Moses, Daniel, and Job prayed for sinners but did not succeed, as the Lord says: “Even if Noah, Job, and Daniel were in their midst, they would not save their sons or daughters, but they alone would be saved” (Ezekiel fourteen, verse twenty).
If only you would rely on Cyprian as a witness and agree with such sound opinions.
When urging the lapsed to repentance, who did not want to repent and claimed they had received peace from confessors or martyrs, he taught that even those patriarchs could not intercede for the unrepentant.
Indeed, who can free someone who is unwilling?
Who can humble themselves for the proud?
Who can intercede for those who do not repent?
When he said this, he was urging them towards the remedies of repentance.
A man of such seriousness and merit did not speak against himself but taught that sinners should offer prayers and practice confession diligently.
However, consider Cyprian's examples, where he notes that even Moses and other saints didn't always succeed in their petitions for sinners.
Really?
Don't you see for whom Moses didn't succeed?
When he returned to the people, what did he hear in the camp?
The voices of drunkards and the songs of idol worship resounded.
The people still persisted in wickedness, still remained in their very crimes, and didn't know how to repent.
Yet, who among us told you that Moses didn't succeed?
God had indeed said to him: "He has sinned before me, I will erase him from the book" (Exodus 32:33).
However, God spoke with the authority of a judge and the power of the Lord; but see how quickly he changed his sentence against the people's wickedness.
Listen.
The prophet immediately said: "And Moses prayed before the Lord, his God; Why, Lord, are you so angry with your people?" and the rest (Exodus 32:21).
Further down: "And the Lord was appeased from the harm which he said he would do to his people" (Exodus 32:14).
Do you see that God's anger was softened?
Do you see that the offense was placated?
And Moses didn't pray for the people, nor did he repent for what he had done.
Really?
Don't you see for whom Moses didn't succeed?
When he returned to the people, what did he hear in the camp?
The voices of drunkards and the songs of idol worship resounded.
The people still persisted in wickedness, still remained in their very crimes, and didn't know how to repent.
Yet, who among us told you that Moses didn't succeed?
God had indeed said to him: "He has sinned before me, I will erase him from the book" (Exodus 32:33).
However, God spoke with the authority of a judge and the power of the Lord; but see how quickly he changed his sentence against the people's wickedness.
Listen.
The prophet immediately said: "And Moses prayed before the Lord, his God; Why, Lord, are you so angry with your people?" and the rest (Exodus 32:21).
Further down: "And the Lord was appeased from the harm which he said he would do to his people" (Exodus 32:14).
Do you see that God's anger was softened?
Do you see that the offense was placated?
And Moses didn't pray for the people, nor did he repent for what he had done.
But Noah, you say, and Daniel, and Job could not save their sons and daughters.
And this is the reason: if they ask for those who do not ask; if they intercede for those who persist in crime; if they defend not individuals, not a few, but many thousands.
However, Noah saved his own household from public ruin; and Job recovered everything he lost; and Daniel diverted that impending sword from the wise men of Babylon by his prayer.
Lot certainly prayed for the safety of the town, and Paul prayed for the passengers on the ship.
Thus, those who know how to repent are absolved by the just.
Finally, I observe what is written: Ezekiel 14:20: "They alone will be saved."
Who are they? Certainly, those who intercede for sinners. They will be able to ask for such things without punishment. And why do you condemn the Church? Why do you forbid praying for the repentant; if it is allowed to ask even for those for whom it is not allowed to obtain?
Therefore, read my Cyprian more diligently: read the entire letter on the Lapsed: read another which he gave to Antonianus; where Novatian is urged with all examples: you will already know what he pronounces about the treatment of the penitent.
I speak of Cyprian, who opposes your views and retains the rights of the Catholic Church. After his heresy (for you have taken many things from him) you will hear Tertullian himself confessing in his letter, and the very one he published as a Catholic, that the Church has the power to forgive sins.
But Noah, you say, and Daniel, and Job could not save their sons and daughters.
And this is the reason: if they ask for those who do not ask; if they intercede for those who persist in crime; if they defend not individuals, not a few, but many thousands.
However, Noah saved his own household from public ruin; and Job recovered everything he lost; and Daniel diverted that impending sword from the wise men of Babylon by his prayer.
Lot certainly prayed for the safety of the town, and Paul prayed for the passengers on the ship.
Thus, those who know how to repent are absolved by the just.
Finally, I observe what is written: Ezekiel 14:20: "They alone will be saved."
Who are they? Certainly, those who intercede for sinners. They will be able to ask for such things without punishment. And why do you condemn the Church?
Why do you prevent prayers for those who repent?
If it's acceptable to pray even for these people, for whom is it not acceptable to seek mercy?
Therefore, read my Cyprian more diligently:
read the entire letter about the Lapsed:
read another letter he gave to Antonianus, where Novatian is confronted with all examples:
you will then know what he pronounces about the care of penitents.
I speak about Cyprian, who opposes you and upholds Catholic laws.
After the heresy (for you have taken much from there), you will hear Tertullian himself confessing in his letter, and even in the one he published as a Catholic, that the Church can forgive sins.
Therefore, you see that the Church is a queen in a garment of gold and varied colors (Psalm 45:9); clearly composed of many bodies and many peoples.
This painting is not of one color, nor does such diversity shine forth in one appearance.
One part of the garment covers, another part shapes it.
Some adhere to the chest, some are dragged at the hem, and some even get dirty at the feet.
Some are compared to the purple of martyrs; some to virginal silk; some are sewn with a folding hem, or repaired with an inserting needle.
For one person is this way, another is that way (First Corinthians 7:7); and yet, one queen is composed of all.
The same fruitful and rich vine, having many branches, is adorned with many clusters; has none of these suffered from the cold of winter?
Has it endured no harsh hail?
Has it not faced scorching summers?
This gem is tougher for the clusters, that one stronger, another purer; this one spreads itself in fruits, this one only overflows in foliage.
Yet the vine is beautiful everywhere.
This mother of young women, whose number is beyond count (Song of Solomon 6:7).
Finally, if you can count the Catholic flocks, and number the throngs of our people.
Not only those spread throughout the whole world, filling all regions; but also, brother Sympronian, those that dwell with you in the neighboring territories and nearby city.
Observe, how many of ours do you see alone, how many of my people do you meet alone.
Are you not like drops from the great fountains?
Are you not swallowed up like a small drop from the ocean?
Tell me, are these young women born from your people, or do you alone give birth to them?
That queen, I said, is chosen and perfect for her mother Song of Solomon chapter 8.
For nothing is chosen unless it is better and greater than something else; nothing can be perfect unless it is complete.
You see then that the Church is a queen in a golden and variegated robe Psalm chapter 45, verse 10.
Certainly composed of many bodies and many peoples with diverse characteristics.
This picture is not of one color, nor does such great diversity shine in one form.
One part of the garment covers, another part adorns.
Some cling to the chest, some are dragged to the lowest fold, and get dirty among the very footsteps.
Some are likened to the purple of martyrs; some, to the silk of virgins; some are sewn with a folding hem, or repaired with an inserting needle.
For one person is this way, another is that way First Corinthians chapter 7, verse 7.
Yet, in all, one queen is composed.
Therefore, the same fruitful and wealthy vine, having many branches, is extended with many shoots; did none of these suffer from winter's cold?
Did none endure harsh hailstorms?
Did none complain of scorching summers?
This gem is harsher for the shoots, that one stronger, another purer; this one spreads itself into fruits, this one into mere leaves.
Yet the vine is beautiful everywhere.
This is the mother of the young women, who are countless Song of Solomon chapter 6, verse 7.
Finally, if you can count the Catholic flocks, and tally the numbers of our people.
Not only those spread throughout the whole world, filling all regions; but these, brother Symproniane, which are with you in the nearby borders and neighboring city.
Consider how many of ours you alone see, how many of my people you alone encounter.
Are you not swallowed up like raindrops by great fountains?
Are you not, like a drop from the ocean, absorbed?
Tell me, are these young women born from your people, or do you alone give birth to them?
That queen, I said, is chosen and perfect for her mother Song of Solomon chapter 8.
For nothing is chosen unless it is better and greater than something else; nothing can be perfect unless it is complete.
Now, also consider this: whether it is mainly built on the foundation of the prophets and apostles, with Jesus Christ himself as the cornerstone.
If it started before you, if it believed before you, if it did not depart from the earlier foundations, if it did not move away, if it did not separate itself from the rest of the body to establish its own teachers and its own instruments, if it argued something unusual, if it discovered some new law, if it declared a rejection of peace to its own body: it must clearly seem to have departed from Christ, to have been established outside the prophets and apostles.
This, then, will be the great house, rich with all sorts of vessels, in which pure gold shines, in which malleable silver gleams.
But, as it is written in Second Timothy chapter 2, verse 20, it also honors wooden and clay vessels.
For a great house serves many uses and demands various works.
It does not only seek silver, nor is it solely delighted by golden decoration.
Often, a great house is more fitting with simplicity; and among noble ambitions, even small things are pleasing.
No artist despises his own works, nor considers anything he has made to be worthless.
And why do you think Christ suffered for sinners, if not because he did not want to lose anything he himself created?
Why do you think he still intercedes for the miserable today, if not because he does not reject even the smallest and most despised, intending to lose none of those he has accepted?
Even if they are compared to wooden and clay vessels, he still arranges all the vessels in his house this way.
Here, then, will be a grand house, rich with diverse kinds of vessels, where pure gold shines brightly and ductile silver gleams.
As it is written in Second Timothy 2:20, it also includes wooden and earthen vessels.
For a great house serves many purposes and requires various works.
It does not seek only silver, nor does it delight solely in golden ornaments.
Often, what suits the great more is humility; and among noble affairs, even small things are enjoyable.
No artist despises his own works, nor does he think the things he made are worthless.
And why do you think Christ suffered for sinners, if not because He did not want to lose anything He created?
Why do you think He still intercedes for the wretched, if not because He does not reject even the smallest and most despised?
He will not lose anyone He has accepted, whether they are like wooden or earthen vessels.
And so, He arranges all the vessels in His house.
Finally, brother Sympronianus, do not hesitate to be with the many; be willing to leave behind the remnants of the Novatians and your own sect.
Look upon the Catholic flocks and the people of the Church spread so widely.
You say, "Where there is one, there I am also; and where there are two, there is the Church." Where there is one who is in harmony; where there are two, they are peaceful.
Where there is one, there is the Church; how much more so where there are many? "Two are better than one," he says, "and a threefold cord is not quickly broken" Ecclesiastes 4:12.
Hear David: "I will praise your name in the great assembly" Psalm 35:18. And again: "I will praise you among a mighty throng."
And: "The God of gods has spoken, and summoned the earth from sunrise to sunset" Psalm 50:1. Why is the seed of Abraham, as numerous as the stars and grains of sand, content with your poverty?
"In you," he says, "all the tribes of the earth will be blessed" Genesis 22:18. Tell me, does Novatian fulfill this? God did not redeem such a small number with His blood, nor is Christ so poor.
Recognize now, brother, the Church of God expanding its tents and fixing the tent pegs to the right and left. Understand, "From the rising of the sun to its setting, the name of the Lord is to be praised" Psalm 113:3.
Look, I beg you, while the Novatians argue over words, the wealth of the Catholic Church is spreading throughout the whole world.
I have instructed you on everything you asked about.
I didn't skip any of the topics or questions you raised.
I answered down to the details and words.
If you asked with a curious mind, it was shown with love; if with a challenging mind, it was debated with vigor.
I will add another letter when I have time, in which I will not refute your points, but present ours: if you read it kindly and without disdain, perhaps it will not offend you.
Meanwhile, I ask that you carefully consider each point in this letter.
Things read quickly are easily forgotten: if you desire better gifts and have a soul seeking good education, you will not easily despise the truth.
May the Lord be pleased to guard and protect you forever and make you live as a Christian in spiritual harmony.
Amen.
Finally, brother Sympronian, do not be ashamed to be with the many; be willing to scorn the remnants and fragments of the Novatians; look at the Catholic flocks and the people of the Church spread so widely.
Where there is one, you say, there I am too; and where there are two, there is the Church: where one is in harmony; where two are peaceful.
Where there is one, there is the Church; how much more where there are many?
Two are better than one, he says, and a triple cord is not easily broken.
Ecclesiastes 4:12.
Listen to David: I will sing praise to your name in the great assembly.
Psalm 35:18.
And again: I will praise you among many people.
And: The God of gods has spoken and called the earth from the rising of the sun to its setting.
Psalm 49:1.
How does the seed of Abraham, according to the stars and the sands of the seashore, fit with your poverty?
In you all the tribes of the earth will be blessed.
Genesis 22:18.
Tell me; can Novatian fulfill this?
God redeemed us with His blood, not for so little, nor is Christ so poor.
Recognize now, brother, the Church of God expanding its tents, and setting up its stakes to the right and to the left: understand, from the rising of the sun to its setting, the Lord’s name is to be praised.
Psalm 113:3.
Look, I beg you, while the Novatians argue over words, the wealth of the Catholic Church is spreading throughout the whole world.
For everything you asked me about, I have provided instructions.
I didn't leave out any topic or sentence from your questions.
I responded to every detail and word.
If you asked with a seeking heart, I answered with love.
If you asked with a challenging spirit, I debated without hesitation.
I will add another letter when I have time, in which I will not refute your points, but present my own.
If you read it kindly and without disdain, it might not offend you.
Meanwhile, in this one, I ask that you consider each point carefully.
Things that are read quickly are easily forgotten.
If you desire better understanding and have a passion for learning, you won't easily dismiss the truth.
May the Lord choose to keep and protect you forever, and make you live as a Christian in spiritual harmony.
Amen.