Historical Notice.
From Mansi, the most extensive Collection of Councils, Volume Eighteen, page 405.
Agapetus succeeded Marino in the year 946 AD, during the time of Constantine the Eighth.
After several synods concerning the case of Hugo and Artald, he confirmed Artald's assignment to the Archbishopric of Reims.
He granted the pallium to Bruno, the Archbishop of Cologne and brother of Otto, upon request.
After King Otto defeated the Danes in a significant victory and they embraced Christianity, he congratulated the Church of Hamburg and renewed its ancient privileges, as noted in Adam, Book Two, Chapter Two.
During this time, after Lothair's death, Berengar invaded the kingdom of Italy.
Emperor Otto, approached by Adelheid, daughter of Rudolf and widow of Lothair, along with Pope Agapetus, expelled Berengar's entire family and accepted Queen Adelheid, Lothair's former wife, as his own.
He defended the kingdom with great integrity.
Agapetus served diligently in the pastoral office for nine years, seven months, and ten days before passing away.
Letters and Privileges of Pope Agapetus the Second
One: PRIVILEGE OF POPE AGAPETUS THE SECOND FOR THE MONASTERY OF SAINT SAVIOR IN FULDA.
(Year Nine Hundred Forty-Six.)
This is the confirmation of the privileges that Pope Marinus the Second granted to the Fulda monastery.
AGAPETUS, the bishop and servant of the servants of God, addresses HADAMAR, the devout abbot of the revered monastery of the Lord Savior, and through him, to all his successors as abbots in this esteemed monastery, forever.
With the utmost concern for all revered places, as much as is possible through divine assistance,
we endeavor to ensure their stability.
Through this effort, we both honor divine mercy and elevate the praise of the Church of Christ.
With greater confidence, we dare to seek eternal mercy for the forgiveness of sins.
Your reverence has requested that the venerable monastery of the Lord Savior, established by Saint Boniface the bishop at the site called Boconia by the Fulda River, be granted the protection of the apostolic seat's privilege.
This ensures it is not subject to the jurisdiction of any other Church, but remains under the jurisdiction of our holy Church, which we serve by God's will.
In support of your pious wishes, we enact your request with our apostolic authority, following the series of privileges previously granted by our predecessor, Marinus, the bishop of this blessed seat.
Therefore, we prohibit any priest from any church from having authority in the aforementioned monastery, except for the apostolic seat, unless invited by the abbot of the monastery.
No one should presume to celebrate masses there without an invitation.
This ensures that, as established, it remains endowed with the firmness of apostolic privilege, enjoying perpetual stability in its places and properties.
This includes both those it currently holds and those divine mercy may wish to increase in the future as gifts, offerings, and tithes from the faithful, without contradiction from anyone.
From this point forward, as we consider this matter, we have decided that at appropriate times, our church should be informed about how monastic life is guided by regular practice and dedicated to proper ecclesiastical study.
We must be vigilant so that, under the guise of this privilege, the principles and actions of righteousness remain aligned with true justice.
No king, bishop, count, or any other individual, regardless of status, should impose force or create disputes concerning the affairs and families of the esteemed monastery mentioned here.
By our authority, we also prohibit any woman from entering the monastery, and no one is allowed to hold court within its premises or other associated places.
Furthermore, no one should compel the servants or tenants to any service, except those whom the abbot has specifically permitted for his needs.
The brothers should have the freedom to choose an abbot for themselves as needed, according to the rule of Saint Benedict, without interference from anyone.
To you, beloved son Hadamar, known for your education and eloquence, we grant and command by the authority of Saint Peter to preach the word of God.
Therefore, by apostolic decree, we declare through this document that anyone who dares to violate this privilege, which we affirm by the authority of the chief of the apostles, will be cursed unless they quickly repent.
They shall incur the wrath of God and be excluded from the company of all the saints.
Nonetheless, the dignity of the aforementioned monastery, granted by us, shall remain perpetually intact, strengthened by apostolic authority.
Whoever preserves and observes this privilege of ours shall receive blessing and grace from the Lord.
This document is written by the hand of Leo, the clerk of the Holy Roman Church, in the month of October, during the fifth indiction.
Issued on the 25th of October.
In November, under the leadership of Stephen, the head of the apostolic seat.
During the year, by the grace of God, in the pontificate of Lord Agapetus, the second supreme pontiff and universal pope.
In the month of October, in the fifth indiction year.
Letter 2 from Pope Agapetus the Second to Atenulf, Prince of Benevento, written in the year 946.
The Pope urges that the monastery of Saint Sophia be returned to the monks of Monte Cassino.
Agapetus, bishop and servant of the servants of God, sends greetings and an apostolic blessing to Atenulf, Prince of Benevento.
Our duty requires us to be vigilant, to prepare for the day of judgment, to encourage those doing well to improve, and to correct the negligent, following apostolic instruction: Reprove, rebuke, and exhort.
Second Timothy, chapter four, verse two.
The Lord also says through the prophet in another place: If you do not warn the wicked of their wickedness, I will require their blood at your hand.
Ezekiel, chapter three, verse eighteen.
We were very pleased to hear from our beloved son, Abbot Baldwin, about your eagerness to promote the exaltation of churches.
However, the pastoral care of all churches compels us to be watchful, and as our spiritual son Baldwin, the most reverent Father of monasteries, reported to your dominions, you have not continued in the good work you began.
We are deeply saddened and grieved that the monastery in honor of Saint Sophia, located within the city of Benevento and under the authority of the blessed Father Benedict of the monks established at Monte Cassino from its very foundation, remains so during your time.
You have boldly ignored the decrees of kings and the universal apostolic men and have not feared to remove the said monastery of Saint Sophia from the authority of the monastery of Saint Benedict with unheard-of audacity.
However, Baldwin, the most reverent abbot, has restored it under canonical authority and the legal precepts of kings and apostles to the jurisdiction of that holy monastery.
When our predecessor, Pope Marino, summoned it to himself, you presumed to seize the same monastery.
We earnestly urge you, and sincerely ask, to return the entire monastery to the abbot who has requested it.
Additionally, please do not cause any issues for the monastery of Saint Sophia of Cassino.
If, God forbid, you choose to do otherwise, be aware that, as stated by our previous popes, you will face the penalty of anathema.
AGAPETUS II PRIVILEGE FOR THE ESSEN ABBEY.
(Year 946.)
He confirms the privileges of the Essen Abbey at the request of Abbess Hatewig.
AGAPETUS, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to HATHEWIGA, religious abbess, and the monastery of Asinda, built by the late Bishop Altfrid, and to her successors forever.
The highest apostolic dignity shines with divine foresight when it diligently works to praise God.
Therefore, because you requested from us, through the intervention of our lord and glorious King Otto, we command, by our apostolic authority, to newly grant you the same privilege given by our predecessor, the lord Pope Zachary, to the aforementioned monastery called Asinda, built by Bishop Alfrid.
This monastery was destroyed by fire, along with the tithe, which, with the permission of the aforesaid lord apostolic and the consent of all the bishops of the clergy, Gunthar, Archbishop of the Church of Cologne, had assigned for the sustenance of the same nuns, and the right of election.
This ensures that when the abbess passes away, the nuns will have the freedom to choose from among themselves a worthy and God-pleasing abbess to lead them.
To ensure that the same monastery is honored with the privileges of the apostolic seat and remains under the jurisdiction of our holy Church, which we serve by God's guidance, it should not fall under the jurisdiction of any other Church.
Therefore, supporting your pious desires, we implement what you request.
With apostolic authority, invoking divine judgment and under the threat of anathema, we establish that no one, regardless of their rank or status, whether of great or small importance, should ever presume to take away or alienate in any way the goods or possessions, or anything that seems to belong to it.
Nor should anyone cause any harm, distress, or loss during times of peace or turmoil.
We decree that it should remain firmly under the jurisdiction of our holy Church.
However, whoever, with pious intent, observes this apostolic privilege of ours shall receive many blessings from the most merciful Lord God.
Letter Four.
From Pope Agapetus the Second to Leo and Benedict, regarding their unauthorized involvement in the churches of Trivento and Termoli.
(Year Nine Forty-Seven.)
Agapetus, bishop and servant of the servants of God, addresses Leo, priest and monk, and Benedict, also a priest, who were improperly consecrated as bishops by us and currently hold this office.
We previously sent you letters requesting that you come to us to address the accusations and complaints made by John, bishop of the holy seat of Benevento, against us.
He appealed to us and presented the privileges granted by our predecessor pontiffs of the Holy Roman Church and apostolic seat, along with a strict anathema, so that no one would dare to diminish the boundaries of the Church of Benevento.
He also stated that the churches of Trivento and Termoli have long been subject to the bishop of Benevento, along with all other churches built or to be built within these boundaries and other areas within the cities and fortresses, all under the authority of the Beneventan principality.
Since you refused to come and provide an explanation, we understand that you did not enter through the proper channels, but like thieves and robbers, you intruded from elsewhere and improperly took on the episcopal ministry.
It appears a new presumption has arisen where people under the diocese and bishopric of the Benevento province, against the rules of the canons, have chosen you as their bishops through the heresy of simony, involving bribery and payment.
Therefore, we excommunicate you by the authority of Blessed Peter, the chief of the apostles, so that you may not presume to hold the episcopal seat in the congregations of Trivento and Termoli, nor be allowed to perform any episcopal duties in any other church.
We want to acknowledge that, although it was once held by ancient pontiffs, we are fully restoring, renewing, and confirming everything, including parishes and dioceses, to the principality of Benevento.
This is for Bishop John of Benevento and his successors to possess forever, with nothing diminished by our successors.
Therefore, we urge and command, under the authority of blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, the clergy, and all the people of Trivento and Termoli, that if anyone, without the consent of the local officials, clergy, or people of those cities, attempts to invite the aforementioned monk Leo or the priest Benedict into those cities to perform the duties of a bishop, they shall remain excommunicated.
However, if anyone, which we do not desire, dares to oppose these statutes established by us for the glory of God and the stability of the Church of Benevento, or transgresses in any way, or attempts to diminish its boundaries, let them know they are excommunicated and condemned to eternal punishment with Judas, the betrayer of the Lord, and all the wicked.
But whoever, with foresight, observes and upholds this apostolic constitution in all ways, looking to the worship of God, may they receive an abundance of grace from our most merciful Lord and be deemed worthy of eternal life.
This was given by the hand of Stephen, the chief of the holy Roman and apostolic see, in the year of the pontificate of Lord Pope Agapetus the Second, in the most holy see of blessed Peter the apostle, first, in the fifth indiction.
Five: Epistle of Pope Agapetus the Second to Adalgar, Archbishop of Hamburg (Year Nine Hundred Forty-Eight)
AGAPETUS, bishop and servant of the servants of God, sends greetings to the most reverend and holy ADALGARIUS, Archbishop of the Holy Church of Hamburg, and to your successors forever.
The apostolic office should support those who excel in pious religion with compassionate kindness and fulfill the requests of those who ask with sincere devotion.
By doing this, we undoubtedly earn the greatest reward from God, the creator of all, when venerable places are brought to a better state.
You have asked us to confirm the entire archbishopric of the Church of Hamburg to you, as decreed by our predecessor, Lord Nicholas of this apostolic see.
Inclined by the prayers of Hadamar, the abbot of Fulda, we grant this by apostolic authority, with all places generally and specifically pertaining to your archbishopric.
This includes everything your predecessors acquired through their efforts, as well as gifts given out of love for the eternal homeland by the faithful followers of Christ.
It also includes those now converted to the faith of Christ through divine protection, such as the bishops of the Danes, Norwegians, Swedes, and all northern regions.
We also decree that the pallium and its use in the aforementioned places, as made by the said pope, be held by you and all your successors forever.
From this moment on, we declare that no archbishop, whether from Cologne or elsewhere, shall claim any authority over your diocese.
Instead, we urge them and all those devoted to religion to offer you assistance and support in every way, so they may earn full reward from the Lord for this act of kindness.
We firmly believe that everything beneficial to the church, which aligns with divine commandments, should be carried out and provided under the authority of Almighty God and the blessed apostles Peter and Paul.
By our authority, in accordance with the decree of the late Pope Nicholas and the desire of the most reverend King Louis, we declare that the dioceses of Hamburg and Bremen are no longer separate but united as one.
We also pronounce anathema and eternal punishment by demonic fate on anyone who opposes, contradicts, or in any way plots against our sincere efforts.
This is so we can zealously defend the cause of God, with the love of the apostolic leaders, and protect it from adversaries on all sides.
By apostolic authority, we instruct Bishop Bernhard of Alverstadt, Thidard of the Hisden Church, and other neighboring bishops to assist you in all matters, so you may fulfill your priestly duties and more effectively gain souls for the Lord Jesus Christ.
Therefore, by apostolic authority and with the warning of divine judgment, and under the interdict of anathema, we establish that no person, regardless of status or rank, shall violate anything granted by us or our predecessors to your church and to you.
Whoever alters or dares to violate anything, unless they repent, shall be bound by the perpetual bond of anathema by the authority of God, of Saint Peter, and of us, who act in his stead.
However, whoever has been its keeper and observer may deserve to receive the grace of blessing and the reward of heaven from our Lord God, the just judge.
This was written by Aaron, the regional notary and secretary of the Holy Roman Church, in the month of January, during the sixth indiction.
It was given on January 2nd by Andrew, the treasurer of the holy apostolic see, at the most sacred seat of Blessed Peter the Apostle, in the sixth indiction.
Six: Letter from Pope Agapetus the Second to Abbess Windilgarde, dated 948.
The monastery of Gandersheim in Saxony is placed under the protection of the apostolic see and granted various privileges.
Agapetus, bishop and servant of God's servants, addresses Windilgarde, the venerable abbess of Gandersheim monastery, founded by Count Otto of Saxony, as well as the other abbesses of her order, forever.
Since it is always necessary to grant things that align with rational desires, it is fitting that the founder's devotion should not be denied the authority of pious preservation when granting privileges.
Therefore, because the venerable abbot Hathumar requested, through his intervention and plea, that we confirm your monastery of Gandersheim, located near the river Aterna, by apostolic authority, it is established under the jurisdiction of our holy church, which we serve by the grace of God, and should not be subjected to the jurisdictions of any other church.
For this reason, favoring these pious desires, we enact this authority of ours to fulfill the request.
Therefore, we prohibit, by our authority, any priest from any church from having any authority in the aforementioned monastery, except for the apostolic see.
By the authority of the blessed apostles Peter and Paul, we command that no king should dare, without your permission, to give the monastery to any individuals as a benefice.
So that, indeed, according to what is subject to the apostolic see with the firmness of privilege, it may remain undisturbed, enriched with places and goods, both those it currently has or possesses and those which divine grace may increase in the future for the right of the monastery.
It may enjoy with perpetual firmness the gifts, offerings, and tithes of the faithful without any person's contradiction.
However, when the abbess of this monastery departs from this world, it shall not be permitted for anyone to appoint an abbess there, except from the same congregation, if such a one is found worthy of God.
If she is not found there, the king has the authority to appoint an abbess who is deemed worthy to please God.
We also decree through this document that anyone, regardless of their rank, who tries to violate this charter of our privilege-which we affirm by the authority of the prince of the apostles-shall be cursed.
They will incur God's wrath and be cast out from the company of all the saints.
Nonetheless, the dignity of the mentioned monastery, granted by us, shall remain perpetually inviolate, supported by apostolic authority.
This was written by the hand of Stephen, the scribe of the holy Roman church, in the month of January, during the sixth indiction.
Farewell.
Given on the third day before the nones of January by the hand of Andrew, by divine grace, the treasurer of the holy apostolic see, in the year, with God's favor, of the pontificate of Agapetus, the supreme pontiff, Junior, the pope, in the most holy seat of the blessed Peter the apostle, the second year.
Seven: The Privilege of Pope Agapetus the Second for the Monastery of Saint Boniface in Fulda.
Year Nine Hundred Forty-Eight.
This document confirms the privileges of the newly renovated Fulda Monastery.
Agapetus, bishop and servant of the servants of God, addresses the venerable abbot Hadamar and, through him, the future abbots of the monastery originally built by Saint Boniface and recently renovated, for all time.
Since it is essential to grant what matches reasonable desires, the founder's authority in a pious construction should not be denied when granting privileges.
Therefore, since you have requested that the monastery of the Savior, originally built by Saint Boniface and recently rebuilt by you at Boconus near the bank of the river Fulda, be honored with the privileges of the apostolic seat and established under our jurisdiction,
guided by God whom we serve, it shall not be subjected to the jurisdiction of any other Church;
we support these pious desires and, with our authority, bring your request to fulfillment.
Therefore, we forbid any priest or bishop from any Church to have authority or jurisdiction in the aforementioned monastery except for the apostolic seat,
ensuring that no one presumes to celebrate Masses there unless invited by the abbot of the monastery,
so it remains firmly endowed with the privileges ascribed to the apostolic seat,
along with the places and properties it currently holds or will acquire through divine mercy from the gifts, offerings, and tithes of the faithful,
without contradiction, enjoying perpetual firmness.
We also declare through this decree of ours that anyone, whether a leader or person of any rank from any Church, who attempts to violate this charter of our privilege-affirmed by the authority of the prince of the apostles-shall be cursed and incur the wrath of God.
They shall be banished from the assembly of all saints.
Nevertheless, the dignity of the aforementioned monastery granted by us shall remain perpetually inviolable, upheld by apostolic authority.
This was written by the hand of Stephen, notary and scribe of the Holy Roman Church, in the month of January and in the sixth indiction.
Given on January second.
Letter 8.
From Pope Agapetus the Second to Archbishop Gerard of Lorch, Year Nine Forty-Eight.
This letter resolves the dispute between the churches of Lorch, known as Passau, and Salzburg.
It assigns western Pannonia to Salzburg, while Lorch, being older, receives the honor of blessing and the eastern Pannonia, covering the regions of the Avars, Moravians, and Slavs.
It also grants the authority to preach freely throughout all the lands of the Slavs, to ordain bishops there, and to establish everything with apostolic authority.
Agapetus, bishop and servant of the servants of God, to the most beloved and most reverend brother Gerard, archbishop of the holy Lorch Church, greetings in Christ.
Your requests to renew or approve the privileges of your Church were presented to us by the venerable abbot Hademar of the Fulda monastery, who came here for prayer with great benevolence.
He also reported the very serious disputes and arguments between you and Archbishop Herold over the authority of the pallium received by both in one province, with lamentation.
We, in our pastoral care, also grieve with great sorrow of heart and detest such profane discord.
Indeed, the holy and universal Church, over which we preside by the authority of God, is supported by its religious and peaceful priests, solidified in sincere love, like so many pillars.
However, when they are discordant and lift their minds against each other with hostile pride, especially such great bishops, it is as if it were shaken from its own position with great danger and loss of its strength, with its supports torn away.
Moreover, while this kind of contention is persistently exercised between you outside for the honor of the pallium, it results in the honor of the priesthood being emptied within through fraternal rivalry.
Therefore, brother, as it is our duty to ensure that seeds of hostility do not grow among you, causing division in the holy Church of God and scandal without regard for your counsel and benefit, we come as mediators to settle your dispute.
We are motivated both by the concern of the governance entrusted to us by the Lord and by love for both of you.
We aim to address your complaints about the conflict with fair judgments, satisfying justice, and, with Christ's guidance, bring you back to brotherly harmony once all controversy is set aside.
It is known and documented with us which church locations should be granted the dignity of the pallium from this apostolic seat.
The city of Lauriacum, regarded since ancient times as a metropolitan and archbishop's seat, over which your holiness is known to preside, is mentioned in authentic privileges sent to us by you.
We also found some very old documents in the archives of St.
Peter revealing this.
We learned that, at the beginning of the nascent Church and during the most severe persecution of Christians, this seat received the foundations of the Catholic faith from its teachers.
From there, subsequent preachers spread the grace of this faith to the provinces of Upper and Lower Pannonia.
Until the time of the Huns, no one other than the archbishop of the holy Lauriacum presided over these two provinces and their bishops.
The barbaric savagery of the Huns devastated not only the aforementioned city of Lauriacum but also the surrounding regions, leaving them completely desolate.
Consequently, compelled by necessity, the bishops abandoned that seat, relocating elsewhere, and also deserted the archiepiscopal honor of that seat.
In more recent times, not too long ago, after the apostolic vicariate of the Bavarian kingdom was vacant, Arno was appointed as the first archbishop of the holy Church of Salzburg.
This is confirmed by the long-standing historical records of the sacred archives.
Now, with Christ favoring mortals, peace and safety have been granted to the holy Church of Lorch from its enemies, and your position should be held there.
Therefore, we reinstate you to the same Church of the holy Fathers, namely our predecessors, in memory of the blessed Lord Pope Leo, from whom your excellency received the pallium and privilege, executing the sanctions and statutes.
We release, ordain, and elevate the frequently mentioned holy Church of Lorch to metropolitan status by the authority and on behalf of the blessed Peter, the chief of the apostles.
We confirm and strengthen the privileges handed down to us with our own hand, and we firmly establish them as valid.
Again, we give you the pallium with this present decree, according to the previously granted usage, to be held by your successors perpetually.
With these matters restored to justice, we have decided to settle your disputes and disagreements arising from the aforementioned cause, and to reconcile you to fraternal love.
We encourage you to uphold the honor of the pallium, so that, as ordained by the apostolic authority, you may no longer remain in contention and rivalry.
It is indeed recognized that according to canon law, each province appoints its own metropolitan.
So, we believe it's beneficial and peaceful to organize and define the parishes for you like this: the two provinces of the Noric region are divided, and Archbishop Herold is given the care and oversight of western Pannonia.
However, to you and your successors, due to the well-earned antiquity of the Holy Church of Lauriacum, which rightfully commands the respect of the younger generation, we entrust the responsibility for eastern Pannonia, as well as the regions of the Avars, Marahars, and the Slavs, who are now Christians or are yet to be converted through baptism.
We delegate our apostolic authority in these areas to preach, establish bishops where needed at your discretion, and arrange everything with such authority and power as if we were present ourselves.
If the aforementioned Archbishop Herold or any of his successors is not satisfied with the set boundary and persistently tries to reclaim the diocese separated from his authority, and does not adhere to our apostolic traditions and determinations to avoid forbidden disputes, he shall be completely deprived of the gracious dignity granted to him.
According to ancient law, Upper Pannonia should be united with Lower Pannonia, and both should always be under the dominion of you and your successors.
We give our approval and consent to these most beneficial decrees of ours, bless them, and uphold them as Catholic.
But those who resist, attempt to undermine, or completely overturn them, we strike with the strictest anathema of the Holy Trinity, and we condemn them with the apostolic sentence by which Ananias and Sapphira perished, assigning them to eternal punishment with the blasphemers of the Holy Spirit.
LETTER 9. A LETTER FROM POPE AGAPETUS THE SECOND TO ABBOT AYMARD OF CLUNY.
The Privilege of the Abbey of Cluny.
AGAPETUS, servant of the servants of God, to our beloved son Aymard, the venerable abbot of the monastery of Cluny, established in honor of the blessed apostles Peter and Paul, located in the Macon region, and through you to the same monastery and your successors forever.
It is the duty of the apostolic office to support with kind compassion the pious requests of those who ask and to grant them with eager devotion.
Through this, we especially earn a reward from God, the creator of all.
Therefore, since you have requested us to decree by our apostolic authority that the aforementioned monastery remains in the state decreed by Duke William in his testament, subject to the Holy Roman Church, which we serve by God's authority:
moved by your prayers, we grant you the right to govern it.
Thus, let that monastery, with all its possessions, whether it has them now or will receive them in the future, be free from the dominion of any king, bishop, count, or any of William's relatives.
No one should presume to appoint a leader there against the will of the monks after your death:
but they shall have the free authority, without consulting any prince, to appoint whomever they choose according to the rule of Saint Benedict;
unless, God forbid, they choose someone who consents to their vices.
Whoever wishes, let them prohibit this with zeal for God.
Furthermore, we fully restore to you the tithes that once belonged to your chapels and have been taken away by the current authority or permission of any bishop.
We allow any chapels that have already been built or are to be built to remain, provided that nothing from the tithes is diminished from your churches.
Moreover, what our beloved son Bishop Bruno has granted you regarding the aforementioned chapels, we decree to be valid and firm forever.
Furthermore, we decree that a portion of the tithes from the vineyards and fields assigned to you should also benefit your hospital.
This includes what you are about to receive, such as what Leobald left to the mentioned monastery and what pertains to Magiona and other matters that should belong to that monastery.
We also reaffirm, with our apostolic authority, the abbey of the Carilocensis monastery granted to the same monastery, as well as the abbeys of Saint John and Saint Martin located in the suburb of Matisco.
We decree that they shall permanently remain with the aforementioned place, ensuring that no bishop, count, or any individual may make decisions there without the command of the rector of the said place.
Similarly, we decree concerning the lands of Celsanicas, which belonged to Count Hecfred.
Our son Stephen, after careful consideration, assigned these lands to the aforementioned place for the benefit of all Christians.
Furthermore, we bolster with apostolic authority all villages belonging to the same Cluniac monastery, namely Solustriacum, Caninias, Seneciacum, Arpagiacum, Saint Victor, Scociolas, Kaerdasemscum, Dabormacum, and Piscatoria, known as Osa; Tosciacum, and the church of Saint Desiderius, Ambariacum, and the estate of Saviniacum, which Engelbald and Waldo, upon his conversion, gave.
Similarly, Amberia and the church of Saint Abundus, which Artald left to the aforementioned monastery upon his death, and the church of Saint Saturninus, along with all the estate that Gerald, the archbishop, donated to the aforementioned monastery.
And because the monastic order seeks utmost immunity, we grant you the reverence owed to holy places everywhere, ensuring no one may seize or invade your towns or any property without your consent.
To affirm that the aforementioned monastery belongs to the holy apostolic see for protection and support, ten solidi shall be given every five years.
If anyone tries to oppose this highly beneficial constitution of ours by resisting or attempting to corrupt any part of it, and does not follow everything we have decreed in this privilege,
let them be aware they will face eternal consequences under the threat of divine judgment and excommunication unless they repent, and will be separated from the kingdom of God and tormented endlessly with the devil.
However, whoever becomes the guardian and observer of this highly beneficial decree of ours, may they be worthy to receive a blessing from Christ the Lord and absolution from the holy apostles, judges of the world, both now and in the future.
Documented by the hand of Leo, the king's notary, and the scribe of the holy Roman Church, in the month of March, during the seventh indiction.
This is a letter from Pope Agapetus the Second to Abbot Williarius.
(Year Nine Hundred Fifty.)
It confirms Otto the Great's decision regarding the immunity of Saint Maximinus.
Agapetus, servant of the servants of God, to the most reverent Abbot Williarius, sending all expressions of love in Christ.
We warmly welcomed the messengers you kindly sent, Asolf and Gunthar, to the thresholds of the holy apostles and our apostolic authority, and we listened attentively to their mission with all the Roman clergy present.
We've learned from their reports that you have been frequently and significantly troubled by Ruotbert, although he is a venerable archbishop, because he unjustly wanted to subject the monastery entrusted to you to the church under his care.
Were it not for the fair judgment issued by the royal authority of the most serene Otto, along with the charters of Charlemagne and other ancient kings being read aloud, this issue would have continued.
Therefore, with the backing of our apostolic authority, all the Roman clergy decreed that regarding your monastery, the one founded near the walls of Trier in honor of Saint John the Evangelist and dedicated to the holy confessors Maximinus, Agritius, and Nicetius, the decisions written in the charters of King Otto and his predecessors, the kings of the Franks, shall remain unchanged.
This means that now and in the future, it remains under royal authority alone and is never to be subjected to anyone else, except the abbot chosen by the brothers of the monastery through common agreement according to the rule.
If the aforementioned archbishop, any of his successors, or any other brother in the monastery unjustly and cruelly disturbs the peace, unless he first repents according to this present writing and then is admonished by apostolic authority, he is to be regarded not as a shepherd, but as a hireling.
Therefore, if he continues in such stubbornness, let him ultimately be excommunicated by our apostolic authority.
Furthermore, may he never succeed in his desires against the good kings, dukes, and just judges who oppose him.
Written by the scribe of the Holy Roman Church.
Given on February 28, in the eighth indiction.
Farewell.
Eleven: Agapetus the Second, Privilege for the Monastery of Saints Germanus and Michael of Cuxa.
This document, from the year 950, confirms the privileges of the monastery of Cuxa.
Agapetus, bishop and servant of the servants of God, addresses Gondefred, the devout abbot of the venerable monastery of Saint Germanus and Saint Michael, located in the valley of Confluent at a place called Coxano, also known as Saint-Michel de Cusan, and to your successors, the abbots of the same monastery, for all time.
We are deeply concerned and attentive to all of God's Churches to ensure that they suffer no harm or loss due to any necessity.
So, because Soniarius, a devoted priest and monk, came to us on your behalf and requested that we affirm the aforementioned monastery to you and your successor abbots in its entirety, along with all its boundaries, limits, surroundings, and belongings forever;
moved by your requests and for the love of Almighty God and Saint Peter, we now confirm the said monastery with its boundaries and limits.
It starts on the eastern side, at the top of the ridge running from Bovaria to Jovem of Celerano, then goes from the mountain called Laccarias, and continues through Laccarias up to Mount Canigone, bordering Mount Canigone on the south.
It descends through the ridge above Miliarias, reaches the cross above the estates, then to Chero Clarinto, and continues to the top of the ridge at the Merdario stream.
From the west, this ridge of Chero Clarinto meets the Merdario stream and leads to the Tede river.
On the north, it borders the public road that leads to Duas Sorores, passing through that road to Litterano, then beneath Saint Felicio, and extends to the estate of Saint Mary.
And the village of Tauriniano with the church of Saint Fructuosus, including tithes and first fruits, and the church of Saint Martin of Clerano, and the church of Saint Andrew, which is established in the village of Catellano with its estate, and the village of Torrente with its boundaries and limits, as stated in your authentic writings.
And the valley of Taresago and estates, and the cell of Saint Vincent with its estate, as detailed in your writings, and the estate of Tonegale, Manzunculas, Ocenias, Tres-Valles, and Lare with the church of Saint Andrew.
The cell of Saint Thomas with its estate, the church of Saint Peter founded in the village of Inforcadis, Laguna with its church, and your estates in these places.
In the county of Roussillon, there are several villages and valleys: Miliarii, Camelas, Relano, Saint Felix, the windy valley, Mount Auriolo, Insula, the valley of Locas, Puio Nadalino, the valley of Vincano, Saorla, Arbussolas, Planicolas, Interrivos, the valley of Molegica, Orto Falguerias, Arriano, Folioliis, Verneto, Corneliano, the valley of Foliano, the valley of Savrra, Torre Sindo, Pino, Campelias, Segondaniano, Juloss, Flazano, Angerro, Enne, Porciliarios, Evole, and Altino.
In the county of Cerdanya, you'll find the village of Sallagosa, along with Onzes and Annes.
In Fenouilledes, there are the villages of Tavernulas and Sauriniano, or Perolas, Vallemagna with its church, and the valley of Stavia.
In the county of Bergitan, there are the villages of Gilmari and Canes, and other locations where the monastery's property is situated.
In the counties of Roussillon, the valley of Conflent, Cerdanya, Fenouilledes, and Bergitan, these mentioned places and counties hold as much as the monastery possesses or is recorded in your documents.
With God's help, you will acquire these, along with the boundaries and limits of your monastery.
We also grant you the first fruits and tithes from your lands, and the offerings to be gathered for the aforementioned monastery, including all its possessions of the Holy Roman Church, which we serve by God's grace.
Through this privilege, we establish your monastery and associated places or churches, starting from this ninth indiction, for you and your successors, the servants of God dwelling there.
They will lead a monastic life, governed with the fear of God, and remain securely and peacefully under apostolic protection, subject to no other power.
Additionally, by apostolic authority, we command that Christ's faithful should be kindly received in hospitality, according to God.
When you leave this world, ensure that only someone from the same community is chosen as abbot.
The abbot should be selected by the community, following God's will.
We command with apostolic authority that no one, regardless of status, should ever try to force or intrude upon the monastery or its properties.
Therefore, under divine judgment and the threat of anathema, we declare that none of our successors, nor anyone of any rank, should dare to violate this apostolic privilege.
While we don't expect it to happen, anyone who acts otherwise should know they are excommunicated, bound by anathema, alienated from God's kingdom, and cast into Tartarus to perish with the wicked.
However, those who serve as guardians and observers deserve to receive abundant blessings from Christ our Lord God.
Written by Leo, notary of the region and scribe of the Holy Roman Church, in December, during the specified indiction.
Farewell.
Agapetus, servant of the servants of God, extends greetings to the most reverend and holy Wisadus, bishop of the holy Church of Urgell, and to your successors forever.
It's appropriate for apostolic leaders to assist those strong in pious religion with kind compassion and to fulfill their requests with devoted eagerness.
By doing so, we undoubtedly earn the greatest reward from God, the creator of all things, when venerable places, duly organized, are brought to a better state.
Therefore, since you have asked us to confirm the aforementioned bishopric of the Church of Urgell, including all its buildings, villages, churches, parishes, houses, vineyards, lands, fields, meadows, pastures, forests, saltpeter deposits, fruit-bearing trees, non-fruit-bearing trees of various kinds, wells, fountains, streams, mills, fisheries, waters and watercourses, castles, mountains, valleys, hills, clearings, and adjacent lands, whether cultivated or uncultivated, as well as the areas pertaining to the same bishopric, namely the region of Cerdanya, Llivia, Berga, Pallars, Ribagorza, Jussa, Cardona, Anabi, and Terbi, and the places of St.
Deodata with their boundaries, and Fencris with their boundaries, and Submonte with their boundaries.
.
We also confirm the third part of the toll of the same bishopric, along with the market rights, and everything that generally and entirely pertains to this bishopric from all its places within the aforementioned bishopric, from the territory of Urgell, Cerdanya, Berga, Pallars, and Ribagorza.
We also confirm to you and your successors the first fruits and tithes from the places and properties of the aforementioned bishopric.
Furthermore, we establish that no person, whoever they may be, should presume to unjustly impose restrictions or unjust laws upon the clergy of your bishopric in collaboration with any lay person.
The aforementioned bishopric, with all its possessions, has been confirmed and solidified by the authority of the Frankish kings through a written decree.
We also confirm it by our apostolic authority.
From now on and in the future, whatever you and your successors lawfully acquire, starting from this year of the Incarnation of Our Lord Jesus Christ, 991, in the tenth indiction, we confirm and establish through your royal decrees.
This privilege allows you and your successors to hold, possess, and manage with the fear of God.
No king, prince, count, marquis, judge, or any person, big or small, should presume to use force or invade the bishopric or its possessions.
Therefore, under the divine judgment and the threat of excommunication, we decree that none of our pontifical successors, nor any individual, great or small, should dare to act unjustly against this apostolic privilege or attempt to break it.
If anyone, though we do not believe this will happen, attempts to break it in any way, let them know that unless they repent, by the authority of God and Saint Peter the apostle, and ours, as his vicar, they shall be bound by the unbreakable chains of excommunication and alienated from God's kingdom.
With the devil and his terrible followers, and Judas the traitor of Our Lord Jesus Christ, they shall be consumed in fire; and let them perish, plunged into the abyss of Tartarus with the wicked.
But whoever acts as a guardian and observer will gain the grace of blessing and the reward of heaven from the just judge, Our Lord God, and will deserve to partake in eternal life.
Amen.
Farewell.
This was written by the hand of Leo, the regional notary and scribe of our holy Roman Church, in the month of December, in the aforementioned year, in the indiction named above.
Agapetus, bishop and servant of the servants of God, to Sunyer, the devoted abbot of the esteemed monastery of the holy Mother of God, Mary, our lady, located in the county of Carcassonne, by the river Orb.
And after you, to your successors in the same revered monastery forever.
It is appropriate for the apostolic authority to support those who excel in devout faith with kind compassion and to eagerly approve those who ask.
By doing this, we undoubtedly gain the greatest reward from God, the creator of all, when venerable places are improved and well-organized.
Therefore, through your representative, Arnulf, the humble abbot of Ripoll, you requested that we confirm the aforementioned monastery, with all its properties, including churches, villages, houses, lands, vineyards, fields, meadows, pastures, woods, groves, threshing floors, and presses, waters, watercourses, mills with their water sources and fisheries, whether cultivated or uncultivated.
This also includes, in the county of Carcassonne, the village of Agrifolio, with the church of Saint Cyricus and its boundaries, the village of Verzeliano with the church of Saint Mary and its boundaries, and the village of Cucuniano with the church of Saint Mary and its boundaries.
And also half, and as much as in the already mentioned county that place.
.
before.
We confirm the following holdings: in the county of Toulouse and its districts, the church of Saint Mary, Saint Savior, and Saint John in Ercino, including the place of Camboni with all its assets.
This includes everything granted by Simplicius, the archdeacon, and his relatives, as recorded in their documents, along with any acquisitions you've made in these areas.
In the county of Redense, we affirm all that Simplicius, the archdeacon, granted, covering both parishes and other locations, including the villages of Boxamaurea and Aureliosa with all their rights.
In the suburb of Petrapertusiense, we recognize what Roger gave in Cucuniano, Retgas in Ollito with its church, and in Paterno, from the village of Corneliano to the previously mentioned areas, as granted by Holiba.
This includes the village of Corneliano with its church, the village of Stagello with its church, and any holdings in the village of Gologias with its church, half of Vernettum with its church, the village of Ripas Altas with its church, and the Villar itself with its church, the village of Coningos with its church, and the villages of Palsas, including fishing rights in the village of Canonae.
In the county of Confluent, we confirm all your holdings in the meadows and fields.
In the county of Girona, this includes the church of Saint Felix in the village of Lorostaria and its church.
In the county of Besalu, we recognize the church of Saint Stephen and Saint Peregrine, the village of Enuscho, and Mediano with its church and associated properties.
Additionally, we confirm holdings in Barcelona, Oriellense, Sardari, Cabastense, Albiense, and Minerbense.
In the county of Narbonne, we acknowledge the village of Erciam with its church, and on the island of Sici, the church of Saint Peter with its belongings, along with all that Remigius, the archdeacon, provided there.
In Toulouse, this includes the village of Palma and the villages of Alianto, Fabriciano, and Ferrales, as well as the holdings of Fabarios of Saint Stephen and Saint Genesius, and in the village of Miliano, as much as they possess there.
In the county of Ausona, we confirm the church of Saint Martin, along with its tithes and belongings, and in the village of R.
.
In the region and settlement of Asenario, along with Salmas near Narbonne by the lagoon, everything they have there, or anything that fully belongs to the aforementioned monastery, is acknowledged.
We affirm your rights to the bridge toll, boat toll, salt toll, and market toll, just as the kings have granted you through their written decrees.
We also decree that when the abbot of the monastery passes away, no king, count, or anyone motivated by greed or vanity should appoint a new abbot.
Instead, all the servants of God in that monastery should elect abbots according to God's will and the rule of Saint Benedict.
The aforementioned monastery is located in the Carcassonne territory, near the Narbonne region.
Additionally, we confirm to you and your successors the rights to the places and properties of that holy monastery, including first fruits and tithes.
Furthermore, we reaffirm that no one should wrongfully subject the monks of your monastery to unjust secular laws.
Since the aforementioned monastery is confirmed and strengthened by a decree of the King of the Franks, and by our apostolic authority as stated above, and influenced by the prayers of your envoy, Abbot Arnulf, as well as the royal decrees and other privileges, we confirm and establish this for you and your successors to hold in perpetuity.
From now on, you are to administer and govern with the fear of God, ensuring that no king, prince, count, margrave, judge, or anyone, great or small, ever presumes to commit any force or invasion upon that monastery or its properties.
Therefore, invoking divine judgment and under the threat of anathema, we declare and decree that none of our successors, and as we have stated above, no person, great or small, should dare or presume to act against this, our apostolic privilege, in any way, nor attempt to break it.
However, if anyone-which we do not believe will happen-tries to break it in any way, let them know that unless they repent, by the authority of Almighty God and Saint Peter, the chief of the apostles, and our own, who serve as his representative, they will be bound indissolubly with the chains of anathema.
They will be alienated from the kingdom of God, along with the devil and his most atrocious displays, and with Judas, the betrayer of our Lord Jesus Christ.
They will be eternally consumed by fire and plunged into the abyss and chaos of Tartarus to perish with the wicked.
Written by the hand of Stephen, notary and secretary of the holy and apostolic Roman Church, in the month of December, during the tenth indiction.
Farewell.
XV. Privilege Granted by Pope Agapetus the Second to Maimbodus, Bishop of Macon.
(Year Nine Hundred Forty-Six to Nine Hundred Fifty-Four.)
This confirms the privileges and possessions of the Church of Saint Vincent of Macon for the canons.
Agapetus, bishop, servant of the servants of God, extends greetings to the most reverend and holy Maimbodus, bishop of the Church of Macon, and his successors forever.
Since the teachings of Peter, the prince of the blessed apostles, advance the state of all holy churches of God, and what has fallen is restored by his support, it is appropriate that the holy Church of Macon, which is suffering a reduction in its diocese and lacking in dignities, should be quickly restored to maintain its honor.
Therefore, realizing it is shaken in all things, it is right to extend our helping hand for its restoration, so that, nourished by the source of the blessed apostle Peter and with the help of Christ, it may regain its honors.
Let all devotees and the faithful of the holy churches of God understand that Maimbodus, our beloved bishop and spiritual son, has suggested to our apostolic benevolence that we grant his canons and laypeople residing in the Church of Saint Vincent the Martyr the right not to appoint a bishop from elsewhere unless chosen among themselves by the canons, together with the aforementioned religious laypeople, as the sacred canons decree.
We also grant to him and his successors that due honor should always be given.
We confirm to the aforementioned canons all the possessions given by the decrees of kings or the generosity of faithful men and women of Christ in that place, so that they may have them without any contradiction forever.
This includes the Abbey of Saint Clement the Martyr, located in the suburb of the aforementioned city, with all its integrity, churches, lands, and servants, both male and female, belonging to it.
Also included is the Church of Saint Desiderius located in the village of Vergiaco, with the small land of Saint Peter adjacent to it from the episcopate in the aforementioned village, along with the Church of Saint Romanus located in the village of Cathenaco.
However, concerning the tithes from the ninths and tenths, as well as the thefts from the aforementioned district, and a third of the forest near the Arar River, along with the villa of Adolani, these were granted just as our beloved son, the pious King Louis, agreed with Bishop Maimbodus regarding the tithes and land.
Marquis Hugo and the very moderate Count Leothald also consented, driven by their passion for the growth of the aforementioned church.
Therefore, through this apostolic privilege, we grant perpetual holding of the tithes of Saint Alban the Martyr and Gisario:
so that from now on, whatever has been given or granted in this place, or whatever divine mercy wishes to increase in the future by any person, they may hold and possess without any disturbance or compulsion.
This is with the condition that no king, duke, count, tax collector, or public official shall impose any forced service, restriction, burden, or command over them.
Except for what the faithful canons of the aforementioned place wish to grant from their own goodwill.
Establishing and proclaiming before God and His terrible judgment, through the confirmation of this apostolic privilege, we decree by the authority of blessed Peter, the chief of the apostles.
We urge future bishops of the apostolic see, as well as those administering ecclesiastical functions, and individuals of all ranks, that no one shall have permission in any way to separate or alienate any of these chapters, granted by us, from the often-mentioned place, especially for the grace of apostolic prayer joined together.
If anyone, though we do not expect it, recklessly dares to oppose what has been piously and firmly decreed by our authority through this privilege of ours,
or presumes to go against or transgress in any way the things ordained by us for the glory of God and the stability of the aforementioned church,
let them know they are bound by the authority of Saint Peter, the chief of the apostles, whose unworthy representatives we are,
and are to be punished with eternal fire along with the devil and his most terrible followers, as well as Judas, the betrayer of our Lord Jesus Christ.
However, whoever, with pious intent, acts as a guardian and observer in all things, keeping this apostolic decree with reverence for God,
may they receive eternal blessing from our most merciful Lord God and be deemed worthy to partake in eternal life.
Epistle of Pope Agapetus the Second to the People of Auvergne.
(Year Nine Forty-Six to Nine Fifty-Five.)
Bandits should be kept away from the Celsinian Monastery.
AGAPETUS, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to all the children of God's holy Church dwelling in Auvergne, eternal peace and everlasting salvation in Christ Jesus.
We are deeply astonished as to why those entrusted with pastoral care among you have their minds' eyes closed.
They allow the holy Church, as has been reported to us, to be torn apart by the rage of the wicked, devastated, and stripped of its possessions, without standing as a wall for the house of Israel, nor standing in battle on the day of the Lord to use their authority to confront robbers and bandits.
Instead, they see their own mother dishonored and remain silent, not rebuking the wrongdoers with harsh reproach.
It seems as though we either ignore or are not at all afraid of that terrible voice which said: "Cursed is he who keeps his sword from blood" from the book of Jeremiah, Chapter Forty-Eight, Verse Ten.
Therefore, we express our sorrow to all of you, fearing that the wrath of God, from His sanctuary, that is, from the foolish prelates, may be justly allowed to strike down upon their sheep.
You know well, brothers, and if anyone is unaware, let them become aware, that the place of Celsinian belongs specifically to the holy Roman Church since its founding and has remained under its protection from the beginning.
We have determined that it should be cherished with special love and judged to be elevated with great honor at all times.
This is not without reason, for the beneficial fragrance of the monastic order arising from that place seems to be spreading usefully in our regions, by the grace of God.
Therefore, we ask and beseech you, and earnestly implore you, to ensure that you show reverence to the aforementioned place and that no one presumes to disturb those serving God there.
If anyone unjustly holds anything from the land belonging to the said monastery or those monks, or from their family against the will of the abbot of that monastery, we command by our apostolic authority that they hasten to return it without delay.
If he doesn't do this, we order him to come before us to explain his reasons.
But if he also refuses to do that, he will be punished and bound by our excommunication, as we act, though unworthy, in the place of the blessed Peter, whose rights he unjustly invades without fear.
Therefore, we specifically beseech and command Lord Stephen, the bishop of Arverni, on our behalf, since the Celsinianias monastery is in his diocese, that he should not hesitate to use the sword of excommunication against all those who destroy the property of the monastery or harm the monastic community there.
They should be excluded from the holy Church of God until they are compelled to make amends with appropriate satisfaction.
XVII. LETTER OF AGAPETUS II TO LANDULF OF CAPUA.
(Year 946-955.)
Urges against violating the freedom of the monastery of Capua.
AGAPETUS, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to LANDULF, Prince of Capua.
We have learned, and it pains us deeply, that the monks of Monte Cassino are acting dishonorably and shamefully.
No faithful person is unaware of how harmful and wicked this is, as the Prophet testifies:
"The precious sons of Zion, worth their weight in fine gold, how they are regarded as earthen pots, the work of a potter's hands!"
(Lamentations 4:1).
These monks, who should serve God according to the rule of Saint Benedict, seem instead to be living in towns and streets.
Abandoning the monastic life, they follow their own desires and pleasures as if that were the rule, instead of serving the Lord.
This misconduct reflects on your late father Landulf, who, by building a monastery within Capua, not out of reverence for God but for temporal glory, ignored the danger to souls, aiming to control the monastery.
He wanted to rest with a corrupted flock so that the entire possession of the monastery would be left to his heirs as if by hereditary right.
We are deeply saddened by this and surprised that such a great man did not reconsider his blind greed, which took over the property of the ruined church of Cassino against the Prophet's words:
"All the princes who have said: Let us take possession of the sanctuary of God for ourselves; My God, make them like a wheel, as stubble before the wind, as the fire that burns the forest, and as the flame that sets the mountains on fire"
(Psalm 83:13-15).
May God avert such things from him, if possible.
However, he was frequently warned, and as long as he lived, as Abbot Baldwin himself testifies, he admitted his guilt before his bishop and fully restored the aforementioned monastery with all its possessions to the same abbot, leaving no further power of dominion for himself or his descendants.
Let us now give thanks to God for the reverence of the blessed Father Benedict.
We have decided to ordain the Capuan monastery with the mentioned abbot and strengthen it with the privilege of our authority.
By the authority of God and the blessed Peter, the chief of the apostles, we establish and ordain that in this Capuan monastery, which was built not out of love for God but out of worldly desire, one, two, or at most three elder monks, whose lives are beyond doubt, should remain to manage and guard it.
All other monks, both senior and junior, along with all the monastery's possessions, should return to the main monastery of Monte Cassino to serve God there, living under the rule of the blessed Father Benedict.
It has been defined and proclaimed since ancient times by our predecessors, emperors, and kings, that it should not be subject to the rule of any prince, duke, steward, or any great or small person in any way, but should be governed and managed with fear of God under our and the kings' protection, under the abbot's direction.
Anyone who presumes to act otherwise, or attempts to make any arrangement concerning this monastery, or presumes to invade the possessions of the aforementioned monastery, and attempts to break this our apostolic command in any way, should know that, unless they repent, by the authority of God and the blessed Peter, the chief of the apostles, and our authority, acting in his place, they are excommunicated, deprived of the church's entry, and of the body and blood of Christ, and segregated from the company of Christians.
Furthermore, they should know they are bound by the chains of anathema by the sanction of privilege.
However, whoever acts as a guardian, observer, and helper will multiply the grace of blessing and heavenly reward from Christ our Lord God.
We command that this apostolic command be held as a testimony for the future for the aforementioned monastery.
Letter 18.
A letter from Pope Agapetus the Second to Archbishop Wilhelm of Mainz, Year Nine Fifty-Five.
He grants the same privilege that Maximus the Second had given to Friduric.
Inspired by brotherly love and guided by the faith of the ancients, we cannot deny you and the holy Church of Mainz, which you lead, the requests your messengers have brought to the holy seat of the prince of the apostles and our apostolic authority, just as our predecessors did not deny your predecessors.
We understand from your letters that Saint Boniface, your predecessor, received this authority from Gregory the Second, Gregory the Third, and Zachary, among our predecessors, and indeed from our predecessor Marino to Friduric, our fellow brother and your predecessor, so that he might serve as the overseer of the holy seat of Mainz across all parts of Germany and Gaul, as an apostolic vicar and emissary.
Thus, if he encountered anyone straying from the path of justice, he could summon them, admonish, correct, and organize a synod wherever needed, wielding the power of the apostle.
Since you profess faith and submission as nearly all previous overseers of the holy seat of Mainz have done, we grant you the same authority that our previous apostolic leaders granted to your predecessors:
so you may correct the wicked and those living depraved lives, guiding them back to the path of truth through your exhortations, as you know, our vicar was sent to the regions of Germany and Gaul.
Wherever you find bishops, priests, deacons, monks, or people of any status violating the canons and constitutions of the holy Fathers, or disregarding ecclesiastical rule, do not hesitate to correct them with apostolic authority, in accordance with the canons and constitutions of the holy Fathers, and guide them back to the path of truth.
We grant you, the provisional metropolitan of the Mainz seat, the authority to convene a synod wherever it seems appropriate for the regions of Germany and Gaul, without facing opposition from anyone.
However, if anyone, God forbid, tries to oppose you, the apostolic vicar, by appealing to the apostolic seat, they should know they will not receive our decision before the time you have set.
They will lose the apostolic blessing and be bound by the chain of excommunication.
We also write a privilege for the holy seat of Mainz, stating that if anyone, regardless of their position, attempts to plunder it, they themselves will be plundered.
Unless they repent, they will be bound by the eternal chain of excommunication, imposed by apostolic authority, which has the power to bind and loose.
They will have to account for it on the day of judgment, by which I mean the day of all traitors.
Nineteen: Privilege of Pope Agapetus the Second for the Monastery of Saints Stephen, Dionysius, and Sylvester in Capite (Year Nine Hundred Fifty-Five)
In the name of the Lord.
This is a copy of the privilege written on parchment, and here's what it says, though it's barely legible.
AGAPETUS, bishop, servant of the servants of God, to the beloved in Christ, Leo, a devout son, priest, and monk, appointed and ordained by us as abbot of the venerable monastery of the saints, martyrs of Christ, Stephen and Dionysius, and the confessor Sylvester.
This monastery is known as being at the head of the former Pope Paul, and it is for you and your successors, the abbots and monks residing in the same monastery forever.
It is fitting for apostolic governance to assist those who excel in pious religion with benevolent compassion and to support their perpetual devotion with an eager spirit.
This earns the highest reward from the Creator of all, the Lord, for those who are worthy of mercy, or for venerable places of the saints, undoubtedly brought to a better state.
Therefore, because your religiousness has humbly requested our apostolic authority to grant and confirm to you and your successors forever the aforementioned monastery with all its churches, buildings, and appurtenances, both within and around it.
This includes the mountain called Augustus of Saint Angel at its summit, along with the vineyards and lands around that mountain, and the church of Saint Nicholas in its entirety with all its appurtenances.
The borders are defined on one side by the public road leading under the arch known as Virgin's.
The form itself is hidden; it's the very form of the Virgin and the mountain known as Pinzi.
On the third side, there's the wall of this city of Rome and the gate of Saint Valentine, and on the fourth side, the wall extends back to the Posterula, which belongs to Saint Agatha.
The road next to the Posterula leads by the mentioned church into the public road, and the sowing land held by Constantius, a nobleman, as well as the public road that goes to the Posterula from Pigna, the church of Saint Blaise, and leads to the form of the Virgin with lands .
.
benefits.
We also confirm to you the entire monastery of Saint Valentine, with all its buildings and surroundings, and its properties everywhere, said to be outside the gate of Saint Valentine, which rightfully belongs to your monastery.
Additionally, we grant and confirm to you the Molvian Bridge in its entirety with all its entrances and exits and gifts and tributes in the same manner.
The vacant sowing land, about a bushel of wheat, with all that pertains to it, is located before the gate of Saint Valentine next to the often-mentioned wall of this city of Rome, and it neighbors, on one side, the Fossant, that is, the Carbonaria between the wall itself.
This land extends from there to the larger river .
.
public road which leads and returns to Saint Valentine, and on the fourth side, the rights of the Holy Roman Church.
Moreover, another sowing land in its entirety, with all that pertains to it, is positioned with the right hand there going to Saint Valentine with the larger arch within it, called Passarana .
.
in the place known as Orto Pisce, between neighbors on one side already mentioned public road, and on the second side, the fountain of living water which is shared between the monastery and heirs .
Once, to Gregory, the custodian of the school of the confession of Blessed Peter, extending up to the top of the ancient wall, and on the third side, land from the venerable monastery of Saint Cyriacus, known as Via Lata.
It runs straight along the boundary leading up the slope of the mountain called Bassitulo.
On the fourth side, it borders the public road that descends through the valley named Bussitudo and leads out onto the Via Flaminia.
We also confirm for you the entire estate, which Girulo owns, complete with various trees and everything generally associated with it.
This property appears to belong to you according to the series of writings mentioned earlier, located in the area of Saint Valentine, approximately one mile from the city of Rome.
The boundaries include, on one side, the public road with ancient stone leading to Sanguinaria, and on the second side, a small stream that flows from beneath the mountain of the aforementioned Girulo or the meadow of the venerable monastery of Saint Cyriacus.
On the third side is the mountain above the already mentioned mountain of Saint Valentine or the arable land belonging to you and the aforementioned monastery, held by the heirs of the late Roman from Campo Marzio; and on the fourth side.
.
Likewise, we confirm for you the entire estate called Pelajolum, with its arable lands, fields, meadows, pastures, mountains, and the plain where the church of Saint Sylvester once stood, situated in a deserted area.
This includes everything generally pertaining to it, as it was once granted to your aforementioned monastery through an exchange document by Alberic, the former senator of all Romans.
He and his siblings, Constantius, a nobleman, Sergius, bishop of the holy church of Nepi, along with Bertha and another Bertha, subscribed and consented with their own hands, specifically for the valley of Saint Vitus, which Alberic donated to the venerable monastery of Saint Agnes, placed from your aforementioned monastery.
As previously mentioned, outside the gate at the mile marker from the city of Rome near the Tiber River, there lies land between the boundaries of Gurgini on one side and the Tiber River on the other.
This includes the cultivated land and its meadow from the venerable monastery of Saint Basil, located in the School of the Dead, along with an additional parcel of land.
Additionally, there is another meadow from the venerable monastery of Saint Mary, located on the Aventine, and also land with a meadow from Gregory at the Field of Mars.
On the third side, there is the estate with six columns and the hill known as Mollario, and on the fourth side.
.
rights.
Similarly, there is one complete meadow you hold outside the Solar Bridge in the area known as Fliscari.
It is bordered on one side by the Ditch, on the second side by another meadow, on the third side.
.
and on the fourth side by the meadow which Benedict holds of the Saint of Candida Woods the bishop.
Also included are the rights and the complete estate known as Gallorum or Balneolum and Paccianum, or by whatever other names they were known from the beginning.
Just as John, known as Oudino, once did through a charter gift in your aforementioned monastery, with sowable lands, sand pits, fields, meadows, pastures, buildings, ruins, and adjacent flat areas and wells; whether cultivated or uncultivated, with all things that generally and completely pertain to it located outside the Salarian Bridge, about a mile from that bridge.
The boundaries include, on one side, the estate that was Roserii belonging to Peter; on the second side, the ancient wall and land that once belonged to the late Maczoni, son of the sacristan, now held by Ylpizo, a nobleman; on the third side, the land of Stephen of Theodorus the prefect; and on the fourth side, the crypt known as Serpentaria and another vacant land next to it, rights belonging to the venerable monastery of Saint Vitus.
There are also other cultivated lands, two complete sections placed next to the estate and adjacent to the aforementioned crypt on the side of the crypt, within boundaries on two sides, land that once belonged to the aforementioned Rosa above.
On one side, the land belongs to the heir of Leo Camburlingo, and on the other side, it's bordered by the public road near the monastery of Saint Vitus.
Additionally, there is a large column, intact, with a chamber beneath it and surrounding vacant land, seemingly encircled by the public road, located within this city.
Likewise, outside the Numentano bridge, an entire estate owned by Lampati is bordered on three sides by the river surrounding Tiberone, and on the fourth side by a ditch and the public road leading to the monastery of Saint Lawrence, known as Palacina.
Additionally, there is a woodland, measuring a few bushels, with sand quarries and broken walls, located outside the gate of Saint John, a few miles from Rome.
The neighboring lands are: on two sides, the land of Adrian, a nobleman and son of the late Adrian the archivist; on the third side, the land of the heir of the late Stephen Chaumati; and on the fourth side, the aqueduct.
Moreover, other cultivated lands are located there with various trees, as indicated by a series of documents, with everything related to them.
These lands are found outside the aforementioned gate, about six miles from the city, bordered by: on one side, the land of Stephen Denimentis and Theodore the prefect; on the second side, the land of the heir of the late Theodore of Aventino; on the third side, the land of Morani; and on the fourth side, the aqueduct and the estate known as Seven Bassi, with its associated lands, including other cultivated lands, located in the area called Mil, outside the gate of Saint John.
Furthermore, we confirm for you the ownership of three complete plots of land.
The first is called the Bridge of Nine, located within the bridge itself, and it includes various farmland and trees.
This plot also consists of gravel pits, ruins, and specific areas, whether they are in use, cultivated, or left uncultivated, along with everything generally associated with them.
These are situated outside the gate of Saint John, known as the Via Latina, approximately nine miles from the city of Rome.
Among the neighboring boundaries, one side borders the aqueduct called Claudia and the bridge called Nine.
The second side borders the aqueduct known as Abeberatorium.
The third side is adjacent to the area known as Corte de Moreni, and the fourth side leads to the cave belonging to the holy Roman Church, known as Ardenda.
Additionally, there is another entire plot called Dompnicaria, which includes a deserted church with its ruins, farmland, and various types of fruit-bearing trees, whether they are cultivated or not, along with everything related to it.
This plot is located on the Via Latina next to the plot from the Bridge of Nine.
The boundaries for this plot include, on one side, the plot itself, on the second side a flowing stream called Papati, on the third side a public road with ancient paving, and on the fourth side, a larger layout and the plot called Seven Vassia with all its appurtenances.
There is also another complete plot called Casana, which includes various places and names, such as the valley Marciano, the house Pretiosa, the hill called Paulelli, and the field known as Albanensis.
If there are any other names from its origin, these encompass farmland, woods, various trees, and water mills, similar to the deserted church of Saint Peter's, along with everything generally associated with it, located already on the Via Latina.
About ten miles from the city, among his relatives, lies the land where there used to be meadows called Paul's.
On the second side, there's the estate known as Civitella.
On the third side, you'll find the vineyard of the mentioned monastery, along the public road leading to a place called Sella of Saint Peter.
On the fourth side, there's the deserted church called Saint Mary in Diaconia, and from there, it descends through the ditch to the area mentioned earlier.
If there are any other neighboring lands or those originally part of the rights of the venerable monastery of Saints Andrew the Apostle and Bartholomew, known as Honorii, they are included as well.
This includes a church in its entirety, which belongs to Saint Angel, with vineyards and lands around or distant from it, along with everything generally and entirely pertaining to them, as you hold them in your hands, located in the territory of the Appian patrimony, near the Alban Hills, about a mile from the city of Rome.
On the hill known as Crescentuli, among neighbors on two sides, there's the land of Monte from the heir of the late lord called Cacainbocte, as marked by boundary and trees.
On the second side, the Clasura continues through the trees and the side land held by Peter the doctor, reaching the boundary alongside the vineyard of the venerable monastery of Saint Mary, which is on the Aventine.
On the third or fourth side, there's also the vineyard of the aforementioned monastery on the Aventine, along with the vineyard in its entirety, with its entrance and return to Calcatorio, and everything pertaining to it, located in the territory of the Alban Hills, about a mile from the city of Rome.
Neighboring on one side is the vineyard that belonged to Aczo Accariti, and the vineyard of the venerable monastery of Saint Lawrence outside the walls.
On the second side, there's the vineyard of Aczo of Albano.
On the third side, the vineyard of the aforementioned monastery of Saint Mary of Aventine, and on the fourth side, also the vineyard of the aforementioned monastery of Saint Lawrence outside the walls.
There are four vineyard plots in total, complete with pressing rights and entrances, along with everything that belongs to them in the same area.
These are located in a place known as Rufi, bordered on two sides by Lady Marocze's vineyard, on the third side by another vineyard, and on the fourth side by the vineyard of the venerable Saint Sabba called Cellanova.
There's an entrance through the vineyard from Silice Majore, and another vineyard with pressing rights and entrance from Silice Majore, including everything belonging to it in the Ariciens territory.
This is situated in a place called Cucuruczii, bordered on one side by the aforementioned Silice, on the second by a vineyard, on the third by the road leading to a wall called Longum, and on the fourth by a vineyard.
We also grant you the entire estate known as Zizinni, including the Church of Saint Mary, vineyards, lands, a mill, and crypts, just as you currently hold them.
It is located in the Albanens territory, about 13 miles from the city of Rome, under the jurisdiction of our major vestarius, with a payment of three gold solidi.
It is bordered on one side by the estate of Saint Euphemia and the vineyard of Urso, formerly the primicerius, on the second side by the vineyard of the heir of the late Gausbert, on the third by the public road and the field of the venerable Stephen, and on the fourth by the estate known as Luczano.
Additionally, there are two vineyard plots in a place called Honori in the Aritiens territory, as you currently hold them, specifically in the aforementioned Aritiens territory.
This is located in a place with a vineyard at the foot of Silice Majore; bordered on one side by the aforementioned Silice, on the second by a vineyard, on the third by another, and on the fourth by a vineyard under the jurisdiction of the venerable diaconia of Saint Mary at Cosmidi.
Similarly, we grant and confirm to you half of a saltwork at the location known as Greater Ditch, as it was previously assigned to you through a series of documents from the estate formerly called Cacainbocte.
Among the co-owners, the other half comes from the heir of the late Leoni, completing the entire saltwork.
This involves, on one side, the saltwork of Benedict, and on the other side, the saltwork of Salini, from the aforementioned heir of the estate.
And on the third side, there is the previously mentioned Greater Ditch; and on the fourth side.
.
Additionally, a complete saltwork from the heir of the late John the Elder is included.
Likewise, another full saltwork belongs to Saint Sylvester at the place called Bad Field, among the relatives.
On one side.
.
and on the second side lies your mentioned monastery.
We also confirm to you a full watermill on the Tiber River next to the Saxons' school.
This was granted to you by the late Alto Achomatos.
Among the relatives, on one side is the watermill.
.
and on the second side is the watermill of Benedict Virgarius at the gate of Saint Peter, along with his other co-owners.
On the third side is the Greater Port of the river itself, and on the fourth side is the public road leading down to those watermills, including its connection and entrance, along with all its structures and everything belonging to it, as it was offered by our predecessor John, in the document of the decree to your monastery.
Likewise, by the page of the privilege, it was granted and confirmed to you on the aforementioned Tiber River before the sewer, with water behind you, to establish another watermill.
Within these boundaries, on one side, lies the watermill of the venerable monastery of Saint Mary on the Capitol, and the watermill of Leoni, the chief scribe.
On the second side is half of the river itself, and on the third side is the watermill of Theophilatus, indeed the nomenclator, and the watermill of the venerable monastery of Saint Cyriacus, known as on the Broad Way, and on the fourth side exists the public road of the right.
The entire monastery of Saint Terentianus, along with all its affiliated cells, including those of Saint Stephen, Saint Mary, Saint Benedict, Saint Sylvester, and Saint Valentine, with all their buildings, surroundings, and related properties in the Polimarcensis region, belongs to the venerable monastery of the martyr of Christ, Saint Lawrence, known as Foris Muro, preserved by the grace of the citizens of Rome.
Additionally, I confirm to you the entire property of Paternus with its lands, as well as the entire estate of Majana with all its places and lands, including the court, Tujanum, Pollejanum, Anticuum, Sutanum, Occanum, Betujanum, Terentianum, Centumcelle, and others.
This includes vineyards, lands, forests, houses, male and female workers residing there, and all related fields, meadows, pastures, willow groves, various trees, wells, bridges, streams, and permanent structures, cultivated or uncultivated, located in the Ortano region, about 40 miles from Rome, belonging to your monastery.
We also establish for you various small farms within the city of Ortano and all immovable lands that fall under your monastery's jurisdiction, both within Ortano and in various named locations, with legal documents made accordingly.
Furthermore, in the Ortano region, we confirm for you the church of the martyr of Christ, Saint Juvenal, with all its complete properties, as it seems to belong to you from the Ortano bishopric.
Moreover, we establish for you all immovable lands belonging to your monastery within the city of Gallisana and its surrounding regions, including the estates of Cazanum, Casinianum, and Cesa Narniens.
Additionally, the estate of Preciliana.
.
We grant you everything generally and entirely belonging to the area located in the Sabine territory, under the jurisdiction of the Holy Roman Church, within the following boundaries:
On one side, the area called Massa, which is Pausa.
On the second side, the stream of Utriculo, which is Butino.
On the third side, the property of the monastery of Saint Mary.
On the fourth side, the property of the monastery of Saint Savior.
We also confirm to you the estate of Campi Mort beyond Albatum, situated between the city of Ortana.
Additionally, we confirm all the properties belonging to your monastery's jurisdiction in the territory of Nepesino and Casamala.
This includes the estates known as Casanova, Bovarico, and Boltejano, along with the male and female servants residing there, belonging to the said monastery.
Furthermore, we confirm what belongs to you in the territory of Alto, formerly Achomato, as documented by the same monastery.
Additionally, we confirm to you the entire estate known as Pacianum with everything belonging to it, located in the territory of Sutri.
Likewise, we confirm all the properties that belong to the rights and dominion of your monastery in the entire territory of Collinens.
This includes the place called Valle and Tintoriscii, and on the mountain called Asca, or in Saint Cassano, and in Curte and in Baccaricia with vineyards and arable lands, woods with its larger marsh, along with the tenants residing there belonging to your monastery.
Of the immovable places of the Holy Roman Church and the monastery, or other previous places whose rights exist.
We also confirm to you one entire estate known as Ruscitulo with all its general and entire belongings, located in the territory along the Flaminian Way.
From the city of Rome, there are approximately 14 estates, known by names such as Sergianum, Staturianum, which is also called Nuce estates, or Saburiam and Pontianum.
This also includes Bavianum and any other names it might have, along with houses, vineyards, lands, forests, and all their boundaries, limits, and borders.
On one side, the neighbors are bordered by the public road leading to the ditch from the heir of the late John the grammarian, and continuing through that ditch to the stream that goes to the bridge called Veneni.
On the other side, the public road leads straight through Montecello, which takes you to the stream, then through the sowing land on the road from Solaro.
From there, it follows the boundary to the well, and then from that well, it continues to the mentioned Veneno Bridge.
This includes any other neighbors or rights they might have held originally.
Furthermore, we confirm one complete farmstead for you, known as a rural villa, or by any other name, with all its estates and names.
This includes houses, vineyards, lands, forests, fields, meadows, pastures, various trees, sand pits, springs, whether cultivated or uncultivated, and all its boundaries, limits, lines, and everything generally and completely belonging to it, located about a mile from the city of Rome.
Moreover, we establish and confirm for you all immovable places that legally belong to your aforementioned monastery in Rome and everywhere outside Rome, as the document truthfully made for it pays the rent.
However, in the places where you have been accustomed to paying rent annually, we order you to continue paying the rent.
But for the other places where no rent has been paid over the years by your predecessors or by you, and through negligence to the officials of this seat, you should not be required to pay henceforth, without dispute from your predecessors and without your dispute.
Pray for the unwavering restoration and stability of the monastery we've mentioned.
Through this decree, we grant and establish the monastery, along with its properties, servants, handmaidens, settlers, and their families as previously listed, from this thirteenth indiction, to you and your successors, the abbots, and the servants of God of this esteemed monastery.
Make sure any necessary improvements, constructions, or defenses are made for the places mentioned, without any doubt.
Furthermore, ensure there's no delay in providing the annual pension.
The agents of our holy Church and our sacred places must be paid on time.
Therefore, under the solemn day of future judgment and under the strictest prohibitions of anathemas by the authority of our Lord and the blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, we decree.
No future pontiff or any other individual, regardless of their status or honor, is allowed by any means to undo what we have established and confirmed with a pious intent to honor our Redeemer.
No one shall take away or alienate anything from these places, possessions, families, or goods associated with this venerable monastery.
Instead, as stated above, everything shall remain intact in this holy place.
We decree, declaring by the power of our almighty God, under the severe obligation of anathema, that no one shall ever presume to bring any opposition or harm to this monastery or its related causes, places, or families, nor hold a plea or make a division, except with your permission and that of your successors.
If anyone, whether one of our successors as pontiff, a powerful person, or someone of lower status, regardless of their rank, presumes for any reason or pretext to disrupt or diminish what we have established and confirmed for the worship of God, and, though we do not wish it, tries to take away or alienate any place, possession, or anything recognized as belonging to the aforementioned monastery, let them know that by the authority of our Lord and the blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, they are bound by an unbreakable anathema and alienated from the kingdom of God.
All the saints resting in that same monastery stand against them, and they will be called before the judgment seat of Almighty God on the dreadful day of judgment to account to those same saints.
They will be condemned with the devil and his most wicked followers, and with Judas, the betrayer of our God and Savior Jesus Christ, along with all the impious, to be consumed in the infernal fire and unquenchable blaze and the abyss of chaos forever.
However, those who defend the monastery itself and keep all that is contained in this apostolic privilege of ours with complete sincerity of mind will find themselves at the right hand of God, placed in the realm of light, and will have all the saints of God who rest in that same monastery as their steadfast protectors.
They will be aided by their prayers in this present life and in future happiness, receiving the joys of the heavenly kingdom with the angels of God and all the saints and chosen ones through endless ages.
This was written by the hand of Leo, the notary of the region, and scribe of the holy Roman Church, in the month of April, the thirteenth indiction.
+ Farewell.
Given on the eighth day before the Kalends of April by the hand of Bishop Marinus of the holy church of Polimartium and the librarian of the supreme apostolic see.
In the year, by the grace of God, of our lord Agapitus, the supreme pontiff and universal junior pope.
In the most sacred seat of the blessed Peter the Apostle, in the ninth year and the thirteenth indiction.
I, Omnia, a judge and notary of the Holy Roman Church, found and read the said privilege of Carticinus, which was neither canceled, erased, nor altered.
I examined it carefully in the presence of the discerning Lords, Priest Gyptius of Saint Apollinaris and Bartholomew of Saint Mary of Caccabari, clergy of the city and rectors of the Roman fraternity appointed by the apostolic seat, and by their authority, decree, and mandate.
This was done in the presence of the undersigned literate witnesses, who were specially called and requested, namely Lord James, archpriest of Saint Mary in Via, Lord Aegidius, priest and rector of the Church of Saint Lucia of Confinium, and Lord Raynald, priest and rector of the Church of Saint Andrew of Urso.
Also present were Lord James, prior of the Church of Saint Andrew of Columna, Lord Thomas, canon of the Church of Saint Lawrence in Lucina, Lord Angelo Ronterii, canon of the same Church of Saint Lawrence, and Lord Angelo Scholari, son of Lord James Consolini, judge.
Thus, word for word, with nothing added or taken away as far as it could be read, I have faithfully copied and rendered it into public form.
This was at the request of the venerable and religious man, Lord Matthew, abbot of the venerable Monastery of Saint Sylvester de Capite in the City, of the Order of Saint Benedict, and by the decree, authority, and mandate of the above-mentioned rectors under the year of Our Lord 1267, indiction 5, month of July 27.
The privilege of Carticinus had a leaden seal suspended by a violet silk thread.
On one side, these letters were read in a circle around a central cross: AGAPITUS, and in the middle was a certain sign representing a star.
On the other side, these letters appeared with a cross placed there: PAPAE.
Place + sign of the notary.
+ I, Priest Gyptius of Saint Apollinaris, rector of the clergy of the city and the Roman fraternity, trusting in this publicly exemplified document, therefore subscribe myself.
I, Master Bartholomew de Caccabari, rector of the clergy of the city and the Roman brotherhood, trust in this faithfully copied public document, and thus, I subscribe myself.
I, Lord Jacob, archpriest of Saint Mary on the Way, as an aforementioned witness, subscribe myself.
I, Priest Giles, rector of the church of Saint Lucy in the mentioned vicinity, as a witness, subscribe myself.
I, Priest Raynald, rector of the church of Saint Andrew at Urso, as an aforementioned witness, subscribe myself.
I, Jacob, prior of the church of Saint Andrew at Colonna, as an aforementioned witness, subscribe myself.
I, Thomas, canon of the church of Saint Lawrence in Lucina, as an aforementioned witness, subscribe myself.
I, Angelus Ronterii, canon of the church of Saint Lawrence, as an aforementioned witness, subscribe myself.
I, Angelus, a student of law and son of Lord Jacob Consolini, judge, as an aforementioned witness, subscribe myself.
I, Jacob Consolinus, judge and now chamberlain of the judges of the city, trust in this faithfully copied document and privilege, and subscribe myself under the year of our Lord 1277, fifth indiction, on August 26th.
I, Adenulfus, judge and rector of judges, trust in this faithfully copied document and privilege, and subscribe myself.
I, Maximus, judge of Peter Odonis and now chamberlain of the judges, having faithfully copied this privilege, subscribe myself.
The Privilege of Pope Agapetus II for the Monastery of Saint Martin of Lenis, Year 955.
Agapetus, bishop and servant of the servants of God, addresses Segarius, the devout abbot of the esteemed monastery of Saint Martin, known as Lenis, located on the bank of the Atace River in the valley of Bolicarnea, and through him, extends this message to the entire venerable monastery forever.
We are deeply committed to ensuring that all churches do not experience any loss but instead receive the necessary benefits for their needs.
Therefore, it is our duty to care with a sincere pastoral heart and to diligently provide the support they require.
The grants we have made for the sanctity, honor, praise, and glory of our Lord Almighty's divine majesty to our venerable places should be acceptable and bring us abundant mercy, worthy of this kind of pious work, as a reward in the heavenly realms.
Therefore, since you have requested that we grant you the church of Saint Mary in Coronulas, along with its lands, vineyards, and all its revenues,
similarly, the church of Saint Stephen in Bolorda, with its lands, vineyards, and all its belongings;
likewise, the church of Saint John in Combreto, with all its belongings;
also, the church of Saint Peter in Petralata, with lands and vineyards;
furthermore, the village of Buxo and Petrus, with lands, vineyards, forests, and water mills;
similarly in the village called Cassanges, with houses, vineyards, and lands, and half of the village called Barosa, as well as in the village of Adasate with lands and vineyards;
in the same manner, the village called Artosol, with all its belongings: equally within the county of Feniolotense, and the county of Rodense, and Rosselione, we should grant to your religiousness.
.
forever.
This is to ensure that from you and your successors, each according to the ecclesiastical regulations, a tribute of ten silver coins.
.
Twelve denarii should be paid promptly for our improvement or decision, ensuring there is no doubt in handling this matter.
Moreover, there should be no delay from you in making the annual payment.
It should be given to the shareholders of our holy Church at the designated time.
We decree with apostolic authority, by the authority of the blessed Peter, prince of the apostles, under the threat of divine judgment and anathema, that none of our successor pontiffs or any other person, regardless of their status, should presume to remove these aforementioned places from the power and control of the aforementioned monastery.
If anyone, regardless of their status, dares to act against this apostolic command of ours with reckless boldness, let them know they are bound by the chain of anathema, alienated from the kingdom of God, and condemned with all the wicked to eternal punishment by fire.
However, whoever observes this command is deserving of grace, mercy, and eternal life from our most merciful Lord.
Written by the hand of Leo, scribe of the holy Roman Church, in the month of October, in the thirteenth indiction.
Farewell.
The Privilege of Pope Agapetus II for the Monastery of Monte Cassino, Year 955.
Agapetus, bishop and servant of the servants of God, grants to Baldwin, a beloved son and abbot of the venerable Monastery of Monte Cassino, and to all those who enter it in accordance with the rules, forever.
It is fitting for apostolic leadership to provide compassionate assistance to those strong in pious religion and to grant suitable support to just desires.
Therefore, because you have requested us to grant you the Monastery of Saint Stephen, the first martyr of Christ, which has long been in ruins and deserted, along with its churches, cells, waters, streams, lands, fields, pastures, forests, cultivated or uncultivated, and everything generally belonging in entirety to the aforementioned monastery, situated in the territory of Terracina within these boundaries:
From the first boundary, the farm called Vorke, and the farm Clevini;
From the second boundary, descending the mountain slope as it ascends by the foot of the mountain, under the very mountain, by the foot of Mount Lacui, and as it goes to Campilla Mountain, by the Balanus stream, the mountain of Montania, and the farm Rustizanu and Tauri.
From the fourth boundary, the farm Salissanu, and Plage, and Baleranum up to the David stream, and returns to the Barkas farm.
By the authority of the holy Roman law, which we serve under God's guidance for the Church, we are obliged to grant you the right to maintain it for all time.
In response to your requests, through this decree, we grant you and your successors the right to hold the aforementioned monastery and everything related to it, as stated above, starting from the present 14th indiction, forever.
We decree and proclaim, under divine judgment and the threat of excommunication, that none of our successors, nor any person of any rank, should presume to take away what you have received from us for the restoration and return to its former status, for the salvation of the soul of our spiritual daughter Stephania.
However, if anyone, which we do not wish, should dare to oppose this apostolic decree of ours, let them know they are bound by the authority of God and of the blessed Peter, the chief of the apostles, and excluded from the kingdom of God.
But those who, with pious intent, act as guardians and observers of this apostolic constitution of ours in all things, may they merit to obtain the grace of blessing and mercy from our righteous judge, the Lord God.
Written by the hand of Acritioneri, the scribe of the holy Roman Church, in the month of October, in the aforementioned 14th indiction.
Farewell.
Given on the 17th day before the Kalends of November, by the hand of Andrew, the divine, with regard to grace, the treasurer of the holy apostolic see.
In the year, by God's favor, of the pontificate of Lord Agapitus, the supreme pontiff and universal pope, in the most holy seat of the blessed Peter the apostle, the 10th year, in the aforementioned month and indiction.
Twenty-Two: Privilege of Pope Agapetus II for the Cell of St. Mary and St.
Hunegund of Humolaria (Year Nine Hundred Fifty-Five)
In the name of the holy and inseparable Trinity:
I, Agapetus, with the help of Christ's mercy, am the bishop of the holy Roman seat.
When we respond favorably to the holy requests of the devout, we believe we are serving the Lord's will.
Therefore, let it be known to all the children of the Catholic Mother Church that our son, the child of glorious nature, Lothair, King of the Franks, has humbly asked us to strengthen a certain cell located in the region of Vermandois, built in honor of the blessed Mother of God, Mary, and Saint Hunegundis, the virgin, with the protection of apostolic authority.
At the suggestion of his father, King Louis, and equally to himself, King Lothair, Count Adalbert, and a suitable man named Eibert, who possessed the same little abbey by right of benefice, are trying to elevate it to the venerable worship of sacred religion and strive to reinforce it with a royal decree.
Rejoicing in his request, we exercise the strength of ecclesiastical vigor, bolstered by authority.
We command that no secular person should ever possess the aforementioned abbey, nor should anyone usurp anything from the goods of the same cell for themselves, whether king, count, bishop, or any prince with whatever power endowed, unless perhaps for the purpose of guarding and defending, and this only with the permission of the regular abbot of the same place.
If anyone gives money or any gift to the king or any prince, or promises to do so to obtain this, they shall be subject to the curse to be inflicted.
Let there be, therefore, an abbot for the same cell, appointed according to the rule of Saint Benedict, and monks subjected to regular discipline, whom we prohibit, with all authority, from suffering any loss from the goods of the same cell.
Therefore, the properties of the same church include the village of Humolarias, where a cell has been built, along with all its associated dwellings.
Additionally, the estate of Merulf with its surroundings, the estate of Eudold and its appurtenances, and Caviniacus with its dwellings are included.
In the village called Frisia on the river Summa, twelve dwellings are permanently designated for the church's benefit, specifically for fishing.
If anyone acts against the protection of this apostolic privilege, we excommunicate them.
Thus, they are bound by the chain of this curse and are accursed.
Amen, amen.