Sulpicius Severus, who knew him well, clearly testifies that Saint Martin, the bishop of the Church of Tours, was outstanding not only in the holiness of his life but also in the excellence of his teaching.
He says: "Indeed, in his words and conversations, what gravity and dignity he had!
How sharp, effective, and quick he was in answering questions about the scriptures!
I swear by Jesus and our common hope that I have never heard from anyone so much knowledge, intelligence, and such good and pure speech.
Although, in the virtues of Martin, how small is this praise!
Except that it is remarkable that even this grace was not lacking in an unlearned man."
And elsewhere: "Now if you turn slightly to the left and enter the Gulf of Achaea, let Corinth know, let Athens know, that Plato was not wiser in the Academy, nor was Socrates braver in prison.
Greece was indeed fortunate to have heard the Apostle preaching; but Gaul was in no way abandoned by Christ, who granted them Martin."
This is from Sulpicius.
Furthermore, under the name of such a great Father, the Confession of the Triune Unity and the One Trinity is circulated, written in a simple style and somewhat obscure in places, perhaps due to the ignorance of the scribes.
It was first published in 1512 by Jodocus Clichtoveus along with other works of the ancients.
Subsequently, this same booklet has often been reprinted through the efforts of learned men like Pierre Pithou, Caspar Barth, Christian Daum, and others.
It is also found in most libraries of the Fathers and in collections of councils.
Combefis has this to say about it: "I copied," he says, "a sermon on the Holy Trinity, bearing his (Martin's) name, from a manuscript of Cardinal Mazarin; but it was so corrupted that it did not seem worth presenting.
This seems to have happened because the copyist was not able to transcribe successfully from the older parchments or wax tablets.
However, this aligns with the conjecture of what Severus writes with such strong testimony about the learning and eloquence of the unlearned Martin.
"
So, Combefis reflects on the passage we just recited from Sulpicius.
The same Confession of Utrecht was published in 1514 by Theodorus Pulmannus from old manuscripts.
His various readings at the end of his edition, which appeared in Cygneae in 1677, were dismissed by Daumius.
Above all, the diligence of Thomas Beauxamis is particularly commendable.
He acquired three very ancient manuscripts, carefully compared them, and published the same book by the holy bishop of Tours.
This edition, with a short commentary attached to the Life of Saint Martin by Sulpicius Severus, was released in Paris in 1571.
We've followed this edition because it's much more refined than others and considered quite rare.
It's helpful to share some insights from the same Parisian editor.
While he shows the effort he put into this work, he also establishes its integrity and value.
He says:
"Three volumes were brought to me from different libraries, and the handwriting itself indicated they were quite ancient. The characters, when compared with others used a thousand years ago, were held to be very similar by everyone's testimony. Furthermore, these three volumes contained a triple history of Severus Sulpicius."
"But when I recognized the summary of our faith written by Saint Martin at the beginning of each book, I was truly astonished. Given that Severus's works were frequently published, not even a mention was made of this. I believe that, aside from the antiquity of the characters, the complexity of the subject matter deterred others. The text lacked periods, commas, or other marks, making it appear ambiguous to some, incomplete to others, and generally obscure."
"Because it encompasses such a difficult matter with utmost brevity, who could have drawn anything certain from such perplexing words? Therefore, I thought it worthwhile to restrain the flowing words with punctuation, like bonds, thus easily rendering the Confession of Saint Martin."
To ensure nothing was overlooked, I added small notes so readers wouldn't be confused by any unclear words.
Our Parisian editor then continued to highlight the excellence of the booklet, demonstrating how this Confession of Blessed Martin refuted several heresies: those of Ebion, Cerinthus, Marcion, Mani, Apollinaris, Arius, Macedonius, and Eunomius.
After explaining these, he concludes:
"You see, Christian reader, how Martin succinctly dismantles many heresies?
He emerged at a time when attempts to undermine the Trinity or the singular divinity were arising.
Consider the numerous schisms, factions, and sects that appeared during his era, and you'll easily understand that this statement on the faith of the Trinity and singular divinity was published with good reason."
That's what he says.
Anyone who examines these matters carefully will likely argue, in my opinion, that some scholars mistakenly viewed such a Confession with suspicion, even though it's mainly supported by the authority and credibility of the oldest manuscripts.
It's truly worthy of comparison with the Exposition of Faith by Gregory the Wonderworker, if you overlook a few harsh words, which might be due to scribes' errors.
The Confession of Saint Martin on the Trinity of the Unity and the Unity of the Trinity
The compassionate Trinity is one divinity, known through the sacrament: unity comes from Him who is holy and spirit.
From Him, who is the only begotten, existing in divine nature, light, and spirit.
From Himself, through nature, through the substance of majesty, power, virtue, and divine light.
One Spirit in two, and both in the same: Father in the Son, Son in the Father, in the Holy Spirit.
Thus, in three persons, we confess the body of knowledge: which above all, encompasses everything.
In this mystery, we believe that all things arose from nothing.
A mystery the human mind cannot comprehend, nor can an eloquent tongue explain.
Nor can extensive discourse, even if it filled the whole world with books, explain divine knowledge.
He who is indescribable cannot be described or comprehended, neither in word nor substance of His own divinity.
He is the source of divine light, of light, of His own substance, nature.
Let the eloquent tongue be silent, for speech fails about the indescribable: when the human mind has finished speaking of divine majesty, then it begins.
However great divine mercy is, no one knows, except He who begot: and no one discovers the secrets of the Father, except He who by nature, lost the beginning of being born.
Therefore, let all meekness and modesty of the learned turn to the prophet, and presume by the Lord's authority, saying:
Psalms 116:10.
I believed, therefore I spoke.
Through the mystery, the profession is simple, as the foundation of the Church, solidified by Apostolic authority.
Let the following predestination presume, saying.
Henceforth let no one trouble me, I believe in Christ, and Him crucified.
Because when he confesses the Son of Man, he also confesses the Holy Spirit: because from the Holy Spirit, and Mary the virgin, the mediator is born.
When he confesses the firstborn, it is necessary to speak of the only begotten, who testifies that He is one and only without origin: the third person he confesses as the Father, existing in divine nature, light.
The Spirit, as I mentioned, is unified in the divine nature, being one in two, and each within the same.
The Father is in the Son, the Son is in the Father, all within the Holy Spirit, and the holy Church.
Now and forever and ever.
Amen.