Letter to His Relative Valerian on the Contempt of the World and Secular Philosophy
by Eucherius of Lyons
Those who are bound by love are also united by blood.
So, it is fitting for us to take great pride in this gift from God, that we are connected by both affection and kinship.
Two relationships unite us into one feeling: one from our fleshly parents, the other we chose ourselves.
This dual bond of lineage and love has compelled me to write to you at length, to commend to your mind the cause of your soul, and to assert the true happiness and capacity for eternal things, which is the work of our profession.
Since I love you as much as myself, it is necessary for me to desire the highest good for you, just as I do for myself.
Indeed, you are not averse to the profession of a holy life, having a devout nature that has anticipated many teachings of sacred institutions with early maturity.
You seem to have embraced certain duties of religion almost by providential nature, already with the indulgence of our Lord and God towards you.
By His grace, divine teaching can find and contribute some good in you.
Although you have been elevated to the highest peaks of the world by your father and father-in-law, surrounded by illustrious titles from both, I long for a far superior honor for you.
I call you not to earthly, but to heavenly dignity; not to the dignity of this age, but of the ages.
For this glory is certain and indelible, to glory in eternity.
Therefore, I will speak to you not of the wisdom of this age, but of that hidden and secret wisdom, which God predestined before the ages for our glory.
First Corinthians 2.
I will speak to you with great effort, caring little for myself, considering more what I wish for you than what I can achieve for myself.
This is the first duty of a person who has been created and brought into the light, my dearest Valerian: to know their Creator, and having known Him, to embrace Him; and to dedicate their life, which is a divine gift, to divine service and worship.
So that what they received as a gift from God, they may complete with devotion to God, and what they unworthily received from Him, they may offer back to Him in submission.
We are guided by a sound belief that since we were brought forth by Him, we belong to Him.
Therefore, whoever understands this clearly and magnificently perceives the intention of our Creator in forming humans, knows that both we and He were made for each other.
It is then best to give primary care to the soul, so that what is more important in benefit is not less considered.
The primary concerns should take the first place in our lives, and the highest parts of our worries should be claimed by salvation, which is the highest concern.
This should occupy us for its own protection and guardianship, not just primarily, but solely.
It should surpass everything with the effort that precedes all.
We owe the highest observance to God, and the greatest to the soul; and yet, this is so that, since both are paramount, it appears that neither can be observed without the other.
Thus, whoever satisfies God must necessarily have already taken care of the soul; and conversely, whoever takes care of the soul must necessarily have already satisfied God.
In this way, the matter concerning both the highest and most beneficial in us is resolved in a forced yet beneficial summary; so that if someone diligently fulfills one, they achieve both, because by the ineffable divine kindness, utility itself becomes a sacrifice to God.
Much effort is spent on bodily treatments; much work is given to the hope of healing.
Does the soul not deserve medicine?
And if various aids are applied to the body in the pursuit of health, it is not right for the soul to be left lying as if excluded and neglected, wasting away in its diseases, and exiled from its own remedies.
Indeed, more should be provided for the soul if so much is given to the body.
For, if some have rightly said that the flesh is a servant and the soul a master; it is not fitting for us to place the master in a lesser position and unjustly prefer the servant.
Deservingly, a better part of us seeks higher pursuits, as we should aim for the greater dignity of our being.
It is not fitting, in this noble endeavor, to subject ourselves to something lesser.
The flesh, inclined towards vice, pulls us back to the earth, as if to its origin Genesis 8.
But the spirit, coming from the Father of lights, strives for higher things, like iron drawn to fire.
This is the image of God within us, this is the precious pledge of divine grace.
We must protect it with all our strength; if we govern and preserve it, we are safeguarding God's trust Second Timothy 1.
Who can build without first laying the foundations?
For anyone seeking to build other benefits, health is the cornerstone.
But how can one add to these without first securing the basics?
How will the growth of what follows increase if the foundation is lacking?
How can one think they are attaining happiness when they lack even health?
How can someone who lacks life abound in a happy life?
And what good is it to add food if there is nothing to nourish the soul?
About this, our Lord Jesus Christ said: "What will it profit a man if he gains the whole world, yet forfeits his soul?" Matthew 16.
Therefore, no profit can exist if it means the loss of the soul. Where there is a loss of health, there certainly is no gain; for how can gain be found if the foundation for holding it is not secure? And so, towards that true profit, that holy and desirable exchange, while there is still time, let us hurry Galatians 6.
A few days can produce eternal life; but even if these days held the untouched and unstained happiness of life, because they are few, they would be considered of little value. For nothing is truly great if it is short-lived; nor is joy lasting if it ends quickly. The fleeting usefulness of this world offers only brief comforts.
Therefore, it seems right to prefer the benefit of eternal life over the good of a short life.
Eternal happiness is everlasting, while the joys of a short life are temporary and fragile.
Eternal life is truly blessed. What could be happier than eternal life?
In contrast, this short life is filled with burdens.
It is pressed from all sides by troubles, wearied by evils, and tossed by the injuries of events.
This life is untrustworthy, variable, and calamitous.
It is full of labor, anxiety, cares, and dangers.
It becomes restless with bodily afflictions, anxious with mental anguish, and uncertain in the whirlwinds of dangers.
What reason is there not to desire eternal goods and instead follow temporary, even bad, ones?
In this life, a prudent person invests generously in a place where they expect to stay longer.
Where they expect to be for a short time, they provide little; where for a longer time, they provide more.
Likewise, because the present time is very short and constrained by narrow limits, and the future holds ages, let us enrich eternal life with appropriate abundance and equip the short life with what is suitable.
We should not give the greatest care to the short time and the least care to the greatest time.
It's hard to say what should compel us more quickly or effectively to this most blessed life: the benefits of the future life that are promised or the inconveniences of the present life that are apparent.
The future benefits entice us sweetly, while the present inconveniences strongly drive us away.
Even the worst things can support the better part.
If we are not attracted by the good, we are pushed by the bad.
To encourage better things, the best harmonize with the worst, and different things converge for the same benefit.
While some things invite us, others repel us, both urging us toward the better.
If a famous and wealthy person were to summon you to adopt you as their child, you would go through all sorts of difficulties and travel great distances to reach them, wouldn’t you?
God, the Lord of the universe and all things, calls you to adoption, offering you the sweet name of "child" if you are willing, the same name He calls His only Son.
First Corinthians chapter 8, Galatians chapter 4, Ephesians chapter 1.
And yet, you are not moved or urged to hurry, lest death snatches away this great opportunity with its swift arrival?
And to obtain this, you won't venture through desolate lands or the uncertain seas of far distances?
Whenever you want, this adoption is with you.
Will this matter make us sluggish and lazy because it is as accessible as it is great?
The more reluctant will experience this condition more harshly.
For it is more harmful to those who are unwilling, the easier it is for those who are willing.
Certainly, it is the desire for life that has tied us to the enjoyment of the present reality.
So, those who love life, we urge you to life.
It is reasonable to persuade when we ask you to obtain what you desire.
For the life you love, we act as ambassadors to you.
Second Corinthians chapter 5 verse 20.
Ephesians chapter 6 verse 20.
And we suggest that you love the eternal life, which you all love in a small measure, so that you may love it more.
How can we love it, I wonder, if we don't desire this life to be as beautiful as possible?
Therefore, that which pleases even when it is brief should please more if it can be eternal; and that which has value to us, even though it has an end, should be beyond value to us if it can be endless.
It is right, then, to consider lesser life in view of greater life, so that we may build a passage to the latter through the former: a plan that should not be hindered by the dubious benefits of the associated one.
It should not oppose itself to the extent that it harms.
It is indeed absurd and contradictory for the love of life to bring harm to life.
Therefore, whether you think this life should be despised or embraced, my argument is easy in either case.
For if it is despised, there is one reason for doing so, which is to seek a better one.
And if it is loved, then the greater life should be loved all the more.
However, I want you to see this as an experiment itself.
Acknowledge that it's extremely troublesome and filled with uncertain exhaustion, and judge it accordingly.
Reject it along with its preoccupations and dismiss it.
Let the endless chain of worldly affairs be broken, and let that single labor for many necessities throughout life be ended.
Let's break the bonds of futile concerns, whose succeeding links entangle us, making our occupation always seem to begin anew.
Remove those empty but intertwined causes, in which, as long as we live, human endeavor never finishes, constantly starting new tasks.
The tireless focus on these things has already made our inherently short and narrow life even more restricted.
From these come vain joys, bitter sorrows, anxious wishes, and suspicious fears.
Finally, let us discard everything that makes this present life short due to busyness and long due to pain.
Let us reject the life of this untrustworthy world, which is suspect in every way.
In this world, both high and low are equally unsafe.
The lowly are trampled by humiliation, and the high sway in their prominence.
Whatever position you choose, there is no rest in either the lowest or the highest states: both conditions cannot escape the heavy fate of the whirlwind.
The lesser is subjected to insult, the greater to envy.
Two main things, I believe, hold people bound in the affairs of the world and captivated by its seductive allure: the pleasure of wealth and the dignity of honors.
Of these, the former should be called not pleasure, but need; the latter, not dignity, but vanity.
Both of these, entangling us in alternating knots, hinder our steps, deceptively embracing our fellowship.
They insidiously inspire vices into human hearts with their enticing desires and solicit the weary minds of mortals with easy pleasure.
For what is more pernicious than riches, to speak of them first, which are rarely amassed without injustice?
Such a resource is achieved with such an administrator, preserved with such a guardian.
For the love of money, says Scripture, is the root of all evil.
(First Timothy chapter 6, verse 10)
There is almost a kind of partnership, even in name, between these two things: vices and riches.
Aren't those riches a source of insults?
As one of our own has said:
"What else are riches but pledges of injustice?"
Don't they, like rewards placed before the wicked, provoke the eyes and minds of troublemakers, practically displaying and inviting their own confiscation?
But suppose that does not happen. Can we be sure where they will go after us, who will wander and flee?
"He stores up wealth and does not know who will gather it"
Psalm
38:7.
But suppose the heir comes as desired. Doesn't the heir often squander the wealth, and the accumulated riches are wasted by either a poorly raised son or an ill-chosen son-in-law?
What pleasure do these riches have in themselves, whose possession is miserable and transmission uncertain? Where, misled and headlong, are you taking the love of men?
You know how to love the things that come to you, but you don't know how to love yourself?
What you love is outside; what you desire is outside yourself. Rather, return to yourself, so that you may be dearer to yourself than your possessions.
Indeed, if someone well-versed in matters were to approach you, wouldn't you prefer that he love you yourself rather than those things that are with you? And you would choose that he direct his affection more towards your life than your wealth. You want to be faithful to a person, not to things. What you would want another to give to you, you, who are your own most faithful friend, should give to yourself. Let us love ourselves rather than our possessions.
And these things have been said against wealth. As for the honors of this world, to remain silent on other matters, what dignity can there be in things when the wicked rise to these positions just as ambitiously as the good, and a single honor does not encompass men of a single merit, and dignity no longer distinguishes between the worthy and the unworthy, but confounds them?
Thus, what should have preferred the better to the worse has begun to equalize them: and in a new way, there is almost nowhere less distinction between the best and the worst men than in honor. Isn't it a greater honor to prefer to be without such dishonorable honors, and to be valued more for one's own morals than for shared honors?
And these very things—whatever they may be—how fleeting and temporary they are.
Recently, we saw men distinguished by honor, sitting in lofty positions, spreading their wealth across the world.
Their successes surpassed their desires, and their achievements exceeded their wishes.
But I only recall private fortunes.
Even kings, exalted by great power, shone with jewels.
Their garments glittered, their crowns sparkled with interwoven metals and adorned trees.
Their palaces gleamed with royal splendor, and their ceilings glimmered with gilded beams.
Their wills were the laws of men, their words were called statutes.
Who can rise above the transient happiness of man?
Behold, their grand ambitions are gone, their abundant riches have vanished, and the very masters of such wealth have passed away.
As it is written in the book of Job chapter 14, and in the book of Wisdom chapter 5.
Some of the most recent and renowned kingdoms are now merely stories to us.
All those things that were once great here are now nothing.
Nothing, as I think, or rather, as I certainly know, did they take with them from those riches, honors, and kingdoms, except—if there was any—the essence of faith and piety.
This alone follows them, devoid of other things.
This alone accompanies them faithfully as if it were an inseparable companion.
They are now nourished by that help, now rest in those riches, now find peace in those honors.
These are the rewards they now possess.
Therefore, if we are captivated by honors and riches, let us be moved by true riches and true honors.
The best of us transfer earthly honors and earthly riches to heavenly honors and heavenly riches.
Certainly, to that place where there is a clear and undisturbed distinction between good and evil: where, what we once obtain, we always hold: where, if there is a place for obtaining, there is none for losing.
But since we have spoken about the fragile possession of temporary goods, we must also mention the condition of this brief life itself.
What is this, I ask, what is this?
Nothing do men see daily as much as death: nothing do they forget as much as death.
Humanity is swiftly heading towards its demise, and every generation follows this unavoidable law.
Our ancestors have passed away; we will depart, and future generations will follow.
Just like waves crashing on the shore, one after another, ages are broken by the boundary of death.
This thought should echo in our minds day and night, reminding us of our mortal condition.
We must consider that the end of life is always approaching; the more it is delayed, the closer it gets.
We should expect the day to be near, for we do not know if it is far off.
Let us prepare ourselves for the end, as it is written in Malachi 3:1.
If we think about these things and meditate on them, we will not fear death by fearing it.
Blessed are those who have reconciled with Christ.
There is little fear of death for those who wish to be released and to be with Christ, as stated in Philippians 1.
Those who are ready and at peace, awaiting the end of their life in silence, will not be much affected by the timing of their temporary end as they transition to eternal life.
Let us not be swayed by the negligence of others in life, nor be led astray by their errors to the detriment of our own salvation.
What good will the multitude do us in God's judgment, where each will be judged individually and only personal merit and actions will absolve anyone, not the crowd?
Let misleading comforts cease.
Surely it is better to have lived with the few than to have perished with the many.
Therefore, let not the number of sinners lead us to negligence in our sins.
Let the fact that others care little for themselves not become an authority for us.
I implore you, always regard another's sin as a disgrace, never as an example.
If you must look at examples, look to those who, though they may be fewer, are abundant in virtue.
Look to those who wisely understand why they were born and, while they live, pursue the purpose of their life.
Those who are distinguished by useful deeds and outstanding virtue enhance the present life and sow for the future.
There are not only abundant examples of these, but also great ones are not lacking.
What nobility, honors, dignity, wisdom, eloquence, and literature have not already devoted themselves to the service of this heavenly kingdom?
What high position has not already submitted to this light heavenly yoke with surrender?
Indeed, it is above all error and ignorance for anyone to neglect the matter of their own salvation.
If it were not too lengthy, I could recount by name many illustrious men who have followed this stricter observance of divine worship and life: whose examples, lest I omit them all, I will briefly mention a few.
Clemens, from an ancient lineage of senators and even from the line of Caesars, filled with all knowledge and highly skilled in all liberal arts, transitioned to this righteous path; and he flourished so excellently in it that he also became the successor of the chief of the apostles.
Gregory from Pontus, a priest, outstanding in philosophy and eloquence in the world; but later greater and more outstanding in virtues, so much so that, as the faithful accounts of our histories tell, among other remarkable signs of merit, it is said that by his prayers and orations, a mountain withdrew, and a lake dried up.
Another saint, also named Gregory, equally devoted to letters and philosophy, desired this heavenly philosophy.
It should not be omitted, as it pertains to the matter, that he, while still engaged in secular studies, entered the lecture hall of Basil, who was still devoted to the profession of rhetoric, and, taking him by the hand, led him out of the school, saying: "Leave these things and apply yourself to salvation." Later, both memorable priests left behind in the books of our Church the illustrious monuments of their genius.
Paulinus, the bishop of Nola, a unique and blessed example for our Gaul, once had immense wealth and abundant eloquence.
He embraced our perspective and purpose so fully that he spread his eloquence and deeds to almost all parts of the world.
Recently, Hilary and now in Italy, the bishop Petronius, both from the highest seats of worldly power, have risen—one in the name of religion, the other in the name of the priesthood.
And when will I recount the most renowned eloquent men like Firmianus, Minucius, Cyprian, Hilary, John, and Ambrose from that vast number?
They, I believe, said to themselves what one of us said, stirring themselves to this more blessed life from the secular world:
What is this?
The unlearned rise and seize heaven, and here we are, with all our theories, wallowing in flesh and blood.
(Matthew chapter 11). They said this?
And so, they later forced their way into the kingdom.
Having mentioned a few of those whose great fervor for our faith existed, who had experienced worldly philosophy, eloquence, and honors, I will now turn to kings and that head of the world.
I will not now recall all those ancient men devoted to religion and royal dignity; only the remarkable ones, David for his piety, Josiah for his faith, Hezekiah for his humility, will be drawn from the venerable annals of memory.
Some also from more recent times, even in our own age, have become leaders who have drawn closer to the recognition of the true king, and with utmost contrition of heart, have confessed the supreme Lord of lords; both sexes from the court have shown attentive reverence to the divine majesty.
These, I think, should be proposed as worthy examples to emulate, whose examples provide salvation for the future and authority for the present.
You see how even days and years, and all these ornaments of the sky, preserve God's word and command with tireless observance, and keep his precepts with unwavering service.
Are we, for whom these things have been made, for whose eyes they have been given, knowledgeable of heavenly commands and not ignorant of divine will, going to ignore God's command with deaf ears?
Indeed, once it was commanded to these aids of the world what they should observe through the ages; but for us, the commands of divine law are reiterated in so many volumes, so that at least, as it is attributed to man himself, he may learn to obey the will of the Creator and attend to His commandments.
Because all of this, while it provides service, also sets an example.
And yet, if some do not want to return to their Creator, can they therefore avoid their Lord?
Or where can they escape to, those who turn away from God?
Let them listen to you, holy David, let them hear you saying:
"Where can I go from your Spirit, and where can I flee from your presence? If I ascend to heaven, you are there; if I descend to hell, you are there; if I take the wings of the morning and dwell in the uttermost parts of the sea, even there your hand shall lead me, and your right hand shall hold me" (Psalm 139).
Therefore, whether they want to or not, they belong to the Lord of the universe, and if they take themselves away by will, they do not withdraw by right.
They are indeed absent in affection, but He is present in dominion.
So, what is unwise and most thoughtless, the wandering ones live closed off from the consideration of the Lord, but within His power.
And if anyone pursues a fleeing servant with threatening pursuit, and as the enforcer of his right follows the one evading him, why does he not return his own right to the heavenly Lord, and as soon as possible, offer himself in voluntary servitude to His service, being just both to himself and to his own judge?
Why are we fixed on the delightful sight of present things?
Why do we dwell so much on what we see?
Do we live only by these eyes, or do we carry our eyes solely for use?
We also live by ears, so that we can be eager for promises.
Great affections draw us through this part of the body as well.
Let us eagerly await with fervent vows and pressing desires those things that are promised and preached.
The faithful one, that author, instills faith in promises.
Let us strive for the best things that are promised.
If we aim to use our eyes effectively and beneficially, we are often driven by a desire for the future.
When we turn our admiration from observing the world back toward the creator of such a grand design, or when we reflect on how much greater the light's splendor will be when it meets our eyes in the future, given the current magnificence of the light:
How much more magnificent will the form of eternal things shine, when even perishable things are so beautiful now.
Therefore, we should not misuse our bodily functions for lesser purposes but rather balance them well for both our physical and eternal lives.
Use what is temporary in a way that we do not neglect service to the eternal.
If this distraction and love please us, and if the delight of sensation draws us, this love truly is the height of pleasure.
It is not only something that can be immensely loved but also something that should be loved the most, as it is pleasant, splendid, unique, and an eternal good.
God, our God, whom you can burn for with such a great and pious fire, if precious desires follow in place of former ones.
If the dignity of such magnificence captivates you, nothing is more magnificent than that.
If something adapted to glory and fitting for it seizes you, nothing is more glorious than that.
If you are led by the sight of splendid, shining things, nothing is brighter than that.
If you are drawn by the sight of beauty, nothing is more beautiful than that.
If you think you embrace truth in something, nothing is truer than that.
If you believe in the generosity of something, nothing is more generous than that.
Do you marvel at what is pure and simple?
Nothing is more sincere than that goodness.
Are you attracted by the abundance of flowing things?
Nothing is more plentiful than that abundance.
Do you love something for its faithfulness?
Nothing is more firm in faith than that.
Do you love something for its convenience?
Nothing is more convenient than the love of this itself.
Does something draw you with its severity or pleasantness?
Nothing is more magnificent or worthy than that.
Kindness is required in adversity and sweetness in prosperity.
It is unique in providing either joy in happy times or solace in sad times.
Therefore, it is most reasonable for you to love Him above all, in whom you have everything.
Wealth and whatever else currently delights you not only reside within Him but also come from Him.
Let your scattered love henceforth be devoted to divine watchfulness.
Your wandering affection should be brought back to sacred use, now pure love.
Correct and direct your straying affection, suppressing error, and turn your love towards God, because whatever you love now is His; His, I say, it is His.
For He is so great that those who do not love Him, unfairly indeed, still cannot love anything except what is His.
Yet, I would like a just judge to consider whether it is fair to love the work while neglecting and abandoning the Creator of all things; to rush into desires and pursuits for His creation indiscriminately, when surely it should have been proper to be drawn to love God through this very affection for His works.
And now man is turned against Him, towards the desires and services of unworthy creations, with minds discordantly at odds, seeking the art but abandoning the artist, embracing the appearance without marveling at its creator.
And what have we said about that great multitude of His sweetness?
Or what have we spoken of such great and ineffable goodness, the holy and profound treasure of His love?
Or when has anyone ever been able to fully express the dignity of this matter by speaking of it?
Therefore, let us consider that loving Him is not only pleasurable but also necessary.
Indeed, it is impious not to love Him, to whom you cannot repay even when you love Him.
It is most unjust not to want to give Him what you can, to whom, even if you wanted to, you could not repay.
For what shall we return to the Lord for all He has given us?
Psalms 116:12 asks, "What shall I return to the Lord for all His bounty to me?" What shall we return, even for this one thing, that through faith He gave salvation to man and established it, so that it was as easy as possible to spread hope to the world and life to mortals.
And to delve into these matters, do you think that all those external things, like nations and kingdoms, came under Roman control and law for any other reason?
Was it not so that faith might penetrate more easily through one nation, like medicine through one body, allowing what is given to the head to quickly spread to the limbs?
Otherwise, there wouldn't have been such a unification among nations with different customs and languages, nor such a long journey through new stages.
Finally, Blessed Paul, noting the spread of faith through this same people, writes that from Jerusalem all the way to Illyricum, he has filled everything with the Gospel of Christ.
Romans chapter fifteen, verse nineteen.
When would this have happened among nations, either countless in number or savage in their barbarity?
This is why now the whole earth, from the rising to the setting of the sun, from the north and the sea, proclaims Christ.
This is why all sides of the world converge towards life, while the Thracian, the Libyan, the Syrian, and the Spaniard accept faith.
Therefore, a great proof of divine mercy is that under Caesar Octavian, when the Roman Empire was at its peak, God gave Himself to the earth.
So, to quote your own words, when about 1,185 years had passed since the beginning of this kingdom, whatever was added to the Roman Empire under the ancient kings or later under the dual administration of the consuls, all was prepared and provided for the coming of Christ and the spread of faith, if anyone is a suitable witness to show it.
We will return to the topic.
Do not love the world or the things in the world, First John chapter two, because all these things deceive our sight with false colors.
The power of the eyes, given to light, should not be directed to error: and while it is open to the uses of life, it should not admit causes of death.
The desires of the flesh, as the Apostle excellently says, wage war against the soul.
First Peter.
All these things are prepared for our destruction and disaster; they keep a vigilant watch, rising against us like foreign enemies.
They gain as much strength as they take away from us.
So far, I have spoken about the inescapable temptations of this deceitful world, including honors and riches, as if the world thrived on its pleasant allurements.
Whatever appearance those things once had, polished with a sheen, has now faded, and all false splendor has disappeared.
The world now barely has the power to deceive.
The image of those things, once beautiful enough to deceive, has perished.
It used to try to seduce us with true brilliance but could not; now it almost cannot corrupt us with false display.
It lacked solid goods, and now it even fails in fleeting ones.
Neither temporary ornaments adorn it, nor do enduring ones strengthen it; unless we deceive ourselves, the world can hardly deceive us.
But why do we hesitate to express what is stronger?
We speak of the dissipated wealth of the world, while the world itself is moving towards its end in its final stages.
How much greater and more serious is it that it will not last long?
Why do we recall its worn-out belongings?
It is not without reason that, with its strength consumed by age, it is pressured into decline and abandoned by its supports, as it now collapses under the burden of its old age.
The last age of the world is filled with evils like the diseases of old age.
Famine, pestilence, devastation, wars, and terrors have been seen and are still seen in this gray age.
These are the weaknesses of its final years.
Hence, those signs in the sky, earthquakes, changing seasons, and monstrous births of animals are often seen.
All these are still wonders of the passing time, but they are already fading.
And this is confirmed not only by our weak words but also by the authoritative sayings of the apostles.
For it is written: "The ends of the ages have come upon us" (First Corinthians 10).
Since this was said long ago, why do we delay, why do we wait?
That day compels us, not just for ourselves, but for our time as well.
Every hour reminds us that the moment of decision is near, where the end, with its uncertain danger and dual crises, threatens everyone equally with death.
The world's mortality now weighs on me, as if my own fear weren't enough.
Why do we fuel our fears?
There's no room for security when the end threatens us all, both individually and collectively.
How much worse is the miserable condition of people, not just at the end of an age, but even in its decline; who neither place their hope in future joys, nor enjoy present pleasures.
They don't seize the joy of this brief life and have no hope for eternal life.
They don't use temporal goods, nor will they use eternal ones.
Here, there's little substance, and there, no hope at all.
This is a truly pitiable and miserable state of humanity; unless perhaps, one turns this bitter condition into a necessary correction, striving for better remedies and more wholesome desires; especially when the present time is so torn apart that losing the benefit of one future age means losing both.
All our focus must be directed to the hope of the future: to achieve this hope more fully and clearly, I won't hesitate to use an example.
If someone today offers you 5 bronze coins and promises 500 gold coins tomorrow, giving you the option to take the bronze now or wait for the gold: is there any doubt you would prefer the larger reward with a small wait?
You, too, considering the nature of this brief and eternal life, wouldn't choose the worthless things when you can hope for the precious ones.
It's not worth taking the small things when it's better to wait for the great ones.
If all the fragile things in the world, which we see and grasp (for hope is based on what we hope for), it's clear that hope is not to be found in this age, in which we enjoy what we see.
For hope that is seen is not hope.
For who hopes for what they see? (Romans 8:24).
Therefore, whatever hope mixes with human affairs must be sought in the future; otherwise, it cannot even be called hope if it is not hoped for.
And so, we follow a more evident hope in the future than the hope of what we experience in the present.
Behold, the things close to our eyes are not looked at absolutely as if our vision is overwhelmed; but much more certainly, we focus on things offered from a distance, as if our eyes are free.
Therefore, it is not to be doubted that it happens similarly with present and future things.
For present things, as if thrust into our eyes, are not seen correctly; future things, as if drawn back from our eyes, are seen most clearly.
And we do not presume this confidence in future things from an uncertain author, but from our Lord Jesus Christ, the truest guarantor of truth, who promises an endless kingdom to the just and ample rewards of the most blessed eternity; who also, through the ineffable sacrament of assumed flesh, being both man and God, reconciled man to God; and through the great and hidden mystery of his passion, absolved the world of sin.
Thus, he was manifested in the flesh, justified in the spirit, seen by angels, preached among the nations, believed in the world, taken up in glory: for this reason, God exalted him, so that everything in heaven, on earth, in the sea, and in the depths, may now confess that the Lord Jesus is in glory, King and God before all ages.
(Philippians 2).
Why don't you, rejecting the precepts of philosophers to which you apply your effort and intellect, turn your mind to the studies of Christian teaching to imbibe them?
There, too, you will find material for your eloquence and intellect to exercise; and it will soon be clear to you how much our precepts of piety and truth surpass those of the philosophers.
For in their precepts, either virtue is shadowed, or wisdom is false; but in these, true justice and solid truth are contained.
Hence, it is legitimate to say that others have usurped the name of philosophy, but we have the life.
Indeed, what kind of precepts for living can be given by those who do not know the cause?
Ignorant of God and turning away from righteousness from the very beginning, they fall into further error in other matters.
Thus, it happens that the end of such pursuits is vanity.
If some among them define more honorable things, they serve this boastfulness and labor for it.
Thus, among them, abstinence from vices is not free from vices.
These are, as it is written, those who are focused on earthly things.
Philippians 3:19
.
Hence, it is clearly shown that they do not see true righteousness or true wisdom.
Will anyone from that school of Aristippus see the truth, who in his nature is no different from pigs or cattle, when he places happiness in bodily pleasure: whose god is his stomach, and whose glory is in his shameful parts?
Will he teach what is honorable and just, who philosophizes while being a spendthrift, shameless, and adulterous?
But let another occasion be reserved for speaking against philosophers; I will now come to those matters for which I speak with you.
Leave aside those general opinions of theirs that you find pleasing, mostly brief and collected from various disputations, and turn yourself to the studies and writings of our people.
There, you will satisfy your mind with diverse instruction.
There, to instill faith, you will hear not these exact words but the following meanings:
The Word of God, who does not believe, does not understand.
There, you will be reminded: Fear the Lord, because you call Him Lord; love Him, because you call Him Father.
There, you will learn about true sacrifices by hearing: The most acceptable sacrifices to God are righteousness and mercy.
There, it will be suggested to you: If you love yourself, love your neighbor; for nothing benefits you more than what you give to others.
There, it will be commanded to you: Do not consider any cause so worthy that it justifies the death of a person.
There, you will be advised against unlawful acts: Resist lust as the most bitter enemy, who rejoices in insulting the defeated, even with the shame of the body.
There, you will be taught not to covet: It is better to not want what you do not have than to have what you desire.
There, you will be instructed not to get angry: He who gets angry when provoked only does not get angry when he is not provoked.
You will hear about enemies: The one who is loved does not love the one who loves, because hardly anyone does not love the one who loves them.
It will be repeated to you often: He who divides his treasure with the needy, stores it well.
For he cannot lose what he has invested by giving it away.
You will be persuaded of happier things, when it is said: The result of faithful marriages is self-control.
You will learn to discern when you hear: The evils of this world are common to both the just and the unjust.
You will be offered this to hear: Greater sorrow is when the soul suffers from vices than when the body suffers from diseases.
This will be pronounced to commend peace to you: Similarity of manners among the impatient is a cause of discord.
To avoid following the wicked, you will hear: The wise and the prudent inform, and the foolish; the former teaches what should be imitated; the latter what should be avoided.
These things too are brought forth: Many things benefit the ignorant; therefore, God's kindness is no less in secret than in the open.
You will be reminded: Give thanks to God not more in prosperity than in adversity; and when things go well, admit that you did not deserve it.
More distant things will also be revealed to you when these are preached: Ask the nations or their laws whether there is fate; for they certainly do not punish, except according to the will of actions.
You will hear these things prescribed to maintain purity: If you want to be truthful, you will not be suspicious.
For we do not suspect what we do not know.
You will also hear this about higher matters: With the mind fixed on God, when it is tickled by passions, it is brought down from heaven to earth.
You will be reminded of these things too: When here the wicked sometimes receive good things, and the good are afflicted by evils; those who do not believe in God's future judgment judge God unjust (which should never be).
It will be suggested to you: Do not do in secret what you wish people not to know; do not even think what you wish God not to know.
You will be told against all deceit: It is more unfortunate to deceive than to be deceived.
These things will also be prescribed to you against boasting: Avoid vanity all the more, the better you become.
For other vices grow with vices, but vanity grows with virtues.
These few insights into studies have been briefly touched upon.
But if you delve into the very sources of sacred texts, you will marvel not only at the surface but even more at the depth within.
When Scripture shines from within, like a precious gem at the bottom, it draws the eyes of those who contemplate into its deep radiance.
Train yourself not to turn away from the dimming vision of the mind; learn to satisfy the soul's hunger with this inner and wholesome nourishment.
We do not doubt that through the work of the merciful Lord, you will desire our teachings, disdain your own, shun the trivial, and long for the substantial.
It is most foolish, when God has done so much for us, that we have done nothing for ourselves; and although He has looked to human welfare in His works, man is unwilling to provide for himself.
Indeed, we provide for ourselves if we return our affection and devotion to God.
True happiness is to scorn the happiness of the world and, neglecting earthly things, to burn with divine love.
Therefore, from now on, direct all your words and deeds to God or for God's sake.
Ensure that she always accompanies you, and she will be your guardian.
Innocence is already faithful.
It is great to follow virtue and to contribute to it with our strength.
Do not fear that the soul cannot free itself from the habits of life for a better life.
The same one to whom we offer ourselves to be healed and protected provides strength to our affection.
From where, however?
So that anyone might be able to grasp the reward of future goods even in estimation.
Behold the divine generosity, as we see, has granted the use of the most beloved light to all indiscriminately.
The common sun is given to the pious and impious alike; all creation serves its duty with kind services, and the entire world's possession is indiscriminately shared by the good and the bad.
Since God grants such splendid things to the just and unjust here, what must be reserved for the just?
Let us consider, He who gave so much, how much will He restore?
He who is so great in gifts, how great will He be in rewards?
If the generosity of the giver is so immeasurable, what will be that of the one who rewards?
The things God has prepared for those who love Him are beyond description, truly immense, especially considering how greatly He rewards the good who give so much to the ungrateful.
Look around, and from the sea of your concerns, look ahead and steer your course, as if navigating toward the harbor of our profession.
This is the one harbor to which we are brought back from all the turbulence of the fluctuating world.
We seek it, weary, among the crashing waves of life; here everyone must flee who is harassed by the storm of the raging world.
Here is the most faithful station, and certain peace.
Here a wide recess, shut off from the waves, is silent.
Here gentle tranquility shines serenely.
When you have been brought here, your ship will be safely held by the anchor of the cross after fruitless labors.
But now, the longer page of writings demands an end.
Receive the essence of the heavenly commandments, collected briefly and concisely, for the honor of God.
These are all the commands, forgive me, and recognize me.