Chapter One
The writer's aim is explained.
As we dive into another segment of Manichaean history, we face numerous and quite serious challenges.
First, we must discuss Mani's disciples and identify those who propagated this heresy further after his death.
We also need to pinpoint the regions and locations where it infiltrated to undermine the Catholic faith.
Finally, we should mention the Church Fathers who worked tirelessly to destroy and refute the books, letters, and fictional writings of these heretics.
In tackling this task, we discovered that both ancient and modern writers often disagree with each other, making it very difficult to establish anything with certainty.
This is particularly true because Beausobre, following his own interests and studies, adopted critical rules that don't aid in discovering the truth.
Instead, he adhered to those which, as we've discussed before, do not seek the truth.
We find it unnecessary to give an example of this approach at the start of this second book.
Besides the examples already provided in the previous book, there are countless other lies, slanders, and fictional interpretations that remain to be exposed.
We are ready to address and refute these at the appropriate time and place, to show how deceitfully and less learnedly he wrote many things.
We believe these writings contain clear errors of heresy, or at least lead to heresy.
Meanwhile, we cannot overlook the liberty and freedom he takes in attacking those Church Fathers who either described or opposed the Manichaean heresy.
He constantly accuses them of ignorance, as if they contradict themselves.
He criticizes them for opposing their own statements and claims they didn't fully grasp the systems and mysteries of the Manichaeans.
It is as if he alone deserves the glory and honor for more successfully penetrating the entire philosophy, theology, and religion of that heresy.
I admit that I've also found many aspects of this type of writing to be hidden and wrapped in layers of obscurity, making them difficult to understand, even with enthusiasm and diligence.
When we encounter such complexities, it's often best to consider the opinions of others, sometimes agreeing with them, or acknowledging our ignorance of what remains completely hidden, rather than creating fanciful and absurd tales that can't be trusted.
Here, the reader gets a general, albeit rough, idea of what Beausobre described in the preliminary discourse to the second part of the Manichaean History.
However, since we can't cover everything in detail at the beginning, we'll make sure to refer more extensively throughout the rest of this work to what we deem necessary.
Chapter Two
Let's explore how, after the murder of Manes, his heresy spread and grew.
We'll address the errors made by Beausobre and Cave.
We'll also correct the excessive freedom in Augustine's criticism.
Finally, we'll investigate how this vile sect eventually disrupted regions like Armenia, Mesopotamia, and other parts of Asia.
After Manes's brutal death, the seeds of his wickedness weren't extinguished.
Instead, scattered here and there, they took root quickly, spreading through the zeal of other wicked individuals, and expanded in opposition to the Christian faith.
If we trust Archelaus, Turbon, and Ephraem the Deacon of Edessa, the Manichaean doctrines were initially preached mainly in the East, in places like Syria, Mesopotamia, and Egypt.
This occurred because Manes, before his death, appointed his main false apostles to those regions.
He instructed his disciples, the followers of Manes, to go to three parts of the world.
Among them, Adda was assigned a portion of the East.
Thomas took on the lands of the Syrians.
Hermas traveled to Egypt to spread this doctrine.
However, when it comes to this order and division of provinces, ancient writers slightly differ, as noted by William Cave.
For example, in the works of Cyril and Epiphanius, Thomas is placed first, and Epiphanius claims he went to Judea, though Dionysius Petavius, in his annotations, disagrees, suggesting Judea should be read as India.
Theodoret claims that Thomas was sent to the Indians, a view supported by Nicephorus in Book 6, Chapter 32.
If this is true, the impostor may have wanted to mimic Christ by sending the apostle Thomas to preach his gospel in India.
Now, moving past this Thomas, let's shift our focus to Adda, the teacher of Turbon, another key false apostle of the impostor Manes.
So, Archelaus claims he was sent to deceive the Syrians.
However, Peter the Siculus calls him Budda, Cyril refers to him as Badda, and Theodoret names him Alda.
Finally, Epiphanius and Nicephorus, following the Acts of the Disputation of Archelaus, called him Adda.
Regardless of the name, it's clear that the man we're discussing not only followed in his teacher's footsteps but also invented many new ideas, making the Manichaean doctrines more influential through his efforts.
For this reason, he compiled a book called the Modion, mentioned by the author Tollianus.
Against this book, according to Photius in his Bibliotheca, several years later, Titus, the bishop of Bostra in Arabia, and Diodorus, the bishop of Tarsus in Cilicia, wrote in opposition.
This indicated that by the fourth century of the Church, these provinces had been affected by this kind of influence.
However, Beausobre argues differently and somewhat inconsistently, stating that when discussing Bishop Titus of Bostra, it wasn't Adda's Modion but the book on Mysteries, circulated under the name of Manes, that Titus rejected.
He asserts that Bishop Titus took a different approach in refuting this book, saying it was divided into 22 chapters according to the Syrian alphabet.
The errors were effectively refuted by this wise and learned bishop without any personal attacks on his adversary, avoiding calling the author a magician or someone involved in abominable mysteries.
He adds that Manes, the author of this book, was a philosopher who convinced himself that this world did not align with the idea we have of divine perfections, and therefore believed it must have had another origin besides God himself.
Beausobre claims to have used the works of Titus of Bostra as sources because he wrote much more accurately and moderately than Epiphanius himself.
But what happened?
Despite the wealth of knowledge at his disposal, Beausobre fell into such negligence that he soon forgot what he had said.
Since he forgot that he had written that Manes was not accused by Titus of Bostra of magic, invoking demons, and abominable mysteries, he later adds that this bishop was deeply troubled to revisit and examine what had been mystically devised by Manichaeus.
However, the more mystical inventions of Manichaeus, which are numerous, are largely passed over in silence.
Titus of Bostra, therefore, was hesitant to explore these more mystical inventions of Manichaeus.
It shouldn't be assumed that he omitted them for any reason other than to avoid offending his readers, much like how Saint Leo the Great refused to discuss these abominable mysteries.
Yet, there remains the question of whether Titus of Bostra critiques the volume of Manes' mysteries in his work or another, specifically the Modion, written by Adda, guided solely by the authority of Beausobre, which I do not claim to define.
Those familiar with his diligence in composing his Library will agree with me that the testimony of Photius should prevail.
But we will discuss Adda's book further below.
Regarding this Addas and his work, William Cave once admitted he made a serious error by believing him to be no different from Adimantus, who is often mentioned by Augustine and whom the holy bishop refuted in a special work.
However, Cave has since retracted this mistaken belief, aligning with the history of Peter the Siculus and the authors of the Cotelerian and Zolian formulae.
Yet, to excuse himself, he wrongly attributes the cause of his previous mistake solely to Augustine, reciting the following: "For that other work, which had begun to be written in the same manuscript 110, is the work of Adimantus, the disciple of Manichaeus, who is called by his proper name, Addas."
But what could be more negligent or unjust than such an excuse? For he did not quote Augustine's genuine words but falsified them.
By omitting the word "son" from the testimony, he inserted another, namely the pronoun "his," completely changing the meaning of the holy doctor's words to what Cave thought would benefit him.
Is this a sign of wanting to rise from his previous mistakes and make amends, even while unfairly criticizing and attacking Saint Doctor?
It's certainly nonsense.
These are Augustine's words:
"As for the other thing that began to be written in the same manuscript, it is the work of Adimantus, the son of a disciple of Mani, called Addas, either by his own name or, as the Maurini Fathers read, by a given name."
The given name followed by the manuscripts, included by the Maurini Fathers in the latest edition, is not an error.
It's not due to Cave's misinterpretation, negligence, or bad faith.
Instead, the mistake is in the word "son," which was incorrectly changed to the pronoun "his."
In fact, in no editors or manuscript copies do we find this word "his," but they consistently show the word "son."
This makes it clear from Augustine's own words that Addas and Adimantus were different people, even though both were very impious defenders and promoters of the Manichaean doctrine.
So, when Augustine refers to the name Addas not as a son but as a disciple of Mani, it seems most relevant to Cave's and our discussion.
Namely, that Adimantus either had Addas as his father or was at least called his son due to the terrible teachings he absorbed;
for these reasons, the surname Addas could also be appropriately applied to him,
indicating Adimantus' lineage or the school from which he came.
Finally, what stops Adimantus from being initially called Addas by his given name and then changing it later, following the example of his leader Cubricus?
Nevertheless, this doesn't mean that Addas should be identified with another primary pseudo-apostle of Mani, who was chosen to travel the East while his master was still alive.
Besides Thomas, Addas, and Hermas, the primary followers of Mani, the rest of that group of twelve also eagerly spread that wicked heresy.
Peter the Sicilian tells us that after the killing of Manes, some of his followers made their way into Armenia, reaching Samosata.
There, they spread seeds of impiety and led many Armenians into deception.
This seed grew significantly, becoming an evil root that extended to Phanaria, bringing deadly consequences to many.
Peter the Sicilian, who later served as an ambassador to the Armenians on behalf of Emperor Basil, briefly explained whose efforts primarily caused that vile heresy to nearly destroy Armenia and Phanaria.
He mentioned a woman named Gallinicia, who had twin sons named Paul and John.
These two, nurtured by their mother, were taught the wicked sect and sent as preachers of error from Samosata.
They entered the territory of Phanaria and reached a village, where they found people naive and uncertain in faith, spreading the poison of impiety and the dire enemy's tares.
Dionysius Petavius asserts that this woman, Gallinicia, was impure and depraved.
He also learns from the same Peter the Sicilian that she sent her wicked offspring to various parts of Armenia to spread the teachings of Manichaeism.
Meanwhile, a serious controversy can arise about when exactly this mission took place and at what specific time this heresy borrowed its new name from these two brothers.
This question is wrapped in much obscurity and cannot be easily defined.
Indeed, it is very likely that Peter the Sicilian intended to indicate two things: first, that after the killing of Manes, some from that group of twelve disciples immediately entered the province of Armenia.
Being received there, they poured out all the poison of corrupt doctrine, which grew more with each passing day, destabilizing the entire region and corrupting it with wicked doctrines.
Here's the thing: it was only after many centuries had passed since the death of Manes that a woman from Samosata sent her twin sons to Phanarion as new leaders and messengers of this dreadful sect.
Their goal was to spread the terrible teachings they had learned to mislead uneducated people.
This might be why, after many centuries, the old name of the heresy changed to the Paulicians.
However, to avoid speculation or disrupting the flow of our historical narrative, I will present the evidence on which our previous assumptions are based.
Among these, the most important is from Augustine, in his book on Heresies.
He was well-versed in the mysteries and profane rituals of the Manichaeans, describing not only how, after the death of Manes, a leader among the elect presided over twelve others called teachers, but also how much that assembly grew and expanded.
According to him, mirroring the Christian Catholic hierarchy, those twelve false apostles, along with their wicked leader, began ordaining seventy-two bishops.
These bishops then ordained priests and selected deacons.
They had twelve teachers among their elect, with a thirteenth as their leader, and seventy-two bishops ordained by the teachers, along with priests ordained by the bishops.
The bishops also had deacons.
Besides those they ordained with profane and sacrilegious rites, forming the elite of that diabolical hierarchy, they also sent others from the same elect group to various places to deceive uneducated and simpler people.
This was done to more easily spread or confirm their doctrines.
Augustine immediately adds: And now the others are only called the chosen ones.
However, those who seem fit for this error are sent either to support and increase it or to places where it hasn't even been introduced.
These practices were common among the Manichaeans in Augustine's time, as the same holy teacher confirmed with these words: The number that the Manichaeans still keep today.
Since Augustine, who was well-versed in all the doctrines, mysteries, philosophy, ranks, ordinations, hierarchy, and development of the Manichaean sect, never mentions these twin brothers, it's reasonable to conclude that in the year 428, when he wrote the work on heresies, this offshoot had not yet appeared in the world from infernal dungeons, and the Manichaeans had at that time adopted a new name from the Paulicians.
It shouldn't be suspected that this was hidden from Augustine, because the regions of Armenia and Asia, where, according to the author Peter the Siculus, these events occurred, were very far from the city of Hippo in Africa, from where Augustine wrote this work.
No one should think this, I say.
For the holy teacher, who had encountered the errors of the Manichaeans since childhood and had devoted himself deeply to the study of their philosophy, also knew well the names by which that sect was known, and described it, acknowledging without any doubt that it thrived in Paphlagonia, part of Armenia, in Gaul, in Africa, and other regions.
Indeed, in his praised book on heresies, he asserts that the Catharists are called Manichaeans, as if they are purifiers.
From this name, he takes the opportunity to severely criticize and attack them, because they polluted human food with horrendous filth.
In book one hundred and twelve on the Nature of Good, he criticizes some disgraceful acts, where they improperly and offensively claimed to bind a part of God through the sexual acts of men and women.
These acts, they claimed, were then dissolved and purified by eating.
He refers to certain public confessions of these crimes, testified in public judgment, not only in Paphlagonia but also in Gaul, as I heard from a Christian Catholic in Rome.
This was quite convincing to Augustine, who wrote this in the year four hundred and four, believing this heresy was spreading more widely in Paphlagonia in Armenia, based on public judicial records and the accounts of others.
Augustine would not have failed to report and reject the claims later made by the Paulicians to affirm, expand, and strengthen this sect.
These two deceitful brothers eagerly seized upon these claims to more disgracefully undermine the Catholic religion, attacking the Catholic ministers of the cross, the mysteries of the Eucharist, the perpetual virginity of the Mother of God, and other matters, aiming to insult them.
In the numerous books and works written by Augustine against the Manichaeans and other heretics, the name of the Paulician brothers does not appear, nor does he recount those heretical additions that Peter of Sicily mentioned to us.
I am not convinced that after the death of Mani, those twin brothers were defenders and authors of this heresy.
For that reason, I find it unnecessary to discuss them further now, as we will need to speak about them later when we follow the order and logic of time.
We will describe how the offspring of this heresy was still spreading more widely in the regions of Syria and Asia during the seventh century of the Church, to the contempt of the Catholic religion.
Meanwhile, it's important to note that even before Augustine's time, in the early fourth century, the Church in Armenia and Paphlagonia faced significant challenges from the errors of Mani.
This is evidenced not only by the sermons of Mani's false apostles and the destructive writings spread by Thomas, Agapius, and others during the reign of Constantius Chlorus, but also by the clear testimonies from the Acts of the Council of Gangra, which still exist today.
Only fifteen bishops attended that synod, alongside the great Hosius of Corduba, during the time of Pope Saint Sylvester, just before the first general council of Nicaea was called.
Gangra, a city in Paphlagonia in Asia Minor, was where these fifteen bishops and Hosius gathered in response to the heresy of Eustathius, which had roots in the Manichaean beliefs and was spreading through various parts of Armenia, threatening the Catholic faith.
This is clearly evident from both the synodical letter of the Gangran Fathers and the twenty-one canons they issued.
In their synodical letter, they addressed "To the honorable fellow ministers set in Armenia."
Many canons from that synod directly denounce, challenge, and condemn various errors of the Manichaean sect, as Severinus Binius rightly and knowledgeably noted in his collection of councils.
These include canons written in support of marriage, discussions on the permissible eating of meat, and the ecclesiastical rules of fasting, excluding from the Catholic community those who disrespected the Lord's Day and the Day of Resurrection by spending it in mourning, sorrow, and fasting.
These and similar issues were indeed established to condemn Eustathius, a monk from Armenia, who had misguidedly drawn his errors from Manichaean sources.
In a similar vein, he attempted to completely abolish marriages, the procreation of children, the practice of virginity, sacred gatherings established by the Church, fasting, eating meat and animals, owning wealth, celebrating feasts, especially the solemnity of the Lord's Day, and other sacred rites approved by the Church.
Without a doubt, in the year 324, the errors of the Manichaeans had spread in Paphlagonia and Armenia through the efforts of this same monk, Eustathius.
To counteract these errors and cleanse this plague, the Fathers of Gangra had to convene.
The acts of this synod were eventually endorsed to oppose the Manichaeans' hatred and destruction, supported by the apostolic seat at the First General Council of Nicaea.
This endorsement was not only revealed by the delegation of Ossius of Cordoba for Pope Saint Sylvester but also through the decrees of Symmachus and Leo the Great, Roman pontiffs.
I am aware, however, that the delegation of Ossius of Cordoba for the apostolic seat at the Council of Gangra is questioned not only by Peter de Marca and Pagio but is outright denied.
The main reason for this skepticism is that his name appears in the fourteenth position among the bishops' names in the surviving acts, rather than first.
But when resolving these questions, it's not always helpful to trace the prerogatives of bishops by the order of their names in manuscripts.
We will illustrate this concerning the bishop of Trier, Britton, in the context of the Priscillianists, against Tillemont and others.
For sometimes, due to scribes' errors, manuscripts could be corrupted, or at least the genuine order of these bishops might be disturbed.
However, for two reasons, I think this discussion should now be avoided.
The first reason stems from the purpose of writing this history.
We are not among those who, clinging to doubtful and very obscure matters, seek to assert and vindicate the rights of the apostolic seat.
In a matter as certain and serious as that concerning the judicial power and rights of the Apostolic See, which have been clear throughout the Church's history, it would be inappropriate to indulge in personal studies, rely solely on conjecture, or veer off-topic by questioning issues that are evidently not relevant.
Therefore, since that synod was only provincial and its canons were strengthened and approved with the support of the Apostolic See, as even council collectors acknowledge, does it really matter whether Hosius of Corduba acted there as a delegate for the Apostolic See?
Another reason, out of fairness to a distinguished and learned man, is that a few years ago in Rome, at the solemn pontifical council academy, before Pope Benedict the Fourteenth, Reverend Father Antoninus Bremond, a notable theologian and a member of the Dominican family, thoroughly explained and clarified each obscure and difficult question about the time, canons, authority, and confirmation of the Council of Gangra.
His work received great applause from the entire literary assembly.
It is not permitted at present to discuss the same matters.
In this work, as well as in others, he gained the support of all scholars.
Indeed, with the common wishes of all, we promise that such a work will eventually be made public.
However, since I also presented a theological dissertation on the same Gangran canons at the pontifical academy on April twenty-third of the same year, I will include this as an appendix to the Manichaean history in the last chapter of this book.
Chapter Three
On the Manichaean Books in the Fourth and Fifth Century of the Church, Almost Spread Throughout the Entire World.
As we thoroughly discussed in the previous chapter, after Mani's death, his disciples and followers spread this heresy across various provinces in both the East and the West.
The defenders of this harmful religion didn't just rely on words and preaching to mislead the uneducated and illiterate; they also used numerous harmful books.
If unsuspecting people spent time reading these books, they became trapped and committed to the same errors.
So, I've decided to briefly mention these books for now.
We shouldn't only discuss the works of Scythianus, which he left to Terebinthus upon his death and which Mani himself revised and edited.
We've already covered the four volumes of Scythianus, a collection of stories from pagan philosophers and the foulest sources of ancient heretics, in the previous chapters of this History book.
To avoid repetition, let's now focus on other writers of this sect and describe their works.
Notably, we consider Thomas, who was credited with an apocryphal and false Gospel by all the ancients.
However, if we look at the oldest writers, there are only a few things to be said about this work.
It is mentioned as a work produced by the Manichaeans and filled with their tales.
But as far as I have seen, nowhere has anyone clearly and expressly pointed out the blasphemies contained within.
The main question to investigate is whether Thomas created this monstrosity of impiety entirely on his own, or if he took the original Scythianus Gospel, attached his name to it, and then added and exaggerated its contents.
But who would dare to settle such a question, even if the latter seems more probable?
The ancients indeed testified that the Manichaeans had only one Gospel, not two, and they falsely tried to circulate it under the name of the Apostle Thomas.
However, Cave, for reasons unknown to me, claimed that there was a distinct Gospel of the Scythians and another of Thomas.
It would be less difficult, however, to guess what fragments and blasphemies filled that Gospel.
Since it primarily addressed the birth, deeds, preaching, passion, death, and resurrection of Jesus Christ the Lord, attacking the doctrines and mysteries of the Catholic faith, it's quite likely that every deadly poison was spread there to overthrow and abolish the main foundations of our religion.
As we have seen, even according to Augustine, they denied that Christ was born of a Virgin, claiming his flesh was fake, not real, and thus arguing that his passion was false and his resurrection nonexistent.
Cyril of Jerusalem clearly indicated that wicked content about the sending and coming of the Holy Spirit, supporting another key error of Mani, was in that Gospel.
He warned Catholics to beware of reading it.
We understand that this book of devilish impiety was not only rejected by the decrees of the Roman popes, namely Siricius, Innocent the First, and Pope Gelasius, among the apocryphal scriptures, but the most holy Pope Leo the Great even decreed it should be completely removed and burned.
Concerning these and similar writings of the Manichaeans and Priscillianists, the holy Pope Leo spoke seriously, warning Catholics not to let themselves be drawn to their reading by a certain false appearance of piety that such writings seemed to present.
Although he mentions that some elements in them seem to have a form of piety, they are never free of poisons.
Through the allure of stories, they secretly work to ensnare those captivated by tales of wonders in the traps of any kind of error.
Regarding these, the decrees of the Apostolic See, upon observing the Nicaean Council's many observations, especially about this Gospel of Thomas, stated:
Concerning these false writings, which were once circulated under the name of Paul, the Manicheans introduced the Gospel according to Thomas, which the Catholic Church rightly rejects as impious.
To all these, we finally add this one point: the Gospel of Thomas is very different from the book titled the Revelation of the Apostle Thomas.
In the same Gelasian decree, both are mentioned as two distinct books, although there's no indication that the latter book, namely the Revelation of the Apostle Thomas, originated from the Manichaean workshop.
However, this opinion is not obscurely revealed by the letter of Bishop Turibius of Astorga to Saint Leo the Great.
In chapter five, discussing apocryphal books either composed or falsified by the greatest leader Mani and his disciples, he specifically mentioned the Acts of Saint Thomas and similar writings.
From these, he says, the Manicheans and Priscillianists, or whatever sect is similar to them, attempt to confirm all their heresies.
Besides one or two volumes of the Gospels, written impiously in imitation of the form of the Catholics, they also had another book of letters, namely, of the Manicheans.
It was believed by the ancients that this was primarily produced from the workshop of Mani.
Indeed, mention of this book or collection of letters occurs in both Goar and Peter the Sicilian, as well as in the author of the Cotelerian and Tollian formula.
From this body of letters, there is no doubt, says William Cave, about that famous letter which the Manicheans called the foundation, which Augustine repeatedly cites in On the Nature of Good and in the acts with Felix.
He also wrote an entire book opposing this letter.
In it, after dismissing the earlier parts of the same letter from Mani, he demonstrated that instead of the clear and certain knowledge Mani promised, he offered only uncertain and absurd nonsense to his misguided followers.
On the other hand, the Manichaean sect revered this letter as if it summarized all their beliefs.
So much so that, following Augustine's example, whenever it was read aloud, they would bow their heads and say Amen, as if to thank the wicked author for reading this so-called enlightened letter.
The letter began with: "Mani, apostle of Jesus Christ, by the providence of God the Father. These are the beneficial words from the eternal and living source."
We've already seen a similar beginning in the letter to Marcellus, as found in the Latin fragments of Archelaus mentioned earlier, and in Epiphanius, heresy 66.
But Augustine alone testified that all the letters collected in that book started the same way.
He addressed them in Book Thirteen, Chapter Four against Faustus, saying: "For your Mani was not a prophet of the coming Christ. Indeed, he calls himself an apostle of Christ, with the most shameless deceit."
And a little further below, he adds: "Yet all his letters begin this way: 'Mani, apostle of Jesus Christ.'"
Regarding various letters of Mani, William Cave mentions them on page 92.
Thirdly, we consider it necessary to review the Book of Mysteries, which the Manichaeans themselves diligently composed to overturn the law and obliterate all the prophecies of the ancient prophets.
William Cave cites a fragment from Goar, where such a book is declared anathema.
This was also one of the Scythian books, but Mani greatly expanded and interpolated it in countless places to serve his own interests, the same author asserts.
Therefore, Tollius stated that it was divided into 22 parts in alphabetical order, written in the Syriac and Palmyrene languages.
These books were followed by a fourth, which some people mistakenly insisted should be titled "The Business of All Things," based on some corrupted Greek manuscripts. However, according to both the writings of Timothy of Constantinople and other notable ancient sources, as highlighted by William Cave in his Literary History, it was observed to have a different title. Relying on various conjectures, he demonstrated that this booklet received its name from the topics it covered, and it was called: "On the Difference of Those Who Approach Pure Faith." Indeed, it was proven earlier by Augustine that the Manichaeans falsely boasted about the purity of their faith, referring to themselves as Catharists, or purifiers.
Now, moving on to the items published after the Goarian formula by Cotelerius and Tollius, we encounter another book called the Apocryphon. As Cave noted, it is likely that the more secretive rites, tricks, and detestable mysteries of the Manichaean religion were contained in it. These teachings were passed down only to initiates and those involved in their vile ceremonies. We do not at all dismiss Cave's conjecture. Besides the common doctrines that the Manichaean school spread to its followers, it also taught and protected other hidden and secret knowledge, known only to the leaders and top teachers of this sect. We have already noted in the previous book, chapter 11, that Turbon testified to this in his renunciation of heresy, not obscurely. It is likely that this book described all the profane rites, sacrilegious ceremonies, fasts, and prayers used by Manichaean worshippers during their sacred and festive ceremonies for the god Bema. Therefore, in the Cotelerian formula, books of such rites and deceptions are indicated with these words: "All things that are done and celebrated by them in sacred rituals and that are contained in their Manichaean or deceptive books are to be condemned."
However, they added certain interpretations to all these, known as the commentaries of Manes and memorable sayings.
Among the Manichaean writers, Addas held a significant place, as we mentioned earlier.
He wrote a single book called Modion, filled with numerous axioms and philosophical principles.
These principles seemed entirely foreign and opposed to the common reasoning inherent in nature, recognizable even at first glance.
Some of these principles claimed that humans were inevitably led to sin by a certain evil author existing without beginning and opposed to God.
Others made the impious claim, insulting divine Providence, that this visible world was not at all governed by divine rule.
He also attempted to show that the two testaments, the Old and New, were at odds due to apparent contradictions, or rather allegories and mysteries.
In discussing the New Testament, he specifically tried to demonstrate that the errors of the Manichaean sect had drawn their strength and foundation from it.
These claims were contained in that wicked and diabolical book, as the writings of Titus of Bostra clearly demonstrate.
That very holy bishop of Arabia, with Heracleon, bishop of Chalcedon, as the author, dedicated all his scholarly efforts to rejecting and overthrowing the blasphemies and errors of that book, as noted in the works of Photius.
Curiously, William Cave recounted details about Aristocritus, one of Manes' notable disciples and writers.
Although he did not hesitate to portray his teacher as an evil man, he nevertheless adhered to his doctrines and published a work attempting to show that the teachings of the Jews, Gentiles, Christians, and Manichaeans were essentially the same.
This type of argument was also indicated in Addas's book, as is clear from what was previously stated.
From various ancient records, we understand that the early leaders, teachers, elect, and listeners of the Manichaean sect didn't rely solely on the previously mentioned books.
For instance, Timothy, a priest from Constantinople, mentions a book of Prayers, which contained formulas for prayers and tricks.
Manichaean penitents were also instructed to denounce the book of Prayers when renouncing their errors.
All other apocryphal scriptures described in the Gelasian decree are of this kind, and ancient writers believed they originated either from Manichaeus or his disciples, as noted in Cave's work, in the section on the Novatian century, page 92.
He also listed two other writers of this infamous sect from uncertain times, whom he claimed were among the more prominent.
The first of these is Agapius, whom he describes as a rather obscure writer, and aside from Photius, none of the ancients, as far as I know, mention him.
Tillemont supported Cave, adhering to Photius's testimony, asserting that Agapius was a contemporary of Eunomius and attacked and criticized him in his writings, even though he had disgracefully defected to the Manichaeans.
Nevertheless, there was some disagreement between the two.
Cave, delving deeper into the matter and considering what Peter the Sicilian had written about Agapius, argued that Photius's testimony could be interpreted differently.
From the same Peter the Sicilian, we have noted that Agapius was indeed one of the twelve disciples of Manichaeus, who composed a book called Heptalogus.
How, then, could he have been alive during the time of Eunomius to critique him and his errors?
Over 80 years passed from when Manichaeus's heresy was condemned to the fall of Eunomius, the notary of Aetius.
This time interval cannot possibly align with these two facts; that Agapius was one of the twelve primary disciples of Manichaeus and lived long enough to critique Eunomius in his writings.
William Cave foresaw this serious challenge and endeavored to address it with great diligence.
He suggests that both scenarios could have occurred and presents various conjectures from both Epiphanius and Cyril of Jerusalem, which he believes are relevant to his case, advising readers to consider them.
Ultimately, he chose not to draw any definitive conclusions on the matter.
We don't have the time to investigate this issue or its reasoning more thoroughly now, as those ancient records that could resolve such questions have either vanished or remain completely hidden.
There are still some points to cover regarding the remaining works of Agapius.
The esteemed Photius attributed two other works to him.
One of these works was divided into twenty-two books, while the other contained one hundred and two chapters, and the author himself dedicated both to a certain Urania, a woman of his sect and a companion in his studies.
If we ask Photius about the nature of the arguments Agapius explained in these books, it becomes clear that only wicked and fictitious tales were contained in them, as we have explained more clearly from Turbon's confession and Augustine's testimonies in previous sections, making it unnecessary to dwell on them again now.
William Cave believed that a certain Alexander of uncertain age should be classified among these writers, whom the ancients called Lycopolitan, from Lycus, one of the cities of Thebaid in Egypt.
Initially, he was a pagan by culture.
Then, when the Manichaeans retreated to those regions of Egypt, he defected to their camp.
However, he eventually renounced this heresy and embraced the Catholic religion.
Before he rid himself of the stain of this heresy, he wrote a book about the beliefs of the Manichaeans, which he knew very well and intimately.
In this book, according to Cave, he accurately explains their inner beliefs and effectively refutes the unhealthy doctrines of this sect with arguments drawn from the depths of philosophy.
The writing style here, which is somewhat rough and difficult, is criticized by Caveus himself.
He didn't dare to pinpoint its exact age, though he suspected it wasn't far from the times of Manes, since Alexander confirmed he received these teachings from those closely acquainted with the man.
We believe these words should be attributed to Papus and Thomas, disciples of Manes, as only these two are mentioned.
Various pieces of information about the works and age of this Alexander were reported by William Caveus, but they don't quite align, so we omit them to avoid uncertain and doubtful matters.
Now, let's discuss Adimantus, a notable disciple of the Manichaean sect, as our current topic requires.
Augustine has discussed his writings and deeds multiple times in his works.
However, he engages with him in a way that suggests Adimantus had already passed away, focusing on challenging and dismantling his writings.
This is evident from the first book of Retractions, chapter 13, where he reviews his own works, stating that while he was still serving as a presbyter, he said:
"At that time, certain discussions by Adimantus, a disciple of Manes, came into my hands, which he wrote against the Law and Prophets, trying to show them as contrary to the evangelical and apostolic writings."
Therefore, the holy doctor informs us of the title and scope of Adimantus's book.
But since he refers to the writer as a disciple of Manes and speaks of him as someone who had long since passed away, we can scarcely doubt that he both heard Manes and, through his relative Adda's influence, secured at least a place among the second-order disciples.
Furthermore, Augustine also mentions Adimantus's works in the book against Faustus.
Initially, when attributing Faustus's words to this person, who claimed the teachings of Manes and Adimantus as his own, he is forced onto the stage, boldly declaring in his madness:
"It is more than enough now that the errors, as well as the Jewish superstitions and the deceptions of the half-Christians, have been thoroughly exposed by the most beloved and only diligent Adimantus to us after our blessed Father Manichaeus."
From Faustus's words, it's clear that the Manichaeans often accused the followers of the Catholic religion of being misled by false and corrupt teachings. They also emphasized the writings of Adimantus, whom they regarded as a second leader of their sect after Manes.
Augustine criticizes Faustus again for making more shameful errors, whether concerning the nature of humans, animals, and plants-whose lives Adimantus claimed were similar in nature to Manes-or when discussing the transmigration of souls into new bodies, or lastly, when reasoning about the vain and superstitious selection of foods from the Scriptures of the New and Old Testament.
Augustine clearly demonstrated in the sixth book that Faustus absorbed these errors mainly from Adimantus's writings and defended atrocious blasphemies from them. Finally, the holy doctor harshly attacks Adimantus himself, refuting the error by which he taught that even rational souls, meaning human souls, could be thrust into animal bodies.
What, then, will Adimantus do about such a grave crime if he ever whipped or restrained a slow beast with a bridle, in which perhaps his father's soul resided?
Not to mention, he could have killed his parents among lice and fleas, which they do not refrain from killing.
Augustine also knew that some Manichaeans, when confronted with these and similar arguments, often denied that human souls could be returned to such tiny creatures.
The holy doctor willingly allowed this escape, using it as an opportunity to further criticize Adimantus and the other Manichaeans.
He cleverly mocked them and reasoned so skillfully, moving from minor points to more significant ones.
For instance, what good does it do if they sometimes deny things?
They deny to avoid being held responsible for many killings, or to avoid having to spare lice, fleas, and bedbugs, enduring such nuisances without any permission to kill them.
But when they are still strongly challenged, Augustine adds:
"Why can the human soul be turned into a little fox and not into a weasel, when a fox cub may be even smaller than a large weasel?"
Finally, to fully mock their statements, he concludes his argument with these words:
"Then if it can be in a weasel, why not a mouse? And if it can be in this, why not a lizard? And if it can be in it, why not a locust? Or a bee, or a flea, or anything much smaller?"
Through this line of reasoning, he demonstrates that Adimantus and the other Manichaeans are guilty of countless murders, as their conscience, entangled in these massive errors due to their adherence to this superstitious and nonsensical belief or doctrine, suffered gravely.
In the book against Adimantus, Augustine is entirely focused on reconciling the different views of Scripture, which Adimantus had compiled as if they were mutually contradictory, arguing that the Old and New Testaments could not possibly be from the same source.
Augustine also recalls another book he had published against Adimantus, where, after presenting Adimantus' words, the Holy Father provided his own 120 responses.
This work, he said, is contained in one volume.
In it, I answered certain questions not just once, but twice because the first answers were lost, and they were found only after I had already answered again.
I have certainly resolved some of the same questions with popular church sermons, and there are still some I have not answered.
If anyone truly desires to be more fully informed on these matters and were to ask us which church and popular sermons Augustine wished to invoke here, we would immediately respond to them.
Addressing Adimantus's accusatory objections in sermon twelve, particularly where he wishes to continue discussing the deceit and tricks of the Manichaeans, attacking Adimantus, who, by corrupting and distorting the testimony of the Apostle Paul, argued that neither rulers, nor authorities, nor powers knew God.
Therefore, to overturn such slander, he said: But first, I would like to ask them where Adimantus read this in the Apostle, for he is the author of such slanders.
I would like him to say where he read the Apostle testifying and confirming, as he claims, that neither rulers, nor authorities, nor powers knew God.
Even the Lord says that the angels of those who believe in Him see the face of the Father daily.
Therefore, Augustine brings forth these and similar matters to reconcile the famous testimony of Job, which we read in chapter one, verse six, with those other words of Matthew chapter five, verse eight, upon which Adimantus insisted, to suggest and persuade a contradiction between the Testaments.
However, since nothing else worthy of note about Adimantus appears in the works of Augustine or in the writings of others, it is now necessary to turn our attention from him to Fortunatus the priest, also a follower and defender of Manichaean doctrine.
He, according to Possidius, was stained by such a blemish, and when this infamous and nefarious heresy was spreading widely throughout the regions of Africa, he worked very diligently to undermine and corrupt almost the entire city and province of Hippo.
While he was staying there, the poison of this heresy spread rapidly, infecting many citizens and foreigners in the city with its harmful influence.
Meanwhile, Possidius mentions that both Catholic and Donatist Christians in Hippo, locals and visitors alike, approached Augustine, the presbyter, asking him to meet with Fortunatus, a Manichaean presbyter believed to be knowledgeable, to discuss the law with him.
During these events in Hippo, a major city in Africa, Arcadius Augustus and Rufinus, renowned figures, were serving their second consulship in the year 382 A.
D.
Augustine, the presbyter, willingly accepted the challenge to satisfy everyone's wishes, showing he was ready to discuss matters of faith when called upon.
Given this arrangement, the Manichaeans urged Fortunatus to debate Augustine, fearing for the safety of their shared beliefs.
Fortunatus, who had known Augustine in Carthage when he too was entangled in the Manichaean error, hesitated to face him.
Yet, pressured and embarrassed by his followers' insistence, he agreed to participate in the debate.
On the fifth day before the calends of July, at the baths of Sossius in Hippo, the debate between Augustine and Fortunatus began.
A large crowd gathered to listen, particularly learned and curious individuals supporting both sides, as is usually the case.
With the notaries' tablets ready, Augustine initiated the debate, focusing on the primary issue: the origin of evil.
In this discussion, Augustine, defending Catholic doctrine, explained that evil in humans stems from free will, while Fortunatus argued that the nature of evil was co-eternal with God.
However, on the last day of the debate, unable to maintain consistency in his arguments, Fortunatus admitted he had no response to Augustine's points.
However, when he didn't receive a response, he finally said he would consult with his superiors about the issues he couldn't refute.
If they didn't satisfy him, he promised to look after his own soul.
Possidius mentions this in a notable place, but we learn more from the words of the presbyter Fortunatus, spoken in front of everyone during the second day's debate.
These words, recorded by scribes, were also faithfully entered into the church records.
This can be seen at the end of the second day's debate, which is included with the first in volume eight of the Works of Saint Augustine.
Meanwhile, no one should assume that Fortunatus the Manichaean, overwhelmed by such shame and disgrace, decided to turn away from his errors or intended to join the Catholics later.
Indeed, any rational person, realizing their faith was shaken and led to ruin, would have come to such a decision immediately.
But Fortunatus, affected by this confusion, left the city of Hippo and never returned, nor did he become a Catholic.
Augustine does not mention Fortunatus the Manichaean presbyter, as far as I know.
There is only a certain letter written by him to another Manichaean presbyter, whom the Fathers of the Congregation of Saint Maur suspected in the latest edition of Augustine to have been named Felix.
When Augustine had already been appointed to the bishopric of Hippo, he addressed him with these words:
"Therefore, I warn you in the name of Christ. If you are ready, resolve the question in which your predecessor Fortunatus failed. He left here not to return unless he could find something to counter by disputing with his brothers after consulting with his own."
From this, it is clear that the Manichaean presbyter who succeeded Fortunatus was urged and provoked by Augustine to solve the same question in which his predecessor had failed even more shamefully.
He left the city of Hippo, eager to meet with other Manichaean leaders to discuss the accusations against him.
Fortunatus, a priest, was welcomed by Faustus, an African from the city of Milevis and a bishop of the Manichaean sect, who was prominent around the year 400.
William Cave, among others, described Faustus's talents, studies, mental abilities, and writings, saying:
He was pleasant in speech, clever-minded, more talkative than eloquent, and more of a dilettante than deeply learned.
He further adds:
Faustus wrote a volume against the true Christian faith and Catholic truth.
However, this praised writer did not accurately describe the book's content.
Augustine, who carefully examined Faustus's Manichaean work, explains its content in Book 2 of Retractations, chapter 7, as follows:
Against Faustus the Manichaean, who blasphemes the Law and the Prophets, their God, and the incarnation of Christ, claiming that the New Testament Scriptures proving him wrong are falsified, I wrote a large work, presenting his arguments and responding to them.
Augustine indeed knew this man, and in the sincere offering of his Confessions, where he discusses how he fell into the Manichaean sect, he said:
A certain Manichaean bishop named Faustus had already come to Carthage, a great snare of the devil, and many were entangled by his smooth speech.
.
For I had heard that he was exceedingly skilled in all honorable doctrines and thoroughly educated in the liberal disciplines.
The widespread fame of Faustus the Manichaean among his followers had long sparked in Augustine a desire to hear him teach and debate.
During those nine years when a wandering mind seemed drawn to this sect, the Holy Father found himself more of a listener than one of the chosen ones.
He encountered difficult questions and challenges that the other followers of this profane religion couldn't solve.
They eagerly awaited the arrival of Faustus, believing his presence and conversation would easily resolve these issues, and even any greater questions I might have had.
This was what the other Manichaeans promised Augustine when discussing matters of faith.
It was as if the mysteries of that infamous sect were known only to Bishop Faustus.
However, Augustine was ultimately deceived by the fame of that Manichaean group.
For when Faustus arrived, Augustine found a man pleasant and engaging in words, speaking the usual things but in a more charming way.
But what use is an agreeable server to my thirst for more precious drinks?
Augustine's ears were already accustomed to similar things, and they didn't seem better to him just because they were spoken better, nor true because they were eloquent, nor wise because the appearance was proper and the speech was decorous.
But when examining the deeds, knowledge, and understanding of divine and natural matters of Faustus, Augustine, through various interactions, assessed the extent to which this man, so highly esteemed by his followers, excelled.
He ultimately concluded:
After departing from the opinion of those who considered him wise and prudent because he delighted them with his speech, Augustine writes, "Through various interactions, I found the man to be unskilled in the liberal disciplines, except for grammar, and even that in the usual way, because he had read some of Cicero's speeches, very few of Seneca's books, some poets, and any volumes of his sect written in Latin and composed."
Through daily practice, eloquence developed, becoming more agreeable and enticing, guided by intellect and natural charm.
These qualities, admired by other Manichaeans in Bishop Faustus, neither soothed nor deceived Augustine's intellect.
When it became clear that Faustus lacked skill in the arts he claimed to excel in, Augustine began to doubt that Faustus could clarify the questions troubling him due to the Manichaeans' fanciful principles.
Augustine realized this especially when he looked at their books, filled with nonsense, wanting to fully understand their claims about the heavens, stars, and the sun and moon's movements and qualities.
Faustus, lacking education in mathematics, couldn't explain these things, which he freely admitted.
All of Augustine's efforts to progress in that sect stopped upon realizing this about Faustus, though he didn't completely separate from them, as he found nothing better to turn to.
As Augustine's misguided desire to learn all the Manichaean doctrines cooled, his mind began to waver, although he didn't immediately yield to divine grace.
Yet, the Lord's hand, in His hidden providence, did not abandon his soul and worked through the heartfelt prayers and tears of his mother, who offered sacrifices day and night for him.
Regarding Faustus's deeds, his study method, his knowledge of sciences, and his understanding of divine and human matters, Augustine wrote these accounts.
In examining these, we should not dwell too long, lest we seem to focus more on Augustine's deeds than those of the Manichaean bishop.
We believe it's important to add one final point: Augustine, after freeing himself from the snares of the Manichaeans and rising to the rank of bishop, took up the pen against Faustus and refuted him in thirty-three books.
He cleverly crafted this work by first presenting words under the name of Faustus and then providing Catholic responses to each chapter that he himself had written.
Regarding the fate of Faustus, Augustine recounts in Book Five, Chapter Eight, where the holy father fully exposes the audacity of the Manichaeans, who recklessly and sacrilegiously claimed they endured persecution and hostility for the sake of righteousness.
This happened when the proconsuls of Africa, enforcing strict penalties against this vile sect, found Faustus guilty, or he confessed to being a Manichaean, and along with several others brought before the proconsular court, he was exiled to an island.
We will discuss this type of judgment more fully and conveniently in the following chapter.
Now, we need to talk about a certain Secundinus, another defender and writer of the Manichaean sect, whom William Cave mistakenly thought to be of African descent.
He also claimed that this man lived after Augustine returned to the Church and completed the three books on free will, and that the letters between Secundinus and Augustine should be dated to the year three hundred and ninety AD.
These two assertions could only be made by someone speculating boldly and reasoning falsely about the writers of the Church out of mere caprice.
Firstly, concerning his origin, Secundinus was not from the African people but from the Roman populace, as his writings indicate.
For when discussing himself, he addressed Augustine as follows: "He indeed read some of my humble work and whatever talent of a Roman man the writings of your revered dignity contained, in which you are as angry with the truth as Hortensius was with philosophy."
Secundinus identifies himself as a Roman and references the writings where Augustine, who long ago converted to the Catholic faith, criticized the Manichaeans.
Once again, Augustine addresses Secundinus as a Roman, mocking the intelligence that Secundinus seemed so proud of.
He says, "I ask you, a sharp and clever man, with your Roman intelligence, as you boast, how does this good nature endure what it endures, and agree with evil?"
There's also confusion in William Cave's definition of when Secundinus attacked Augustine with his writings, or when Augustine, in response, refuted all his arguments.
According to Prosper, Possidius, and other contemporary writers, Augustine renounced Manichaeism and joined the Catholic community in 387.
If the exchange of letters between Secundinus and Augustine happened years after his return to the Church, as William Cave carelessly suggested, then these writings would have been published around 390.
However, this timeline falls apart if Secundinus, in his writings, mocked and attacked Augustine as if he had already become a bishop, and Augustine, responding to these slanders, didn't hide from Secundinus that he had indeed become a Catholic bishop.
Secundinus accuses Augustine of leaving the Manichaeans out of fear and a desire for honor, always using phrases in his writings typically reserved for bishops, like "your excellent holiness," "lord rightfully praiseworthy and cherished," or "I cannot do this for your most patient holiness," and "although saying this to your holiness is too absurd," along with other terms that were only used for bishops at that time.
What more is there to say?
Augustine himself, when meeting with Secundinus, states that he had already attained the honor of being a bishop.
He then questions, even if you thought I left the Manichaean heresy out of fear of some inconvenience from your group, or for the honor I received in the Catholic Church, why should I continue discussing this?
Augustine left a record of the timing of his works in two books titled Retractions.
In these, as he reflects on his life, he revisits the book we're discussing among those he worked on as a bishop.
Cave could have known this if he had checked Chapter 10 of Book II of Retractions, where Augustine clearly mentions this book against Secundinus, as we will see later.
Since Augustine, after becoming a priest, did not become a bishop until the year 304, their correspondence could not have occurred before then.
However, the congregation of St.
Maur of the Benedictines examined this more closely in the latest edition of Augustine's works.
Based on more probable conjectures, they concluded that the writings of Secundinus the Manichaean and Augustine the Catholic bishop should be dated to the year 404 or the following year, which is the tenth or eleventh year after Augustine became a bishop.
They noted: In the Retractions, the work on the Nature of Good follows closely, which is linked to the books written against Felix at the end of the year 404.
Therefore, this book against Secundinus relates to around the year 405.
Having pointed out Cave's errors regarding the homeland of Secundinus the Manichaean and the timing of the letter, we must address a third error, which is more significant.
He wrote about Secundinus saying: A great familiarity existed between him and Augustine while both were involved in the Manichaean heresy.
Anyone who reads Augustine cannot ignore Cave's mistake.
He honestly admitted that he had never seen this man, truly and without any hint of falsehood, even though both were once ensnared by the Manichaean beliefs in Rome.
In the second book of Retractations, chapter 10, Augustine writes:
"A certain Secundinus, not from those whom the Manichaeans call elect, but from those they call hearers, whom I did not even know by appearance, wrote to me as if a friend, respectfully reproving me for attacking that heresy in writing, advising me not to do so, and instead urging me to follow it with a defense of it and a reproach of the Catholic faith."
Would Caveus, if he had taken the time to investigate the deeds of Secundinus, his background, customs, and close associates from Augustine's perspective, have fallen into such an opinion? Would he have claimed there was a great familiarity between these two men, while each was involved in the Manichaean heresy, when Augustine asserts he had not even seen the man?
Meanwhile, let's set these matters aside and instead turn our attention to the exchange of letters between Augustine and Secundinus the Manichaean, focusing on the arguments within those letters. Initially, Secundinus, pretending to be a friend of Augustine, attacks, mocks, and criticizes him for leaving the Manichaean sect. He even calls upon the wrath and indignation of Mani the Persian to befall Augustine, especially on the day of judgment.
He accuses Augustine of two reasons for his defection: one being fear, suggesting Augustine feared the physical punishments unjustly imposed on the Manichaeans, or sometimes inflicted by public authorities; the other being a desire for honor, implying Augustine longed for the rank of bishop within the Catholic Church.
Augustine wanted to confront these slanders and crafted a significant work divided into more than twenty-six chapters. He aimed to refute the two main slanders that were cunningly and falsely charged against him.
First, he clarified that his departure from the Manichaean sect was driven solely by the words of the Apostle to Timothy, chapter four, verse one, which states:
"Now the Spirit clearly says that in later times some will abandon the faith, following deceitful spirits and teachings of demons."
This passage was widely believed by the ancients to refer to the Manichaeans.
Addressing the second reason for his departure, he again refers to the Apostle Paul in his letter to the Romans, citing:
"Glory, honor, and peace to everyone who does good,"
to clearly indicate that these blessings come not from an evil creator, as the Manichaeans thought, but from the highest and unchangeable good.
Augustine doesn't stop at refuting just these two accusations. He systematically addresses each argument raised by Secundinus from the Manichaean school, effectively dismantling, rejecting, and overturning all the opposing arguments.
In his disputes against the Donatists, Augustine mentioned two men with the same name: Secundinus of Cedia and Secundinus of Carpis. Since they are very different from Secundinus the Manichaean, it's important to clarify this to avoid any confusion.
It would be worthwhile to include the actions of Felix, a former Manichaean priest, who had at least two or three public debates with Augustine. This would greatly benefit the reader by consolidating the events involving the Manichaeans in Africa during Augustine's time, fulfilling the promise made at the beginning of this chapter.
However, since the debate about this Manichaean seemed to concern not just private individuals but the public cause of the Catholic Church, and because it occurred when priests and secular judges began taking action against the Manichaeans with various punishments, and since Felix, a priest, after discussions with Augustine, realized his mistake, renounced the heresy, and sought to clear his name by joining the Catholic communion, we will discuss him and other Manichaeans in Africa who were judged publicly as briefly as possible.
Chapter Four
The actions of Saints Leo the Great, Gelasius, Symmachus, and Hormisdas, Roman pontiffs, in destroying and burning the books of the Manichaeans are defended against Beausobre's critics.
The examples of ancient pagans also show that it was always considered a serious sin to allow the public to read such books, which might lead to even a slight deviation from ancestral teachings in religious matters.
While I understand that the actions of the Roman Church, which have consistently destroyed and burned the books and volumes of non-Catholic peoples, are not favored by some, I feel it necessary to discuss this topic, prompted by Beausobre's writings and arguments.
Beausobre has frequently mentioned the four Roman pontiffs who banned the reading of Manichaean books and made every effort to have them burned, spreading various complaints, claiming that these books, which contained knowledge of ancient philosophy and theology, have completely vanished, preventing an honest understanding of the doctrines and systems these heretics promoted.
He criticizes and attacks this approach as unjust, but he does so imprudently and foolishly.
For someone who claims to be as learned as he is, he should be deeply embarrassed to overlook what has been accepted at any time and in any religion.
Therefore, he should first recognize that religion was described by the ancients as a concept that involves the care and ceremony of a superior nature, which they referred to as divine.
Cicero himself acknowledged that those who oversee divine matters and manage civil affairs possess piety and holiness.
Given the excellence of their roles and the authority of their positions, it is their duty to necessarily ban and prevent anything that could undermine or destroy the worship of the divine.
For this reason, anything that was falsely devised by the opinions of the unskilled to harm and tarnish even some secular religion, and was gradually introduced anew into sacred matters, was rejected and abhorred by every nation.
They restrained those who dared to alter divine matters with various kinds of punishments, changing their ancestral laws.
Although we could provide countless examples from Titus Livius, the historian of Roman affairs, to stay within the scope of our discussion, we offer this one instance.
It shows that the Romans disapproved of introducing foreign and new religions, considering them harmful to themselves, their ancestors, and their gods.
Therefore, during the consulship of Quintus Fabius and Titus Sempronius, when Hannibal spent the summer in the Tarentine region and the war dragged on, even religious matters began to change, especially from an external perspective, making it seem as if either the people or the gods had suddenly transformed.
Roman rites were no longer secretly abolished within walls; instead, even in public, in the forum and on the Capitol, a crowd of women gathered, neither sacrificing nor praying to the gods in the traditional manner.
When the problem grew too severe for lesser magistrates to manage, the Senate assigned Marcus Atilius, the city's praetor, the task of freeing the people from these religions.
He proclaimed the Senate's decree in an assembly, announcing that anyone with books of prophecies or written prayers, or a written art of sacrificing, was to bring all those books and writings to him before the first of April.
No one was to sacrifice in public or sacred places according to a new or foreign rite.
However, Beausobre does not deny that this effort, inspired by sacred and divine counsel, was used by Roman pontiffs and other Christian pastors and emperors as a defense and protection of the Catholic religion.
However, without considering the actions and strategies of magistrates and ancient pagan leaders, he boldly criticized and found fault with a judgmental style against all those Catholic Popes who ordered the burning and destruction of Manichaean books.
He pointed this out not only in the first part of his History but explained it more clearly in the introductory speech of the second part.
He starts by stating that it's a very difficult, if not nearly impossible, task today to present a fair and complete understanding of the philosophy and theology related to the Manichaeans, as their written volumes no longer exist.
He then mentions that he does not know if Leo the Great was the first among the ancients to order the destruction and burning of Manichaean books.
However, he does know that Leo was imitated by his successor Gelasius, who ordered these books to be burned in front of the Church of Saint Mary.
This practice was shortly followed by Pope Symmachus.
Anastasius the Librarian tells us: "He burned all the images and books of the Manichaeans before the doors of the Constantinian Basilica."
Firstly, he argues that the Manichaean images could not have been burned.
This is because the magi, whose religion the Manichaeans followed, according to Epiphanius, did not have idols.
Additionally, the Manichaeans worshiped fire, the sun, and the moon, whose idols could not be burned.
Finally, he concludes that Pope Hormisdas followed the example of his predecessors regarding these heretics.
From what has been described here, nothing appears that would seriously offend the way Roman leaders acted.
We only find the weak argument where he claims that Pope Symmachus could not have burned the Manichaean images because they represented fire, the sun, and the moon, as if such images possessed the same power and nature as the things they represented.
For the substance of fire, like that of the sun and the moon, cannot be consumed by fire.
But who will deny that images of these made of wood, clay, or metal cannot be burned?
Following this, Beausobre's author aims to subtly shape the reader's thoughts.
Pretending to be somewhat uninformed, he occasionally debates whether the actions of ancient bishops deserve praise.
These actions inspired Christian emperors to decide that heretical books should be burned, and they imposed the death penalty on anyone who dared to read or keep such books.
He convinces himself that the purpose and intention of these laws were noble; however, he criticizes this precedent as extremely harmful and notes that even today, Christians condemn it as unjust and violent.
To support or bolster this minor and malicious speculation, which is followed by many superficial scholars today, he references the second apology of Justin Martyr.
In it, Justin bitterly complains about the Roman law enacted against those who consulted the Sibylline and Hystaspes books, which Christians used to validate their teachings.
But who doesn't understand that Saint Justin Martyr's complaint was entirely justified?
The Sibylline books were used among the pagans, and for addressing challenging issues, the Romans themselves turned to these books for guidance.
So, why did they trust these books in empire matters?
And in their hatred of the Christian religion, which these books at least vaguely predicted, did they become so enraged as to destroy them?
Justin believed these books could even assist the pagans themselves, helping them more readily accept the name of Christ.
Indeed, they had so much faith in them, as Titus Livius noted: "When, by decree of the Senate, no end to the irreparable disaster could be found, the Sibylline books were consulted."
Justin's complaint wasn't about the loss of sacred monuments suitable for confirming the Catholic faith.
Rather, it was because pagans deprived themselves of certain aids from which even a small light of our Christian faith could have been drawn.
Who could ever have claimed that the Sibylline books were necessary or suitable for strengthening Catholics in their faith?
Catholics were taught by the Scriptures of both the Old and New Testaments, listened to apostolic preaching, and were enlightened by constant miracles and signs.
Let's not forget the great care and concern of the pastors in instructing and strengthening the early Christians in their faith.
Therefore, they had no need to refer to the Sibylline books.
If Justin and other early Church Fathers referred to them to criticize pagans, it was likely based on a certain presumption.
They knew that these books were revered by the pagans' ancestors, priests, pontiffs, and officials.
Thus, Beausobre's argument, drawn from the complaints of Justin Martyr, completely falls apart, and we return to our main topic, from which we have slightly deviated.
What benefit or support could Catholics have derived from the Manichaean books to argue against the decrees of the Roman popes with any reason?
The Manichaeans falsely gave their books the most serious and sacred names to claim authority for their faith, such as Gospels, Mysteries, Revelations, Treasures, and similar names.
They presented these books as containing divine knowledge and labeled them as sacred and canonical under the names of the apostles, knowing well that they could not easily deceive simple, uneducated, and unsuspecting people unless they coated their poisonous teachings with a semblance of sweetness.
As Saint Leo the Great said, how could they more easily deceive the simple unless they coated the poisonous drinks with a kind of honey so that they wouldn't always feel unpleasant, even though they would be deadly?
Therefore, to prevent Catholics from absorbing these corrupt and impure doctrines to the detriment and ruin of the Christian faith, it was necessary to completely remove such writings and consign them to the flames.
Therefore, Bishop Turibius, the vigilant shepherd of the Church of Astorga, is instructed not only to forbid the reading of such writings, which are sources of many falsehoods, but to completely remove and burn them.
It must be ensured, as Leo the Great himself says, with particular priestly diligence, that corrupted books are not used for reading at all.
Apocryphal scriptures, which falsely claim the names of apostles and contain many seeds of falsehood, must not only be forbidden but also entirely removed and burned.
Who does not see that this decree of Leo the Great is fair and just?
Beausobre, along with his non-Catholic followers, who are overly devoted to philosophy and ancient studies, almost shamelessly denies this.
He states that he does not wish to criticize or praise this practice, so firmly established by many laws.
He adds that indeed some books are worthy of burning.
These are the ones that corrupt morals or completely undermine the foundations of religion and human society.
But for another kind of books, not so harmful, it would suffice to hide them from the people, rather than completely suppress them, since many wise people could benefit from them.
If, therefore, the books of the Manichaeans are as described, Beausobre concludes, I would assert that it was a great injustice for them to be burned, because the Catholic faith would have gained more by preserving those writings, despite their ridiculous and obscene tales.
This is how Beausobre reasons, adding some fabled sayings of the Manichaeans, which we have noted from the previous Acts of Archelaus.
Yet, he should be ashamed of having written these things.
What?
Do the books of the Manichaeans not subvert all the mysteries of our Catholic faith?
For which doctrines of our religion have they not attacked, and have they not also tried to overturn?
Let him review the Apostles' Creed and say if they left any article of our faith untouched.
But let us leave these matters aside.
It's well known and widely acknowledged that the Manicheans deny the existence of one God, reject the true incarnation, passion, death, and resurrection of our Lord Christ, desecrate the Eucharist and other sacraments, and spread sacrilegious tales about the coming of the Holy Spirit.
What more?
Didn't the Manicheans claim that the divinely inspired Scriptures were derived from an evil author?
Even when they accepted the New Testament, they argued it shouldn't remain whole and perfect, corrupting it with interpolations, additions, and other false alterations.
In short, there's nothing in the Catholic religion that the Manicheans haven't tried to undermine and completely overthrow.
Therefore, even according to the author Beausobre, those books that overturn the foundations of religion and human society deserve to be considered worthy of destruction by fire.
The actions of the Roman pontiffs can't be criticized or condemned since Manichean books accomplished both.
Besides the crimes committed against religion, they also dissolved and opposed marriages and unions, engaging in vile sins of lust that nature abhors.
Should such things contained in their books have been allowed by ministers under the name of apostolic scriptures?
Sacrilege be gone.
Lastly, as I went through Beausobre's arguments, I easily came to suspect that the author had no religion or only professed it outwardly.
If he had any semblance of piety inwardly, he would have recalled how much reverence those writings could earn for themselves.
Although falsely circulated under the name of respected forebears, they already have great authority and reputation.
Indeed, nothing more effective for dissolving religions can be found than these books, said Quintus Petillius to Lucius Petillius, when two chests were found in his field, one of which contained books attributed to Pythagoras under the name of Numa Pompilius.
It was a common belief that Numa was a listener of Pythagoras.
When these books, written in Latin and Greek, were created, the first seven covered pontifical law and the last seven dealt with the discipline of wisdom, as understood in that era.
However, they weren't intended to be preserved for academic study.
Instead, after reviewing the content, it was noted that many of the books seemed designed to undermine religion.
L.
Petillius himself stated that he would throw them into the fire.
Beausobre should not assume these books were burned on someone's personal authority.
First, the matter was reported to the praetor, who judged that the books should neither be read nor preserved.
Then it went to the senate, which decided they should be burned in the comitium as soon as possible.
Eventually, the books were publicly burned in the comitium by the victimarii, who were public servants.
I am not aware of anyone accusing or criticizing L.
Petillius, the praetor, or the Roman senate for unjustly consigning these books, which largely contained content capable of dissolving religions, to the fire.
What is clear to me is that in the public assembly of the Roman people, with the agreement of all orders and the applause of the entire populace, as the laws of the comitia required, these books were burned by the victimarii.
But I ask Beausobre: Were there individuals among the Romans at that time who were dedicated to pontifical law or philosophy?
Indeed, there were.
However, it seems no one of any standing complained about losing such books.
They believed that religion should not be weakened by new and foreign practices.
As Cicero says, the worship of the gods is the best, most chaste, most sacred, and fullest of devotion.
We should always venerate them with a pure, whole, and uncorrupted mind and voice.
But how can a pure mind and voice maintain the integrity of sacred institutions if they begin to stray and indulge in any superstitious or insolent practices?
In these situations, drawn from the ancient histories of non-Christians,
we needed to elaborate a bit more.
This was to ensure we didn't overlook Beausobre's harsh criticism of the ancient
customs of the Catholic Church and his malicious writing style against the deeds
of the popes of Rome, without a proper rebuttal.
Especially since even non-Catholic individuals of our time, seeing their books
banned by apostolic authority and publicly burned by officials,
complain loudly about what they see as an unjust and harmful policy.
Although it is used in the most holy and religious manner to protect the purity
and integrity of the Catholic faith.
Chapter Five
We're taking another look at the strictness of the imperial laws against the Manichaeans in Africa.
Felix, overwhelmed by fear and the authority of Saint Augustine's debates, eventually renounced his heresy in Hippo.
Various issues that arose in this case were resolved.
After the Manichaean beliefs were introduced in Africa, their errors began spreading rapidly.
In every community, many men and women found themselves shamefully caught up in it.
This caused significant insult, disgrace, and destruction to both the civil and Catholic state.
The customs and teachings of the Manichaeans first dissolved all marital rights, tainted the purity of children with shameful promiscuity, corrupted young women devoted to a sacred life, and indulged in heinous crimes, as if they were free from any divine or human laws, which was naturally abhorrent.
Once this secretive lifestyle of the Manichaeans came to the attention of the rulers, various laws were passed against them and their sacrilegious gatherings, subjecting them to many punishments.
Moreover, it is unsettling to think about what the elect of the Manichaeans were compelled to do sacrilegiously and superstitiously with any foods, and even with the holy sacrament of the Eucharist.
But the horror and shame we feel can be eased by the words of Augustine, which we share.
He explains, or rather out of necessity due to their despicable superstition, their elect were forced to consume something like the Eucharist mixed with human semen, believing that this, like other foods they consumed, would purify the divine substance.
Other impious and sacrilegious practices were also kept by the Manichaeans, which Augustine elsewhere condemns for greatly abusing our rites.
It became clear that, in great disgrace and contempt of our Catholic religion, followers of this sect were kneeling before the elect, asking them to lay hands on them-not only from their priests, bishops, or deacons, but from any of the elect.
This led to the first wrongful idea that laypeople could establish and ordain sacred ministers of the Church.
This error, long abolished, was revived after centuries by Calvin and other notorious authors, to the detriment of the entire ecclesiastical hierarchy.
Since the most wicked sect of the Manichean elect was accustomed to these and similar practices, the rulers of the age exerted all their efforts to completely eradicate these corrupt practices.
This is not known to us merely from one or two testimonies of Leo the Great.
It is also evident from the Theodosian Code itself, which describes many laws enacted by emperors for the destruction of the Manicheans, as we will note in a more suitable place.
Meanwhile, we need to consider the law that Emperors Diocletian and Maximian issued at the request of Julian, the proconsul of Africa, as Tillemont also recounts.
In the year of our Lord 290, after hearing Julian's complaints about a new sect from the borders of Persia causing disturbances within the cities of their kingdom and threatening the affairs of the Roman Empire, both emperors sought to address these growing problems.
They issued a law in March of the same year in Alexandria, stating that the people of this sect, along with their unspeakable writings, were to be burned by fire.
Furthermore, any nobles found corrupted by this stain were to be exiled and stripped of all their possessions.
The rest of the lower-status men were ultimately subjected to capital punishment.
Tillemont more plausibly considers that such a law was still in force in Africa during the age of Augustine, among others.
After carefully examining the situation with Felix in the Acts of Augustine, it was observed that this heretical man was intimidated by the bishop's authority, as he mentioned, and by the strictness of the laws that the emperors had established against this wicked sect.
Yet, Augustine aimed to challenge both of this man's evasions.
First, by demonstrating that the authority of the sacred bishops comes from God, he showed it doesn't instill fear in the guilty when discussions are peaceful, and that the people present during these discussions cause no force or fear at all.
Second, he explained how the strictness of imperial laws, arising from the power of the sword, can never hinder the truth of religion and sincere confession, but rather have always provided ornament, protection, and growth to the Catholic Church and its sacred teachings.
You also mentioned that the authority of the bishop frightens you: when you see how peacefully we act among ourselves, how calmly we discuss, and how the people present cause you no harm or fear, but listen with utmost calm, as befits Christians.
You also said that you fear the laws of the emperors: this is not something that someone filled with the Holy Spirit would fear for the sake of true faith.
To illustrate this, he offers the example of the Apostle Peter, who was crucified by the divine action of the Spirit for the Lord's faith.
However, Felix, driven by excessive zeal for argument, dared to respond to Augustine: "Even the apostles were afraid."
The holy Father, wanting to address this new evasion by Felix the Manichean, immediately explained with these words how the apostles feared tyrants.
"They feared," he said, "to be cautious, not because they would hesitate to proclaim their faith if captured."
And shortly after, he gently and without any ambiguity or insult reproached him for not fearing the emperor before, as he pretended, because he did not remain silent before: "For if you had feared the emperor, you would have been silent before."
Since yesterday, Felix was suspected of Manichaeism and appealed to the city official of Hippo.
He publicly declared, presenting a document, that he was ready to be burned along with his books according to Diocletian's law, if any evil was found in them.
Therefore, as if mocking him, Augustine closes his response: "Yesterday, you were demanding laws as if you were brave; today, you flee from the truth like a coward."
These public acts of Bishop Augustine with Felix the Manichaean highlight the severity of imperial laws, which in Africa targeted people of this sect, as those professing such heresies were handed over to be burned with their books.
Furthermore, it is evident that the authority of bishops was not only in condemning those infected with that stain to renounce their errors but also in completely eradicating from their dioceses any novelties that opposed the Catholic religion.
This ecclesiastical authority of bishops shone brightly in this case of Felix.
In the year 404, on December 6th, when Honorius was consul for the sixth time, Felix recklessly and openly claimed in the city of Hippo that he could defend the writings of Mani and assert that they held the truth.
Due to this reason, as we have seen, he was rightfully summoned as an accused of execrable blasphemy by the city official and by Bishop Augustine.
He was forced to face a public inquiry.
Felix did not reside in Hippo but had come there to spread Manichaean errors.
Being one of their more learned members, though uneducated in liberal letters, but more cunning than Fortunatus, he hoped to spread the errors more widely and confidently.
Possidius adds that he was among those they call "the elect," who, besides defending wicked doctrines, were also devoted to the most impure debauchery and obscenities.
This meeting, therefore, began the following day, on December 7th, in the presence of the people, in the church.
This meeting, described as a church proceeding or church judgment, was documented in writing by notaries and is mentioned by Augustine.
It started with a debate based on a letter from the Manichaean, which they refer to as the foundation.
However, the meeting and the episcopal Acts did not wrap up on the same day.
When Felix was confronted with the truth and significantly challenged by Augustine's arguments, he asked for more time to respond.
Augustine, graciously and politely, agreed to Felix's request, as was appropriate for a bishop of the Catholic Church.
He extended the discussion over five days, concluding on December 12, the day before the Ides of December.
Although Augustine wanted to treat Felix with compassion and granted him this extension, he remained concerned that Felix might consider fleeing to avoid the consequences meant for those guilty of such crimes.
Therefore, before bringing the meeting to its previous conclusion, Augustine exercised great caution.
Specifically, he questioned Felix to see if he was contemplating escape.
When Felix denied this repeatedly, he was asked to renounce the Manichaean and place himself under the custody of a certain individual.
In all these matters, once Felix publicly kept his word and the records of the initial discussion were signed by Felix, Augustine, and a certain Boniface under whose custody Felix placed himself, the earlier Acts were completed with great honor for Catholic truth.
What transpired after the five days is clearly shown in the Acts of the second day with Felix the Manichaean.
Indeed, when they gathered with a large crowd and notaries in the Church of Peace on the twelfth day of the same month, Augustine began a new discussion based on the matters or teachings with which the previous meeting had concluded.
Augustine once questioned, if God could not be harmed in any way, why would He wage war against the race known as the darkness?
In this conflict, would He mix the nature of demons with His own essence, which is identical to Himself, as has been previously acknowledged?
Indeed, Bishop Felix approached him with this very question.
When faced with this fictional tale, the heretic, using cunning and evasion, claimed that he was unprepared.
He didn't have the scripture at hand during his leisure because they hadn't been returned to him for study.
He argued that no one enters a contest without being armed, and no litigator can present a case without their documents.
Similarly, he couldn't respond without his scripture.
Thus, Felix tried to avoid this new threat.
But Augustine was well aware of the man's evasive tactics.
So, addressing him with a serious and authoritative tone, Augustine sharply criticized him for attempting to conceal his sacrilegious errors with such excuses.
He accused him of a new offense for not seeking the books, which were kept under public seal, despite requesting five days to respond.
Therefore, Felix did not receive the extra two days he wanted.
Instead, he was only given the books.
Once he had them, the bishop pressed him so firmly and with such strong reasoning that, with all the Manichean stories, errors, and impieties stripped away, he was ultimately defeated by the truth of the arguments.
To the great applause of the Catholics, he renounced Manichaeism and its teachings in front of a large assembly.
Meanwhile, to show everyone that he was sincerely and wholeheartedly renouncing Manichaeism and its errors, he asked Bishop Augustine for a written formula of anathemas.
He especially requested that Augustine first pronounce the anathema against Manichaeism and the spirit that spoke within him to strengthen his resolve.
He finally accomplished this.
When Augustine received the letter, he denounced it with an anathema.
Felix did the same, writing in his own hand: "I, Felix, who once believed in Manichaeism, now condemn him and his teachings."
You can find more similar details in the conclusion of Augustine's second book.
However, we believe that those who have read the Life of Augustine, thoughtfully written by the Fathers of the congregation of Saint Maur, might say that recounting all these details was unnecessary.
In the fifth book, chapter twelve, they have already provided a more comprehensive description of Augustine's debates with Felix.
So, are we not allowed to revisit these matters, to reference the laws passed by pagan emperors against the Manichaeans, as Felix had, and to show how he feared the strictness and penalties from both powers?
Indeed, the editors of the Works of Saint Augustine, who are very learned, might have omitted these details, possibly arguing it was beyond their scope, as they only intended to narrate the events concerning Augustine's interactions with Felix.
Our goal in writing the history of the Manichaeans was to compile the noted crimes of that sect from one hundred thirty-four serious and credible sources into a single narrative, keeping the chronological order as much as possible. Therefore, we included these details, adding annotations where others, focused on different tasks, either omitted or should have omitted them.
Meanwhile, to ensure we don't overlook important details, we acknowledge there were not two, but three meetings between Augustine and Felix.
Possidius hinted at this, albeit obscurely, in the Life of Augustine.
But it becomes clearer from Augustine's own words.
In the record of the first day's meeting, documented by notaries, he referenced a prior meeting by addressing Felix the Manichaean: "He knows he spoke yesterday."
Felix himself, when faced with questions from the Augustinians, promises that he is ready to prove his blasphemous and sacrilegious claims if he's provided with the Manichaean scriptures.
"The five authors I mentioned to you," he says, "whatever you ask of me, I will prove to you."
His words should indeed relate to those books he requested in the last meeting, which were kept under public seal.
However, these books had already been secured under seal before any public and formal meetings were recorded by notaries.
Considering all these factors, I easily conclude that the holy bishop had only two meetings or disputes at the church gates in front of the people; but these were preceded by another meeting with the imperial official, when Felix, submitting to the penalties of imperial laws, finally handed over the apocryphal books to be kept under public seal.
This conclusion is reasonable for anyone who diligently studies both Possidius's testimony and the Acts of these disputes without delay.
This brings us to another question, which seems to concern Felix's status as a Manichaean within the church.
This inquiry was sparked by Augustine's letter seventy-nine, which the holy bishop addressed to the Manichaean presbyter Fortunatus, who succeeded Felix.
From this letter, editors of Augustine's works began to suspect that this presbyter was the same Felix we've been discussing.
But is this suspicion, based on whatever reasons or conjectures, significant enough that we shouldn't dismiss it as entirely baseless?
On what grounds do we base this suspicion?
As someone without partisan bias, if I sincerely share my thoughts, I would judge that the Manichaean presbyter whom Augustine addressed was different from Felix.
But to clarify the basis of this opinion, I will explain briefly.
I'll reach out to the latest editors of Augustine to see if letter 79 mentions the discussions between Augustine and Felix, or if it was written before those talks.
However, it can't be considered to have been written after those discussions.
By that time, Felix had already sincerely converted, openly confessed the Catholic faith, and renounced Manichaean beliefs.
We can't assume he reverted to his previous errors without substantial evidence.
Therefore, the editors are likely confident that the well-regarded letter 79 came before the two discussions recorded in writing.
It seems they hinted at this when they noted in the margin of the editors' copies: "Written probably in the year 404."
While we might question placing Augustine's public meetings with the Manichaean Felix in that year based on some authentic consul notes, since these meetings happened in the same year, specifically on December 12, no reasonable person could argue that letter 79 was written later.
In considering this, I compared the topics of the letter with what is described in the discussions carefully; I found they didn't align with each other. The Manichaean priest, whom the respected editors suspect might be Felix, had raised a question with some of Augustine's brothers about not avoiding visible death, arguing it's not just the separation of mind from body but also the detachment of good from evil.
Since the priest claimed this from Manichaean doctrine, Augustine attempted to critique him while also inviting him to public discussions to resolve the issue, which his predecessor Fortunatus had not managed to do. Yet, the sequence of the Acts shows there are different arguments in those discussions.
Moreover, Augustine does not mention in his books of Retractions or in the Acts of the discussions that this letter was addressed to Felix; and Possidius also remains silent about this in the Life of Augustine.
I must admit, I'm completely in the dark about which assumptions to rely on to avoid hastily suspecting that the letter we're discussing might have been addressed by Augustine to the presbyter Felix the Manichaean.
However, others might judge this more accurately and easily, as we now plan to focus on describing other more certain matters, instead of making further decisions to avoid the difficulties that the latest editors of Augustine's works seem to have encountered.
Chapter Six
On the Judgment of the Church of Carthage in Cases Involving the Manichaeans.
The Dedication of Catholic Bishops and the Approach of Church Discipline in Receiving Those Who Repent.
Among the many heresies affecting Africa in the fifth century, Manichaeism was particularly prominent.
This was partly because it predated other sects like the Arian, Priscillian, Pelagian, and Donatist, having arrived from Persia or Armenia around the year 290.
For a long time, it remained hidden from Catholic leaders, occasionally taking root in different places.
Its appeal was also due to its division into two groups: the hearers and the elect, which attracted different kinds of people.
Some were drawn in by ignorance of divine mysteries, while others were enticed by a desire for shameful lusts.
Saint Augustine was relentless in addressing both groups after their conversion, using conversations, debates, and writings to challenge them.
He was even more forceful in refuting and uprooting the Manichaeans when some were discovered in Carthage,
leading to action against them by public and ecclesiastical authorities.
According to Prosper's Chronicle, Ursus, the prefect of Emperor Constantius's household, who also held the rank of tribune and managed civil affairs in Africa,
was committed to the Catholic faith and defended it vigorously.
He captured some Manichaeans, known as the elect and the elect women.
Rufus, the tribune and defender of the laws, ordered them to be brought before the Church's tribunal.
In front of the bishops and the people, a formal questioning was arranged.
They were first asked about their misdeeds and doctrines, and after confessing all their crimes as required by law, actions were taken against them.
To hear these confessions, not only were there scribes documenting the Acts, but also bishops serving as judges to ensure the investigation followed both human and ecclesiastical laws.
We are unaware of most of the bishops' names, except for one, Aurelius, who was praised as the head of the Church of Carthage at that time.
It's likely that bishops from the entire province were gathered.
Augustine was also present and perhaps more than others became aware of the doctrines and crimes of this abominable sect.
It's very difficult to determine what was revealed during these Carthaginian episcopal proceedings and how many others the tribune Rufus had captured and ordered to be brought before the ecclesiastical judges.
Due to the passage of time, records of these Acts taken by scribes have been lost, and Augustine and Prosper only briefly mentioned certain corrupted women, leaving out the rest of the events.
Augustine specifically mentioned two women in this group.
One was named Margarita, who exposed a disgraceful act; she claimed that, although she was not yet twelve years old, she was corrupted because of this wicked mystery.
Another woman, Eusebia, a Manichaean who was considered a nun, was forced to confess to suffering the same vile disgrace.
Initially, she falsely claimed to retain her virginity and requested an examination by a midwife.
After being examined and found out, she similarly revealed the vile act where flour was spread to catch and mix the semen of those lying together.
This was something Margarita had revealed, though she was not present to hear it herself.
So, Margarita's confession exposed in the Church at Carthage the most disgraceful sexual practices of the Manichaeans, among which the deflowering of virgins was the least serious.
Eusebia, forced to confront her own disgrace and shame, also revealed other detestable crimes of her sect.
One particularly notable crime involved the abuse of women and even wives, where they sought only physical pleasure while deliberately avoiding conception and the birth of children.
This was done to prevent the divine substance, which they claimed entered them through food, from being trapped in the flesh of offspring.
These are the main points that can be shared about the investigation in Carthage concerning the elect men and women of the Manichaeans in our discussion.
It's nearly impossible to describe every detail linked to the confessions of the guilty and the summary of episcopal records without making assumptions.
It's also challenging to express the intense horror felt by the people of Carthage, which all who witnessed this ecclesiastical investigation must have anticipated against such a deadly sect.
From this, we can conclude that all Catholics called for the destruction of the Manichaeans, and anyone would have eagerly taken an oath to immediately report any known member of the Manichaean sect to the ecclesiastical judges without hesitation or delay.
Although the records of the Carthaginian notaries have been lost, we have evidence from one or two of Augustine's letters.
The first letter was written to Quodvultdeus, then a deacon of the Church of Carthage.
He had asked Augustine to write a book about heresies.
In his response, Augustine explained the difficulty of this work, which had already been attempted and completed by Philastrius, the Bishop of Brescia, and Epiphanius of Cyprus.
He then offered his opinion on both writers' works, stating that Epiphanius's work was preferable to Philastrius's book.
Before ending the letter, he asked not to be burdened with writing back to him, explaining how a certain Theodosius, who had betrayed some Manichaeans, remained in the Catholic faith.
And those believed to have been betrayed by him were corrected.
Augustine clearly states that the Manichaeans were exposed by Theodosius.
However, whether Augustine himself was influenced by Manichaean beliefs remains uncertain.
It seems likely, and Augustine's words hint at this, but I wouldn't define it with certainty.
This letter from Augustine should be dated to the year 428, when he dedicated the book about heresies to a deacon from Carthage.
At that time, some Manichaeans were discovered again in the same church, as indicated by the episcopal records sent to Augustine by Quodvultdeus.
Under careful questioning, these Manichaeans admitted that this was not a sacrament but an ex-sacrament, with one of them named Viator.
The occasion of these episcopal records revealed to Catholic bishops a schism among the Manichaeans.
Indeed, they were divided into various factions: some were called Catharists or purifiers, others were known as Mattarians, who slept on mats, and some were simply called Manichaeans.
This schism was also confirmed by the records from Carthage.
It's clear Augustine had known about this for a long time, as seen in his writings against Faustus in Book Five, Chapter Five.
This should be discussed at another time, as we will explain shortly.
The Manichaeans boasted arrogantly about their perfection in following Christian commandments, claiming they alone practiced what the Gospel commanded.
However, there was such a significant difference in their morals and lifestyle that they didn't agree on adhering to Manichaean laws.
Some particularly bragged about Christian poverty, which others completely scorned.
Augustine, who refuted their lies and pretenses, specifically criticized Faustus for teaching that money should not be carried in belts.
He pointed out the hypocrisy of the Manichaeans, who professed one thing but lived differently.
While they didn't carry money in belts, they were eager to hoard gold in small boxes and purses.
For that reason, he turns to Constantius, a Roman citizen who was once influenced by the Manichaean beliefs.
After leaving those beliefs behind, he converted to Christianity.
Constantius is called upon as a reliable witness because he once eagerly invited and gathered many Manichaeans into his home in Rome to follow Mani's teachings.
Although these teachings were quite empty and foolish, they were highly valued by his followers.
However, when the strictness of these laws became too much for them, they scattered, each going their separate way.
So, whenever someone claimed they could break Manichaean laws, a division arose among them.
As mentioned earlier, because some slept on mats, they were called Mattarians, whose simple bedding was very different from the luxurious featherbeds and goat hair blankets of Faustus.
This luxury not only led them to look down on the Mattarians but also on their own humble origins, like the home of their father, a poor man from Milevis.
Augustine humorously mocks Faustus and describes this division among the Manichaeans, which was one of the main reasons he rejected this heresy.
He details this in his book On the Morals of the Manichaeans, where he recounts the story of Constantius, a Manichaean auditor, which became so well-known that it spread far and wide.
Augustine, who first learned about the situation from a trusted friend, later confirmed it when he arrived in Rome around 383 AD.
He tells how Constantius, troubled by the differences in behavior among the Manichaeans, tried to make those in his house live according to a rule proposed in a letter by Mani.
Many found it unbearable and left, but some stayed out of shame.
He started living in a way that was both pleasing and as authority demanded.
Meanwhile, Constantius, always attentive, urged everyone to take action, yet he never asked anyone to do something he hadn't done himself first.
Frequent quarrels arose among the chosen ones, with accusations of wrongdoing flying around.
He listened to all of this with a sigh, trying to make them unknowingly reveal the truth in their arguments.
They ended up exposing unspeakable and monstrous deeds.
After a few comments, Augustine adds: What more can be said?
Eventually, they had to admit that those commands couldn't be maintained, leading to unrest.
In the meantime, don't think that this discussion is longer than necessary.
Also, don't criticize our writing style, as we've chosen to mix the events in Africa against the Manichaeans with older occurrences in Rome.
Indeed, as we briefly move away from the episcopal matters in Carthage, two main reasons have prompted us to do so.
One is the schism increasingly apparent in the Manichaean confessions recorded by notaries.
Since a similar issue in Rome occurred earlier, we thought it appropriate to highlight this for our readers' benefit.
The other is the opinion of some once-prominent figures, who, by dismissing all ecclesiastical history monuments, argue that the Manichaeans only arrived in Rome in the year 427.
If their opinion were to hold, it would not only shake the credibility of Augustinian writers but also undermine the decrees and constitutions of several Roman pontiffs, from which African Church leaders derived their rules for action against the Manichaeans.
The main advocate of this opinion was Quesnellus, as we will demonstrate in the following chapters.
Returning to that law of ecclesiastical discipline, from which we have digressed a bit, another letter from Saint Augustine clearly shows how strictly it was upheld, without any leniency from the bishops.
He discovered that a certain Victorinus from Malliana, who held the clerical rank of subdeacon, was tainted by the Manichaean heresy.
Driven by zeal for the Catholic faith, Augustine immediately wrote to Deuterius, the bishop of the same province, urging caution regarding this cleric.
This was to prevent the enemy, who had begun to lay in wait for the Lord's flock, from destroying Christian souls that had been redeemed at a high price through negligence or indifference.
Thus, Augustine summoned Victorinus to trial; and before being convicted by the witnesses who accused him, Victorinus could not deny his breached faith when questioned.
As a result, he admitted he was a follower of the Manichaeans, though not an elected member.
Augustine relayed the essence of this confession to Bishop Deuterius, so that by examining the enormous and sacrilegious crimes, he might understand the corrupt customs and impious doctrines of this sect.
Afterward, Augustine wanted to suggest or remind him of the ecclesiastical discipline rules to follow when receiving Manichaean penitents.
After thoroughly considering these rules and observing Victorinus's past behavior, Augustine strongly suspected that Victorinus would not adhere to them.
To avoid acting on mere suspicion, he highlighted Victorinus's past behavior, exposing the deception he used to conceal his Manichaean beliefs while pretending to profess the Catholic faith and maintain the appearance of a sacred ecclesiastical subdeacon.
Troubled by this serious concern, Augustine decided that even after renouncing his errors, Victorinus should not be received as a penitent in the Church.
Upholding the full rigor of ecclesiastical discipline, he ensured that Victorinus was expelled from the city and diocese of Hippo.
However, he instructs Bishop Deuterio to impose an even stricter ecclesiastical penalty on Victorinus.
Through his letters, he directs Deuterio to demote Victorinus from the clergy with appropriate severity, stripping him of all honor and communion, making it widely known.
He completely forbids granting him a chance for repentance unless Victorinus reveals others he knows, not just in Malliana but throughout the entire province.
Additionally, we've extracted the core of these matters from Augustine's letter number two hundred thirty-six, previously numbered seventy-four, to illustrate the Church's discipline against the Manichaeans.
The exact year when the holy doctor wrote this remains unknown to the latest editors of Augustine's Works, who categorized it among letters whose dates are less certain.
In the preface to the two books concerning the Acts with Felix the Manichaean, the editors present an ancient fragment of Feliciana's profession, both from Baronius and the Gervasian code.
From this, we understand that those coming to the Church from this heresy were never accepted unless they first betrayed others of the same sect, reporting them to their bishops or church leaders.
The Manichaeans, admitted as penitents, were not only required to reveal names of sect members within the same diocese after the sacrament of reconciliation but also to disclose others scattered throughout the entire province or nearby areas.
This is clearly evident from the confession of Felix, a former follower of Manichaeism, whom we mentioned earlier.
Specifically, Felix, having converted from Manichaeism, stated under oath to God that he confessed everything truthfully.
He admitted what he knew about the Manichaeans in the Caesarean area, including Mary and Lampadia, the wife of Mercury the silversmith, with whom we also prayed for the chosen Eucharistus, Caesaria, and her daughter Lucilla, Candida, who resides in Tipasa, Victorina of Spain, Simplicianus, the father of Antonius, Paul and his sister, who are in Hippo, whom I also knew to be Manichaeans through Mary and Lampadia.
From this confession of Felix, the former Manichaean who returned to the Catholic faith, the ancient discipline of the Church becomes clear.
It ensured that they would never be admitted to the sacrament of reconciliation unless, under the testimony of the almighty God, they revealed all those they knew to be tainted by that heresy.
If a penitent failed to report someone known to them to the ecclesiastical judges deceitfully, they would be deemed unworthy of the praised reconciliation.
Therefore, Felix concluded his confession with these words: "I only know that if it is found that I know anything beyond what I have said, I myself confess to being guilty of it."
However, from this preceding confession of Felix, the full and complete understanding of that ancient discipline is not yet fully revealed.
Indeed, since many among the Manichaeans had never been reborn through the sacred washing of baptism and lived always in the manner of pagans, while others, fleeing from the Catholic community, had taken the name of Manes, the approach of the bishops could not be the same in receiving both groups.
Each individual who repented had to create a confession and penance document.
In this document, they first had to denounce Manes and then earnestly request to become either a catechumen or a penitent.
Bishops would review these documents to ensure they followed ecclesiastical rules.
If they did not comply, a letter of reconciliation was withheld unless it included the date and consul, ensuring protection from any past issues, whether from public laws or church discipline.
If someone, after receiving ecclesiastical testimony and a document, still showed signs of being a Manichaean, they were subjected to the full extent of justice according to civil and ecclesiastical laws.
They were then instructed to be completely avoided by Catholic men, in line with the apostolic command of Saint Paul.
Those who had letters from the bishops were recommended to religious Catholic neighbors or roommates, whether clergy or laypeople, who would help them regularly attend the hearing of the Word of God and become known through their testimony.
This is highlighted in a reminder to the Catholic Church, often attributed to Augustine, which the latest editors of Augustine's Works have included in the appendix of the eighth volume.
From this reminder, we gather that these converted Manichaeans were not immediately admitted to baptism or the sacrament of reconciliation.
They had to remain either as catechumens or penitents until the threat of death, or at least stay in one status or the other as long as deemed fair by the bishops.
This decision was based on the strength of their faith and the testimony of those who vouched for them, allowing these penalties to be eased by indulgence.
Finally, the letter of testimony or document given to the penitent Manichaeans varied in form.
Since the chosen ones were more harmful than the listeners, they faced harsher penalties.
So, first of all, listeners, after confessing and denouncing their blasphemies and the most impious and unclean heresy, they easily obtained commendatory letters from bishops against those who tried to accuse them of the past error of Manes.
However, such testimony was not easily granted for the chosen ones.
Instead, they were first secluded with God's servants, whether clergy or laypeople, in monasteries or guest houses, until all suspicion of the previous heresy was completely purged.
Finally, they were deemed worthy to receive either baptism or reconciliation.
Now, we need to pause briefly to preemptively take away arguments from the enemies of the apostolic see, especially those they might claim from our previous discourse.
Indeed, since their aim is to undermine the rights and authority of the Roman pontiffs in eradicating heresies and establishing ecclesiastical discipline, they might flatter themselves that the church laws described thus far were derived either from Augustine or other bishops of Africa.
For this reason, they claim to have gained such strength that the Roman Church, following their actions, later adopted these laws and wished to adhere strictly to them in judging the Manichaeans.
Thus, they might indeed babble, who not only published that volume as the genuine code of Roman Church canons, compiled from the statutes of other churches and the letters of bishops, but also, when discussing the affairs of the Eutychians, assert that Leo of Rome undertook no other parts than those which Athanasius once undertook with the Arians, Augustine with the Pelagians, and Cyril with the Nestorians.
Moreover, speaking again about the Pelagians, they falsely claim that the decrees of Innocent, Zosimus, Boniface, and Celestine gained strength only from the African councils themselves.
To all these, and similar trifles and lies, we wished to respond in these historical writings of ours to counter these slanders against the apostolic see, and to immediately remove what they might object.
When it comes to church discipline, we can't credit that law to Augustine or any African bishop.
This law was actually set and defined by the apostolic see of Saint Peter before Augustine became a Catholic and before African bishops dealt with the Manichaeans.
Pope Siricius documented this law, drawing from the traditions of the apostolic Roman see, right at the start of his pontificate, during a time when Augustine was still involved with the Manichaean errors.
In fact, at that time, the African leaders hadn't even started to impose ecclesiastical penalties on the Manichaeans yet; we know this first took place in Carthage when Augustine was already the bishop of Hippo.
So, it couldn't have come from Augustine or any other African bishop's church discipline, since Augustine and the other African bishops followed the decrees long established by the apostolic see of Saint Peter to eliminate that sect.
Now, it's worth mentioning the decrees of Pope Siricius, which were later respected not just by the African bishops in their dealings with the Manichaeans, but also by all the Churches worldwide with deep devotion.
However, this isn't something we can delve into now, as the upcoming chapters will involve various discussions with Paschasius Quesnel, where we'll describe the actions of many Roman pontiffs against the Manichaean threat.
Meanwhile, to ensure we give due recognition to the brightest figures in doctrine and holiness, we must acknowledge the significant efforts of Augustine and the African bishops who fought vigorously against the Manichaeans, ultimately defeating and abolishing that notorious sect.
Above all, Augustine deserves every honor and praise.
From the day of his conversion, he focused solely on exposing the hidden and wicked mysteries of the Manichaeans.
He aimed to dismantle the false teachings of this sect, highlighting their shameless writings, mocking and cursing the hypocrisy of the elect, and attacking the profane rites and sacraments they practiced.
Moreover, he challenged the more learned individuals, whom other Manichaeans regarded as their teachers, to public debates.
After uncovering the falsehoods of Manichaean doctrine, he worked tirelessly to make the holiness of the Catholic faith known to all.
Indeed, these are the actions that Saint Augustine, the holy teacher, undertook with great zeal for the good, honor, and benefit of the Catholic Church.
His glorious works are celebrated not only in many learned writings, especially those against them, but also in all his other works against the Donatists, Pelagians, and Arians.
In these writings, he frequently attempted to refute one Manichaean error or another.
With such a wealth of Augustine's books, Africa, in particular, and the Catholic Church were enriched, especially at that time when heresies were spreading over that land like the serpents of the Egyptian magicians.
The remaining African bishops, guided by the rules of the Apostolic Roman Church and supported by civil laws, were fully able to crush and eradicate the Manichaeans.
We assume that the holy teacher intended to convey this when he addressed the catechumens during a barbaric time, speaking to them in this way, "The poison of the Manichaeans had crept in, it has been crushed, it has been eradicated."
However, it was not eradicated in such a way that the Manichaeans, affected by exile, left the kingdom of Africa in Augustine's time to migrate elsewhere, nor because they had been led to repentance, leaving that kingdom purified from all Manichaean stain. Not so, I say.
The viperous offspring, fearful of civil and ecclesiastical punishments, was used to finding hiding places for itself and never completely left Africa, even though the Vandals later devastated the kingdom.
Augustine aimed to show that the poison of the Manichaeans had been crushed and consumed by curses and proscriptions.
Their diabolical snares were completely shattered and broken by the efforts and writings of the Catholics, so that neither the unlearned nor the more educated could be caught by such traps anymore.
The matters we've described relate to Augustine's time.
If anything else about the same heresy raging in Africa comes to our attention and needs addressing, we will do our best to maintain the timeline and indicate this historical exploration accordingly.
Chapter Seven
Defending Saint Leo the Great's Response to Beausobre's Insults and Slanders Regarding His Approach to the Manicheans.
We'll explain how the Holy Pope not only preached in sermons but also exposed their errors.
Similarly, we'll demonstrate that Saint Augustine's writings against the Manicheans, contrary to Beausobre's claims, contain neither fables nor sophisms.
Here, we'll address several questions that, once clarified, not only illuminate our previous statements but also dismantle the arguments Beausobre unfairly raised against Saints Leo the Great and Augustine, the valiant opponents of the Manicheans.
First, it should be noted how that unfortunate sect of the Manicheans, after the Vandal occupation of proconsular Africa where it had spread widely, was forced into exile.
Some of its followers came to Rome, while others sought refuge in different places or cities.
Those who came to Rome hoped to receive comfort and support from their brethren so they could live more safely.
But this hope soon failed them.
Saint Leo the Great, being informed of their arrival and residence, spared no effort to cleanse his Church of this pestilence.
However, Beausobre claims that he adopted a method against them that led more to anger and despair than to repentance and renunciation of their crimes.
Beausobre adds that Saint Leo contended they were convicted of abominable ceremonies, about which he later warned the bishops of Italy through encyclical letters.
This approach resulted in two harmful effects.
The first was to arouse horror among the people and the populace against the Manicheans and prompt the authorities to impose the penalties already established by law.
A more damaging effect was the growing fear of the Catholic Church among the Manichaeans, as they witnessed the bishops becoming increasingly hostile towards them.
They were subjected to slanders and severe persecutions, despite not being guilty of the crimes they were accused of.
Amidst these insults and slanders, Beausobre pressured Saint Leo the Pope to be more lenient with the Manichaeans and to clear them of serious accusations.
Can we then tolerate such audacity in writing or reasoning, especially when the author claims throughout his work that he is unbiased and only seeks to present the truth in the history of the Manichaeans?
However, the following points will clearly demonstrate that our writer has been dishonest in these matters.
First, how does he conclude that the Manichaeans arrived in Rome after proconsular Africa was devastated by the Vandals?
The followers of this notorious sect had already sought refuge in Rome long before, during the time of Saint Siricius the Pope.
Those who persistently and boldly defended their errors were ordered into exile; however, those who repented were allowed to partake in the sacrament of reconciliation, provided they spent the rest of their lives in monasteries.
Thus, the approach of the Roman Popes towards the Manichaeans did not start with the great Leo.
They were not discovered in Rome only after the Vandal devastation of proconsular Africa, as Beausobre carelessly claimed, nor was the path to repentance closed to them, driving them to anger and despair.
They could choose between the strictness of sacred laws on one side or ecclesiastical peace and gentleness on the other, depending on where their spirit was more inclined.
So, we shouldn't judge Saint Leo the Great too harshly for his actions towards the Manichaeans.
It's not like he disregarded the decrees of previous popes, such as Siricius and Anastasius, by not seeking the conversion of the Manichaeans or refusing to reconcile with the penitents.
If public hatred arose against these individuals after their horrendous crimes were revealed, prompting harsh actions from the authorities, this shouldn't be blamed on Leo.
In fact, his efforts deserve praise for striving to cleanse the Roman Church, which was under his care, of such wickedness.
Furthermore, if the Manichaeans developed a strong aversion to bishops and Catholics, this is typical of criminals: they fear judges and detest the punishments they deserve.
However, this doesn't mean the bishops were their slanderers or persecutors.
They merely exposed the Manichaean crimes in court, proven through formal investigations and their own confessions, whether spoken or written.
We clearly show that Leo maintained this stance in public sermons and in letters he sent to all the bishops of Italy, advising them to protect themselves and their congregations from the Manichaeans' doctrines-who had recently been expelled from Rome.
By discussing Leo's investigation into the Manichaeans, the reader will have enough evidence to refute Beausobre's slanders and insults against Saint Leo the Great.
Moreover, Beausobre didn't stop at criticizing Saint Leo the Great's approach to the Manichaeans.
He went on to claim that Leo's letters and sermons don't describe Manichaean doctrine at all.
Instead, he argues that these writings are filled with attacks against the Priscillianists and Manichaeans, as he tries to confuse these two distinct sects and subject them to the same punishments.
Leo is praised for his zeal, but a bit more moderation would have been preferable.
He was a leading bishop who supported the punishment of heretics as fair and just.
Beausobre wraps up his discussion by saying he looked into the cause of the great unrest linked to Leo and considered the character of this revered pope.
He described Leo as ambitious, more focused on imposing through force than on winning hearts through teaching and persuasion.
However, Beausobre didn't stop there; to further express his discontent with the pope and the apostolic see, he cites words from Saint Leo about the execution of Priscillian and his followers by Emperor Maximus's officials in Trier.
These words seem to show the pope supporting the ruler's violent actions, and then he adds.
Quesnell's note on this point is worth mentioning:
Neither Severus Sulpicius, Jerome, nor any other holy Fathers of Priscillian's time approved of such violent measures; not Leo either.
Refuting and dismissing these accusations and slanders against Saint Leo's reputation and holiness isn't difficult for us.
Other objections are so weak and ridiculous that just a quick look at the Works of Saint Leo the Great will reveal the lies of his opponents.
So, I ask, where does the claim that Leo didn't outline the main errors of the Manichaeans in his Letters and Sermons come from, suggesting he was merely giving speeches like a rhetorician?
He certainly didn't get this from Quesnell's notes and writings, which he used as a guide, as we've seen from the earlier narrative.
Quesnell, at least, listed various Manichaean errors from the holy pope, as shown in chapter ten of this book.
Although he mentions others throughout, Quesnellus likely omitted them due to excessive negligence.
Why did Leo need to detail in his sermons the entire doctrine of Manichaean philosophy and theology, all the superstitious and profane rites, and all the devilish mysteries of that sect?
He didn't aim to write treatises on faith to attack those heretics; instead, he simply wanted to warn the Roman people to guard against their customs and practices.
He typically did this on the more solemn days of the year when the sacred mysteries of our faith were celebrated in the temple.
So, it was enough to briefly highlight their obvious errors so that the people would reject them.
However, when writing letters against the Manichaeans, he took a different approach, as shown by the texts and the order of subjects in those letters.
Regarding the letter sent to the bishops of Italy, Beausobre seems to have barely glanced at it.
If he had even briefly reviewed its text, he would have realized that Leo's goal was to warn the bishops about the events in Rome during the solemn judgment against the Manichaeans.
This was to prevent the vices, eradicated in Rome, from secretly taking root and spreading in their dioceses.
In short, Leo discussed the Manichaean heresy in general and invited the other bishops to share his concern by informing them that he had discovered many followers and teachers of Manichaean impiety in the city, made these discoveries publicly known, and restrained them with authority and censure.
Since he followed the formal procedures and rules of solemn judgments, he sent copies of all the proceedings, along with this letter, to fully inform them.
The series of events we've shared with you through these records is meant for your instruction.
After reading them, you'll know everything we've discovered.
It's unfortunate that such a series of Acts has been lost to the ravages of time.
But it's even more regrettable that Beausobre ignored this letter, choosing instead to attack the holy pope with slanders and insults.
As for the other letter, numbered 15, it addresses questions posed to the holy pope by Bishop Turribius of Astorga regarding the Priscillianists.
However, it wasn't appropriate or necessary for Leo to write a lengthy treatise on this or Manichaean heresy, as it would have gone beyond the scope of the questions he was asked.
It's insignificant that in the praised letter he discussed the practices of both the Priscillianists and the Manichaeans together, since these heresies were closely related.
The Priscillianists adopted many false doctrines from the Manichaeans, and both absorbed the ancient Gnostics' poison.
Therefore, Leo, the holy pope, shouldn't be accused of error if he sometimes called the Priscillianists Manichaeans.
Idacius even notes that Manichaeans, hidden in Astorga, were discovered through episcopal actions, put on trial in the year 145, condemned, and publicly exposed across Spain.
It's confirmed that he was speaking about the Priscillianists.
Even Jerome didn't shy away from this style of writing, as Quesnellus observed.
Furthermore, it's clear that he wanted to attack Saint Leo more harshly with the final accusation.
He portrays the holy pope, driven by ambition and fury, as having approved the tyrant Maximus's bloody plan against the Priscillianists, executed in Trier.
To those who wish to call Beausobre a liar and imposter, let them refer to the Leonine letter.
From there, they'll find enough evidence, as no more unjust reproach or bolder insult could be devised.
In the first chapter of his letter, Saint Leo explains how the bishops of his time swiftly acted to ensure that a dreadful heresy was eradicated from the Church.
Was there anything wrong with this approach?
Clearly, nothing that would tarnish the dignity of the bishops or harm the Church's gentleness.
The Fathers took decisive action by condemning Priscillian and his followers, expelling them from their episcopal positions and from communion with the Church, treating them like outsiders.
Beausobre doesn't agree with the harsher judgment that Saint Leo mentions next, stating:
Even the rulers of the world were so appalled by this sacrilegious madness that they executed its leader and many of his followers according to public laws.
This harsh judgment was attributed not to the bishops but to the severity and seriousness of the crimes.
He adds:
The rulers saw that all respect for decency was being removed, marital unions were being dissolved, and both divine and human law were being overturned if such beliefs were allowed to spread.
If the Priscillianists had only opposed religious doctrines without disrupting all laws of decency and divine and human rights, the secular rulers would not have resorted to such severe measures.
But because their actions threatened the very fabric of civil life, it became necessary to eliminate the leaders of such madness through public law.
Therefore, Saint Leo, to prevent any misinterpretation of his earlier words, differentiates between the two types of judgments, showing how ecclesiastical gentleness, satisfied with priestly judgment, avoids bloody vengeance.
If it avoids it, it does not endorse it.
He adds: Yet, it is supported by the strict laws of Christian rulers, as sometimes those who fear physical punishment turn to spiritual remedies.
So, how does Beausobre conclude that Leo approved of violent measures?
Maybe it's because he spoke of the gentle nature of the church, content with priestly judgment and supported by the decrees of Christian rulers?
But in what way did Leo affirm this?
Clearly, it was because those caught up in serious crimes, when faced with the fear of physical punishment, sometimes turn to spiritual remedies, renouncing their past impieties and crimes.
Thus, how pointless and futile are Beausobre's accusations against Saint Leo the Great, as our previous reasoning and method have shown.
From this, the reader can also refute Quesnel's subtle fourth annotation, although he isn't as boldly inventive as Beausobre.
Now, I had decided to pause and, setting aside for a moment the defenses of Saint Leo the Great, I intended to move on to address Augustine's cause, to also clear him of Beausobre's unjust accusations.
But while reviewing the writings of a non-Catholic author, I found other points that seemed to harm Leo's piety and sincere faith.
I felt it necessary to spend more time on this examination, so as not to be judged as entirely careless by critical and envious adversaries.
Therefore, once again, he brings the holy pontiff into the spotlight, not only to engage in discussions on the doctrines of the Manichaeans but to attack him with new slanders and reproaches.
First, he claims that Saint Leo followed the opinion of Cyril of Jerusalem, who said that Mani blasphemed by calling himself the Holy Spirit; he says: At least this accusation is more respectable; and Leo would have done better to adopt it rather than expand and explain the aforementioned words with inexcusable freedom, suggesting that the Manichaeans (according to Leo) worship Mani as the Holy Spirit, the master of such impieties.
And again: They believed the Holy Spirit appeared in their leader Mani.
.
so that Mani himself was nothing other than the Spirit.
Indeed, if this had been true (adds Beausobre), our heretic would have been driven by pride and blasphemy to the highest degree of malice.
If Leo is no more reliable in his accounts than he is fair in his words, we are certainly justified in doubting his statements.
Especially when, with just a few words, he aimed to counter the arrogant pride of Manichaeus, leading him to say the following.
He spoke about that part of the world which supposedly cannot receive the Spirit of truth, as if suggesting that the Holy Spirit is confined to narrow limits and that the people of the East are the most unfortunate of all.
Honestly, I would never have believed, adds Beausobre, that a bishop, who earned the title "Great," could have uttered such nonsense in a sermon that has been passed down through time.
He seemed to forget that the first among the Gentiles to come and worship the Messiah were the Magi, Persian philosophers, and almost ancestors of Mani.
Similarly, he forgot that in another sermon he stated that the Magi did not recognize Christ born in Judea from a celestial sign, but surely through divine inspiration in their hearts.
This is the essence of Beausobre's argument, who exposes the actor's shamelessness and deceit, if we look at the context from which Leo's three selected passages have been taken.
In the first passage, there is nothing that contradicts faith and truth, which the holy pontiff did not find the Manichaeans professing.
In that fourth sermon on Epiphany, while reminding people of the mystery of the incarnation and explaining in detail the day's celebration, including the arrival of the Magi in Bethlehem and the gifts they offered, as well as the celestial sign that guided them from far eastern lands, he condemned the Manichaeans, who he soon discovered were hiding in the city, briefly recounting to the people the sacrilegious tales and falsehoods by which they attempted to undermine the truth of the incarnation.
To avoid misleading people with numerous errors, he summarized the main points of all these errors: specifically, how they rejected the Mosaic Scriptures, corrupted the Gospels, scorned the apostolic truth of the creed, and taught that Christ was worshipped in the sun and the moon, while denying that Christ would judge the living and the dead.
They also venerated Manichaeus as a master under the name of the Holy Spirit.
It's clear how different these two things are: Manichaeus claimed to be the Holy Spirit, and his followers worshipped Manichaeus as the Holy Spirit.
Saint Leo the Great specifically confirmed this point about the Manichaeans.
They sacrilegiously argued that Christ was worshipped in the sun and moon, even though they did not claim that the sun and moon were Christ.
Likewise, in another sermon on Pentecost, our Leo began to refute the Manichaeans of his time, who claimed to follow a great and exalted authority.
They believed the Holy Spirit appeared in their teacher Manes, asserting that the promised Paraclete from the Lord did not come until this deceiver of the unfortunate arose.
They believed that the Holy Spirit resided in Manes, making him nothing other than the Spirit of God.
If we consider these statements of Leo in light of the Manichaeans' beliefs, we find no basis for Beausobre to call Saint Leo unfaithful and unjust.
It was clear to the holy pontiff that such perverse doctrines were professed by the Manichaeans, not from false rumors or the testimonies of others, but he proved all these from the Manichaeans' own confessions and their denouncement of their crimes.
Therefore, everyone should be convinced that the non-Catholic Beausobre always sought to create confusion by inventing fraudulent interpretations.
But at least it would be true that the holy pontiff was injurious to the Holy Spirit when he confined it to narrow limits and suggested that the Easterners were deprived of its help and guidance.
Away with such an invention.
Saint Leo recounts how Manes, the founder of Manichaeism, was condemned in the world during the consulship of Probus and Paulinus.
From this historical reference, Leo demonstrates that from the death of Christ up until this time, the Church had endured eight major persecutions, during which countless Christians became martyrs.
According to divine promises recorded in Matthew 19, these martyrs were given the Holy Spirit: "Do not worry about how or what you should speak," and so on. Therefore, it is impossible to believe that God withheld His divine gifts and inspiration from the Church for so many generations, only to bestow them later on a false teacher like Manes.
Following the reasoning of Archelaus, Leo firmly states that Manes did not receive even the smallest portion of divine inspiration. He argues that Manes came from a part of the world that could not receive the Spirit of Truth. However, these words should not be interpreted, as Beausobre mistakenly or maliciously claimed, as referring to Persia or the entire East. Instead, they refer to the devil, the father of lies, whose work Manes carried out by spreading false doctrines.
Saint Leo immediately clarifies this by saying: "Filled with the spirit of the devil, he resists the Spirit of Christ. And while the saints of God received the teaching of the Paraclete..." Since it is clear, even from Scripture, that the world is divided into two opposing sides; one ruled by God and truth, the other by the devil and lies; there is no reason why Leo's words, which align with divine teachings, should not be preserved for future generations.
Christ Himself declared that "the world cannot receive the Spirit of Truth because it neither sees Him nor knows Him," as recorded by the Gospel of John. But who would dare claim that the Holy Spirit is therefore limited to specific boundaries? Once we remove Beausobre's misleading interpretation, the other objections raised by the critic collapse completely.
With this matter settled, let us now proceed to refute additional false accusations made against Saint Augustine.
If anyone thought I could briefly explain this, they'd be mistaken.
There are countless malicious interpretations scattered throughout Beausobre's entire work, attacking and slandering the holy bishop.
It's not our intention to pursue, point out, and refute each one here, as that would extend our work immensely, making it laborious and troublesome.
So, I'll briefly touch on a few points from the preliminary discourse to the second part of his History.
When speaking about Augustine, Beausobre begins with words from Leontius of Byzantium, who noted that no one could describe the Manichean heresy more accurately unless they had been a Manichean themselves.
This statement fits Augustine, who, from the age of nineteen to twenty-eight, joined this sect and vigorously defended its errors against Catholics in numerous debates.
However, Beausobre insists that this should be attributed to Augustine's eloquence and intellectual fervor.
Secundinus criticizes him for not understanding Manichean mysteries:
"You seemed to me, and it is indeed so, that you were never a Manichean, nor could you have known its unknown secrets, and pursued Hannibal and Mithridates under the name of Manichean."
Beausobre ironically asserts that this paradox faces many contradictions. Firstly, it was stated by a heretic. Secondly, the prejudiced opinion of the world, namely those with greater knowledge and authority, opposes the slanderer.
What? Could Augustine, more learned and insightful than the other Latin Fathers, the oracle of the Western Church, have lived among the Manicheans for nine years without understanding their system? Could Secundinus have said anything more reckless or absurd?
He suggests that we have two options: either Augustine didn't fully grasp this system, or he changed, which some think is impossible to say without implying heresy.
He adds that he deeply admires Augustine's exceptional qualities above others.
While he holds great respect for Augustine's intellect and wisdom, he reflects on Augustine's memory and values his extensive efforts.
However, he believes the best lessons from logic and experience have taught him not to depend solely on Augustine's statements and testimonies.
The ancients never claimed to be infallible, a trait later generations attributed to them.
They were human, just like us.
After a brief aside, he says he doesn't wish to argue that Saint Augustine altered or corrupted the Manichaean system to win, as that would accuse him of betraying his faith; but it is certain he used certain sophisms and often misrepresented their religion.
These criticisms, he says, and other similar ones were written against Augustine, which we are embarrassed to recount individually.
To establish credibility for his claims, he presents various examples and proofs.
The first example comes from Augustine's words: For the enemy who thought he had crucified the Savior, the father of the righteous, was himself crucified; at that time, something different happened than was shown.
He argues that Augustine spoke from the Manichaean perspective and commends both the letter on the Foundation and the book on Faith, chapter twenty-eight.
He adds that the Manichaean was compelled to claim it was not Christ, but the prince of darkness and his allies who suffered those things.
Finally, let's talk about the concept of plant souls.
The Manicheans believed that plants contained a piece of divinity, and these divine qualities were preserved in plants and fruits.
They claimed that these souls only ceased to exist when fruits and vegetables were consumed.
As they entered the eater's flesh, they lost all intelligence, which is why a Teacher was sent to humans, because the divine part within them had become foolish.
And thus, a Teacher was not sent to melons, because they supposedly had a wise soul.
Beausobre was the first to highlight these three examples as if Augustine had portrayed them from the Manichean view.
He argued that such accusations were wrongly attributed to the Manicheans by the orthodox, as if they were actual doctrines of that sect.
I'll admit that I was bothered by these three points in the book "On Faith Against the Manicheans," which was incorrectly attributed to Augustine.
However, these ideas are clearly absent in another book that Augustine definitely wrote against the "Epistle of the Foundation."
I carefully reviewed this work and found no trace of such ideas.
But who could be unaware that the book "On Faith" is not genuinely the work of Augustine?
For scholars like Bellarmine and Vandingus noted that it wasn't listed among his works, nor in the Retractions, nor in Possidius's index.
They observed that the style was different from Augustine's and weaker in reasoning, suggesting the author only attempted to imitate Augustine.
This imitation involved expressing similar thoughts and sometimes using his words, especially from the book "On the Nature of Good Against the Manicheans."
Therefore, later editors of Saint Augustine's works attributed this piece to Evodius and placed it in the appendix of the eighth volume.
Those who tried to pass off uncertainties as certainties and falsehoods as truths should be astonished at Beausobre's negligence, if not deceit.
But even if we admit Augustine wrote these things from the Manichean perspective because he may have expressed similar ideas in the book "On the Nature of Good," what then?
Augustine came up with similar stories to incite fear against the Manicheans, as he later mentioned, accusing them with other examples.
In the passages praised by Beausobre, Augustine neither relies on false principles nor draws false conclusions from the true principles of the Manicheans.
In those passages, Augustine talks about the disgraceful things that the Manicheans invented against God, which I won't detail here, as it would be too tedious, and I don't want to burden the listener.
I also think it's unnecessary since anyone can read Augustine's text directly.
However, I can't overlook Beausobre's bold claim that false conclusions are drawn from Manichaean principles.
He says that these unfortunate people read, say, hear, and believe these horrors; it's written like this in the seventh book of their Treasury (which is what the Manicheans call a certain scripture where these blasphemies are recorded): then that blessed father, etc.
Thus, Augustine didn't add anything from his imagination, as he cites the Manicheans' own words, copies them, and includes them in his work, as shown in the entire chapter praised by Beausobre.
Furthermore, if Augustine had acted with malicious intent, does Beausobre really think that Faustus, Felix, Fortunatus, Adimantus, Secundinus, and all those from the Manichaean sect whom he criticized would have stayed silent without accusing him of being a liar and a fraud?
But Secundinus's words, mentioned earlier, show that he didn't stay silent, as he criticizes the holy bishop for not understanding the Manichaean mysteries and for chasing Hannibal and Mithridates under the name of Manichaeus.
I admit that Secundinus did voice these opinions.
But let Beausobre tell us whether Secundinus should be believed, as he criticizes Augustine for his writings, saying if they had been aligned with the truth, they would have been a great asset for them.
Don't, I ask, go against your nature, and don't be the spear of error that pierces the side of the Savior.
So, what does Secundinus here mock and scorn, if not the profound eloquence of the Holy Father?
If he had wanted to align it with the Manichaean principles, which the heretic claimed to be holy and true, while proclaiming that the doctrines of our faith were subject to falsehood, it would have been a great adornment for them.
But let's allow that Secundinus said Augustine was ignorant of the mysteries of the Manichaeans.
Still, I ask, who should be believed?
A heretical man, who, with a bad cause, seeks support from everywhere to defend it at least superficially, and to avoid failure, boldly resorts to lies, exaggerations, and deceit, even slandering the reputation and name of the holy bishop?
Or Augustine himself, who, having barely received the letter from this heretic, took up his pen and refuted all the accusations posed by his adversary?
If he had been ignorant of the Manichaean mysteries, he would have ignored the accusation.
But he did not ignore it; instead, he abundantly rejected the sect and doctrines of the Manichaeans based on the arguments put forth by Secundinus himself, to the point that the heretical man was very shamefully and utterly silenced, and for as long as he lived, he never dared to attack or slander Saint Augustine with insults again.
Therefore, the entire artifice of Beausobre collapses, and Augustine understood the Manichaean system very well; he did not change or corrupt it in the slightest.
Now, moving on to other matters, Beausobre foolishly attacks Augustine by raising the question of why, indeed, the holy doctor gave his name to the Manichaean sect, which taught such abominations, for nine years.
Why did he boldly defend the same against the Catholics?
He should not respond, I ask, that he was among the auditors, not the chosen ones, and therefore was ignorant of such blasphemies.
For he himself asserts that they are contained in the seventh book of the Manichaean Treasury, a book that all followers handle.
And he refers to those words taken from the book "On the Nature of Good," which we praised just a moment ago.
Augustine didn't know about these blasphemies when he was a Manichaean.
Or if he did know, he was surprised that he stayed in that sect for so long.
Beausobre gathers these and other similar things to show how the Manichaean system and doctrines were horribly altered and corrupted by poor interpretations.
To make this point more convincing, he refers to the two debates Augustine had with the priests Felix and Fortunatus.
He mentions that Felix was completely ignorant.
But Fortunatus, who was more knowledgeable than Felix, provides some insight into understanding the doctrine of that sect.
However, it's not our current task to discuss these two debates, as we've already spent enough time reviewing all of Augustine's writings, meetings, and actions against the Manichaeans.
So, with that topic set aside, we've decided to investigate more thoroughly when the Manichaeans came to Rome.
Chapter Eight
From Which Year of Christ the Arrival of the Manicheans in the City Should Be Recounted.
The False Judgment of Paschasius Quesnellus on This Matter.
Returning to our earlier point, there's little doubt that by the third year of his papacy, Saint Leo was already actively opposing the Manicheans through public actions.
Even Quesnellus, despite his reasoning, acknowledges Leo's efforts, although he overlooks what had long been done in Rome against the Manicheans by previous leaders.
Quesnellus claims that the Manicheans arrived in Rome after the fall of Africa, which was devastated by the Vandals.
According to Prosper, Victor, and Procopius, this disaster struck Africa in the year 427, when Geiseric crossed the sea with his forces and gradually took control of the region.
Given these events, their arrival in the city likely dates back to the time of Popes Celestine or Sixtus.
Quesnellus might also suggest that these heretics long disguised themselves as devout people, hiding their true beliefs under a severe demeanor and lifestyle.
However, Quesnellus must reconsider his stance if he realizes the Manicheans had been present in the city for a long time and had been exiled by both papal and imperial decrees.
Regarding Siricius, who became pope in 384, it's noted that he discovered the Manicheans, exiled them, and decreed they should not participate in communion, as their impure mouths should not defile the holy body of the Lord.
However, he didn't completely forbid them from seeking reconciliation through penance, as long as they sincerely returned to the Church's embrace and spent the rest of their lives in monasteries, dedicated to fasting, prayers, and other bodily afflictions.
This was to ensure they were thoroughly tested until the end of their lives, and because of their humanity, the Church would grant them the sacrament for their final journey.
We consider it beyond doubt that Saint Siricius acted against the harmful sect of these men in the fourth or fifth year of his pontificate.
This is evident from the new law issued by Emperor Theodosius the Elder in 388 and from the response of Bishop Ambrose of Milan, along with Sabinus, Bassianus, and other bishops of that province, sent to the same pontiff in 390, after they convened regarding the case of Jovinian.
Among other things, they assert: A Manichaean is one who denies the truth and the flesh of Christ; therefore, there is no forgiveness of sins, and the impiety of the Manichaeans, which the most merciful emperor has cursed, led all who saw them to shun them like a contagion.
They also add that the Manichaeans were expelled from Milan during Siricius's time, supported by the law of Emperor Theodosius the Elder: As our brothers and fellow priests Crescens, Leopardus, and Alexander, fervent in the Holy Spirit, testify, they drove them out of the city, condemned by the execration of all, as if they were fugitives.
These three priests, whom the Fathers of Milan call witnesses, were sent by Siricius to Milan with letters, where, acting as legates of the apostolic see, they expelled the Manichaeans from the city, as we also understand from this pontiff's letter to the Church of Milan.
Finally, the praised Fathers of the Church of Milan declare in their reply that they followed the judgment of the Roman pontiff so closely that they did not dare to add or take away anything from it.
This clearly shows that all heresies have been condemned by the authority of the Roman popes and through an unchangeable judgment, as we've demonstrated in previous chapters.
So, they say, know that Jovinian, Auxentius, Germinator, Felix, Plotinus, Genial, Martinian, Januarius, and Ingeniosus, whom your holiness has condemned, are also condemned by us according to your judgment.
It's evident that the Manichaeans had already found hiding places in Rome and other Italian cities at least forty years before Africa's devastation by the Vandals.
As early as the year 390, that harmful group was being punished by both imperial and priestly authority, when the Fathers of Milan issued such a decree.
Gothofredus supports us in his note on the Theodosian Code, where he deduces from the praised words that Pope Siricius was undoubtedly the proposer of the Theodosian law against the Manichaeans.
However, we acknowledge that this heretical group, having come from Africa or other overseas regions, inhabited Rome and other Italian cities.
This can be easily inferred from the Life of Pope Anastasius the First, who, upon Siricius's death, was elevated to the pontificate and issued decrees:
that no overseas person should be admitted to clerical honor unless he provided written endorsements from five bishops, because at that time Manichaeans were found in Rome.
But Anastasius ascended to Peter's throne in the year 398, which is twenty-nine years before the Vandals crossed the seas with their troops.
Therefore, the migration of the Manichaeans to the City cannot be attributed to the events in Africa caused by the Vandals.
Although we acknowledge that after Africa's devastation, the Manichaeans became more frequent in the City, where long before, members of this wicked sect had already found refuge in hiding places.
This is supported by the words of Leo in sermon fifteen, chapter five:
"Therefore, these utterly detestable and pestilent men, whom the disturbance of other regions has brought to us more frequently, should be completely rejected from your company."
At this point, since Quesnellus failed to notice, he made a disgraceful mistake.
But let's put aside Quesnellus's error; we don't want to seem too eager to criticize those who, both when he was alive and now after his death, have so valued his words and opinions.
They believed he wasn't misguided, at least not in matters of doctrine or historical and ancient discipline, and that he deserved high regard.
Meanwhile, as we follow a similar path, we want everyone to be convinced of one thing: that the arrival of the descendants of the Manichaeans in the City happened at least forty years before Africa was occupied by the troops of the Vandals.
Therefore, having established such solid foundations, we believe that the Manichaeans remained hidden in the regions of Italy up to the time of Pope Leo.
Despite this, the Roman city wasn't completely cleansed of this stain, even though both civil and ecclesiastical law had already decreed that such people should be exiled beyond Italy's borders, and those who repented should be confined to monasteries.
Yet, these cunning individuals, after laws were enacted against them, didn't dare to openly profess their sacrilegious superstitions.
Instead, they used great deception in everything, so to better conceal their infidelity, they continued attending the divine mysteries with the Catholics.
This was to avoid suspicion of their superstition and condemned religion by either secular or Church authorities.
Additionally, they only gathered in hidden and secret places, especially for their sacrilegious meetings.
Access to these places was only granted to those who had first been instructed in obscene and wicked rituals and, enticed by carnal temptations, swore an oath to uphold the nefarious heresy.
So, is it any wonder that, with such dedication and diligence, they managed to remain hidden for so long?
It's typical for wicked people, who want to commit serious crimes more cunningly, to fear the power of judges.
Fueled by vain hope, they convince themselves they can avoid public punishment by using hiding places as accomplices in their crimes.
When the Manichaean offspring lived in the city, the Roman people weren't entirely free from superstition.
Many remnants of pagans and Jews still participated in public spectacles like the Lupercalia, circus games, Bacchanalia, Augustalia, and Saturnalia.
This is clearly reflected in the letters of Pope Hormisdas and the sermons of our Leo.
Since the Manichaean heresy openly professed many errors similar to the fictions, rites, and indecencies of pagans and Jews, as we have seen, it could easily remain hidden within the city walls for a long time.
Not all citizens shared the same level of piety, faith, and religion.
Leo, upon discovering this, did not hesitate to address it publicly.
While the devil leads in various perversities, he established his stronghold in the madness of the Manichaeans, finding in them a vast hall to boast more joyfully.
There, he didn't just have one form of depravity but a blend of all errors and impieties together.
He then adds something more relevant to our matter:
Everything profane among pagans, blind among carnal Jews, illicit in magical secrets, and sacrilegious in all heresies converged into these people like a sewer accumulating all filth.
So, the holy pope didn't let himself be fooled by a fake display of virtue or the misleading appearance of piety.
He upheld the rules set by his Roman pontifical predecessors and the laws of the emperors, ensuring that nothing from the holy flock entrusted to him would be lost.
He spared no effort to uncover the practices of these heretics, their corrupt lifestyles, and the hidden places they lived.
To tackle this serious issue, which was secretly spreading like cancer and causing many to falter, he began to publicly denounce this sect of the devil in churches, especially during large gatherings.
He emphasized that it would be disgraceful for the children, whose ancestors learned the Gospel of the cross of Christ from the blessed apostles Peter and Paul, to let themselves be corrupted by such wicked errors.
He was remarkably successful in both respects.
As he consistently spoke out against such corruption during sacred rites, he launched a general inquiry into these heretics.
Those misled into superstitious crimes due to weakness or ignorance sought to correct their faults.
They sincerely condemned their crimes with great sadness and heartfelt lament.
However, others, who stubbornly defended heresy while indulging in carnal pleasures and other superstitions, faced physical and spiritual penalties.
Not only were they wandering vagabonds deprived of all rights and honors, forced to leave from place to place, but they were also excommunicated from the Church and shunned by all rulers and officials of the state.
Eventually, they sought refuge outside Italy's borders.
Thus, with the cities of Italy cleansed of heretics, we owe thanks to Siricius and Leo.
Especially because we see that through the actions of the holy popes, the form of ecclesiastical inquisition against the depravity of heretics was established and strengthened, as will soon become clear from what follows.
Chapter Nine
The Roman Investigation of Saint Leo the Great into the Manichaeans.
From this judgment, five main points are noted and examined, both from the writings of the same Holy Father and from the laws of the Roman emperors.
I already anticipate that what I am about to share might be quite unpleasant, or at least not very enjoyable, for those with limited knowledge, not to mention those with weakened faith.
To them, since they haven't deeply read the volumes of the ancient holy Fathers nor the history of ecclesiastical matters-unless they have drawn or tasted them from corrupted and depraved sources-we might seem like we're speaking nonsense or making things up.
Just as once, when I began to talk about this type of investigation by Leo in private discussions on ancient literary matters, certain people, who at that time hadn't fully examined the writings of the Holy Pontiff, judged me incorrectly.
They argued that the rights of the apostolic seat and the management of ecclesiastical judgments should never be based on doubtful and uncertain conjectures.
Those who opposed my words preferred to believe that this form of judgment and the concept of investigation in the Church's judgments came not from Leo but from more recent centuries.
At that time, I had planned to write a rather lengthy dissertation on this matter, one drawn solely from the works of the Holy Pontiff.
And, in this, to demonstrate the ancient discipline of the Church and especially the method of Saint Leo in identifying and condemning the heretical Manichaeans.
However, upon further reflection, I thought it more fitting to delay the discussion of this topic here, and for that reason, I am compelled to propose five points.
The term of inquiry was used during the age of Leo to describe the judgment process the Roman Church employed to identify Christians of any rank who were considered heretical.
Second, those suspected of heresy were required to appear before Church judges to present their case and receive their sentence.
Third, it was customary for the accused, when brought before the priests, to be compelled to confess their crimes and renounce them.
Fourth, Christians of any rank were obliged to take an oath to report, or denounce, those suspected of heresy to the priests of their churches or parishes.
Fifth and finally, those identified with heresies faced ecclesiastical censures and, if these were deemed insufficient, were handed over to secular authorities for further punishment, with the Church's request for assistance.
We aim to clarify these five points using evidence from Leo so that deceitful lies may be silenced from now on.
The first point, which we seek to prove, is primarily drawn from the fifteenth sermon, where the holy pontiff discusses both the fast of the tenth month and almsgiving.
Shortly before this, in the presence of priests, clerics, the esteemed Senate of the City, and other noble men, he had observed some people tainted with the Manichaean heresy.
To demonstrate the form of judgment his pastoral vigilance had maintained, in investigating and uncovering these individuals or publicizing and restraining them, he used the term inquiry.
Thus, in the fourth chapter, when discussing their obscene and unspeakable sacrifices and ceremonies, he says:
"Concerning their rites, which are as obscene as they are unspeakable, we do not remain silent about what the Lord has made known to our inquiry."
He then explains how those brought to trial revealed their wicked beliefs and terrible crimes.
The audience was horrified by these confessions.
Saint Leo, endowed with divine power and forewarned by revelation, knew that only some of the guilty hiding in the city were restrained and exposed at that solemn and holy gathering.
Therefore, before concluding his homily, he resolved to continue his efforts.
He promised to persist in the investigation until the entire city was cleansed of such corruption, driven by his diligence for the supreme apostolate:
"And so, merciful God revealed a certain part of the harmful people to us, so that by exposing the danger, we would be more cautious.
What has been done is not enough; the investigation must continue, so that with God's help, not only do the righteous remain unharmed, but also many who have been misled by diabolical seduction are brought back from error."
Therefore, illuminated by the divine spirit, with great strength of mind and firmness, Leo understood that nothing was more beneficial to the Church of God, and nothing holier or more desirable for Christians than the approach he employed.
From this, the integrity of faith and morals is defended and preserved, the worship and honor of God are increased, and the Church remains free from many vices that could corrupt it through diabolical contagion.
Conversely, if anyone in the Church is tainted with heresies or corrupted by wicked crimes, they can easily return to the right path of truth if they begin to repent.
But if they persist in their errors, they are struck with ecclesiastical censures and removed, cut off from the communion of the entire Church.
This approach was already recognized by world leaders and magistrates as perfectly suited for overseeing public affairs.
They used the term to describe the judgment applied to those accused of treason.
But let's move on to the next point.
Moreover, it's clear what we proposed secondly: the Manicheans, coming out of hiding, were summoned to court by the order of Pope Leo.
They faced accusations of betraying the faith before an assembly of bishops, priests, and other devout individuals to undergo the Church's judgment.
From this and similar events, even in Carthage and other African Churches troubled by the Manicheans during Augustine's time, we understand that Christian wrongdoers, regardless of rank, status, or gender, should be subject to the public judgments of sacred pastors, especially in matters concerning the integrity and truth of the faith.
Therefore, the harmful opinion of those who want to narrowly restrict the Church's jurisdiction, claiming it should only extend to those dedicated to altar ministry through clerical orders, is easily refuted.
They argue that these sacred pastors, especially when gathered in councils, can remove clerics from their ranks, strip them of church benefits, titles, and stipends, and confine them within monasteries or the strictest prisons.
On the other hand, they claim that laypeople, living outside the sacred hierarchy, should not be subject to such inquiry and judgment.
They have their own magistrates and judges, who can summon them to court, and it is primarily up to these authorities to examine the lives, morals, and institutions of the citizens.
Ultimately, if Church leaders had any authority over the laity, it would solely pertain to matters like participating in sacred communion, administering sacraments, or celebrating divine mysteries.
In these areas, laypeople can be justly and reasonably excluded from sacred gatherings.
In truth, those with ignorant and corrupt consciences might attempt to undermine the foundations of Catholic law.
They lack the light of faith, which would help them understand that the Church has rights over those who have renounced worldly impieties and dedicated themselves to Christ.
This is especially true when, through solemn rites, they have sworn in the principal sacrament of the Catholic religion to profess it throughout their lives and obey the Church.
What should be said then?
If, after breaking their faith, they could misuse divine and sacred matters, tearing apart the body and core of this holy mother Church, as if the Church had no jurisdiction over the laity to restrain impiety, who would ever mend the divisions caused by heresies?
Who would cleanse the threshing floor?
Who could ultimately address and heal more serious issues, preventing the spread of harmful opinions from shaking the entire Christian community and leading it to ruin?
Could it be that secular rulers and world magistrates could do what they deny the Church can do?
Away with such a notion!
They are focused on the civil administration of temporal matters, ensuring that when the rights of nature and principalities are broken, the state is not upended, causing great harm to justice by those who, due to crimes, boldly bring disturbance, violence, and injury to themselves, public affairs, and common tranquility.
However, secular rulers cannot, without showing contempt for divine law and committing sacrilege, involve themselves in ecclesiastical and spiritual matters unless priests themselves request assistance to defend the rights of religion.
Throughout Scripture, the writings of the Church Fathers, and the letters and laws of ancient kings and emperors, this is attested.
However, our method doesn't allow us to present all of these examples right now, so we remain focused on the writings of the Leonine Works when moving from fact to law.
To support our credibility, we could refer to Pope Siricius's decrees mentioned earlier, or the similar approach adopted by the African bishops during the time of Augustine and Possidius.
For example, when Urso, the tribune overseeing the royal household, was in Carthage, the Manichaeans there were brought before the Church's tribunal.
Among them was a girl named Margarita, not yet 12 years old, who claimed to have been corrupted due to their crimes, and another called Eusebia, considered a nun, who suffered a similar disgrace from a shameful crime.
These cases and others like them would support our claims.
But since we're discussing the Roman investigation into the Manichaeans, our method requires us to return to Saint Leo.
Leo, defending his integrity, openly stated that he was not misled by any deception nor acted rashly in exposing the Manichaeans' impieties.
He didn't rely on doubtful rumors or uncertain opinions.
Therefore, he adds:
"With the bishops and priests present with me, and 157 Christian men and nobles gathered in the same assembly, we ordered their chosen men and women to be presented. They were detained in chains or at least under guard, as the holy pontiff commanded them to stand before such a large and distinguished assembly. Indeed, if they had not been apprehended and were completely free, who does not see that they would have immediately tried to escape the disgrace and infamy by fleeing?"
It's natural for people of all backgrounds to fear judges, harsh sentences, and severe punishments.
When Pope Leo referred to those brought before him as "chosen ones," he was highlighting that these criminals were not from the lower ranks but had positioned themselves as leaders.
Among them, the most prominent was someone who had been declared a kind of bishop through profane and diabolical rituals, to lead others. Leo notes that everyone involved in the unspeakable crime was present: a girl about ten years old, two women who raised and prepared her for the crime, a young man who corrupted her, and the bishop who orchestrated their heinous acts.
Augustine, in his book on Heresies, writes to the deacon of Carthage, Quodvultdeus: Recently, some were discovered and joined the Church, as shown by the episcopal acts you sent us. I wish to pause here with those who, for reasons unknown, dread the name and duties of the Holy Inquisition, as they criticize this method of judgment more boldly.
Let them consider whether those men and women Leo mentioned could have been admitted to the clerical orders and the ministry of the altar. Let them explain why that sacred assembly acted against the immoral and incestuous, against pimps and corrupt women, mixing impropriety with religious matters. If we suspect this was done unjustly, why was there no protest from the Roman senate, the Roman people, or ultimately the emperor?
Did the Church pastors in the fourth and fifth centuries, by divine right, exercise the power to indiscriminately punish all baptized individuals, restraining the audacity of those who strayed from devotion to the true God?
However, since this matter is so clearly explained with obvious examples and evidence, there's no need for us to linger on it any longer.
We've thoroughly examined two key points with plenty of evidence and compelling reasons, and now a third point emerges, shining with the light of pure truth.
As we unfold the sequence of events and learn about the public confession of crimes by the Manichaeans, it leaves no room for doubt about the ecclesiastical discipline we're discussing.
The inquiry wasn't conducted just based on evidence or serious testimonies.
Instead, after a thorough examination of the facts, those involved were brought before the assembly, questioned and answered, and notaries recorded the proceedings.
With the utmost diligence, all doctrines, lies, disgraceful acts, and even the unspeakable oaths, mysteries, and ceremonies of that sect were thoroughly investigated, leaving nothing ambiguous for skeptics or detractors.
As for how much these proceedings might influence the less credulous or detractors of our time, I think everyone is aware.
Since the crimes of the Manichaeans were revealed not in secret or hidden confession, which we call sacramental, but in an open and formal court of judgment, the entire assembly noted them.
They were recorded by ecclesiastical scribes, just as had been done in the Church of Carthage in 158, which Saint Leo ordered to be preserved in the archives of the Roman Church for the memory of posterity, as he attested multiple times in his writings.
In the often-praised speech, it is said: "There was equal confession among all of them, and the abomination was revealed, which our ears could scarcely bear."
To avoid speaking too openly and potentially offending modest listeners, the records of actions are sufficient.
From these, it is clear that in this sect, there is no chastity, honesty, or purity to be found.
Here, lying is the law, the devil is the religion, and sacrifice is considered disgraceful.
In summary, the holy pope proclaims what was contained in the records of Acts.
In the 4 sermon on the Epiphany, chapter 5, after reviewing many doctrines of the Manichaeans, he states again: It benefits the whole Church that many of them, namely the Manichaeans, were exposed with the Lord's mercy, and their confession revealed the sacrileges in which they lived.
Again, in the 4 sermon on the Nativity, chapter 4, he writes: Those who, besides inventing all of the devil's insults, as revealed by their recent confession, find joy in both mental and physical corruption during the main feast of their observance.
In the second sermon on Pentecost, after explaining the mystery of the Holy Trinity and the mission of the Holy Spirit, he denounces in chapter 2, as we have already mentioned, the Manichaeans.
They claim that the divine Spirit appeared to their leader and that the promised Paraclete by the Lord did not arrive until this unfortunate deceiver arose, in whom the Holy Spirit resided, so that the Manichaean was nothing other than the Spirit, leading his disciples into all truth through a bodily voice and tongue.
At that time, he only addressed and dismissed this error of the Manichaeans.
The holy pope, however, chose not to speak about the rest, fearing that in such a frequent and solemn gathering of pious faithful, he might offend their ears or create a scandal for the more holy and pure Christians.
He concludes this chapter with these words: Those things which, out of modesty, are not to be mentioned in our speech, since they are already abundantly revealed by their confession.
The confession and detestation of their crimes by the Manichaeans were so solemn and public that the fame of these actions should have reached the ears of all Romans.
Therefore, since all these events unfolded before the entire Church, as Prosper writes in his Chronicle, no one of sound mind could doubt the power and jurisdiction of the sacred bishops, which had been approved by the consuls, the senators, and ultimately the emperor himself through common consent.
The letter to the bishops of Italy clearly showed that no one opposed Leo's actions or attempted to protect the Manicheans, who were exiled, as is often the case when there is uncertainty about a legitimate judge.
We learn that after the city was thoroughly cleansed of that heresy, he sent the bishops copies of the Acts, which faithfully and sincerely recorded the confession and denunciation of the Manicheans' crimes.
Indeed, shortly after, when it was suspected that the Manicheans might use their usual cunning to find new hiding places in other cities and regions of Italy, he, acting as the most vigilant shepherd, safeguarded the faith and moral integrity of other Churches.
To ensure he fulfilled his duty, he commended the letter and warned all the bishops of the cities of Italy about the events in Rome, so they would not, through ignorance or lack of instruction, allow the vices that had been eradicated to secretly take root in their dioceses.
He begins the one hundred and fifty-ninth letter with: "We call you, our most beloved brothers, into the partnership of our concern..." and after a few interjected words, adds: "Lest the disease, which by the Lord's mercy is driven away from our flock through our care, spread among your churches, and, with you not forewarned and unaware of what is happening, find secret tunnels of hiding; lest what we extinguish in the city be secretly sown among you with dark roots."
The immense contributions that the Roman people and the entire Church owe to him were clear to the bishops of Italy.
This is evident from the following words, which reveal his thoughts, actions, and achievements when he uncovered the followers and teachers of the Manichaean sect hidden in the City.
"Our investigation," he states, "uncovered many followers and teachers of the impious Manichaean sect in the City. Vigilance exposed them, and authority and discipline restrained them.
We corrected those we could, compelling them to publicly renounce Manichaeus along with his teachings and disciples in the Church by public declaration and signing with their own hand. Thus, we lifted those who confessed their sins from the depths of their impiety by granting them repentance.
Behold, in this one action, the encompassing authority of the Roman See and the divinely inspired method of Leo. The teachers of the Manichaean sect, along with their disciples, were first detained by the Church's command, then brought into assembly to publicly confess their crimes and retract them with a solemn profession. This required the signature of the guilty and their sincere intention to undertake penance.
Such an approach, revealed by divine mercy, was used by our Leo to lift the corrected and penitent Manichaeans from the depths of their impiety.
The crimes and disgraceful mysteries recorded and attested in the Acts of the inquiry were fully explained in that series of events.
Therefore, the Holy Pontiff himself, to instruct other bishops and ensure they had the proper guidelines on how to conduct themselves in such cases, ordered various copies of those same Acts to be made and sent along with the present letter to those bishops.
By examining the written volume, they could quickly see what had been done and what should be done in similar cases in the future.
To further reinforce this truth, what else can we do but transcribe the words of the Holy Pontiff?
We've shared everything from their writings and secret traditions that is profane or shameful, so the Christian community knows what to avoid or shun.
We even had their so-called bishop reveal the disgraceful things hidden in their mysteries, as the events have shown.
For your understanding, we have also sent these records: by reading them, you'll know all that we have condemned.
The fourth point contains something more significant, ensuring clarity and enlightenment for our purpose: to assert the ecclesiastical law declared to all the faithful, instructing them to avoid the company of heretics, especially the most harmful ones, and to report them to the sacred pastors of the Church.
As we noted earlier, Leo spoke in sacred assemblies and before the gathered people about their doctrines and secret traditions, highlighting their profane and shameful mysteries, so people would know what to flee from or avoid.
Sacred pastors have always clearly shown the marks and signs of false doctrine to Catholic followers.
This is so those with pure hearts would shun the disgraceful appearance of superstitions, avoid them, and protect the weaker and less knowledgeable from being misled by false piety, ensuring they don't fall into the company of such people and become corrupted by the same vices.
This was indeed the holy pontiff's approach; his aim in delivering his sacred homilies.
Therefore, when publicly rebuking the Manichean and his disciples, he refused to hide their crimes and errors, making them known openly so no one would be deceived by their food restrictions, dirty clothing, or pale faces.
He expressly ordered that no Christian should associate or have fellowship with such individuals.
Then, after revealing the rest of their deceitful tricks, he adds to our discussion: Up until now, they have harmed the unsuspecting and mocked the inexperienced.
From now on, no one will have an excuse for their downfall; and anyone who gets caught in this wicked error in the future must be considered not just simple, but very wicked and corrupt.
Similar insights can be found elsewhere, such as in the fourth sermon on the birth of the Lord, and likewise in the fourth sermon on Lent.
Also, in the fifth sermon on the fasting of the tenth month, which we have praised here more than once, where all the faithful are generally warned first to reject the friendship and company of the Manicheans.
Then specifically, turning to the women with all his strength of mind, he warns them to keep away from their acquaintance and conversations, lest, while the ear is delighted with their fabulous stories, it falls into the devil's traps.
Finally, to strengthen their faith and protect their chastity, he recalls the fall of the first woman, who, deceived by the devil's suggestions, cast the entire human race from the bliss of paradise into a state of misery and sorrow, from which it would still remain, if the mercy of Almighty God had not broken the snares of the demon and freed it from the bonds of sin.
The devil, knowing that he led the first man astray through the woman's words, and through feminine credulity cast all humans from the happiness of paradise, now also lies in wait with more secure cunning for your sex, so that those he can entice through the ministers of his falsehood may be stripped of both faith and modesty.
Truly, if the fairness and justice of this commandment are rightly considered, I can scarcely believe that it could be criticized or disapproved by anyone of sound mind.
It aligns well with the laws of all nations and peoples, which forbid anyone to deviate from ancestral rites and customs on their own authority, or to make and have new gods for themselves, or to secretly introduce or establish a different religion and sacred rites, unless all these were approved by public authority.
If everyone were free to follow their own desires regarding religion and moral teachings, join with innovators, or form alliances with them, what kind of confusion and disorder would arise in both sacred and secular matters?
What disagreements would occur among citizens?
How much variation would there be in rituals, ceremonies, and sacrifices?
Wouldn't there be intense arguments, envy, disagreements, and endless conflicts among priests and other ministers of the altar?
To prevent these issues, the senate and public officials, along with priestly colleges, decided for the sake of public peace and growth, even among pagans, that private individuals should not be allowed to change ancestral laws, invent new institutions, assign honors to gods, follow foreign rites and customs, come under their patronage, or attend their gatherings, lest a serious crisis among citizens threaten existing institutions.
Sacred and secular writers have discussed this issue clearly, as seen in the works of Titus Livius and Tertullian.
Thus, the command of our holy pontiff was mainly based on the precepts of the old and new laws, which advised avoiding the company of wicked and most criminal people, who, with malicious cunning, harm not only themselves with their corrupt morals but also aim to harm others.
For this reason, they seek and recruit partners in their crimes, especially targeting those they know to be unsuspecting, weaker, and simpler.
Therefore, Saint Leo, concerned for the peace and welfare of the entire Church, first wanted to exclude the Manicheans from the society of Catholics, and then instructed each faithful follower of Christ to investigate them and report them to the sacred priests.
Nothing could be clearer than this apostolic command, expressed in these words: "I also urge you, beloved, that if any of you know where they live, where they teach, whom they associate with, and in whose company they rest, you should faithfully inform us of this concern."
It is made clear that no one, not even the more virtuous and holier individuals, is exempt from this duty of reporting, as it says: "For it is of little benefit to anyone if, protected by the Holy Spirit, he himself is not captured by them, if he is not moved when he understands that others are being captured."
Against common enemies, there should be united vigilance for the common safety, so that the injury of one member does not also corrupt others.
If among them there are some who, indifferent to the Christian faith and church matters, are led by vain pretexts-like the honor, fame, and good name of the world-and persuade themselves that it is unnecessary to report those shaken by heresy to legitimate judges, or to bring them before them, they certainly cannot care for their own salvation. Instead, they prepare a broader path for themselves to undergo ultimate punishment.
This silence, which allows harmful men to be hidden and not pay the penalties owed for their crimes, is excessively destructive to them.
Such silence is a grave offense, says Saint Paul, on which the Lord will pass judgment on the last day, even if they have neither associated with heretics nor been shaken by the same errors.
Saint Leo's words are certainly golden: "And those who think such people should not be reported will be found guilty of silence in the judgment of Christ, even if they were not contaminated by agreement."
To simplify the process and provide the easiest way to make such accusations, and to help those who find it burdensome, extremely difficult, and risky to stand before such a great judge to report those suspected of heresy, this responsibility is given to the leaders of the churches in the city of Rome.
This is so every faithful person can quickly and easily, without shame or modesty, and with all fear and disgrace set aside, report the names, behaviors, and homes of heretics.
We also urge you in this mission to reveal any Manichaeans hiding anywhere to your priests.
For it is a great duty to uncover the hiding places of the impious and to defeat the devil himself whom they serve.
Moreover, he praises the greatness and excellence of this duty a little later at the end of that chapter, emphasizing that it is completely wrong to leave hidden and unpunished those who reject, corrupt, or deny the mysteries of the new and old law, among whom nothing is sacred, nothing is whole, nothing is true.
Furthermore, he adds: They must be guarded against to prevent harm to anyone; they must be reported so they do not settle in any part of our city.
Beloved ones, it will benefit you before the tribunal of the Lord, that which we declare, that which we ask.
Here, indeed, as many noteworthy things present themselves to us, a vast field is opened, where the discipline of ecclesiastical inquisition is defended, and its principal method of proceeding shines forth most clearly.
First, what can be observed, is it not what almost all heretics strive with all their might and effort to overturn?
Since they argue that even matters of religion and the Church should be brought before the tribunals of secular power?
Did not the matters of the Manichaeans, which we are discussing, concern both divine and human affairs simultaneously?
And yet it was not brought to the Roman consuls, not to the tribunes of the people, not to the senators, nor even to the emperors themselves; but to the presiding priests of the churches, who were appointed by the pontiffs throughout the regions of the city, whom we now call parish priests.
The second issue is that the holy pontiff sought to use this serious and comprehensive formula of apostolic authority to establish true, not merely temporary or symbolic, ecclesiastical jurisdiction over all citizens and residents of Rome.
They should be expelled so that they do not remain in any part of our city.
No one, in a formal assembly and among the people, would claim a city as their own if they were deprived of true jurisdiction, merely living there, or if they had originated from there.
They would indeed call it their homeland rather than their city.
And finally, setting other matters aside, a third point cannot be overlooked.
We are clearly taught that those who do not obey such a command, deviating from the law that mandates those stained with or suspected of heresy must be brought to the ecclesiastical tribunal, are guilty of impiety.
Their transgression, which attracts God's wrath, will not escape punishment, at least on the last day, since it is shameful, indeed most shameful, not to have worked for the common cause of faith, in matters where we can, and not to have wanted to combat the devil, whom all heretics serve.
However, the holy pontiff did not fully agree with these actions.
Instead, with another newly devised plan, he declared the Manicheans through a new indication, so they could be more easily caught, and Catholics were almost compelled to report their names.
He knew well that this pestilent offspring, whether under the guise of feigned piety or the wicked doctrine they professed, had accustomed themselves to detest all grape wine, whether pure or diluted with water, so that they would not taste it.
Perhaps, with that most wicked persuasion, they thought it was equivalent to the gall of dragons and produced by a certain evil creator whom they imagined as a god in their doctrines.
To dispel such a false and unworthy belief, Leo, with his utmost wisdom in handling sacred matters, decreed that all Catholics, in the communion of the sacraments, should be refreshed not only with the Eucharistic bread but also by drinking the blood of redemption from the chalice.
This was so that, by partaking in both kinds of communion, they would openly demonstrate sincere testimonies of piety and faith.
With this evidence, it became easier to reveal, even during the sacred mysteries, if anyone was engaging in the impieties of the Manichaeans.
Leo himself explains this more clearly than anyone else could:
"Even though they dare to intrude upon our mysteries to conceal their infidelity, they behave in such a way during the communion of the sacraments that sometimes they cannot entirely hide, receiving the body of Christ with an unworthy mouth, yet completely avoiding drinking the blood of our redemption."
He then explains why he made this known to the faithful of Christ:
"We make this known to your holiness so that such people might be revealed to you by these signs, and those whose sacrilegious pretense is discovered may be marked and expelled from the society of the saints."
Quesnellus removed the two words, "marked and expelled," which were retained in other editions and manuscripts.
Meanwhile, let no one think that Leo's policy could in any way favor the Lutherans or others troubling the Roman Church, because, depending on the circumstances of the times, he prohibited laypeople from the communion of the cup.
For laypeople are not deprived of the reception of the blood, even if they communicate under one kind only, as the learned doctors of theology clearly demonstrate even in the schools.
Therefore, there is no need to examine these arguments, lest I repeat stale comments, as they collapse by the mere reading of the Scriptures.
I believe, then, that what we have said so far regarding the care and diligence of all the faithful in reporting heretics indiscriminately is more than sufficient.
Now, it's important to discuss the deep devotion of Catholic rulers, whom the Church's pastors have often turned to in serious matters.
These rulers enforce decrees related to faith, moral discipline, church governance, rights, peace, and protection.
This is a straightforward issue, which we've saved to discuss now.
To confirm this, we only need to recall the so-called imperial constitutions, issued at the urging of the Roman popes, bishops, and general councils.
These were published across all Catholic regions to ensure even the most stubborn heretics faced severe penalties.
Words can hardly express how fervent the religion of former Catholic rulers was against those who tried to disturb or weaken the Church's peace and faith.
As soon as the rulers declared themselves for Christ, they supported the Church leaders.
They used their power to abolish idol worship or invalidate the decrees of previous pagan rulers.
These decrees had treated Christians as slaves and hunted them down for death.
Moreover, they had such disdain for heretics that they stripped them of all honor, rights, and privileges.
They confiscated heretics' possessions for the royal treasury, banished them from society, and sometimes imposed capital punishment.
This, I say, was the faith of Constantine the Great before he was misled by the followers of Eusebius.
All the Valentinian emperors, including Gratian, Theodosius, Arcadius, Honorius, Leo, and other Catholic emperors, wholeheartedly embraced this faith.
They believed that all the rights of the empire were granted by God Almighty, not merely as a generous act or as proof of their goodwill towards religious matters.
They consistently supported the Church with this belief, understanding that these matters were more significant than civil governance.
They viewed it as a grave sin to neglect the Church's duties and leave any aspect of its well-being unprotected.
What else does Saint Leo remind the emperors of, when writing to Theodosius, Valentinian, Leo Augustus, and Pulcheria Augusta, but this very issue?
He urged them to provide the support, befitting their position and power, to the troubled and afflicted matters of the Church.
Indeed, sometimes the holy pontiff demanded such assistance with such vigor, as if it were a duty owed to the religion of Christ, that, while respecting the honor of their imperial status, he seemed to press them quite strongly.
He would remind them of serious, alarming thoughts, such as the risk of incurring the wrath of Almighty God, threatening the empire's fortune, and disrupting all temporal affairs, if they, the emperors, failed to use their power to suppress heretics or those suspected of heresy, and to exclude them from the company of Catholics.
Therefore, to more easily secure divine mercy and remain true to the piety and customs of their ancestors, all the worldly powers they held were dedicated to the destruction and downfall of heretical people.
We don't need to delve into the laws of the emperors from the Theodosian Code regarding such a common issue, particularly those laws enacted by five devout emperors for punishing the Manichaeans.
Instead, let's focus on the new decree by Emperor Valentinian, which he personally wrote, addressing the recent crimes of the Manichaeans uncovered by Leo's investigation and condemned by judgment.
We're discussing the Manichaeans, whom past emperors' decrees considered detestable and banished from the world.
Valentinian refers to the decrees of Theodosius, the elder Valentinian, Arcadius, and Honorius, as documented by the jurist Gothofredus.
Valentinian then adds, "The newly discovered crimes cannot remain hidden."
These were obscene revelations made during the judgment of the blessed Pope Leo, confessed openly before the distinguished senate!
Their supposed bishop even betrayed and revealed all the secrets of their crimes.
Valentinian's words offer new evidence showing that Saint Leo acted as a true and legitimate judge in investigating the Manichaeans, demanding confessions and condemning their crimes, as we've previously established.
Valentinian also indicates that Leo's formal judgment actions did not escape his notice.
Therefore, to ensure that ecclesiastical judgments were enforced and divine injustices avenged, Valentinian strengthened ecclesiastical authority by issuing a public law intended to last forever:
"Wherever a Manichaean is found, they shall face the penalties prescribed by law for sacrilegious persons, under the authority of public severity."
Valentinian referred to the traditional penalties the Church imposed on sacrilegious individuals, ensuring there was no way for these offenders to escape by granting public authorities the power to enforce strictness.
"Let it be a public crime," he stated, "and let everyone have the ability to accuse such people without risking danger."
Later, this very devout ruler, while discussing temporary punishments for the future punishment of the Manichaeans, added:
"It's neither lawful nor safe for anyone to conceal or collaborate with such individuals; they are stripped of military rank, the right to live in cities, and are excluded from society.
They are forbidden from receiving or leaving inheritances; all their goods and property are to be collected into the imperial treasury.
They are permanently deprived of the right to enter contracts or reclaim possessions before judges; and finally, any military or office leader is fined 10 pounds of gold if they know someone tainted by this superstition is serving.
Nothing seems too severe to decree against those whose vile corruption commits acts under the guise of religion that even brothels would be ashamed of or unaware of."
With these words, the vigorous and great defender and advocate of ecclesiastical authority concluded his new decree on May 20th, 445 AD, when Valentinian himself and Flavius Nummius held their sixth consulship, as well-documented in the ancient records of the Roman Empire.
Chapter Ten
The Roman Council on the Case of the Manichaeans.
The Judgment of Antonio Pagi and Paschasius Quesnell on This Question.
From whose critical annotations the opinion of Cardinal Baronius is eventually vindicated.
Although many records have been lost to time, and we lack all the resources to address new questions that could shed light on the ancient ecclesiastical discipline observed by the apostolic seat of Saint Peter for those marked by heresy, we still have access to important sacred resources.
These resources are deemed useful, and even necessary, for thoroughly resolving the questions already raised among recent critics.
This controversy falls into this category, stirred long ago by Father Antonio Pagi and Paschasius Quesnell.
Driven by a strong eagerness to debate, they opposed Cardinal Baronius, arguing that no council was ever convened in Rome regarding the Manichaeans.
However, since the renowned author of the Ecclesiastical Annals relied heavily on the letter of Leo to the bishops of Italy and considered all aspects carefully, we find it hard to believe he erred so gravely when he asserted that a council of bishops and priests was indeed held in Rome.
As we aim to address this disagreement, we present the main arguments from the opposing side.
Specifically, those by which Pagi and Quesnell claim that the gathering in Rome regarding the Manichaeans was never called a council by Saint Peter, but was only referred to as a meeting, session, and judgment.
To back up this theory, they refer to the new law of Valentinian, which, according to Quesnel, includes the term assembly.
They then challenge Baronius with these arguments:
But there was no need for a council, which Saint Prosper does not mention, because it wasn't about condemning a new heresy or affirming the faith, but rather about enforcing punishment according to the Church's canon.
Moreover, it isn't considered a council when it includes both members of the clergy and the senate and the people.
Therefore, they believe these weak arguments should entirely dismiss the idea of it being a council.
But doesn't this put Quesnel and Pagy in an awkward position?
They boldly criticize and scrutinize the words of others, thinking Baronius can be challenged with completely baseless and deceptive theories.
They eagerly search for issues while indulging in their own interests, inventing new ideas; and when they engage in disputes purely about words, they stray far from the truth and end up fighting against the shadow of the truth.
Although this kind of issue doesn't seem relevant to our purpose, nevertheless, before we conclude the Exercises on the works of Saint Leo concerning the Manichaean cause, we will attempt to refute each argument from both critics, so the opinion of the distinguished Baronius does not go unchallenged.
First and foremost, they argue over mere semantics, denying it can be called a council, which the Holy Pontiff sometimes referred to as a gathering, and sometimes a session and judgment.
Who are these two serious critics disputing with?
Is it with beginners in the Latin language, or at least those who have never examined the ancient monuments of the Church?
Indeed, even the writers of the golden age of Latin often used "gathering" for "council," as seen in the works of Titus Livy, Cicero, and Caesar.
The earliest Christian writers didn't hesitate to use the term convent to describe the sacred gatherings of Catholics for setting rules of faith or morals.
Writers like Tertullian, Eusebius of Caesarea, and Rufinus the presbyter of Aquileia were among them, though we won't list them all right now.
What's the point?
The term convent was used to mean council, so much so that even today in collections of synods, we see titles like: Convent of Sirmium, Convent of Alexandria, Convent of Hippo, and many others.
This clearly shows that the ancients used the two terms interchangeably.
However, all this detail might not have been necessary for such a well-known fact.
This is especially true because Saint Leo, acting as his own interpreter, used convent to mean council.
A notable example is Quesnel, who, when enhancing the works of the holy pontiff, followed the faith of the old editors and manuscripts, publishing the seventh chapter of the thirteenth letter of Leo with the title: On the holding of provincial councils.
This document, containing what is found in section 18, chapter 2 of the councils, and in the decree of Ivo, strongly proves that Saint Leo intended for the terms convent and council to mean the same thing.
To avoid any suspicion of inaccuracy, it's worth quoting Leo's words as they appear in Quesnel's edition.
Regarding episcopal councils, we decree nothing other than what the holy Fathers have beneficially ordained: namely, that there should be two conventions every year, where all disputes that typically arise between different orders of the Church are judged.
And again, in the same Quesnelli edition, these readings appear in letter 16, chapter 7, about the Councils to be held annually in Rome.
The Holy Father, discussing canon 5 of Nicaea, adds:
"Therefore, we originally demand for the safeguarding of the most harmonious unity, that since it was very beneficially established by the Holy Fathers, there should be two meetings of bishops every year."
Thus, because of two critics, it has deteriorated, since Leo himself, following the Nicene Fathers, wanted to use the term 'meetings' to denote both provincial and general synods.
This can be increasingly proven by many other examples taken from the works of the holy pontiff.
Nor can the same cause become stronger due to the other term 'assemblies,' which the famous oration of the great Emperor Constantine reveals was used by the ancients to indicate a council.
He addressed the Nicene Fathers gathered together:
"Because," he said, "it was greatly desired by me, my dearest friends, to enjoy this gathering of yours at some point."
And shortly after, congratulating the same Fathers for proceeding to synodal actions peacefully without personal rivalries, he adds, "And although I am indeed very happy when I now see your assembly, then I consider, etc."
Meanwhile, I am ashamed to get involved in these entanglements with people who despise the basic elements of knowledge.
For they do not ponder that among the ancients, one thing was often named by multiple terms.
Especially because these, being dependent on human will, can easily change without the nature and substance of things being altered.
Furthermore, Latin speech should not be considered so barren that each thing must be assigned a singular term, beyond which no other term could express the things themselves, or the properties, functions, and virtues of those things.
According to Cicero, the Latin language is incredibly rich in vocabulary, even surpassing Greek in its abundance.
As I've often mentioned, I believe Latin not only isn't lacking, as many think, but is actually richer than Greek.
So, is it any wonder that a council, which the Greeks call a synod, meaning a gathering where judges meet to manage Christian affairs, naturally has several names, including the most fitting ones?
The ancients sometimes referred to it as a meeting, while other times used words like assembly and judgment.
In essence, isn't every council both a gathering, an assembly, and a judgment?
Critics should reflect on this and realize the serious error lies with them, not Baronius.
It's important to consider that when Quesnel noted this, he might have been either inattentive or flattering himself, thinking his readers wouldn't notice the switch from assembly to judgment.
Valentinian didn't use the word assembly in his novella, but rather judgment, as Quesnel himself confirmed when he published it, revealing: What things, and how obscene to say and hear, in the judgment of Pope Leo before the most distinguished senate, were made manifest by their own confession.
From start to finish, the word assembly never appears.
Now, it's time to move beyond these words and focus on the matters themselves, carefully considering the other arguments of both critics.
Unless I'm mistaken, these arguments are so weak that they lack the force to challenge Baronius.
The first point is particularly weak, as it's based on Prosper's silence.
Quesnel notes that Prosper doesn't mention the council.
So what?
Does Prosper explicitly omit the Roman council held by Saint Leo regarding the Manicheans?
However, he recounted how, through the diligence of this holy Pope, he discovered the Manicheans hiding within the city.
He exposed them to the entire Church, condemned and denounced all the vile teachings of that heresy, and had their books burned.
Quesnellus completely ignored all these things.
But Prosper actually recorded in the Chronicles: During the time of Maximus the Second and Paterius (or Paternus), many Manicheans were uncovered in the city through the diligence of Pope Leo.
He brought them out of hiding and presented them to the entire Church, condemning and denouncing all their vile teachings, with their books burned.
Therefore, there is no doubt about the public and solemn condemnation of the Manicheans.
If both critics claim this was done by Saint Leo outside a council, they face a difficulty they always strive to avoid.
They essentially concede to us that heresies and heretics can be condemned solely by the authority of the Roman pontiffs and sometimes have been condemned without any council's approval.
A council is only necessary when the Roman pontiffs deem it appropriate.
They have customarily summoned them when the entire assembly of the Church was to solemnly receive the decrees of faith already defined by the apostolic see; when a larger gathering of bishops was deemed useful to curb the audacity of heretics for a more solemn judgment; and finally, when it was considered appropriate to resolve church matters disturbed by schismatics or by the power of princes and other secular officials more easily and peacefully.
There is no law mandating councils as necessary for the Church.
In fact, the laws themselves ensure that general councils are not held unless the Roman pontiff deems them necessary.
If new heresies and schisms arise in the Church, they must be immediately and necessarily suppressed and removed, following divine and apostolic commands.
This is to prevent the seeds of wickedness from spreading or taking root, which would harm the Catholic faith, and to stop the tares of demons from growing more each day.
The cure for these evils wasn't just a single remedy of councils prepared by the founder of the Church, but several.
The Roman pontiffs can address these evils through letters filled with sacred doctrines, frequent admonitions, or by sending their legates with strong warnings, without convening general synods.
Such solemnity in judgments isn't absolutely necessary, but only when church matters are completely disturbed, or when questions are so doubtful and convoluted that, for the sake of peace and salvation, the apostolic see finds it necessary to convene a council.
So, we cannot accept what critics have asserted in this matter, that there was no need for a council because it wasn't about condemning a new heresy or affirming the faith, but about imposing a penalty according to the canon of the Church;
as if in either case it would be necessary to convene councils, or if no other reason exists, provincial or general synods could be called and held.
Where did they get such a doctrine?
Let them present canons, the monuments of the Fathers, and the customs of the Churches, so we too may know the sources from which this unique and unheard secret discipline originates.
If we consult the Fathers, councils, and the practice of the Church, we must defend and believe the opposite.
In the second century, when councils began to be held more frequently in the Church after the apostles, bishops gathered in Asia and Palestine to discuss the question of celebrating Easter.
A great witness is Irenaeus, the apostle of the churches of Gaul, and a most splendid light, to whom all, both ancient and more recent scholars, have given credence.
Among these scholars is Eusebius of Caesarea in Book 5 of the Ecclesiastical History, chapters 24 and 25.
But who will assert that in the same synods it was discussed to denounce a new heresy or to establish faith?
In the third century of the Church, when in Rome and in Africa, then in Phrygia, and in Neocaesarea in Pontus, many Church Fathers gathered either to impose beneficial penance on those who lapsed during times of persecution, to restore ecclesiastical discipline, or to dissolve accusations against bishops and vindicate them.
Yet, nowhere was there any discussion of a new heresy or articles of faith, as the writings of Eusebius, Cyprian, Dionysius of Alexandria, and other Fathers who flourished in that age reveal.
Some fragments of their writings have reached us.
What more?
In the fourth, fifth, and subsequent centuries, countless councils were held either to pronounce anathema on already condemned heresies, establish various ranks of penitents in the Church, remove bishops from their seats, restore those unjustly deposed to their rightful places, or to deal with appeals, church dedications, immunities, and concessions of indulgences to penitent lapses, and matters of that kind.
Therefore, it is wrongly fabricated that the holy pontiff did not have a council regarding the Manichaeans, because it was not about condemning a new heresy or asserting faith.
It is sufficient that anathema should be pronounced on the Manichaeans found in the city; it is sufficient that the discipline of the Roman Church required that the Manichaeans be sent far from all the borders of Italy.
Even though the Manichaeans judged the penalty according to the Church's canon, Saint Leo publicly exposed their shameful doctrines before the entire Church, leading to their condemnation.
This was documented by Saint Prosper of Aquitaine, as we've seen, and nothing could stop these actions from being carried out in the council.
Especially since the holy pontiff aimed to establish new policies for exposing and reporting heretics, and for handling their reports, which he intended to impose on all Catholics under the weight of Almighty God's disapproval.
So, is it any surprise that before setting such obligations on both the people and the priests, he wanted to create a new canon to be followed in similar situations?
His sole aim was the safety of religion and all Catholics.
So, he called an assembly, made a judgment, and included both part of the senate and part of the people, setting a general rule of conduct to bind everyone's conscience, from which no one could stray without bearing the mark of a crime.
Now, critics might feel pleased when they encounter a complex issue, perhaps thinking it as daunting as Hercules, when they speak as if from an authoritative position:
There is no council where both a part of the senate and a part of the people are included with the priests.
This recent point would challenge Baronius if it were truly solid and opposed to the sacred synods' sanctions and divine law rules, if the Manichaeans' case had been judged alongside the priests and presbyters, with part of the senate and part of the people gathered.
However, it's highly questionable that part of the people was summoned when discussing the Manichaeans' doctrines and crimes.
Neither Valentinian, Saint Leo, nor anyone else claimed this.
Valentinian, in his novella, indeed states that their crimes were revealed in the presence of the distinguished senate through their own confession.
Leo, discussing the meeting he organized, stated:
"With bishops and priests sitting alongside me, and Christian men and nobles gathered in the same assembly, we arranged for the chosen men and women to be presented.
If there is debate about Leo's two mentions of 'Christian men,' suggesting that a portion of the common people was at least indirectly indicated, I'm open to agreeing.
But what's the point?
Is it unusual in the Church for leaders, royal ministers, the senate itself, and some from the people to be included in councils as witnesses?
Wasn't that the practice and custom in many councils?
Setting aside the councils of the apostles, where the apostles and other disciples, along with all the faithful and the entire multitude of believers, gathered, didn't laymen skilled in philosophy also attend the first general council of Nicaea, besides the bishops and Emperor Constantine, to engage in debates in front of everyone?
We indeed have strong witnesses, not only from all Catholic writers but even from the heterodox ones like Calvin, Illyricus, Luther, the Magdeburg Centuriators, and others, who agree with us on this well-examined matter. Although they later misuse these praised examples, trying to create new schemes against the Church, wrongly teaching that laymen should be included in sacred synods not just as witnesses but as judges, and that they can be deprived of a decisive vote only by extreme injustice.
But why should I concern myself with these heretics now, who distort everything or at least twist it to the opposite?
Instead, I should return to Quesnel and Pagius and ask whether they have ever examined the records of the Council of Chalcedon?
This synod, however, was convened seven years after the condemnation of the Manicheans by the same Pope Leo's authority and was confirmed in the year 451, as we will mention at some point.
Were only bishops, priests, and other church clerics and ministers present, or was the senate, along with some others from the people, also involved?
According to the authentic Acts, senators, magistrates, consuls, prefects, and other imperial officials gathered in Chalcedon.
It's said that Emperor Marcian himself attended this grand assembly, accompanied by a large entourage of nobles and commoners.
Following the example of Constantine the Great, he presented himself as a defender of the faith.
He wanted to participate in the synod to strengthen faith, not to exercise any power, following the example of the religious leader Constantine.
This is how Marcian addressed the people of Chalcedon.
Could this not be considered a council, with the emperor, senators, provincial prefects, and even the people present alongside the priests?
Pure nonsense; let's dismiss such fiction!
The presence of laypeople in councils does not harm the truth of the councils, as long as bishops, their representatives, or other ministers and followers of religious orders discuss ecclesiastical matters and define issues of faith.
And if only these individuals subscribe to synodal decrees as judges.
Princes, magistrates, or common people would not be deprived of a role in councils if they are admitted and called as suitable witnesses and defenders of truth, as is customary.
However, to avoid any suspicion that such a distinction between laypeople and church ministers was not observed in the Leonine Manichaean assembly, I would like you to pay attention to how the holy pontiff describes it.
He first describes the bishops and priests sitting with him as if in a tribunal.
Then he says that, with Christian men and nobles gathered, he ordered the chosen men and women to be presented.
Thus, the noble men did not sit with Leo and the other bishops or priests; they were simply gathered when the crimes of the Manichaeans were being testified and condemned.
And when those Manichaeans whom the holy pontiff had brought to repentance were being received.
This is what those words of Saint Prosper mean, which we also mentioned earlier.
He revealed the Manichaeans who were hiding in the city to the entire Church and made them renounce their shameful doctrines.
So, if Leo's approach was such that the Manichaeans couldn't be received into the Church as penitents unless they publicly denounced their sect's errors, why is there a strong argument that the assembly of the holy pope could be called a council, given that part of the senate and part of the people were present?
What's the point of all this?
Setting aside all biases and focusing solely on the truth, which should be sought in writing and debate, I see nothing in that Roman inquisition of the Manichaeans that contradicts the traits of a true council, especially since we can easily refute the arguments of Quesnel and Pagi.
Indeed, I understand something that pleases all Catholics and helps preserve the purity of faith in the Church, though it may displease some: the current approach to general inquisition has adopted some methods similar to Leo's inquisition against the Manichaeans.
If we face opposition, even from the learned and erudite, questioning whether it can be consistently proven that this form of judgment has never changed or been interrupted from Leo's time to ours, I wish our intention were clear.
We are not those whose minds stray beyond the set goal.
Our intention was simply to review, embellish, and draw certain exercises from Leo's works and to defend the deeds of the holy pope from criticism.
Therefore, we have dedicated our efforts to avoid excess and arrogance, to steer clear of rashness and verbosity, and we wouldn't have mixed the actions of others with those of the holy pope unless we encountered matters we couldn't overlook without seeming ignorant.
What does it mean if the approach and method for dealing with those stained by heresy, or suspected of heretical influence, were sometimes interrupted?
Our Leo had not yet passed away when barbarian forces from the North and Africa brought the Roman Empire to its end, thereby disturbing the affairs of the Catholic Church.
These forces made alliances with demonic powers, spreading wickedness, tyranny, and the errors of many heresies far and wide.
The supreme pontiffs and other leaders struggled to steer Catholics away from vices, to dissuade rulers from slaughtering citizens and burning cities, and to convince the numerous heretics, especially Arians, to renounce their errors and profess the true faith.
Amid such great turmoil and surrounded by fierce enemies, there was constant fear.
As a result, with Church laws somewhat softened by leniency, they adequately fulfilled their pastoral duties of rooting out the errors that were growing daily and repelling vices that could undermine the piety of the faithful.
However, this does not mean that during these challenging times of war and change, the ancient discipline of the Roman Church was erased or altered, even if it wasn't always implemented due to practical reasons.
It was impossible to maintain the same rigor of inquiry under barbarian rulers, who harbored countless errors, as Saint Leo had established under devout Catholic rulers.
Therefore, no one should be surprised if, during these troubled times for the Christian republic, church pastors had to serve in a way that ensured all Catholics, along with the true faith of Christ, would not suffer under the yoke and persecutions of the barbarians.
We can better illustrate the management of the Roman popes by looking at the apostles.
While preaching the gospel of the cross to both Jews and Gentiles, they had to adapt to the times in ways that did not conflict with the Christian faith.
This approach gradually brought people of all ranks and backgrounds to Christ.
Please don't be upset with me for being thorough in refuting the arguments of Pagi and Paschasius Quesnel, nor should anyone complain that in defending Baronius, I've mentioned many things that could have been left out or explained more briefly.
Necessity alone drove me in both cases.
It is the enthusiasm of Quesnel and others like him, who often overlook their own positions without enough consideration, ignoring what should be highlighted in the works of the holy Fathers.
They strive to overturn what ought to be defended, and they attempt either to diminish or obscure matters related to the authority and dignity of the apostolic see.
However, ancient writers took a different approach, as shown by Theodoret's Greek letter to our holy pope Leo, where he sincerely recounts the honors, prerogatives, and duties of the apostolic see.
For this reason, all nations used to flock to this see, saying, "Let us receive a remedy for the wounds of the churches from you, for it is fitting for you to hold the first place in all things."
In another part, he goes on to praise certain deeds of the holy pope, including his zeal against the infamous Manicheans, saying, "Your holiness recently undertook this, and through this diligence in divine matters, you revealed your love for God."
We find it fitting to close this discussion with these words.
Chapter Eleven
After the death of the great Leo, the Manichaeans returned to the City.
Pope Gelasius made efforts to uncover them.
William Cave's mistaken judgment about communion under both kinds.
Saint Gelasius finally expelled these wicked people from the City, destroyed their books, and added a sentence of excommunication.
What other heresy is bolder and more cunning than Manichaeism, or more confident?
For being so sacrilegious in its religion, corrupted by wicked morals, and profane in its rituals, it should have avoided places where civil and ecclesiastical laws strongly opposed it, and where judges from both courts were ready to restrain, eliminate, and completely abolish it.
To see such audacity, one does not need to look far from Rome itself.
Although they were harassed in many ways and suffered enough punishment, under the direction of the great Leo, the Manichaeans were driven out and sent into exile far from all the coasts of Italy.
Yet, not long after the death of such a great pope, they were found to have settled in Rome again.
When I considered this, I strongly suspected that the Manichaeans in Rome, terrified by Leo's general inquiry against them, used every deceitful tactic to hide.
Therefore, to avoid having their disgrace exposed, they sacrilegiously participated with Catholic men in sacred assemblies and divine mysteries, as Saint Leo had complained of this most serious crime.
If this suspicion of ours is not proven by learned men, it must be affirmed that the Manichaeans, having been sent away from Italy by Leo, upon hearing of the holy pope's death, returned to Rome to seek their old hiding places.
As it is not possible to determine this matter without a credible witness, we merely describe how the Manichaeans settled in the City again after the death of Saint Leo.
Pope Leo the Great passed away in 461, and Hilarius was appointed as his successor.
In the sixth year of his papacy, Hilarius died, and Simplicius succeeded him.
It's not clear from any sacred or secular sources whether the Manichaean sect was present in the city during the time of these two popes.
So, instead of relying on uncertain records, let's move directly to the papacy of Pope Gelasius and his actions.
According to the Pontifical book and Anastasius in the Lives of the Roman Pontiffs, during Gelasius's time, Manichaeans were discovered in the city.
He ordered them to be exiled and their books to be burned in front of the Basilica of Saint Mary.
To identify these individuals, Gelasius used the method established by the decree of the great Pope Leo in the Roman Church.
He required all who approached the sacred communion to participate in the mysteries of both kinds, as the Manichaeans, due to their extreme superstition, completely abhorred wine.
By refusing the communion of the cup, they were easily distinguished from true believers.
Regarding this Gelasian decree, William Cave noted and praised the method of the holy pontiff for exposing the Manichaeans who tried to hide under the guise of Catholicism.
He then gradually attempts to criticize the Roman Church's practice of communion under only one kind as a novelty, adding that the ancient custom in the Church from its beginnings was that no one participated in sacred gatherings without receiving communion under both kinds, which Gelasius confirmed with his decree.
But as a man of the Reformed sect, who favored his own side and wanted to accommodate the Greeks, he had to make these claims.
However, Cave, can you tell us when the Roman Church followed this custom?
Provide records that show laypeople, who did not perform the Eucharist, were required to communicate under both kinds when gatherings were held in the early Church.
If Pope Leo the Great and Pope Gelasius had supported this practice with their decrees, it implies that before their time, Catholics were forbidden from abstaining from the chalice.
Therefore, priests preparing the Eucharist would have needed to consecrate a significant amount of wine during their gatherings to suffice for both themselves and the congregation participating in the sacred mysteries.
However, only the Manichaeans would have refrained from sharing the chalice.
So, why was it necessary to compel the faithful to partake of both kinds of communion?
Why confirm by decree what was already a common practice among lay Catholics?
If the Roman Church, always eager to rely on the doctrine received from the apostles, understood this practice as divinely instituted from the beginning, it would never have denied the use of the chalice to laypeople not preparing the Eucharist and would never have discontinued this rite.
Yet, the decree of the same holy pontiff shows that offering the chalice to the laity wasn't practiced during Leo's time.
He required Catholics to use the chalice for expediency, to expose the Manichaeans.
But with the Manichaeans expelled from the city, why doubt that this practice or expediency was immediately abandoned?
Isn't it true that, according to Caveo, Pope Gelasius, who became pope over thirty-one years after Leo the Great's death, found the Manichaeans and, to strip them of their Catholic disguise, compelled Catholics by his decree to partake of both kinds?
He certainly wouldn't have compelled them if that practice or rite hadn't been discontinued at least after Leo's death.
However, I think it's unnecessary to dwell on these trivialities any longer.
Indeed, not only does the decree we've discussed reveal that Gelasius followed Leo's expediency, but also the efforts he made to ensure the Manichaeans found in Rome were forced by judicial power, arrested, and exiled.
However, Gelasius himself didn't feel he had adequately protected the integrity of the Catholic faith if, after exiling those wicked individuals from the city, their sacrilegious books or writings still existed.
So, wishing to follow in the footsteps of Saint Pope Leo, he aimed to completely destroy and abolish those volumes that were being widely distributed to deceive others.
For this reason, he gathered all the Manichaean books he could find and carefully reviewed them, ensuring they wouldn't become a stumbling block for anyone in the future.
He ordered them to be burned in front of the Basilica of Saint Mary.
It's very likely that on this occasion, Gelasius sought to convene the famous council of seventy bishops, where, after revisiting the decrees of his predecessors, he compiled a catalog of the divine books of both the Old and New Testaments.
He identified their authors and distinguished the authentic Scriptures from the apocryphal ones.
In the latter category, he specifically rejected writings used by heretics, which groups like the Manichaeans, Montanists, and Marcionites falsely introduced under the apostles' names.
Thus, not only did Pope Gelasius reject these books along with other heretical volumes meant to destroy or undermine the Catholic religion, but he also removed them from the entire Roman Catholic and Apostolic Church.
With the full council's agreement, he declared these books, their authors, and followers eternally condemned under the unbreakable bond of anathema.
Regarding the nature and quality of the Manichaean books that Pope Gelasius condemned as false and spurious by his decree, I don't think it's necessary to detail them here.
Firstly, that catalog of apocryphal books has been revealed through the diligent work of many distinguished scholars, and we've already discussed such books in previous chapters.
Chapter Twelve
After the death of Saint Gelasius, the Manichaeans entered the city for the third time.
Eventually, Pope Symmachus, following the example of his predecessors, exiled them and burned their statues and books in front of the Basilica of Constantine.
While discussing the use of these statues, we explain how Symmachus, who was variously harassed by Emperor Anastasius, was wrongly accused of being tainted with Manichaeism.
After losing their refuge in Rome, the Manichaeans believed they couldn't find a more favorable residence elsewhere.
They longed to return from exile with great zeal but feared the vigilance of Pope Gelasius, who was attentive to them and their writings.
Therefore, it seems inconsistent with the truth that they returned here, exhausted from punishment, while he still held the papacy.
Gelasius died in the year 496 and was succeeded by Anastasius the Second, who, after two years as pope, passed away without any notable mention of the Manichaean sect in Rome.
However, this was not the case during Pope Symmachus's time.
When he ascended to the throne of Saint Peter in the year 498, under the pressure of the severe faction of Antipope Lawrence and relying on the authority and power of Emperor Anastasius, the Manichaeans, previously exiled twice, seized the opportunity from this great schism to make another journey to Rome.
They believed no time could be more opportune for them than this, as the Church and the empire were divided into factions, and neither the rigor of sacred ecclesiastical discipline nor the severity of imperial laws could easily be enforced by the ministers of both the sacred and civil monarchies.
This schism was indeed very serious, dividing the clergy and the senate into two factions.
One side supported Lawrence, the deacon of the Roman Church, who had taken over the basilica of Saint Mary.
The other side backed Symmachus, who had been elected and ordained with legitimate votes and sacraments in the Constantinian basilica.
With Rome shaken by these severe disturbances, it was no wonder that the cunning Manichaean followers found a way to inhabit the city for the third or fourth time.
The path was made easier for them when Pope Symmachus and his rival Lawrence were summoned to Ravenna by King Theodoric, the Arian, and had to present themselves before him to receive his judgment as the appointed arbiter of this schism and turmoil.
This disgraceful act of the schism introduced a kind of tyranny into the Church.
Symmachus, who could not be subject to the laws or decrees of secular rulers regarding his legitimate election, was forced to submit to the royal judgment and decree to prevent greater scandals during those troubled times.
Moreover, God Himself helped in wonderful ways to protect the fairness and safety of the Church so that the gates of hell would not prevail against it.
All the disturbances of ambition and the dreadful schism were brought to a fortunate and happy conclusion.
King Theodoric decided, in accordance with the sacred canons, that of the two bishops, the one who had been ordained first, or where the majority was recognized, would sit in the apostolic seat.
Fairness and the recognition of truth were found in Symmachus, as stated in the words of the Book of the Pontiffs, and Symmachus became the bishop.
With everything arranged, Symmachus set out for Rome.
There, he organized a council against the deacon Laurentius, who had tried to seize the Roman episcopate through a deceitful ordination.
Out of compassion and using his apostolic authority, Symmachus released Laurentius from the canonical restrictions he had incurred due to the attempted schism and unlawful ordination.
He then appointed him as bishop in the city of Nuceria.
Meanwhile, although the factions of that dreadful schism seemed almost resolved, the poison of hatred and jealousy had tainted the hearts of many clergy and noblemen, even those of high standing due to their past consular dignity.
This same poison had secretly corrupted them more deeply.
As a result, Symmachus's opponents, growing bolder over time, erupted into fiercer revolts.
After four years had passed, with Festus and Probinus renewing their hostility against Symmachus, they accused him before King Theodoric as if he were a criminal.
They arranged for false witnesses and secretly recalled Laurentius, the false pope, from Nuceria to Rome.
By reigniting the previous schism, they petitioned the king to grant them oversight of the apostolic see.
As unrest increased daily, partly due to the boldness of Bishop Peter of Altinum, who, relying solely on royal authority, involved himself in the affairs of the Roman see against sacred canons, and partly due to the animosity of Festus and Probinus, the former consuls, who instigated civil war within the city against other senators, especially Faustus, the former consul they disliked.
The violence and killings of this conflict could not be avoided even by clerics; some of them, along with women and virgins in monasteries, were afflicted and wounded.
In the end, priests were struck down by either clubs or swords due to immense envy.
The records of the Ecclesiastical Annals reveal that these events occurred in Rome at the beginning of the sixth century, in the year 502 AD.
At this time, it's clear that the Manichaean descendants hiding here could not have enjoyed happier days than when both church and state affairs were so chaotic that nobody paid them any attention.
However, their joy quickly turned to grief and sorrow, as shown by the actions of Symmachus.
After initially resisting King Theodoric and his envoy Peter of Altinum, and later overthrowing the usurper of his position, he gathered a council of one hundred fifteen bishops in Rome.
There, he bravely appeared and cleared himself of the accusations against him.
The virtuous life of the holy pontiff, along with his integrity and other virtues, which envious and hateful individuals had attacked with slanders, were praised by all good men and became well-known, like gold tested across the nations of the world.
This fortunate and just vindication of the holy pontiff was soon followed by another positive event.
As senators and the Roman people gradually ceased killings, uprisings, and robberies, peace and tranquility began to emerge for the City and the Church.
However, I will not delve into the various and numerous ways in which Symmachus was troubled by both King Theodoric and Emperor Anastasius, as well as other church and state officials, to avoid straying from our topic and objective.
This speech would certainly be too lengthy if I were to list all the slanders against Symmachus or discuss the six synods he convened to defend his position, prove his innocence, restore and strengthen the collapsing discipline of the Roman Church, and repel all heretics and schismatics from the community of Catholics who, tainted by Arian, Eutychian, or Acephalian errors, were corrupting the true doctrines of religion.
These matters do not pertain to the Manichaean history we intend to explore.
While there are many aspects that reveal and defend the supreme rights of the Apostolic See, let's focus on those that highlight Symmachus's great courage in the case we're discussing.
Despite being besieged by significant challenges from all sides, he refused to be swayed by worldly powers and continued to expel the Manichaeans who were hiding in the city under imperial protection.
He destroyed and burned their images and books.
Following these actions, the author of the Pontifical Book in the Life of Symmachus notes, that the blessed Symmachus discovered Manichaeans in Rome, burned their images and books in front of the Basilica of Constantine, and exiled them.
The mention of "all images" deserves our attention, as it suggests a new rite or custom of the Manichaeans that we haven't seen documented elsewhere, and none of those who have chronicled the Lives of the Roman Pontiffs have explained it. Beausobre even dared to deny this, as we discussed in Chapter 4 of this book.
However, if we look to Augustine, who described all the Manichaean customs, we might infer that the Manichaeans used profane signs and images to represent their corrupt and mythical stories and sacrilegious theology. This might be suggested by Augustine's words, where he referred to the Manichaeans' shameful religion not as a sect but as a schism of the nations. This is because they aligned with the primary pagan doctrine of multiple gods but differed from pagans by teaching that good and evil, light and dark, eternal and transient, changeable and certain, corporeal and divine do not originate from the same principle.
Faustus posed this as a Gordian knot or Achilles' argument to Augustine, challenging him not just to reject the label of schismatics of the nations but to assert that they were far worse than the pagans.
However, Augustine argued against this assumption by criticizing Faustus and the Manichaeans, who sacrilegiously and superstitiously worshipped the sun and other heavenly bodies, like Hile the Earth and the imagined Atlas holding up the world.
They even worshipped things that didn't exist and were mere inventions of their own.
Therefore, the holy doctor reasoned from these practices and customs, saying,
This makes you worse than the pagans.
You are similar only in that you worship many gods, but worse because they worship things that exist, even though they are not gods, while you worship things that are neither gods nor anything at all, as they don't exist.
Then, the holy doctor brings up some pagan myths created by poets for entertainment, briefly mentioning stories about the lame Vulcan, blind Fortune, adulterous Venus, warlike Mars, and Cupid, the boy with a bow and arrow, which the pagans themselves tried to interpret in relation to nature or human behavior.
He concludes:
We mock them because they worship these poorly interpreted stories, which, if not understood, they might worship more excusably, though still blameworthily.
Augustine asserted that something of all these could be found in reality, although they are of no benefit or use to human salvation, and what they interpret from these can be found in things.
Therefore, Augustine emphasizes these and many other things taken from the fables of pagan poets, contrasting them with the Manichaean doctrines to conclude that this harmful offspring is worse than the sects of all nations.
Among other things, these stories include the myth that describes humans fighting with the five elements, or the one where they imagine a powerful spirit creating and magnificently maintaining the world from the captive bodies of the nation of darkness.
This spirit supposedly holds the remains of the members of your God in its hand, lamenting everything else that is captured, oppressed, and polluted.
Or, finally, there's the tale of the great Atlas carrying on his shoulders the figure they fancifully invented, depicted as if on a theatrical tapestry.
These tales, I say, and countless other similarly foolish and insane ideas, were never demonstrated by the Manicheans in paintings, sculptures, or interpretations, as Augustine himself testified.
However, since the language of these writings seems quite obscure, it's exceedingly difficult to determine whether, in the time of the holy doctor, the Manicheans used statues, paintings, or images to more easily instill these harmful tales in the minds of their followers and listeners.
It is also challenging to understand this practice and custom of the Manicheans in accepting images of the nations based on earlier testimonies.
However, by frequently considering these matters and others like them, we suggested that they should not stray far from the words of the Book of the Pontificals or from the testimony of the librarian Anastasius, which states that Symmachus scattered and burned all the Manichaean images and all the manuscripts before the doors of the Constantinian Basilica.
Indeed, we deemed it a serious offense not to insist on these points or to question their credibility.
Above all, the use of images undoubtedly convinces us of the laws of the Persian homeland, from which the sacrilegious religion of the Manichaeans originated.
They also inform us about those sacred festivals of Bemmatis, celebrated annually in March in honor of Manes' death and in contempt of the resurrection of the Lord.
They built a magnificent throne, lavishly decorated, claiming it symbolized the glorious birthday of their teacher, Mani.
As we pondered this, we noticed that the Manichaeans themselves sought to honor their teacher by placing their beds on reeds, reminding them that Mani was skinned in Persia, as Nicetas claims, supposedly out of hatred for truth.
These acts were designed by the Manichaeans as a testament to their impious beliefs and as a mockery of our Catholic faith.
They sacrilegiously and superstitiously altered and defaced symbols borrowed from us, including the sign of the cross, images of the Mother of God, and others like them.
They presented these altered items sometimes as revered objects and other times as objects of disdain, using these artificial symbols to indicate the doctrines their notorious leader introduced into the world.
Thus, there's no doubt that the great pope Symmachus, fully aware of the sacrileges and superstitions of this wicked sect, destroyed and burned all their signs and images, along with all the books that hinted at some evil mystery.
The holy pope could not tolerate the Manichaeans and their methods of showing contempt for our religion.
The nature and duty of the supreme pontificate, challenged by such great adversities, required this public demonstration of his sincere faith, so that everyone would understand how far his spirit was from the Manichaean doctrine and how deeply he despised that sect.
Finally, it is believed that everyone is aware that among the many slanders fabricated against the holy pope Symmachus by the envy and malice of the opposing faction, the accusation of being guilty of Manichaean doctrine was significant.
His enemies spread this stain of disgrace and violated faith so widely that it reached the ears of Emperor Anastasius, the patron of the Acacian and Severian factions, in Constantinople.
To allow Anastasius to escape the excommunication imposed by Symmachus, he accused the holy pontiff of a serious crime with much criticism.
As a result, Symmachus had to publicly demonstrate his faith.
He did so by exiling the Manichaeans and destroying their books and images.
However, Pope Symmachus did not believe this public demonstration was enough to refute every accusation.
When he learned that Emperor Anastasius had written a defamatory letter, slandering him as a Manichaean among the Easterners and other peoples, he responded with a speech in his defense, completely clearing any suspicion of association with the Manichaeans.
The details of Symmachus's apologetic letter and Emperor Anastasius's role as a patron of the Manichaeans will be explained in the next chapter.
Chapter Thirteen
On Pope Symmachus's Apologetic Letter Against Emperor Anastasius's Defamatory Writings.
This emperor, a supporter and protector of various heretics, even took Xenaia, the leader of the Manichaeans, under his wing.
From these events, we take a moment to briefly explore Xenaia's character, practices, and writings.
Pope Symmachus's reputation was never more severely damaged than when his enemies dared to spread rumors of him as a supporter of Manichaean teachings.
This was particularly the case when a defamatory letter written by Emperor Anastasius against the holy pope was circulated, filled with insults and accusations, publicly portraying him as guilty of numerous crimes and betraying the faith.
Despite being placed in such a serious predicament and examining the defamatory writings, he was not moved by hatred or anger.
Instead, considering his duties and the honor of the apostolic see, he never thought of avenging the insult.
He carefully composed that famous letter, responding to the defamatory writings of Emperor Anastasius, and successfully cleared and erased each slander.
He began his defense of the Catholic faith by following the example of the eight books that Ambrose had written to Emperor Gratian, as he was not ashamed to speak of it gloriously, and the emperor was not reluctant to accept it gratefully.
Then, the holy pope openly demonstrated the strength and steadfastness of his spirit, showing no fear in standing before a tyrannical pagan emperor who threatened him with death, contemplating and referring to the apostolic warning of Paul:
"Woe to me if I do not preach the gospel"; and that it is better to risk the loss of this present life than to be punished with eternal damnation.
In a straightforward and gradual manner, he firmly addresses Anastasius, speaking to him as if he were the emperor of the Romans and a Catholic leader.
He encourages him to embrace these roles, just as he is used to graciously receiving delegations from barbarian nations and patiently listening to the apostolic leader.
Unmoved by severe accusations, he recalls the Lord's promise in Matthew: "When they persecute you and say all kinds of evil against you for righteousness' sake, rejoice."
This inner joy, which he cannot hide, compels him to return blessing for curses, honor for insults, and love for hatred to the emperor, even though the emperor is hostile to him.
Yet, he warns him to beware of the divine judge's anger, emphasizing that the more willingly he forgave great offenses, the more punishment would be demanded from the offender.
He mentions the scandal in the Church caused by the infamous document the emperor wrote against the Church's head, and the anathematized opinions of Acacius, Severus, and the Acephali, which the emperor supported.
He immediately cites various testimonies from Holy Scripture, hoping the emperor might reveal the falsehood of these heretical opinions.
Meanwhile, as the pope seeks not his own interest but the honor and majesty of his seat, he challenges the emperor, pointing out that by disregarding human and divine laws, the emperor took on the role of accuser and judge against the highest pontiff of the Church, bringing great disgrace to the imperial crown.
Therefore, he rebukes him by writing: "You say that I am a Manichaean. Am I a Eutychian, or do I defend the Eutychians, whose madness especially supports the Manichaean error?"
By speaking in this manner and using irony, he not only highlights that he was wrongly accused of Manichaean heresy but also aims to criticize Anastasius.
While Anastasius supported the Eutychians, he also defended the Manichaeans by protecting Xenaia.
Xenaia, a leader of the Manichaeans, tried to gain the emperor's favor by aligning with the Eutychian faction.
Thus, Symmachus, in an effort to clear his name and prove he was never guilty of Manichaean scandal, calls upon the city of Rome as a witness and references the records of the Apostolic See, where the authentic acts of true faith were preserved.
He challenges anyone who judges his religion unfairly or suspects him to engage in debates with him and to openly provide real evidence of the crimes he is accused of.
Otherwise, he declares they should be considered infamous and guilty of slander.
I believe it's appropriate to share his words here so that the sentiments of the holy pontiff are well known to all:
"Rome is my witness, and the records bear testimony to whether I have deviated in any way from the Catholic faith, which I received coming from paganism at the seat of the blessed Apostle Peter. Let someone come forward and prove it by any means. Otherwise, these are insults, not proofs of crimes."
Following this, he entrusts his case to divine judgment, recalling how he once experienced God's supreme wisdom and providence. When he was legitimately elected as pontiff and on his way to the Basilica of Constantine to assume the papal order, he safely escaped an assault of stones. Hoping to always have God as his helper, he is confident that nothing harmful will happen to him or his See. Nor could the emperor have any evidence that God was angry with Symmachus or the Roman See.
With great resolve, he spoke to him like this:
Show what you believe should be accused, so you can prove that God, in extreme anger, allowed things that were improper.
And to cleanse or heal the wounds that had harmed and corrupted the emperor's mind: Is it because I do not comply with the Eutychians?
These things do not harm me; instead, they clearly show that you aimed to reject the honor that blessed Peter bestowed upon me through his intervention.
He does not clarify that God might be angry with him for this reason, having provided various explanations.
For when he opposed the Eutychians, whom he neither accepted into communion nor embraced their teachings, he took on roles most fitting for the supreme pontiff, whose sacred power was as distant from imperial power as divine matters are from human affairs.
Thus, by comparing both dignities, he addresses the emperor like this:
You, emperor, receive baptism from the pontiff, partake in the sacraments, ask for prayer, hope for a blessing, and seek repentance.
In the end, you manage human affairs, while he dispenses divine matters to you.
And to ensure he does not seem to claim superior honor for himself, he insists that at least equality should be acknowledged for both.
These matters, and others like them, Pope Symmachus presents for the glory of his pontifical dignity, the defense of his innocence, and the protection and honor of his apostolic seat, aiming to clear the unjust stain of disgrace that Anastasius had branded on him by portraying him as a defender of the Manichaean sect with slanderous writings.
Indeed, through these slanderous writings, Anastasius had accused Symmachus of conspiring against him, claiming that he, with the Roman Senate's help, had excommunicated him.
The pontiff, responding to this accusation with compelling and truthful reasons, easily overturned this slander as well.
The pontiff first stated that he had introduced nothing new, but had continued the practices of his predecessors:
You say that with the Senate conspiring with me, I excommunicated you.
I indeed follow these practices reasonably, just as my predecessors did without a doubt.
So, Symmachus was not the first to pronounce a sentence of excommunication on Emperor Anastasius.
However, he was condemned as a defender and supporter of the Eutychian and other heresies by two other Roman pontiffs, namely Gelasius and Anastasius the Second.
Symmachus would have certainly revoked this sentence if the emperor, having abandoned the heretics, especially Acacius, and resolved the schism in Constantinople that he supported, had chosen to associate himself only with Catholic and apostolic bishops.
By withdrawing from their society and no longer involving himself in their meetings, the emperor could have dissolved the bonds of excommunication, as if he had repented from his previous obstinacy.
Therefore, the most gentle pontiff offers this remedy for the serious evils that afflicted him greatly: Do not involve yourself with his-Acacius's-excommunication, and you are not excommunicated by us.
If you involve yourself, you are excommunicated not by us, but by yourself.
Thus, in either case, whether you withdraw or not, you are not excommunicated by us.
After this lengthy exaggeration, Symmachus criticizes Anastasius, first because, upon being elevated to the apostolic seat of Peter, he did not write the imperial letters (as was the custom) to assure the pontiff of his faith and filial love, since the care of the entire Church had been entrusted to him by the word of the Lord and Savior.
The pontiff criticizes this grave omission solely to avoid appearing negligent in the care of the Lord's flock, not because he wanted to be seen as more concerned with his own honor.
Then indeed, he attacks the same emperor for compelling Catholics by military force to communicate with those polluted by schismatic and heretical corruption.
He denounces this course of action as a horrendous and detestable crime.
While it might not seem appropriate for the leaders of the world, no matter their power, to break those ecclesiastical laws that have been established since the early days of the Catholic Church by both divine and imperial authority, he is reminded of how the Christian religion, from the apostles to his own time, has endured many persecutions by adversaries but could neither be oppressed nor destroyed.
The persecutors themselves met unfortunate ends, and the orthodox truth prevailed everywhere.
Meanwhile, the pope was particularly troubled by the fact that pagans, or even those worse than pagans, with apostolic traditions being broken by the evil opinions of other heresies, had the freedom to publicly profess their wicked beliefs in the East, especially in Constantinople.
Only the freedom of Catholic communion was seen by those who considered themselves religious as being undermined.
Since the pope felt tormented by these serious issues and could not address them as he wished, he appealed to divine judgment, whose protection could not be expected by those who had rashly dared to attack Catholic truth.
Finally, he praised the custom of ancient emperors who, upon taking power or when new leaders of the apostolic see were appointed, immediately sent their writings to show their alliance.
Since Anastasius neglected to do this, he professed himself to be alienated from it; for this reason, the holy pope considered him a rival, a criminal, and an enemy to be avoided.
Furthermore, the holy pope briefly indicated how the emperor also supported the Manicheans, as we will soon explain when discussing the cause of Xenaia.
Xenaias, also known as Philoxenus, was often claimed to be a follower of the Manichaean doctrine.
His identity is clear from both ancient and more recent sources.
When he first traveled from Persia to the Roman Empire, he received significant support from Peter Chnapeus and Emperor Anastasius, which caused considerable turmoil and challenges for the Catholics.
As a result, the bonds of Christian society were severely disrupted, leading to widespread schisms and errors.
Pope Symmachus, in his apology against Emperor Anastasius, indirectly referred to Xenaias, criticizing him as a defender of falsehood with these words:
"It is no surprise that the patrons of the Manichaeans persecute the Catholics, as falsehood inevitably opposes the truth. It is no wonder they are harsh towards the orthodox, as they can align with all heresies and are only friendly with those who do not err."
Before delving into the specifics of this man's cruelty towards the Catholics, we should discuss his homeland, origins, character, and practices.
In doing so, we have consulted the works of the renowned Joseph Assemani's Oriental Library to extract relevant information.
We learn that Xenaias was of Persian origin, from the town of Tahal in the province of Garmaeans, and, according to many ancient writers, he was a slave and lacked divine baptism.
However, Assemani challenges these claims, defending Xenaias against such disgraceful accusations with various arguments.
He asserts that this otherwise notorious man did receive baptism and did not masquerade as an ordained cleric when he traveled from Persia to Syria.
He presents two very important conjectures on this matter.
The first is based on Xenaia's actions, where, before leaving Persia, he actively opposed the teachings of Nestorius, as well as those of Ibas of Edessa and Maris of Persia in the city of the Garmaeans, among others.
These actions don't seem to match someone who was a native and not yet baptized.
The second conjecture is drawn from Xenaia's own writings, where he not only explains the true form of baptism but also repeatedly states that he was baptized and had embraced Christ.
These writings could indeed sway our opinions if we were more inclined to trust the author's authority over the strength of the arguments.
His knowledge and ability to describe the affairs of the Syrians surpass those of others, both before him and among his contemporaries in his nation.
However, I must ask forgiveness from a learned man, who is otherwise very friendly to me, if I suggest that both conjectures, which he insists upon to defend Xenaia's baptism, seem to falter.
Regarding the first conjecture, that in the city of the Garmaeans, Xenaia, along with some others, opposed the Nestorian doctrine, as well as the efforts of Ibas of Edessa and Maris of Persia, what then?
Even if these accounts, which are drawn from entirely uncertain records, were true, could a cunning person who professed the Manichaean sect not have the skill to hide his impiety?
The doctrines of Nestorius and Eutyches directly contradicted one of the principal errors of the Manichaeans.
The Manichaeans denied that Christ was truly human, truly born, truly suffered, and died, and they preached only a shadowy and imaginary flesh in him.
The Nestorian and Eutychian doctrines were very far removed from this error.
The Nestorians taught that there were two true natures in Christ, as well as two persons.
The Eutychians didn't deny Christ's humanity but argued that it was either absorbed into the divine Word's nature or transformed into Divinity.
Although it's clear that Xenaia strongly opposed both heresies, it can't be assumed she was purified by baptism, since she had already associated with the Manichaeans.
I'm not sure if Xenaia could have easily opposed the efforts of Ibas of Edessa and Maris the Persian in the Persian city of the Garmaeans.
It's evident to everyone that those bishops' efforts began after the Council of Ephesus, driven by hostility toward Cyril of Alexandria.
This conflict continued until the assembly at Berytus, as noted in the tenth session of the Council of Chalcedon.
But who proves, or where is it shown, that Xenaia emerged at that time?
In the Acts of the Council of Berytus, convened over Ibas, or in the petitions and writings accusing Ibas of Edessa of various crimes, we don't find the name Xenaia or Philoxenus.
Yet, all the names of Ibas's accusers are listed.
What if, after the Council of Ephesus, which condemned Nestorius, Xenaia came to light?
Would we consider him to have been so mature, authoritative, and knowledgeable that he could have opposed two bishops debating matters of faith?
Certainly, in fulfilling this role, basic faith teachings, typically taught to children, wouldn't have sufficed, as the Nestorian doctrine was a major issue for over 200 bishops.
From the rest of his life's events, we learn that either Xenaia hadn't been born yet or was barely reaching puberty at that time.
Indeed, more than 90 years passed from the Ecumenical Council of Ephesus to Xenaia's death.
Xenaias passed away after the year 522, as noted by Assemani, and the Council of Ephesus took place in 431.
At that time, I doubt this leader of the Manichaeans was even born.
If it's suggested that the efforts of the Nestorians, including Ibas of Edessa and Maris the Persian in the city of Garmaeans, should be dated to a later time, I won't disagree.
However, there's no need to create such a long gap between these events.
We can reasonably propose that Xenaias was born and amassed considerable resources to actively oppose the Nestorian doctrine and its supporters.
Ibas did not continue his efforts until the end of his life.
Instead, after reconciling with Cyril of Alexandria, he withdrew from all heretical activities before 445, as inferred from the synods of Tyre and Berytus.
Therefore, even if we trace Xenaias's birth back from this year or the next, Assemani's earlier assumption would be incorrect.
This so-called monster of heresy and wickedness would have died at 77, which clearly contradicts Assemani's description of him before his death.
He admits that before the end of his life, Xenaias, with the support or order of Emperor Anastasius, presided over many false synods; undertook numerous and lengthy journeys; and was exiled from his position for four years by Emperor Justin's decree.
Moving from place to place, sometimes in Thrace, at Philippopolis; other times in Paphlagonia, at the city of Gangra, where he died from smoke inhalation.
All these events, involving such extensive labor and hardship, make it difficult to believe that such challenges could be endured by someone in extreme old age.
A more significant theory presented by Assemani is to prove that Xenaias was not denied baptism.
First, he refers to Xenaias's own writings, where he attests to his faith and baptism; then he attempts to demonstrate that he was baptized by the Syrian fathers.
In silence, they wouldn't have let Xenaia influence them if they knew he wasn't baptized or properly ordained.
But this justification becomes weaker when we consider the writings of others.
Theodore, a reader from the Church of Constantinople who had met Xenaia and lived during his time, writes not just from hearsay but from the accounts of Syrian bishops:
A Persian named Xenaia, found by Calendio during his priesthood to be corrupting church teachings and causing trouble, was expelled from the area.
I'll talk partly about this from what I've heard from various sources.
After fleeing his master in Persia, he came to the Romans.
Soon after, Peter appointed him as bishop of the Church of the Hierapolitans instead of Cyrus.
Shortly after, bishops from Persia accused him of being a foreigner and not having received divine baptism.
Upon learning this, Peter, unconcerned with what should be done, claimed that consecration by a bishop was enough for the completion of the divine sacrament.
When we carefully examine the validity of this testimony, it's hard to dismiss.
Theodore the reader didn't speak of someone completely unknown or absent to him, whose significant actions weren't well known to both him and the people of Constantinople, especially given the favor Xenaia had with Emperors Zeno and Anastasius of the East.
Theodore thrived around the year 515 AD, so he described history not just from hearsay but from what he saw and heard from others of his time.
Moreover, didn't the Persian bishops protest when they saw Xenaia appointed as bishop of Hierapolis?
The protests indeed came from the Persian bishops: that Xenaia, consecrated as bishop of Hierapolis, was a foreigner and lacked baptism.
If Assemanus believes these sources are unreliable, then what trust, I ask, can Xenaias possibly deserve?
Xenaias faced criticism from his fellow bishops and was accused of being a pagan.
In an attempt to clear his name and avoid losing his episcopal position, he wrote a letter to Zeno about the Incarnation of the Word, where he cleverly and eagerly pretends to have been baptized.
Don't these very words, which Assemanus highlights, reveal Xenaias's true intentions?
In nearly the same sentence, he mentions his baptism two, three, or even four times whenever he gets the chance.
Indeed, he uses the same strategy all deceivers employ, trying to counter just accusations against them by relying solely on their own testimony.
Here are the words of Xenaias that Assemanus quotes:
The Only Begotten Son is one with the Trinity, as He himself indicates when he says to his disciples:
Go and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
So, let us note the writer's method, so I was baptized in the name of Him who died; and I confess that the One in whose name I was baptized died for me; finally, I believe that I have put on Him in whose name and death I was baptized through baptism.
Therefore, it is far from us to consider Xenaias baptized by this method of writing; on the contrary, it leads us to suspect even more that he was without baptism.
For he does not call any witnesses to his baptism, does not name the minister of the sacrament, nor does he specify the place or the time when he put on Christ through baptism, but he makes himself the sole witness and defender of his baptism.
The Acts of the Second Council of Nicaea also show that Xenaias had no other defender besides himself.
In the fifth session, 185th action, when Demetrius the deacon, keeper of the vessels, read the previously praised words of Theodore the reader, none of the three hundred and fifty Fathers dismissed this testimony as fabricated or of doubtful faith, at least for the honor of the episcopate, but they all placed their trust in Theodore who documented it.
Indeed, it was so evident that when Tarasius, a very learned and holy man and the bishop of Constantinople, spoke, all the other bishops declared anathema upon Xenaeas.
He was not baptized, was a Manichaean, and preached illusions while denying the humanity of Christ.
I wonder, therefore, why or how anyone could now clear Xenaeas of these accusations, believing he neither lacked baptism nor joined the Manichaeans.
None of those 350 Fathers hesitated even slightly when proving the soon-to-be-praised testimony of Theodore.
Nevertheless, we should not rely solely on the unique testimony of Theodore the reader and the approval of the Second Council of Nicaea, which Assemanus, with his great diligence and learning, attempts to explain more gently.
We will not hesitate to refer to the pseudo-synod of Antioch convened by Peter the Fuller, as expressed by the author of the synodical book.
This synod was convened by Peter the Fuller upon returning from exile to the Church of Antioch, with Emperor Zeno being hostile to the Catholic bishops and favoring him, around the year 485 AD, as noted by Labbeus, Pagius, Stephanus Baluzius, and others.
At that time, driven by terrible rage, Peter the Fuller marked the Chalcedonian ecumenical synod with anathema and appointed Xenaeas as bishop of Hierapolis.
Xenaeas, a Persian by birth, lacked baptism, was a runaway of servile condition, and was a fierce leader accusing Christians of heresy.
Theophanes indeed spoke about these profane and illegitimate ordinations performed by Peter the Fuller, writing:
"Peter the Fuller, having entered Antioch, committed many wicked deeds, such as the curses of synods, the removal of bishops, the intrusions of the guilty, illegitimate ordinations, and similar things."
Hence, Theophanes, a sharp writer, even though he followed Theodore the reader in recounting various ancient deeds, because he was not far from the age of Xenaeas, by describing illegitimate ordinations, wanted to at least obscurely indicate this servile man, devoid of baptism, being intruded into the bishop's seat of Hierapolis.
Having documented the events between the Romans and Persians up to the year 573, he must have been aware of the actions of Peter Fullo, the Bishop of Antioch, and the bishop unlawfully ordained by him.
So, please don't criticize me for writing about these things or frown because I haven't agreed with a very learned man who has already received much praise for his literary work in this area.
My desire to seek and discover the truth, not a love for arguing, has completely guided my thinking so that I can openly express what I understand with strong religious conviction.
Indeed, I won't stray from this approach as I explain Xenaia's Manichaeism.
Despite this reputation, the distinguished Assemanus did not accuse Xenaia of Mabbug of this, even though he referred to him as a most wicked man.
It's clear from many volumes soon to be reviewed how much Xenaias despised the Manichaean heresy, in which he explicitly refuted the Eutychians and Manichaeans.
First of all, if Xenaias clearly refutes the Manichaeans in his works, why does Theophanes of Byzantium write that Xenaias, also known as Philoxenus, the Bishop of Hierapolis, shared the views of the Manichaeans and was exiled by Justin the Elder?
This took place in the year 518 AD, as the eminent Norisius proves regarding the Epochs of the Syro-Macedonians.
Furthermore, why does the same writer, describing Xenaias' second journey to the royal city of Constantinople, say: Xenaias, a follower of the Manichaeans, also called Philoxenus, was summoned by Anastasius to Byzantium because he shared their views?
Emperor Anastasius not only supported the Manichaeans, as mentioned in the previous apology of Pope Symmachus, but also upheld Manichaean doctrines because he was born to a Manichaean mother.
The Manichaeans and Arians, says Theodorus the Reader, an eyewitness, celebrated the rise of Anastasius.
The Manichaeans, particularly because his mother was a devoted follower of their sect.
If both Xenaias and Emperor Anastasius held the same beliefs, and because of this shared doctrine, the emperor brought the Manichaean Xenaias to Constantinople,
and if Anastasius's mother was a devoted follower of the Manichaean sect, how could we dismiss the credibility of ancient writers who strongly support this, based on some lighter conjectures?
Clearly, our ancestors did not do so.
In the name of Christ, they convened at the Second Council of Nicaea and judged the wicked Xenaias to be a follower and leader of the Manichaeans,
following the testimony of the older writer John Diacrinomenus, who claimed that Xenaias used to hide images depicting Christ in secret places,
suggesting that Christ did not assume true human nature but only a phantasmal and shadowy one, a prominent Manichaean doctrine we have already proven in previous chapters.
I would be remiss if I didn't mention what Assemanus provided to refute this Manichaean taint on Xenaias.
Xenaias wrote a letter to some monks of Syria about the Incarnation of the Word, where he affirmed the truth of both divine and human natures in Christ the Lord.
He presents a summary of this letter, originally in Syriac and divided into five chapters.
In the third chapter, he includes these words translated into Latin:
"If he who was incarnate is God, then he who was born is also God; and just as he who entered the Virgin was a spiritual being, whose spiritual nature is from the Father, so the same one came forth from the Virgin, possessing a true body by nature.
Therefore, the Virgin is rightly called the Mother of God, because she ineffably gave birth to the incarnate person of God."
These statements, and others like them from various letters or writings of Xenaias, as declared by Assemanus, completely oppose the Manichaean heresy.
There's no doubt about the reliability of this writer and translator, especially when it comes to translating monuments from Syriac into Latin.
However, it's questionable whether Xenaias followed his own faith in writing these works.
We can also doubt whether the writings currently attributed to Xenaias actually originated from him, or if they were inserted into the books and manuscripts of the Syrians through the deceit and fabrication of an impostor.
In fact, these writings were completely unknown to Theodore the Reader, Theophanes, Evagrius, the bishops of the Persians, the Fathers of the Second Council of Nicaea, and later writers.
These individuals, not out of baseless fear but convinced by solid reasons, denounced this impostor as the leader and chief of the Manichaeans.
So, it seems very challenging for these writings, if they truly existed, not to have been known by those who described the homeland, condition, morals, institutions, and dignities of this notorious man.
Or if they did exist, perhaps they were hidden away in the archives of the Syrians and kept securely, only to come to public knowledge recently through the efforts and labors of Assemani?
Certainly, Assemani, who took it upon himself to shed light on such works with his observations, doesn't praise even one trustworthy writer who attributes these works to Xenaias.
And although he sometimes calls upon witnesses, he criticizes, mocks, and condemns them as Eutychians and Monophysites.
Moreover, with the testimonies and consensus of the aforementioned writers now lacking, shouldn't there have been efforts to find responses that align with Xenaias' letters?
He wrote to Emperor Zeno and to monks of various monasteries.
Where, I ask, are the responses from all of these, so we might examine whether they agree with him or if they contain any indication of fabrication to scholars?
When I found myself in such a predicament, I was highly suspicious that those works attributed to Xenaias had been falsely ascribed to him by some deceiver.
This suspicion was shared by the distinguished.
.
Assemani's approach to handling these major challenges, which he could barely avoid, led him to suggest that Xenaias either created or planned to create some fiction under Xenaias' name.
An example of such fabrication is the claim that Nestorius, the heresiarch, was called by Saint Leo the Pope to the Council of Chalcedon.
Xenaias mentions this in a letter to the monks of Senones, and Assemani, after considering its arguments, noted that it should be dismissed as a baseless fabrication.
Before Saint Leo the Great took the papal office of the Catholic Church, Nestorius had already been banished to a fourth place of exile and passed away in the year 436, with some saying his tongue was consumed by worms; or he lived in an oasis until 439, as Socrates claimed.
Saint Leo the Great, however, became pope only in the following year, 440, on July 28.
He planned for the council to be held at Chalcedon in 450, and it was finally held the next year, as both sacred and secular records show.
Assemani points out this obvious mistake and, being uncertain, does not know whether to attribute it to Xenaias or some Monophysite who sought Xenaias as a patron.
Thus, the learned Assemani did not consider such writings credible enough to fully believe that this person rejected the errors of the Manichaeans.
He also found some expressions from Xenaias suggesting a heretical Manichaean meaning.
Among these is the well-known claim by an Eastern writer from a theological book called "Rays"; supposedly, Philoxenus acknowledges the passions of the Lord as voluntary, not natural.
Moses Bar Kepha also notes that the body of Adam, before he sinned, was assumed by the Lord.
Finally, in the history of Mar Barsuma, it is said that the body of our Lord is not like a human body.
Who doesn't see that all these expressions reek of Manichaeism and contain the Manichaean's mythical fabrications?
Even though the author of the books doesn't attribute all of them to Xenaia or Philoxenus, our previous writings clearly show that each originated from the wicked workshop of Manes.
Assemanus himself confirms that Philoxenus's statement indicates Manichaeism, specifically the voluntary sufferings of the Lord.
He argues that this gave the writers we have reviewed the chance to accuse Xenaia of this heresy.
However, the learned man believes that Philoxenus either fell into the error of the Incorruptibles, which stems from Manichaean principles, or, due to a tendency for inconsistency often found in heretics, he adopted certain Manichaean beliefs, despite frequently denouncing them in his own writings.
Therefore, whatever the case may be, according to Assemanus, even Xenaia himself cannot be entirely cleared of the stain of Manichaeism.
Nor can the works attributed to him and circulated under his name be free from fabrications, alterations, and interpolations.
So, on what foundation should we judge his faith, aside from the testimonies of ancient and later writers?
Relying on the praised writings leads us into the risk of error, as it's unclear whether those volumes came from the true workshop of Xenaia, whether he followed his own faith in composing them, or whether they were altered by others to conceal or erase the mark of Manichaeism that ancient writers and the Fathers of the Seventh Council had branded upon him.
However, I realize I've spent more time on these matters than is appropriate, especially since I cannot examine or interpret the monuments written in the Syriac language, which should undoubtedly be essential for anyone wishing to bring such a case to a conclusion.
Therefore, leaving aside this manner of discussion, we add just one more point: nearly the whole East was tainted by the Manichaean stain through the efforts of Emperor Anastasius and the Acephali.
To clarify and simplify things, we're wrapping up our discussion on the history of the Manicheans.
The remaining details about this notorious heresy, which later spread among the Armenians due to the zeal of the Paulicians, have been thoroughly covered by Peter the Sicilian and Photius.
Chapter Fourteen
Pope Hormisdas expelled the Manichaeans who were still residing in Rome through investigation and punishment.
Beausobre's minor arguments are dismissed.
The Synod of Patriarch Mennas in Constantinople condemns Severus, Anthimus, and other leaders of the Acephali for supporting Manichaean doctrine.
Finally, some notes are shared about the Manichaeans from the historical works of Peter the Siculus and Photius.
Before we delve into the actions taken by the Eastern bishops regarding the Manichaeans, it is necessary to briefly outline Pope Hormisdas's approach and judgment towards these heretics.
Upon discovering this troublesome group hiding in Rome, he made every effort to completely eradicate them.
In the year 514, while Anastasius was emperor, Pope Symmachus passed away.
Ecclesiastical records indicate that Hormisdas was appointed in Rome that same year.
It's unclear whether remnants of the Manichaean sect remained from Pope Symmachus's previous inquiries or if they arrived in Rome in the years following his death from regions like Africa, the East, or Italy.
However, if we follow the order of the Pontifical books, which outline the deeds of the Roman bishops, it seems Hormisdas discovered the Manichaeans in Rome after many years in his papacy.
During the first four years of his rule, the supreme pontiff focused on guiding Emperor Anastasius, who supported many heresies, back to the right path.
Despite sending envoys to Constantinople for this purpose and writing one hundred eighty-nine letters, his efforts were continually thwarted until the emperor was struck by a divine blow and died miserably.
When the deeply religious ruler Justin took control of the empire, he accomplished what Hormisdas had long desired in the year 519.
Envoys were sent to Constantinople, including the very holy man, Germanus, bishop of Capua.
Once peace was restored between the Eastern churches and the Roman See, along with the condemnation of the memories of Acacius, Euphemius, and Macedonius, as well as the emperors Zeno and Anastasius, Hormisdas finally expelled the Manichean descendants from the city.
If we believe the author of the Liber Pontificalis followed the sequence of events accurately when describing Pope Hormisdas' deeds, we can affirm that this judgment against the Manicheans took place after the year 519.
However, setting aside this somewhat unclear and uncertain question, let's focus on Hormisdas' actions against the Manicheans.
According to the esteemed writer, Hormisdas discovered the Manicheans and, after examining them and their wounds, exiled them.
This represents a new form of ecclesiastical judgment applied by Hormisdas against the Manicheans, as described by the author.
Before this pope's time, there is no record of heretics being examined with wounds by ecclesiastical authority.
Although emperors and secular judges had long decreed various punishments to eliminate this group, either by confiscating their property or forcing them into exile stripped of all human rights, there is no understanding that anyone had decreed they should be afflicted with wounds and beatings.
However, it is believed that it was carried out under public secular authority to ensure that the laws of leniency, to which church leaders adhered most sacredly, were not violated.
Additionally, after all the books and writings of the Manicheans were gathered, the supreme pontiff, following the example of his predecessors, burned them in front of the doors of the Constantinian basilica.
Such fear and terror were instilled in the minds of these wicked people that they did not consider returning to the city from exile.
The actions of Hormisdas, Symmachus, Gelasius, Leo, and other Roman popes in burning the books of the Manichaeans were not entirely approved by non-Catholic figures.
Isaac Beausobre, in his writings on the History of Manichaeism, argues that this approach was particularly neither useful nor safe.
He examined various laws from emperors and magistrates regarding the destruction and elimination of heretical or Christian books.
Beausobre defends these laws as reasonable, mainly because such books contained content that corrupted religious devotion and human society, which we discussed clearly in Chapter 4 of this book.
Now, setting aside Beausobre's viewpoints and commentaries, let's begin to explore other Manichaean customs, worship practices, and church governance from the Constantinopolitan synods.
One of these synods dates back to the time of Hormisdas, and another to the era of Agapetus, as we will demonstrate using the most reliable documents.
It is well established for those who have reviewed their Acts that these synods, alongside individuals like Severus, Anthimus, Zoaras, Philoxenus, and others known as the Acephali, were condemned as defenders of Manichaean doctrines by the unanimous consensus of the Fathers.
Therefore, in reviewing these Acts, we have concluded without any doubt that teachers of Manichaean rites attempted to disguise themselves under the name of the Acephali.
To avoid appearing as if I'm telling untruths, I will first recount what the impious emperor Anastasius did to spread his heresy.
Specifically, he brought Xenia to Constantinople and welcomed Severus, a notorious individual, along with two hundred monks who accompanied him, with honor.
As Petavius notes, this marked the beginning of Severus's unclean influence, who in the year 513 forcibly took over the Antioch seat, from which Flavian had been expelled the previous year due to his steadfastness in the Catholic faith, and tried to persuade all the Easterners to condemn the Council of Chalcedon, while expelling the Catholic bishops who resisted from their seats.
Let's take a moment to understand who Severus was, where he came from, and his early religious training.
This background is important for those following our current exploration.
Severus was born in Sozopolis, a city in the province of Pisidia.
As he grew up, Evagrius, Nicephorus, and Deacon Liberatus tell us that he was involved in business in Berytus, a city in Cilicia, while adhering to pagan customs and rites.
Later on, after leaving his legal studies, he was baptized in the church dedicated to the revered martyr Leontius in Tripoli, Phoenicia, and immediately embraced monastic life in a place between the city of Gaza and the town of Maiuma.
A document read at the Synod of Menas in Constantinople revealed that from an early age, he was involved in sorcery and, before his baptism, worshiped demons in the city of the Berytians.
This leads us to suspect he may have only pretended to be drawn to baptism to escape the legal penalties for sacrilegious sorcery.
This suspicion is strengthened by his flight from Berytus to seek refuge in Tripoli.
Our theory is supported by the fact that Severus, unable to suppress his wickedness under the guise of the Catholic religion and unable to return clearly to his previous pagan beliefs, chose a different path to achieve his aims.
Fearing punishment, he avoided openly returning to pagan rites.
Instead, he crafted new deceptions, attempting to conceal his Manichaean beliefs under the doctrines of the Acephali, to continue pursuing the rites and mysteries of Manes more diligently.
It's not surprising that after being rejected by the Church and by Severus, who had baptized him, he quickly went to Constantinople to see Emperor Anastasius, the supporter and defender of the most wicked people.
The emperor welcomed him warmly and with great honor, along with 200 monks.
With such powerful support, and after being elevated to the Antioch or Theopolis seat, he ordered many violent attacks against Catholic priests and abbots who strongly opposed his illegitimate and canonically unlawful ordination.
He also desecrated houses of God and churches, consecrated with solemn rites and mysteries, with the blood of the slain, calling them hostels of heresy and impiety, and rejected the baptism he had once received.
Moreover, as the religious monks mention in their praised booklet, it became clear from subsequent events that Severus did not sincerely adhere to the Acephali but only pretended to follow their religion.
They first note that he did not accept the union of two natures in Christ, as they claim, but only a new one, calling it divisive and condemning it in his writings.
Although this language may seem difficult to understand, it implies that the divine Word did not assume true humanity or unite with it.
He also refused to associate with Peter Mongus, who had been placed in the Alexandrian seat due to the Acephali's leadership, or with those misled and taught by Peter, believing Peter should be removed from the Alexandrian Church.
For this reason, he wanted the names of Peter Mongus and those who communicated with him to be erased from the diptychs of the Theopolis Church.
Consequently, by causing new disturbances almost daily, he tried to overthrow and destroy not only the Catholic religion but also the religion of the Acephali and its followers.
Then, after teaming up with a certain Peter, known as the Iberian, who unlawfully took the episcopal throne of Apamea, they plotted the complete destruction of the city of Alexandria.
They created divisions among the Alexandrians, inciting the people against each other, which led to civil wars.
Many houses were set on fire, and much blood was shed.
They barely escaped the rightful punishment for these acts by fleeing.
From these events, the monks wisely concluded in their book that Severus and Peter the Iberian, or the one from Apamea, were never true followers of the Christian religion.
They seemed equally hostile to both Catholics and heretics.
Since they dared to unjustly anathematize the entire Church, they were rightly anathematized by the Church as a whole.
Indeed, the universal condemnation they faced, and the horror everyone felt towards their way of life, stemmed from their cruel and savage actions in seeking the death and destruction of Jesus Christ's followers.
By breaking and abolishing all sacred and divine laws, they handed over priests and other ministers of the Church, who served in temples and at altars, to violent deaths, suffocating them with their own hands.
They harassed devout monks with chains and prisons, aiming to plunder all the monasteries' goods and slaughtered them with swords and weapons.
When they traveled, they invaded the venerable cloisters of Saint Simeon, attacking honorable monks with a gathered crowd of Jewish thieves, showing no respect for their gray hair.
They killed around 350 of them, leaving their bodies scattered along the road without burial or sparing their huts.
All these actions, I say, though they reveal a cruel, savage, and ferocious spirit far removed from piety and religion, would not expose their Manichaean principles unless one considered the aim of their actions.
What were Severus and Peter Iberus considering when they carried out these immense massacres?
They were offering bloody sacrifices to the demons they served, a ritual known to be used by the Manichaeans.
Moreover, Severus and Peter engaged in other superstitious and magical rituals.
Just like the pagan soothsayers, their profane and false priests would lay hands for suffocation and speak words of invocation over the living as if they were dead.
This wasn't from divine grace, but rather speaking out of their stomachs and of the earth.
They aimed to overthrow and devastate God's Churches, the mystical sacraments, and the mysteries of our faith, establishing new gatherings and contrary baptisms.
They boldly and shamelessly stole Christian souls for money, for glory, and for carnal pleasures.
When entering homes, they led away captive the souls of men and women who were not firm, corrupting them not only with evil doctrines regarding the soul but also physically.
The account of these and similar actions had long been sent to Hormisdas, the bishop of the Roman and apostolic see.
It is proven through multiple records that the highest pontiff issued a sentence of deposition and anathema against these same heretics.
The respected assembly of abbots and monks from the monasteries of Saint Dalmatius, Jerusalem, Second Syria, Mount Sinai, and the three Palestines declared that they earnestly demanded nothing else but that these wicked men be considered and punished as Manichaeans.
Indeed, the holy pontiff Hormisdas acted against them as followers of the Manichaean doctrine.
This is clearly shown in his letter to the priests, deacons, abbots of Second Syria, and the other orthodox living in any Eastern region and remaining in communion with the apostolic see.
Hormisdas, speaking from the apostolic throne of Peter, states that the heresies spreading throughout the East have either stemmed from the impure teachings of Photinus or Mani.
He points out that these misguided doctrines have been further spread through the efforts of Severus of Antioch, Xenaias of Hierapolis, Cyrus of Edessa, and Peter of Apamea.
These individuals, deeply entangled in wicked superstitions, have tainted the episcopal thrones with numerous crimes.
To prevent priests, deacons, archimandrites of Second Syria, and other Eastern Orthodox members from being misled by profane rites, the supreme pontiff firmly instructs them to reject anything that goes against the rules of the Fathers, especially those coming from certain false commentaries.
"Let no one," he insists, "disturb you with inappropriate commands or new practices. For if they are worldly, they cannot sustain the Churches, since it is more appropriate for them to learn than to teach."
And finally, possibly alluding to Manichaean offerings, he adds: "It is wrong to bring foreign offerings to pious altars, because God has set specific boundaries for religious practices, even from the very beginnings of His worship."
Alongside these credible records of faith, which reveal Severus, Peter of Apamea, Zoaras, and others as followers of Manichaean rites and doctrines, there is another petition from the clerics and monks of Antioch to John, the bishop of Constantinople.
In this petition, not only are the previously mentioned crimes detailed, but many others that could only be attributed to the followers of Mani. For instance, Severus borrowed practices from the Jews, such as when, during the widespread slaughter of Christians, he allowed the bodies of the holy Syrian martyr monks to be consumed by dogs and birds. Additionally, he performed sorcery at the springs in Daphne, worshiping demons with wicked sacrifices, and showed no respect for sacred altars or vessels, breaking some and melting others to spend the money, bronze, and silver for entirely wicked and profane purposes.
He took silver cups and golden doves shaped like the Holy Spirit, which hung over holy washbasins and altars, arguing that the Holy Spirit should not be represented as a dove.
Who would deny that this kind of teaching was rooted in one of the main doctrines of Mani?
They strongly rejected the idea that God could take on a physical form.
As a result, he taught that the Word did not take on true human flesh, nor did the Holy Spirit appear in a visible, bodily form.
To challenge these core points of the Christian faith, they destroyed images of Christ, the Holy Spirit, and the angels, attempting to erase them everywhere.
These were indeed the principles of Manichaean philosophy and theology, and even the non-Catholic man Beausobre could not deny it.
Although he indulges too much in his own biases while writing the history of the Manichaeans, aiming to provoke the Catholics, scorning and mocking the opinions of the ancient holy Fathers of the Church and writers, taunting Catholics with disputes and insults, and ultimately, trying to refute or distort the main doctrines of our faith with incorrect interpretations from Lutherans, Calvinists, and Socinians; yet in his eighth book, he attributed to Mani and his followers the actions we described regarding Severus, Zoara, and others.
However, concerning Severus, Zoara, and others who attempted to disguise Manichaean impiety as Acephali in the sixth century of the Church, Beausobre did not mention a word, as his focus and writing extend only to Mani and his initial associates and their equally profane teachings, neglecting those places and authors where that heresy flourished, whose efforts helped it spread far and wide over time.
So, if you take a closer look at the author's intentions, it's clear that he didn't aim to write an unbiased historical and critical work about the Manicheans.
Instead, he wanted to attack Catholics and criticize the most holy and ancient Fathers who bravely opposed this wicked sect.
He decided to accuse them of ignorance and errors, as we've already mentioned earlier.
To keep the flow and order of our history intact without delving into Beausobre's wrongdoings, let's present the new statements from the Eastern Orthodox bishops against Severus, Anthimus, and other Acephali.
These statements will make it clear that we didn't fabricate anything in the matter we're discussing out of self-interest, nor did we rely solely on conjectures.
We aimed to investigate and draw the truth from the most reliable sources.
So, forty-seven Orthodox bishops from the East, either in person or through their representatives, submitted a petition to Pope Agapetus of Rome, who had been summoned to Constantinople.
In this petition, they not only testified against the criminal acts of Severus described so far, but also demanded that he be condemned as a wicked supporter and defender of the Manichaean doctrine.
They said, "We implore you, most holy one... we cry out: Help us and the holy souls, whom you must wisely consider as present, and show that they were handed over to death for Christ by a beast with many heads, so that he cannot again, through his evident deceit and Manichaean error, which he boldly dared to bring into the pure royal halls."
The esteemed bishops reached this conclusion not for any other reason but because, after carefully examining Severus's morals and teachings, they diligently inquired which sect he should be declared a supporter and defender of.
Indeed, ever since it was revealed that he shared the same views as the pagans, pretended to agree with Eutyches, and sometimes followed Nestorius's ways, he was rightly and truthfully called both the tool of the devil and a Manichaean.
Therefore, no one should falsely claim that the esteemed bishops of the East improperly judged Severus's doctrines or errors, especially since their judgment was based not on uncertain rumors but on well-established and known facts.
Furthermore, from the principles of Manichaean philosophy and theology, they denied the true birth of our Lord Christ from the Virgin, his true flesh, and death.
Severus himself, along with Peter of Apamea, Zoaras, and Isaac the Persian, devoted themselves diligently to the study and practice of magic.
Beausobre explained in various places that Manichaeans were known to engage in such superstitions.
Regarding Zoaras, we read in the esteemed book that he disregarded divine Scripture, all sacred orders, and the mass.
Moreover, with great audacity, he undermined all true and sacred ecclesiastical rites through secret gatherings and false baptisms, which he conducted daily.
His synagogue, as the esteemed bishops of the East wrote to Agapetus, was filled with women devoted to feasting, drunkenness, luxury, and adultery.
The most holy bishops of the East made every effort to repel these evils from the Church's embrace, bravely presenting themselves before the emperor and earnestly pleading with him not to allow bloodthirsty beasts to be gathered with the lambs.
Otherwise, as the religion of Christ would gradually be corrupted and weakened throughout the East, honor, justice, holiness, and true worship of God would be led to ruin.
Isaac the Persian, who came to the East and joined those other wicked men, was discovered to have committed even graver crimes.
When the orthodox bishops were about to speak to Agapetus about this man, they couldn't hold back their tears and lamentations, nor could they adequately express in words the wicked acts he dared to commit.
They recount one of his crimes, which they testify as especially detestable.
Specifically, they say that when he visited an inn with an image of the most pious Emperor Justinian, this wicked and arrogant man blasphemed against God, seemingly competing to do so in a novel manner.
It is clear that this Persian devised a unique form of blasphemy against God and spoke the preceding words.
However, we couldn't determine exactly what it was from this account or any other source, especially since those Fathers, continuing their narrative, immediately add:
Extending a staff, which he pretended to use to support his dishonored old age, he deceitfully performed in front of those he had misled, striking without mercy the likeness of the Christ-loving emperor.
He called the emperor a heretic united with God, protected by Him, and a guardian of the truth of preaching.
They assert that Isaac persisted in this madness until he tore apart the tunic with the noble image and kept a part for himself, which he consigned to the fire; but he couldn't destroy it all.
We also suspect that along with the emperor's image, there was a depiction of Christ the Lord.
For in the subsequent part of the discourse, they add: It was preserved by the better providence of the divine, as a clear and known rebuke of murderous recklessness.
These things we have either copied or explained concerning Isaac the Persian and others, we believe to be a clear exposure of Manichaean customs, practices, and their nefarious religion, beyond any shadow of doubt.
We are particularly intrigued by the belief that the Manicheans dismantled, destroyed, and rejected temples, altars, sacrifices, images, and other elements that symbolized the true human nature of Christ.
In certain areas, they would gather in synagogues or meeting places with their disreputable women only at night to present certain profane offerings to God.
Beausobre explored their customs in more detail, aiming to assert that some of these practices aligned entirely with the original Christian religion, rites, discipline, and doctrines, suggesting that the Manicheans sought to emulate the apostolic men in every way.
Seriously?
He claims that the early Church Fathers shared the same views as the Manicheans.
Specifically, he argues that they taught Christians should only offer pure prayers to God, and he boldly references Tertullian and Clement of Alexandria, suggesting that the early followers of Christ did not accept temples, altars, or images, rejecting them to avoid appearing to follow pagan religion.
However, evidence from the same Church Fathers he cites shows that Beausobre's assertions are baseless and entirely fabricated.
Tertullian, for instance, while he refers to pure prayers of the heart as sacrifices in a broad sense in his book addressed to Scapula, which Beausobre praises, he also frequently mentions the sacrifice of the Mass, the priesthood of the Church, and the altars and temples of Christians.
Particularly in his works on the Exhortation to Chastity, Monogamy, the Resurrection of the Flesh, and others; he not only praises but also details the dignity of the priests and the ceremonies by which ministers of the altar are consecrated.
Beausobre similarly misleads by craftily citing Clement of Alexandria in Book One of the Stromata, Chapter Seven.
Even though he praises the offering of pure prayers, he never denies the unbloody sacrifice of the body and blood of Christ, nor the Christian temples or altars.
We could explain this with numerous excerpts from his works if our writing purpose did not prevent it.
Therefore, having noted Beausobre's similar deceits, we will briefly recount what needs to be said specifically about Anthimus.
Anthimus, along with his associates, first stormed into the city of Constantinople, setting up profane altars and foreign baptisteries opposite the true altar and holy font in many well-known places of the city, its suburbs, and even in his own home, constantly committing injustices there.
A monk named Marianus testified in his petition to Emperor Justinian, along with the archimandrites of the Monastery of Saint Dalmatius and other monks and archimandrites of the monasteries of the royal city of Constantinople, Jerusalem, Mount Sinai, and Second Syria, that Anthimus had done these things in Constantinople with the common effort of Severus, Peter the Iberian, Zoaras, and Isaac the Persian.
He specifically added that Anthimus had abandoned his native Church of Trebizond, where he had been ordained as bishop, for a long time against divine and ecclesiastical laws and had held secret meetings with heretics under the guise of false continence, aiming to seize the seat of Constantinople with their support against all ecclesiastical canons and laws.
All orthodox men were horrified by this violent and unjust promotion of Anthimus to the throne of Constantinople, both because the legitimate sacraments of the Catholic Church were being undermined and because they were forced to endure great hardships.
Let us consider what the emperor decided in such a great crisis of ecclesiastical matters.
For after hearing all the charges against Anthimus, he did not wish to take action against him.
However, the wise leader, mindful of the church's rights and the priests' immunity, sought a canonical judgment from the Roman Pope against Anthimus and his associates.
He was convinced that he should not interfere in ecclesiastical matters.
Thus, guided by the universal Church's pastor, he learned that the judgment should adhere to the precepts of both Testaments, namely, Ask your father, and he will tell you; your elders, and they will say to you, or another, Obey your leaders, and be submissive, for they watch over your souls as those who will give an account.
The crimes committed by Anthimus and his associates, as long demanded by the authors of the praised pamphlet along with the Palestinian bishops and other Eastern prelates, were to be reviewed and judged by Pope Agapetus.
He wanted it to be sanctioned by sacred imperial law.
Indeed, Anthimus was condemned and stripped of all priestly honor by none other than the Roman Pope Agapetus himself.
When the holy pope traveled to Constantinople, he witnessed the impiety of the crimes and confirmed them fully.
He removed Anthimus from his position, declared him a heretic, and stripped him of all dignity, sacred office, and the title of orthodox and bishop, which Anthimus greatly boasted about, completely erasing him from the list of sacred ministers.
To successfully conclude this sentence of the apostolic see, without any contradiction or obstacle, Agapetus entrusted its execution to Justinian Augustus, as the defender of the sacred canons.
The authors of this praised pamphlet earnestly requested, saying: We implore your empire, not to disregard the just judgment of the aforementioned holy man, but to carry it out, and to free the Church of God and the whole world from the plague of Anthimus and the aforementioned heretics.
For with the holy man Agapetus called from this present life, after God, we looked to your piety to receive this end from you.
The role that the highly praised and devout ruler of the time should have played in the eradication of the heretics is immediately clarified with these words:
By enforcing what was rightfully and canonically decided by him, and endorsing it with your general approval while prohibiting such actions in the future, you honor his blessed soul.
In this context, it is clearly demonstrated from genuine sources that the leaders of the Acephali were engaged in the customs and rituals of the Manichaeans.
However, as we examine the Acts of the Council of Menas in Constantinople, we come across other points that not only address the current issue but also thoroughly refute the absurdities noted by Beausobre in earlier sections.
Therefore, our purpose in writing suggests that we present these details so it doesn't appear as though we have overlooked them.
These issues mainly concern Peter the Iberian, bishop of Apamea, about whom we have mentioned various aspects in the previous sections.
It is widely acknowledged by the clergy of the Holy Church of the Metropolis of Apamea that he was a proponent and advocate of all Manichaean doctrines and rituals, and that he completely disrupted the sacred and divine governance of the churches of Syria.
Our approach doesn't allow us to cover everything the clergy of Apamea praised in their letter to the most holy Fathers and bishops of Second Syria about such a wicked man.
Nor can we now discuss how Peter gained the throne of Apamea, the means he used, or the support he had.
We won't delve into the cunning schemes he employed to erase the memories of orthodox bishops of the East from the sacred diptychs, nor the plundering that repurposed sacred vessels, church funds, and furnishings for profane use.
We also won't discuss the forceful ordinations he used to sideline humble and opposing clerics, who were guardians of these matters, by promoting them to higher ministries.
He even boldly claimed with sacrilegious words that not even Jesus Christ crucified could save them from his grasp.
We have decided to remain silent on these issues and others like them, as they can easily be examined by anyone in the Acts of the Councils.
Instead, we'll only focus on those actions that clearly indicate Manichaean behaviors.
For example, the acts by which he undermined sacred baptism by introducing unworthy female impurity to the holy font and placing it beside the sacred font.
And when the divine mysteries, as the praised clergy say, are concluded in the oratory of the house of the Mother of God, the unworthy speech he makes, which Christians have had to endure, reflects such impiety both spoken and enacted.
All these things are said to have originated from the school of the Manichaeans, according to Photius.
Speaking about their gatherings and assemblies, he notes they used to call their meeting places "proseuchas" or oratories. He adds: Even though they reject the saving baptism, they pretend to accept it, subtly hinting at the Gospel's words of baptism.
Indeed, they claim that the Lord said: I am the living water.
A little further down, in explaining how some people suffering from physical illnesses would sometimes ask to be washed with baptism, he says: "They foolishly believe that the cross and baptism benefit the body, when in reality, they are people unworthy of any help or assistance. They think that these sacraments have no power or effect, neither for the cleansing of the soul nor for any other benefit." Since we have clear evidence from the Acts of that synod that Severus, Anthimus, Zoaras, and others hiding under the name of the Acephaloi engaged in such corrupt practices and customs; that they defiled all the sacred mysteries with profane rites and sacrilege, that they declared war against holy images and the sign of the cross, breaking them and trampling them underfoot who can deny that they were Manicheans? Indeed, they were condemned as Manicheans, both by Pope Hormisdas and by another Constantinopolitan synod under Mennas. This is clearly shown in their letters and official records, which any diligent scholar can easily examine. Having now completed this first part of our Exercitationsconcerning the history of the Manicheans, it would be fitting for us to discuss the sects of the Paulicians, Bogomils, Waldensians, and other heretics who absorbed the teachings of Mani and followed his doctrines and practices. However, since Peter Siculus, Photius, and Christophorus Wolfius have already treated these sects in an orderly and methodical way, we have instead decided to describe the heresies of the Priscillianists, Pelagians, and Eutychians, which were opposed and rejected by the great Pope Leo. We have especially chosen this path because we are already weary of having written the previous two books at such great length. We recognize that, in our previous way of arguing, we wandered into certain questions that may not seem relevant to the purpose and title of this work; at least not to those who are accustomed to judging us with less kindness and fairness.
Who isn't aware that even the most educated individuals, when discussing literary topics, often struggled to restrain themselves when dealing with those constantly proposing new systems?
These people attempted to undermine or abolish sacred religion, church governance, and apostolic discipline.
It was challenging for them to disentangle themselves from the objections, mockeries, and deceptive arguments of these individuals.
This was especially true when they faced questions from non-Catholics and schismatics, which couldn't be resolved by the testimony of just one or two Holy Fathers.
It's not surprising, then, that when explaining the actions of the Holy Pontiff, we sometimes needed to refer back to the origins and institutions of things or highlight the previous practices and customs of the Church.
This was to clearly show that Saint Leo the Great stayed within the boundaries of ecclesiastical matters, didn't try to enhance his own status by ignoring or removing the prerogatives of bishops from other churches, and wasn't motivated by ambition or undue harshness to constrain the enemies of the Apostolic See and the Christian religion.
We have thus far defended him against such accusations from Beausobre, Quesnell, and others.
We plan to continue this defense in upcoming Exercises.
Since the three theological points concerning Manichaean history were deemed relevant to public discussions in the pontifical councils at the Academy of our most holy lord Benedict the Fourteenth in past years, we have decided to include this Exercise, considered an appendix to the previous ones, in this work for the esteemed and especially illustrious and reverend Lord Nicolaus Antonelli, secretary of the Holy Consistory and the aforementioned Academy.
We hope that our work, though modest, will be appreciated by readers,
as it presents the ecclesiastical rules of the Council of Gangra against Manichaean doctrines.
The summary, purpose, and reasoning of these rules, or canons, were explained by the most distinguished and learned men in the year of our Lord seventeen forty-three at the papal court,
and were adorned with the most learned observations, as we have mentioned.