The Council of Rheims was presided over by Hervaeus.
During this council, a curse was pronounced on those who killed Archbishop Fulco, on the day before the Nones of July, in the year 900.
From Labb.
Concil.
vol.
nine, col.
481.
In the year 900 of the Lord's incarnation, on the day before the Nones of July, specifically the first day when Hervaeus was ordained as bishop in the archbishopric of Rheims, the following excommunication was read in the Church of Saint Mary of Rheims, in the presence of the bishops listed below.
Hervaeus, undeservedly called the Archbishop of Rheims and servant of the people of God, Vito, Archbishop of Rouen, Riculfus, Bishop of Soissons, Hetlo, Bishop of Noyon, Dodilo, Bishop of Cambrai, Herinandus, Bishop of Thérouanne, Otgarius, Bishop of Amiens, Honoratus, Bishop of Beauvais, Mancio, Bishop of Châlons, Rodulfus, Bishop of Laon, Otfridus, Bishop of Senlis, Angelrannus, Bishop of Meaux.
Let it be known to all the faithful of the holy Church of God everywhere, both clergy and laypeople, that we and the entire Church entrusted to us are greatly disturbed by excessive sadness, for an event unheard of since the persecution of the apostles and their successors, namely the murder of our father and pastor Fulco, wickedly carried out by impious men.
He tirelessly labored day and night for the benefit of the kingdom and the state of the whole holy Church, putting himself forward as a protective wall for the defense of all the churches in this kingdom, as their possessions were being seized by Count Baldwin, son of Baldwin and Judith, against all divine and human law.
Therefore, by the men of this Baldwin, Vineemar, Evarard, and Rotfeld, along with their accomplices, he was cruelly slain.
Because of his death, the entire order and procession of the Church is rightly saddened and emits laments of compassion from the deepest sighs of their hearts.
Since they dared to commit such a crime in our times, something previously unheard of in the Church except perhaps by pagans, in the name of the Lord, through the power of the Holy Spirit, and by the authority given to bishops through blessed Peter, the chief of the apostles, we separate them from the embrace of the holy mother Church and condemn them to a perpetual curse and anathema.
They shall never be restored by any human means, nor have any interaction among Christians.
May they be cursed in the city, cursed in the field, cursed be their barns and their remnants, cursed be the fruits of their wombs and the fruits of their land, their cattle, and their sheep.
Cursed shall they be when they enter and when they leave, and may they be cursed in their homes and fugitives in the fields.
May their insides spill out like the treacherous and unfortunate Arius; may all those curses come upon them that the Lord threatened through Moses against those who broke the divine law.
May they be anathema maranatha, and perish at the second coming of the Lord.
Furthermore, let all the curses declared by the sacred canons and the decrees of the apostolic men against murderers and sacrilegious people apply to them.
For we mark them with the name of sacrilegious people, who dared to lay hands on this Christ of the Lord.
May all divine judgment be heaped upon them, leading to their everlasting destruction.
Therefore, let no Christian even say "Hello" to them. Let no priest ever celebrate mass in their presence, nor, if they become sick, receive their confessions, or presume to give them holy communion unless they repent, even at the end of their lives. But let them be buried with the burial of a donkey, and be on the manure heap on the face of the earth, so that they may be an example of disgrace and curse to the present and future generations. And just as these lamps are extinguished from our hands today, may their lamp be extinguished forever.