Dissertation on the Charter of Louis the Pious
Among the ancient documents, none has surfaced more often than the charter of Louis the Pious.
Notably, Baronius, using the best Vatican manuscripts, and in our time, the most eminent Antonellus, who was the superintendent of the archive of the Mausoleum of Hadrian, published it very accurately from a copy of that same archive, since the original has been lost.
The nature of my work requires that I also bring this precious document to light.
Therefore, since I have a very old example from the Albinian manuscript, which does not differ much from the copy of the Mausoleum of Hadrian, I will present it with the varying readings of that same copy.
I believe that both were similarly recorded by Cencio in the Book of Taxes, as Panvinius, in whose time this genuine book existed in the Vatican library, mentions in the catalog of privileges of the Holy See (Vatican Codex 3924), where he lists the Louis charter (page 45): Extracted from the Book of Taxes of the Roman Church, folio 110.
He then provides the beginning of the Charter: Privilege of Emperor Louis confirming the regal rights to Pope Paschal.
In the name of the Lord God Almighty, Father, Son, and Holy Spirit.
I, Louis.
This is the exact wording of the Albinian manuscript, except that the name Louis is expressed with a double "w," which, along with other words in the charter, reflects the style of the ninth century when the document was created.
From this, we can infer that Albinus took great care in copying ancient documents, and that the Louis privilege was taken from the original document, from the authentic codex of the Lateran archive.
The author of the codex is the same witness to the matter, as I noted in the preface to the first volume (number 25).
Indeed, no one should be given more credence than Albinus and Cencio, each of whom examined the Lateran archive.
When the genuine Codex of Cencius was stolen from the Vatican Library after Panvinius's time, I am certain of this because no codex at the Holy See matches the number of pages cited by Panvinius.
I present this notable monument from Albinus because Cencius is both older and wrote his codex by hand.
I must add something that the integrity and chastity of history require: Albinus had another old copy of the document at his disposal, and he included its title with the first one.
The title reads: "And the pact of the constitutions of the Emperors Louis the First, Otto the First, and Henry the First with the Roman Pontiffs." After the complete privilege, the codex continues with another privilege of Otto the First and Henry the First. It then lists Otto's privilege, omitting what Otto took from Louis's document and confirmed. Finally, it states: "From the privilege of Emperor Henry," including only what pertains to Henry's donation and omitting the rest.
Therefore, unless I am mistaken, a very similar copy was made, which Dominicus Georgius found in Codex Vaticanus 1984, from the time of Gelasius and Callixtus the Second, or the early twelfth century. He published it in the new edition of Baronius' Annals (volume thirteen, page six hundred twenty-seven) and challenged Pagi and Muratori, who questioned the authenticity of the document.
I also used it elsewhere (Orsi Dom. Temp. Append.) as a copy older than others I have seen.
Since the Albinian codex had not yet been found, I could not examine it.
However, when this valuable codex came into my hands, after much handling and careful reading of those mutilated documents attached to the Louisian one, I discovered an important omission in both.
Where Otto and Henry each said in their document: "And also the patrimony of Sicily, if God grants it into our hands," both mutilated versions read similarly: "And also the patrimony of Sicily."
Such an omission clearly indicates the era of three charters being joined together, doesn't it?
When the Norman leaders had been pacified and absolved of excommunication, Nicholas the Second traveled there to assert the rights of the Holy See in Apulia and other provinces.
He held a council there and received an oath of loyalty from those leaders in the year 1059, as recorded in the Book of Taxes and more clearly by Baronius.
Similarly, Nicholas the Third did the same with Rudolph, to whom he sent the same three charters, also incomplete, which will be discussed in its proper place.
Nor should it be thought that those charters were accidentally shortened or that the condition "if God, etc." was omitted by the scribe in both cases.
Since the Normans were no longer hostile to the Apostolic See, it needed to be shown that Sicily was under the jurisdiction of the Roman Church, as it truly was due to the invasion of the patrimonies of Calabria and Sicily.
As we have seen in the previous dissertation, Adrian equated this with the persecution of sacred images.
Since Louis had issued his charter before the arrival of the Saracens and confirmed the grant of the island made by his ancestor Charlemagne, it made sense-as the Greeks had possessed those patrimonies for ninety years to great detriment-and thirty thousand and five hundred thousand gold coins, possibly more than the island was worth at that time, had been taken from the poor and the churches, provoking divine retribution.
Since, I say, Louis had issued his charter before the Saracen invasion, there was no reason for him to include that condition, which had to be included in the charters of Otto and Henry, because the rights of the Holy See had to be asserted by the expulsion of the Saracens.
During the time of Pope Nicholas, the island of Sicily suffered under Saracen rule for 230 years, with the Greeks losing all hope of reclaiming it.
Meanwhile, the Normans had taken control of Calabria, Apulia, and Capua, which later came to be known as Sicily cis Pharum, through military force.
Pope Leo the Ninth had tried and failed to reclaim these territories by force to assert the rights of the Holy See.
Fortunately, Pope Nicholas, guided by divine counsel, managed to reconcile the Normans with the Holy See.
Through imperial decrees, he effectively taught them the rights of the Roman Church, achieving more in a concise manner than if he had elaborated on the nearly tripled sums involved in fraud against the poor and churches, which further confirmed these rights.
The oaths of fidelity from Robert Guiscard, Duke of Apulia and Calabria, and the mission to reclaim Sicily from Saracen control, achieved through apostolic authority, stand as a testament to this success.
These oaths are documented in the Albinian Codex shortly after the decrees and in Baronius's account in the Book of Censuses (1059, n. 70 seq.).
An oath of fidelity to Alexander the Second, granted to Richard of Capua two years later, is also recorded in the Albinian Codex: Acted in the hall of the Lateran Sacred Palace on October 2, in the third year of the 15th indiction, namely in the year 1061.
A similar oath was taken by the same Richard to Gregory the Seventh, as recorded by Baronius (1073, n. 63) in the register of the holy pontiff in Labbe's work (Conc. vol. X, p. 23) with some variations at the end.
Regarding the fidelity of these oaths, Robert declared, "And to no one will I swear fidelity, except saving the fidelity to the Holy Roman Church." This statement is absent in Baronius's account because it was not found in the Book of Censuses; however, it must be restored. The Normans knew that Apulia and Calabria were Greek territories, and Robert maintained their rule, acknowledging the supreme authority of the Holy See.
Similarly, Richard said: "To King Henry, I will swear loyalty, as I have been advised by you or your successors, but with loyalty to the Holy Roman Church preserved."
But we will discuss these matters in more detail when we talk about Otto's charter.
It's important to note that the Norman princes couldn't have known all these things without examining their charters.
So, without guessing, but firmly arguing from the evidence, I am confident in saying that Nicholas II is the author of the aforementioned mutilation of the charters, and that it happened in the year 1058 or the following year.
However, let no one blame the Pope for this act, as if he had deceitfully removed that condition.
The autographs of both charters are still diligently kept in the archive of Castel Sant'Angelo, where that condition is evident, and nothing obstructs the donation of Sicily made by Charles before the Saracen invasion, and confirmed by Otto and Henry, provided that they restored it to the Holy See after it was taken from their grasp.
Neither Augustus had recovered it, and therefore it was necessary for the successors to rely purely on the donation of Charles, which Nicholas evidently did.
Perhaps the Italian annalist, in the year 1059, sensed something; for he had forgotten himself, as he had depicted the submission of Louis in 817 contrary to the opinions of the most learned men, Baronius, Gretser, Natalis Alexander, Pierre de Marca, Cointius, Claude Fleury, Gootius, Hottoman, and Basnage, not to mention more recent scholars, all of whom acknowledge Louis as legitimate, and imagined that during these times, those three charters with additions according to the wishes of the Roman pontiffs came to light.
But I have shown that something was rather taken away from Otto's and Henry's charters than added.
As for Louis's charter, whose value lies not in its antiquity but in its contents, I trust I will make it clear why those praised most learned men unanimously declared it the legitimate offspring of Augustus.
Meanwhile, it's worth noting that the complete privilege of Louis, along with two others, is listed among the first records of the eleventh century in the codex titled: Privilege of Louis, emperor, etc.
Conversely, two other complete ones are included in the records of the twelfth century and are titled: Example of the privilege of Otto, emperor, etc.
Example of the privilege of Henry, emperor, etc.
Thus, it seems we can affirm that the privilege of Louis was transcribed from the original document during the time of Nicholas the Second, just like the other two.
Although in the declining twelfth century, when Albinus was flourishing, none of the originals were in Rome.
Whatever reasons I might present for why the others, moved here and there, managed to reach us, but the privilege of Louis could nowhere be found, would be mere speculation.
However, it is a minor loss, given that excellent copies exist with Albinus and in the archive of the Adrian Mole.
The essence of the matter is to reveal the nature of the document, which, as it seems to have been made by no one else, I willingly and gladly take upon myself.
And first, the document itself manifests as a pact of confirmation, repeatedly calling itself a decree of confirmation once and again.
The chronographer of Saint Vincent at Volturno (Duchesne, volume three, page six hundred eighty-one) in the Life of Abbot Joshua, who was present at the Aachen assembly where this document was issued, calls it a pact of constitution and confirmation.
The same words are used by the chronologist of Monte Cassino, Leo of Ostia, believed by the scholar Fontanini (Dif. one, page one hundred forty-five) to be the introducer of the new term constitution, which the document itself rejects.
However, to state what I think, it seems more like a redundancy of words rather than a new meaning of the matter.
For it can either simply be called a pact according to the custom of that age, or a pact of constitution; it will always be an instrument requested by agreement, or a stipulation, whose nature the word confirmation reveals.
Indeed, in that entire agreement, not even an inch of land was granted to the Roman Church by Louis.
Neither Stephen the Fourth nor Paschal the First, through his legate, asked the emperor for it.
They simply wanted the old rights to be confirmed by imperial authority, as was done by the aforementioned confirmation agreement.
Therefore, the Astronomer, a contemporary of Louis the Pious and part of his entourage who wrote the Life of the same emperor, says: The carrier of the legation was Theodorus the nomenclator.
After completing the task and obtaining the requested items, specifically the confirmation of the agreement and friendship, he returned in the manner of his predecessors.
Furthermore, the same chronographer of Volturno, as Mabillon attests (Annals, book twenty-eight, number forty-five), asserts that Abbot Joshua was so favored by Pope Paschal that when he received the confirmation agreement from Louis, he wished to be present among the abbots of France on behalf of the Apostolic See.
Here, as you see, he passes over in silence the voice of the constitution, which is less acceptable to Fontanini.
In the same place, however, the chronographer seems to testify freely to me that he found the confirmation agreement in the Pontifical Book of the Church.
Indeed, you will find donations described there in the most abundant words, but the confirmations of the same, unless joined with a new donation, you will hardly find.
Thus, the silence of this agreement in the Pontifical Book supports my interpretation.
The same Albinus, or rather Nicholas the Second, and Cencius do not attribute any other title to Louis than the privilege of Louis, the emperor, for confirming the royal rights to Pope Paschal.
In contrast, they inscribe the title in the privileges of Otto and Henry as concerning the royal rights granted to Saint Peter, for each added a new donation.
If Pagius had understood this, he would not have wrongly asserted (787, number eight) when he acknowledged the legitimate diploma of Louis.
Regarding the other Tuscany, always possessed by the emperors, it included other places that Louis the emperor granted to the same see in parts of Tuscany, as we will show in the year eight hundred and seventeen.
This does not appeal to the most learned and venerable cardinal's critic, but rather to a man of great delusion.
When the reader examines the previously mentioned year (817, n. 7), they will find Pagium siding with Molinaeus and Goldastus, and doing so with no small admiration.
Pagium asserts that the donation claimed to have been made by Louis the Pious to the Roman Church, as noted by Gratian, is just as fictitious as the one attributed to Constantine the Great, a point already recognized by some learned individuals.
This opinion resonated so strongly with the Italian annalist that he not only embraced it wholeheartedly but also scrutinized the ancient document for all the formalities of legal documents, arguing its falsity due to their absence.
This view gained traction among certain foreign writers, who were equally hostile towards the Catholic religion and the Holy See.
One writer, almost as if this diploma had been widely proclaimed, dedicated his writings-essentially mockeries-against the apostolic see's dominion to the same annalist.
In many parts, he professed that he owed to this annalist whatever he produced by dismantling that principal monument of papal authority.
The diploma itself, considered insignificant, was not sourced from any reputable copy nor from any of its many editions known to scholars, but was instead composed based on the commentaries of Urban Volaterranus, who was almost unknown to everyone (Geography, book 3, p. 41).
Utilizing his creativity, he relegated it to the end of his small volume.
I will present its title to demonstrate how highly the opinions of a Catholic writer on the temporal dominion of the Roman Church are valued among people of his sect, who are not without erudition, rather than to waste time refuting numerous falsehoods.
VII.
The critique of the diploma by Christian Wilhelm Franz Walch, which is said to have been granted by Emperor Louis the Pious to Pope Paschal the First.
Dedicated to the esteemed Ludovico Antonio Muratori, and in opposition to the renowned historian of the Paduans, Antonio Sandino.
The diploma itself is included, with noted variations in readings.
Leipzig, etc.
If you want to understand the writer's thoughts briefly, consider these words from the dedication:
He praises the Italian Annals highly because they are very useful in defending and maintaining the most august right of our German Empire to Italy, a right confirmed by the constant usage of eighteen hundred years, and suppressing the impudence of the adversaries.
And further down:
Regarding the Louis Document, the investigation, which the great man Hermann Conring adorned with the example and imitation of the historians of our nation with the title of eighty-nine, consecrated to your famous name in the ancient manner, I offer it to you, and I earnestly beg and beseech you to accept it kindly.
It is unjust to brand a Catholic writer with such a mark.
He does not speak with the sectarians about all of Italy, but about Italy properly so-called, or the Kingdom of Italy, or if you prefer, Lombardy.
Although he did not achieve participation in the supreme power by Roman coronation, he wrote about the same to the detriment of the pontifical power, which we discussed in the previous dissertation.
Thinking the Louis Document to be forged, because his genius did not grasp it in the same way, he showed himself to be a rather unskilled writer than a supporter of the sectarians, as the censor considers.
However, lest the incautious youth, deceived by a writer of such renown, think that the Louis Document should be dismissed along with the Edict or Donation of Constantine, I have decided to discuss his genius more thoroughly, aiming to serve the truth rather than opposing the false opinions of others.
I will start with the very causes that gave rise to this pact of confirmation.
The Annals of Lorsch, erroneously attributed to Einhard, and the Fulda Annals, according to Baronius and Pagus (eight fifteen, number one), report how certain Roman nobles conspiring to kill Pope Leo were executed.
The Astronomer narrates the matter more fully (chapter thirty-eight) for the aforementioned year:
This year, he says, as the course turned, it was reported to the emperor that some powerful Romans had entered into wicked conspiracies against Pope Leo.
Those whom the apostolic leader condemned to capital punishment, according to Roman law, were convicted and punished.
However, the Emperor was greatly troubled upon hearing this, as he was disturbed by such severe actions from the highest priest of the world.
Therefore, he sent Bernard, King of Italy, to investigate the truth and report back through Gerold.
King Bernard himself went to Rome and reported back what he had seen through the aforementioned envoy.
But soon after, envoys of the same apostolic leader Leo-Bishop John of Silva Candida, Theodorus the nomenclator, and Duke Sergius-cleared Leo of the accusations.
Note that it was Louis, not the Emperor as the Astronomer calls him (writing almost 30 years later and prematurely giving him this title), but the king, as Theganus rightly calls him, who, entrusted by his father with the care of the Roman Church, sent to inquire whether the Pope had indeed punished the guilty, and upon learning the facts, remained calm.
For the popes conducted themselves in such cases, as the Liber Pontificalis recounts about Adrian:
The most holy bishop, at the request of the judges and the entire Roman populace, ordered the chamberlain Calvulus and the aforementioned Campanians to be handed over to the prefect of the city, to be examined before the entire populace in the manner of murderers.
Taken to the public prison on the Elephant, they were examined before the entire populace.
Thus, the Campanians confessed in this examination as they had before.
However, Calvulus, hardening his heart, barely confessed to everything, and he died a cruel death in the same prison.
But after the aforementioned conspiracy against the holy pontiff, he fell gravely ill and died the following year.
Wherefore the Astronomer continues: When Pope Leo was weighed down by illness, all the estates called "domocultae," which had been newly established by the same apostolic leader, as well as those that were unlawfully taken from him, were looted and efforts were made to restore them without awaiting any judge.
Similar accounts are found in the Annales Laureshamenses.
So, it's not surprising that Leo's successor, Stephen the Fourth, shortly after his consecration, went to France to discuss confirming various rights with the pious prince who had been crowned with the imperial diadem by him.
After Stephen returned, his death shortly thereafter prevented him from retrieving all the documents of donations from the Lateran archives, organizing them, and completing a pact or diploma in every detail.
This pact was supposed to cover all rights, including the most ancient ones, starting from the city of Rome and its duchy, which had been under the Holy See for 25 years before the first donation from the Frankish kings.
It was also supposed to include the discipline of the election and consecration of Roman pontiffs.
What Stephen couldn't accomplish in a span of two months and a few days, his successor Paschal completed.
Paschal then sent a delegation to the prince to confirm everything, as affirmed by the cited writers, especially the Astronomer (chapter 40) for the year 817.
Theganus, who thoroughly describes the character of the pious Augustus, is silent on this matter but had mentioned in chapter 18 about Stephen: "As long as the most blessed pope was there, they had daily discussions about the benefit of God's holy Church."
And when the Astronomer adds in chapter 39 for the year 816: "The apostolic lord, having obtained all he requested, returned to Rome," it seems to me there is no doubt that Stephen reached an agreement with Louis about the confirmation pact, which Paschal later secured. This is corroborated by two chroniclers, Volturnensis and Cassinensis. Although they are quite distant from those times (Volturnensis reaches the year 1071, and Cassinensis, although appearing more recent to the Italian annalist, reaches 1115, when Leo Marsicanus, bishop of Ostia, who wrote the Chronicle, had died), no scholar doubts that these chroniclers relied on ancient records when writing about events that occurred before their times.
So, from the records of the Life of Abbot Joshua of Volturno, who was present at the council in Aachen, he gathered this:
Then, after making an agreement of constitution and confirmation with the most blessed Pope Paschal, and sealing it with his own hand and that of his three sons, he sent it through the emissary Theodore, the nomenclator of the Holy Roman Church, to the aforementioned Pope.
In this agreement, ten bishops, eight abbots, fifteen counts, a librarian, a steward, and a doorkeeper signed.
However, Leo of Ostia reports the same event with slightly different words in Book One, Chapter Sixteen:
Here, Louis made an agreement of constitution and confirmation for the blessed Peter the apostle and his vicar Lord Paschal, just like his parents Pepin and Charles did.
Sealing it with his own hand and that of his sons, he had ten bishops, eight abbots, fifteen counts, a librarian, a steward, and one doorkeeper sign it, and sent it through the emissary Theodore, the nomenclator of the Holy Roman Church, to Lord Pope Paschal.
The testimony of the Cassinese Chronicle, or Leo of Ostia, may seem superfluous to some; but it's not.
Indeed, the first mention of this document is wrongly attributed to Leo by Pagi (817, number 7):
Leo of Ostia, who died at the beginning of the twelfth century, was the first to mention it, so it wasn't conceived long before.
What confidence in the man!
So what does Du Cange (Glossary, under the word Seal) say about a charter of Charlemagne, two royal decrees of Charlemagne and his son Louis; and from the chronicle of Saint Vincent of Volturno (Book Two, page 681) he quotes these words:
Sealing it with his own hand and that of his three sons?
Indeed, Leo of Ostia says, with the seal of his own hand and that of his sons.
Therefore, the first mention of the document should not be attributed to Leo, but to the ancient records of the Monastery of Volturno.
While working on the Cassinese chronicle, he shows that he had both the Volturno record and the diploma of Louis in front of him.
From that place, he seeks the essence of the matter and compiles the varying readings from the charter.
Hence the words of the charter: To you blessed Peter, prince of the apostles, and through you to your vicar, the Lord Paschal.
He adapts the words of the Monument of Volturno, which he transcribes from 92, saying, Blessed Peter the Apostle and his vicar, the Lord Paschal, and immediately adds, imitating his parents Pipin and Charles because in the charter the donations of Pipin and Charles are distinctly listed.
The rest is evident by itself.
However, Ostiensis is mistaken when he says that Louis imitated his parents.
Each of them adhered to the boundaries of their donation.
Pipin, the first expander of ecclesiastical authority, donated provinces and cities to blessed Peter and his successors.
Charles, the confirmer of his father's donation, added his own extensive donation.
Louis, on the contrary, ventured far beyond the donations of the Franks and did not grant any cities or provinces at all.
Therefore, the simple tradition of the Volturno chronographer about the agreement of confirmation is to be preferred over Ostiensis, who, according to Pagus's opinion, did not first mention the charter but was the first to disturb the charter with his additions.
Now, indeed, the charter itself must be examined.
We have already said enough about its title.
The beginning or invocation of the Trinity, at first glance unique, makes the reason for its uniqueness clear if considered attentively.
The most learned Mabillon, in Dipl.
Book 2, Chapter 3, against the Propylaeum of Papebrochius, brings forth the invocations of the Carolingian era: In the name of God and our Savior Jesus Christ, In the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, In the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit.
Godefridus, noting this matter in the Chronicles of Gotw.
Volume 1, Book 2, Chapter 1, Page 117, and following, notes that the style of the notaries varied in these formulas.
Especially in Chapter 6, Page 231, about the various invocations of Henry I.
"I do not see," he says, "why it should be rejected in the Henrician charter granted to the Roman Church..."
In the year 1014, the invocation "In the name of God Almighty, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit" was produced, which D. Frider. Hahnius considered suspicious in his History of the Empire, part II, chapter 6, section 10, page 208, letter a. However, this phrase is found in many documents, especially Italian ones, reflecting the style of Italian notaries.
No one, I think, will disagree with the scholarly observation that imperial documents were usually made in Rome, including those of Charlemagne, who issued his donation in the City. Regarding the invocation in the diploma of Louis, whether arranged by Stephen the Fourth or Paschal and confirmed in France, it might be judged differently. Baronius (811, number 44) mentions Charlemagne's testament, made in France, which also includes the invocation: "In the name of God Almighty, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit." This phrase is also found in Labbe (Councils, volume VII, page 1202) and in Bolland (Acts of the Saints, volume II, page 887), who presents the Life of Saint Charlemagne from two high-quality manuscripts of Eginhard, compared with five other manuscripts and editions.
The only difference is that in all of them it reads: "In the name of the Lord God Almighty," etc., as seen in the Ludovician copy of Adrian Mole, and in the diplomas of Otto and Henry from the Albinian codex according to their autographs.
From this, it can be safely inferred that all the privileges granted by the Carolingians to Saint Peter and his successors preferred this invocation, which Otto and Henry also imitated, clearly in the style of the scribes of the Holy See, whose job it was to produce these from the archive records. I do not doubt that if the donation of Pippin existed, it would bear the exact same invocation that all successors embraced.
That holy republic, namely Rome and its duchy, which existed even before the donations of the Frankish kings, was confirmed by Louis as belonging to the apostolic see, following the surrender of the people who defected from the impious Greeks.
Because Emperor Stephen IV had agreed, with the authority of the emperor, to prevent lootings, he also wished to protect all ecclesiastical domains with strong fortifications.
The emperor himself explains the matter clearly: Just as you have held and managed in your power and domain from your predecessors until now.
Then he lists each city, both of Roman Tuscany and Campania; for the duchy was divided into two parts, as all scholars know, into Cistiberinum and Transtiberinum.
We see clearly in the letters of the Codex Carolinus that these cities were under the jurisdiction of the Apostolic See before any donation, making it unnecessary to demonstrate it again here.
It suffices to recall that Stephen II told Pippin, who had returned to France (Codex Carolinus, letters 6, 7, others 7, 9), that the Lombards had nullified the donation and had not given even a palm's width of land to the holy see.
On the contrary, they had conducted raids, plundering, and devastations in the cities and places of blessed Peter.
Again urging him to undertake a new expedition (Codex Carolinus, letters 8, 9, others 4, 6), while Rome was besieged by the Lombards: No improvement has been made for us, he said, but rather after the desolation of our entire province, etc.
What is desired more clearly to hold, that the city of Rome and its duchy were of the jurisdiction of the Apostolic See before any donation?
From the same source, there is even more ample testimony: for the same pontiff says below, The city of Narni, which your Christianity granted to blessed Peter, they have taken away, and they have seized some of our cities.
He distinguishes the city of Narni of the Roman duchy from the others, and reports to Pippin that it was taken because it had been previously invaded by the Duke of Spoleto (Book of the Pontiffs, section 254) and was restored by Aistulph, frightened by Pippin's royal emissaries upon his first arrival (Codex Regius, Mazarin, Thu.) 13.
But because Pagius and others argue that this part of the papal territory was owed to royal generosity, they are not afraid to claim that the words of Louis refer to your predecessors against the consistent faith of all the manuscripts, substituting ours, so that Pepin and Charles seem to have given Rome and its duchy to Saint Peter and his successors.
It will be worthwhile to show the opposite, not by reasoning, which I did in the illustration of the Codex Carolinus, but by their own confession.
They do not count Charles Martel among the predecessors of Louis, although they dispute so much about his patriciate with empty contention.
They say that in the year 741, he was prevented by death from aiding the endangered Church.
Moreover, they admit that the Roman pontiffs did not abandon their obedience to the Greek Emperors, however impious, until the year 753.
In the following year, during Pepin's first expedition, they say that Narnia, one of the cities of the Roman duchy, was restored out of fear of the Franks.
Therefore, whatever they imagine the lord of the Roman duchy, whose capital is Rome, to have been, this territory, by their own confession, was subject to its own ruler before Pepin's donation took effect.
However, who this ruler was, Pepin himself testified to the Romans one year after his donation, as the Romans themselves teach us in the letters they sent to the king: "Concerning your most blessed and co-angelic spiritual father, our lord decreed by God, Pope Paul."
Therefore, the predecessors mentioned in your Louisian document were Gregory the Third, Zacharias, Stephen the Second for 25 years before the donation, and after the donation, Paul the First, Stephen the Third, and Adrian.
They themselves, admitting what they cannot deny, state that Pepin's donation was confined within the borders of the exarchate and Pentapolis. They do not even dare to speak about Adrian and his successor Leo the Third, although some of them might try to evade this authority in another way, which I have abundantly demonstrated in the notes to the Codex Carolinus.
Why, then, would they prefer to adhere to Gratian, who was the first to place our matters, rather than to the consistent testimony of the codices and their own confession, is not difficult to understand: they do not know what they are saying.
The second chapter of Louis' diploma shows the very donation of Pepin-not as we said, made at Carisiacum in the year 754 and confirmed by Pepin's two sons, Charles and Carloman, but as Charles the Great confirmed it in Rome in the year 774.
The former was indeed very diligently kept in the archive of the Lateran Church; when twenty years later, in 774, Charles came to Rome and had the promise made in Francia at the place called Carisiacum read to him again.
He was pleased with it, and with his judges, added everything that was attached to it, as it is in the Pontifical book (section 318).
The Most Christian king of the Franks himself, corroborating it with his own hand, made all bishops, abbots, dukes, and counts sign it.
Then, placing it first on the altar of Saint Peter, and later inside his holy confession, both the king of the Franks and his judges, promising by oath to the blessed Peter and his most holy vicar Pope Adrian to preserve everything contained in that donation, handed it over, as Albinus read in his time, and with little difference, all the codices, both published and manuscript, have it.
A donation so solemnly and so sacredly confirmed by Charles, which Adrian not once, nor without reason calls an offering and holocaust in his letters, is sought in vain elsewhere; it exists complete in the one Louis' diploma.
The most diligent collector of ancient monuments, Francesco Bianchini, thinks he has published it from the most famous Farnese Codex for the benefit of the public (Anastasius, volume II, page 57).
As a fair evaluator of that precious manuscript, when he was transferred to Parma along with the Farnese library, he went there repeatedly, taking a sample of the uncial script.
He indicated that the manuscript was from the time of Charlemagne, which Holstenius and Schelstratius had neglected while it was in Rome.
He described the entire passage I referred to when discussing the letters of Stephen the Second as a monument of Pippin's donation.
But the very learned man was deceived by the account in the Pontifical book.
Although it mentions how Pippin, confirming with a new diploma everything he had granted to Saint Peter and his successors with his diploma at Carisiacum, also added Comaclum, the cities listed are only those whose possession Fulrad, Pippin's envoy, took and brought the keys to Rome.
Therefore, it will be found that ten cities are missing in the Pontifical book, all of which are found in the diploma of Louis, except for the city of Narnia in the Duchy of Rome.
Fulrad had also taken possession of Narnia, even though it was later separated from the old jurisdiction of the Holy See by the donation.
Therefore, Louis rightly includes it among the cities of the Duchy of Rome.
Pippin's donation, complete and with such precision and distinction, is listed in the diploma, so it is surprising why the two more recent scholars did not refrain from suspecting its authenticity.
Indeed, although it mentions only Pippin's donation, it does not attribute it solely to Pippin but makes Charles a participant in it.
In the twenty years that followed Pippin's donation and preceded Charles's first arrival in the city, the ten cities, whose possession the Lombards refused to hand over, were often promised but never returned.
Charles, after capturing Desiderius, the king of the Lombards, and subduing their kingdom, claimed the entire donation for the Holy See.
This is evidenced by the two letters of Charles.
A few months after Charles's departure, Adrian informed the king about the invasion by Archbishop Leo of Ravenna into Faenza, Imola, Ferrara, Bologna, and Adria, also known as Gabellum, where he had appointed a count recommended by Charles in the church of Saint Peter.
This makes it clear that all the cities of Emilia were under the control of the Roman Church.
Regarding the four cities of the Pentapolis, letters confirm that both Pentapoles, from Rimini to Gubbio, remain faithful to the apostolic see.
Additionally, other letters, ninety or ninety-two, reveal that the territory or town of Valva served as a refuge for five of Charles's envoys during the Beneventan unrest.
You might wonder why Emilia is not mentioned among the other cities in the Codex Carolinus, which follows Ravenna in the diploma.
However, it is mentioned in other letters and documents as a province.
Therefore, I believe the medieval Italian geographer made a significant mistake by converting the province into a city.
And you are not alone in this confusion: I too was once misled and embraced that erroneous opinion.
Why?
Because I saw that the Exarchate had narrower boundaries during the Lombard period than during the Roman Republic, and that Emilia was divided into two parts up to the territory of Bologna, making it part of the Italian kingdom, and from there the Exarchate began.
Nevertheless, I discovered that Emilia was indeed granted to the apostolic see in this diploma, which many learned men considered legitimate.
In these complexities, what was I to do?
A unique and previously unheard-of doctrine emerged from the geographer, who seemed to have strong reasons for removing Emilia's name as a province in the Exarchate, and I followed his opinion.
Afterwards, I turned my serious attention to defending the rights of the Holy See, refusing to accept any opinions that contradicted the clear records of the annals.
I discovered that this chronicler, highly regarded by the Italian annalist in many other matters, was greatly mistaken in detracting from the honor of the province of Emilia.
The province did not lose its status, as evident from the division of ecclesiastical provinces; instead, it began to be more limited in civil administration.
Since it retained the name Emilia in the exarchate, in the Kingdom of Italy, that prominent kingdom name absorbed the provincial name.
Furthermore, the formation of the dual Pentapolis within the exarchate restricted Emilia.
Thus, three provinces began to exist in the exarchate: Emilia, Maritime Pentapolis, and Inland Pentapolis.
When Fulrad was about to take possession of the cities of Pentapolis and Emilia, as stated in the Farnesian Code, he advanced into the exarchate and brought the keys of both the city of Ravenna and various cities of the exarchate of Ravenna to Rome.
The cities are listed in the code without distinguishing between the provinces of the exarchate.
Adrian, announcing to Charles the invasion by Archbishop Leo (Code of Charles, letter 51, also 54), said that he invaded the cities of Emilia and then tried to incite the Pentapolensians to rebellion.
However, they remained steadfast in their obedience to the Holy See, just as they had under our predecessor, Lord Pope Stephen, to whom your late father and your own distinguished excellence entrusted the exarchate to remain under the authority of the Blessed Peter.
Similarly, in another letter (letter 53, also 52), he lists the provinces separately, clearly showing that the people of Ravenna and those in the province of Emilia are distinct from the Pentapolensians.
None of the Ravennates or people of Emilia; hence, he commends the loyalty of the Pentapolensians.
Therefore, I am ashamed to have trusted the chronicler in this matter.
Restoring the former honor of Emilia, I confirm it with the authority of the diploma.
Louis confirms the donation made by his grandfather Pepin, which was restored by his father Charles, by reciting it exactly as it was.
This includes Ravenna, the head and metropolis of the entire exarchate, and Emilia, one of the provinces of the exarchate, listing each city individually to prevent any extension of this province beyond its original boundaries.
He then adds another province, including Pentapolis, which during Pepin's time was divided into two provinces.
This further validates the sincerity of the donation.
He lists the cities of that province, along with their territories, 98 towns, and their boundaries.
This is described so clearly and distinctly that the same boundaries, which the ecclesiastical domain holds today and by which Emilia is divided from the Duchy of Modena, are noted.
Indeed, more famous writers of the sixteenth century, contrary to all ancient records and in line with the times of the Roman Republic, extend this province very broadly.
However, because they considered the ecclesiastical provinces and given that their era was somewhat less illustrious, some leniency is warranted.
It is different for the writers of our time, who should have referred to the Carolingian Code and the diploma of Louis, instead of asserting the validity of both monuments by following the previous writers.
The expansion of the exarchate, or the cities they add to the donation of the Frankish kings, will have to be discussed elsewhere.
However, it should be noted that they remove one of these from the same donation.
This is Bobium, today known as Sassina, located somewhat south of Cesena, which the diploma lists first.
The Carolingian Code (letters 51, 53, or 54, 52) names it next to Cesena, and the Farnesian Code lists it between the Castle of Saint Marino and Urbino.
It is an ancient city of Emilia, whose bishop attended the councils of Symmachus at the end of the fifth century (Labbe, Councils, volume IV, pages 1367-1376).
In the census book of the Albinian Code of Bobium's bishopric, it is found situated with three monasteries between the territories of Forli and Populonia.
Besides the fact that out of the fifty districts subject to Sassina, four make up the county of Bobium, as Ughellus pointed out in Italia Sacra, Volume 2, page 652, this noble and ancient city of Aemilia was taken from the donation of Pippin and replaced by the town of Bobium, famous for the monastery of Saint Columban in Insubria.
It was granted an episcopal see by Benedict the Eighth at the beginning of the 11th century, as noted by Ditmar in Baronius, 1014, number 4, and by Ughellus, Mabillon, and many others.
Whether this city should be sought outside the extensive limits of Aemilia is left to the judgment of the reader.
Indeed, I see that it is impossible to narrate the fervor of the debate.
For Fulrad, sent by Pippin, who took possession of Bobium as well as other cities, certainly did not venture into such distant regions.
And since I am certain that all the successors of Saint Peter protested according to the words of Adrian, in Codex Carolinus, letter 71, or 56, I call upon God as a witness.
For I irrationally seek the boundaries of no one; I confidently say Bobium never belonged to the jurisdiction of the Holy See.
Regarding the other cities, which they join to the exarchate, I admit it is otherwise.
Not because they were included in the donation of Pippin or Charlemagne, which is equally false to affirm, as it is to transfer Bobium from Insubria to Flaminia and claim it for the Holy See without any authority; but because from another source they altogether pertain to the dominion of the Apostolic See, as I will show in due course.
Meanwhile, to more firmly establish the boundaries of ecclesiastical dominion, I will briefly add some points from Charlemagne's division of the kingdoms among his sons Louis, Pippin, and Charles.
For he gave Italy, also called Lombardy, to Pippin to be divided among the brothers if he predeceased them.
Although elsewhere in Volume 1, page 298 and following, the same has been brought to another matter.
From the entrance of Italy through the city of Augusta, Charles shall receive Eboracum, Vercelli, Pavia, and then along the Po River as the boundary to the borders of Regenses, and Regium itself, and the city of Novara, and Modena up to the boundaries of Saint Peter.
These cities, along with their suburbs, territories, and counties, and everything on the left side as one travels to Rome from the kingdom that Pippin ruled, together with the Duchy of Spoleto, will be received by Charles, as we mentioned earlier.
However, everything on the right side as one travels to Rome from those cities or counties, from the aforementioned kingdom, that is the portion that remained from the region beyond the Po River, along with the Duchy of Tuscany, up to the southern sea and the province, will be assigned to Louis to expand his kingdom.
You see the kingdom of Italy ending with the territory of Modena, because the territory of Bologna, as of today, was adjacent to Modena.
Moreover, you see this division marked by boundaries from the entrance of Italy up to Modena: and from there, a considerable part of Italy or Lombardy, which extends to the left as one travels to Rome, where the vast dominion of the Venetian Republic is now, together with the Duchy of Spoleto, which, though offered to blessed Peter and his successors, belonged to the supreme right of the emperor, as will be explained below, will be an expansion of Charles's kingdom.
The other part assigned to Louis is best explained by another designation through the boundaries of ecclesiastical dominion, which is contained in Otto's diploma.
It is granted to Charles both in the same diploma and in the Pontifical Book, and it is as follows:
From Lunis with the island of Corsica, then in Suriano, then in the mountain of Bardonis, then in Berceto, from there in Parma, then in Reggio, from there in Mantua, and in Monte Silicis, and the province of Venetia and Istria.
This will be discussed further in the notes on Otto's diploma.
Meanwhile, Louis's portion of the Italian kingdom beyond the Po is acquired; do not understand the designated boundaries as the walls of the named cities themselves, but as the extremity of each territory.
Additionally, you will receive the Duchy of Tuscany, just like the Duchy of Spoleto, under the supreme right of the emperor, although it was offered to the apostolic see; therefore, it is included in this jurisdiction and added to Louis's portion.
So far, we've talked about the complete donation of Pepin, confirmed by his son Charlemagne in Rome, before the most sacred body of the prince of the apostles, in the year 774.
Now, we need to move on to the donations made by Charlemagne himself.
This great prince, with his piety towards God, and his devotion, love, and generosity towards Peter, came to Rome four times, as stated in the Codex Carolinus, in the years 774, 781, 787, and 800.
During his first visit, aside from confirming his father's donation before the blessed ashes of that apostle, he granted Tuscia Langobardica, or at least a part of it.
The whole region was once called Langobardica, though it was later named Regalis by more recent people (Codex Carolinus, Vol. I, pp. 297, 321).
On his second visit, he granted the entire Sabine territory (Codex Carolinus, pp. 383, 415).
During his third visit, he granted six cities of the Duchy of Benevento (Codex Carolinus, pp. 475 and following).
What he granted on his fourth visit for the remission of sins and for the merit of his soul, as both he and his father had always done (Codex Carolinus, pp. 228, 325, 330, 333, 341, 384), is not contained in the Codex Carolinus, since it was compiled nine years earlier.
However, he seems to have donated Corsica, Sardinia, and Sicily.
Corsica is mentioned in the letters of Pope Leo the Third to Emperor Charlemagne, and Einhard attests that Charlemagne did not leave the city without bestowing gifts upon the holy see.
Finally, because the Codex Carolinus, a witness of donations beyond any exception, remains silent about these islands.
Therefore, it is certain that none of them was donated to the holy see before the year 791.
Why not then in the year 800, when he was made a partner in the supreme pontifical power by Pope Leo the Third through the imperial crown?
However, I admit that this is confirmed by no old monument, except for a diploma of Louis; so I long adhered to the opinion of Balutius, Mabillon, and Leblanc, who believed that some privilege or diploma had been interpolated somewhere.
However, upon closer examination, I realized that the donation of Sardinia and Sicily was uncertain.
I immediately decided to set aside the opinion of those who thought otherwise and follow the views of Baronius and other very learned men, which Grotius, Hotman, and Basnage also supported.
Indeed, the rights of the Holy See to Sicily were less doubtful, as we discussed extensively in the previous treatise.
Otto the Great claimed this right for the Holy See, as we will see in the next section; and Saint Henry not only followed Otto's example but also confirmed Louis's diploma, despite the objections of those who disagreed.
But regarding these islands, nothing should be affirmed rashly.
Therefore, I assert that their donation is not at all doubtful, but the timing of the donation is uncertain.
As for the other donations of Charlemagne, I believe there is nothing to add to what has been thoroughly covered in the previous commentary on Adrian's letters.
However, I should mention that the Sabine patrimony or territory is listed immediately after the Pippinian donation in Louis's diploma because the geographical locations of the regions were prioritized over chronological order.
Moreover, the letters of the Codex Carolinus, all dated before the year 781, provide evidence that the Lombard cities of Tuscany, along with the duchies of Tuscany and Spoleto, were given by Charles.
The second donation, namely the Sabine territory, was certainly not made before the year 781 when Carloman was baptized in Rome and was given the auspicious name of Pippin by Adrian, thereby acquiring the name of his godfather for his parents.
This unique aspect of the diploma is evident in that Itherius and Maginarius, the abbots, resolved all disputes between the Holy See and the people of Rieti by establishing boundaries between them and the Sabine territory after the year 784, for in that year Maginarius succeeded Fulrad as abbot of Dionysius's monastery in July.
This could not be found in the letters of the Codex Carolinus (67, 68, 71, 72, 73, etc.).
were all given before Maginarius became abbot, during the lifetime of Ildegarde, who died in 783.
However, the third donation of six cities in Campania should be listed last.
This is because it pertains to the year 787, when Charlemagne, after subduing the Beneventans and taking Grimoald along with twelve other hostages, brought Arichis, Grimoald's father and the Duke of the Beneventans, and the entire region under his control.
After reviewing the ancestral and paternal donation, Charlemagne confirms both patrimonies as belonging to the Holy See, even though they were not in its possession.
He lists Benevento first, which Adrian (in Codex Carolinus, letter 59, or 49) mentioned to Charlemagne.
Adrian stated that various emperors, patricians, and other God-fearing individuals had donated parts of Tuscany, Spoleto, or Benevento to the apostolic see for the sake of their souls and the forgiveness of sins.
A few years earlier, Stephen the Third had praised Itherius, the envoy of Bertrada and Charlemagne, for immediately going to the Duchy of Benevento to reclaim the patrimony in those regions (Codex Carolinus, letter 46, or 44).
Charlemagne then mentions Calabria, without adding Sicily, because he had confirmed the entire island in an earlier donation.
Regarding this patrimony, it is important to note that since 756, Stephen the Second, while thanking Pippin (Codex Carolinus, letter 11, or 8), had earnestly discussed with the king the possession of the exarchate obtained through Fulrad.
Inspired by God and by the blessed Peter, the prince of his apostles, he urged that the part of the Greeks be arranged in such a way that the holy Catholic and apostolic faith remains whole and unshaken, and that the holy Church of God be freed and secured from others and their malicious intentions.
This would ensure that the preparation of lights for the Churches of God continues for the salvation of souls, and that the hunger of the poor, needy, and pilgrims be alleviated.
In third place, the Neapolitan patrimony is confirmed.
Like the Calabrian patrimony, it was unjustly held by the Greeks, similar to how the Beneventan patrimony was held by the Beneventans, who at that time were more friendly to the Greeks than to the Holy See.
It would take too long to go through the entire history of this patrimony, but you can review it in the Codex Carolinus, page 495.
It is sufficient to point out that Adrian subdued Terracina with papal soldiers, which represented that patrimony.
Gaeta was also captured for the same reason, and after Charles gave six cities in Campania, the territory of the Holy See expanded in that region, highlighting the value of the Neapolitan patrimony.
However, the history of the three great patrimonies is not the focus here.
But the donation of Sicily, whenever it was made by Charles and confirmed by Louis, makes it more plausible.
Moreover, the Italian annalists highlight an inconvenient, if not audacious, observation.
In the year 1059, this ancient rival of papal domination claims a diploma with additions emerged in the 11th century, discussing Benevento, Calabria, Sicily, and other regions, concerning matters of great interest to the Holy See at that time, not for their status in previous centuries.
This will convince the ignorant public and Walch and his followers, as stated in the Preface, page IV, that the Italian annalist is a treasure of antiquity and historical events, and a chief ornament of our age.
But to men of true learning and those knowledgeable in papal history, all historical rules seem to be suddenly violated.
Doesn't falseness, audacity, and hostility shine through?
The monuments of the Codex Carolinus clearly show that the annalist is lying.
Nicholas the Second, following in the footsteps of his predecessors, repels the injury recklessly inflicted on him.
The annals themselves, repeatedly sprinkled with such matters, manifest the hostility towards papal domination.
It's worth noting that in the confirmation pact or privilege, Sicily was included by Stephen the Fourth or his successor, Saint Paschal the First, in the Donation of Charlemagne.
This donation was made multiple times, each instance specifying new regions.
Sicily had to be included in that confirmation pact: were the ancient rights of the Sicilian patrimony any less certain than those of Benevento, both Calabrias, and Naples?
So, what did Stephen the Second do in the year 756?
In the same letters where he thanks Pippin for gaining possession of the cities of the exarchate, as I mentioned earlier, he persuaded the same king that the Calabrian and Sicilian patrimonies should be claimed by the apostolic see as his property.
What does Adrian testify to Charles in the year 794 (Council, volume eight, page 963) that he would consider the Eastern Emperor heretical unless he restored the patrimonies with the consecration of bishops, as stated earlier in the previous dissertation, number 10?
Or, reminding about the patrimonies, if the emperor refuses to restore them to our holy Roman Church, we will declare him a heretic for persisting in such an error.
I will address the lesser matters in the notes.
Given this context, it should be noted that the authenticity of this document is so strong that the same annalist who depicted it as fabricated in the year 817 claims it was only interpolated in the year 1059.
However, unless I am mistaken, I demonstrated that this second opinion should be disregarded.
Now, let's briefly consider the main reasons why the patrimonies of both Sicilies are specifically confirmed, aside from the other matters, so that the legitimate authority of the document becomes increasingly evident.
The vast estates in Syracuse and Palermo, celebrated in the letters of Gregory the Great, were once called by the name of Sicily and later by the name of a single Sicilian.
These estates are confirmed for all of Sicily, similar to the patrimony of Sardinia mentioned in the confirmation of this island.
They are not listed among the remaining patrimonies because the rights of the Roman Church were abundantly secured in that review.
It is different with both Calabrias and Naples, which are located in regions still under the power of the Greeks, like Sicily.
The Calabrians, being too remote, were treated in the same way as Sicily by both Stephen the Second and Adrian.
However, about Naples, which could have been taken from the Greeks by the Lombard king through the Beneventans under his rule, Pippin had already dealt with the matter much earlier.
Therefore, in the year 766, Paul the First thanked him for ordering King Desiderius to compel the Neapolitans and Gaetans to return the patrimonies to your protector, the blessed Peter, located there in Naples (Codex Carolinus, letter 40).
And in the year 780, Adrian (Codex Carolinus, letter 65) reminded Charles of the unreliable faith of the Neapolitans because they did not want to keep the agreed pacts and refused to return the patrimony of the blessed apostle Peter, who is placed there in Naples.
The Beneventans, although not under Greek power, still showed difficult conditions even in the year 788, as clearly shown by three letters in the Codex Carolinus (89 and following).
Therefore, the confirmation of the Ludovician pact was necessary for this patrimony and those under Greek power, so that the rights of the holy see, which the grandfather and father had unsuccessfully tried to assert, would not suffer any loss.
These rights would be restored when it seemed good to God the best and greatest.
And we finally saw this happen in the 11th century, when the Italian annalist, completely ignorant of antiquity, dared to brand Nicholas the Second with the mark of an impostor without any monument, any little history, or any even condemnable witness.
There are two titles, or rather, two types of rights, on which papal dominion relies, that have been clearly and distinctly demonstrated.
First, the voluntary submission of the people, after their separation from the Greeks, subjected Rome and its duchy to the Roman pontiffs.
Additionally, through the generosity of the Frankish kings Pippin and Charles, they acquired the remaining provinces and cities.
All of this was perpetually confirmed by Louis for Paschal and his successors, allowing them to maintain their right, rule, and dominion.
Another type of generosity or donation from the aforementioned kings followed, which was not agreed upon with the kings, but voluntarily granted to the prince of the apostles and his successors.
We will discuss these types of donations, which are not expressly mentioned in the diploma, when the order of events leads us to the privilege of Saint Henry.
There, we will talk about the voluntary donations of all this emperor's predecessors.
One must consider here the Carolingian, which dismisses and indeed discredits some recent questions about the type of dominion by which the pontiffs obtained them.
Therefore, in the year 774, when Charles first came to the City, he not only restored and confirmed his father's donation, adding a significant part of Lombard Tuscany, but also offered another part of Tuscany, distinct by the name of duchy from the former (which recent scholars have named Regal), containing the cities of Luna, Pisa, Lucca, Volterra, Siena, Pistoia, Florence, Arezzo, and new Chiusi, along with the Duchy of Spoleto, separated from Italy properly so-called, or from Lombardy, to Saint Peter.
This matter is evidenced by Adrian 105 (Codex Carolinus, letter 56, others 58).
Indeed, in the year 776, he says, you also presently offered the Duchy of Spoleto to your protector, blessed Peter, prince of the apostles, through our lowliness, for the salvation of your soul.
However, a similar thing concerning the Duchy of Tuscany is not found in the letters of the Codex Carolinus.
Its condition is found to be very different from that of Spoleto in these letters.
Several leaders from other cities were found, including those from Clusium, Florence, and Lucca.
Codex Carolinus, epistle 55, also 60, 80, and 64; 50, and 55.
These leaders provided both credibility to the matter and thwarted the trivial attempts of those trying to investigate the metropolis of Tuscany at that time.
However, both the Duchy of Spoleto, which was entrusted to one person, and the Duchy of Tuscany, which was administered by several leaders, were offered by Charles to Saint Peter and his successors.
These offers are uniquely documented in a charter by Louis, which not only declares this matter genuine but also abundantly testifies to the papal supremacy over the remaining territories.
Indeed, the grant of such useful dominion, the decree or papal charter by which both duchies are restored to Charles, the donor, and the clear declaration of the supreme right reserved for the same Charles, are such evident indications of sincerity that they make any other proof unnecessary.
Furthermore, the inclusion of these in the document, or that final clause: "Always safeguarding our dominion over these same duchies in all things, and their subjection to our part," provides two less doubtful arguments:
First, all revenues of these duchies are confirmed for Saint Peter and his successors, which were previously individually specified through taxes, pensions, and gifts, as the accurate transcript of the Adriatic records, not donations, as the erroneous script of the code suggests.
Second, in the entire ecclesiastical domain, these duchies alone were not under the supreme power of the Roman pontiff during the time of Louis. For the emperor, to comply with the pope, had confirmed the remaining rights with imperial authority, so that they would remain under the jurisdiction, dominion, and authority of the Holy See until the end of the century; which he indicates in the following with the same words and other stronger ones.
The reason for this was so that in the regions granted by the kings of the Franks, and in Rome and its duchy, the popes would seem to rule with supreme authority by imperial power.
This was intended to curb the audacity of subjects who, restored by imperial majesty for the same purpose, could not be restrained from seeking the life of the supreme ruler through treachery, and from invading the properties of the Church.
As I mentioned earlier, anyone who thinks otherwise is far from the truth.
The many arguments for dominion, evident before the donations of the kings, are demonstrated in the Codex Carolinus, 106.
After the donations, when there was no longer any fear from the Lombards, and the patriciate of the Franks served as a great defense against Greek threats, almost as many arguments can be found in the same Codex as there are letters from the Roman pontiffs.
More certain and evident arguments can be found for brevity's sake from the previous commentary on the letters of Adrian and from letters 63, 65, 76, 75, 81, 67, 97, and 85.
I cannot be convinced that the often-praised two men, or their attendants, did not notice this.
The inconsistency of both, since they called the diploma of Louis sometimes legitimate, sometimes forged, and sometimes interpolated, clearly shows that each one was aware of his own error.
How could it be otherwise?
A single interpolation at first glance seems to confirm the three islands.
But what follows removes suspicion:
"And to the territories, maritime coasts, and ports pertaining to the aforementioned cities and islands."
And again below, where all the rights of the holy see are gathered in one:
Namely, concerning the aforementioned provinces, cities, towns, fortresses, villages, islands, territories, and properties, as well as pensions and taxes.
And finally, thirdly, where he promises to defend the islands together with all the aforementioned things, so that all these may firmly remain under his control for use, enjoyment, and disposal.
What?
No matter which city they come from, those who seek refuge with the Holy See-whether to escape papal authority out of a desire for independence, to incite rebellion, or out of fear of punishment-he promises to take them in.
If their offense is minor, he seeks pardon for them.
If their offense is serious, he sends them back to their own ruler for punishment.
The only exceptions are those who have suffered violence or have been oppressed by the overwhelming power of other citizens and need imperial intervention before the pope.
And don't think these measures are random: Archbishop Leo of Ravenna's audacious act had not been forgotten (Code of Charlemagne, letter 52, also 53).
Without the pope's knowledge, he went to Charlemagne in the year 775 to plot rebellion in the Exarchate.
The example of Adrian had not been erased from memory (Code of Charlemagne, letter 61, also 1).
He demanded the return of certain offenders under his authority from Charlemagne, just as he had sent back a subject of Charlemagne to France two years earlier for the same reason.
A more recent example was also retained (Code of Charlemagne, letter 97, also 85).
In the year 790, he requested Charlemagne to return some people from Ravenna and Pentapolis who wished to withdraw from his obedience.
Inspired by this example, Eccard (History of the Franks, book 25, chapter 38) and an Italian annalist (Annals 789) openly admitted that the Roman pontiff at that time had dominion in the Exarchate and Pentapolis.
Indeed, I see evidence of dominion in the city of Rome just as clearly as in the Exarchate.
In the praised letter (Code of Charlemagne, letter 61, also 50), Adrian not only demands the return of his subjects but also demands that they be punished.
After exaggerating their heinous crimes to Charlemagne, he pleads with him in these words:
"That you rise up manfully, inspired by God, and as a pious king, order lawful vengeance to be executed upon them for their miserable and disgraceful presumption, or deign to send them to us so that Almighty God, looking down from on high, may grant you, etc., for the just punishment we inflict upon them."
Yet, I am not surprised that they acknowledge dominion in the Exarchate but deny it in Rome.
Since some people expect the donation of the City to occur in a different year, with an uncertain type of dominion, it is deeply seated in the minds of French writers that the Roman pontiffs refer their indirect or temporal power to the donations of the Frankish kings.
We hold this opinion to be completely false, as we know for certain that twenty-five years before Pippin, who was the first to expand the pontifical domain, granted the provinces of Emilia and Pentapolis to the exarchate, Gregory the Third, Zacharias, and for some time Stephen the Second, ruled Rome and its duchy.
Other writers, however, having absorbed the same false opinion, and seeing that the praised pontiffs did not abandon the hope of converting the Greeks before the year 753, when Stephen the Second sought protection from them in France, and knowing that the exarchate alone was donated by Pippin and nothing else was added to Pippin's donation until the first arrival of Charles in Rome in the year 774, attribute the donation of the City to Charles in an uncertain year, with uncertain dominion and an uncertain author.
The misconceptions of both kinds of writers are dispelled by the letters of Adrian's predecessors, and there is no reason to tackle them again.
However, I will briefly demonstrate the significant difference that intervenes between the dominion of the City and its duchy and the rest of the apostolic see's domains, for greater clarity of the Ludovician diploma.
Although the supreme pontifical dominion of the City, and therefore its duchy, is confirmed by several letters of the Codex Carolinus, none proves it better than the one (97, also 85) in which the patrician status of Peter is compared with the patrician status of Charles.
From this, Eccard and the Italian annalist are compelled to admit the same supreme dominion in the exarchate, as we said.
Before Charles became emperor, his role in the City was primarily its defense, and later, he shared supreme power with the popes.
When he was designated as patrician in France alongside his father Pippin and his brother Carloman by Stephen the Second in 754, Stephen was the ruler of Rome, just like his predecessors Gregory the Third, Zacharias, and his successor and brother Paul the First.
Paul the First was referred to as "Our Lord decreed by God" in letters to King Pippin and the Roman patrician.
However, this rule did not exclude the involvement of the Roman Senate and the people, who swore an oath of loyalty to the pope as their highest leader while maintaining Roman civil law.
Thus, the Roman pontiff was indeed the highest leader at that time but did not hold absolute power in governing the republic.
Neither Stephen the Fourth nor Saint Paschal tried to introduce anything new to the Senate and people when they later sought support from imperial authority for their supreme power in the City.
The Roman pontiffs traditionally did not change the administration established by their predecessors, ensuring the Senate and People of Rome's role remained intact, reinforced by Louis.
The document's words are clear and need no commentary:
"Just as you have held and managed in your power and authority from your predecessors until now.
Therefore, I wish this to be ratified and confirmed, not to start a new rule under Paschal, but to be reinforced by Emperor Louis.
For almost ninety years, the Senate and People of Rome, breaking away from the impious Greeks, willingly embraced this under Gregory the Third as head of the holy republic, and acknowledged in letters to King Pippin, without any reduction in their own authority, as subsequent times have clearly shown, as I made clear in the preceding dissertation."
In other territories, ruled by the generosity of their leaders, only the Roman pontiff governed as the absolute prince, without any intervention from the senate or the people.
This authority over these lands had been granted to Peter and his successors.
The letters of the Codex Carolinus, which are beyond all dispute, attest to this in many ways:
"What you have bestowed upon blessed Peter for the great reward of your soul," said Paul about the cities of Pentapolis (letter 18, also 15);
and elsewhere (letter 40, also 26) regarding the entire exarchate:
"Those things," he said, "which you promised to blessed Peter and sought to grant for the pardon of your sins, you strive to preserve forever with his inviolate right."
Likewise (letter 42, also 19), he mentions that a donation was made to Blessed Peter and his vicar, our predecessor, my brother of holy memory, Pope Stephen.
In the same context, Adrian (letter 52, also 53) addresses Charlemagne:
"What you have given to blessed Peter for the great reward of your soul and for the stability of the kingdom protected by God."
He accuses Leo, archbishop of Ravenna (letter 53, also 52), of saying about the cities of Emilia, that your excellency did not grant those cities to blessed Peter and us.
Moreover, he recalls in the following letter how you personally offered that same promise to the apostle of God with your own hands.
Finally (letter 59, also 49), speaking of all the patrimonies:
"Which," he said, "through various emperors, patricians, and even other God-fearing people, have been granted for the reward of their souls and the pardon of sins in the regions of Tuscany, Spoleto, Benevento, and Corsica, as well as the Sabina patrimony to blessed Peter the apostle, and to the holy and apostolic Roman Church of God."
I omit many other details which, along with these, have been appropriately repeated here from previous writings; for these few demonstrate the great distinction that exists between the donations of kings and the dominion of the City and its duchy.
Because of this, not even the Suevi, considered the greatest invaders, imitated the Romans.
The Romans, leaving only the title of prince to the pontiffs, usurped the temporal administration of the republic for a long time with stubborn determination.
The defense of the apostles' leader far surpassed that of the Augusti!
The archbishops of Ravenna also dared to challenge this absolute dominion in the exarchate.
But what happened?
Adrian reported to Charles how Stephen the Second overthrew Sergius, who had become too self-assuming.
"We, most excellent son," he says, "just as during the time of Lord Pope Stephen, who went to France and to whom the exarchate was handed over, so in our time, we want to manage and order it under our power. Everyone can recognize the kind of power his thrice-blessedness had over the city of Ravenna and the entire exarchate, as he also removed Archbishop Sergius, who acted with a spirit of pride against his will."
However, Leo's stubbornness was curtailed by a short life; for in the year 777, he passed away, having troubled Adrian for barely three years. After that, no similar example of such audacity is found.
Furthermore, in the year 790, the same pontiff held a similar view regarding the Franks subject to Charles and the people of Ravenna and Pentapolis subject to Blessed Peter and himself:
"Just as your men do not come to the thresholds of the apostles nor to us without your absolution, so our men who wish to come to you must come with our absolution and letter. For just as we always receive your men, urging them to remain in your service with true faith and purity of heart, so we also ask your royal prudence to similarly exhort and admonish any of our men who come to you, as your father of blessed memory..."
Lord Pippin the Great, King, granted them to Saint Peter and his vicar, and later your excellency confirmed it.
Therefore, you should be instructed and urged that they should in no way dare to become proud and arrogant when they come to you, but rather remain humble and submissive in the service of Saint Peter and our commandment.
Encourage them because we will never withdraw from serving and ruling under Saint Peter and his vicar, but will remain in the faith and purity we promised to Saint Peter the apostle until the end of the world.
Now I believe I have clearly explained why Louis, confirming the rule of the Roman pontiffs in the City and its duchy, uses that condition: Just as you have held and disposed of it in your power and rule from your predecessors until now.
Conversely, he clearly confirms the domains granted to the seat through the document of donation, without omitting any condition, to Paschal the supreme pontiff and universal pope and his successors until the end of the world, in such a way that they hold them in their own right of principality and rule.
This was indeed of great importance to validate the sincerity of Louis's document and to reveal his intention.
However, since most of what I have discussed so far is established from the ninety-nine letters of the Codex Carolinus and ten of Leo, edited by Conring, I have rightly called this document the summary of this epistolary history, since it briefly collects and strengthens all the rights of the holy seat.
After this, the discipline of the election and consecration of the Roman pontiff is confirmed: which matter, concerning the predecessors of Stephen the Fourth, can be sought both from the preliminary commentary on the letters of Adrian (number 2 and following) and from the notice to the letters of the false pope Constantine.
The summary is that the election and ordination, or consecration, of the Roman pontiff was entirely free.
This is more and more confirmed by the presence of the legate of King Pippin at the consecration of Paul the First (Cod. Car. epistle 12, or 13).
When he arrived in Rome during the election of the pope, Paul, along with our noblemen, spoke with him and said, "We saw it fit for him to stay here until, by God's providence, we received the sacred apostolic blessing."
Then, fully satisfied with our own purity and that of all the people, and with the love we bear towards your most gracious excellence and all the Frankish people, we would send him back to you with our apostolic envoys.
These envoys would testify to the king that the pope would remain in the same faith, love, and unity of charity and peace, which our most blessed lord and my brother, the most holy pope, confirmed with you.
The discipline of electing and consecrating the pope, and then sending envoys to the king of France to renew the aforementioned concord between the kingdom and the priesthood, is so firm and constant that no example contrary to it can be found.
The usurper Constantine, only after his detestable election and ordination (Codex Carolinus, epistle 43, also 98), sent envoys to the king, promising to remain in your love and faithful affection, following the example of Stephen and Paul, and in sincere friendship.
He repeated and urged this again in the next letter.
The missions and letters of Stephen the Third and Adrian sent to the kings after their consecration do not exist, but the same sentiment is found in other letters from both popes (Epistle 47, 62).
Stephen wrote to Charles and Carloman, the brothers: "In your love and affectionate charity, we firmly remain and will remain with all the people, even to the point of soul and bloodshed."
And Adrian wrote to Charlemagne: "We trust that you will remain in the same faith, love, and promise, in which we also firmly and steadfastly remain, as we promised face to face, with the Lord presiding and blessed Peter, the prince of the apostles, mediating, until the end."
The letters of King Charles, sent through Angilbert and found in Labbe's collection (Council, volume seven, page 1128), confirm that Leo the Third, after his consecration, announced Adrian's death and his own exaltation.
In these letters, Charles expresses his desire to restore the harmony between the priesthood and the kingdom that flourished under Adrian:
"Just as I made a pact with the most blessed predecessor of your holy fatherhood, I wish to establish an unbreakable bond of the same faith and charity with your blessedness."
Given this, I would gladly hear from Pagius and the Italian annalist about the differences they perceive in the words of Louis's diplomas.
They claim that the one whom all Romans, by divine inspiration and the intercession of blessed Peter, elected to the pontificate with one mind and harmony, without any promise, should be consecrated according to canonical custom without any ambiguity or contradiction.
Once consecrated, envoys should be sent to us or our successors, the kings of the Franks, to establish friendship, charity, and peace between us and them.
However, these two men confidently declare the diploma to be a forgery, as they infer from the legation of Leo's successors and the letters to Louis the Pious, Charlemagne's son, mentioned by the Astronomer in the year 816 and following.
Regarding Stephen traveling to France, it is stated that he first sent a legation to satisfy the emperor about his ordination.
And about Paschal: After completing the solemn consecration, he sent envoys with an apologetic letter and great gifts to the emperor, indicating that he had been compelled to this dignity by election and the people's acclamation, rather than by ambition or will.
They claim these letters are less doubtful signs of imperial confirmation.
Indeed, what was decreed in the Lateran Council of 769, to prevent any detriment to the supreme election and consecration of the pontiff, is reaffirmed here: without any promise.
This further confirms the integrity of the diploma.
Because what had once been established to avert the heresy of Simony
(Council of Chalcedon, chapter 2; Symmachus to Caesar, letter 5, title 2; Hormisdas to the bishops of Spain, letter 25, chapter 2),
is now found to be renewed by new decrees and sanctions for Italy, the Kingdom of Lombardy, Tuscany, the Exarchate, and even for the Kingdom of the Franks.
For that pestilence was spreading far and wide at that time.
Therefore, in the year 790
(Codex Carolinus, letter 97, or 84),
Adrian wrote to Charles:
"Many funds are seen to have been alienated through such wicked payments, so that not having gold and silver anymore, even the properties of the Churches are found to be alienated through written leases."
And a little below, regarding the ordination of bishops and their examination:
"We solemnly ask,
inquire: See that you have made no promise or payment to anyone, because it is Simoniacal and against the canons."
Charles himself, in the year 795, in a memorandum
(Council, volume VII, page 1129),
especially wanted to remind Leo the Pontiff through Angilbert:
"You should most diligently persuade him to abolish the Simoniacal heresy, which stains the holy body of the Church badly in many places."
What more? In the year 816, when Stephen the Fourth, who was imitated the following year by Paschal, announced his election to Emperor Louis the Pious as free from any stain after his consecration, the same emperor issued a capitulary
(book I, chapter 84)
also reported by Labbeus
(Council, volume VII, page 1479),
in which these things are read:
"Not ignorant of the sacred canons, so that in God's name the holy Church might more freely enjoy its honor, we have given assent to the ecclesiastical order, that bishops should be elected according to the statutes of the canons by the choice of the clergy and people from their own diocese, with the exclusion of persons and rewards, on account of their merit of life and gift of wisdom."
Considering these facts, it is astonishing to read in Pagi
(817, number 7)
after that part of the diploma about sending a legation to us, or to our successors, kings of the Franks, that this inference, full of falsehood and audacity, was made.
That is a complete fabrication.
While Louis the Pious was alive, Pope Eugene the Second, at the request of Lothair, co-ruler of his father's empire, decreed that the Roman pontiff should not be consecrated unless in the presence of imperial envoys.
This proposition does not make sense to a rational person:
The rule for creating the Roman pontiff, confirmed in Louis' diploma in the year 817, is fictitious.
In the year 825, Lothair, son of Louis, obtained a privilege from Eugene the Second stating that henceforth Roman pontiffs should not be consecrated without the presence of imperial envoys.
Additionally, the falsity of that privilege has been observed by Baronius, Cointius, Natalis, Papebrochius, and various Catholic authors.
Even Italian annalists find that privilege from the year 825 very suspicious, although Eccard embraces it with open arms by altering the chronology to fit his opinion.
But neither Eccard nor the annalists remove the falsehood of the time with this remedy.
The privilege does not rest on any serious authority;
Rather, its mention exists in a supplement to the Lombard history, which is falsely attributed to Paul Warnefrid by an imposter, according to the custom of such people.
To give credence to their compilations, they borrow the name of some illustrious writer.
Thus, after the booklet about the bishops of Metz, it reads:
Year.
In the year 825, Emperor Lotharius returned to Italy and celebrated Mass for Saint Martin in Rome.
This is the oath he ordered the Roman clergy and people, along with Pope Eugene, to take:
"I therefore promise by Almighty God, and by these sacred four Gospels, and by this cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, and by the body of the most blessed Peter, prince of the apostles, that from this day forward I will be faithful to our lords, Emperors Louis and Lotharius, as long as I live, to the best of my ability and understanding, without deceit or evil intent, while maintaining the faith I promised to the lord apostolic.
I also promise that I will not consent to any election of a pope in this Roman seat that is not conducted canonically and justly, according to my ability and understanding.
And the elected person shall not be consecrated as pope with my consent until he makes such an oath in the presence of the emperor's envoy and the people, with an oath similar to the one Pope Eugene made in writing for the preservation of all."
To address the misconception held by Pagii and his followers, I believe the true constitution of Eugene and Lotharius, given in the atrium of Saint Peter the Apostle in the year 824, should be referenced here (Coll. Rom. part II, p. 207), which we will see almost entirely confirmed in the privileges of Otto and Henry.
Regarding the election of the pope, the pope and the emperor established in chapter 111:
"In the election of the Roman pontiff, no one, whether free or slave, should presume to cause any impediment.
But only those Romans, to whom it was anciently granted by the constitution of the holy Fathers, should elect the pope.
If anyone presumes to act against this constitution of ours, they shall be exiled."
Indeed, I dare not deny that the consecration of the pope has again succumbed to the yoke of imperial confirmation. However, the age of this new subjection is certain, the causes are certain, and the condition is certain, which demonstrate that it was far different from the old usurpation by the Goths and the emperors of the East.
The annals of Bertiniani describe the year 844 like this: Pope Gregory the Fourth of the Roman Church passed away, and Sergius the Second succeeded him, taking his place.
When Sergius was ordained to the apostolic seat, Lothair sent his son Louis, along with Drogo, the bishop of Metz, to ensure that no one would be ordained bishop without his command and the presence of his envoys.
When they arrived in Rome, they were honorably received.
After completing their mission, the Roman pope consecrated Louis as king with anointing and decorated him with a belt.
Drogo, the bishop, was appointed as his vicar for the regions of Gaul and Germany.
If such a privilege isn't older than the year 844, then it wasn't Eugene the Second who granted it to Lothair's son Louis twenty years earlier, but Sergius the Second who granted it to Louis.
However, the fabricator, a false deacon, distorted names and years, and from a genuine privilege, he forged the false one we heard about.
But the fabricator, Pagus, and all those hostile to the apostolic seat in their own destruction, are accused by the false fabrication itself.
For they constantly read the privileges of Otto and Henry, which confirm the credibility of the false matter: "What kind of promise our lord and venerable spiritual father Leo is known to have made willingly." This more and more confirms the age of the privilege; for Leo the Fourth, succeeding Sergius the Second, although consecrated without the command of the prince due to fear of Saracen invasions, still affirmed the privilege granted by his predecessor through a promise made willingly.
And the Liber Pontificalis, a witness above all exception, will support the true and false privilege. Behold the entire ceremony of the election and consecration of Valentine, who succeeded Eugene the Second in the year 827, without the presence of an imperial envoy, and without any promise or oath: elected by the voices of the noble populace and the joyful soldiers of both Roman armies to the seat of the pontiffs.
With appropriate praises of glory and grandeur, he was led to the Lateran Patriarchate and placed on the pontifical throne.
The entire Roman senate joyfully kissed his feet.
After all the necessary rites and ceremonies were performed reverently and properly, there was great sobriety and joy among the people of all ages and sexes.
On the day of his consecration, at the break of dawn, they led the bishop from the Palace to the church of Saint Peter, the prince of the apostles.
With the help of divine majesty, they consecrated him as the supreme pontiff on a high throne.
In contrast, regarding the successor of Sergius the Second, Leo the Fourth, section 497: Terrified by fear and future events, they consecrated him as bishop without the prince's permission.
About the successor of the same Leo, Benedict the Third, section 558: The clergy and all the nobles fortified the decree with their own hands and, as ancient custom demands, sent it to the most invincible emperors, Lothair and Louis.
After Gregory the Third in the year 107, the ancient custom of sending the election decree to the prince was restored.
In the year 847, during the election of Leo the Fourth, imminent danger to the city prevented the imperial orders and envoys from being awaited.
Therefore, the age of this kind of restoration is so certain that it should not be doubted based on unreliable documents.
A specific cause preceded this restoration of ancient subjection.
Sergius allowed the apostolic see to again bear the yoke that had been cast off long ago because Louis had approved the canonical election of Gregory the Fourth in the year 827.
Upon the death of Valentine, after a brief pontificate of forty days, Gregory the Fourth was duly elected.
He firmly refused the supreme honor, and Louis's authority intervened before the consecration of the elected pontiff.
This is testified by the Astronomer in the Life of Louis the Pious: Gregory, priest of the title.
Saint Mark was chosen, but his consecration was delayed until the emperor was consulted.
With the emperor's approval and the agreement of the clergy and people, he was ordained in place of the previous one.
This event is confirmed by the annals of Eginhard and the words of the Bertiniani:
He was not ordained until the emperor's envoy came to Rome and examined the people's election.
Pagius and others use these testimonies to support the supposed constitution of Eugene and Lothair, which we have mentioned.
However, as these same annals report the election and consecration of Valentine without any mention of imperial consent, they show that the emperor's authority was invoked because Gregory refused, to ensure a canonical and just election, rather than attributing such an unjust usurpation to the pious emperor.
Besides, if they try to weaken the discipline confirmed by Louis the Pious in the year 817 in the diploma we are discussing with these later arguments, I have already mentioned how significant this type of argument should be considered.
Moreover, the certain cause of the renewed subjection was the invocation of the aforementioned imperial authority: the restorer was Sergius the Second at the request of Lothair, son of Louis.
While his pious father lived, he did not attempt anything new, but after Louis died in the year 840, and Gregory the Fourth also died at the beginning of 844, when the Romans, for the sake of that period's discipline, elected and ordained Sergius without consulting the emperor, he sent Louis the son to the city to obtain the aforementioned privilege from the apostolic see.
Indeed, I would not dare to define whether Lothair, due to the animosities that had arisen between him and Gregory, because Gregory had refused to abandon the friendship of his father Louis and adhere to him, or for some other secret reason, following the example of Gregory who had taken on the pontificate with imperial authority, sought that privilege from the apostolic see.
This I know for certain: neither Lothair nor his son Louis from the Carolingian emperors, nor any of the Goths or Eastern emperors from Germany, imitated this in any way.
It was not by a privilege attached to the imperial dignity, but by an apostolic concession, that they considered the elections of the Roman pontiffs valid during their lifetime, as will be evident from the elections of these pontiffs.
During the times of Charlemagne and Louis the Pious, Leo the Third, Stephen the Fourth, Paschal the First, Eugene the Second, Valentine, and Gregory the Fourth were elected.
For Gregory the Fourth alone, the necessary confirmation of the election was requested by the clergy and people, due to chance and necessity, from the reluctantly elected one.
An irrefutable argument is the election of Sergius the Second, who succeeded Gregory the Fourth, and his consecration without consulting Lothair at all.
Another argument comes from Gregory the Fourth himself: unlike Saint Gregory the Great, his predecessor, or Saint Gregory the Seventh, during whose time imperial confirmation was required, he did not write supplicating letters to the Emperor to confirm his election.
Aware of the discipline of his time, he first hid and then firmly testified through his constancy that he rejected such a burden.
However, after Louis the Second obtained the apostolic privilege by order of his father Lothair, Leo the Fourth, Benedict the Third, Nicholas the First, Adrian the Second, and John the Eighth were inaugurated over a span of twenty-five years according to this discipline established by papal authority.
It was different for the nine successors of John the Eighth elected over sixteen years from 882 to 898, namely Martin the Second, Adrian the Third, Stephen the Fifth, Formosus, Boniface the Sixth, Stephen the Sixth, Romanus, Theodore the Second, and John the Ninth.
All of them were ordained without the order of the prince or the presence of his envoys, showing that this personal privilege was lacking for Charles the Fat and his successors.
Forty-three pontiffs were elected and consecrated during the reign of Charles the Fat.
The last one, Stephen the Fifth, displeased the emperor for reasons unknown to us, as he was created without his knowledge.
The Fulda Annals (in Freher, vol. 1, p. 60) also report this and illustrate how futile the emperor's complaint was regarding his Roman pontiff.
Upon the death of Stephen, they appointed someone else in his place.
This angered the emperor because they made such an appointment without consulting him.
He sent Liutward and some bishops of the Roman See to remove the new appointee, but they couldn't do it.
The pope, through his envoys, sent the names of more than 30 bishops, all the priests and deacons of the cardinals, as well as lower-ranking individuals and lay leaders of the region.
They had all unanimously elected him and supported his ordination of 118.
I will skip discussing the opinions of others, especially those who attribute to Adrian III the decree concerning the freedom of consecration from then on, for the sake of brevity.
However, I firmly believe that only these two among the Carolingians used this personal privilege.
In the sixteen years following the death of John VIII until the creation of John IX in 898, many evils occurred, and John's election was disrupted by the Sergian schism.
This pope realized that handling such a significant matter with imperial authority would be beneficial.
Therefore, in the same year, he convened a council, as mentioned in volume IX, page 502, and, due to other serious causes, decreed the renewal of this privilege.
He stated in chapter 10: "Because the holy Roman Church, which we preside over by the grace of God, suffers many abuses when the pope passes away, these abuses occur because the consecration of the pope happens without the knowledge of the emperor and without the presence of his envoys. Thus, we want this to be abolished, and the pope to be elected in the presence of the gathered bishops and all the clergy, requested by the senate and the people. Then, having been most famously elected in the sight of all, he should be consecrated in the presence of the imperial envoys."
No one should be forced to swear an oath or make promises through new inventions, except those required by ancient customs, so that the Church is not scandalized, and the emperor's honor remains intact.
If you look into the history of that time, you'll see how pointless the restoration of this privilege was.
At the end of the year 899, Arnulf, the last of the Carolingians, died while John the Ninth was still alive.
Around that time, Emperor Arnulf passed away on November 29 and was honorably buried in Regensburg, where his father, Carloman, the brother of Charles the Fat, is also buried, as recorded in the Annals of Metz.
The Annals of Fulda, according to Freher, mark the year as 900, with a slight difference of about one month.
In the same declining year, John died, and with no emperor, Benedict the Fourth was elected and consecrated.
Pope Benedict crowned Louis the Third as emperor in 902, but Louis was captured and blinded by his rival Berengar, leading to a miserable and uncertain life under Pope Benedict.
Therefore, it's clear that his six successors-Leo the Fifth, Christopher, Sergius the Third, Anastasius the Third, Landus, and John the Tenth-were elected and consecrated without any emperor's approval.
However, John the Tenth crowned Berengar as emperor in 916, but Berengar died while John was still pope.
Even if Berengar had obtained a privilege, which no one claims, he couldn't have used it.
Later, Marozia and the counts of Tusculum usurped control of the City and its duchy for thirty-eight years, refusing to be subject to both papal and imperial power.
You can read about this in Liudprand.
The venerable Cardinal Baronius rightly condemns the perversity of that age.
Indeed, in Rome, both sacred and secular matters were entangled with factions, making the promotion to the apostolic see of the Roman pontiff dependent on whichever party seemed more powerful.
As a result, sometimes the leaders of the Romans and sometimes the princes of Etruria would use their secular power to install their chosen candidate and depose any Roman pontiff promoted by the opposing faction.
These actions continued throughout much of this century until the German emperors, particularly the Ottos, intervened, arrogantly claiming for themselves the right to elect and depose the pope.
It's clear that this invasion by the princes was more a sign of the corrupted discipline of that iron tenth century than a continuation of a privilege granted by the apostolic see to the emperors.
Moreover, from the following privileges, it is evident that Otto and Henry ignored the decree of John the Ninth, as it was never implemented, instead confirming the discipline from the times of Eugenius the Second and Leo the Fourth.
Hence, the mention of the privilege granted only to Louis, at the request of Sergius the Second, to his father Lothair, which Louis also used, is well known and verified.
However, from the decree of Nicholas the Second in the council held in Rome in 1059 regarding the election of the Roman pontiff, it is clear that this was a personal privilege for the German emperors, if any of them were found to have used it.
"Let him be chosen," he says, "from the clergy of that Church if a suitable one is found; or if not, let him be taken from another, with due honor and reverence to our beloved son Henry, who is currently considered king and hoped to be the future emperor, God permitting, as we have already granted him, and to his successors who have personally obtained this right from the apostolic see."
This monument could not be more appropriate to refute the opinions of Pagi and the Italian annalist, who confidently, yet recklessly, assert that the imperial right was the confirmation of the papal election.
Nicholas clearly stated that he had granted that privilege to King Henry IV in 120, and it could be used by anyone who personally obtained it from the Apostolic See, as shown in the acts of the Vatican regarding the creation of Saint Gregory the Seventh, as attested by Baronius (1073, no. 27).
Following the example of Gregory the Great, he quickly sent messengers to King Henry, revealing the election made from above and earnestly begging him not to give his assent.
If King Henry did not comply, it was certain to Nicholas that he would not tolerate more serious and manifest excesses without punishment.
However, as soon as the king understood the truth of the election, he gave his assent and sent Gregory, the bishop of Vercelli and chancellor of the kingdom of Italy, to the City to confirm the election with royal authority and attend to his consecration, which was done without delay.
This entirely removes the stain from the Carolingians and the German emperors, which the often-praised two men adhering to the sectarians impute to both.
They had not imitated Odoacer and the Eastern emperors by attributing to themselves a matter which, without the authority of the Apostolic See, is mere usurpation.
It was not only the emperors who acquired a share in the supreme pontifical power along with the imperial diadem, but also the kings, who, by the constant confession of all, had nothing to do with the City and urban affairs, obtained such a privilege from the supreme pontiffs.
Did it seem to Saint Gregory the Seventh, who was about to decline the pontificate, that he should not follow the examples of his predecessors and should completely free the Holy See from that subjection?
I would be lying, says Baronius (1085, no. 12), if these things could not already be shown by the experience of present matters-namely, that Gregory recovered the investitures of churches from the hands of princes, restored the free election of Roman pontiffs by postliminium, completely repaired the collapsed ecclesiastical discipline, and brought about many other countless benefits.
And indeed, nowhere will you find any further need for imperial or royal consent for the ordination of Roman pontiffs.
Therefore, it can safely be said that only two emperors from the Carolingians and King Henry from the Germans used this privilege.
Regarding the six German emperors who preceded that king, we must think differently.
The three Ottos, who followed the corrupt practices of the 10th century, should not be considered at all.
Saint Henry, crowned by Pope Benedict the Eighth, never deviated from what was right and just, given his piety.
However, both he and Benedict died within a short span in the year 1024.
John the Nineteenth, a layman, was then elevated to the pontificate at the age of 21 through bribery, as Glaber mentions according to Baronius (1024, n. 4), and was confirmed by no one.
It is never found that Benedict the Ninth, elected similarly, was confirmed by Conrad the Second.
Only Henry the Second, King of Germany, is noted for using this privilege for the third time.
However, since he did not obtain it through apostolic authority, I do not consider him comparable to the two Carolingians either.
Peter Damian (Disceptationes inter regem adversum et Romanae Ecclesiae defensorem, Conciliorum tomus IX, p. 1159) held the same opinion as me before.
I will bring the exact words here; for it is of no small importance to restrict this privilege to one King Henry the Fourth, which the Italian annalists considered an imperial right.
The royal advocate is introduced speaking thus: "The father of my lord, the king of blessed memory, Henry the emperor, was made patrician of the Romans, from whom he received the preeminent role in the election concerning the ordination of the pontiff.
Additionally, what is more outstanding is that Pope Nicholas granted this privilege to my lord the king, which he had already inherited from his father, and confirmed it through a page of synodal decree."
The advocate of the Roman Church, relying on the authority of Emperor Henry, also holds the right of the Roman people; and venerating only the authority of the holy see, he states: "We defend this privilege for our most invincible king as well, and wish that he may possess it fully and intact."
Then he shows that the ordination of Alexander the Second was done without his consent because he was still underage.
Indeed, we have recently seen that Gregory, Alexander's successor, was mindful of the same privilege.
Anyone who thinks differently about this matter is supporting corrupt practices and mixing usurpation with the tolerance of the popes, attributing more than is due to the emperors, to the great detriment of papal authority.
So much for the privilege of Henry the Fourth.
But when Otto and Henry praise the constitution of Eugenius the Second and the voluntary promise of Leo the Fourth in their privileges, from which the patchwork mentioned above (n. 35) originated, it is worth understanding from almost contemporary historians what the true discipline of papal election and consecration should have been during the time of the Germans, and what should be attributed to Eugenius and Leo.
The Astronomer narrates in the Life of Louis the Pious (Pithou's edition, p. 222) how Lothair, sent to Rome by his father, was warmly received by Pope Eugenius.
When he complained about the events that had taken place, specifically why those who had been loyal to the emperor and the Franks were unjustly killed and those who survived were left to be ridiculed and held in contempt, and why such great complaints against the Roman pontiffs and judges were heard, it was found that, due to either the ignorance or negligence of some pontiffs and the blind and insatiable greed of the judges, many estates had been unjustly confiscated.
Therefore, by restoring what had been unjustly taken, Lothair created great joy among the Roman people.
The annals attributed to Eginhard report the same matter:
When he (Eugenius) revealed the state of the Roman people, long corrupted by the perversity of certain prelates, he corrected it with the benevolent assent of the mentioned pontiff, so that all who had been gravely desolated by the plundering of their possessions were magnificently consoled by the restoration of their goods, which had come about through his arrival, by the grace of God.
Eugenius' predecessors were Saint Leo the Third, Stephen the Fourth, and Saint Paschal the First.
The Astronomer rightly accuses judges of greed and calls the popes ignorant or lazy, rather than corrupt, as any chronicler might do.
Besides, the privileges granted by Otto and Henry are said to cause unreasonable harshness towards the people subject to them.
The constitution made by Eugenius and Lothair restrains this chronicler's excessive freedom, as we will see when we discuss these privileges.
But let's set aside these trivial matters: the oath imposed by Lothair and Eugenius on the Romans, as mentioned in the aforementioned compilation about the canonical and just election of the pope, seems very likely to be true if certain.
However, what is claimed there about a voluntary promise made by Eugenius, which is clearly a lie, reveals the deception of pseudo-Warnefrid.
Otto, Henry, the papal archive, and the Pontifical Book bear witness, and thus the voluntary promise should be delayed until the consecration of Leo the Fourth in 847, after the privilege granted three years earlier by Sergius the Second.
Leo is said to have made this promise voluntarily because of the fear of the Saracens, as neither an order nor an envoy from the emperor had been expected.
Therefore, that promise was not necessary.
In section 46, we saw that this discipline had already been established by Lothair and Louis the Pious, and then was unsuccessfully revived by John the Ninth in 900.
It was confirmed in the great corruption of the 10th century by Otto and Henry, but it was never put into practice.
Finally, we find it was only observed in the creation of Gregory the Seventh, who abolished it.
Now, let's return to Pagi's objection, who believes the Ludovician diploma is a mere fabrication because it presents a discipline entirely different from the one instituted about thirty years later.
Isn't that passing judgment on entirely unexplored matters?
Any sensible person would disregard the remaining objections.
When he claims that none of the Roman popes remember the donation of Louis the Pious, and Otto and Henry mention the donations of Pepin and Charlemagne but are silent about Louis's, he shows his own ignorance.
He hasn't understood the nature of the documents that confirm all the rights of the Holy See, without adding even an inch of land to the ancient donations.
Similarly, when he thinks that Sicily and other islands were granted to the Apostolic See by Louis, with all due respect, he is grossly mistaken.
To prove a document false, which learned men recognize as legitimate, you need to uncover words and formulas in it that don't fit the age it claims to be from.
Just as Ludwig (Preface to the collection of manuscripts of all ages,  22) declared a supposed diploma of Charlemagne for Frisia to be false because it mentioned Feudal Law, always August, Duchy of Saxony, feudal dependencies of the empire, King of Saxony, council of the faithful, consent of the princes of the empire, subscriptions of the King of Bohemia, Marquis of Meissen, and Landgrave of Thuringia.
No matter how much effort the creators of some forgery put into imitating the character of a distant age, they inevitably fall into the customs of their own time.
Indeed, if Pagius and the Italian annalist had objected to any of these things, I would be ashamed to argue so vehemently for the validity of the document.
But to the objections of Pagius, which I said should be regarded with contempt rather than refuted, the praised annalist adds one more.
This is more fitting for a current case than for reviewing old monuments (year 817); namely, that the diploma did not originate from the chancellery of Louis because it lacks a date, which is a sign that only an incomplete example of it survives.
But who among the learned has ever dared to affirm that the autographs of the diplomas of Pepin, Charlemagne, and Louis have come down to us late descendants?
Nevertheless, they gain such credibility from the Carolingian Code and other annalistic monuments that the lack of autographs is consistently judged to be a very minor loss.
The medieval Italian geographer Pagio and the annalist serve as substitutes.
However, whatever truth exists in their table relies heavily on that key source.
He would rather be like a person who drills a hole in the ship he himself is sailing on than oppose the aforementioned authorities, whose words he swears by.
Despite the given defects, or rather external flaws, common to other monuments not of such great antiquity, they do little harm to the Ludovician manuscripts.
It was given at the Aachen assembly in the year 817, on the sixth day before the Kalends of July, as read at the beginning (Council, volume 7, page 1507).
In the year of the incarnation of our Lord Jesus Christ 817, in the fourth year of the reign of the most glorious prince Louis, on the sixth day before the Ides of July, several abbots with their monks gathered in the house of the Aachen palace, called Lateran.
Among them was Joshua, abbot of the Volturno monastery, very dear to the pope, as taught by Mabillon (Annals, book 28, number 45), who provided the monastery's document to its chronicler, as mentioned (number 9 and following).
What must be particularly noted in the diploma are the ancient subscriptions, said to have been added to the donation first made by King Pepin at Carisiac.
Regarding the Pepinian donation, the Book of the Popes (section 318) relates this in the Life of Adrian: That promise which King Pepin, and the most excellent Charles with his brother Carloman, and all the judges of the Franks made to the blessed Peter and his most saintly memory lord Stephen the younger pope.
And elsewhere (section 253) it was said: Sent to be possessed by the blessed Peter and the holy Roman Church and all the popes of the apostolic see forever, which remains stored in the archive of our holy Church to this day.
I don't see how the end of Louis's diploma differs from the following:
We sent Theodore, the nomenclator, as the legate of the Holy Roman Church to Lord Pope Paschal.
The subscriptions of the emperor, his sons, bishops, abbots, counts, and palatine officials are listed in the diploma itself, as noted by both the Volturnensi and the Cassinensi chroniclers.
This is considered the greatest evidence of antiquity, as gathered from Anselm of Lucca.
Unless the author of the collection attributed to him is somewhat more recent, Anselm took up the episcopate of Lucca in the year 1073, when Gregory the Seventh began his pontificate.
In his collection of canons, later expanded by Gratian, Anselm included from the privileges of Otto and Henry the chapter on the election of the pope, Book Six, Chapter Thirty-Five.
He says at the end:
"And both emperors signed in their own time, and twenty-three bishops, six abbots, thirteen counts, and seventeen nobles, whose names we will see below in both privileges; namely, ten bishops in Otto's, and thirteen in Henry's; and so with the others joined together by Anselm."
Therefore, it cannot be denied that a copy of Louis's diploma has reached us. It is a copy of great antiquity, known to Anselm, Book Four, Chapter Thirty-Five, as well as the other two, not from autographs, but from those examples mentioned at the beginning, number two and following. The main part was the complete Louis document, with the other two contracted, as evident from the review of the subscriptions.