On the Prophet Haggai
by Haymo of Halberstadt
The prophet Haggai, whose name means festive or solemn, foretold the restoration of the Lord's temple, the downfall of nations, the shaking of the world, and, using Zerubbabel as a figure, predicted the coming of Christ.
He was among those who had recently returned from the Babylonian captivity under Zerubbabel, the priest Joshua, and Ezra.
Jerusalem was not yet rebuilt, nor was the temple of the Lord.
The people were living in low and humble houses, and because of this, the word of the Lord was not directed to them.
They were deemed unworthy to receive it, as they had no concern for rebuilding the temple, being content with their modest dwellings.
They were under Darius, king of Persia, whose name means "generation not made," or refers to those who serve the works of the flesh and lust. Such a king was fitting for a people who were without the temple of God and who lived not on Mount Zion, but below.
Chapter One
In the second year of Darius, king of Persia, in the sixth month, on the first day of the month, the word of the Lord came by the hand of Haggai the prophet.
The number two is often associated with negative connotations.
It divides the first unity and can signify either marital union or discord.
In Genesis, it is mentioned that God saw that it was good at the end of all the other days, but this is not stated at the end of the second day.
In the sixth month, there is also no legal feast, unlike in other months, because it signifies the works and labors of servitude.
Thus, it is fitting that in the second year of Darius and in the sixth month, the word of God comes to Haggai for the aforementioned reasons.
They did not have a temple and lived in hollow places, and under Darius, they were serving carnal works.
However, since the altar was already built and the foundations of the temple laid, the word of the Lord came on the first day of the month, so that they, leaving the second year of Darius, might return to the unity of God.
The phrase "the word of the Lord came by the hand of Haggai" shows that he had good works and that the word of God rested in these deeds.
Haggai means festive.
This implies that whoever strives to celebrate the feasts of the Lord, not with the leaven of malice and wickedness but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth, can receive the word of God.
To Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, the governor of Judah, and to Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, saying.
This Shealtiel, whose son Zerubbabel is said to be, was the son of Jeconiah the king, who was taken to Babylon.
Zerubbabel means flowing adjacent, exposed, or born in Babylon, or a prince in Babylon.
He signifies Christ Jesus, who built the temple to God the Father from living stones, that is, the faithful of both Testaments.
He is exposed to us as a very abundant flowing stream for drinking.
But to be able to drink from this, we must ask God, which Shealtiel his father implies, for Shealtiel means the petition of God.
Here, he was born in Babylon, and Christ, the Son of God, appeared incarnate in the confusion of this world to rescue us, who were held captive by sin, and to lead us back to the promised land.
The word of the Lord came to Zerubbabel and also to Joshua, the high priest.
Historically, there were two men: one from the tribe of Judah and of royal lineage, and the other from the priestly tribe.
Mystically, however, they both represented the same Christ, who is the true king and great high priest.
As king, Zerubbabel was his type; as priest, Joshua, the son of Jozadak, represented him, that is, the Lord is just.
For God the Father is just and holy, and his Son is Jesus Christ, our Lord and Savior.
The Lord of hosts says this: "This people says: 'The time has not yet come to build the house of the Lord.'" It was not Zerubbabel or Joshua, the high priest, who said this, but the people who had returned from captivity and were still under Darius. Similarly, everyone who serves the pleasures of the flesh does not want to build a temple for the Lord of chastity within the seat of their heart. This can also refer to the Jews of this time, who expect the Antichrist instead of Christ and say that it is not yet the time for the Church because Christ has not yet come.
And the word of the Lord came through the hand of Haggai the prophet, saying: "Is it time for you to live in paneled houses, while this house lies in ruins?" In response to what the people were saying, "The time has not yet come to build the house of the Lord," the Lord replied: "Then it is not the time for you to live in well-built and decorated houses, which are not only for use but for pleasure. And you say it is not yet time to build my house, in which were the holy of holies and the cherubim, which now lie in desolation, scorched by heat, and drenched by rain."
And now, this is what the Lord of hosts says: "Give careful thought to your ways." Because you say: "The time has not yet come to build the house of the Lord," consider what you have done and what you have suffered.
For all your hard work, you have achieved nothing.
You've sown a lot but reaped very little and gathered much less than you planted.
However, you cannot say that hunger followed because the farmer was lazy.
You've eaten, but you are not satisfied; you've drunk, but you are not filled; you've clothed yourselves, but you are not warm.
And the one who earned wages put them into a bag with holes.
Yet, you cannot say it was voluntary fasting, but because you gathered few fruits in your barns.
You drank wine, but not enough to gladden the hearts of those drinking.
Even the clothing could not drive away the cold or warm you.
If anyone earned wages, whether through trade or as a hired hand, they labored in vain because all the money flowed away as if put into a bag with holes.
Spiritually, those who place their hearts on their ways are the ones who do nothing without the judgment of discretion and always have the lamp of God's word before their mind's eyes.
One who sows much but gathers little is one who toils constantly in the work of preaching but receives very little fruit from the faith and actions of the listeners, while showing them scandalized by word and example.
He eats and is not satisfied; he drinks and is not filled, who does not practice what he knows to be right.
Hence Solomon says: The righteous eats and fills his soul, but the belly of the wicked is insatiable.
He puts the gathered wages into a bag with holes, who performs acts of virtue for the sake of empty glory, or who gives alms to the needy from stolen goods.
He clothes himself but is not warmed, who receives divine wisdom to adorn himself and be defended from the cold of wickedness, but by executing it lukewarmly and slothfully, he is deprived of its warmth.
This says the Lord of hosts: Set your hearts on your ways.
Go up to the mountain, bring wood, and build the house.
Consider everything you do, and leave behind the concern for your homes.
Go up to the mountain of Lebanon, cut down wood, and build my house.
And it will be acceptable to me, and I will be glorified, says the Lord.
Why does He command to bring wood only and not stones?
The Hebrews say it's because after the temple was burned, the walls remained, so only wood was needed for rebuilding.
Mystically, to ascend the mountain is to rise to the height of divine contemplation through the progress of virtues and to search the testimonies of the Scriptures so that the temple acceptable to the Lord may be built from them.
You looked for more, and behold, it became less; you brought it into the house, and I blew it away.
I will say (He says) something else that happened to you.
When the time for harvesting was near, and you thought you were about to hold the grain in your hands, you harvested empty stalks and gathered straw without grains.
But even the small amount that was selected from large heaps, when you brought it into your houses, I blew it away, and by my power, it was scattered and reduced to nothing.
Spiritually, they look for more and receive less, who, boasting about their works, falsely promise themselves eternal reward from the Lord.
For this reason, says the Lord of hosts, because my house is deserted, and you hurry each to his own house.
Mystically, they hurry to their own house, leaving God's house deserted, who, caught by worldly desires and occupied with earthly activities, neglect to build the temple of God.
Because of this, the heavens have withheld dew over you, and the earth has withheld its produce.
Not only (He says) did the heavens not give rain, but not even the morning dew, so that the drying fields might at least be tempered by a little moisture.
Typically, the heavens are the apostles, pouring the dew and rain of heavenly doctrine into the hearts of the listeners.
The heavens were forbidden to give dew when the word of salvation was spurned by the faithless Jews, and the apostles were commanded to go into the entire world and preach to the nations.
And I called for a drought upon the land, the mountains, the wheat, the wine, the oil, and everything the ground produces.
This drought was also called upon humans, animals, and all the labor of hands.
The drought first affects the land and everything it produces, and ultimately impacts humans and animals.
With famine comes death for humans and animals, and the same sword consumes all that human hands have labored over.
Zerubbabel, son of Shealtiel, Joshua, son of Jehozadak the high priest, and all the remnant of the people heard the voice of the Lord their God and the words of Haggai the prophet, as the Lord had sent him to them.
The people feared before the Lord.
It's important to note that neither Zerubbabel nor Joshua the priest are said to have feared, only the people did.
This is because each signifies Christ, who is both king and priest in the two natures of God and man in one person.
Therefore, when Zerubbabel and Joshua the high priest heard the words of the Lord, only the multitude, who had not yet become a perfect man, feared before the Lord.
This means they feared His indignation, as the face of the Lord is against those who do evil.
Then Haggai, the messenger of the Lord among the messengers of the Lord, spoke to the people:
Some have mistakenly believed that Haggai was an angel who had assumed a human body because it is said: Haggai, the messenger of the Lord, spoke.
They think the same of Malachi and John the Baptist.
However, it should be known that they were human by nature but angels by office, meaning messengers who announced God's will to the people.
Thus, this prophet is called a messenger, or an angel, because he bore the type of the Lord the Savior, who is also called the angel of great counsel.
As it says: The messenger of the Lord among the messengers of the Lord, it means a prophet among prophets.
I am with you, says the Lord.
This message is not directed to Zerubbabel or Joshua but to the people who feared before the Lord.
They are received in the person of Christ, as it has been said, and the Lord was always with them and in them.
Therefore, the Lord strengthens the people, saying: I am with you, I will be your helper.
And the Lord stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel the governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua, son of Jozadak the high priest, and the spirit of the rest of the people.
The spirit of Zerubbabel and the spirit of Joshua were stirred up so that the kingdom and the priesthood might build the temple.
The spirit of the rest of the people was stirred up, that is, their devotion of mind and will, to do what the Lord had commanded.
They entered and did the work in the house of the Lord of Hosts, their God.
They entered because they had gone out, meaning they had forgotten themselves, like the prodigal son, of whom it is said that he came to himself when he decided to return to his father.
Chapter Two
On the twenty-fourth day of the sixth month in the second year of King Darius, they began to build.
This was the same year and month mentioned earlier, but not the same day.
The first day was mentioned earlier; here, it is the twenty-fourth day.
From this, we see that between the first day when the Lord spoke through Haggai and the twenty-fourth day when they began to work, there were twenty-two days.
Interestingly, there are twenty-two letters in the Hebrew alphabet.
This indicates that the people needed to be taught and to learn the basics of God's word.
Mystically, as long as we are in this life, we live as if under Darius, because the flesh opposes the spirit, and the spirit opposes the flesh.
In the sixth month, when God completed His creation, and in the second year, when the restoration of offspring is confirmed, we must fear the Lord, and engage in His works.
This means building a temple for the Lord within ourselves from virtues.
The twenty-fourth day, which doubles the number twelve, represents the faithful gathered from both Jewish and Gentile peoples, who will build the spiritual temple.
Additionally, a tripled eight makes twenty-four: because circumcision, which was performed on the eighth day, and the construction of the spiritual temple, are founded in the faith of the Holy Trinity.
In the seventh month, on the twenty-first day, the word of the Lord came through Haggai the prophet, saying:
Speak to Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, the governor of Judah, and to Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the rest of the people, saying.
In the same year as mentioned earlier, the second year of Darius, but now in the seventh month and on the twenty-first day, the word of the Lord again came through Haggai.
The seventh month was entirely festive and solemn.
Thus, it is fitting that the word of the Lord comes to Haggai in this festive seventh month, and on the twenty-first day, with the completion of three weeks, fulfilling the mystery of the Trinity.
For three times seven is twenty-one.
Who among you remembers seeing this house in its former glory?
And how do you see it now? Isn't it like nothing in your eyes?
But now, be strong, Zerubbabel, says the Lord.
Be strong, Joshua, son of Jozadak, the high priest.
Be strong, all you people of the land, says the Lord of hosts, and do the work, for I am with you, says the Lord of hosts.
This is the word I promised you when you came out of Egypt.
The Lord very kindly comforts the people who had seen the former house in its glory, which makes this one seem like nothing in comparison.
Do not despair, He says, do not let your hands fall limp, for I am with you.
I, the Almighty, have spoken.
My word is as good as done, and I will fulfill what I promised you when I brought you out of Egypt.
And my Spirit, that is, the divinity of my majesty, or the Holy Spirit, who is all consolation and hence called the Comforter, will be among you.
Here, the entire Trinity is mentioned.
The Father is the one who says: I am with you.
The Son is the word I covenanted with you.
The Holy Spirit: My Spirit, He says, will be among you.
Do not be afraid, for this is what the Lord of hosts says:
In a little while, I will once more shake the heavens and the earth, the sea and the dry land, and I will shake all nations.
When the Covenant was first given on Mount Sinai, I shook the heavens; when I spoke to you from heaven, I shook the earth; when my presence was seen in a cloud, darkness, and storm, as the Psalmist says: God, when you went out before your people, and so on.
I shook the Red Sea when I divided it and provided a path for the people to cross.
I also shook the dry land when I led the people for forty years through a desolate and uncultivated wilderness.
Therefore, I, who did those things then, will once more shake these elements, which indeed happened at the coming of the Lord.
At the time of His Passion, the sky changed as the sun darkened, and darkness fell from the sixth hour to the ninth hour.
The earth shook, rocks split, tombs opened, and the ground itself trembled.
The sea of this present age was also stirred, agitated by the winds of demons into rebellion, and the dragon-that is, the devil-was defeated, who lay in the sea of this age.
He also moved the dry, barren, and unproductive hearts of the Gentiles.
Therefore, with the whole universe moved, all nations were stirred by the preaching of the apostles, as their voice went out into all the earth.
And the desired one of all nations will come, and I will fill this house with glory, says the Lord of Hosts.
It is clear that the coming of Christ is foretold, who was desired and awaited to redeem the nations, about whom the Apostle says: Into whom angels long to look.
After He came, the house of the Lord was filled with glory, that is, the Church, which is the house of God built from living stones.
For if the house built by the servant was glorious, as much as a servant differs from the Lord, so much better is the house over which the Lord presides than that over which the servant presided.
The silver is Mine, and the gold is Mine, says the Lord of Hosts.
The glory of this latter house will be greater than that of the former, says the Lord of Hosts.
As if to say: Do not doubt that I can fulfill what I promise.
For I am the one who created everything, in My hand are silver and gold and all wealth; I will give everything necessary for building or decorating the temple.
According to the mystical sense, gold is the spiritual sense and understanding that lies hidden in the Scriptures, about which Solomon says: A desirable treasure rests in the mouth of the wise.
Silver, however, is the clear words of the Scriptures, from which the Psalmist says: The words of the Lord are pure words, silver, and so on.
With these metals, the Church is adorned and becomes brighter than the Synagogue once was.
And in this place, I will give peace, says the Lord of Hosts.
Because we know there's nothing more beneficial for building a renowned house than peace, He promises it.
When peace is granted, other good things follow more easily.
In an allegorical sense, the Lord gives peace to the present Church, with the enemy's malicious plots suppressed and the wars of vices mitigated.
In the future, He will grant true and eternal peace.
On the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month in the second year of King Darius, the word of the Lord came to the prophet Haggai, saying: This is what the Lord of hosts says: Ask the priests about the law, saying: If a man carries consecrated meat in the fold of his garment, and with the fold touches bread or stew, or wine, or oil, or any food, will it become holy?
Note that it is often said: The word of the Lord came by the hand of Haggai, but here: The word of the Lord came to Haggai.
Previously, he had pure works but hadn't fully received wisdom in his heart.
Among them were those who didn't want to build the temple for the Lord, so it is said that the word of the Lord came by his hand.
Now, because the foundations of the temple have been laid and the people, along with their leaders, are working on the temple of the Lord, the word of the Lord comes to Haggai for that reason.
The word is given in the ninth month because he is about to speak about the impurity of the sinful people.
The number nine is never taken in a good sense in the divine Scriptures.
But since they were still given time to do penance, the word of the Lord comes to the prophet on the twenty-fourth day of the same month, a date where the number twelve is doubled, a number sacred everywhere.
Ask the priests about the law, for it is their role to know the law, and they should answer when asked about it.
Therefore, Haggai the prophet asks them in the person of the Lord, saying: If a man carries consecrated meat.
Consecrated meat referred to the meat of a sacrifice offered on the altar, although there was a great diversity among the consecrated meats, as explained in Leviticus.
However, a person was considered impure in soul if they touched a dead body.
For as long as the soul is in the body, the human body is not impure, because it has a soul made in the image and likeness of God.
But as soon as the soul leaves the body, it becomes impure, as it is earthly and formed from carnal pleasure.
This applies to nature; however, the bodies of saints, whose death is precious, are holy due to the merit of the holy soul inhabiting them.
The prophet asks: if a man takes sanctified meat and ties it to the hem of his garment, and that hem touches bread or any other food, can it be sanctified by the touch of the garment where the holy meat is tied?
The priests answered: No.
Another question is posed, and the prophet asks: If someone who is unclean in soul, that is, made impure by contact with a dead body, touches any of these good things, will they become contaminated?
The priests answered and said: They will become contaminated.
And Haggai responded and said: So it is with this people and this nation before me, says the Lord.
Everything they offer will be contaminated.
Regarding the first question, the prophet is silent, but he responds to the second, showing why he proposed these questions.
For anyone who is unclean in soul and has touched a dead body, everything they touch or offer will be unclean.
The meaning is: O people, who offer sacrifices on an altar that is merely built, while my house lies in ruins, and you think you are sanctified by these sacrifices, know that you are not sanctified by the offerings you make in my ruined temple.
Rather, everything you do is contaminated because you neglect my house while diligently building your own houses.
And now, set your hearts from this day forward.
Before a stone was laid upon a stone in the temple of the Lord, when you would come to a pile of twenty measures, and it would become ten; when you would go to the winepress to draw fifty vessels, it would become twenty.
O people of Israel.
Look back at the past days, and from this twenty-fourth day of the ninth month of the second year of Darius, consider everything that has happened before.
Ponder how much you have endured when the temple was not yet built, and how much good has come to you since its construction began.
He specifically lists these things.
Before you started building the Lord's temple, when you went to the heap of barley or wheat, expecting twenty measures, you barely found half of that.
Similarly, when you went to the winepress, estimating you would have fifty amphoras, you barely found twenty.
He explains why this happened.
"I struck you with scorching wind, mildew, and hail-all the work of your hands-and there was no one among you who returned to me," says the Lord. The blight of the crops is named for their golden color. He says, "I did this so that at least in your affliction, you might return to me, but no one among you returned to me."
Therefore, as long as the Lord's temple was in ruins and its construction delayed, everything went against them. But after they started rebuilding the temple, everything prospered.
From this, it is understood that it is futile to offer gifts to the Lord and seek to appease God with alms or offerings as long as they do not build the Lord's temple within themselves. One must first make oneself a temple of God by advancing, and then be able to offer gifts to God on the altar of faith.
Set your hearts from this day forward, from the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month, from the day the foundations of the Lord's temple were laid. Set it upon your heart. Is the seed already in the sprout, yet the vine, the fig tree, the pomegranate, and the olive tree have not blossomed?
The ninth month for us is November, for we begin the year in March. But for the Hebrews, whose first month is Nisan, which is April, December is considered the ninth month, when seeds lie hidden in the ground, and it cannot be guessed whether barrenness or fertility will follow.
Because it was the ninth month, the prophet asks: Is the seed now sprouting?
Or, as another translation more clearly says, is it still in the pod, that is, in the husk of the grain?
Or have the fig tree and other trees blossomed, so that from the flower the abundance can be recognized?
But I predict to you the abundance of all things, not by mere speculation of flowers, but by prophetic spirit, because you have begun to build the temple of the Lord.
Mystically, the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month signifies the end of evil deeds.
The number nine, as mentioned above, is always associated with evil, because it lacks unity, which when added completes the perfect number ten.
Whoever ends evil within himself, as if at the end of the ninth month, begins to build the house of the Lord (that is, dedicates himself to the divine service), will be filled with the fruits of the vine, fig tree, and olive tree.
That is, he will be filled with the grace and blessing of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, having attained the spiritual joy, refreshment, and illumination of the Holy Trinity.
But these, that is, the vine, fig tree, and olive tree, will be found where the pomegranate tree was, called thus because its fruit is full of many seeds, having various small chambers contained within one crimson skin.
Hence, it is also called Punic apple, and therefore it signifies the innumerable multitude of holy peoples united under the fellowship of one faith, as if gathered within the embrace of one skin.
And on this day I will bless.
And the word of the Lord came a second time to Haggai on the twenty-fourth of the month, saying:
It should be noted very carefully that the word of the Lord is said to have come a second time on the same day as above, that is, the twenty-fourth.
But the ninth month is not mentioned, because the prophet is to speak of all things prosperous and full of joy concerning the coming of Christ and His kingdom.
Nor does it say: In the hand of Haggai, as at first; nor To Haggai the prophet, as in the fourth vision, but rather, To Haggai, that is, to the one celebrating the feast, who now does not announce the coming, but shows the one who has come to be seen.
Speak to Zerubbabel, the leader of Judah.
The prophet is commanded to speak to Zorobabel alone, who carries the image of Christ, because what is said is symbolic and pertains to the end of the world.
Here's how these things are shown in the order of history:
I will shake heaven and earth together.
To Zorobabel alone, who we said bears the person of Christ in human form, these things are spoken about what is to come.
I will shake (he says) heaven and earth, meaning I will change them for the better, so there will be a new heaven and a new earth.
For thus the figure of this world passes away while the substance remains.
Then follows:
I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms, and I will destroy the strength of the kingdom of the nations, meaning I will destroy all principality, power, and might, whether they are opposing spiritual wickednesses, so the destruction of their kingdom benefits not only the nations but also the kings who ruled over them.
I will overthrow the chariot and its rider, and the horses and their riders will come down, meaning all the efforts of waging war will cease, and when that is taken away, peace follows.
This is clearly shown to be fulfilled in Christ by the prophet Zechariah, who says of Christ: Behold, your king is coming to you, humble and riding on a donkey's colt; and immediately adds: And he will destroy the chariot from Ephraim, and the horse from Jerusalem.
A man will rise against his brother with a sword.
The Apostle says:
Take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the spirit, which is the word of God.
Therefore, the sword is the word of heavenly doctrine, cutting and tearing apart all perverse teachings.
With this sword, a man is separated from his brother, a son from his father, a daughter from her mother, a daughter-in-law from her mother-in-law, and a man's enemies are his own household.
On that day, says the Lord of Hosts, I will take you, Zorobabel, son of Salathiel, my servant, says the Lord, and I will make you like a signet ring, for I have chosen you, says the Lord of Hosts.
It was previously said that Zorobabel holds the image of Christ.
The Father calls him a servant because he took the form of a servant.
And the Apostle says of the same:
When God the Father has subjected all things to the Son, then the Son himself will be subjected to Him who subjected all things to Him.
For in all things being subjected to Him, He Himself will also be seen as subjected.
When this has been fulfilled, God the Father will take him and place him as a seal in His hand.
For he is the image of the invisible God and the form of His substance.
Therefore, the Son himself says: "For this one the Father, God, has sealed."
We seal things that we want to be specially cherished and kept safe.
So, the Father specially sealed this one, meaning He chose and gifted him with special grace, so that just as he was a true man, he would also be true God.
Whoever believes in him and strives to please him through good works is sealed with this seal or ring.
Amen.