On the Prophet Obadiah
Haymo Bishop of Halberstadt
In the prophet Obadiah's time, the Hebrews say he lived during the reign of Ahab, the king of Samaria, and the very wicked queen Jezebel.
Obadiah fed one hundred prophets in caves who did not bow their knees to Baal.
These were among the seven thousand whom Elijah is said to have not known about.
His tomb, along with the mausoleums of the prophet Elisha and John the Baptist, is still greatly venerated today in Sebaste, which was formerly called Samaria.
Because he fed one hundred prophets, it is said that he received the spirit of prophecy.
From being a leader of the army, he became a leader of the Church.
What the Lord said was fulfilled in him: "He who receives a prophet in the name of a prophet will receive a prophet's reward."
Then, in Samaria, he fed a small flock; now, in the whole world, he tends the Church of Christ.
Chapter One
The Vision of Obadiah
We might wonder why it's called the vision of Obadiah, as the text doesn't mention him seeing anything, but rather hearing.
However, vision here means understanding, because what he heard, he saw—that is, he understood it like the prophets did.
There are three types of visions: physical, like seeing stones; spiritual, like seeing horses run and men fight in dreams; and intellectual, the way the holy prophets spoke.
They understood spiritually everything they spoke.
This is what the Lord God says to Edom.
Edom refers to Esau and Seir; the region is also known by these names.
He was called Esau because he sold his birthright for red lentil stew.
Edom translates to red.
He is also called Seir, meaning hairy, because he was hairy.
The region was also known as Idumea, Seir, and Teman.
Hence, it is said through Amos, "For three transgressions of the sons of Edom, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment," and through Isaiah, "Seir calls to me, 'Watchman, what of the night?'" and through Jeremiah, "Is there no longer wisdom in Teman?" and so on until the end of the prophecy.
The sons of Israel were enemies of the sons of Edom, just as their father had been to his brother Jacob.
The Prophet speaks: "We have heard a report from the Lord, and a messenger has been sent among the nations."
He joins the other prophets who spiritually announce the divine sentence against Idumea.
In Hebrew, Edom is called Idumea in Greek.
"We have heard a report," he says, "from the Lord, I and the other prophets like me, who have written against Edom.
And a messenger has been sent among the nations," that is, His Son, who is indeed the Word of God the Father, sent to Nebuchadnezzar and his army to come against the Edomites and destroy them.
About this messenger, the Lord speaks through Haggai, "I will shake all nations, and the Desired One of all nations will come."
"Arise, and let us rise up against him in battle."
The messenger sent to the nations says this: "Arise," he says, "you who sleep, and do not consider the battle heavy and unusual."
I will be at the forefront of the battle line.
As your leader, who once appeared with a sword to Jesus, son of Nave, let's rise against him in battle, for victory will be easy.
Similarly, Jeremiah speaks against Edom in a vision, saying, "I have heard a message from the Lord, and an envoy has been sent to the nations. Look, I have made you small among the nations; you are greatly despised."
Jeremiah also says, "Look, I have made you small, contemptible among men."
Compared to the other nations around, it was small but raised itself in pride, although it was very despicable. O Edom, he says, while you are the smallest among all the surrounding nations, and small in number, you lift yourself up in pride beyond your strength.
Hence it follows: The pride of your heart has deceived you, dwelling in the clefts of the rock, raising your throne: who says in your heart. The land of the Edomites was situated in the southern part, and because of the excessive heat of the sun, they lived in caves or rocks. The meaning is: Although you live in caves or the clefts of rocks, humble and very poor, and do not have high rooftops of buildings, because of the hardness of your heart or pride, you try to exalt your throne or kingdom as if you were omnipotent, and you say in your heart: Who will bring me down to the ground? That is, no one. For "who" sometimes means "rarely," sometimes "no one," as here, and as in the psalm: "God, who is like you?"
If you are exalted as the eagle, and if you set your nest among the stars, from there I will bring you down, says the Lord. You swell with pride, and like the eagle, which flies higher than all other birds, you lift yourself up, so much so that you can even penetrate heights beyond nature. Even if you have set your nest among the stars, that is, your dwelling, from there I will bring you down to the ground, as it often suddenly throws itself down into the depths of the sea from a great height among the clouds.
The eagle is renowned among bird enthusiasts for its ability to soar higher than any other bird.
Its keen eyesight allows it to spot small fish swimming in the sea from great heights, even when it is invisible to human eyes.
When these fish are near the shore, the eagle swoops down like a missile, snatches its prey, and carries it back with its powerful wings.
This imagery can be spiritually applied to heretics who, though small and insignificant, rise in pride against the Church, confident in their understanding of mysteries.
The Lord warns them that if they elevate themselves in pride, He will bring them down.
If thieves came to you, if robbers by night, how would you have kept silent?
This means: If thieves and robbers, who break into houses at night to steal, came to you and hid in the corners of your house under the cover of darkness, how could you have kept silent?
It implies that you would remain silent when Nebuchadnezzar comes with the Chaldeans, Assyrians, and other nations, not daring to resist them.
This is a comparison of dissimilar situations.
Would they not have stolen enough for themselves?
Meaning, would they not have taken whatever they thought was sufficient?
If grape gatherers came to you, would they not have left at least a cluster for you?
If grape gatherers came to your vineyard with hostile intent, would they not have left at least a cluster for you?
Undoubtedly, they would have, because even though they worked diligently, they would have left some clusters hidden among the vines and leaves.
However, these grape gatherers are understood to be the Babylonians with their leader, who, by the Lord's command, killed and plundered, leaving nothing hidden that could escape them.
Thus, the prophet wonders and adds: How have they searched out Esau, how have they investigated his hidden things?
The Chaldeans explored all its secrets, the caverns, and the holes of the caves where they lived.
They could hide nothing from them.
This is very remarkable, considering that the entire southern region of the Edomites has small dwellings in caves.
Because of the intense heat of the sun, since it is a southern province, they use underground huts.
They pushed you to the limit.
This means that not just a part of your region was taken captive when Nebuchadnezzar arrived, but they reached the borders of your kingdom and drove you out of your throne.
All the men of your covenant have mocked you.
The men of your peace have prevailed against you.
This refers to the Moabites, the Midianites, and other neighbors who were once allied with you, but later joined the Assyrians and mocked those they were once allied with.
They prevailed against them, leading them into captivity, those who were once peaceful and a shield for their cities.
Those who eat with you will set traps for you.
This means those who now enjoy peace and friendship with you, who eat bread with you, will, when the enemies arrive, set traps for you, ensuring that none of your people can escape.
There is no wisdom in him.
This means the kind of wisdom he should have had, expecting that those who are now his allies will become his adversaries.
It indicates there is no wisdom in Edom because he did not foresee that those with whom he had peace would become his enemies.
Is it not on that day, says the Lord, that I will destroy the wise men of Edom, and the prudence from the mountain of Esau?
This means when your enemies possess your borders, and all the men of your covenant mock you and prevail against you, I will destroy the wise philosophers of Edom.
Edom is called Idumaea in Greek.
I will also take away the prudence from the mountain of Esau, so that the cunning of their folly may be shown, and they can find no plan by which they can escape the impending evil.
He says he will take away wisdom from the mountain, either because the city of Edom is situated on a mountain, or because that entire region facing south is elevated with steep mountains.
And your strong men will fear from the south, causing the man from the mountain of Esau to perish.
Another translation says, "your fighters will tremble from Teman." Teman indeed means "south."
Just as Esau was called by three names, the region facing south is also called by three names: Darom, Teman, and Negeb. These names, according to Ezekiel, signify the south, the southwest, and the noon.
The meaning is: After you start hearing the attacking enemies and they begin to mock you, those you trust for peace, the strong men of your kingdom who live in the south will tremble, leading to the demise of the man from the mountain of Esau, who used to fight for the city and give wise counsel.
This is because of the killing and iniquity against your brother Jacob. He explains that the wise men will perish from Edom and the prudent from the mountain of Esau due to the killing and injustice committed against his brother Jacob.
When the Babylonians were devastating Jerusalem, Esau was their ally. The hatred Esau held against Jacob for stealing his blessing was carried by these people and their descendants forever. They grieved over losing the goods the Jews had received.
For this reason, when Nebuchadnezzar first came to Jerusalem and the Chaldeans and Babylonians were devastating it, they joined them and together killed the Jews. For this sin, the Lord speaks to them, saying: "Shame will cover you, and you will perish forever."
Indeed, they were shamed afterward when they were captured by their enemies and perished forever, condemned to perpetual captivity.
On the day when you stood against him. That is, during the obvious captivity, when Jehoiakim was captured and Daniel and the other youths were taken into captivity, during Nebuchadnezzar’s first arrival in Jerusalem, you stood against your brother.
When people who were not of God and not descendants of the Jews took His army and strangers entered the gates of Jerusalem, they cast lots over the city to divide its spoils among themselves.
You were just like one of them.
Therefore, these things will happen to you because, instead of being their protector and helper, you became their destroyer.
Do not look down on your brother on the day of his exile, and do not rejoice over the children of Judah on the day of their downfall.
The prophetic word now openly threatens Edom, saying when a man from Mount Esau dies and is covered in eternal shame for killing and impiety against his brother, he will not repeat his actions against his kin.
It is as if saying, when the second and third captivity of the Jews comes, you will not despise them, nor will you rejoice on the day of their downfall as you did before because you are now held captive by enemies.
First, as it has been said, Nebuchadnezzar came to Jerusalem under Jehoiakim, when Ezekiel was taken to Babylon with the same king; the third time was under Zedekiah, whom he took captive with his eyes gouged out.
So, during the second or third captivity of the Israelites, the Edomites did not rejoice because they were already held captive.
Therefore, it follows: you will not boast in the day of distress.
Saying: "Destroy, destroy, down to its foundation," as you did the first time. Hence, the Psalmist speaks with a voice of imprecation, saying: "Remember, O Lord, the children of Edom in the day of Jerusalem."
For the two tribes that reigned in Jerusalem, called Judah, when captured by the Chaldeans the second or third time, the Edomites did not boast as if they were allies of the victors in their brother's distress. Nor will you enter the gate of my people on the day of their ruin, nor will you look down on them in their misfortune on the day of their desolation. That is, you will by no means enter Jerusalem's gate boastfully on the day of its people's destruction and ruin because, having been handed over to them, you will suffer similar things.
You won't be sent against his army on the day of his destruction, like you once sent an army against him.
Nor will you stand at the exits—on the roads—to kill those who flee.
You won't lock up his remnant in prison and hand them over to their masters on the day of tribulation.
When they begin to flee through the paths and byways they know towards the wilderness, you won't stand at the crossroads or wait at the intersections to kill those who have been freed, capture others who have been taken, or save them for the captivity of the enemies.
For the day of the Lord is near for all nations.
That is, the day of the Lord's vengeance upon all nations will come, and it means: When all nations feel the vengeance of God's wrath and drink from the cup of His fury, will you be left as if innocent?
As if to say: You will not be innocent, but you will drink much more from this vengeance of all nations.
Jeremiah speaks under the metaphor of a cup given to all nations: A golden cup is Babylon in the hand of the Lord, intoxicating all nations.
Indeed, the Assyrians and Babylonians subdued all nations, as testified by Herodotus, up to the Propontis, the Scythian Sea, and the Ionian or Aegean Sea.
As you have done, it will be done to you.
Just as you killed the Jews and became their enemy, so you will be killed by enemies.
Hence it is added: He will turn your recompense onto your own head.
What you have done, you will receive.
In this sense, the prophet also prays against Babylon: O daughter of Babylon, miserable, blessed is he who repays you for what you have done to us.
For just as you drank on my holy mountain Zion, all nations will continually drink.
Just as you rejoiced with the Assyrians and Babylonians on my holy mountain, where my temple and the altar of burnt offerings were, so all nations with you will drink.
They will rejoice over you, whom you have with the Babylonians in your stronghold, and they will drink, and swallow, and be as if they were not.
Not only will they rejoice in your destruction, but also by killing you, they will consume you, so that the Edomites will be as if they were not.
The phrase "they will be as if they were not" refers to all the nations mentioned earlier, as in "The Day of the Lord is upon all nations."
Anyone who does not adhere to Him, who is "I Am," will be as if they were not.
We also read in Esther: "Do not hand over your scepter, Lord, to those who are not."
It suggests that all nations are nothing because they are devastated and absorbed by each other.
Such a cycle of vengeance has occurred because, just as the Edomites killed the Jews, they were themselves killed by the Assyrians and Chaldeans, who were then killed by the Medes and Persians. The Persians were conquered by the Macedonians, who were then defeated by the Romans, whose kingdom was ultimately overtaken by the reign of Christ.
However, on Mount Zion, there will be salvation, and it will be holy.
This prophecy was fulfilled when, after 70 years, the tribes returned to Judea under Zerubbabel, Ezra, and Nehemiah. They experienced the salvation of freedom, and the mountain of the Lord's temple was made holy through the priests, sacrifices, offerings, and other practices that sanctified the people in their worship.
The house of Jacob possessed those who had previously possessed them. Edom was overturned and devoured by enemy nations, with whom it had once made a pact against Jacob. On Mount Zion, there will be salvation, and a remnant will remain. The house of Jacob, having returned from captivity, will inherit those who had once possessed them.
As they returned, many from the Medes and Persians followed them, and they were possessed in religion and faith fellowship.
The house of Jacob, representing the two tribes along with the tribe of Levi, will be fire, and the house of Joseph, representing the ten tribes, will be flame. The house of Esau will be stubble. Just as fire and flame devour stubble, so the two kingdoms of the two and ten tribes, united according to Ezekiel, will devastate and consume Edom.
The ten tribes are signified by Joseph because of Joshua and Jeroboam.
Along with the two tribes, many from the ten tribes also returned and would fight against the Edomites with equal zeal.
Thus, it is added: "they will set them on fire and devour them, and there will be no survivors from the house of Esau."
No one will remain to announce the downfall of the adversaries to the neighboring nations.
That's why the Septuagint says: "There will be no more grain carriers in the house of Esau."
Those whom we now call couriers were once called grain carriers by the ancients.
Why will all these things happen? Because the Lord has spoken, whose word is action, referring to the army of Babylon.
All these things we've mentioned, and those we will mention, are dreams the Jews falsely imagine for themselves, referring them to the times of the Antichrist.
And whatever we have interpreted against Edom, they dream against the Roman Empire.
However, we say that either it happened historically under Zerubbabel, or it is being mystically fulfilled daily in the Church.
But when it happened or will happen, only He knows who commanded these things through the prophets.
Those in the south will inherit the mountain of Esau, and those in the plains will inherit the land of the Philistines.
When Judah returns to its kingdom, those in the south, meaning the two tribes that lived in the southern part of the promised land according to the division by Joshua, son of Nun, will inherit the mountain of Esau. This means they will not be restricted by narrow boundaries but will also possess the mountains that Edom once held.
Those who lived in the plains from these two tribes will possess the five cities of the Philistines: Gaza, Ashkelon, Ashdod, Ekron, and Gath, and all that region, which according to the Acts of the Apostles, is called Sharon.
They will reach the coast and subjugate the Philistines under their rule, whom they had not previously subjugated.
They will possess the region of Ephraim and the region of Samaria.
The boundary of the children of Israel will extend as far as Ephraim, so they will not only possess the kingdom of other nations but also the kingdom of the ten tribes, whose capital is Samaria, and their enemies will possess it.
And Benjamin will possess Gilead.
Gilead was a city or a mountain in the tribe of Gad.
This city or mountain, the whole of Arabia, previously known as Gilead and now called Jerash, was possessed by Benjamin.
Its borders extend northward from Jerusalem.
Whether this was entirely achieved is known only to God.
It might have been partially completed over five hundred years up to the coming of Christ, and it continues to be fulfilled and confirmed in the Church.
Those who live in the true light inhabit the plains and lowlands.
They are the disciples of Him who says: "Learn from me, for I am gentle and humble in heart." They possess the mountain of Esau and the Philistines, who can be seen as the philosophers of the nations due to their eloquence. They will also possess the region of Ephraim and Samaria, where, as we often read in Hosea, heretics are depicted.
Moreover, Benjamin, meaning the son of the right hand, that is, the Christian people, will possess Gilead, which means a heap of testimony. This refers to the believing Jews, from whom we received the testimonies of the law and the prophets.
The exiled children of Israel will possess all the Canaanites' land up to Sarepta. This means those who return from the captivity of the ten tribes will possess all the places of the Canaanites up to Sarepta. They will not only possess the southern, western, and northern regions, including the Edomites of Cilicia, the Philistines, the mountain of Esau, and Samaria, but they will also rule over all the lands of the Canaanites to the east up to Sarepta of the Sidonians, where a widow once fed Elijah.
The exiles of Jerusalem, who are in the Bosphorus, will possess the cities of the south. By Bosphorus, it means the borders or ends. The Septuagint translates it as Sapharad, meaning limit or place. This implies that those transferred from the metropolitan city of Jerusalem to Sapharad, meaning the borders of the Babylonians, will return and possess the cities of the south, which are in the tribe of Judah. Those living in their city will obtain the areas adjacent to the city.
And saviors will ascend Mount Zion, just as Zerubbabel and others were, just as Othniel and the other liberators whom the Lord sent, up to Saul and then up to Zedekiah, to judge the mountain of Esau.
They will indeed ascend from captivity to judge and distinguish, as if the mountain of Esau—that is, the Edomites along with their land—were subject to and serving them.
And the kingdom will belong to the Lord.
With all being subdued, the kingdom will belong to the Lord because He will establish His reign in various places.