On the Fact that Christ was Born of a Virgin
by Ratramnus a Monk of Corbie
ACHERII'S WARNING
About Ratramnus, Acherius notes the following in his Preface:
Ratramnus, also known as Bertram, was a monk and priest of Corbie.
He wrote a little work about Christ being born of the Virgin, which had been buried in darkness for many centuries in England.
I finally managed to bring it back to France with considerable effort.
Usher of Armagh gave me the opportunity when he tried to taint Ratramnus with the stain of heresy, claiming that in the two books he wrote about this sacrament, Ratramnus did not accept that the substance of the bread in the Eucharist is transformed into the body of the Son of God.
Usher incorrectly argues this in God's History, chapter 2, as follows: Among his works that did not reach Trithemius' knowledge, there is one on the Nativity of Christ, in which he supports the same doctrine as in the book on the Body and Blood of the Lord.
Another is on the soul, etc.
How far this assertion is from the truth is proven by the very little work itself, in which there isn't even a trace of this error.
Indeed, even the leaders of the adversaries, the Magdeburg Centuriators, in Century 9, chapter on Doctrine, column 212, briefly refute Usher: Bertram has seeds of transubstantiation, for he uses words of change and conversion.
And in chapter 6 on the Ceremonies and Rites of the Church, column 243: Bertram, in the book on the Body and Blood, shows that the body and blood of the Lord are placed on the altar or table and then distributed to the people, etc.
Ratramnus has been clearly and learnedly defended from any blemish by Sixtus of Siena, in the preface to the holy library, Cardinal Perronius, and President Mauguin: the former in book 2 of the Eucharist, chapters 1 and 2; the latter in chapter 37 of the Historical and Chronological Dissertation, proving that Ratramnus flourished in the time of Louis the Pious and Charles the Bald through the works he produced.
We have copied Acherius up to this point.
we inform you that the writings about the birth of the Virgin by Ratramnus and his abbot Ratbertus seem to have been written independently of each other.
It's unlikely that if they had read each other's works, both would have used the same testimonies to support their opinions, without showing any concern that these testimonies had been twisted by their opponent.
Also, the first edition was compared with an old manuscript of Dalleus by Dom Edmund Martene, who shared various readings with us.
Author's Preface
If we are all considered Christians under one teacher, Christ, and if we all glorify one heavenly Father, united by the bond of one Spirit in the framework of one love, then there is no reason for me to fear that I am separated from your esteem, or that my writings are not suitable for your faith.
For the kinship of the Spirit is much greater than any blood relation.
Earthly lineage is certainly much lower than divine lineage, and the duties of temporal service do not produce as much grace of love as the fire of divine love generates.
Therefore, let any unfamiliar face, unknown name, or lack of acquaintance be set aside here, where such great and necessary rights of social union are agreed upon.
Thus, do not reject as a stranger the one whom the heavenly condition has made your close brother.
Since this is the case, I implore your reverence not to hesitate to respond to the suggestion of my humility.
Chapter One
On the errors about Christ's birth in Germany.
The author explains why Christ had to be born like other people.
There is a rumor, and we have learned from some reputable sources, that the ancient serpent is spreading new deceitful poison in parts of Germany, trying to undermine the Catholic faith regarding the birth of the Savior with subtle fraud.
It claims that Christ's infancy did not involve a true human birth through the virginal gate of the womb, but that he emerged monstrously from the hidden path of the womb's secret into the light.
This is not being born, but bursting forth.
For whatever did not follow the paths of the uterus in being born, but burst forth in any direction like through a wall of a house, was not born properly but exited violently.
Therefore, Christ was not truly born, nor did Mary truly give birth.
But the Catholic faith holds that Jesus was born of the Virgin Mary.
This is clearly announced by the Angel sent to her with specific words:
"Behold," he says, "you will conceive in your womb and bear a son" (Luke 1:31).
See how clearly he refutes the abominable sect.
He does not say: "You will conceive a son, and he will exit from your womb," but, "you will conceive and bear," referring to both events, so that with her virginity intact she would conceive as a woman and bear as a mother, making the mother of divinity glorious by the conception and not dishonored by the birth.
One part would pertain to her role, the other to the one being conceived: thus, she would be called an unblemished mother, and the Savior's birth from the mother would be perfect.
Even if the angel sent to Mary had spoken this way, it would not necessarily compel the belief that Christ's birth from the mother was extraordinary.
For he who chose to be conceived by a virgin woman could easily be believed to be born of a virgin woman, since he who chose to be born from the frail sex of humanity would not disregard the mode of human birth, while preserving the integrity of virginity.
It was indeed inappropriate for the divine plan to choose a virginal body for the womb in which He would be conceived, formed, and carried for nine months, and then to reject the womb's path by which He would proceed from the virginal chamber.
Therefore, let those who speak such nonsense either show another way that women naturally give birth or admit that Christ had a natural exit from the Virgin's womb, as the law of nature demonstrates, without violating her integrity or modesty.
Before vipers give birth, it's said that the young, not waiting for the full term, eat through the mother's sides, resulting in her death.
There's also a common belief that weasels conceive through the mouth and give birth through the ear.
So, anyone who denies the human birth of Christ either suggests a viper's deadly birth for the mother or attributes to Him a weasel's birth made up by fables.
Would the Redeemer of mankind, conceived by the Virgin, prefer to be born in a way contrary to nature like a serpent's or in a fabricated way like a weasel's, rather than a human birth?
This way, anything could be imagined or blasphemed about Christ's birth, as if He were born in any manner other than the virginal birth, the Word made flesh, but rather through a miraculous exit.
Chapter Two
It's argued that the mother's integrity was violated.
The response is that Mary remained a virgin.
But I ask, why refuse to attribute to Christ the natural passage through the virginal door?
You say it's because if He exited the womb's door, the Virgin's integrity wouldn't remain intact.
Indeed, according to your reasoning, whichever way He exited, the integrity would be violated.
If the Savior’s birth had to corrupt the natural path, then wherever He exited—whether through the side, the stomach, the kidneys, or any other part of the body—it would cause damage to the integrity.
But let it be far from Catholic beliefs that the birth, through which corrupted things were restored, should be believed to have corrupted the intact.
Understand finally, presumptuous fool, that if the Savior’s birth could happen through any part of the virgin's body without damage to her integrity, then it could also happen through the womb's door.
If this would have violated her, then wherever He exited, it would have violated her.
But the Catholic faith confesses about the Virgin, the Savior’s mother, that she was a virgin before birth, a virgin during birth, and a virgin after birth.
Both are believed, both are confessed: the mother's virginity and the birth of the infant.
Therefore, because of the inviolate hall of modesty, it is proclaimed that she was a virgin before birth, during birth, and after birth; and because of the true nature of the birth, it is confessed that she truly gave birth.
What is a virgin before birth, if not a virgin who conceived?
What is a virgin during birth, if not a virgin giving birth?
And what is a virgin after birth, if not a virgin remaining a virgin after birth?
So where is the virgin giving birth if the birth is denied?
Moreover, if it is proclaimed that the virgin did not give birth, then she did not give birth if the birth proceeded otherwise than through the natural door.
For indeed, such a birth is not the birth of a virgin, but merely the exit of the infant itself.
Let this false claim be silenced, and let the Catholic faith remain unshaken.
It acknowledges that Christ was truly born of a mother and firmly believes, proclaims, and venerates that Mary was a virgin when she conceived, gave birth, and remained a virgin after giving birth.
That is, after her son was born.
Chapter Three
The author demonstrates that Christ was born through the womb.
Parts of the body are not inherently shameful.
Why some parts of the body are considered shameful.
The Holy Spirit sanctified the Blessed Virgin from all impurity.
Why certain parts of the body are viewed as dishonorable.
You argue that it was shameful for the Son of God to be born through the womb.
This shame is either due to nature or sin.
But nothing is shameful by nature; Genesis testifies that every creature is good.
What is good is also honorable; and what is honorable is not shameful.
Therefore, every creature, as created, is not shameful.
So, the womb of a woman is not shameful but honorable; since all parts of creation are honorable.
Therefore, the path of the womb should not be avoided by the unborn Christ as if it were something shameful, but rather it should be embraced as the means of birth.
Just as He did not disdain the womb in which He was conceived and formed, He did not reject the womb from which He was born.
Furthermore, you, questioning the senses of the body, think those parts of the womb are inappropriate.
Do not judge the truth of things by deceptive senses, that is, bodily senses; seek the judgment of the mind, and you will find that what seems shameful is actually beautiful.
Indeed, no part or member of a creature is not beautiful; it becomes inappropriate when disordered and illicit movement makes it shameful.
Before the transgression, Adam and Eve were not ashamed, as they did not feel any disordered movement in their bodies; but when they transgressed, they began to feel shame.
Not because of the members, which we now, due to the guilt of sin, call shameful; for even before they sinned, they were not ashamed of them.
But when shameful movement came to the once modest genitals, now no longer modest due to sin, confusion followed—not because of the shamefulness of the honorable parts of the body, but because of the shameful irrational movement of passion.
Through the Fire of the Holy Spirit, whether in our mortal bodies or in the future life made incorruptible by resurrection, this susceptible motion will be restored to the most dignified harmony of nature.
With weakness driven away, the body's members will be free from confusion, shame, and dishonor.
Meanwhile, the law in our members continues to resist the law of the mind and takes us captive to the law of sin, making us feel embarrassed and ashamed.
However, it was not necessary for the Savior to avoid the way of birth established by law because of this law of sin reigning in our members.
The Holy Spirit, who sanctified the Virgin's womb where the Son of God would be incarnated, purged it from all contamination.
It might seem unbelievable that He could make that place worthy by divine conception if He could not cleanse it from the heat of lust and the temper of a lesser flame.
From the words of Holy Scripture, we understand that lust rules in the navel, under which the womb lies in women.
Yet, it is not because of the law of sin, but because of the deformity of nature, that the genital member seems dishonorable to you.
Why is this?
Because you rely on the perception of the flesh to understand things, which no wise person has followed in seeking truth.
It is no wonder if you are deceived, being instructed by the author of falsehood.
All who embrace the plausible as true, that is, the corruptible as eternal, follow him.
Instead, turn your eyes away from temporal things, which Ecclesiastes teaches are not only vanity but vanities of vanities, and learn the perception of truth from those senses participating in truth.
When you do this, you will see nothing shameful in nature except disordered motions, which arise not from the wisdom of the Creator but from the fault of sin.
You will no longer judge the Incarnation of the Word as unworthy of being born from a virgin womb.
Indeed, you will perceive that nothing is more fitting for the humanity of the Creator than to affirm the disposition of His own creation.
Just as He approved the womb in which He was conceived,
He did not abolish the gate of the womb at His birth;
lest He reject the way of being born which He had established by the manner of His human birth.
If you think this to be impious, you are attempting something new,
to proclaim that there was nothing closed to the Savior when He was born,
since nothing in creation can obstruct the Creator:
indeed, everything that exists is open and passable to Him.
If you think this way, you are thinking very wisely.
When you intend to apply this rule to the origins of Christ's birth,
you are teaching clearly regarding His power.
But as to the property of the body He assumed,
and the nature of His human birth,
you are straying far from the path of truth.
Certainly, to the power of Christ's will, nothing is closed, nothing is impenetrable.
However, the humanity He assumed,
just as it was contained within the womb,
did not experience the outside of the womb as long as it remained there.
But once it left the secret chamber of the virgin,
and appeared outside, it ceased to be inside.
By this change of place, it showed that although according to the property of divinity He is everywhere, according to the limitation of the body He existed locally.
Therefore, what is local is not always everywhere,
but moves to another place when it leaves the first place;
so also, when it moves, it does not hold both right and left at the same time,
just as it does not walk both forward and backward simultaneously,
nor equally both above and below.
Certainly,
even the Savior, just as at one time He was in the womb according to the body,
and at another time outside, so in His exit, though nothing was closed to His will for exit, He nonetheless held one way of exit, not passing through all parts of the body in which He had been formed.
Certainly, decide upon whichever part of the body you wish for the Savior's birth.
For He did not exit through the whole body,
although no part of the body was closed to His will for exit.
He did not exit in a non-local manner,
for this is proper to an incorporeal nature, far removed from a bodily one.
Certainly, decide upon whichever part you choose.
You reject the womb and attribute it to the navel,
or, if you prefer, any more honorable opening of the body.
And if the natural openings displease you,
tear open the stomach, expose the ribs, break the spine, or,
as some of the most foolish rant, open the armpit, and thus claim the Savior's birth from a shadowy and dense mountain.
Will such a door of the ruler's birth be deemed worthy, as the opinion of fools suggests,
while what the wisdom of the Creator gave to nature for conception is disdained?
Should we follow the opinion of the Brahmins,
that just as they claim their sect's founder Buddha emerged from a virgin's side,
we should proclaim Christ to have been born?
Or rather, that the wisdom of God is born from the Virgin's brain, like Minerva from Jupiter's head,
or like Father Liber from the thigh?
Should the follower of Christ learn about the Virgin's birth not from established nature or the authority of sacred scripture,
but from pagan superstition and fabulous tales?
CHAPTER Four.
The author presents testimonies from the Old Testament to suggest that Christ emerged through the womb of the Virgin.
Now, let's look at the divine testimonies and learn about the birth of the Savior so that we aren't deceived by vain tales and false opinions.
The prophet Isaiah, revealing the mystery of this birth, says, "The Lord himself will give you a sign. Behold, the virgin shall conceive and bear a son" (Isaiah 7:14).
He acknowledges that a virgin will conceive and bear a child, and that this will be a sign given by the Lord, indicating that the virgin will miraculously accomplish both, not that the birth will occur contrary to the natural way.
If it were to happen otherwise, it would need to be announced with the same prophetic mystery as the virgin conception and birth were announced.
Such a birth would no less signify a divine operation when it had transposed the natural order.
Now, separating the work of men and hinting at the gift of integrity, Isaiah teaches that this sign from the Lord is that a virgin will give birth to the Savior.
He does not indicate a new way of giving birth contrary to nature for the virgin mother, but rather highlights the birth's sublimity with the palm of incorruption given by nature.
I do not think it necessary, nor does brevity allow, to present examples from the entire body of Scriptures showing that women can only give birth through the legitimate opening of the womb, such as: "A woman who conceives and gives birth to a male child" (Leviticus 12:2).
Also: "Consecrate to me every firstborn who opens the womb among the Israelites" (Exodus 13:1).
For if a woman gives birth otherwise than through the womb, that is, the mouth of the uterus, then not every firstborn is consecrated to the Lord.
But since this is foolish to say, the virgin did not give birth except through the womb.
The meaning and significance of the word itself clearly provide evidence for understanding: just as seeing relates to the eyes, hearing to the ears, smelling to the nose, and tasting to the mouth, so does giving birth relate to the womb.
Otherwise, if the meaning of words can be varied at the discretion of individuals, everything will be confused, and even men will be considered capable of bearing and conceiving.
Why shouldn't these responsibilities of words be acknowledged if the Savior's birth did not follow the natural path of the womb but came about in another way?
Poets have used fiction to suggest that even a man can conceive and give birth.
But as a Christian, instructed in the words of truth, I trust you reject this.
So, don't overturn the natural order, which is expressed through common words, with a new opinion.
Instead, accept it with a true and usual interpretation.
When you read, hear, or say that the Virgin gave birth to Christ, or that Christ was born of the Virgin, you should immediately think of the natural pathway and the gate of the womb.
This way, you won't be led astray by error, but will stay on the right path with true understanding.
However, to back these points with arguments, let's learn the truths about the Savior's birth from testimonies we hold to be true.
The prophet Isaiah said: And I went to the prophetess, and she conceived and gave birth to a son: and the Lord said to me: Call his name: Speed to the spoil, hasten the prey (Isaiah 8:3).
Notice the birth of the virgin as marked by the prophetic ministry.
The prophet went to the prophetess because the Holy Spirit came to Mary: she conceived and gave birth to a son, more by the gift of the Holy Spirit than by a man's seed.
Just as Sarah, barren and old, was prophesied to become a mother by the Holy Spirit, she was conceived and gave birth.
Therefore, both the conception and birth occurred in the prophetess to condemn future heresies that claim Mary conceived but did not give birth as a woman.
The prophetess does not mislead in one aspect while prefiguring the truth in another; because the Mother of the Savior conceived as a virgin by the Holy Spirit and gave birth as a woman while preserving her modesty.
Again, elsewhere: Drop down, ye heavens, from above, and let the skies pour down righteousness; let the earth open, and bring forth a Savior (Isaiah 45:8).
The prophetic word, with admirable brevity, explained the announcement of the angel, the prophecies, the virgin's conception, and the manner of birth.
The angel hints at the birth of Christ, and the prophets do not remain silent.
The womb of the virgin opens to her offspring, and the enclosure of modesty brings forth the Savior.
In the opening, you see the virgin's conception; in the sprouting, you understand the birth of modesty.
Just as a sprout preserves its native vein without being formed by foreign seed but is sown by the mother herself, according to what Genesis attests about trees and plants, saying: "Whose seed is in itself" (Genesis 1:11), so the Virgin Mary conceived not from a man but from her own seed and brought forth the conceived through a genital channel.
Therefore, Aaron's rod blooms into a sprout, bursts into flowers, and forms almonds as its leaves unfold, to signify the coagulation of the seed, the formation of the conception, and the manifestation of the birth.
Just as Aaron's rod produced sprouts, flowers, and fruit natively without the assistance of earth and water, so the virgin mother bore the flesh of the Word made flesh not from a stream of pleasure or marital union but through a genital channel.
Chapter Five
Other Testimonies.
Jeremiah, also foreseeing this sacred birth of the Virgin, says:
The Lord will create a new thing on the earth:
a woman will encompass a man (Jeremiah 31:22).
Consider what he said would be newly created: with only the seed of a woman, through the ministry of the Holy Spirit, a male is formed in the womb.
And since such a conception would not bypass the natural path of birth, which is granted to all mortals, he rightfully kept silent about it.
In this, nothing new is brought forth except for preserving inviolate modesty under the law of birth.
Ezekiel also says:
And I turned to the way of the outer gate of the sanctuary, which looked toward the east; and it was shut:
and the Lord said to me:
This gate shall be shut, it shall not be opened, and no man shall pass through it, because the Lord God of Israel has entered through it; therefore, it shall be shut for the prince.
The prince shall enter by way of the vestibule of the gate, and shall go out the same way (Ezekiel 44:2-3).
I believe that this passage resolves all the complexity of this question.
Indeed, the gate described by the prophet is understood by the elders to be the Virgin Mary, who is clearly shown to be shut because she remains always intact as a virgin, and no man shall pass through her.
Pay close attention to whom passage is denied, and by what means it is denied.
It is absolutely denied to a man who could violate her, and it is removed from him who could corrupt her through intercourse.
For no one removes an entrance, because the reasoning of nature neither admits a way nor a passage.
Therefore, when it is said:
No man shall pass through her, it is not said of the side, nor of the brain, nor of the thigh, because conjugal passage relates to other parts of the body, to which nature has provided a way and passage for intercourse.
But because through the way where male passage is removed, the Lord God of Israel has entered, the subsequent discourse shows this by saying:
The Lord God of Israel has entered through her.
And to remove all ambiguity, it adds:
He shall enter by the way of the vestibule of the gate and shall go out the same way.
Let no new heresy doubt the way of the Savior, which he followed in being born.
Here, the prophet metaphorically presents the image of a woman's womb and its entrance.
The Lord God of Israel entered through this gate because He came into the womb through the mystery of the virgin birth.
He exited through this gate, as having taken on humanity, He came into the world through an untouched womb.
Therefore, do not imagine that the Son of God exited the mother's womb in any other way.
May the Holy Spirit teach you the truth, who sanctified both the chamber and the gate for such a worthy groom.
But why dwell on difficult and mystical passages?
Let's move to the clear ones and transition from the secret figures to the openness of the gates, so that we may contemplate the footsteps of the groom and the emissions of the bride under the sky.
In the law, every firstborn was sanctified to the Lord, signifying Him who alone is holy and born without sin.
For it is written: "Sanctify to me every firstborn that opens the womb among the Israelites" (Exodus 13:1).
Again: "When the Lord brings you into the land of the Canaanites, as He swore to you and your fathers, and gives it to you, you shall separate every firstborn that opens the womb for the Lord" (Exodus 13:11-12).
Again: "When Pharaoh was stubborn and would not let us go, the Lord killed every firstborn in the land of Egypt. Therefore, sacrifice to the Lord every male that opens the womb, and redeem all the firstborn of my sons" (Exodus 13:13-15).
Note that the firstborn are those who, by being born first, open the womb, so that you may understand that being born of a woman means coming out through the womb.
In the list of commandments: "You shall give me the firstborn of your sons" (Exodus 22:29).
Elsewhere: "Every firstborn of the male gender that opens the womb shall be mine" (Exodus 13:2).
In Leviticus: "If a woman conceives and bears a male child..." (Leviticus 12:1).
Again: "But if she bears a female child..." (Leviticus 12:5).
It teaches that to conceive and to bear children means to bring forth through the womb.
In Numbers: "Every firstborn is mine since I struck down all the firstborn in the land of Egypt."
"Consecrate to me whatever is first born in Israel." Numbers 3:13.
Earlier, it says: "I took the Levites from the Israelites in place of the firstborn who opens the womb among the Israelites." Numbers 3:12.
And in another passage: "Count the firstborn males among the Israelites from one month old." Numbers 3:40.
Above, it says: "You shall take the Levites for me in place of the firstborn of the Israelites." Numbers 3:41.
Later, it states: "For the firstborn who open every womb in Israel, I have taken them." Numbers 8:16; referring to the Levites.
All the firstborn of the Israelites are mine. Elsewhere, it says: "Whatever first opens the womb of all flesh which they offer to the Lord, whether of humans or animals, shall be yours." Numbers 18:15.
So, every birth, whether human or animal, comes through the womb. Because of this, everything born of a woman comes out through the womb.
Therefore, let the words, which, by their custom and the usage of the Scriptures, provide a clear notion of their significance, not generate uncertain questions for us. Just as walking pertains to the function of the foot, we proclaim that giving birth pertains to the function of the womb.
Let us not let doubt confuse what the clear meaning of the words indicates. Just as one does not reach the intended destination without the direction of the road, the truth of expression is not revealed without the true significance of the words.
So, regarding birth or being born, or whatever other name such an action is called, we understand from the truth of nature, the custom of birth, and the authority of the Scriptures, nothing other than the words signifying the things they signify. This way, we do not stray far from the truth while we either do not recognize the signs of the truth or attempt to pervert them with wrong interpretation.
Let us contemplate the words concerning the birth of the Savior according to the given rule of the Gospels. In Matthew, we read it written like this: "An angel of the Lord appeared to Joseph in a dream, saying: 'Joseph, son of David, do not be afraid to take Mary as your wife, for what is conceived in her is from the Holy Spirit. She will give birth to a son, and you are to give him the name Jesus.'"
For he will save his people from their sins.
All this happened to fulfill what was spoken by the prophet who said: Behold, a virgin will conceive and bear a son, and they shall call his name Emmanuel, which means God with us.
When Joseph woke up from his sleep, he did as the angel of the Lord commanded him and did not know her until she had given birth to her firstborn son, and he called his name Jesus.
Matthew 1:20 and following.
When Jesus was born in Bethlehem of Judea, the birth of the Savior was proclaimed many times.
The birth from a Virgin was narrated many times.
Virginity is fully taught, the embrace of a man is removed, but the passage through the womb is not denied.
Indeed, both the words of the evangelists and the prophecy of the prophets show that the birth of the Savior came through the womb; for a woman does not give birth except through the womb, and a child does not come out except through the door of the womb.
Luke speaks thus about this birth: The angel entered to Mary and said: Hail, full of grace, the Lord is with you, blessed are you among women.
When she heard this, she was troubled and wondered what kind of greeting this could be, and the angel said to her: Do not be afraid, Mary, for you have found grace with the Lord.
Behold, you will conceive and bear a son, and you shall call his name Jesus.
Later, Mary said to the angel: How will this be, since I do not know a man?
And the angel answered her: The Holy Spirit will come upon you, and the power of the Most High will overshadow you.
Therefore, the holy one to be born will be called the Son of God.
Luke 1:28 and following.
If you do not yet accept what it means to give birth either by the solemnity of nature or by the example of those being born, at least let the angel sent to Zachariah instruct you from the Gospel itself.
The angel said to him: Do not be afraid, Zachariah, for your prayer has been heard; and your wife Elizabeth will bear you a son.
Luke 1:13.
One word is promised for both births, and how is the same door of the womb not signified?
The order of conception is different, but the law of birth is the same.
John is conceived from the seed of a man, and Jesus from the Holy Spirit.
John’s birth is revealed through the gate through which a man has passed, while Jesus is born through the untouched hall of modesty.
However, both are born because each is received through the gate of the womb.
Our prayer is also confirmed by the evangelist when he says: "Therefore, what is born of you is holy."
Remember what the lawgiver commanded about the firstborn, that is, those who open the womb, and you will understand why the holy firstborn is called and why the firstborn who opens the womb is also called Jesus. If he is the firstborn, he certainly opened the womb, not to corrupt it by breaking it open, but to open the door for his birth. As described in Ezekiel, the gate is closed but is said to be opened for the Lord of Israel, not that the gates of its threshold were moved for his exit, but that it remained closed and yet was open to the one who dominates.
The same evangelist again: "And it happened that while they were there, the days were completed for her to give birth, and she gave birth to her firstborn son" (Luke 2:6).
And about Elizabeth almost the same things are written: "Now the time came for Elizabeth to give birth, and she bore a son" (Luke 1:57).
Just as the time for each woman to give birth is assigned, so the same word shows the same gate of the womb for both infants being born.
And thereafter: "When the days of Mary's purification according to the law of Moses were fulfilled, they brought Jesus to Jerusalem to present him to the Lord, as it is written in the law of the Lord: Every male that opens the womb shall be called holy to the Lord" (Luke 2:22).
If the words by which Mary is taught to have given birth did not satisfy you enough so that you might claim Jesus came out from some other place than through the womb of the Virgin because the shame of a woman needed to be covered by more decent speech, finally consenting to the words of the evangelist, learn that the mouth of the female womb is indicated by its own proper term, and through it the Savior underwent the process of birth.
If it had been anything other than Mary giving birth to a male child that opened her womb, then according to the law's command, she should not have presented him to the Lord, nor should he have been called holy to the Lord.
Because every male child that opens the womb will be called holy to the Lord Luke 2:23.
Mary the virgin truly gave birth to him, and the Savior came through her womb.
As the firstborn, he opened it, not by violating the integrity of the womb, but by emptying the palace of the womb.
So, even though she conceived without seed, because a male child truly opened her womb, Mary fulfilled the days of purification according to the law.
She brought the offering to the temple and presented the child to the Lord.
Chapter Six
He asserts his opinion from the Fathers.
Since we have briefly gathered these points from divine texts, explaining the birth of the Savior through the untouched womb of the Virgin, it is also fitting to support our view with the traditions of the elders.
This way, by presenting numerous testimonies, we can refute adversaries and further instruct the faithful.
We will, however, only cite a few passages to keep this task concise.
If we were to compile all their sayings on this matter, we would end up with a vast collection of volumes.
Ambrose, a heavenly trumpet, a model of sanctity, and an unassailable strength of faith, while discussing the human birth of the Savior (in Luke, Book 11, Chapter 2), said:
"Is God proven by minor signs, that angels minister, that wise men adore, that martyrs confess?
He is brought forth from the womb, but he shines from heaven: he lies in an earthly inn, but he thrives in heavenly light.
A married woman gave birth, but a virgin conceived.
A married woman conceived, but a virgin gave birth.
How subtly he teaches the secret of inviolate purity, and how magnificently he describes the virgin, proclaiming the mother as married yet untouched!
He narrates Christ being brought forth from the womb to make it clear he came through the natural way, and so you do not think his birth sought foreign exits, but came into the light by the natural flow of the womb.
To clarify, he added that a married woman gave birth, but a virgin conceived, and a married woman conceived, but a virgin gave birth; so that in the conception and birth of the virgin, you may remove the involvement of a male.
You observe that the parts are assigned by nature to their functions, with conception referring to the womb and birth to the opening.
Thus, you believe that a virgin both conceived and gave birth just as a married woman does.
Furthermore, he states: 'Every male opening the womb shall be called holy to the Lord.'
For by the words of the law, the birth of the Virgin was promised.
And truly holy, because immaculate."
Finally, the being designated by the law is declared in the same way by the repeated words of the angel: "Because what will be born," he said, "holy, will be called the Son of God."
It wasn't a man's involvement that revealed the secrets of the virgin's womb, but the Holy Spirit poured out the immaculate seed into the inviolable womb. For the Lord Jesus alone, born of a woman, is holy in all respects. He did not suffer the contamination of earthly corruption by His immaculate birth and repelled it with heavenly majesty.
If we follow the letter of the law, how is every male holy, when it's well known that many have been most wicked? Was Ahab holy? Were the false prophets holy, whom the avenging fire consumed at Elijah's prayers for heavenly justice? But He is holy, through whom the divine prescriptions of the pious law signified the mystery by a figure. And He alone opened the virgin's secret of the Holy Church to generate the people of God with immaculate fertility. He alone, therefore, opened the womb for Himself.
Nor is it surprising: for He who had said through the prophet, "Before I formed you in the womb, I knew you, and in your mother’s womb, I sanctified you" (Jeremiah 1:5).
Therefore, He who sanctified another's womb so that a prophet might be born, is the one who opened His mother's womb, so that He might come forth immaculate.
(Saint Ambrose, Book II on Luke, Chapter 2; Saint Augustine, Book II on Original Sin, Chapter 40, and Book I against Julian, Chapter 2.)
The distinguished speaker, explaining the edict of the ancient law in this oration, first teaches that the holy legal mystery of the one true saint, born of a Virgin at the end of the age, did not suffer the contamination of earthly corruption by the novelty of His immaculate birth.
Thus, He opened the virgin's womb by being born, yet left it closed by not violating it.
Otherwise, if the Scripture did not signify Him, which decreed that males should be considered holy, it would show that the decree is not true due to the depravity of many males.
But the law of the Lord is immaculate and the testimony is faithful.
Therefore, we must seek understanding that aligns with the truth.
Here, only the holy one is mentioned, who was conceived without sin, born without fault, and who revealed the generative secret of the holy Church, the virgin, to bring forth the people of God with immaculate fertility.
This narrative would not be related to the Church through mystery unless it intended to teach that it truly happened through the revelation of the virgin's womb.
The following words confirm this understanding; for it says: "Therefore, he alone opened the womb for himself." What more do you need when the recorded words confirm what we say? For it says both "opened" and "womb," so you cannot think anything was said figuratively.
Therefore, the clear statement confirms what the old Scripture spoke about: every male that opens the womb shall be called holy to the Lord, so you may learn it was marked not in modern times but in the most ancient times, not only that Jesus would be born of a Virgin, but that he would be born through the untouched purity of the womb. To ensure this birth is considered unstained and inviolate, not defiled by corruption, it is taught by the example of the prophet sanctified while still in the womb. It adds: For he who said to the prophet: "Before I formed you in the womb, I knew you, and I sanctified you in your mother’s womb," he who sanctified another's womb so a prophet might be born, is the same one who opened his own mother’s womb so he might be born immaculate.
Let our words cease now, where we are instructed by the words of such a great teacher on what we should believe about the birth of the Savior. For we should not explain what he said, since we might obscure rather than clearly reveal it, unless perhaps someone is so ignorant they do not know that a woman’s womb is a private part.
Chapter Seven Testimonies from Augustine and Hilary.
Let Augustine come forward, a river of eloquence, a scrutinizer of secrets, a revealer of hidden things, a defender of the Church, a conqueror of heretics; and let him openly declare what he believes about the birth of the Savior.
In a sermon about the Nativity of the Lord, while speaking about the modesty of the Virgin and the miraculous conception of the Savior, he said:
"Upon the announcement of the birth by the angel, the Word began to take shape. With the conception, God is united with man, and the womb, which was small for the world, holds Him. Within the short space of the Virgin's body, majesty was incarnated for us; the fertile womb is stretched by the Author of the Word; and after nine months, the womb brought forth the heavenly man: the angelic message proclaimed the birth of the Lord."
He described with careful brevity both the principles of the conception and the formation of the solidity and the growth of the body. He also spoke of the span of months in which the infant was formed in the secret of the womb, its progress to the air, and the angelic proclamation of the birth of God.
Indeed, you see that the conception is mentioned, as well as the formation and the birth, that is, not through a foreign rupture but through the gateway of the Virgin's womb.
Likewise, in another sermon on the same nativity:
"Therefore, our Lord was born from the flesh, but not from carnal corruption: born as a man, but not begotten as a man. He took on flesh in such a way that He preserved the honor of majesty; and thus He separated the purity of His birth from the pollution of human conception."
Indeed, He accomplished in His birth the full dispensation of a man, but He did not abandon the dignity of God.
You see that this learned man both indicates the divinity of the Son of God and the order of human birth. For he says that He was born from the flesh, that is, from the members and humanity of the Virgin, according to the law of the flesh, but without the corruption of the flesh; so that you might more clearly understand what is being said, he states: "Born as a man, but not begotten as a man."
See how fully he has explained the mystery of Christ's birth: He states, "Born as a man, but not begotten as a man."
What does it mean to be born as a man?
He came into the world through the womb, specifically through the virgin's womb.
And what does it mean to not be begotten as a man?
He was incarnate not from a man's seed, but from the Holy Spirit.
If he had not come through the door of the belly, it wouldn't be true that he was born as a man.
But he was born as a man, so he came through the door of the belly, that is, the womb.
Hilary, a man of great virtues and accomplishments, and as distinguished in eloquence as in life, writes in the second book of the Faith On the Trinity Book Two, around the middle: The one only-begotten God, inserted into the form of a human body in the womb of the holy Virgin, grows.
He who contains all things, and within whom and through whom all things exist, is brought forth by the law of human birth.
He teaches that he took on the form of the body from the Virgin and within the Virgin, and in the manner of human birth, penetrated the secrets of the virgin womb.
By changing the words, it's the same as what Father Augustine declares: he testifies that he was born as a man; but this one proclaimed that he was brought forth by the law of human birth.
Thus, as both agree in the harmonious sacred Scriptures about the process of the Savior from the Virgin, the truth is taught, and falsehood is subverted.
Chapter Eight
From Pope Gregory and the Venerable Bede.
To leave no room for contradiction from the adversary, let Gregory, the mirror of holiness, with honeyed speech, a rule of morals, and the teacher of the truth of the birth of the Lord, come forward and teach in truth.
In Homily 26, while addressing a question about the body of the Lord being real and entering to the disciples through closed doors, he provided the following example.
Just as the body of the Lord entered to the disciples through closed doors, so too did it emerge from the closed womb at birth.
It is said that just as the Lord Jesus Christ, after the glory of the resurrection, entered the disciples' lodging with a real body, not through the wall or back door, but through the door, though it remained closed, so did he emerge from his mother's womb, passing through the vulva, though it remained closed.
You might argue that the Lord entered to the disciples through closed doors, but not through the actual doorway, rather through another part.
First, what is the significance of the divine miracle if he entered through another route?
Or what is commendable about the evangelist's account if the Lord entered through a place where any mortal could find entry?
If nothing should be closed to the Almighty, why not accept that he entered through the doors, even though they were closed, they would open for his arrival to the disciples?
And what will you say about the tomb, which was not only closed but also sealed, from which his revived body emerged into the air?
Will you claim that the body of Jesus was so subtle, finer than the winds and air, that the walls of the tomb could not confine it?
But even though it might seem blasphemous to think such things about the body of the Savior, remember that after the resurrection He told the disciples: "Touch and see, because a spirit does not have flesh and bones, as you see that I have," and by nature, it is not possible for something to be both solid with the hardness of bones and flesh, and delicate with the thinness of subtlety.
The Catholic faith does not attribute the fact that He left the tomb closed or that He entered through locked doors to the nature or quality of His body, but to the power of His Divinity and the glory of the resurrection. Otherwise, it would no longer be a miracle demonstrating the power of the Deity but something limited by the laws of nature.
Yet, we acknowledge these points, even though they may seem blasphemous and contrary to the faith. Do you not admit the same about the closed doors? Whether you want to or not, you are caught in this argument. Therefore, He exited the closed tomb and entered through locked doors. Thus, whether you like it or not, you must also concede the same for the virgin womb. The offspring of divine power was neither weaker nor less human when it came to the confines of His mother's womb, allowing Him to leave it closed and pass through it, just as He exited the sealed tomb and entered the disciples' locked house without opening it.
Bede, a priest of the English and a faithful member of Christ, offers a similar opinion on this question in his Commentary on Luke, chapter 2, when he speaks about the birth of the Savior and the virgin birth. He says: "That Mary is described as having given birth to her firstborn son should not be taken according to Helvidius, as if she had other children, since the firstborn can be called such even if he has no brothers, just as the only begotten is called one who has no brothers. For both the testimony of the law and clear reason declare that all only-begotten sons are also firstborn, but not all firstborn sons are only-begotten. This means not only those firstborn after whom others are born, but all those before whom no one has proceeded from the womb."
Finally, because every male that opens the womb is commanded to be called holy to the Lord, whether brothers follow or not, the firstborn that emerges must be consecrated by law.
These words both defend Mary's virginity and hint at the human birth of the Savior by law.
While he is taught to be the firstborn and the only begotten, it is shown that he could have had brothers, which could not be true if Christ had not been born by human law.
He would not be rightly called either the firstborn or the only begotten if he was not begotten.
However, being begotten, he was brought forth under the law of human birth.
Therefore, Christ was not born like a man.
If Mary had given birth to another besides Christ, he could not have been called the firstborn, because he would not have been begotten but either cast out or brought forth against the laws of nature.
Now, by the authority of the law and the truth of the Gospel, this well-instructed teacher proclaims Jesus as the firstborn of the holy Virgin, because he was both the first and the only one born from her by the law of human birth.
By being born, he opened the womb, not to violate its purity, but to proceed through a marked and unblemished gate, from the secret of the womb to human sight.
Thus, because he was the first to be born from the womb, he is consecrated by the right of the firstborn.
I do not know what more would be necessary to gather as evidence for the confirmation of this question.
So many and such great men of authority can not only suffice for any Catholic but also crush any heretic with the weight of faith and the light of wisdom.
Chapter Nine
Also from Jerome
To ensure no one thinks anything new is being invented, let's present the modesty of the Virgin herself, named plainly, and through her, the Savior born.
Jerome, interpreter of the holy law, highly skilled in all disciplines, an unshakable tower of faith, a splendid lamp of wisdom, eloquent in speech, and well-versed in Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, in his little book against Helvidius, first sets forth Helvidius's words on this matter, and then offers his own opinion, thereby confirming what was rightly suggested by the heretic.
It reads thus:
Do not children form daily in the womb by the hands of God?
Should we then be ashamed to think that Mary married after giving birth?
If this seems shameful, it follows that we should not believe that God was born through the Virgin's reproductive organs.
For it is more shameful to them that God was born through the Virgin's modest parts than that the Virgin married her husband after giving birth.
Thus far, the heretic blasphemously barks about the Virgin's marriage after giving birth.
But he tells the truth about the generation of the Son of God through man, as the following speech of our teacher clearly declares:
Add, if you like, other natural indignities: nine months of a swelling womb, discomforts, childbirth, blood, and swaddling clothes.
Imagine the infant wrapped in the usual covering of membranes: the harsh manger, the cries of the little one, the circumcision on the eighth day, the time of purification, to prove He was unclean.
We are not ashamed, we do not remain silent.
The more humble the things He suffered for me, the more I owe Him.
And when you have recounted everything, you will bring forth nothing more humiliating than the cross, which we profess, believe in, and through which we triumph over our enemies.
But as we do not deny what is written, we reject what is not written: we believe that God was born of a Virgin because we read it; we do not believe that Mary married after giving birth because we do not read it.
With careful distinction, the learned man removed what had been wrongly introduced by the adversary and accepted what was spoken in a Catholic manner.
He confirmed what was true and refuted what was blasphemous.
He affirmed that God was born through the Virgin's genitals and rejected the idea that Mary married after giving birth.
He condemned the notion that the genitals and private parts could be used to insult the sacred birth.
He approved the belief that the Word became flesh and emerged through the secret door of the womb.
Furthermore, he included other natural occurrences: the nine months of pregnancy, the discomforts, the birth, the blood, the cloths, the baby wrapped in the usual covering of membranes, the harsh manger, the crying, the circumcision, the time of purification, and finally, the humiliation of the cross.
He embraced, accepted, and venerated all these as a Catholic.
The more humble the sufferings the Creator endured for the chosen, the more people owe it to themselves to reflect on this through the words of the distinguished doctor.
He enumerates many things that a child could not have endured if he was not born under the law of human birth: the birth, the blood, the cloths, the wrapping in membranes, the crying.
All these, along with the secret of the virginal birth and the law of human birth, bear witness.
Likewise, learn that the Holy Spirit, who proclaimed this sacred birth, and the holy and learned men who later commended it to the people through their words and writings, preferred to convey it with more honorable speech rather than simple language to avoid offending listeners.
It was fitting to express such a great matter not with humble but with grand and honorable words, as in: "A star shall come out of Jacob, and a man shall rise out of Israel, and a rod shall come from the root of Jesse, and a flower shall descend from his root. Drip down, O heavens, from above, and let the clouds rain the just one; let the earth open and bring forth a Savior" (Numbers 24:17; Isaiah 1 and 45:8).
The Holy Spirit did not lack words to describe the virgin birth but chose to convey this remarkable and magnificent event through splendid and grand figures.
Yet, He also revealed it with proper and fitting words.
Thus, the Prophet says, "Behold, a virgin shall conceive in the womb, and bear a son" (Isaiah 7:14).
And, "For unto us a child is born; unto us a son is given." The angel also said to Mary, "Behold, you will conceive and bear a son" (Luke 1:31), among many similar expressions.
In all these instances, the birth of Christ is described with natural and fitting words.
However, the specific part of the body from which birth emerges is deliberately not mentioned by name, as it is neither honorable nor necessary.
When the functions and actions are described, we naturally understand the body parts involved.
For example, we understand seeing by the eyes, hearing by the ears, and walking by the feet.
When it is said that someone saw, heard, or walked, the eyes, ears, and feet are not explicitly mentioned unless for clarity.
We comprehend the meanings of these words without needing to specify the parts involved.
Therefore, what was unnecessary and inappropriate about the act of holy birth was avoided by the heavenly message, and the holy men also refrained from mentioning it.
However, they did explain what was meaningful and modest.
They did not completely avoid it, either, to counter future enemies of the truth or to remove any occasion for doubt.
Thus, Luke the evangelist says, "When the days of Mary's purification according to the law of Moses were fulfilled, they brought Jesus to Jerusalem to present Him to the Lord, as it is written in the law of the Lord: Every male that opens the womb shall be called holy to the Lord" (Luke 2:22).
It is not surprising that serious and reverent teachers did not wish to refer to such things in connection with the glorious birth, things which even common people are ashamed to confess about the birth of any poor woman.
This esteemed teacher, whose testimony we've shared, received an account of the divine birth from an opponent of the truth but remains offended by the insults to the Virgin.
With those words, although natural and proper, he described the Virgin's birth in a way that was humble yet somewhat immodest.
Chapter Ten
Proofs from Christian Poets
So now there's nothing more for you to ask, since we have explored everything about the holy birth.
We've already discussed the Virgin's reproductive organs and the private parts of the woman giving birth.
If understanding wasn't gained through conception, childbirth, generation, birth, or the opening of the womb, then let these private parts and reproductive organs teach and instruct.
If the natural and honest aspects didn't provide understanding, then at least let the symbolic and perhaps embarrassing aspects do so.
Our investigators of secrets are so educated that they prefer obscure and foreign meanings over clear and proper ones.
But let's now call upon the proofs from poets, so that all eloquence may bear witness to the truth.
Prudentius, a man well-versed in liberal studies, while discussing the sufferings endured by the world's life for the world's freedom in his work "Apotheosis," and distinguishing the inviolable (that is, divine) nature from the passible (that is, human) nature, says this:
"This is how the flesh of man was affected, which a pregnant woman, under the old law, gave birth to without the law of a husband."
With a truly faithful and wise narration, he distinguished between intercourse and the naturally given offspring. He removed the law of the husband and substituted the law of the womb, showing that she conceived from the Holy Spirit and did not keep silent about giving birth through the womb.
Similarly, Fortunatus, a foreign priest but a citizen of heaven, poor in possessions, rich in faith, says this in praise of the Virgin Mary (Book 8, Poem 5, after the beginning):
"But I return to the praise of the Virgin who draws us in with her praise, such as none was before and none will come in the future. The one whom the clouds rain down as righteous from the serene dew, this earth gave as the Savior from her offspring. This is the closed gate, through which no one has entered or exited, except the Lord alone, for whom even the closed gate opens."
It doesn't contradict the previous statement; in fact, it expresses the same idea in different words.
It uses repetition to emphasize the same point: it praises the purity of virginity, describes the birth in a human manner, narrates the divine conception of the Savior, and explains the natural process of birth.
To make his point clearer, he attests that Mary was the gate mentioned by Ezekiel, through which no man has entered or exited; only the Almighty, for whom nothing is closed, passed through it.
He, who decided to be conceived by a Virgin, was born according to the law of human birth.
After all, let Athanasius of Alexandria come forward, who, with his virtues, steadfast faith, wisdom in teaching, and perseverance in confession, single-handedly, so to speak, overthrew the numerous followers of Arian perfidy.
He, bearing the banner of true belief as an invincible defender, restored the wall of the Church and strengthened its state.
Let him support our debate and vigorously overturn the sect of error.
Addressing Epitectus against those who taught that the Word and the body He assumed for our redemption were of one substance, since Christian faith holds that there are two substances, divine and human, united in Christ, so that in one person each nature retains its distinction; thus he says among other things: Therefore, Mary was necessary, that He might take a body from her, and offer it as His own for us; and Isaiah prophesied this, saying: Behold, a Virgin.
Gabriel was sent to her, not to a temporary virgin, but to a virgin betrothed to a man, to show that Mary was truly human.
Scripture remembers the birth, and it is said: She wrapped the child.
And: Blessed are the breasts that nursed Him.
And, a sacrifice was offered because He who was born opened the womb.
These were all signs of the virgin in labor, and Gabriel himself clearly announced that he would be born from you, not fleetingly, but directly from you.
This makes it clear that his body wasn't given to him from outside, but from you.
It shows that what was naturally born came from you.
Nature demonstrates this because it's impossible for a virgin to produce milk, and a body can't be nourished by milk and wrapped in swaddling clothes if it wasn't naturally born first.
The steadfast defenders of the orthodox faith, whom the Lord placed in a fortified city, as a bronze wall and an iron pillar to the kings of Judah, its princes, and all the people of the land, couldn't think or speak any differently about the Virgin's birth than the way the Church feels and preaches.
The Church is a house built on the most solid rock, a pillar and support of truth.
For this reason, when he lists many things to prove that Christ was incarnate and born of a Virgin, and to dispel a new heresy, it is said that he who was born opened the womb.
Further emphasizing this doctrine of true confession, he adds: "It would be impossible for a virgin to produce milk, and it would be impossible for a body to be nourished by milk and wrapped in swaddling clothes if it wasn't naturally born first."
What more do you want, new and unheard-of heresy of past ages, either from authors or defenders? Behold, Athanasius himself stands against your arguments. He once fought against the deceit of Arianism, defending the divinity of the Word. In this contest, he champions humanity. Then, the truth of the birth from the Father was contradicted, and now the truth of the birth from the mother is resisted. Those enemies argued that the Son wasn't born from the substance of the Father but was made from nothing. These opponents claim that Christ wasn't naturally born from his mother's womb but was miraculously taken out.
Everywhere Christ is opposed, and everywhere the world's liberation is insulted by the tongues of the cursed.
But a learned defender, knowing how to win and not knowing how to give up, should approach.
Not relying on himself but trusting in the one for whom he fights, he should cut down the swollen pride and empty arrogance with the sword of truth.
The opposing side throws a weapon and claims: God was not born through the nature of a woman.
The faithful man puts up the shield of faith and brings forth the sword of the word of God.
The sacrifice was offered because the one who was born opened the womb.
Why are you astonished by the falsehood?
You were not pricked by a sword but struck by a very powerful weapon; the sacrifice was offered, and you cannot deny it; therefore, you are forced to admit that the womb was opened.
If the womb was opened, he was born through the natural process of a woman.
Old serpent, where do you turn your gaze?
Where do you try to object with your slippery head?
Do you still try to wound and hiss with your three-forked mouth?
If he opened the womb, did he corrupt?
But let the pestilent mouth be stopped by the defense of Daniel, so that the scaly dragon, scattered into pieces, ceases to drive the Chaldeans mad.
The prophet Isaiah says: Behold, a Virgin.
And Gabriel is sent not temporarily to the virgin, but to a virgin betrothed to a man.
After the birth, after the wrapping of the child, after the nursing, after the offering, because the one who was born opened the womb, he cries out.
All these were signs of the virgin giving birth.
Therefore, the virgin gives birth and is not corrupted; God, being born, opened the womb of the virgin mother and did not violate the seal of modesty.
And perhaps you are still not completely at rest, but you dare again to prepare your shattered and cut hand for blows: Nothing was closed to God who was to be born, but as soon as the will to be born existed, the exit flowed immediately, and he did not suffer the delays of birth, for whom the birth was made without process.
And the defender of faith thus crushes this calumny of faithlessness, not by adding anything to the power of divinity, but by bearing witness to the truth of human birth to the man-God; so that it may be clearly believed that what was born was naturally human.
Therefore, it naturally follows that God was born as a man, so that you may understand He came into the world through the natural process of human birth.
It also teaches that the Virgin could naturally produce milk to nourish Him and wrap Him in swaddling clothes, having given birth naturally.
So, in every way, having defeated the adversary, let us hold true to our faith, confessing with honest speech that the Word became flesh through the ministry of the womb and was born naturally, according to reason, the testimonies of the divine Scriptures, and the respected authority of the learned.
It has been shown abundantly and sufficiently, in my opinion, that the Lord and Savior was born of the Virgin as a man, without compromising her integrity.
Mary was a virgin before birth, a virgin during birth, and remained a virgin after birth.
But He who took on a body from the Virgin and grew within her womb was also born naturally through the virgin passage.
If these explanations are not sufficient for someone, either due to a lack of understanding or a desire to argue, help is available if they are willing to seek it and do not cling to the destruction of contention.
We have written these things as students: if anyone disregards them, our efforts will still be meaningful to us.